<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>World Chess Championship on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/world-chess-championship/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in World Chess Championship on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/world-chess-championship/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>My predictions after Carlsen and Anand are tied after round 4 of the World Chess Championship</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/12/my-predictions-after-carlsen-and-anand-are-tied-after-round-4-of-the-world-chess-championship/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2014 23:01:25 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/12/my-predictions-after-carlsen-and-anand-are-tied-after-round-4-of-the-world-chess-championship/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/11/06/my-predictions-and-hopes-for-the-2014-carlsen-anand-world-chess-championship-rematch/&#34;&gt;Last week I made some predictions&lt;/a&gt; about the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sochi2014.fide.com/&#34;&gt;2014 Carlsen-Anand World Chess Championship&lt;/a&gt; match before it began. Now, four rounds later, there have been two draws and a win for each player. What next? Since I correctly predicted some things already, I thought I&amp;rsquo;d speculate about the next couple of rounds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;anand&#34;&gt;Anand&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;as-white&#34;&gt;As White&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I expected, Anand opened with d4 with a view to aggressive, sharp lines based on home preparation. In round 1, he lost his nerve and lost his initiative, but in round 3, he won convincingly, first inviting a Queen&amp;rsquo;s Indian (as I expected he would) but then defeating the Queen&amp;rsquo;s Gambit Declined. I do not see why he would vary from d4 as White in the future unless he ends up ahead in the match and has psychological reasons to mix things up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;as-black&#34;&gt;As Black&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far, Anand has only faced 1 e4 as Black. In round 2, Anand made what seems like a stupid decision to try to go into the Berlin Defense, and got punished by a loss. I see no reason for him to play the Berlin Defense again; playing 1&amp;hellip;e5 just seems to be playing into Carlsen&amp;rsquo;s strengths. In round 4, Anand went for the Sicilian, as I expected; he used an &amp;hellip;e6 move order to avoid the Moscow and Rossolimo, causing Carlsen to vary with a g3 anti-Sicilian, resulting in a draw. My suspicion is still that Anand might be aiming for a &amp;hellip;Nc6 Sicilian through transposition, perhaps a Taimanov. I expect him to try this again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m most curious about how Anand would face the English. I think it would depend on his situation. 1&amp;hellip;e5 would be an ambitious, unbalancing choice, while transposition to a Slav structure is also possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;carlsen&#34;&gt;Carlsen&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;as-white-1&#34;&gt;As White&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I made no specific prediction about how Carlsen would open as White. He has played 1 e4 twice, once with success but once leading to a draw. Psychologically, his inability or unwillingness to engage Anand in an Open Sicilian does not make continuing with 1 e4 right now seem plausible. I expect him to vary, possibly using the English. I certainly hope he doesn&amp;rsquo;t try the Reti again as he did last year, even though it worked then; he is facing a different Anand this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;as-black-1&#34;&gt;As Black&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Grünfeld in round 1 was a surprise, but exactly true to my expectation that &amp;ldquo;he will do whatever might confuse Anand&amp;rdquo;. That he varied in round 3 with the Queen&amp;rsquo;s Gambit Declined suggests that the Grünfeld may not appear again soon, but he lost with the Queen&amp;rsquo;s Gambit Declined, so will he play it again? It is possible. Another possibility is to resort to the Queen&amp;rsquo;s Indian, making sure to avoid sacrificial lines (which means possibly playing a traditional &amp;hellip;Bb7 instead of &amp;hellip;Ba6). Or he could play a Ragozin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right now I think Anand is actually in good shape in the match, having a certain momentum. It appears Carlsen is mainly winging it, in the last two rounds. I expect him to change things up.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My predictions and hopes for the 2014 Carlsen-Anand world chess championship rematch</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/06/my-predictions-and-hopes-for-the-2014-carlsen-anand-world-chess-championship-rematch/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2014 21:09:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/06/my-predictions-and-hopes-for-the-2014-carlsen-anand-world-chess-championship-rematch/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sochi2014.fide.com/&#34;&gt;2014 World Chess Championship&lt;/a&gt; is about to begin, featuring Anand and Carlsen again, this time with Anand as challenger and Carlsen as defending champion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year when I followed the World Chess Championship match, I wrote several blog posts looking at each game that was played. This year I&amp;rsquo;m not planning to do the same, but instead, I would like to offer some predictions and hopes for the rematch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recall that I made one prediction that was eerily correct last year:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-correct-prediction-last-year&#34;&gt;My correct prediction last year&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before round 9 began, I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/11/21/world-chess-championship-2013-round-9-i-correctly-predicted-anands-aggressively-opening-choice-but-he-blundered-horribly-again-to-lose/&#34;&gt;predicted correctly&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
It came to me in a dream: Anand playing d4 in the next round, then going for an f3, e4 Pawn storm against Carlsen #FWCM2013
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was a critical game in the match, in which Anand blundered horribly to lose a game that he had very good chances of winning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;for-this-year&#34;&gt;For this year&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;anand&#34;&gt;Anand&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anand&amp;rsquo;s play last year was very disappointing: he did not win a single game in the match, as he was psychologically unprepared to play aggressively enough when he had good positions against Carlsen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I expect that this year, being the challenger instead of the defending champion, he will play in a more forceful way, because he has no choice and nothing to lose. What does this mean?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year I was surprised Anand played e4 as White inviting the Berlin Defense. This was a big mistake. I cannot imagine why he would play e4 again. He surely must play d4, or at least the English Opening with c4. What could he possibly have against the Nimzo-Indian, however, now that the f3 weapon is well-known? There&amp;rsquo;s always the Rubinstein e3 variation but Carlsen, like Karpov of old, should be happy with Black there. The other option is to avoid the Nimzo-Indian and use one of the Pawn sacrifice lines in the Queen&amp;rsquo;s Indian or Catalan. But Carlsen must be prepared against such. So there remains the option of trying for a tiny first-move advantage using the English. I guess we&amp;rsquo;ll see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Black, Anand could stick with the Grunfeld setup from last year, or return to a Slav setup. But what about against e4? There&amp;rsquo;s always the Najdorf, but that allowed the Moscow last year, so maybe a Nc6 Sicilian? In any case, I hope we see fewer Berlin Defense games this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;carlsen&#34;&gt;Carlsen&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Carlsen is still the favorite to win this year, but is not invincible. He can either play like he did last year, or play differently. Because he is versatile, he can change his plans depending on what happens. I suspect that because he is champion now, he may want to prove his dominance, and play more sharply than last year, but he can always fall back on his wait-for-opponent-to-self-destruct style. Since Anand is simply not going to last forever, Carlsen needs to already start preparing to play against his younger rivals such as Caruana and might want to send a message to them in this match.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I expect that his aim will be to psychologically destroy Anand one way or another, so he will do whatever might confuse Anand. I cannot really predict how he will play. I suspect his use of the Reti as White is over, however; there are plenty of ways to still control the situation as White while playing d4 or c4. Playing the English might be smart, actually, especially if Anand is also thinking of playing it. We could see one of those matches where both players decide to enter openings as both colors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have no idea if any of my &amp;ldquo;predictions&amp;rdquo; will actually come true, but thought it would be fun to get them on record in case they do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Are you going to follow this year&amp;rsquo;s World Chess Championship? What do you expect to see in the 2014 match in Sochi?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>World Chess Championship 2013 round 10: Magnus Carlsen is the new world champion</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/11/22/world-chess-championship-2013-round-10-magnus-carlsen-is-the-new-world-champion/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Nov 2013 18:17:34 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/11/22/world-chess-championship-2013-round-10-magnus-carlsen-is-the-new-world-champion/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In my continuing coverage of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://chennai2013.fide.com/&#34;&gt;World Chess Championship between Anand and Carlsen&lt;/a&gt;, today I cover round ten, in which a draw gave 22-year-old Magnus Carlsen the FIDE World Chess Champion title. Congratulations to Carlsen, and thank you, Anand, for showing your fighting spirit by playing the Sicilian Defense today!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Game and notes below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-opening-predictions-for-today&#34;&gt;My opening predictions for today&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I announced my opening predictions the night before today&amp;rsquo;s game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My primary prediction was that Carlsen would play &lt;code&gt;1 e4&lt;/code&gt; and Anand would play &lt;code&gt;c5&lt;/code&gt; for an aggressive Najdorf Sicilian, and that Carlsen would play a &lt;code&gt;Be2/Nf3&lt;/code&gt; line in response. My secondary prediction was that if Carlsen played something other than &lt;code&gt;1 e4&lt;/code&gt;, then Anand would try a King&amp;rsquo;s Indian as Black.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary-of-the-game&#34;&gt;Summary of the game&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that I was partially right in my prediction. There was a Sicilian Defense, and Anand did try entering a Najdorf. I was very happy to see this, because there was some discussion among my chess friends yesterday about whether Anand would simply play for a safe, quick draw, rather than try to fight back in the match for a win. Anand did try to fight back after all, playing the riskiest variation even against Carlsen&amp;rsquo;s avoidance of the Najdorf with the drawish Moscow Variation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Objectively the middlegame was very equal for some time, as Anand set up a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hedgehog_%28chess%29&#34;&gt;Hedgehog&lt;/a&gt; position against Carlsen&amp;rsquo;s Maróczy Bind setup. In fact, Anand implicitly offered a draw by shuffling his King back and forth. Carlsen decided to play on for a win, advancing on the Queenside with &lt;code&gt;a4&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shortly after that, Anand started slipping a bit, allowing Carlsen to improve White&amp;rsquo;s position, and at one critical point Anand made a big blunder that should have lost the game, hanging the important &lt;code&gt;d6&lt;/code&gt; Pawn to White&amp;rsquo;s capture by the &lt;code&gt;e5&lt;/code&gt; Pawn. But Carlsen prematurely captured the Pawn too early, allowing Anand to regain it and simplify into a Knight and Pawn ending that should be a draw.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, White had chances because of the Queen side majority and more active King. Anand found very sharp counterplay that caused Carlson to decide to stop playing for a possible win, and shut the game down for a draw.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-state-of-the-match&#34;&gt;The state of the match&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Carlsen is the new world champion!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-game&#34;&gt;The game&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;link href=&#34;../../chess/pgn4web/template.css&#34; type=&#34;text/css&#34; rel=&#34;stylesheet&#34;&gt;&lt;/link&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;style type=&#34;text/css&#34;&gt;
  #GameLastComment {
    font-style: italic
  }
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;script src=&#34;../../chess/pgn4web/pgn4web.js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;
    &#34;use strict&#34;;

    SetPgnUrl(&#34;/chess/anand-carlsen.pgn&#34;);
    SetImagePath(&#34;/chess/pgn4web/images&#34;);
    SetHighlightOption(true);
    SetCommentsIntoMoveText(true);
    SetCommentsOnSeparateLines(true);
    SetInitialGame(10);
    SetShortcutKeysEnabled(true);
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
    &lt;tr valign=&#34;top&#34;&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;
        &lt;div id=&#34;GameBoard&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div id=&#34;GameButtons&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Move comment:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span id=&#34;GameLastComment&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;/td&gt;

      &lt;td&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Event:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameEvent&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Site:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameSite&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Round:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameRound&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Date:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameDate&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;White:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameWhite&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Black:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameBlack&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Result:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameResult&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Side to move:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameSideToMove&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Last move:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameLastMove&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp; &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;variations:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameLastVariations&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Next move:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameNextMove&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp; &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;variations:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameNextVariations&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;hr/&gt;

&lt;div id=&#34;GameText&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>World Chess Championship 2013 round 9: I correctly predicted Anand&#39;s aggressively opening choice but he blundered horribly again to lose</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/11/21/world-chess-championship-2013-round-9-i-correctly-predicted-anands-aggressively-opening-choice-but-he-blundered-horribly-again-to-lose/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Nov 2013 08:59:36 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/11/21/world-chess-championship-2013-round-9-i-correctly-predicted-anands-aggressively-opening-choice-but-he-blundered-horribly-again-to-lose/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In my continuing coverage of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://chennai2013.fide.com/&#34;&gt;World Chess Championship between Anand and Carlsen&lt;/a&gt;, today I cover round nine, in which Anand finally went for the big win, but blundered horribly and lost instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The night before the game, five hours before it started, I &lt;a href=&#34;http://twitter.com/franklinchen/status/403370754336505858&#34;&gt;tweeted&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
It came to me in a dream: Anand playing d4 in the next round, then going for an f3, e4 Pawn storm against Carlsen #FWCM2013
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have to admit to being proud of myself for having correctly predicted the opening that both players would willingly enter in today&amp;rsquo;s game! I had been thinking about this even before the match, but apparently Anand didn&amp;rsquo;t pull out his weapon until just now. Today, I explain my reasoning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Game and notes below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-correct-opening-prediction&#34;&gt;My correct opening prediction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;1-d4&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;1 d4&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I concluded weeks ago that Anand would have to play &lt;code&gt;1 d4&lt;/code&gt; for the win against Carlsen, as he did against Kramnik in 2008 and Topalov in 2010. I know this is a topic for a post in itself, but I think &lt;code&gt;1 e4&lt;/code&gt; is dead at an elite match level if Black is willing to play &lt;code&gt;1... e5&lt;/code&gt; in response. Alternatively, even in his successful defense of his title against Gelfand in 2012, Anand&amp;rsquo;s &lt;code&gt;1 e4&lt;/code&gt; was neutralized by Gelfand&amp;rsquo;s use of the Sicilian &lt;code&gt;1... c5&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;nimzo-indian&#34;&gt;Nimzo-Indian&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I predicted that Carlsen would play the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nimzo-Indian_Defence&#34;&gt;Nimzo-Indian&lt;/a&gt;/&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Queen%27s_Indian_Defense&#34;&gt;Queen&amp;rsquo;s Indian Defense&lt;/a&gt; opening complex in response to &lt;code&gt;1 d4&lt;/code&gt;. Very solid, dynamic opening choice for Black.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe the Queen&amp;rsquo;s Indian Defense is mostly dead at the elite level, thanks to computer-aided analysis of some of the most important lines that lead to forced draws. Therefore, for Anand to play for the big win would require accepting the Nimzo-Indian challenge, creating positional asymmetries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;white-against-the-nimzo-indian&#34;&gt;White against the Nimzo-Indian&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many ways to play White against the Nimzo-Indian. As White I have tried many of them. The question is, what is the most aggressive way to play against the Nimzo-Indian? I think the answer is clear: &lt;code&gt;f3&lt;/code&gt; aiming for an eventual &lt;code&gt;e4&lt;/code&gt; and King side attack, involving &lt;code&gt;f4&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;e5&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;f5&lt;/code&gt; trying to checkmate Black&amp;rsquo;s King!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some years ago, a nice book by Yuri Yakovich came out, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.gambitbooks.com/books/Play_the_4_f3_Nimzo-Indian.html&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Play the 4 f3 Nimzo-Indian&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; which covers the ideas behind this way of playing for White. There are, of course, reasons why this is not played so often at top levels. Basically, the plan is risky, because White risks getting a weak &lt;code&gt;c3&lt;/code&gt; Pawn, being underdeveloped, or overextended, while Black gets counterplay on the Queen side. But in a must-win situation, I expected Anand to pull out this opening variation as a weapon eventually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He has done this before. In his &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.chessgames.com/perl/chess.pl?tid=65865&#34;&gt;2008 match against Kramnik&lt;/a&gt;, he played against the Nimzo-Indian using this &lt;code&gt;f3&lt;/code&gt; variation in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.chessgames.com/perl/chessgame?gid=1510259&#34;&gt;Round 2&lt;/a&gt;. Kramnik drew, but White had a good game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary-of-the-game&#34;&gt;Summary of the game&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Carlsen characteristically avoided the most popular &amp;ldquo;main line&amp;rdquo; against the &lt;code&gt;f3&lt;/code&gt; Nimzo-Indian, and in fact even transposed into a line of the Saemisch Variation that for a long time, since Botvinnik&amp;rsquo;s famous winning games in it, had been considered bad for Black.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we have computers now that correct a lot of old assumptions. As a result, Carlsen played the most aggressive counterattacking plan right off the bat, going straight for Queen side counterplay before White even began developing the King side! Both players proceeded completely thematically and predictably after that, launching Pawns forward on opposite sides of the board. The question was whether Anand could break through on the King side first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Carlsen cold-bloodedly assumed not, and played aggressively with &lt;code&gt;b3&lt;/code&gt; creating a possibly dangerous passed Pawn, even as Anand prepared &lt;code&gt;f6&lt;/code&gt; trapping Carlsen&amp;rsquo;s King.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Probably objectively the position is defensible for Black. But Anand thought he saw a checkmate coming, and let Carlsen Queen the &lt;code&gt;b&lt;/code&gt; Pawn while lifting his Rook up to deliver a checkmate threat. Alas, he completely missed that &lt;code&gt;Qe1&lt;/code&gt; stops the checkmate and White is dead lost, and had to resign. (It turns out that at the last moment, Anand could easily have forced a draw with &lt;code&gt;Bf1&lt;/code&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this game, it is possible that if Anand had played a slower, less &amp;ldquo;objectively correct&amp;rdquo; line of attack, the game could have gotten interesting, in case Carlsen faltered. But unfortunately, we did not see that more interesting development of the game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-state-of-the-match&#34;&gt;The state of the match&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Carlsen has basically won the match. Carlsen already has 6 out of 12 points. He needs only one draw in the next 3 rounds in order to claim the title of FIDE World Chess Champion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s up to Anand to continue doing the best he can regardless of the inevitable result. It will be tough, especially since he just blundered &lt;em&gt;horrifically&lt;/em&gt; again in a position that should have been a draw.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-game&#34;&gt;The game&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;link href=&#34;../../chess/pgn4web/template.css&#34; type=&#34;text/css&#34; rel=&#34;stylesheet&#34;&gt;&lt;/link&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;style type=&#34;text/css&#34;&gt;
  #GameLastComment {
    font-style: italic
  }
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;script src=&#34;../../chess/pgn4web/pgn4web.js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;
    &#34;use strict&#34;;

    SetPgnUrl(&#34;/chess/anand-carlsen.pgn&#34;);
    SetImagePath(&#34;/chess/pgn4web/images&#34;);
    SetHighlightOption(true);
    SetCommentsIntoMoveText(true);
    SetCommentsOnSeparateLines(true);
    SetInitialGame(9);
    SetShortcutKeysEnabled(true);
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
    &lt;tr valign=&#34;top&#34;&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;
        &lt;div id=&#34;GameBoard&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div id=&#34;GameButtons&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Move comment:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span id=&#34;GameLastComment&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;/td&gt;

      &lt;td&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Event:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameEvent&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Site:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameSite&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Round:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameRound&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Date:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameDate&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;White:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameWhite&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Black:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameBlack&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Result:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameResult&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Side to move:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameSideToMove&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Last move:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameLastMove&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp; &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;variations:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameLastVariations&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Next move:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameNextMove&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp; &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;variations:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameNextVariations&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;hr/&gt;

&lt;div id=&#34;GameText&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>World Chess Championship 2013 round 8: the most boring game in the match so far</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/11/19/world-chess-championship-2013-round-8-the-most-boring-game-in-the-match-so-far/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Nov 2013 08:30:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/11/19/world-chess-championship-2013-round-8-the-most-boring-game-in-the-match-so-far/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In my continuing coverage of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://chennai2013.fide.com/&#34;&gt;World Chess Championship between Anand and Carlsen&lt;/a&gt;, today I cover round eight, in which apparently Carlsen took a break by playing safe for a quiet draw.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Game and notes below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As White, Carlsen played e4 for the first time in the match. Anand countered with the Berlin Defense. Unfortunately, all hope that an interesting game with colors reversed from usual were dashed at move 5, which was implicitly a draw offer by Carlsen. Re1 is a completely harmless reply against the Berlin Defense, and leads to a lifeless position in which usually a series of trades leads to a drawn position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sure enough, Carlsen basically forced the draw quickly thereafter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A total snorefest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-state-of-the-match&#34;&gt;The state of the match&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Carlsen has every right to play for a draw and win the match based on his two-point lead. If Anand had been ready to fight for a win at all costs, he would not have played the Berlin Defense; he could have played the Sicilian instead, for example. I hope I&amp;rsquo;m wrong, but it&amp;rsquo;s looking like Anand may be going down without a fight, in fear of losing another game in the match.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-game&#34;&gt;The game&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;link href=&#34;../../chess/pgn4web/template.css&#34; type=&#34;text/css&#34; rel=&#34;stylesheet&#34;&gt;&lt;/link&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;style type=&#34;text/css&#34;&gt;
  #GameLastComment {
    font-style: italic
  }
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;script src=&#34;../../chess/pgn4web/pgn4web.js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;
    &#34;use strict&#34;;

    SetPgnUrl(&#34;/chess/anand-carlsen.pgn&#34;);
    SetImagePath(&#34;/chess/pgn4web/images&#34;);
    SetHighlightOption(true);
    SetCommentsIntoMoveText(true);
    SetCommentsOnSeparateLines(true);
    SetInitialGame(8);
    SetShortcutKeysEnabled(true);
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
    &lt;tr valign=&#34;top&#34;&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;
        &lt;div id=&#34;GameBoard&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div id=&#34;GameButtons&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Move comment:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span id=&#34;GameLastComment&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;/td&gt;

      &lt;td&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Event:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameEvent&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Site:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameSite&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Round:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameRound&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Date:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameDate&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;White:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameWhite&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Black:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameBlack&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Result:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameResult&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Side to move:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameSideToMove&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Last move:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameLastMove&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp; &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;variations:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameLastVariations&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Next move:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameNextMove&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp; &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;variations:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameNextVariations&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;hr/&gt;

&lt;div id=&#34;GameText&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>World Chess Championship 2013 round 7: Anand catches his breath with a quiet game</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/11/18/world-chess-championship-2013-round-7-anand-catches-his-breath-with-a-quiet-game/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Nov 2013 19:31:52 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/11/18/world-chess-championship-2013-round-7-anand-catches-his-breath-with-a-quiet-game/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In my continuing coverage of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://chennai2013.fide.com/&#34;&gt;World Chess Championship between Anand and Carlsen&lt;/a&gt;, today I cover round seven, in which apparently Anand took a break by playing safe for a quiet draw.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Game and notes below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As White, Anand played e4 yet again (I&amp;rsquo;m still waiting for d4, which he used effectively against Kramnik and Gelfand in past world championship matches), and as in round 4 and 6, Carlsen used the Berlin Defense. Anand played a quiet, unambitious anti-Berlin again with d3, as in round 6, but this time went for a delayed Exchange Variation, giving up the Bishop pair for doubling Black&amp;rsquo;s c Pawns. Nevertheless, this opening is considered harmless, and Carlsen chose a simple, effective plan that involved trading off his light Bishop for Anand&amp;rsquo;s Knight, and then after further simplifications, there was nothing left in the game and they created a draw by repetition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only interesting points in the game to me were the obvious opportunities Anand chose &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; to take to try for more aggressive plans: playing g4 or playing fxe3. That he chose not to indicated that he was content to just get the game drawn and over with to stay safe and avoid creating complications that might allow him to lose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-state-of-the-match&#34;&gt;The state of the match&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anand is running out of time to catch up in the match, but may have bought some time to rest and recover psychologically from losing two games in a row.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some people might criticize his failure to strike back immediately in this game, but if he knew himself and knew he was not ready, then it was the wise thing to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I believe that the next time he has White, Anand should switch away from opening with e4, to opening with d4 for the win, since it looks like Carlsen can easily neutralize e4.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-game&#34;&gt;The game&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;link href=&#34;../../chess/pgn4web/template.css&#34; type=&#34;text/css&#34; rel=&#34;stylesheet&#34;&gt;&lt;/link&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;style type=&#34;text/css&#34;&gt;
  #GameLastComment {
    font-style: italic
  }
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;script src=&#34;../../chess/pgn4web/pgn4web.js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;
    &#34;use strict&#34;;

    SetPgnUrl(&#34;/chess/anand-carlsen.pgn&#34;);
    SetImagePath(&#34;/chess/pgn4web/images&#34;);
    SetHighlightOption(true);
    SetCommentsIntoMoveText(true);
    SetCommentsOnSeparateLines(true);
    SetInitialGame(7);
    SetShortcutKeysEnabled(true);
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
    &lt;tr valign=&#34;top&#34;&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;
        &lt;div id=&#34;GameBoard&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div id=&#34;GameButtons&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Move comment:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span id=&#34;GameLastComment&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;/td&gt;

      &lt;td&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Event:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameEvent&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Site:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameSite&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Round:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameRound&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Date:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameDate&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;White:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameWhite&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Black:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameBlack&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Result:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameResult&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Side to move:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameSideToMove&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Last move:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameLastMove&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp; &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;variations:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameLastVariations&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Next move:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameNextMove&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp; &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;variations:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameNextVariations&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;hr/&gt;

&lt;div id=&#34;GameText&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>World Chess Championship 2013, round 6: Carlsen wins the second game in a row when Anand blunders again in a drawn ending</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/11/16/world-chess-championship-2013-round-6-carlsen-wins-the-second-game-in-a-row-when-anand-blunders-again-in-a-drawn-ending/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Nov 2013 23:51:36 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/11/16/world-chess-championship-2013-round-6-carlsen-wins-the-second-game-in-a-row-when-anand-blunders-again-in-a-drawn-ending/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In my continuing coverage of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://chennai2013.fide.com/&#34;&gt;World Chess Championship between Anand and Carlsen&lt;/a&gt;, today I cover round six, in which Carlsen won the second game in a row.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Game and notes below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;psychology-already-at-move-4&#34;&gt;Psychology already at move 4&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As White, Anand played e4 again, as in &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013-11-13-world-chess-championship-2013-round-4-who-said-the-berlin-defense-was-boring/&#34;&gt;round 4&lt;/a&gt;, and Carlsen again used the Berlin Defense. Anand deviated by refusing to go into the Berlin ending that had gone badly for him in round 4, and chose with d3 to transpose into a line of the Closed &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ruy_Lopez&#34;&gt;Ruy Lopez&lt;/a&gt; that is considered to be not so challenging for Black because of the lack of a White d4.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personally, I think this was a psychological error on Anand&amp;rsquo;s part, playing like Carlsen, avoiding the main aggressive opening lines. As we have seen in the match so far (and in Carlsen&amp;rsquo;s whole career), Carlsen is good at holding his own when the opening is harmless or even worse for him. By giving up the fight for an opening advantage, I think Anand gave up one of his advantages, that of superior opening preparation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;accumulating-small-weaknesses&#34;&gt;Accumulating small weaknesses&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anand did not play the middlegame well. As in round 4, he used time-consuming Knight maneuvers that ended up simply allowing Carlsen to complete piece development with a harmonious setup. The result was a simplified position that looked like it should be a draw.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To my surprise, however, Anand kept on voluntarily accepting small weaknesses in his positions, first in the form of doubled e Pawns and then even isolated doubled e Pawns, when the most &amp;ldquo;natural&amp;rdquo; moves blocking up the position seemed safe and effective to hold for a draw.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;blundering-a-pawn-away&#34;&gt;Blundering a Pawn away&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the 38th move, Anand mysteriously blundered away a Pawn for no good reason whatsoever, in a position that seemed like it should be an easy blocked-up draw. This was a total shock to me. It made no sense whatsoever to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;still-a-draw-but-carlsen-set-a-trap&#34;&gt;Still a draw, but Carlsen set a trap&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Rook and Pawn ending, it looked like the ending should still be a draw, but Carlsen kept playing and making progress on the King side. In fact, he abandoned his Queen side in order to attempt to win on the King side. It was a great winning try.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will confess that while playing over the score at this point in the ending, I lost all confidence in my ability to really understand what was going on without computer aid. I turned on the chess engine to analyze the ending, and it&amp;rsquo;s really quite tricky. Even at a critical moment when the ending was still drawable by White, there is a large number of forcing lines that must be examined. In any case, what happened was that Anand fell into a trap in which Carlsen had a fine deflecting and clearance sacrifice that forced a win. Wow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-state-of-the-match&#34;&gt;The state of the match&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anand is in terrible, terrible trouble. It&amp;rsquo;s just that he has lost two games in a row, and almost certainly will not be able to make up the deficit in the remaining six games in the match. It&amp;rsquo;s the way he&amp;rsquo;s been losing: playing poorly in the middlegame in both rounds 5 and 6, then finally cracking and falling into difficult endings in which he failed to find the draws. He did in each game defend actively and resourcefully in the endings, with plans that should have worked, but each time he eventually blundered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope Anand comes back to play well, regardless of the final outcome of the match, but right now, it looks like Carlsen is the one who has not made any blunders yet of the magnitude of Anand&amp;rsquo;s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-game&#34;&gt;The game&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;link href=&#34;../../chess/pgn4web/template.css&#34; type=&#34;text/css&#34; rel=&#34;stylesheet&#34;&gt;&lt;/link&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;style type=&#34;text/css&#34;&gt;
  #GameLastComment {
    font-style: italic
  }
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;script src=&#34;../../chess/pgn4web/pgn4web.js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;
    &#34;use strict&#34;;

    SetPgnUrl(&#34;/chess/anand-carlsen.pgn&#34;);
    SetImagePath(&#34;/chess/pgn4web/images&#34;);
    SetHighlightOption(true);
    SetCommentsIntoMoveText(true);
    SetCommentsOnSeparateLines(true);
    SetInitialGame(6);
    SetShortcutKeysEnabled(true);
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
    &lt;tr valign=&#34;top&#34;&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;
        &lt;div id=&#34;GameBoard&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div id=&#34;GameButtons&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Move comment:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span id=&#34;GameLastComment&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;/td&gt;

      &lt;td&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Event:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameEvent&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Site:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameSite&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Round:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameRound&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Date:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameDate&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;White:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameWhite&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Black:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameBlack&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Result:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameResult&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Side to move:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameSideToMove&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Last move:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameLastMove&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp; &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;variations:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameLastVariations&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Next move:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameNextMove&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp; &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;variations:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameNextVariations&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;hr/&gt;

&lt;div id=&#34;GameText&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>World Chess Championship 2013, round 5: Carlsen wins in a tense positional battle when Anand blunders!</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/11/15/world-chess-championship-2013-round-5-carlsen-wins-in-a-tense-positional-battle-when-anand-blunders/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2013 20:27:57 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/11/15/world-chess-championship-2013-round-5-carlsen-wins-in-a-tense-positional-battle-when-anand-blunders/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In my continuing coverage of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://chennai2013.fide.com/&#34;&gt;World Chess Championship between Anand and Carlsen&lt;/a&gt;, today I cover round five, a subtle positional battle in which Carlsen won in the ending. This was the first win by either player in the match!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Game and notes below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Carlsen as White gave up on Nf3 and played c4 instead, a very smart choice, as it prevents Black from immediately playing d5. Anand used the Triangle System to try to transpose to a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Semi-Slav_Defense&#34;&gt;Semi-Slav&lt;/a&gt;, an opening that he has shown fantastic preparation for as Black in the past, including a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/18/modern-chess-computers-shutting-down-opening-theory-part-2&#34;&gt;recent brilliancy&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Carlsen sidestepped the Semi-Slav by playing the Marshall Gambit, but cleverly without the gambit, choosing a quiet line instead. After a Queen trade, Carlsen maintained some pressure, and eventually Anand pressed hard for counterplay in an ending in which he stood slightly worse the whole time. Unfortunately, at the critical moment, he mysteriously blundered just as he could have bailed out with a draw, lost the wrong Pawns, and allowed White to simplify into an easy win.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found this game quite interesting because of the themes of bad Bishops, weak Pawns, and weak squares. Precise calculation is necessary to hold off or create invasions for either side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-state-of-the-match&#34;&gt;The state of the match&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although Anand showed creativity in his attempt at Queen side counterplay, and in theory he could have held the draw, Carlsen clearly had the more comfortable and safe advantage for much of the game. Finally winning a game is a huge deal, of course. And Anand cannot be happy that he suddenly cracked during the game and lost. But it was not a one-sided game all the way through: it was only at the final moment when Anand made the losing move.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-game&#34;&gt;The game&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;link href=&#34;../../chess/pgn4web/template.css&#34; type=&#34;text/css&#34; rel=&#34;stylesheet&#34;&gt;&lt;/link&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;style type=&#34;text/css&#34;&gt;
  #GameLastComment {
    font-style: italic
  }
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;script src=&#34;../../chess/pgn4web/pgn4web.js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;
    &#34;use strict&#34;;

    SetPgnUrl(&#34;/chess/anand-carlsen.pgn&#34;);
    SetImagePath(&#34;/chess/pgn4web/images&#34;);
    SetHighlightOption(true);
    SetCommentsIntoMoveText(true);
    SetCommentsOnSeparateLines(true);
    SetInitialGame(5);
    SetShortcutKeysEnabled(true);
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
    &lt;tr valign=&#34;top&#34;&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;
        &lt;div id=&#34;GameBoard&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div id=&#34;GameButtons&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Move comment:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span id=&#34;GameLastComment&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;/td&gt;

      &lt;td&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Event:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameEvent&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Site:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameSite&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Round:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameRound&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Date:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameDate&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;White:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameWhite&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Black:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameBlack&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Result:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameResult&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Side to move:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameSideToMove&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Last move:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameLastMove&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp; &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;variations:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameLastVariations&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Next move:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameNextMove&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp; &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;variations:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameNextVariations&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;hr/&gt;

&lt;div id=&#34;GameText&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>World Chess Championship 2013, round 4: who said the Berlin Defense was boring?</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/11/13/world-chess-championship-2013-round-4-who-said-the-berlin-defense-was-boring/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2013 21:49:28 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/11/13/world-chess-championship-2013-round-4-who-said-the-berlin-defense-was-boring/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In my continuing coverage of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://chennai2013.fide.com/&#34;&gt;World Chess Championship between Anand and Carlsen&lt;/a&gt;, today I cover round four, the most exciting and longest game of the match so far! Things are really heating up!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Game and notes below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The game featured Carlsen as Black defending against Anand as White using the &amp;ldquo;infamous&amp;rdquo; Berlin Defense. I saw a bit more about the Berlin Defense in &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/11/13/the-exact-moment-i-fell-in-love-with-the-berlin-defense-for-black-in-chess/&#34;&gt;a companion post&lt;/a&gt;. Let&amp;rsquo;s just say that it has had a reputation as a &amp;ldquo;boring&amp;rdquo; defensive opening for Black.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this game was hardly boring. Anand seemed to falter in the opening as White, embarking on time-consuming Knight maneuvers that seemed to give Carlsen time to neutralize any attacking ideas. But then Anand provocatively offered a Pawn sacrifice, which Carlsen did not actually need to accept, but did. Then Anand pushed Carlsen&amp;rsquo;s Bishop and Knight all the way back, in an attempt to just run him over with a thematic King side majority Pawn storm. The computer says this was not really sound, but it was &lt;em&gt;exciting&lt;/em&gt; to see an aggressive, risk-taking Anand for the first time in the match, after his cautious play in the first three rounds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Carlsen came up with good counterplay, but in very complex positions, began faltering, and could not refute Anand&amp;rsquo;s play, even as Anand was fighting for his life. Anand sacrificed a second Pawn to continue the attack. That was an amazing idea to find! Carlsen finally faltered enough to allow Anand to achieve a drawn position. What an amazing game!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warning: analyzing the game with a computer might give the wrong idea about whether Anand was lost or not during the game, because the positions are so complex that no human could have been expected under the circumstances (the game went for hours and hours) to calculate everything perfectly. From a practical point of view, Anand&amp;rsquo;s attacking ideas were definitely difficult to counter, and it is to both Carlsen&amp;rsquo;s credit and Anand&amp;rsquo;s that they played out this game to a fighting draw.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-state-of-the-match&#34;&gt;The state of the match&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the situation is about even now for both players. Anand has proved in this round that he is in fact able and willing to fight, and Carlsen has continued his tenacity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-game&#34;&gt;The game&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;link href=&#34;../../chess/pgn4web/template.css&#34; type=&#34;text/css&#34; rel=&#34;stylesheet&#34;&gt;&lt;/link&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;style type=&#34;text/css&#34;&gt;
  #GameLastComment {
    font-style: italic
  }
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;script src=&#34;../../chess/pgn4web/pgn4web.js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;
    &#34;use strict&#34;;

    SetPgnUrl(&#34;/chess/anand-carlsen.pgn&#34;);
    SetImagePath(&#34;/chess/pgn4web/images&#34;);
    SetHighlightOption(true);
    SetCommentsIntoMoveText(true);
    SetCommentsOnSeparateLines(true);
    SetInitialGame(4);
    SetShortcutKeysEnabled(true);
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
    &lt;tr valign=&#34;top&#34;&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;
        &lt;div id=&#34;GameBoard&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div id=&#34;GameButtons&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Move comment:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span id=&#34;GameLastComment&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;/td&gt;

      &lt;td&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Event:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameEvent&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Site:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameSite&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Round:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameRound&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Date:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameDate&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;White:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameWhite&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Black:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameBlack&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Result:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameResult&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Side to move:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameSideToMove&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Last move:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameLastMove&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp; &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;variations:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameLastVariations&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Next move:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameNextMove&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp; &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;variations:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameNextVariations&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;hr/&gt;

&lt;div id=&#34;GameText&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>World Chess Championship 2013, round 3: a fighting game worth studying</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/11/12/world-chess-championship-2013-round-3-a-fighting-game-worth-studying/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2013 22:47:56 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/11/12/world-chess-championship-2013-round-3-a-fighting-game-worth-studying/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In my continuing coverage of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://chennai2013.fide.com/&#34;&gt;World Chess Championship between Anand and Carlsen&lt;/a&gt;, today I cover round three, an exciting fighting game well worth studying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Game and notes below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you were bored by the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/11/09/world-chess-championship-2013/&#34;&gt;first round&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/11/10/world-chess-championship-2013-round-2-declining-the-sacrifice/&#34;&gt;second round&lt;/a&gt; games, because the play in both games involved no major errors and therefore ended quickly in a draw, study this third round game, even though it too ended in a draw!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Carlsen opened with the unambitious &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/R%C3%A9ti_Opening&#34;&gt;Réti Opening&lt;/a&gt; yet again, and Anand was happy to repeat the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gr%C3%BCnfeld_Defence&#34;&gt;Grünfeld Defense&lt;/a&gt; setup of round 1. Carlsen varied by a very quick c4 thrust against Anand&amp;rsquo;s d5 Pawn, but Anand played the most aggressive continuation, taking the Pawn, guaranteeing an asymmetrical Pawn structure and therefore a chance at fighting chess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-ambitious-maróczy-bind&#34;&gt;The ambitious Maróczy Bind&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, Anand aggressively adopted a reverse &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sicilian_Defence,_Dragon_Variation&#34;&gt;Dragon Sicilian Defense&lt;/a&gt; setup, with good long-term positional prospects as Black. Furthermore, he also quickly chose a plan to try to transform the position into a deadly reverse &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mar%C3%B3czy_Bind&#34;&gt;Maróczy Bind&lt;/a&gt; structure to squeeze Carlsen to death. Carlsen played inaccurately and in fact allowed Anand to adopt this structure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are not familiar with the Maróczy Bind setup, check out a couple of my games in which I won using it, so you can see what can happen against weak defense:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/19/round-3-of-pittsburgh-chess-club-tournament-another-approach-against-the-sicilian-squeezing-with-the-bind/&#34;&gt;as White&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://chessimprover.com/the-value-of-thematic-complete-games-against-a-weaker-opponent/&#34;&gt;in reverse as Black&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;carlsen-s-defense&#34;&gt;Carlsen&amp;rsquo;s defense&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Carlsen decided that instead of risking being squeezed to death, he would lash out and sacrifice a Pawn to get some open lines and possibly get chances against Anand&amp;rsquo;s King in order to simplify to a draw. I&amp;rsquo;m not sure whether it was sound, and Anand may have been able to play more challengingly to win (I have not done the intensive computer analysis to draw a conclusion), but in the end Anand wound up allowing simplification and losing back the won Pawn with a dead drawn ending.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-state-of-the-match-carlsen-under-real-pressure&#34;&gt;The state of the match: Carlsen under real pressure&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is now the &lt;em&gt;third game in a row in which Anand acquired an advantage out of the opening&lt;/em&gt;. And in each game, his advantage in the game has only grown. This trend is not at all good for Carlsen. He has been completely neutralized as Anand has consistently gained superior space and piece play. Carlsen had to fight hard for a draw in this game. As White in two games now, he has been playing the opening poorly, which one does not need to be a world class player to see. Is this rope-a-dope or what?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what about Anand? Why did he keep on taking the safe way out to a draw in three games when he could have avoided &lt;em&gt;simplification&lt;/em&gt; each time in an attempt to win? If Anand plays cautiously when he has the advantage, what might happen if Carlsen starts playing differently and gets Anand&amp;rsquo;s back against the wall in a game?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-game&#34;&gt;The game&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;link href=&#34;../../chess/pgn4web/template.css&#34; type=&#34;text/css&#34; rel=&#34;stylesheet&#34;&gt;&lt;/link&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;style type=&#34;text/css&#34;&gt;
  #GameLastComment {
    font-style: italic
  }
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;script src=&#34;../../chess/pgn4web/pgn4web.js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;
    &#34;use strict&#34;;

    SetPgnUrl(&#34;/chess/anand-carlsen.pgn&#34;);
    SetImagePath(&#34;/chess/pgn4web/images&#34;);
    SetHighlightOption(true);
    SetCommentsIntoMoveText(true);
    SetCommentsOnSeparateLines(true);
    SetInitialGame(3);
    SetShortcutKeysEnabled(true);
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
    &lt;tr valign=&#34;top&#34;&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;
        &lt;div id=&#34;GameBoard&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div id=&#34;GameButtons&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Move comment:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span id=&#34;GameLastComment&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;/td&gt;

      &lt;td&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Event:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameEvent&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Site:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameSite&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Round:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameRound&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Date:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameDate&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;White:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameWhite&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Black:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameBlack&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Result:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameResult&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Side to move:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameSideToMove&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Last move:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameLastMove&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp; &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;variations:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameLastVariations&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Next move:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameNextMove&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp; &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;variations:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameNextVariations&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;hr/&gt;

&lt;div id=&#34;GameText&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>World Chess Championship 2013, Round 2: declining the sacrifice</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/11/10/world-chess-championship-2013-round-2-declining-the-sacrifice/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Nov 2013 13:09:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/11/10/world-chess-championship-2013-round-2-declining-the-sacrifice/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/11/09/world-chess-championship-2013/&#34;&gt;Yesterday, I covered the first round&lt;/a&gt; of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://chennai2013.fide.com/&#34;&gt;World Chess Championship between Anand and Carlsen&lt;/a&gt;, which ended in a quick draw.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, in the second round, the colors were reversed, with Anand as White and Carlsen as Black. The game also ended in a draw, but featured much more interesting positions and possibilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Game and notes below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anand played an interesting attacking idea in the opening that featured maintaining a strong Knight on the e5 square to hamper Black&amp;rsquo;s development. This idea inherently involved offering a sacrifice of his h4 Pawn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If Carlsen had accepted the sacrifice, I believe Anand would have had good winning chances. It was a positional sacrifice, with no immediate punishment in sight if Black had taken the Pawn, but there would have been long-term compensation for White. Carlsen wisely declined to take the Pawn, but in doing so deprived spectators of a fierce attacking game!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, after Anand offered a trade of a Knight, the result was that all the Knights were traded off, and then Carlsen offered to trade Queens. Anand could have held out and refused, but for some reason decided to trade, which meant a resulting position that was clearly drawn, and sure enough, a draw was agreed shortly thereafter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Carlsen can be happy about the outcome of the game. Anand seemed too quick to trade off pieces when it was not necessary, even if White&amp;rsquo;s spatial advantage and head start on the King side attack was only small, and there was always the danger that allowing Black to start a counterattack on the Queen side would create complications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is now the second game in a row in which Anand had some advantage but rejected opportunities to maintain complexity in search of a win.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-game&#34;&gt;The game&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;link href=&#34;../../chess/pgn4web/template.css&#34; type=&#34;text/css&#34; rel=&#34;stylesheet&#34;&gt;&lt;/link&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;style type=&#34;text/css&#34;&gt;
  #GameLastComment {
    font-style: italic
  }
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;script src=&#34;../../chess/pgn4web/pgn4web.js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;
    &#34;use strict&#34;;

    SetPgnUrl(&#34;/chess/anand-carlsen.pgn&#34;);
    SetImagePath(&#34;/chess/pgn4web/images&#34;);
    SetHighlightOption(true);
    SetCommentsIntoMoveText(true);
    SetCommentsOnSeparateLines(true);
    SetInitialGame(2);
    SetShortcutKeysEnabled(true);
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
    &lt;tr valign=&#34;top&#34;&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;
        &lt;div id=&#34;GameBoard&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div id=&#34;GameButtons&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Move comment:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span id=&#34;GameLastComment&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;/td&gt;

      &lt;td&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Event:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameEvent&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Site:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameSite&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Round:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameRound&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Date:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameDate&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;White:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameWhite&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Black:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameBlack&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Result:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameResult&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Side to move:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameSideToMove&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Last move:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameLastMove&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp; &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;variations:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameLastVariations&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Next move:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameNextMove&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp; &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;variations:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameNextVariations&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;hr/&gt;

&lt;div id=&#34;GameText&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>World Chess Championship 2013 Round 1: how to understand the short 16-move Carlsen-Anand draw</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/11/09/world-chess-championship-2013/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Nov 2013 12:00:33 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/11/09/world-chess-championship-2013/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the much-anticipated first round of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://chennai2013.fide.com/&#34;&gt;World Chess Championship between Anand and Carlsen&lt;/a&gt;, the game ended in a very quick 16-move draw.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In accordance with &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/11/07/the-chess-improver-how-to-watch-the-anand-carlsen-world-chess-championship-to-improve-your-own-game/&#34;&gt;my own advice on ways to follow the match to maximize learning&lt;/a&gt;, today I saw the match result, downloaded a PGN file of the game score, and then walked through it &lt;em&gt;without&lt;/em&gt; a computer engine running, analyzing the game with my own mind as I replayed the game. Then I double-checked my thoughts with a chess engine. I still have not bothered to read or watch any coverage of this first-round game; I will do that later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Game and notes below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;disappointment-in-a-short-draw&#34;&gt;Disappointment in a short draw?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m sure a lot of people were disappointed by this short draw. But one has to realized exactly what happened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Carlsen played the unambitious &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/R%C3%A9ti_Opening&#34;&gt;Réti Opening&lt;/a&gt; as White, presumably hoping to avoid special preparation by Anand. Anand neutralized the opening early on with simple development using a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gr%C3%BCnfeld_Defence&#34;&gt;Grünfeld Defense&lt;/a&gt; setup. Carlsen attempted to place his remaining undeveloped piece, the Queen Knight, on a more active square than the more &amp;ldquo;natural&amp;rdquo; square that would have overprotected the c4 Pawn, but Anand punished this by immediately attacking the c4 Pawn, resulting in Carlsen basically having to play moves that enabled Anand to choose to repeat the position for a draw.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Carlsen had no choice but to take the draw or stand clearly worse, so he bailed out. The question then is, should Anand tried to continue playing for a win, since it was his choice to take the draw or not?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a match situation at this level, typically the player as Black is quite happy to take a draw, so it made sense for Anand to do so. It was possible for Anand to not force the draw, at the cost of loosening up his own Queen side, but why play in this risky way, as defending champion?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-game&#34;&gt;The game&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below is the game with annotations. My task was made easy in this case because it was such a short and clear game, without much complexity. I hope it will be harder in subsequent games in the match!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;link href=&#34;../../chess/pgn4web/template.css&#34; type=&#34;text/css&#34; rel=&#34;stylesheet&#34;&gt;&lt;/link&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;style type=&#34;text/css&#34;&gt;
  #GameLastComment {
    font-style: italic
  }
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;script src=&#34;../../chess/pgn4web/pgn4web.js&#34; type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;
    &#34;use strict&#34;;

    SetPgnUrl(&#34;/chess/anand-carlsen.pgn&#34;);
    SetImagePath(&#34;/chess/pgn4web/images&#34;);
    SetHighlightOption(true);
    SetCommentsIntoMoveText(true);
    SetCommentsOnSeparateLines(true);
    SetInitialGame(1);
    SetShortcutKeysEnabled(true);
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
    &lt;tr valign=&#34;top&#34;&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;
        &lt;div id=&#34;GameBoard&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div id=&#34;GameButtons&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Move comment:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;span id=&#34;GameLastComment&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;/td&gt;

      &lt;td&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Event:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameEvent&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Site:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameSite&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Round:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameRound&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Date:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameDate&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;White:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameWhite&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Black:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameBlack&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Result:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameResult&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Side to move:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameSideToMove&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Last move:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameLastMove&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp; &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;variations:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameLastVariations&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;Next move:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameNextMove&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp; &lt;span class=&#34;label&#34;&gt;variations:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span id=&#34;GameNextVariations&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;hr/&gt;

&lt;div id=&#34;GameText&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>