<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Diet on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/diet/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Diet on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/diet/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Improving my breakfast and other meals: a paleo progress report</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/01/26/improving-my-breakfast-and-other-meals/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jan 2012 09:40:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/01/26/improving-my-breakfast-and-other-meals/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the past couple of months, I&amp;rsquo;ve made some large changes in my diet. Fundamentally, I&amp;rsquo;ve moved in a &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/paleo/&#34;&gt;paleo&lt;/a&gt; direction. The largest change was breakfast, where I completely gave up my old breakfast and &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/03/one-of-these-breakfasts-is-not-paleo/&#34;&gt;replaced it&lt;/a&gt;. After some experimentation, I&amp;rsquo;ve finally arrived at a breakfast template that seems optimal for me (as gauged by my morning energy level and other criteria I discuss below).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an example, here is what I ate this morning:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/breakfast-with-prune.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Breakfast with flax seeds and prune&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The ingredients, and what has changed, and why:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;recipe&#34;&gt;Recipe&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; tsp &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.organicfacts.net/organic-oils/organic-coconut-oil/health-benefits-of-coconut-oil.html&#34;&gt;coconut oil&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2 &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/28/thankful-for-the-free-range-orange-yolked-eggs/&#34;&gt;eggs&lt;/a&gt;, fried&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; clove of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.garlic-central.com/garlic-health.html&#34;&gt;garlic&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;some shakes of seasoning mix (salt, pepper, etc.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a dash of turmeric&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;some red pepper flakes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;butternut squash&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;spinach&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;uncooked &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.traderjoes.com/how-to/olive-oil.asp&#34;&gt;extra virgin olive oil&lt;/a&gt; on top of the veggies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;about 7 walnuts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 tsp &lt;a href=&#34;http://lowcarbdiets.about.com/od/whattoeat/a/flaxinfo.htm&#34;&gt;flax seeds&lt;/a&gt;, sprinkled on top of everything at the end&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 prune on the side&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;changes-and-rationale&#34;&gt;Changes and rationale&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;carbs&#34;&gt;Carbs&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I stopped my short experiment of eating potatoes or rice with breakfast because I found that my morning energy level was simply better without those high-glycemic carbs. I think there is a legitimate place for such carbs, but not in my current schedule, which does not (yet) include intensive exercise before breakfast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;additions&#34;&gt;Additions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I now always eat two eggs, instead of one. One wasn&amp;rsquo;t really enough to make me feel satisfied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recently added coconut oil, which I had not been using because some past experiments did not work out well. I think that was because of using too much. So I&amp;rsquo;m not using much now. Amusingly, my main use of coconut oil up till now has been to rub onto my skin during this dry winter season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve added more spices such as turmeric and hot red pepper to my breakfast because I like them and because they seem to give me a little wake-up boost and stimulate alertness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The flax seeds are new, as well as the prune. The prune is probably not &amp;ldquo;paleo&amp;rdquo;, according to someone or other, but as I&amp;rsquo;ve mentioned before, I get confused by the different paleo schools of thought, and I don&amp;rsquo;t follow any of them, but just use them as practical sources of ideas for self-experimentation. I have a very specific rationale for the use of flax seeds and prunes: I have to confess that I dealt with constipation issues when initially moving away from my big oatmeal breakfast to my paleo-style breakfast. I tried various solutions, but one that seems to have worked is the addition of flax seeds (which I typically only add for breakfast, but sometimes will also do for another meal too) and the prune. I have had no constipation issues since adding these to my breakfast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;other-meals&#34;&gt;Other meals&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been trying to kick my &amp;ldquo;addiction&amp;rdquo; to rice. I have gradually decreased my consumption of rice (white or brown). Almost imperceptibly, my craving for it has decreased continually. It&amp;rsquo;s now been a couple of days since I have been doing without rice for lunch, but I am still eating it for dinner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still love pizza, and have not yet eliminated it. It&amp;rsquo;s very hard to avoid both convenience and temptation when it&amp;rsquo;s provided at talks and meetings. However, on days when I plan to eat pizza, I have tried to get my metabolism up before eating it. That seems to help. I&amp;rsquo;ll still keep in my mind the idea of giving up pizza.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My experimentation with diet have continued over the months, and will continue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope my report may be of use to you if you are considering changing up your breakfast patterns away from the &amp;ldquo;standard&amp;rdquo; American sugary breakfasts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do you eat for breakfast that works for you? What do you similarly or differently from me?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why soda bans don&#39;t work</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/11/07/why-soda-bans-dont-work/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Nov 2011 19:13:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/11/07/why-soda-bans-dont-work/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I just saw an article, &lt;a href=&#34;http://well.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/11/07/soda-bans-in-schools-have-limited-benefit/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Soda Bans in Schools Have Limited Impact&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. It boggles my mind that anyone would advocate soda bans in school as a policy in isolation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are my thoughts on the economics and politics, and health and cultural aspects of the issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;economics-101&#34;&gt;Economics 101&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The article describes the empirical results from soda bans:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Students were drinking other sugary beverages instead&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Students were bringing in their own sugary beverages&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;economics&lt;/em&gt; of the situation are obvious:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are plenty of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Substitute_good&#34;&gt;substitute goods&lt;/a&gt; for soda that satisfy students&amp;rsquo; demand for sugary beverages.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Since the school is not a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Monopoly&#34;&gt;monopoly&lt;/a&gt;, and there are plenty of other &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Supply_(economics)&#34;&gt;suppliers&lt;/a&gt; of soda and other sugary beverages outside of school, all that happens is that students buy from another supplier.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basic economic theory has a way to reduce consumption of sugary beverages, of course: a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pigovian_tax&#34;&gt;Pigovian tax&lt;/a&gt; such as the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sin_tax&#34;&gt;sin tax&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cigarette_taxes_in_the_United_States&#34;&gt;cigarettes&lt;/a&gt;. A tax on the entire category of sugary beverages would do the trick. There is reason to believe the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Price_elasticity_of_demand&#34;&gt;price elasticity&lt;/a&gt; is sufficient that such a tax would considerably reduce consumption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;politics-101&#34;&gt;Politics 101&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And such a wide-ranging tax is completely impossible, politically. Even an overall &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Soda_tax&#34;&gt;soda tax&lt;/a&gt; is, I believe, politically impossible. Worse, it would not solve the problem, because as we know from the school example, there are other sugary beverages that pose the very same health problems but are not labeled as &amp;ldquo;soda&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;bigger-picture-of-economics&#34;&gt;Bigger picture of economics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Worse, the &lt;em&gt;problem&lt;/em&gt; as narrowly defined, that of decreasing consumption of sugary beverages, is only the tip of the iceberg when it comes to the bigger picture of public health. People will eat cookies and any number of other less perfect substitutes for sugary beverages anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;beyond-economics-to-health&#34;&gt;Beyond economics to health&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the purported motivation for reducing sugary beverages has been to reduce obesity. Obesity happens for all kinds of reasons. Worse, I don&amp;rsquo;t even like the focus on &lt;em&gt;weight&lt;/em&gt;. Poor health has to do with a lot more than weight. Most people, when thinking about their weight, and try to lose it, don&amp;rsquo;t even apply healthy strategies to lose weight, or even to do so permanently rather than temporarily. I don&amp;rsquo;t believe stopgap politically controversial initiatives can do much to address the real problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;culture-and-a-personal-note&#34;&gt;Culture and a personal note&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am bombarded daily with access to sugary beverages. Every time I go to a lunch seminar or party or reception, cans and bottles of soda, sports beverages, juices, and sweetened teas are provided. Clearly American culture is simply not ready to give up on these beverages. I get the impression that I am in the minority in choosing not to drink them. I have had maybe &lt;em&gt;four or five&lt;/em&gt; cans or bottles of such beverages in the past ten years. I get the impression that a lot of people I see around have had approximately &lt;em&gt;ten thousand&lt;/em&gt; cans or bottles in the past ten years. I don&amp;rsquo;t lecture people on why they should abstain, because it is useless even when directed toward, say, my own parents. I don&amp;rsquo;t know what it will take for the culture to change, or what I can do to help. Right now, I just silently abstain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you have any suggestions of what I could really do to help spread the word that life really might be more enjoyable without consuming sugary beverages all the time?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>