<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Quitting on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/quitting/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Quitting on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/quitting/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Quitting the CMU All-University Orchestra: one of the hardest decisions in my life</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/03/12/quitting-the-cmu-all-university-orchestra-one-of-the-hardest-decisions-in-my-life/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Mar 2012 22:45:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/03/12/quitting-the-cmu-all-university-orchestra-one-of-the-hardest-decisions-in-my-life/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s the Monday after what would have been the regular Sunday evening CMU All-University Orchestra rehearsal, except that there was no rehearsal because of Spring Break.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surprise (or not)!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have decided to immediately &lt;em&gt;quit&lt;/em&gt; the CMU AUO that I had &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/02/01/joining-an-orchestra-learning-in-the-face-of-terror/&#34;&gt;just joined less than two months ago&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have already told everyone that I&amp;rsquo;m quitting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t like quitting. I don&amp;rsquo;t like being a quitter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what&amp;rsquo;s the story? And what next?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;orchestra-morale-problems&#34;&gt;Orchestra morale problems&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Five days ago, I reported on &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/07/flute-taking-a-break-while-clarifying-my-goals/&#34;&gt;problems in the orchestra&lt;/a&gt; and deciding that I would probably quit the orchestra after the spring term is over. The memories of that have lingered in my mind. And my relief yesterday at not having rehearsal was a real message to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2012-03-21&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-03-21)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maria just sent the mailing list (which I&amp;rsquo;m still on despite having quit the orchestra) an email saying, &amp;ldquo;It seems that over spring break we may have lost much of what we did in the first portion of the semester.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No kidding. As I had observed earlier, people clearly just weren&amp;rsquo;t taking practice seriously. They probably didn&amp;rsquo;t touch their instruments when they went on spring break. I&amp;rsquo;m so glad I quit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;personal-musical-goals&#34;&gt;Personal musical goals&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past couple of days while off the hook on orchestral practice, I had an opportunity to think about &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/10/flute-loving-it-again/&#34;&gt;what I actually love about music, and what role I want it to play in my life&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;a-chance-opportunity&#34;&gt;A chance opportunity&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that Abby and I have just been invited to a St. Patrick&amp;rsquo;s Day party by Henry, whose &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/01/27/a-new-friends-very-musical-birthday-party-changed-my-life/&#34;&gt;birthday party less than two months ago&lt;/a&gt; had so moved me musically (and right after I had joined the AUO). I was so eager to attend that I asked Henry whether I should bring a tin whistle and play some Irish music, and he said, sure! I had promised myself after his birthday party that if we were ever invited to a party by him, I would play music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;brute-reality&#34;&gt;Brute reality&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, I can no longer deny the reality: being in an orchestra is &lt;em&gt;completely contrary&lt;/em&gt; to the kind of musical life I actually enjoy and want. I need to play music of my choice, I want to improvise, I want to play in small groups. The task of mastering some difficult flute parts in a big orchestral work and being a tiny part of a performance, &lt;em&gt;does not appeal to me at all&lt;/em&gt;, even if I could do it well (which I currently cannot at all).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a concrete example: I could spend my time this week slogging away at AUO music practice, or I could be learning some tunes on tin whistle so that I can play them on Saturday at Henry&amp;rsquo;s party and have a blast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s no comparison, whether in the short term or in the long term.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But emotionally, it&amp;rsquo;s just tough to quit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-did-i-really-ever-hope-to-get-out-of-orchestra&#34;&gt;What did I really ever hope to get out of orchestra?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think part of me hoped that somehow, being in an orchestra was a standard rite of passage that a &amp;ldquo;serious&amp;rdquo; musician should do. When I was a kid, I was kind of envious that classmates joined the school orchestra, while I remained out of music entirely. My younger sister played violin in various orchestras in middle school and in high school and college.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But now it occurs to me that not much of what I could get out of orchestra would help me with my real musical goals anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-art-of-quitting&#34;&gt;The art of quitting&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a policy of never just &lt;em&gt;quitting&lt;/em&gt; something, but &lt;em&gt;replacing&lt;/em&gt; the void instead. &lt;em&gt;Quitting&lt;/em&gt; is negative. &lt;em&gt;Replacing&lt;/em&gt; is positive. In my case, quitting orchestra frees up a considerable amount of time to work toward my real musical goals. Instead of fruitlessly working on difficult flute parts that are currently beyond my capabilities, and beyond my interests, I can focus on gradually improving at the music I do want to play, and building the technique necessary, without arbitrary deadlines like some big concert.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;resources&#34;&gt;Resources&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the United States, we are constantly bombarded with messages in the media and general culture not to be a &amp;ldquo;quitter&amp;rdquo;. And I got that a lot from my parents (who came from Taiwan) when I was a kid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My current point of view: &lt;em&gt;not learning to be an effective quitter was the single worst mistake of my first decades in life&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some articles that really resonated with me about the benefits of quitting correctly:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.projecthappilyeverafter.com/2009/03/sometimes-its-better-to-be-a-quitter/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Sometimes it&amp;rsquo;s better to be a quitter&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cormackcarr.com/2009/12/05/how-to-be-a-quitter/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;How to be a quitter&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s never easy for me to quit something. Part of me always feels like I failed, wasn&amp;rsquo;t good enough, wasn&amp;rsquo;t courageous enough, or something like that. Maybe sometimes that is actually true. But other times, it clearly is not. All signs point to quitting orchestra as the best thing I can do now for my flute playing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-is-your-own-relationship-to-quitting&#34;&gt;What is your own relationship to quitting?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is your gut reaction when hearing about someone quitting (like me just now), or when considering quitting something yourself? Is your &lt;em&gt;gut reaction&lt;/em&gt; one of disdain and shame, or of liberation? Is this a result of your upbringing, or the nature of your relationships with peers? Is it a deliberate rational philosophical position? Or is primarily emotional, based on either moral sentiment or ego?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When was the last time you quit and felt &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt; about it? When was the last time you quit and felt &lt;em&gt;bad&lt;/em&gt; about it? When was the last time you quit and &lt;em&gt;at the time&lt;/em&gt; felt one way, but later felt you had made the wrong decision?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>