<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Sleep on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/sleep/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Sleep on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/sleep/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Report on my third day of Stoic Week 2014: self-discipline and Stoic simplicity</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/27/report-on-my-third-day-of-stoic-week-2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2014 11:03:44 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/27/report-on-my-third-day-of-stoic-week-2014/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There is a reason I&amp;rsquo;m a little late in reporting on my third day of Stoic Week 2014: the theme, self-discipline and simplicity, had me cut short my intended plan of writing and publishing my thoughts at the end of each day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;health-and-self-control&#34;&gt;Health and self-control&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today&amp;rsquo;s reading for Stoic Week 2014 had us reflect on the importance of physical health and self-control in our daily routine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the third day in a row, I did a morning ten-minute sitting meditation, and noticed that my posture and breathing have improved. It took three days to notice this. It will take weeks to notice even more improvements; I know this because I&amp;rsquo;m a backslider, rather than one completely new to meditation. I imagine it must be much harder for a newcomer to adopt a practice like this where patience is required in order to experience the benefits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also kicked it up a notch with exercise. I mentioned in &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/11/25/report-on-my-second-day-of-stoic-week-2014/&#34;&gt;yesterday&amp;rsquo;s report&lt;/a&gt; that I need to do more weight training. I&amp;rsquo;m on that now. I&amp;rsquo;m making exercise a priority for the next several months in my life, at least.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve still been pretty good about refraining from unhealthy snacks. On &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/11/24/report-on-my-first-day-of-stoic-week-2014/&#34;&gt;day one&lt;/a&gt;, I noted that my work colleague brought back snacks from his first trip to Asia and I chose not to eat any of them. I opened up the bag of chips, but ate only a couple of them (in the past I have given into temptations, when confronted with a bag of chips, to eat the whole bag) and stashed the rest away. (By the way, the chips were unexceptional, tasting not much different than ordinary American potato chips, and the ingredients list was scary, with many weird chemicals included.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;sleep&#34;&gt;Sleep&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I haven&amp;rsquo;t been good with my sleep habits. I tend to stay up too late on the computer, for example. Abby wants me to have a &amp;ldquo;computer off plan&amp;rdquo; for my daily routine, but I&amp;rsquo;ve found this difficult because I like to work on personal projects (such as writing) on the computer and I find the time in the evening. I know the benefits of the &amp;ldquo;natural&amp;rdquo; life, and I&amp;rsquo;m sure Stoics would promote being a morning person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the point of this report isn&amp;rsquo;t to talk about becoming a morning person, or even so much about sleep. It&amp;rsquo;s about self-control. The reality is, yesterday when I came home from work, I was very tired. &amp;ldquo;Sleep when sleepy&amp;rdquo; is so logical and natural, yet I find that American culture does not value sleep. It seems countercultural to sleep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, I decided to simplify the evening and choose to stay off the computer (hence not writing this article). Apart from Wednesday evening being designed &amp;ldquo;us night&amp;rdquo; for Abby and me anyway, I decided that before sleeping, I would read (physical books and paper printouts) instead of use the computer, until ready to sleep. I did end up sleeping earlier. I did miss having the use of the computer to look up stuff that would have been helpful in my reading, but for this evening, at least, it was a tradeoff in favor of simplicity rather than stimulation. I&amp;rsquo;ll have to think about how to arrange my life differently if I want to continue to be more targeted in using the computer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Self-discipline and simplicity are not popular in American culture, which prizes maximization and stimulation. I don&amp;rsquo;t find it easy to maintain self-discipline, and am grateful to Stoic Week to remind me of its benefits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Is your gut impression of Stoic teachings that they want to take the fun out of your life, or that they are a guide to the truly good life? What is the balance you purposefully adopt between self-indulgence and renunciation?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My promise to prioritize my sleep</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/12/my-promise-to-prioritize-my-sleep/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Oct 2013 22:33:48 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/12/my-promise-to-prioritize-my-sleep/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Despite my knowledge (both firsthand and from reading research results) that sleep is important to healthy living, I have been failing to get my optimal sleep for a long time now. There are several reasons of this, but I am taking steps to address each one of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;too-many-activities&#34;&gt;Too many activities&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I began the process of catching up on sleep today by sleeping almost all day. Abby and I had yesterday decided to cancel our hiking plan for today because we both felt tired and decided it was a good time to just rest. We both have a bad habit of doing too many activities and not getting enough down time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I already mentioned some of the things I&amp;rsquo;m scaling down on: &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/10/04/final-rehearsal-for-my-first-ukulele-gig/&#34;&gt;musical activities&lt;/a&gt;. Today was the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.coolhanduke.com/&#34;&gt;Cool Hand Uke&lt;/a&gt; workshop and concert, both of which I had decided earlier to skip.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;night-time-distractions&#34;&gt;Night time distractions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not sleeping as early or deeply as I should, because of not turning down the lights and getting off the computer at night. I&amp;rsquo;m going to change that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In particular, social media at night are the worst. My decision today to &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/10/12/taking-a-break-from-twitter/&#34;&gt;take a break from Twitter, Facebook, and Google+&lt;/a&gt; will help a lot. Too much stimulation at night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;exercise&#34;&gt;Exercise&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a symbiotic relationship between sleep and exercise: the better the sleep, the more energy for stimulating exercise, and the more exercise, the more ready the body is to sleep in the evening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, after I slept almost all day, I found myself with energy to go for a run (I&amp;rsquo;ve barely been running in the past week). To my surprise, I effortlessly kept going and going, and ended up doing ten miles, no problem, in Frick Park and Summerset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was huge confirmation to me, that just catching up on sleep enabled me to enjoy a ten-mile run when I&amp;rsquo;ve barely been feeling like running at all in the past week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-2013-10-12/1.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-2013-10-12/2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-2013-10-12/3.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-2013-10-12/4.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-2013-10-12/5.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-2013-10-12/6.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m going to keep up good habits in order to improve my life. Sleep is the number one priority that I believe will benefit everything else.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>