<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Powerbook on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/powerbook/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Powerbook on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/powerbook/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>My PowerBook 145B</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/11/14/my-powerbook-145b/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Nov 2011 20:51:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/11/14/my-powerbook-145b/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not sure what to do with my old Apple Macintosh &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/PowerBook_140#PowerBook_145B&#34;&gt;PowerBook 145B&lt;/a&gt; laptop. It still boots, but is obviously not of much use to me any more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here it is booting &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/System_7&#34;&gt;System 7&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/powerbook-145b/booting-system-7.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;PowerBook 145B booting System 7&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The machine had crashed years ago before I booted it:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/powerbook-145b/last-crashed.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;PowerBook 145B booting after crash&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Finally, boot is complete:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/powerbook-145b/finder.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;PowerBook 145B up in System 7 Finder&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Some personal history and observations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This PowerBook 145B was the second laptop I owned; the first was a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/PowerBook_Duo&#34;&gt;PowerBook Duo&lt;/a&gt; that I bought used, found problematic, and sold. I also bought the 145B used. I didn&amp;rsquo;t splurge and buy a new Mac till the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Power_Macintosh_6100&#34;&gt;Power Macintosh 6100&lt;/a&gt; in 1995.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With only 2 MB (that&amp;rsquo;s no typo; these days computers come with &lt;em&gt;one thousand times&lt;/em&gt; as much RAM, more like 2 GB typically), it was necessary to monitor memory usage and quit unused applications. It was a mistake upgrading to System 7.5 on this machine, I have to admit. And with a 40 MB hard drive, I was always having to put stuff onto floppies. I bought software like RAM Doubler and Disk Doubler and Speed Doubler, but they were obviously not a panacea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still, I got stuff done with this laptop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eventually, the battery refused to hold any more real charge, and since the adapter connection got flaky, that is why the last time I used the laptop, it suddenly just lost power and shut down uncleanly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I already threw away all my floppies years ago, and there is no network card for the laptop, so it really is useless now. I have a cute ADB-based 28.8k modem that I used with the laptop for many years. I even browsed the Web, having &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mosaic_%28web_browser%29&#34;&gt;Mosaic&lt;/a&gt; installed, although I preferred using &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MacWeb&#34;&gt;MacWeb&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I haven&amp;rsquo;t seriously used this laptop since 1998, when I was still taking it with me on travel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My PowerBook 145B is such a museum piece now. What should I do with it? Wipe the hard drive and donate it somewhere, or keep around myself to amuse the millennial generation who are now babies playing with iPads?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>