<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Nsa on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/nsa/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Nsa on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/nsa/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Observing Constitution Day with &#34;The Supreme Court and Privacy: The Fourth Amendment in the Digital Age&#34;</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/09/17/observing-constitution-day-with-the-supreme-court-and-privacy-the-fourth-amendment-in-the-digital-age/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2014 21:54:01 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/09/17/observing-constitution-day-with-the-supreme-court-and-privacy-the-fourth-amendment-in-the-digital-age/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have a habit of observing Constitution Day every year by attending a presentation at CMU and thinking about issues relating to the Constitution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year (2013), &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/09/17/on-not-celebrating-constitution-day-this-year&#34;&gt;I was too disheartened to observe Constitution Day but wrote a little bit about why&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year, I returned because the topic for discussion sounded interesting: &lt;a href=&#34;http://thebridge.cmu.edu/organization/SLO/calendar/details/466499&#34;&gt;Mary Jo Miller gave a talk &amp;ldquo;The Supreme Court and Privacy: The Fourth Amendment in the Digital Age&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; in the Posner Center. (Miller is a Staff Attorney for the Pennsylvania State Education Association and an adjunct professor in Carnegie Mellon&amp;rsquo;s Social and Decision Sciences Department.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/franklinmingchen/15274305882&#34; title=&#34;IMG_20140917_163751 by Franklin Chen, on Flickr&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3836/15274305882_f0eaf5d8fb.jpg&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; height=&#34;375&#34; alt=&#34;IMG_20140917_163751&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-fourth-amendment-http-en-wikipedia-org-wiki-fourth-amendment-to-the-united-states-constitution&#34;&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fourth_Amendment_to_the_United_States_Constitution&#34;&gt;fourth amendment&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
The right of the people to be secure in their persons, houses, papers, and effects, against unreasonable searches and seizures, shall not be violated, and no warrants shall issue, but upon probable cause, supported by oath or affirmation, and particularly describing the place to be searched, and the persons or things to be seized.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mary Jo Miller gave an entertaining and instructive talk in which she discussed various rulings by the Supreme Court involving interpretations of the fourth amendment in various circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, she reminded us that the fourth amendment came about because of the colonialists&amp;rsquo; bad experiences with England when arbitrary searches of people&amp;rsquo;s home happened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then she argued that although it is popularly held that there is a &amp;ldquo;conservative&amp;rdquo; (&amp;ldquo;originalist&amp;rdquo;) wing of the Supreme Court (typified currently by Scalia) and a &amp;ldquo;liberal&amp;rdquo; (&amp;ldquo;living Constitution&amp;rdquo;) wing (typified in the past by Stevens), on fourth amendment issues, they are not always split. In fact, she gave examples of where the Court was unanimous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The primary concern by the Court has been to respect (in the absence of probable cause) the doctrine that &amp;ldquo;each man&amp;rsquo;s home is his castle&amp;rdquo;. Miller gave examples involving surveillance of a marijuana grower&amp;rsquo;s home through a heat detector, as well as examining the contents of a drug dealer&amp;rsquo;s cell phone, as being judged a violation of fourth amendment rights because of what can be considered one&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;home&amp;rdquo;: a cell phone is actually a computer containing much of one&amp;rsquo;s possession, so it is in fact one&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;home&amp;rdquo; and requires a proper warrant in order to search it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s about the &amp;ldquo;exclusionary rule&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;fruits of the poison tree&amp;rdquo;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/franklinmingchen/15271576131&#34; title=&#34;IMG_20140917_164820 by Franklin Chen, on Flickr&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5596/15271576131_6c4a8f4d5f.jpg&#34; width=&#34;375&#34; height=&#34;500&#34; alt=&#34;IMG_20140917_164820&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-about-the-nsa&#34;&gt;What about the NSA?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After almost an hour, I had to leave, and therefore did not stay for questions and answers. I would have asked about what the current thinking is by the Court about NSA surveillance. When is information far enough removed that it is no longer considered one&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;home&amp;rdquo;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did enjoy this year&amp;rsquo;s Constitution Day observance at CMU. Mary Jo Miller gave an excellent talk discussing various Supreme Court rulings and different aspects of the fourth amendment.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On not celebrating Constitution Day this year, 2013</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/09/17/on-not-celebrating-constitution-day-this-year/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2013 08:42:26 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/09/17/on-not-celebrating-constitution-day-this-year/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;For several years, I&amp;rsquo;ve made a habit of observing &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Constitution_Day_(United_States)&#34;&gt;Constitution Day&lt;/a&gt; by attending the annual exhibit and lecture at CMU. Last year I reported on &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/18/is-constitution-day-constitutional/&#34;&gt;an interesting session about the very invention of Constitution Day&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://events.web.cmu.edu/ecal/event/137831259599848837&#34;&gt;This year&lt;/a&gt;, the program for the event &lt;a href=&#34;http://cmlibblog.wordpress.com/2013/08/13/constitution-day-celebration/&#34;&gt;held at the Posner Center&lt;/a&gt; at CMU read:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
David Harris, distinguished faculty scholar and professor of law at the University of Pittsburgh School of Law, will deliver a keynote speech titled &#34;How Will America Be Remembered? A Constitution Day Journey Into the Future&#34; at approximately 3:30 p.m. Light refreshments will be served. An original copy of the Bill of Rights will be on display.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ended up deciding not to attend today, for several reasons. One is that I have a lot of stuff to get done at work right now. But even if that weren&amp;rsquo;t the case, my heart was not into celebrating Constitution Day this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-will-america-be-remembered&#34;&gt;How will America be remembered?&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/6/60/Edward_Snowden-2.jpg/199px-Edward_Snowden-2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Because the story is still far from over, I haven&amp;rsquo;t said much on my blog about the events that have been unfolding for some months now since &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_Snowden&#34;&gt;Edward Snowden&lt;/a&gt; exposed information about the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2013_mass_surveillance_disclosures&#34;&gt;surveillance activities of the National Security Agency&lt;/a&gt;. He &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.theguardian.com/world/2013/jul/12/edward-snowden-full-statement-moscow&#34;&gt;explained his actions as justified by the violation of the 4th and 5th Amendments to the Constitution&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
The 4th and 5th Amendments to the Constitution of my country, Article 12 of the Universal Declaration of Human Rights, and numerous statutes and treaties forbid such systems of massive, pervasive surveillance. While the US Constitution marks these programs as illegal, my government argues that secret court rulings, which the world is not permitted to see, somehow legitimize an illegal affair. These rulings simply corrupt the most basic notion of justice -- that it must be seen to be done. The immoral cannot be made moral through the use of secret law.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I do a Web search for &amp;ldquo;Edward Snowden&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Constitution&amp;rdquo;, I mostly find pro-Snowden articles that affirm his point of view of the NSA programs as being unconstitutional. Here is &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.newsworks.org/index.php/blogs/brandywine-to-broad/item/56244-nsa-leaks-by-edward-snowden-threaten-constitutional-self-government&#34;&gt;one exception&lt;/a&gt; you may wish to read.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find it interesting that much of the media coverage of Edward Snowden&amp;rsquo;s actions do not actually reference his claim of unconstitutionality, but focus on other matters, such as the nature of his education or possible ulterior motives for leaking, or whether his actions may prove harmful to national security or other interests. These may be interesting and important questions, but sidestep his primary claim and stated motive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;too-early-to-tell&#34;&gt;Too early to tell&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did not attend the &lt;a href=&#34;http://wesa.fm/post/us-constitution-224-years-later-why-it-endures&#34;&gt;David Harris&lt;/a&gt;, although it might have been interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think Snowden&amp;rsquo;s actions and their repercussions will add an extra twist to the age-old question of whether the Constitution is to be interpreted under &amp;ldquo;original intent&amp;rdquo; or as a &amp;ldquo;living document&amp;rdquo;, and even whether the Constitution should be &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2012/12/31/opinion/lets-give-up-on-the-constitution.html&#34;&gt;abandoned&lt;/a&gt;, if interpretations either way simply come to be seen as purely political game-playing to justify &amp;ldquo;constitutional&amp;rdquo; as simply meaning &amp;ldquo;what I like&amp;rdquo;. The most interesting thing right now is that prominent voices on both the &amp;ldquo;left&amp;rdquo; and the &amp;ldquo;right&amp;rdquo; (the libertarian wing) have united in denouncing the activities of the NSA as unconstitutional.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not a political blog, and political theory is not my main area of interest or advocacy, but I thought it would be useful to make a few observations about current events for Constitution Day.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>