<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Stoic Week on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/stoic-week/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Stoic Week on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/stoic-week/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Report on my final day of Stoic Week 2014: the view from above</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/30/report-on-my-final-day-of-stoic-week-2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2014 22:16:07 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/30/report-on-my-final-day-of-stoic-week-2014/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s the seventh and final day of Stoic Week 2014! I am very glad I participated in the daily readings and reflections. I&amp;rsquo;ve made so many positive changes in my life already. Now it&amp;rsquo;s time to stick to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;health&#34;&gt;Health&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been spending all of the Thanksgiving long holiday weekend catching up on sleep. I have a meditation habit now and today it was warm out and I went for a run and ended up doing five miles in Frick Park. This is the longest distance I&amp;rsquo;ve run in months!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;nature-providence-the-larger-whole&#34;&gt;Nature, providence, the larger whole&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is fitting that today&amp;rsquo;s theme is the Stoic view of humanity as being embedded in something bigger, call it &amp;ldquo;nature&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;providence&amp;rdquo;. Part of why I enjoy running in the trails of Frick Park is that in its own small way, the experience puts me in touch &lt;em&gt;directly&lt;/em&gt; with something bigger than us; I encounter dogs, chipmunks, trees, creeks, leaves, mud, and even deer (not today, but Abby and I saw one during our hike there yesterday).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I honestly feel more whole and alive when I see more of nature, and not in some self-conscious sentimental way. It&amp;rsquo;s more subtle than that. And there&amp;rsquo;s nothing sentimental about those steep hills that make me gasp for air when I climb them. But I sure appreciate the cleaner air in the park than on the main urban roads of Pittsburgh! And I remember where air comes from and how fragile its quality and composition is. The big picture matters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am grateful for the organizers of Stoic Week for putting it on again this year. Here is something I&amp;rsquo;ve decided to do, to keep its spirit alive indefinitely: I will continue to explore various interpretations of Stoicism (note that I don&amp;rsquo;t feel compelled to buy into any particular school or even call myself a Stoic at all), as well as other philosophy (for example, the Zen I had begun looking into years ago) on a daily basis, to keep my mind always focused on applying principles of practical living.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Did you hear about Stoic Week this year? If you did, why did you choose to participate in it, or more interestingly, choose not to?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Report on my sixth day of Stoic Week 2014: preparing for adversity</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/29/report-on-my-sixth-day-of-stoic-week-2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Nov 2014 18:37:25 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/29/report-on-my-sixth-day-of-stoic-week-2014/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I guess death is the ultimate adversity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;whose-death-and-how-and-what-next&#34;&gt;Whose death and how and what next?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I fear death. Not only for myself, but for Abby, for her parents, for my parents, for our friends. We knew older people who have died even this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today&amp;rsquo;s Stoic theme, &amp;ldquo;preparing for adversity&amp;rdquo;, is particularly relevant to us because not only are our parents aging and already actively preparing for &amp;ldquo;what next&amp;rdquo; if they were to die or get sick and incapacitated, and trying to talk to us about such things, but also because being married, we need to have clear plans and instructions in case one of us suddenly goes. We are not invincible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;decluttering&#34;&gt;Decluttering&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing that makes us anxious is that there&amp;rsquo;s too much clutter in the house, and also clutter in the form of many random online accounts that we need to keep track of. We&amp;rsquo;ve seen how deaths in our families have caused a lot of trouble to survivors because of unfinished business, stuff left behind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel that part of preparing &lt;em&gt;mentally&lt;/em&gt; for adversity is preparing &lt;em&gt;in reality&lt;/em&gt; for adversity. I would have much more peace of mind if I knew that everything would continue as smoothly as possible at home and at work if I suddenly died.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So today I continued on a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/19/really-taking-up-the-challenge-of-minimalism/&#34;&gt;long-interrupted project&lt;/a&gt; of decluttering at home. I dug up old college course notes, exercise log books from a decade ago, and other stuff I just don&amp;rsquo;t need. Dozens of books I no longer read. I filled boxes of stuff to recycle or have Abby donate to the library. I am committed to leaving nothing accidental behind if I die, only what is purposeful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, we don&amp;rsquo;t have wills or the like yet. Time to get cracking on that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;adversity-more-generally&#34;&gt;Adversity, more generally&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel that &amp;ldquo;negative thinking&amp;rdquo; is very useful and that I could do more of it. As a software developer, anticipating failure modes helps me write better and more confident code. Playing chess, I know firsthand that wishful thinking results in big crashes when things don&amp;rsquo;t go your way. Teaching chess, I like to set up unpleasant situations and have the student struggle (in a safe, low stakes environment) to defend, as practice for real tournament chess when the strength to deal with the unexpected is a key to success in competition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;daily-habits&#34;&gt;Daily habits&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, I did meditate and exercise (more dumbbell and body weight strength training) today. Recall that yesterday I had a setback. The advantage of having once had a successful exercise routine is that when I think clearly, I am prepared for adversity, having faced it before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I appreciate the curious technique of envisioning and simulating future catastrophe in order to enable acting more calmly today. Figuring out death seems the ultimate challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How do you feel about the technique of deliberately imagining bad things? Does this seem perverse to you? Or useful?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Report on my fifth day of Stoic Week 2014: action and the reserve clause</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/28/report-on-my-fifth-day-of-stoic-week-2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2014 23:20:43 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/28/report-on-my-fifth-day-of-stoic-week-2014/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I had some setbacks today, the fifth day of Stoic Week, but dealt with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-coconut-oil-accident-yesterday-at-thanksgiving-party&#34;&gt;A coconut oil accident yesterday at Thanksgiving party&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the time we left &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/11/27/report-on-my-fourth-day-of-stoic-week-2014/&#34;&gt;yesterday&amp;rsquo;s Thanksgiving party&lt;/a&gt; in the evening, I wasn&amp;rsquo;t feeling so well. I had blamed eating that one cookie and also drinking a bit of spicy warm cider, but as unpleasant symptoms developed (you don&amp;rsquo;t need to know the details), I immediately knew what must have happened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A bit of history, years ago I experimented with &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/01/26/improving-my-breakfast-and-other-meals/&#34;&gt;using coconut oil&lt;/a&gt; but found that I could tolerate only a little bit, and in fact quickly decided to just not use it any more in cooking, after some incidents in which I experienced very unpleasant symptoms after a meal and found out that Abby had used a good amount of coconut oil in cooking. We had her limit the use of coconut oil in cooking anything I was to eat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it had been quite some time since I experienced those symptoms, but unfortunately, I suffered for over twelve hours with poor sleep overnight, and can only conclude that a large mount of coconut oil was used in Thanksgiving dinner!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-system-temporarily-wrecked-illustrating-today-s-theme&#34;&gt;My system temporarily wrecked, illustrating today&amp;rsquo;s theme&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I not only woke up late in the morning today, but was also still suffering physically, was hungry nonetheless, and grouchy. Normally I try to start my day with meditation, but I just wanted to eat breakfast. Abby had gotten up hours before me and was annoyed I had gotten up late, and snapped at me while I was bleary-eyed and trying to start eating breakfast. I snapped back, and she got very upset and disappeared.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While eating, I recognized that I had gone totally non-Stoic, and so after I finished eating and reading today&amp;rsquo;s theme on &amp;ldquo;action and the reserve clause&amp;rdquo;, I immediately went to meditate for ten minutes before talking with her again, in a much calmer mood, explaining what had been happening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went back to napping, and then before lunch time, after my final visit to the toilet, I finally felt like my coconut oil disaster was truly over and I could start my day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I felt I had &amp;ldquo;failed&amp;rdquo; in that, contrary to Stoic teaching, I had let my physical distress take over my mind and everything I was doing. I could have dealt better with my situation, acting the best I could despite my circumstance rather than giving into my foul mood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &amp;ldquo;reserve clause&amp;rdquo; in Stoicism refers to how we &lt;em&gt;act&lt;/em&gt; even though we may not like what has happened or what might happen. I did not start the morning with this attitude.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;exercise&#34;&gt;Exercise&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I eventually made up, but it really bothered me that I had started off the day so badly. I was also feeling like my muscles were trashed from yesterday&amp;rsquo;s workout (and party play with the two sisters). Later in the afternoon, we went for a hike in Frick Park and both felt better. I considered that my &amp;ldquo;exercise&amp;rdquo; for the day, a lower-intensity day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a setback in my practice of Stoicism but recovered, with even more appreciation for daily reading and study to get back on track.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How do you deal with setbacks? Do you have a system, a philosophical principle, to keep you on track?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Report on my fourth day of Stoic Week 2014: virtue and relationships with others</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/27/report-on-my-fourth-day-of-stoic-week-2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2014 21:47:45 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/27/report-on-my-fourth-day-of-stoic-week-2014/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today was Thanksgiving in the US, a surprisingly appropriate day to be in the middle of observing Stoic Week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;thanksgiving-dinner&#34;&gt;Thanksgiving dinner&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/11/27/report-on-my-third-day-of-stoic-week-2014/&#34;&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve reported on yesterday&amp;rsquo;s theme&lt;/a&gt; of self-discipline and simplicity. At Thanksgiving dinner this year, I decided for the very first time to limit what I ate. I&amp;rsquo;ve always overeaten in the past, with poor results. It was just something I did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year, I did not eat any of the cake or pumpkin pie that was offered. For dessert (after the turkey etc.), I limited myself to one scoop of pistachio gelato and one cookie. Actually, I ended up regretting that cookie, because it was more substantial and sugary than I expected, so I&amp;rsquo;ve made a note to watch myself with the cookies. The gelato I may not have needed, but I enjoyed it all the more knowing it was the one main dessert I was allowing myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;fourth-day-of-health-habits&#34;&gt;Fourth day of health habits&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s my fourth day now of daily meditation and exercise. Actually, I overdid it on the exercise today, but not intentionally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been increasing the intensity of my short (seven-minute or so) daily workouts every day, lifting heavier weights and working more muscles. What I didn&amp;rsquo;t expect was that at the Thanksgiving party, two young sisters (of ages around five and two) were bored and wanted to play, and I rather exerted myself. The older one was the ringleader. We played at scaring each other and I pretended to be sitting on the couch sleeping and suddenly spring up and boo or growl, and I accidentally pulled something in my right arm during one of these explosive, sudden movements. I also pulled my left shoulder when the two challenged me to lift them repeatedly, and the older one (tall for her age) was heavier than I expected and not so easy to repeatedly lift, given that I&amp;rsquo;d already had a workout in the morning at home. All in good fun, but left me a bit overextended.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;on-today-s-theme&#34;&gt;On today&amp;rsquo;s theme&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find sensible the Stoic teaching of developing our &amp;ldquo;natural affection&amp;rdquo;, and expanding outward from ourselves. I feel I have been the beneficiary of much good from many people in my life and am grateful for this. The Thanksgiving dinner that Abby and I went to today is one we have attended for some years now. The hosts I met through Abby, who met them (and other dinner guests) through music and dance circles. I appreciate and deeply admire the generosity that they have shown us and to many others. I look up to them as role models for the kind of genuine affection that human beings can display and share, not only with immediate family or closest friends but outward to larger communities (such as local music communities) and beyond.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tragic shooting and death that happened this year in &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shooting_of_Michael_Brown&#34;&gt;Ferguson, Missouri&lt;/a&gt; has been in the news for some months now, and this week the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shooting_of_Michael_Brown#Announcement_of_no_bill&#34;&gt;grand jury decided not to indict&lt;/a&gt;. I haven&amp;rsquo;t commented in public or in private on any of these events, or on any of the commentary about them, but I do not dismiss what has happened as irrelevant to my life. In fact, I feel that what has happened has been so important, in the biggest possible picture of what has been going on in American history for a long time, that I cannot afford to lightly spew sound bites about it. I do ask myself, how can I best talk about what I am feeling? How can I make a positive difference, in the Stoic &amp;ldquo;cosmopolitan&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;love of all humanity&amp;rdquo;? I don&amp;rsquo;t know the answer yet, but I know what is not the answer: fanning the flames of passion. But simply being silent is also not the answer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2015-01-19&#34;&gt;(Update of 2015-01-19)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wrote something in &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2015/01/19/for-martin-luther-king-jr-day-some-black-american-voices-that-spoke-to-me-recently/&#34;&gt;observation of Martin Luther King, Jr. Day&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I take seriously the Stoic call that we are ethically responsible for more than just ourselves, that we are to develop ourselves outward (not just on inner virtues) and work to honestly consider all human beings our brothers and sisters. I see how I have been treated in such a way by others through my life and aspire to expand beyond myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How do you feel about cosmopolitanism? Do you feel it is naive, that it is best to just look out after family and clan? If you have been following the Ferguson tragedy, do you easily choose a simple &amp;ldquo;side&amp;rdquo;, an &amp;ldquo;us&amp;rdquo; versus &amp;ldquo;them&amp;rdquo;?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Report on my third day of Stoic Week 2014: self-discipline and Stoic simplicity</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/27/report-on-my-third-day-of-stoic-week-2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2014 11:03:44 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/27/report-on-my-third-day-of-stoic-week-2014/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There is a reason I&amp;rsquo;m a little late in reporting on my third day of Stoic Week 2014: the theme, self-discipline and simplicity, had me cut short my intended plan of writing and publishing my thoughts at the end of each day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;health-and-self-control&#34;&gt;Health and self-control&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today&amp;rsquo;s reading for Stoic Week 2014 had us reflect on the importance of physical health and self-control in our daily routine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the third day in a row, I did a morning ten-minute sitting meditation, and noticed that my posture and breathing have improved. It took three days to notice this. It will take weeks to notice even more improvements; I know this because I&amp;rsquo;m a backslider, rather than one completely new to meditation. I imagine it must be much harder for a newcomer to adopt a practice like this where patience is required in order to experience the benefits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also kicked it up a notch with exercise. I mentioned in &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/11/25/report-on-my-second-day-of-stoic-week-2014/&#34;&gt;yesterday&amp;rsquo;s report&lt;/a&gt; that I need to do more weight training. I&amp;rsquo;m on that now. I&amp;rsquo;m making exercise a priority for the next several months in my life, at least.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve still been pretty good about refraining from unhealthy snacks. On &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/11/24/report-on-my-first-day-of-stoic-week-2014/&#34;&gt;day one&lt;/a&gt;, I noted that my work colleague brought back snacks from his first trip to Asia and I chose not to eat any of them. I opened up the bag of chips, but ate only a couple of them (in the past I have given into temptations, when confronted with a bag of chips, to eat the whole bag) and stashed the rest away. (By the way, the chips were unexceptional, tasting not much different than ordinary American potato chips, and the ingredients list was scary, with many weird chemicals included.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;sleep&#34;&gt;Sleep&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I haven&amp;rsquo;t been good with my sleep habits. I tend to stay up too late on the computer, for example. Abby wants me to have a &amp;ldquo;computer off plan&amp;rdquo; for my daily routine, but I&amp;rsquo;ve found this difficult because I like to work on personal projects (such as writing) on the computer and I find the time in the evening. I know the benefits of the &amp;ldquo;natural&amp;rdquo; life, and I&amp;rsquo;m sure Stoics would promote being a morning person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the point of this report isn&amp;rsquo;t to talk about becoming a morning person, or even so much about sleep. It&amp;rsquo;s about self-control. The reality is, yesterday when I came home from work, I was very tired. &amp;ldquo;Sleep when sleepy&amp;rdquo; is so logical and natural, yet I find that American culture does not value sleep. It seems countercultural to sleep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, I decided to simplify the evening and choose to stay off the computer (hence not writing this article). Apart from Wednesday evening being designed &amp;ldquo;us night&amp;rdquo; for Abby and me anyway, I decided that before sleeping, I would read (physical books and paper printouts) instead of use the computer, until ready to sleep. I did end up sleeping earlier. I did miss having the use of the computer to look up stuff that would have been helpful in my reading, but for this evening, at least, it was a tradeoff in favor of simplicity rather than stimulation. I&amp;rsquo;ll have to think about how to arrange my life differently if I want to continue to be more targeted in using the computer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Self-discipline and simplicity are not popular in American culture, which prizes maximization and stimulation. I don&amp;rsquo;t find it easy to maintain self-discipline, and am grateful to Stoic Week to remind me of its benefits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Is your gut impression of Stoic teachings that they want to take the fun out of your life, or that they are a guide to the truly good life? What is the balance you purposefully adopt between self-indulgence and renunciation?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Report on my second day of Stoic Week 2014: mindfulness</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/25/report-on-my-second-day-of-stoic-week-2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2014 23:50:38 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/25/report-on-my-second-day-of-stoic-week-2014/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, I reported on my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/11/24/report-on-my-first-day-of-stoic-week-2014/&#34;&gt;first day of Stoic Week 2014&lt;/a&gt;. Today, the second day&amp;rsquo;s theme was &amp;ldquo;Stoic mindfulness&amp;rdquo;. This is similar to the Buddhist teaching on mindfulness, and is basically a sound psychological observation that &amp;ldquo;You are just an impression and not at all the thing you claim to represent&amp;rdquo;: our thoughts and feelings are one thing but what we do about them is another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found it particularly useful to remember this today, because Tuesdays present an interesting challenge for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;chess&#34;&gt;Chess&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Tuesday nights, I have been playing in the latest 6-round current Tuesday night &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburghcc.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Chess Club&lt;/a&gt; tournament, one round every Tuesday. Tonight was round 4. I had experienced an extremely painful loss last week in round 3 when I was &lt;em&gt;not mindful&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://chessimprover.com/blockading-to-defend-when-things-get-tough/&#34;&gt;got carried away by emotions&lt;/a&gt;: I had an overwhelming advantage during an attack on my opponent&amp;rsquo;s King, but I allowed my excitement to cloud my judgment, make poor moves, and then worse, after I managed to recover and had the opportunity to survive with a draw, &lt;em&gt;and saw this&lt;/em&gt;, I passed it up out of wishful thinking that I could continue an attack, so I ended up losing. In chess, I face the stark reality that most losses at my level in local competition (where I am typically the top-rated player) are due to faulty psychology, rather than lack of sufficient understanding and skill. A loss of &lt;em&gt;objectivity&lt;/em&gt; (which all athletes and other performers under high pressure) is the reason we fail. Mindfulness directly addresses this all-too-human flaw.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;continuing-habits-from-yesterday&#34;&gt;Continuing habits from yesterday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, I noted that I began meditating and exercising again, because it was in my power to do so. I have continued. It&amp;rsquo;s been tricky to get going again, because my body is out of whack, but I remember to do what I can, no more, with faith that incremental progress will pay off. Instead of running, I did a &lt;a href=&#34;http://well.blogs.nytimes.com/projects/workouts/&#34;&gt;7-minute workout&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;ve lost a lot of strength over the years and plan to regain it. I have dumbbells lying around the house from when I was using them a decade ago; it&amp;rsquo;s time to get back to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;tonight-s-chess-game&#34;&gt;Tonight&amp;rsquo;s chess game&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I won a decent game tonight at the chess tournament. It was the third last to finish, taking almost four hours. I&amp;rsquo;ve played against my opponent many times before over the years, mostly winning, but the last time I played him, he held me to a draw, despite a 500-rating-point difference (which is huge). One thing that sometimes happens in tournament chess is overconfidence when facing someone who is on paper much weaker, or fear because of a past bad result. Mindfulness teaches us that although historical facts are facts, we should distance ourselves from distracting feelings about them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As in many hard-fought chess games, I experienced a range of emotions during the game. First of all, in the opening, although I was doing OK, I was frustrated that I allowed a certain kind of position I ordinarily do not allow, because of an oversight. Instead of kicking myself, I focused to do what I could with what I had, assessing that even though I did not want that position, it was actually still OK for me. (Actually, computer analysis afterwards showed that I was more than OK, so I was still more pessimistic than warranted during the game.) In the middlegame, I emerged with an advantage, but then faced a curious choice. My opponent gave me an opportunity to win some material (a Rook for a Bishop and Pawn) at the expense of destroying my Pawn structure and therefore creating good chances for a draw. At the time, I saw no better winning try, so I went for it, deciding that, unlike last week, I was going to settle for a draw if my opponent could prove he could defend; I simply made sure to play soundly and not recklessly. It turned out that he cracked eventually and I won. I was pleased that I remained psychologically strong in the game and was rewarded accordingly. (For those of you interested in the technical details of the game, I will be annotating it in an upcoming article I will write for &lt;a href=&#34;http://chessimprover.com/category/franklin-chen/&#34;&gt;my weekly column in The Chess Improver&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;heavy-traffic&#34;&gt;Heavy traffic&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another thing: when driving home from work to eat dinner before the chess game, I noticed that the traffic was unusually bad. Mindfulness is always helpful when facing stressful situations like this. I was upset with myself for not anticipating apparent pre-Thanksgiving-holiday traffic and therefore being pressed for time to get home and eat dinner before playing chess. I decided to let go of my self-annoyance because it wasn&amp;rsquo;t going to help me get home any sooner and would just sap my mental energy I needed for my game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mindfulness is something I&amp;rsquo;ve had prior experience in trying to adopt well before I even read about Stoicism. But having a daily theme and reading during Stoic Week has been surprisingly helpful in keeping me aware.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Are you familiar with the concept of mindfulness and the scientific underpinnings of it? If so, do you deliberately practice it? Do you have misgivings about it?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Report on my first day of Stoic Week 2014</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/24/report-on-my-first-day-of-stoic-week-2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2014 22:30:51 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/24/report-on-my-first-day-of-stoic-week-2014/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Last year, I heard about the first Stoic Week, &lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.exeter.ac.uk/stoicismtoday/stoic-week-2013/&#34;&gt;Stoic Week 2013&lt;/a&gt;, but did not participate because I was distracted at the time and did not feel like focusing. This week, I decided it was time to sign up for &lt;a href=&#34;http://modernstoicism.com/course/view.php?id=5&#34;&gt;Stoic Week 2014&lt;/a&gt;, and I did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-my-interest-in-stoicism&#34;&gt;Why my interest in Stoicism?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve mentioned Stoicism only briefly in my blog: once in 2012 when &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/11/22/thanking-the-best-of-all-possible-worlds/&#34;&gt;thinking about Thanksgiving&lt;/a&gt; and once earlier this year after &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/01/17/hiroo-onoda-and-the-six-million-dollar-man/&#34;&gt;rewatching an old TV episode&lt;/a&gt;. As I mentioned, it was in 2011, upon reading a book on Stoicism, that I made some major changes in my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that a couple of weeks ago, I decided to make major changes in my life again, but not while thinking about Stoicism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over a year ago, my meditation practice fell apart, and I never really regained it. As a result, my thoughts and habits have become disordered, I have felt. For example, I stopped writing regularly for my blog. I spent too much time on Facebook and Twitter instead, being distracted, annoyed, and worse, behaving in ways that I later came to feel counterproductive. I did &amp;ldquo;quit&amp;rdquo; Facebook in July, and also &amp;ldquo;quit&amp;rdquo; Twitter some weeks ago (part of the big life changes I set in motion), but still, I have felt ungrounded. I decided Stoic Week 2014 would be a good opportunity for me to return to the contemplative life that Buddhism and Stoicism in their different ways aspire to and that I had forgotten.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-i-did-the-first-day-of-stoic-week-2014&#34;&gt;What I did the first day of Stoic Week 2014&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, as I started the first day of Stoic Week 2014, I began by meditating ten minutes, Zen style. &lt;em&gt;This was my first meditation session in weeks&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I read the assigned text for today in the Stoic Week handbook, on &amp;ldquo;What is in our power?&amp;rdquo; A basic principle of Stoicism is that we should know what is under our control and what is not, and summarily refuse to dwell on or resent what is not under our control, and focus on making good decisions about what is under our control. A very simple but powerful concept, especially in a world in which it is easy to get annoyed or angry about many things we hear about in the news or encounter in our daily lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My exercise habit has been very spotty for months now. Well, today I reflected that, what the hell, it is completely under my control whether I choose to exercise or not, so why am I wasting this precious freedom? Some people don&amp;rsquo;t have this freedom. Others, including prisoners in jail, have little freedom but make use of what they have, and &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/17/the-joys-of-convict-conditioning-bodyweight-exercising/&#34;&gt;they exercise&lt;/a&gt;! It happened to be warm outside today, so I really had no excuse. I went for a run in Frick Park. It was short, less than three miles long, but I went. &lt;em&gt;This was my first run in weeks&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was my turn to cook today at home, so I made a substantial beef casserole dish. Abby has (rightfully) complained in the past when I didn&amp;rsquo;t completely clean up after cooking. Well, today I thought to myself that it is completely within my control whether I choose to attend to the details of cleanup as much as I attend to the details of using our skillets and baking pans. So I cleaned up as well as I could.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have not been feeling very well physically for weeks now since an incident involving emergency dental work that somehow resulted in complications. I am still in recovery. OK, so it is not under my control that I am not in good health right now. But what is under my control? After lunch I took a nap, because I felt like I needed it. I have been skimping on naps, but this is stupid, because I know that sleep is the best restorative practice when ill. It is under my control whether I choose to set aside time to sleep as needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At work, a colleague just came back from his first trip in Asia. He gave me samples of some odd snacks: chips, cookies, and candy. In recent months, I would have opened them up and eaten them on the spot. Indeed, I have been having problems with eating too many snacks for no rational reason. Today, I decided that it is up to me whether I choose to give in to random cravings or temptations, and so I chose to put the snacks aside for later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After work, I went to a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/Pittsburgh-Code-Supply/events/210396972/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Code and Supply Build Night&lt;/a&gt;, where food was served. Apart from a Thanksgiving dinner (!), some kind of cake lurked around. I took one glance, and chose not to even look at it again until leaving (when it was already all eaten).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leaving Build Night, I found myself annoyed that it was taking forever for the pedestrian light to change, but caught myself and observed that, first of all, the cycle is as it is, beyond my control; and second, I had mistakenly assumed that someone had pressed the button, so it was my fault I had to wait so long. I pressed the button and eventually got to cross. Next, while driving home, I made the mistake of driving behind a bus, which kept stopping. I got annoyed, not by the bus, but by myself, for mistakenly driving on the wrong street rather than the other one that does not have this problem; I got annoyed that I was too lazy to make a U-turn on the street I was parked on in order to get to that other street. But I stopped myself when I realized that what was done was done, and I simply had to endure the rest of the drive home behind the bus because it was not going to save any more time if I detoured around it late in the game: the best I can do is to be more careful in the future when making choices while driving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I felt I improved my life today by keeping in mind the fundamental Stoic principle of observing what is not under my control and what is under my control. I look forward to continuing to adopt this outlook for the rest of the week, and beyond that.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>