<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Guitar on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/guitar/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Guitar on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/guitar/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Accidentally discovering and performing some music by Brazilian composer Ernesto Nazareth: Coração que Sente</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/12/29/accidentally-discovering-and-performing-some-music-by-brazilian-composer-ernesto-nazareth-cora%C3%A7%C3%A3o-que-sente/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Dec 2015 23:05:10 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/12/29/accidentally-discovering-and-performing-some-music-by-brazilian-composer-ernesto-nazareth-cora%C3%A7%C3%A3o-que-sente/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In November, I fell in love with some music I accidentally discovered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What happened was that I was looking for some music for &lt;em&gt;flute&lt;/em&gt; and
&lt;em&gt;guitar&lt;/em&gt; to play, with me on flute and one of my friends on guitar, and
I did a simple search in the
&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/30/free-to-the-people-since-1895/&#34;&gt;local library&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://librarycatalog.einetwork.net/&#34;&gt;online catalog&lt;/a&gt;, and at the top
sorted by date was
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.halleonard.com/product/viewproduct.action?itemid=49044167&amp;amp;&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Brazilian folk tunes for flute and guitar&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;,
which came with a CD of sample performance tracks,
so I picked it up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What followed was a series of explorations that resulted in unexpected
changes in my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;exploring-the-brazilian-music-in-the-score-book&#34;&gt;Exploring the Brazilian music in the score book&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I listened to some tracks on the CD of this book of arrangements and
found the music (Brazilian polkas, tangos, waltzes) really
enchanting. Most of the music was by a composer
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ernesto_Nazareth&#34;&gt;Ernesto Nazareth&lt;/a&gt;,
who lived 1863-1934. I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t call this music &amp;ldquo;folk tunes&amp;rdquo;: it&amp;rsquo;s
a sophisticated combination of popular and classical styles using
catchy dance rhythms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m a real sucker for waltzes, so at first I thought I would pick one
of the beautiful waltzes to choose to suggest to play with a partner
on guitar. It came down to &amp;ldquo;Confidências&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;Coração que Sente&amp;rdquo;
(English translation: &amp;ldquo;Heart that Feels&amp;rdquo;). The
latter was much easier and shorter, as I learned while sight reading
through it with the CD track, so I thought I was done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;finding-astounding-performances-of-coração-que-sente-on-youtube&#34;&gt;Finding astounding performances of &amp;ldquo;Coração que Sente&amp;rdquo; on YouTube&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking for performances of the piece on YouTube to get an idea of
how people play it, I immediately entered a strange new world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, I learned that the original music was for
&lt;em&gt;piano&lt;/em&gt;. OK. Then, while listening to and/or watching a dozen or so
videos of performances of this piece (OK, I was obsessed), I found a
huge variety of interpretations, and some of them spoke to me more
than others. Some I found light and boring. The ones that interested
me were the ones that were extremely intense and probing. You might
think this music was just fluff, but I found a dark undercurrent
behind it that spoke to me, in that its different sections (the piece
is roughly in rondo form) present clear emotional contrasts, with
longing, melancholy, and manic excitement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;arthur-moreira-lima&#34;&gt;Arthur Moreira Lima&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A very intense performance I found was by a pianist named
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arthur_Moreira_Lima&#34;&gt;Arthur Moreira Lima&lt;/a&gt;
in 1975, used after the fact as soundtrack on YouTube for a silent
film using footage from 1929. What an odd pairing!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lima goes all out in Romantic expressiveness, with extensive rubato
and dynamic and rhythmic flexibility. It was completely different from
the relatively straight, danceable version on the flute/guitar CD
demo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have to listen to his performance (ignore the film or watch it, as
you wish):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Mmjt8RrfXtA&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;joão-carlos-assis-brasil&#34;&gt;João Carlos Assis Brasil&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even more extreme than Lima was this weird guy João Carlos Assis
Brasil, who is apparently so unknown in the English-speaking world
that Wikipedia doesn&amp;rsquo;t have an entry on him, although I found this
random
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bach-cantatas.com/Bio/Assis-Brasil-Joao-Carlos.htm&#34;&gt;pieced-together bio&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His live performance here from 2013 is the single most extreme, yet
deepest, interpretation of this waltz I found (he adds his own
ornamentation). I was deeply moved by it. (Warning, bad sound
quality.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/iG_o94sU1tE&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;other-good-performances&#34;&gt;Other good performances&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://pt.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fernanda_Chaves_Canaud&#34;&gt;Fernanda Canaud&lt;/a&gt;,
with a very expressive performance (including her own extensive
embellishments), uses drastic changes in articulation and tempo for
contrast. I particularly liked how naturally she seemed to express her
personality through the piece:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/-DfOYvNCaqk&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://pt.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maria_Teresa_Madeira&#34;&gt;Maria Theresa Madeira&lt;/a&gt;
captures well the moods of the different sections of the piece; I
really like the rhythmic alertness and drive throughout:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/eeztzLsF6Cc&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some random YouTube guy named Ilton, playing a really crappy upright
piano, but with amazing rhythmic expression that I totally love (if he
played this on a good piano, I would consider his interpretation one
of my favorites, period):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/b-gYk_YUoIM&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://lucianoalves.com.br/&#34;&gt;Luciano Alves&lt;/a&gt;, 2013, in an elegant
performance:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/y8LchR8Mi5Y&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://pt.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marcelo_Bratke&#34;&gt;Marcelo Bratke&lt;/a&gt; in a
relaxed, easygoing, dream interpretation with a lilt (but after all
the intense interpretations, I find this tame, I confess):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Pn5vYhfQYHs&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-performance-that-made-me-decide-to-learn-and-play-the-piece&#34;&gt;The performance that made me decide to learn and play the piece&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I spent a lot of time listening to and watching performances of the
piece, but one performance was the one that made me decide to go learn
and play the piece! It was this one by some random guy Marcelo Chiarella:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/QaQL9VlJy8s&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why? Because I could &lt;em&gt;relate to&lt;/em&gt; his playing:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;He wasn&amp;rsquo;t some famous pro pianist, as far as I could tell.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The sound quality was good and the recording was as though I were
standing right there, made me feel like I was in his home, and
nobody else there.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I could see his hands up close.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I liked various things he did with expression (especially when he
&lt;em&gt;wasn&amp;rsquo;t&lt;/em&gt; pedaling).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I knew that I could be much more expressive and personal
(remember, the title in English translation is &amp;ldquo;Heart that feels&amp;rdquo;)
while playing this piece &lt;em&gt;solo&lt;/em&gt;, on piano, than in a flute/guitar
duet. So I decided to go for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;finding-an-official-free-score&#34;&gt;Finding an official free score&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had to find a score. Luckily, it turned out that there was some
big
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ernestonazareth150anos.com.br/&#34;&gt;150-year anniversary celebration for Ernesto Nazareth&lt;/a&gt;
in 2013, and I found an official &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ernestonazareth150anos.com.br/files/uploads/work_elements/work_43/coracao_que_sente_piano.pdf&#34;&gt;free PDF score&lt;/a&gt; on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ernestonazareth150anos.com.br/works/view/43&#34;&gt;page for the piece&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That page also had a story about the title of the piece and why it was
composed. It was in Portuguese, so I tried with the help of Google
Translate to translate it (I only studied Portuguese for several weeks
many years ago), and pieced together (I hope I didn&amp;rsquo;t get this too
wrong) that Nazareth dedicated it to a student of his, Gabriella
Crauz, who had showed great emotion as Nazareth described the last
days of a dying nephew, as though she had been there herself
experiencing what he experienced as he saw the sights in the city one
last time. (If you know Portuguese, please correct me if I got the
story wrong.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This story only added to the sense I already had that this seemingly
simple piece hid a depth of emotion that some performers already
revealed for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-performance-of-coração-que-sente&#34;&gt;My performance of &amp;ldquo;Coração que Sente&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I started working on the piece, I had to decide where and when to
perform it. It turned out that I learned that friends who mean a lot
to me decided to move. This was really tough news to me, and they have
always invited me and Abby to their December holiday party, where I
play music, so I decided that I was going to perform the piece at
their (now farewell) party and openly dedicate my performance to them,
because they are human beings of deep feeling, hence &amp;ldquo;Heart that
feels&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I performed the piece at the party the day after Christmas. In my
nervousness, I completely lost my train of thought a couple of times
and botched things up inexplicably (I had gone through the piece with
no errors so many times at home), but I made it through, and my
gesture was appreciated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I then decided to quickly record myself at home soon after (and still
botched some things up), so here I am. This is for Henry and Gina:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34;
src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/VBOS9btMUPI&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;
allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;other-music-by-ernesto-nazareth&#34;&gt;Other music by Ernesto Nazareth&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spent all this time talking about just one piece by Nazareth, but he
wrote much more, and more substantial pieces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I totally love Fernanda Canaud&amp;rsquo;s performance of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ernestonazareth150anos.com.br/works/view/133&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Batuque&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, &amp;ldquo;Coração
que Sente&amp;rdquo;, and
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ernestonazareth150anos.com.br/works/view/136&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Odeon&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;
(the performance of &amp;ldquo;Coração que Sente&amp;rdquo; is very different from the one
I posted above: more inward, refined, beautiful rather than super-dramatic):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/U6WaAgRWqaw&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is Nazareth playing his own pieces in recordings from 1912-1930:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/eZS3bDNJEUY&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a one-hour special documentary video &amp;ldquo;Nazareth Revisitado&amp;rdquo;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/TJAT3pJJR6M&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-note-on-the-english-language-oriented-web&#34;&gt;A note on the English-language-oriented Web&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found a whole world of music and musicians that barely register in
the English-language-oriented part of the Web. Most of what I found
when trying to look up Nazareth or various Brazilian pianists was in
Portuguese. So it&amp;rsquo;s been really humbling to remember that many in the
English-speaking world might not even know about all these Brazilian
composers and musicians who are not big enough stars to warrant
international fame.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am grateful for accidentally discovering an entire world of
Brazilian music and performers of it through my search in the local
library catalog for music to play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am grateful for friends who inspire me by their examples as human
beings of genuine and great feeling.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Third year at July 3 music party and finally participated in jamming</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/07/03/third-year-at-july-3-music-party-and-finally-participated-in-jamming/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jul 2014 22:11:59 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/07/03/third-year-at-july-3-music-party-and-finally-participated-in-jamming/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;The past two years, Abby and I have gone to an annual July 3 music potluck/party, and we went again this year. Both &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/03/petrified-at-a-music-jam-session-so-i-didnt-play-but-watched-and-listened/&#34;&gt;in 2012&lt;/a&gt; as well as &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/07/03/second-year-at-july-3-music-party-still-only-listening-without-playing/&#34;&gt;in 2013&lt;/a&gt;, I was too intimidated to participate in music jamming, and only watched. This year I was determined to contribute, and I brought my ukulele (which I only started learning &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/08/23/another-unexpected-life-change-one-month-of-learning-to-play-ukulele/&#34;&gt;a month after last year&amp;rsquo;s party&lt;/a&gt;, actually) and my Irish flute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;piano&#34;&gt;Piano&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After my first round of food at the potluck, I went to Susan&amp;rsquo;s piano and played David Raksin&amp;rsquo;s theme from &amp;ldquo;Laura&amp;rdquo;, which I had so botched up last month at the annual Pittsburgh Recorder Society potluck/recital. I play it much better now, although I somehow messed up the final chords today. There were a few people sitting around listening, and they wanted to hear more, but I didn&amp;rsquo;t have any more, so I scurried away to eat more food.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;old-time&#34;&gt;Old time&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As dinner started winding down, the old time musicians started gathering outside to play. I saw fiddles, banjos, and other instruments make an appearance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;blues&#34;&gt;Blues&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inside, the main guy who plays guitar and ukulele unpacked his soprano ukulele, and so I took out my concert ukulele, and two other guys with guitars appeared. Eventually a woman who sang also appeared, as well as a guy on fiddle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I felt very intimidated, because although I&amp;rsquo;ve gotten some experience jamming while on recorder or flute or tin whistle, my ukulele experience &lt;em&gt;without written music&lt;/em&gt; is still very minimal. Nevertheless, I joined in. I fumbled around, and had to ask what key each song was being played in, and even then, I&amp;rsquo;m still quite shaky in anticipating and knowing chord changes beyond the simplest I, IV, V, and some dominant and major 7th chords. I strummed very softly.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/music-2014-07-04/jamming.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Music jamming&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;They&amp;rsquo;re a great bunch, improvising melodic lines at will and even making up lyrics right on the spot, just as they had at the last two years when I only watched. And the singing in harmony was fantastic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby got a little bit of video footage of us at one point:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/zYb1aBioAao&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For two years, I was afraid to join in the music jams at this annual July 3 party. This year I joined in a little bit. If we attend the party again next year, I hope to be in a position to contribute even more! Many thanks to Susan for hosting this annual party!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Second year at July 3 music party: still only listening without playing</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/07/03/second-year-at-july-3-music-party-still-only-listening-without-playing/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jul 2013 22:10:07 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/07/03/second-year-at-july-3-music-party-still-only-listening-without-playing/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/03/petrified-at-a-music-jam-session-so-i-didnt-play-but-watched-and-listened/&#34;&gt;Last year Abby and I went&lt;/a&gt; to a July 3 music potluck/party at Susan&amp;rsquo;s for the first time. We attended again. I brought my flute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again I enjoyed hearing two groups of people playing music. I am not so much into the &amp;ldquo;old time&amp;rdquo; music, however, which the group outside in the backyard was playing, so I hung out inside instead, where I liked much better the blues guitar and ukulele and singing and piano. &lt;em&gt;I would like to join in one day&lt;/em&gt; myself, but today did not feel up to it. I never took out my flute; it didn&amp;rsquo;t seem appropriate for any of the music anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2014-07-04&#34;&gt;(Update of 2014-07-04)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/07/03/third-year-at-july-3-music-party-and-finally-participated-in-jamming/&#34;&gt;my third year&lt;/a&gt; of this annual party, I actually played both piano and ukulele!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Oblivion obsession: time to start playing melodica!</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/12/02/oblivion-obsession-time-to-start-playing-melodica/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Dec 2012 21:32:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/12/02/oblivion-obsession-time-to-start-playing-melodica/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have been obsessed for some time with Piazzolla&amp;rsquo;s beautiful tango piece &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.astor-piazzolla.org/astor-piazzolla-oblivion/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Oblivion&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. I was planning to perform it some time on flute, but today, by accident, I decided that I want to play it on my &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.grothmusic.com/p-4654-hohner-s32-student-32-key-melodica.aspx&#34;&gt;melodica&lt;/a&gt; instead!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/hohner-student-32-melodica.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Hohner Student 32 Melodica&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-melodica-came-into-the-picture&#34;&gt;How melodica came into the picture&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This afternoon was the first rehearsal of the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/11/24/preparing-to-play-irish-flute-in-the-holiday-ball/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Holiday Ball Orchestra&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. (Today was also round 4 of the Pittsburgh Chess League team matches, but as I did once before for round 1, I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/16/excited-by-the-new-season-of-the-pittsburgh-recorder-society/&#34;&gt;prioritized music over chess&lt;/a&gt; and told the team I could not play.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the rehearsal, I played both flute and Irish flute, depending on the key. Afterward, while socializing, I happened to ask about the ukuleles that some people had. I mentioned that I still hadn&amp;rsquo;t gotten around to learning ukulele, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/11/learning-another-instrument-the-tin-whistle/&#34;&gt;despite having intended to&lt;/a&gt; and bought a soprano a long while back. I just found it very hard to get started with my first string instrument, and other things came up. I joked about the other instruments I have that I don&amp;rsquo;t play, including my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/01/run-shadyside-5k-outrunning-mickey-mouse-and-lending-a-trumpet/&#34;&gt;melodica&lt;/a&gt;. Lynette said in all seriousness that I was welcome to play it at the Holiday Ball.
So after I got home, I pulled out the melodica.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-is-the-melodica-good-for&#34;&gt;What is the melodica good for?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that I don&amp;rsquo;t think the melodica works well at all for the Holiday Ball music, actually. The instrument is not best at fast runs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;But&lt;/strong&gt;, since I had the instrument out: I decided to try playing it &lt;em&gt;in place of flute&lt;/em&gt; for some music I&amp;rsquo;ve been working on, such as tango and bossa nova. And I discovered that &lt;em&gt;melodica works great&lt;/em&gt; for these kinds of music! Then one thing led to another, and I was searching for covers of various songs on melodica on YouTube, and found quite a lot of cool performances by people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So now I&amp;rsquo;m completely serious about preparing to use my melodica in actual musical performances. Frankly, a lot of music I&amp;rsquo;ve been playing on flute sounds better with a darker, reeded instrument such as the melodica. For example, I&amp;rsquo;ve been playing jazzy bossa nova that I think really works best with a saxophone, but I don&amp;rsquo;t (yet!) play saxophone. The melodica works well as a substitute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In tango, of course, a bandoneón is the traditional instrument, and accordions are commonly used instead. Here, again, the melodica is great, for the melody line anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, other music that involves accordions or harmonicas work great with melodica as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;piazzolla-s-oblivion&#34;&gt;Piazzolla&amp;rsquo;s Oblivion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I am confessedly obsessed with &amp;ldquo;Oblivion&amp;rdquo;, here are some performances I found moving or otherwise useful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;flute-guitar&#34;&gt;Flute/guitar&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s Cavatina Duo on flute and guitar:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/sZD7aGqmO6w&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;melodica-with-chamber-group&#34;&gt;Melodica with chamber group&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is someone playing melodica:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/fG0TcCFUrBQ&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;melodica-and-piano-discovered-2013-08-22&#34;&gt;Melodica and piano (discovered 2013-08-22)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Japanese duo:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/AAP4GB8T8DI&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;accordion&#34;&gt;Accordion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s my friend Henry playing his solo arrangement for accordion:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/FrOHDEMOhkc&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;bandoneón-and-piano&#34;&gt;Bandoneón and piano&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Julian Rowlands and Ivo de Greef:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/sj-JUBIGKnE&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;violin-and-orchestra&#34;&gt;Violin and orchestra&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vesko Eschkenazy:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/kP6Vgm4k4xc&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;voice&#34;&gt;Voice&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wow. Wow. Milva singing French lyrics, Piazzolla himself on bandoneón!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/lzC1kKZGxBg&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;recorder-quartet-discovered-2013-08-22&#34;&gt;Recorder quartet (discovered 2013-08-22)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Japanese recorder quartet, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.geocities.jp/sekishirecorderquartet/english.htm&#34;&gt;Sekishi Recorder Quartet&lt;/a&gt;. Very nice!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/3PmaOyZNWo8&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;tango-dancers&#34;&gt;Tango dancers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, here are Daniela Pucci and Luis Bianchi dancing to the piece:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/RdU3eORpNhY&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, here is Daniela Pucci explaining why she gave up her MIT academic faculty career for tango:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/7BbAt1gnkBE&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are a tango fan, make sure to read Daniel Pucci&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.thedelicatestrength.com/?p=1522&#34;&gt;great article on tango dance connection&lt;/a&gt;. It is consonant with my own dance philosophy as well as music philosophy!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By accident, I have rediscovered the melodica, and now intend to work on it as a serious melodic instrument!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2014-10-23&#34;&gt;(Update of 2014-10-23)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/09/13/finally-playing-piazzollas-oblivion-on-flute/&#34;&gt;I put up more videos&lt;/a&gt; I found of &amp;ldquo;Oblivion&amp;rdquo; while thinking back to 2013 when I did play it on flute after all.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Attending the annual Pitt Jazz Seminar for the first time: day 1</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/11/02/attending-the-annual-pitt-jazz-seminar-for-the-first-time-day-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Nov 2012 23:53:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/11/02/attending-the-annual-pitt-jazz-seminar-for-the-first-time-day-1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.music.pitt.edu/sites/default/files/jazz-2012-cropped.jpg?1350921512&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;42nd Pitt Jazz Seminar poster&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This year I decided to attend events of the 42nd annual &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.music.pitt.edu/events/november-3-2012-42nd-annual-jazz-se120813&#34;&gt;Pitt Jazz Seminar&lt;/a&gt; for the first time. I&amp;rsquo;ve never had any instruction in jazz, and frankly have only a little bit of experience trying to play it myself, so I enjoyed the opportunity to attend presentations by great performers who could talk about what they do, where they&amp;rsquo;ve come from, and demonstrate their craft.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went in to Pitt campus on a Friday morning to learn from some master musicians.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;yotam-silbertein-http-yotammusic-com-guitar&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://yotammusic.com/&#34;&gt;Yotam Silbertein&lt;/a&gt;, guitar&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought it was interesting that an Israeli musician, Yotam Silbertein, kicked off the morning of seminars. Of course, as he emphasized in his talk, jazz is an international phenomenon. It happens in Israel, it happens in Japan, it happens in Europe. It may have started off in the United States, but it is everywhere now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, he did eventually have to head to New York, the place to be. He even speaks English with a New York style accent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He emphasized that it&amp;rsquo;s necessary to go where the action is and learn from the best.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;javon-jackson-http-www-javonjackson-com-tenor-saxophone&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.javonjackson.com/&#34;&gt;Javon Jackson&lt;/a&gt;, tenor saxophone&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Javon Jackson spoke a lot about being a professional in music: how you behave, how you work with others, and develop a career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, he pointed out that he wears a suit because it projects a professional image.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;that-s-it-for-the-day&#34;&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s it for the day&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was another session later in the afternoon, but I skipped it because I needed to return to work.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Living Appalachian music of Southwestern Pennsylvania: Mark Tamsula and Richard Withers with Ellen Gozion </title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/09/23/living-appalachian-music-of-southwestern-pennsylvania/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Sep 2012 22:15:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/09/23/living-appalachian-music-of-southwestern-pennsylvania/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As I periodically do, I went to the Carnegie Library of Pittsburgh on a Sunday afternoon to check out a musical event, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.clpgh.org/events/details.cfm?event_id=69114&#34;&gt;part of the regular World Kaleidoscope series&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.appalachianmusic.net/&#34;&gt;Mark Tamsula and Richard Withers&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://ellengozion.com/&#34;&gt;Ellen Gozion&lt;/a&gt; were there to perform some Appalachian music with very local southwestern Pennsylvanian roots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mark talked a good bit about going through the materials collected by the historian Samuel Bayard. It was interesting to me that his research in reviving the music that Bayard documented forced Mark to get more involved in reading music, since as a traditional musician he was used to learning everything by ear, but nobody is alive any more who originally played some of this music, and all that is left to document it is scores!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/appalachian-music/three.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Mark Tamsula, Richard Withers, Ellen Gozion&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/appalachian-music/irish-flute.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Richard Withers on Irish flute&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The two instrumentalists played quite a variety of instruments: fiddle, banjo, flute, guitar, harmonica, accordion, Irish flute. I enjoyed the variety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ellen Gozion sang some traditional ballads. She has a perfect voice and spirit for this music, singing with great purity and depth of emotional expression. Wow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the little concert, they promoted the new CD &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.upinthebattenhouse.com/&#34;&gt;Up in the Batten House&lt;/a&gt; and talked about upcoming projects.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>