<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Lost In Space on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/lost-in-space/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Lost In Space on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/lost-in-space/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>On rewatching a TV episode after over 30 years</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/04/23/on-rewatching-a-tv-episode-after-over-30-years/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Apr 2013 23:54:33 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/04/23/on-rewatching-a-tv-episode-after-over-30-years/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Over 30 years ago, when I was in elementary school in the 1970s, I watched the TV series &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lost_in_Space&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Lost in Space&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. It was very silly, but did engage my imagination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;nightmares&#34;&gt;Nightmares&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One episode haunted me for weeks and gave me nightmares, such that I remembered some scenes very clearly: it was the one in which I first encountered the term &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Antimatter&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;antimatter&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. For decades, once in a while I wondered whether I would ever get to see that episode again. I was particularly curious about whether my memories were accurate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;today&#34;&gt;Today&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that now, it is &lt;em&gt;probably&lt;/em&gt; possible to find any TV episode or even commercial that one saw in one&amp;rsquo;s childhood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, on a whim, I searched for the &amp;ldquo;Lost in Space&amp;rdquo; episode, and not only quickly identified it, but also watched it online for free!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0772539/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Anti-Matter Man&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, and I watched it on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.hulu.com/watch/23809&#34;&gt;Hulu&lt;/a&gt;. Of course, it was not really &amp;ldquo;free&amp;rdquo;, because I had to suffer through some ads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My memories turned out to be quite accurate, although of course not complete. &amp;ldquo;Evil&amp;rdquo; John Robinson was convincingly violent and evil, with the beatings and the cage. The landscape was stark and barren. The misty bridge between two worlds was as creepy as I remembered it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The episode was really quite a dark one, perhaps too dark for me at the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Needless to say, as one who eventually obtained a physics degree, I have to say that the whole scenario is complete nonsense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;future&#34;&gt;Future&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The temptation can be high to relive the past by rewatching old TV shows, the way I used to listen to old music recordings for sentimental reasons. I&amp;rsquo;ve almost completely resisted this temptation in the past several years, but sometimes it is illuminating to compare one&amp;rsquo;s memories with reality, and also reflect on the changes in taste or maturity.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>