<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Constitution Day on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/constitution-day/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Constitution Day on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/constitution-day/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>On not celebrating Constitution Day this year, 2013</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/09/17/on-not-celebrating-constitution-day-this-year/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2013 08:42:26 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/09/17/on-not-celebrating-constitution-day-this-year/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;For several years, I&amp;rsquo;ve made a habit of observing &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Constitution_Day_(United_States)&#34;&gt;Constitution Day&lt;/a&gt; by attending the annual exhibit and lecture at CMU. Last year I reported on &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/18/is-constitution-day-constitutional/&#34;&gt;an interesting session about the very invention of Constitution Day&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://events.web.cmu.edu/ecal/event/137831259599848837&#34;&gt;This year&lt;/a&gt;, the program for the event &lt;a href=&#34;http://cmlibblog.wordpress.com/2013/08/13/constitution-day-celebration/&#34;&gt;held at the Posner Center&lt;/a&gt; at CMU read:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
David Harris, distinguished faculty scholar and professor of law at the University of Pittsburgh School of Law, will deliver a keynote speech titled &#34;How Will America Be Remembered? A Constitution Day Journey Into the Future&#34; at approximately 3:30 p.m. Light refreshments will be served. An original copy of the Bill of Rights will be on display.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ended up deciding not to attend today, for several reasons. One is that I have a lot of stuff to get done at work right now. But even if that weren&amp;rsquo;t the case, my heart was not into celebrating Constitution Day this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-will-america-be-remembered&#34;&gt;How will America be remembered?&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/6/60/Edward_Snowden-2.jpg/199px-Edward_Snowden-2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Because the story is still far from over, I haven&amp;rsquo;t said much on my blog about the events that have been unfolding for some months now since &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_Snowden&#34;&gt;Edward Snowden&lt;/a&gt; exposed information about the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2013_mass_surveillance_disclosures&#34;&gt;surveillance activities of the National Security Agency&lt;/a&gt;. He &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.theguardian.com/world/2013/jul/12/edward-snowden-full-statement-moscow&#34;&gt;explained his actions as justified by the violation of the 4th and 5th Amendments to the Constitution&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
The 4th and 5th Amendments to the Constitution of my country, Article 12 of the Universal Declaration of Human Rights, and numerous statutes and treaties forbid such systems of massive, pervasive surveillance. While the US Constitution marks these programs as illegal, my government argues that secret court rulings, which the world is not permitted to see, somehow legitimize an illegal affair. These rulings simply corrupt the most basic notion of justice -- that it must be seen to be done. The immoral cannot be made moral through the use of secret law.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I do a Web search for &amp;ldquo;Edward Snowden&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Constitution&amp;rdquo;, I mostly find pro-Snowden articles that affirm his point of view of the NSA programs as being unconstitutional. Here is &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.newsworks.org/index.php/blogs/brandywine-to-broad/item/56244-nsa-leaks-by-edward-snowden-threaten-constitutional-self-government&#34;&gt;one exception&lt;/a&gt; you may wish to read.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find it interesting that much of the media coverage of Edward Snowden&amp;rsquo;s actions do not actually reference his claim of unconstitutionality, but focus on other matters, such as the nature of his education or possible ulterior motives for leaking, or whether his actions may prove harmful to national security or other interests. These may be interesting and important questions, but sidestep his primary claim and stated motive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;too-early-to-tell&#34;&gt;Too early to tell&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did not attend the &lt;a href=&#34;http://wesa.fm/post/us-constitution-224-years-later-why-it-endures&#34;&gt;David Harris&lt;/a&gt;, although it might have been interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think Snowden&amp;rsquo;s actions and their repercussions will add an extra twist to the age-old question of whether the Constitution is to be interpreted under &amp;ldquo;original intent&amp;rdquo; or as a &amp;ldquo;living document&amp;rdquo;, and even whether the Constitution should be &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2012/12/31/opinion/lets-give-up-on-the-constitution.html&#34;&gt;abandoned&lt;/a&gt;, if interpretations either way simply come to be seen as purely political game-playing to justify &amp;ldquo;constitutional&amp;rdquo; as simply meaning &amp;ldquo;what I like&amp;rdquo;. The most interesting thing right now is that prominent voices on both the &amp;ldquo;left&amp;rdquo; and the &amp;ldquo;right&amp;rdquo; (the libertarian wing) have united in denouncing the activities of the NSA as unconstitutional.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not a political blog, and political theory is not my main area of interest or advocacy, but I thought it would be useful to make a few observations about current events for Constitution Day.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is Constitution Day Constitutional?</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/09/18/is-constitution-day-constitutional/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Sep 2012 11:01:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/09/18/is-constitution-day-constitutional/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.cmu.edu/posner-center/exhibits/special-images/billrights1.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Bill of Rights at CMU&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Yesterday was &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Constitution_Day_(United_States)&#34;&gt;Constitution Day&lt;/a&gt;, which I&amp;rsquo;ve &amp;ldquo;observed&amp;rdquo; in some fashion since 2005, which was when I saw the first annual announcement of its observance at Carnegie Mellon University. My memory is fuzzy about what I actually did on Constitution Day on most years, but I remember that in 2005 I stopped by the Posner Center to look at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cmu.edu/posner-center/exhibits/bill-of-rights.html&#34;&gt;one of the four existing copies of the US Bill of Rights&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, I watched Pittsburgh Councilman &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.billpeduto.com/&#34;&gt;Bill Peduto&lt;/a&gt; speak at CMU; I remember him focusing a lot on the Bill of Rights and our need to be vigilant in protecting our rights, and telling of his concerns resulting from incidents that happened during the &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittnews.com/newsstory/city-departments-to-investigate-circumstances-of-g-20-arrests/&#34;&gt;G-20&lt;/a&gt;. This year, Magisterial District Judge &lt;a href=&#34;http://judgepedia.org/index.php/Hugh_F._McGough&#34;&gt;Hugh F. McGough&lt;/a&gt; was the featured speaker at CMU; he spoke about the history of the Pennsylvania judicial system and of constitutions in general.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I never actually knew or thought about the origin and nature of Constitution Day until yesterday. I was surprised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-is-constitution-day-observed&#34;&gt;Why is Constitution Day observed?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out (and I did not know this until it was discussed during the presentation) that Constitution Day is a recent invention. It was first observed in 2005, after a bill on spending was amended by Senator Robert Byrd to include the establishment of Constitution Day. The law mandated that any school receiving federal funds had to observe Constitution Day and teach something about the American Constitution on that day (or an adjacent weekday in case of a weekend).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;posner-s-objection&#34;&gt;Posner&amp;rsquo;s objection&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happening to be present at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cmu.edu/posner-center/&#34;&gt;Posner Center&lt;/a&gt;, and in fact sitting next to me during the presentation, were &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rrdc.com/mgmt_bio_posner.html&#34;&gt;Henry Posner III&lt;/a&gt; and his wife. When a question was asked of them near the end of the presentation, regarding whether they thought the institution of Constitution Day was a good idea, Mr. Posner responded in a very interesting way.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.rrdc.com/images/posner.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Henry Posner III&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Mr. Posner quite emphatically stated that he objected to how Constitution Day was slipped into the spending bill with a &amp;ldquo;political&amp;rdquo; agenda and with a mandate and a condition (in order for a school to receive federal funding).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought this objection was interesting and could lead to a good debate, on Constitution Day itself of all days, about what is or should be constitutional, but I really had to leave right after the talk, so I did not stay around to discuss the matter with Mr. Posner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later in the evening, however, I did look up Mr. Posner, since by demeanor and words he struck me as probably having strong libertarian views. I believe I confirmed that in my Web searches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, as I came up with a catchy title for my blog post, I found that others had already used my title. Someone at the George Mason University School of Law in fact had already written &lt;a href=&#34;http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=893903&#34;&gt;a little paper&lt;/a&gt; with the exact title, &amp;ldquo;Is Constitution Day Constitutional?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And last year someone wrote an article, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2011/09/17/opinion/constitution-day-happy-illegal-holiday.html&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Happy Illegal Holiday!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-reactions&#34;&gt;My reactions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not a lawyer, and even if I were, the notion of what is &amp;ldquo;unconstitutional&amp;rdquo; is, as we have seen again and again in the divided opinions on the Supreme Court, controversial. I see the point in being unhappy with too many federal mandates, but at the same time, from a pragmatic point of view, Constitution Day observance does not appear to be too onerous, and I happen to have inadvertently enjoyed and learned from its observance at CMU over since 2005.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed CMU&amp;rsquo;s observance of Constitution Day this year, learning some things about Pennsylvania and other state history from the Honorable Hugh McGough as well as picking up on the history of Constitution Day itself and Mr. Posner&amp;rsquo;s objection to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-09-17&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-09-17)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/09/17/on-not-celebrating-constitution-day-this-year/&#34;&gt;chose not to celebrate Constitution Day in 2013&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2014-09-17&#34;&gt;(Update of 2014-09-17)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I returned to observing Constitution in &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/09/17/observing-constitution-day-with-the-supreme-court-and-privacy-the-fourth-amendment-in-the-digital-age/&#34;&gt;2014&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>