<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Behavioral Economics on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/behavioral-economics/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Behavioral Economics on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/behavioral-economics/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Don&#39;t believe the hype about not believing the hype</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/01/23/dont-believe-the-hype-about-not-believing-the-hype/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2014 19:09:04 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/01/23/dont-believe-the-hype-about-not-believing-the-hype/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;An article came my way with the title, &lt;a href=&#34;http://qz.com/169605/dont-believe-the-hype-about-behavorial-economics/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Don&amp;rsquo;t believe the hype about behavioral economics&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t have any comments on the article itself. Instead, I have a comment about the article title.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t like it when people tell me &amp;ldquo;don&amp;rsquo;t believe the hype about X&amp;rdquo;. I find this way of speaking to be problematic on many levels:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is often a disguised way of saying &amp;ldquo;believe this other thing Y&amp;rdquo;, and in fact very often is a disguised way of saying &amp;ldquo;believe what I consider to be the correct, the status quo before this new kid on the block arrived&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is patronizing, assuming that the reader should &amp;ldquo;believe&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;not believe&amp;rdquo; something, rather than, maybe, actually &lt;em&gt;reason&lt;/em&gt; about pros and cons of some idea.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t actually care whether there is &amp;ldquo;hype&amp;rdquo; or not about something. I only care whether it&amp;rsquo;s true or useful. Sometimes something &amp;ldquo;hyped&amp;rdquo; is in fact correct; sometimes it is incorrect. I don&amp;rsquo;t care about the &amp;ldquo;hype&amp;rdquo; part, only about the truth part. So don&amp;rsquo;t drag in irrelevant matters such as whether someone out there is promoting something, and whether you&amp;rsquo;re promoting it or opposing the promoting of it. I don&amp;rsquo;t want to see articles with titles like &amp;ldquo;Don&amp;rsquo;t believe the hype about the earth going around the sun&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;Don&amp;rsquo;t believe the hype about the sun going around the earth&amp;rdquo;. If you have something substantial to say, choose a more informative title.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t care whether something is new or old, a fad or hyped. Don&amp;rsquo;t try to appeal to me on that debased emotional level when trying to sell me something. Show me whether something works or doesn&amp;rsquo;t, and I&amp;rsquo;ll pay attention. Not all old ideas are bad, not all new ideas are bad. But hype about hype is more annoying than hype itself.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>