<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Carnegie Library Of Pittsburgh on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/carnegie-library-of-pittsburgh/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Carnegie Library Of Pittsburgh on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/carnegie-library-of-pittsburgh/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Doing an unexpected workout</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/01/31/doing-an-unexpected-workout/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Jan 2013 21:53:49 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/01/31/doing-an-unexpected-workout/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;After work, I had originally planned to do the Cathedral of Learning stair climb &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/25/notes-on-exercising-while-sick-or-tired/&#34;&gt;as I have been doing for some weeks now&lt;/a&gt;, stuffing my coat and sweater jacket and shoes and socks into my backpack, before heading to the Carnegie Library of Pittsburgh to pick up some items, but was running late, so I resigned myself to skipping the workout and just picking up the library items and heading home for dinner; the stair climb would have to wait for another day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But after picking up 18 pounds of books from the library, I saw a message from Abby saying that she was out for a walk and would be home later, so I decided that I had time to do one repetition of the stair climb. The &amp;ldquo;problem&amp;rdquo; was that I had a fully loaded backpack of books.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No problem. The situation just gave me an &lt;em&gt;opportunity&lt;/em&gt; for an &lt;em&gt;unexpected&lt;/em&gt; workout: doing the 36-floor stair climb with an extra 18 pounds of weight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I went and did it. The main annoyance was having to keep my shoes on and having to hold my coat and sweater jacket with my arms while going up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I did it, and felt really great afterwards, getting in a nice workout before dinner and successfully completing a new challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When things don&amp;rsquo;t go as planned, often it pays to come up with a different plan.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dan Possumato and friends playing Irish, Scottish, French music</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/11/25/dan-possumato-and-friends-playing-irish-scottish-french-music/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Nov 2012 21:42:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/11/25/dan-possumato-and-friends-playing-irish-scottish-french-music/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/dan-possumato/flyer.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;World Kaleidoscope Flyer&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Abby and I checked out a musical performance at the Carnegie Library of Pittsburgh, main branch. They have a regular Sunday afternoon &amp;ldquo;World Kaleidoscope&amp;rdquo; series featuring world sounds from local musicians: two months ago I reported on some delightful &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/23/living-appalachian-music-of-southwestern-pennsylvania/&#34;&gt;local Appalachian music&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.carnegielibrary.org/events/details.cfm?event_id=69116&#34;&gt;Today&amp;rsquo;s performance&lt;/a&gt; was by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.danpossumato.com&#34;&gt;Dan Possumato&lt;/a&gt; and friends, featuring mostly Irish music, with Dan on button accordion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had a good time. Among the selections:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scottish music&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Irish jigs and reels&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Irish waltz &amp;ldquo;Planxty Irwin&amp;rdquo; that Abby and I danced to&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a French &lt;a href=&#34;http://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hanter-dro&#34;&gt;hanter dro&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/dan-possumato/back.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;View from back&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/dan-possumato/right.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;View from right&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/dan-possumato/dan-possumato.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Dan Possumato&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Living Appalachian music of Southwestern Pennsylvania: Mark Tamsula and Richard Withers with Ellen Gozion </title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/09/23/living-appalachian-music-of-southwestern-pennsylvania/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Sep 2012 22:15:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/09/23/living-appalachian-music-of-southwestern-pennsylvania/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As I periodically do, I went to the Carnegie Library of Pittsburgh on a Sunday afternoon to check out a musical event, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.clpgh.org/events/details.cfm?event_id=69114&#34;&gt;part of the regular World Kaleidoscope series&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.appalachianmusic.net/&#34;&gt;Mark Tamsula and Richard Withers&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://ellengozion.com/&#34;&gt;Ellen Gozion&lt;/a&gt; were there to perform some Appalachian music with very local southwestern Pennsylvanian roots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mark talked a good bit about going through the materials collected by the historian Samuel Bayard. It was interesting to me that his research in reviving the music that Bayard documented forced Mark to get more involved in reading music, since as a traditional musician he was used to learning everything by ear, but nobody is alive any more who originally played some of this music, and all that is left to document it is scores!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/appalachian-music/three.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Mark Tamsula, Richard Withers, Ellen Gozion&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/appalachian-music/irish-flute.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Richard Withers on Irish flute&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The two instrumentalists played quite a variety of instruments: fiddle, banjo, flute, guitar, harmonica, accordion, Irish flute. I enjoyed the variety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ellen Gozion sang some traditional ballads. She has a perfect voice and spirit for this music, singing with great purity and depth of emotional expression. Wow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the little concert, they promoted the new CD &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.upinthebattenhouse.com/&#34;&gt;Up in the Batten House&lt;/a&gt; and talked about upcoming projects.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Latin jazz in Pittsburgh: Puro Queso</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/08/26/latin-jazz-in-pittsburgh-puro-queso/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Aug 2012 22:31:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/08/26/latin-jazz-in-pittsburgh-puro-queso/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One great thing about Pittsburgh is the free cultural programs at the Carnegie Library. Abby and I checked out a local Latin jazz quartet, &lt;a href=&#34;http://puroquesojazz.com/&#34;&gt;Puro Queso&lt;/a&gt;, performing at the main branch of the library in Oakland, as part of their regular &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.carnegielibrary.org/events/details.cfm?event_id=69113&#34;&gt;Sunday afternoon World Kaleidoscope series&lt;/a&gt;. This event was also posted on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/pittsburgh-free/events/77709582/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Free and Almost Free in Pittsburgh&amp;rdquo; meetup group&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was amused to notice that when we arrived, I recognized the saxophonist! It was someone I had seen around a lot on campus at work at CMU. I figured he must be staff or faculty. (I looked him up and sure enough, he is &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.history.cmu.edu/faculty/eiss.html&#34;&gt;Paul Eiss, professor in the history department&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/puro-queso/soprano-sax.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Paul Eiss on soprano sax&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/puro-queso/tenor-sax.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Paul Eiss on tenor sax&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As usual at these library events, where time is limited and the purpose is to spark interest not only in the music but also to encourage concert attendance and CD purchases, the mustical selections tended toward well-known classic crowd pleasers, rather than more adventurous material or wilder improvisation. In any case, it was fun, and Abby and I danced a little too. Some of the selections I recognized:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;bossa nova: Song of the Jet (&lt;a href=&#34;http://letras.mus.br/tom-jobim/49065/&#34;&gt;Samba do Avião&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;bossa nova: &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mas_que_Nada&#34;&gt;Mas Que Nada&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;bolero: &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/B%C3%A9same_Mucho&#34;&gt;Besame mucho&lt;/a&gt;, featuring a female vocalist&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a Cuban &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Son_%28music%29&#34;&gt;son&lt;/a&gt; whose name I have forgotten&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Free to the People: Since 1895</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/09/30/free-to-the-people-since-1895/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Sep 2011 20:36:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/09/30/free-to-the-people-since-1895/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today I made my regular &amp;ldquo;pilgrimage&amp;rdquo; to one of the most special places in Pittsburgh. I never tire of going there, and I stop by usually around once a week to refresh and illuminate my soul. Yet the future of this repository of wisdom and joy is always in doubt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What can we do to safeguard our community resource?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/clpgh.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Carnegie Library of Pittsburgh, Oakland&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.clpgh.org/&#34;&gt;Carnegie Library of Pittsburgh&lt;/a&gt; is, of course, not really &amp;ldquo;free to the people&amp;rdquo;, despite those words in stone above the entrance celebrating this &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Public_good&#34;&gt;public good&lt;/a&gt;. It is paid for by tax dollars, and when money is tight, as it has been for Pittsburgh and many other American cities, there are reductions of hours, closing of small branches, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remember many years of my life during which buying books was simply not affordable, and I used libraries everywhere I lived, and was grateful for the access to knowledge. I don&amp;rsquo;t think access to books, magazines, and other useful and uplifting information should simply remain the privilege of the wealthy who can afford to buy it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I proudly support the Carnegie Library by contributing to it and receiving a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.clpgh.org/about/DonorPlus/&#34;&gt;Donor Plus Card&lt;/a&gt; as a sign of appreciation. We have also donated our own books to the library when we no longer need them.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/clpgh-books-checked-out.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Picking up books on hold for me&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-to-help&#34;&gt;How to help&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are among the over 10,000 who have pledged our support, through &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ourlibraryourfuture.org/&#34;&gt;Our Library, Our Future&lt;/a&gt;, for a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.post-gazette.com/pg/11207/1163032-100.stm&#34;&gt;referendum on a library tax&lt;/a&gt;. I certainly wouldn&amp;rsquo;t mind paying extra tax per year (that amounts to the cost of a single meal out) to help the Carnegie Library to run smoothly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are a Pittsburgh voter, please think about whether you pay too much property tax &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.post-gazette.com/pg/11159/1152094-53-0.stm&#34;&gt;as our mayor Luke Ravenstahl believes&lt;/a&gt; and cannot be bothered to pitch in for our community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Election day, November 8, is coming in just a month!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>