<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Pretty Good Race on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/pretty-good-race/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Pretty Good Race on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/pretty-good-race/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Was it worth sprinting to a terrible fall to finish 25th in the CMU Pretty Good Race 5K?</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/09/06/was-it-worth-sprinting-to-a-terrible-fall-to-finish-25th-in-the-cmu-pretty-good-race-5k/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Sep 2013 22:01:27 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/09/06/was-it-worth-sprinting-to-a-terrible-fall-to-finish-25th-in-the-cmu-pretty-good-race-5k/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On a pleasant Friday late afternoon, not too hot or humid, I ran my 9th CMU Pretty Good Race 5K (and this was Abby&amp;rsquo;s 3rd).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two weeks ago, I did the Run Around The Square 5K in my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/08/24/reflections-on-my-slowest-run-around-the-square-5k-in-13-years/&#34;&gt;slowest time in 13 years&lt;/a&gt;. I was happy to be finishing a 5K race at all. I&amp;rsquo;ve improved some in fitness in the past two weeks, but not enough to make a big difference for today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like last year, I was going into this race not optimally fit. However, given that I just ran a 5K two weeks ago, I had a good idea of what I could do in another 5K, how hard I could push myself. Like I said last year, &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;It&amp;rsquo;s not about how fast I went, but how much I gave of what I had&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I never expected just how much I would give this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;before-the-race&#34;&gt;Before the race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I walked over from my office across Flagstaff Hill to Schenley Park.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pretty-good-race-2013/flagstaff-hill.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Flagstaff Hill&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For some reason, Abby decided to use our dinky Razor kick scooter to come in from home for the race. Unfortunately, she showed up before the race with a bloody hand and knee, having had a nasty fall while using the scooter on the way to Schenley Park. Oops. She&amp;rsquo;s been tired a lot lately (I previously mentioned her dangerous &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/08/24/reflections-on-my-slowest-run-around-the-square-5k-in-13-years/&#34;&gt;decline in fitness all year&lt;/a&gt;) and was regretting signing up to do the Pretty Good Race with me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She tried to be a good sport despite the accident coming in.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pretty-good-race-2013/abby-before.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby before race&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here I am in orange:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pretty-good-race-2013/franklin-before.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin before race&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;weather-conditions&#34;&gt;Weather conditions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Temperature and humidity were much, much better than last year. That promised a considerable time advantage relative to last year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-plan&#34;&gt;The plan&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As with last year, my plan was to make the most of the final downhill part of the course, as well as go for a sprint to pass as many people as I possibly could during the final brief but terrible uphill to the finish line. I was going to have to pace myself intelligently to have something left for the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-race&#34;&gt;The race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I paced myself, not going too fast in the first half of the race. I almost entirely ran my own slow race, as there was nobody else really near my steady pace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After turning around, I starting going hard downhill. I was worried that I didn&amp;rsquo;t see Abby at all during the race. At some point, I passed her walking back to the start. She must have dropped out very early on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was pushing really hard in the final part of the race. Near the uphill finish, I saw a guy slowing down, and he raised his arms as though celebrating finishing. This gesture instantly caused me to go into a sprint more furious than any other sprint finish in my entire life. I made up a huge distance and reached the finish chute just a step before he did. And as I did so, the dry gravel and my leaning too far forward caused me to slip and fall, really, really badly. But I had finished ahead of the guy. Mission accomplished.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;injuries&#34;&gt;Injuries&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I lay stunned and in terrible pain for a few seconds. I had to check whether I was seriously broken. It felt like I was not. I was rather injured, but miraculously, no broken bones. I had managed to break my fall not with my teeth or eyes or fingers, but with my left thigh, right knee, left forearm, left palm, and right palm. I was quite badly scraped and bruised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I heard people asking me, &amp;ldquo;Was it worth it?&amp;rdquo; I didn&amp;rsquo;t know how to answer that. I moved on, stumbling in pain as I tried to catch my breath. I had done what I do, give the race my all, and then some. I was gouged and bleeding, and my right knee had swollen up hugely almost instantly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This wasn&amp;rsquo;t the worst falling injury I&amp;rsquo;ve had in my life, but it&amp;rsquo;s probably my worst since a fall off a bike (also spinning off loose gravel) twenty years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pretty-good-race-2013/left-palm.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Left palm&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pretty-good-race-2013/left-thigh.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Left thigh&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pretty-good-race-2013/right-knee.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Right knee&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pretty-good-race-2013/left-arm.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Left arm&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby returned, and had to explain to the volunteers that she wasn&amp;rsquo;t just finishing, but had dropped out earlier. While I was trying to clean myself up some, she said that she had fallen early on during the race and decided that that was enough and she wasn&amp;rsquo;t going to finish the race. So this is her first Did Not Finish (DNF) in a race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;feeling-lucky&#34;&gt;Feeling lucky&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main thing I kept on feeling while we walked back to my office and then back to my car (very slowly; everything around my right knee was just messed up) and went home for both of us to clean up from our injuries: &lt;em&gt;luck&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It could have been much worse for both of us. My most severe damage was not even to my right knee area (even though walking was difficult) but really my left hand, whose heel of palm was basically scraped away and bruised and my wrist was messed up. But no broken fingers or teeth or wrists or ankles. Same with Abby: lucky us!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;was-it-worth-it&#34;&gt;Was it worth it?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I finished officially tied for 25th place with the guy I actually beat, both of us registering as finishing in 25:28 in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~kalp/PGR/2013.html&#34;&gt;official race results&lt;/a&gt;. Well, I ran 37 seconds faster than last year. That&amp;rsquo;s not nothing, although two years ago I ran 24:36.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I knew the time was not going to be great: I just ran 25:36 in Run Around The Square two weeks ago. The real point was that like last year, I gave it my all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But was it worth getting injured for sprinting for no glory whatsoever? It&amp;rsquo;s not like I was running for first place or something &amp;ldquo;important&amp;rdquo;. Or is that the wrong way to think about it? Why is it worth trying your best for first place but not for 25th place instead of 26th place? Let&amp;rsquo;s ignore the (unfortunate?) fact that in some circles, first place is associated with large monetary rewards, when pondering that question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A different question would be, &amp;ldquo;If you knew you would get this injured from this sprint, would you have done it anyway?&amp;rdquo; I guess the question is &amp;ldquo;no&amp;rdquo;. But how could I &lt;em&gt;know&lt;/em&gt;? There is always risk. There is risk crossing the street, or driving on the turnpike. I&amp;rsquo;ve never fallen during a sprint before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another different question: &amp;ldquo;How will this accident change how you run in the future?&amp;rdquo; I suppose my answer is, I&amp;rsquo;ll be more careful to keep my balance. But am I going to stop the sprinting at the end of a race? I don&amp;rsquo;t see how I can. &lt;em&gt;It is in those moments when I can barely breathe and the world is becoming a blur that I am living with most intensity and purity.&lt;/em&gt; These moments don&amp;rsquo;t come often, but when they are available for the taking, why would I not accept these gifts?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will keep sprinting. I will keep trying to beat whoever is beatable in front of me. That&amp;rsquo;s part of the whole point of racing. I admit to feeling a little odd to being so serious about it when others do it much more casually (and it&amp;rsquo;s their right to do so and they&amp;rsquo;re probably smarter and more balanced than me, I concede). But I don&amp;rsquo;t race often, so when I do, I try to make it matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So my response is: I will need to work on maintaining balance and running on tricky surfaces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, Abby and I decided we should make sure to have a first aid kit around in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-next-race&#34;&gt;The next race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My eleventh Great Race 10K is coming up. I want to do considerably better than I did last year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, I have a lot of healing to do. I am more of a wreck right now than the post-race photos indicate. Things are all swollen and messed up and probably will be for an entire week or two. It&amp;rsquo;s just amazing I haven&amp;rsquo;t broken bones or ligaments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I simultaneously had unfortunate falling accidents today. I was proud to have run as hard as I could given my fitness and will. I don&amp;rsquo;t regret sprinting for 25th place, even if it cost me this time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, we both need to heal.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Running my 8th Pretty Good Race 5K: dealing with disappointment</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/09/07/running-my-8th-pretty-good-race-5k-dealing-with-disappointment/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Sep 2012 19:47:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/09/07/running-my-8th-pretty-good-race-5k-dealing-with-disappointment/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pretty-good-race-2012/registration.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Registration table&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This year I ran, for the eighth time in my life, the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~kalp/PGR/&#34;&gt;CMU Pretty Good Race 5K&lt;/a&gt;; on National Running Day earlier this year, I described &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/06/06/i-celebrated-national-running-day-in-schenley-park-remembering-how-i-began-to-run-13-year-ago/&#34;&gt;how special this race has been to me&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things did not go as planned, but I made the most of the event anyway, and was happy and even amused by some of the things that happened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;preparation&#34;&gt;Preparation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the big problems was that I was not at all feeling prepared for the race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;foot-problem&#34;&gt;Foot problem&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For one thing, I felt very tired for days after my last race, the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/08/25/my-eighth-time-doing-run-around-the-square-5k/&#34;&gt;Run Around the Square of almost two weeks ago&lt;/a&gt;. I gave so much of myself during that race that afterwards, I just didn&amp;rsquo;t feel like running again for a while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Worse than that, my left foot has been bothering me ever since that race, discouraging me even more from continuing my regular running. I am pretty sure that I injured my arch area because I had the shoe strap of my Vibram FiveFingers KSO Trek shoe too tight. I had it on tighter than during my normal runs, out of &amp;ldquo;fear&amp;rdquo; of the shoe coming off or slipping during the race on the Schenley Park hilly trail. &lt;strong&gt;Shoe too tight was a mistake I will never make again.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;life-intervened&#34;&gt;Life intervened&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, and most significantly, I have spent the last week spending a lot of time on the talk I gave yesterday at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://pghrb.heroku.com/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Ruby group&lt;/a&gt;, as &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/08/07/the-first-steel-city-ruby-conference-an-amazing-experience/&#34;&gt;I had promised I would a month ago&lt;/a&gt;. That took a lot out of me. In fact, if I had not already committed, with Abby, to run the Pretty Good Race this year, I would not have done it at all, after all my energy was drained in the past week. But it would have been unfair to bail out on Abby given that this is one of the few races we have started doing together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suppose I could have decided to give the talk for the October meeting of the Ruby group instead, knowing up front the annual date of the Pretty Good Race. That had crossed my mind, but I also had instantly decided (with no regrets) that giving the talk as soon as possible after I promised to do it was of much higher priority than anything involving any of my races.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;weather-conditions&#34;&gt;Weather conditions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The race was made much more difficult by the unpredictable weather. For days it would be cold, then hot. Well, it turned out that race day was very hot. It had to be like 80F. I was even thinking that this might be the warmest race I&amp;rsquo;ve ever run in, but actually, that&amp;rsquo;s probably not quite true: races in July tend to be pretty hot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-plan&#34;&gt;The plan&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I started the race with no hope whatsoever of surpassing last year&amp;rsquo;s time of 24:36. I was just going to try to run an honest race at steady effort, and use my usual mental tricks of trying to speed up in the second half and try to catch people ahead of me. In particular, the fearsome very long uphill at the end is something that I wanted to have enough energy for to sprint up; in every year up till now, I have waited until the finish line is in sight before I start my sprint. I did not always manage to pass everyone in front of me, and I also at least once let someone sprint past me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year, during some training runs on the course, I experimented with running hard for just the second half and figuring out how much energy to conserve so that I would be able to start the sprint from far beyond that point, from around the curve. That way, I would have the possibility of powering through with nobody able to catch me. &lt;em&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d never started my sprint from so far out before in any race&lt;/em&gt;, so this was going to be an experiment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-race&#34;&gt;The race&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pretty-good-race-2012/franklin-before-race.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin before the race&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;beginning&#34;&gt;Beginning&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went out at a steady pace. After less than a mile, runners had more or less spread out and found their pace. I slowly caught up to someone who was running at approximately my pace. This is when things got interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This runner ahead of me sensed that I was catching up and decided to surge. I was confused by this move, but just kept on going at my pace. Maybe she just preferred running with nobody around her; but I was trying to give her some space by coming up from the side and behind her, rather than directly behind her. Having someone breathe down your neck is not very pleasant, after all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;middle&#34;&gt;Middle&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As she kept increasing her distance from me, I concluded that she was probably just faster than me, found her natural pace, and I would never catch her. There was nobody else visible directly ahead of me, so I had no other target during the first half of the race, but I knew that since it was mostly uphill, and I&amp;rsquo;m stronger downhill than uphill, and a lot of runners go out too fast in the first half of races, it was a question of whom I would start catching during the second half.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then, as I approached the turnaround point (this is an out and back course on Panther Hollow Trail), I noticed that far ahead of me, beyond the designated turnaround point (where there were volunteers directing people to turn around, and some runners were in fact there turning around), was this runner who had blasted past me. Maybe she was in the zone or something, but she missed the turnaround point! She started coming back as I reached the turnaround point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I felt bad that she had made a mistake, but then again, this was a new opportunity for me. I already knew that she was faster than me. But she wasted time and energy falling behind me in the race. Could I actually prevent her from coming past me during the entire second half of the race, given my head start?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t look back once as I focused on running the second half of the race, almost all downhill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;end&#34;&gt;End&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Probably no more than a quarter mile from the end, she passed me and started putting distance between us. But at my targeted location to put in my kick, I &lt;em&gt;screamed&lt;/em&gt;, three or four times, while doing what I&amp;rsquo;d done in training: going into an all-out long sprint. I think I totally freaked her out, because she kind of just stepped aside and started jogging or something (that&amp;rsquo;s what it seemed like as I charged past and then around the curve and then up the steep hill).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I continued throwing out a periodic scream until I finished. For the first hundred or so races in my life, I never screamed, but I started this habit only last year, at &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/01/run-shadyside-5k-outrunning-mickey-mouse-and-lending-a-trumpet/&#34;&gt;Run Shadyside&lt;/a&gt;. I believe it actually helps me a lot when I&amp;rsquo;m in pain and need to &amp;ldquo;wake up&amp;rdquo; into a new gear of existence temporarily. I just worry about whether it scares people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that I finished ten seconds earlier than her. Mission accomplished, after all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-is-important&#34;&gt;What is important&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here I am, shortly after finishing:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pretty-good-race-2012/franklin-exhausted.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin exhausted&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s Abby coming up the hill for the finish:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pretty-good-race-2012/abby-finishing.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby finishing on the uphill&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I was pretty proud of having executed the most demanding sprint finish of my entire life. I know that my final race time of 26:05 is far slower than my 24:36 of last year, but as far as my effort was concerned, I did give it my all. &lt;em&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s not about how fast I went, but how much I gave of what I had.&lt;/em&gt; (Apparently, at the London Olympics, some runner was banned for &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.telegraph.co.uk/sport/olympics/athletics/9456916/Algerian-runner-banned-for-not-trying-hard-enough-at-London-2012.html&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;not trying hard enough&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby, in her second Pretty Good Race, ran 2:07 faster than last year, in more difficult conditions. It&amp;rsquo;s really great how she&amp;rsquo;s improved her fitness so much since she started running. &lt;em&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s not about how fast she ran, but how she&amp;rsquo;s improved.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-next-race&#34;&gt;The next race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next race that I&amp;rsquo;m already committed to is the Great Race 10K, which I&amp;rsquo;m signed up already to run for the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/25/blistered-but-blissful-in-the-burgh/&#34;&gt;tenth time&lt;/a&gt;. I still need to recover my energy for it, and also let my foot pain go away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For various reasons, I was not able to run the Pretty Good Race fast this year. But I had an exciting experience anyway and made the most of it.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Walking and running in Invisible Shoes: a review of the Connect</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/07/26/walking-and-running-in-invisible-shoes-a-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jul 2012 21:28:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/07/26/walking-and-running-in-invisible-shoes-a-review/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;For three weeks now, I have been wearing a pair of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.invisibleshoe.com/&#34;&gt;Invisible Shoes&lt;/a&gt; huaraches almost exclusively when walking and running outside. I have worn them daily walking, and I have run in them on roads, on sidewalks, on grass, and in park trails.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a review of the 4mm sole Connect model (I might get a 6mm sole Contact later).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is what the shoes look like with &amp;ldquo;slip-on/slip-off&amp;rdquo; lacing:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/invisible-shoes-connect/without-feet.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/invisible-shoes-connect/bottom.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As you can see, the sole is quite thin, just 4mm:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/invisible-shoes-connect/side-view.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here are some photos of me wearing the shoes:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/invisible-shoes-connect/grass.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/invisible-shoes-connect/asphalt.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-wear-such-a-thin-shoe&#34;&gt;Why wear such a thin shoe?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ten years ago, in 2002, I learned about the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tarahumara_people&#34;&gt;Tarahumara&lt;/a&gt; Native Americans who live in Mexico and are famed for long-distance running. I was fascinated that they chose to run in minimalist huaraches. At the time, I was doing a lot of serious &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/running/&#34;&gt;running&lt;/a&gt;, and perpetually had problems with running shoes. I figured out from trial and error that the more minimalist I got, the more I enjoyed the feel of running and the fewer injuries I received, but I didn&amp;rsquo;t know how minimalist I could really get before the cons outweighed the pros. By 2002, I had gotten as far as wearing racing flats by New Balance and Asics for races and some of my training runs, but no shoe was perfect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had also tried wearing a variety of ordinary sandals for walking and running, but they had all kinds of ergonomic problems that led me to give up on them. The strapping systems, the substantial (by my standards) heels, and the curved &amp;ldquo;arch support&amp;rdquo; all caused discomfort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fast-forward to 2009, when I bought my first pair of Vibram FiveFingers minimalist shoes. These changed my life, being sufficiently minimalist to defeat a number of problems I&amp;rsquo;ve had with traditional mono-toed shoes. As long-time readers of &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/fivefingers/&#34;&gt;this blog know&lt;/a&gt;, I&amp;rsquo;ve been wearing them exclusively for all kinds of activities, ranging from regular everyday walking to running on roads, running on trails, hiking, kayaking, rafting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past year, I have tried a little bit of &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/barefoot-running/&#34;&gt;barefoot running&lt;/a&gt;, but that is still too extreme for me to do often or for a long period of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I decided that now was the time to try to get more minimalist than FiveFingers, toward the &amp;ldquo;barefoot&amp;rdquo; feel, but without the most glaring drawbacks of being barefoot. Luckily, the surprising popularity of &lt;a href=&#34;http://chrismcdougall.com/&#34;&gt;Chris McDougall&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/a&gt; book &amp;ldquo;Born to Run&amp;rdquo; has resulted in a good number of people selling minimalist huaraches for running.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;buying&#34;&gt;Buying&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Barefoot Ted had long sold his version of huaraches, the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lunasandals.com/&#34;&gt;Luna Sandals&lt;/a&gt;. I decided to try, instead, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.invisibleshoe.com/&#34;&gt;Invisible Shoes&lt;/a&gt;, because these are more minimalist than the Luna, which in its classic form has a 6mm sole as well as a foot bed. I may well try the Luna at some point, but my goal for now is to approximate the barefoot feel, rather than pick the best huaraches for serious rugged use, and work up from there. So I went for the 4mm Connect version of the Invisible Shoes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For now, instead of buying a DIY kit, I decided that the simplest hassle-free way to break into huaraches was to buy a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lunasandals.com/&#34;&gt;custom-made&lt;/a&gt; shoe that had the soles cut and punched and laced up, ready to immediately wear. I traced my foot, scanned the trace, and emailed it, and quickly received my pair in the mail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are interested in trying out huaraches, I recommend following this route if the thought of DIY problems might otherwise discourage you. I may go DIY in the future, now that I see the final product.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;tying&#34;&gt;Tying&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question of how to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.invisibleshoe.com/tying/&#34;&gt;tie&lt;/a&gt; laces always pops up. For now, I have not experimented with different methods in order to evaluate what works best for me for secureness and comfort. I have been using the slip-on/slip-off system that came with the shoe, adjusting it as needed when my foot feels too tight or too loose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;walking&#34;&gt;Walking&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I got Invisible Shoes, my regular walking shoes were my Vibram FiveFingers KSO shoes. But once I got the Invisible Shoes, I completely stopped wearing the KSO for everyday walking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;pros&#34;&gt;Pros&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My toes have real freedom. Toe shoes like the Vibram FiveFingers compartmentalize the toes, so although they solve my wide-foot problem, they do not give me total freedom of the whole front of the foot that I like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good ventilation, like being barefoot. FiveFingers get hot in summer, resulting in sweat and sometimes blisters. I don&amp;rsquo;t get blisters walking in Invisible Shoes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the slip-on/slip-off system, I really can slip on and off easily. Since I like going barefoot indoors, it&amp;rsquo;s a plus to be able to slip on and off the shoes so easily.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;cons&#34;&gt;Cons&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is some rubbing at key points on the foot: the knot in the lacing system on top of the foot, and the lacing that passes between the big toe and the second toe. In practice, none of this has been a real problem except when it&amp;rsquo;s raining and my feet get wet, in which case I get chafed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The soles, being so thin, flop around a bit. Occasionally a sole will fold under and cause me to trip, but this happens very rarely. The main problem is mostly social: the flopping sound draws attention; I prefer to walk very silently (which I can do in most closed shoes).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The thinness of the soles also result in my feet getting very hot when I&amp;rsquo;m just standing for a period of time on hot asphalt or concrete (this is the same problem as I have when going barefoot). So standing at a street intersection waiting for a long light or in a parking lot while putting stuff into a car is not so pleasant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The thinness of the soles means walking over rough terrain is not always pleasant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that all the problems with the thinness of the soles might not be present if I had the 6mm sole rather than the 4mm sole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;running&#34;&gt;Running&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Disclaimer: I have run only four or five times in these shoes so far, so I will accumulate more experience as I continue to run in them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;pros-1&#34;&gt;Pros&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Running in these shoes on the roads and sidewalks is predictable and pleasant, very much like running barefoot. I am considering doing more tests to determine whether to run a road race 5K or 10K in these shoes! I have not run at race pace in these shoes yet. I may need to adjust lacing systems in order to feel confident about running at maximum speed without a flopping or lace-loosening problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;cons-1&#34;&gt;Cons&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is sole flopping when running. Actually there is less flopping than when walking, though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Running in the trails has not worked too smoothly. The 4mm sole really is quite thin for trail running. I noticed this when running in Frick Park, where some of the trails are more rocky than others. I also noticed this even when running in &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/06/18/walking-the-scenic-route-through-schenley-park-to-work/&#34;&gt;Schenley Park on the Pretty Good Race course&lt;/a&gt;, where the downhill section had me periodically hitting rocks harder than comfortable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is also the annoyance of stuff getting between the foot and the sole when running in the trails. Since I don&amp;rsquo;t like stopping, I&amp;rsquo;ve tried to simply flex my foot to let the material slide back out during the next couple of strides, and this mostly works. But I got one blister during a run on the trails, possibly because of loose material that got between my foot and the sole that I didn&amp;rsquo;t bother completely shaking out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 4mm Connect model of Invisible Shoes is great for walking around in. For running, I need to do more tests to find out how they hold up in more demanding conditions of speed and terrain. I would also like to compare the 4mm Connect model with the 6mm Contact model.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Walking the scenic route through Schenley Park to work</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/06/18/walking-the-scenic-route-through-schenley-park-to-work/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Jun 2012 22:08:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/06/18/walking-the-scenic-route-through-schenley-park-to-work/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Two months ago, I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/04/16/one-week-of-commuting-on-foot-because-of-cmu-carnival/&#34;&gt;spent a whole week&lt;/a&gt; commuting to work at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cmu.edu/&#34;&gt;Carnegie Mellon University&lt;/a&gt; by walking instead of driving, because of the annoyances of parking during Carnival week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because I enjoyed that experience so much, since then, I have walked to/from work at least once a week! Usually my route has included either Forbes Avenue or Schenley Drive, but once I went on other roads through Schenley Park.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last week I started making the trails of Schenley Park part of my walk. This adds probably half a mile to the walk (for a total of just less than 2.5 miles from home to work); time efficiency was why I had not taken this indirect route before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some photos of my walk to CMU last week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;going-barefoot-to-schenley-park&#34;&gt;Going barefoot to Schenley Park&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went barefoot the entire way from home to Schenley Park.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/commute-schenley-park/barefoot.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Barefoot&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Reaching the Schenley Park sign on Hobart Street:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/commute-schenley-park/hobart.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Schenley Park sign on Hobart Street&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;About to enjoy barefoot running on the grass to cross Beacon Street and Bartlett Street to reach the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.examiner.com/article/schenley-park-bartlett-street-playground&#34;&gt;Bartlett Playground&lt;/a&gt;. Note that the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.tour.pitt.edu/tour-080.html&#34;&gt;Cathedral of Learning&lt;/a&gt; is visible in the background.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/commute-schenley-park/beacon-bartlett-grass.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Grass at Hobart Street and Beacon Street&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Arriving at the Bartlett Shelter sign:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/commute-schenley-park/bartlett-shelter.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Sign for Bartlett Shelter&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Right behind the playground is the entrance to the Panther Hollow Trail:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/commute-schenley-park/bartlett-panther-hollow-trail.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Sign for Panther Hollow Trail&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;panther-hollow-trail-to-schenley-park-cafe-and-visitor-center&#34;&gt;Panther Hollow Trail to Schenley Park Cafe and Visitor Center&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This section of the Panther Hollow Trail that I followed all the way to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pittsburghparks.org/schenleyparkcafe&#34;&gt;Schenley Park Cafe and Visitor Center&lt;/a&gt; is the all-downhill section of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~kalp/PGR/&#34;&gt;Pretty Good Race 5K&lt;/a&gt; course that I ran on to &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/06/06/i-celebrated-national-running-day-in-schenley-park-remembering-how-i-began-to-run-13-year-ago/&#34;&gt;celebrate National Running Day on June 6&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My apologies to the barefoot purists, but I immediately found the trail too rough for my bare feet and put on my Vibram FiveFingers KSO shoes:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/commute-schenley-park/vibram-fivefingers-kso.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Vibram FiveFingers KSO shoes on Panther Hollow Trail&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A typical view while running downhill on the Panther Hollow Trail for about 0.9 mile:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/commute-schenley-park/panther-hollow-trail-downhill.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Panther Hollow Trail going downhill&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A sign at the base of the steps that lead up to the Schenley Park Cafe and Visitor Center. I appreciate the renovations in the Pittsburgh parks in the past several years that include such features as the new signs that I think help visitors a lot.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/commute-schenley-park/steps-sign.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Schenley Park sign at base of steps&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Finally out of the trail:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/commute-schenley-park/schenley-park-cafe-and-visitor-center.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Schenley Park Cafe and Visitor Center&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;across-flagstaff-hill-to-my-office-at-carnegie-mellon-university&#34;&gt;Across Flagstaff Hill to my office at Carnegie Mellon University&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A view of Phipps Conservatory as well as the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.tour.pitt.edu/tour-080.html&#34;&gt;Cathedral of Learning&lt;/a&gt; in the distance:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/commute-schenley-park/phipps-cathedral.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Phipps Conservatory&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One is probably not supposed to do so, but I climbed up the stone border (about four feet high) to enter Flagstaff Hill. The more circuitous route to my office would be to take Schenley Drive, which curves around, but it&amp;rsquo;s shorter (and also more scenic and strenuous) to go up the hill directly and steeply, and then descend.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/commute-schenley-park/flagstaff-hill.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Flagstaff Hill&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Taking in the view of the Cathedral of Learning against the lovely blue sky, while running through the grass on Flagstaff Hill:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/commute-schenley-park/cathedral-of-learning-from-flagstaff-hill.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Cathedral of Learning visible from Flagstaff Hill&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My office is barely visible through the trees as I descend:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/commute-schenley-park/office-through-trees.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Office visible through trees&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A convenient path to Frew Street:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/commute-schenley-park/path-to-frew-street.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Path to Frew Street&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At my office building:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/commute-schenley-park/office-building.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;My office building&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a lot of fun on a nice day to walk to work the &amp;ldquo;long&amp;rdquo; way that goes through the trails of Schenley Park and also Flagstaff Hill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am so grateful that Pittsburgh is friendly and stimulating for walking in. And, of course, I am grateful that &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mary_Schenley&#34;&gt;Mary Schenley&lt;/a&gt; donated the land to Pittsburgh way back that became Schenley Park.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I celebrated National Running Day in Schenley Park: remembering how I began to run 13 years ago</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/06/06/i-celebrated-national-running-day-in-schenley-park-remembering-how-i-began-to-run-13-year-ago/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Jun 2012 21:42:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/06/06/i-celebrated-national-running-day-in-schenley-park-remembering-how-i-began-to-run-13-year-ago/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/melissappc/663419600&#34; title=&#34;Schenley Park by Melissa McMasters, on Flickr&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1309/663419600_66449cdcc7.jpg&#34; width=&#34;333&#34; height=&#34;500&#34; alt=&#34;Schenley Park&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I celebrated &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.runningday.org/&#34;&gt;National Running Day&lt;/a&gt; by, uh, going out for a &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/running/&#34;&gt;run&lt;/a&gt;. Here in Pittsburgh, I have come to like most to run in &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburghparks.org/frick&#34;&gt;Frick Park&lt;/a&gt;, but today I decided to run in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pittsburghparks.org/schenley&#34;&gt;Schenley Park&lt;/a&gt; instead, as I was in a sentimental mood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ran the out and back &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~kalp/PGR/&#34;&gt;Pretty Good Race&lt;/a&gt; course on the Panther Hollow Trail in Schenley Park, as I have done at least several dozen times in the past thirteen years. My favorite part is always the long downhill return back to the start, during which I try to really fly down fast, feeling the wind rush past me. It&amp;rsquo;s the reward for having run uphill in the first half of the course!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~kalp/PGR/pg-race.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Pretty Good Race 5K course&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I was not always a runner. I only started to run at age 29, during a turning point in my life. And it turned out that Schenley Park played a vital role in getting me out the door and on my feet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(The details of my story are distilled from my emails and daily journal I kept in 1999-2004.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-and-when-i-started-to-run&#34;&gt;Why and when I started to run&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In early 1999, weighing 30 pounds more than I do now 13 years later (and being probably prediabetic, in retrospect), I decided to change my life by trying to fulfill a childhood dream of becoming a runner. You have to realize that I was completely out of shape at this stage of my life, barely able to run ten seconds without stopping!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I set a concrete goal to work toward in order to motivate myself to improve little by little. It turns out that Carnegie Mellon University has for decades sponsored a 5K race called the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~kalp/PGR/&#34;&gt;Pretty Good Race&lt;/a&gt; (the name inspired by Pittsburgh&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/25/blistered-but-blissful-in-the-burgh/&#34;&gt;Great Race 10K&lt;/a&gt;), held every year on Friday afternoon of the final week of the incoming computer science graduate student orientation program. A good number of incoming graduate students (as well as faculty, staff, and anyone else who is interested) take part in this race every year. The fast runners are very competitive, of course, but many run the race just for fun; there is a party afterwards for everyone who participates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided to aim to run in the Pretty Good Race in September 1999. I had many months to prepare for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-progress-in-running-recruiting-my-friend-john&#34;&gt;My progress in running: recruiting my friend John&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Progress was quite slow, because I had decades of poor conditioning to overcome. On February 10, 1999, I went for my first run with my friend John (a graduate student classmate of mine) for the first time. John was not much of a distance runner (he could sprint), but at least he had run in the Pretty Good Race in 1998 (and finished at the back of the pack). He was patient with me because I had rest quite frequently. &lt;strong&gt;I owe John for encouraging me and accompanying me.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, I was so out of shape that I could only &amp;ldquo;run&amp;rdquo; for ten or fifteen seconds at a time before getting chest and leg pains and having to walk for minutes before starting up again. I had no idea what I was doing. Also, we did this irregularly, not on a daily schedule or anything. So progress was slow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;failure-in-1999&#34;&gt;Failure in 1999&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that I was dealing with various personal problems in the summer of 1999 and also still not fit enough to run continuously for a mile. So in late August, I decided to give up on my goal, and did not run in the Pretty Good Race in 1999&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-new-motivation-in-2000-30th-birthday&#34;&gt;A new motivation in 2000: 30th birthday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In May, on my 30th birthday, I decided that I was going to get serious about running. I could not just continue to do my low-yield unsystematic run/walking with John. The very next day, I pushed myself harder than I had ever done before, running with John.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I shook off my &amp;ldquo;dependency&amp;rdquo; on John, and decided to run &lt;em&gt;every day&lt;/em&gt;, even if it meant doing it alone. I made extensive use of Frick Park near home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;scientific-training&#34;&gt;Scientific training&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started reading &amp;ldquo;The Runner&amp;rsquo;s Handbook&amp;rdquo;, recommended to me by my sister Linda months ago. Exactly nine days after my birthday, I wrote Linda email telling her that I planned to run the Pretty Good Race in September.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book said that a beginner should run at least twenty minutes, preferably thirty minutes, and at least three times a week, preferably five. This was much more than what I&amp;rsquo;d been doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wrote in my journal:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
I think I will aim to successfully run my Frick Park route for a few weeks, till I can comfortably run 20 minutes.  Then I will invent a new addition in Frick Park in order to make the run 30 minutes.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Progress became more noticeable as I focused on putting in the time and distance, going as slowly as required to avoid going anaerobic (my problem when running with John). Learning the science of distance running definitely helped a lot in making my training scientific.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;really-committing-to-running-the-pretty-good-race-in-2000&#34;&gt;Really committing to running the Pretty Good Race in 2000&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I managed to get some friends of mine to commit to also running in the Pretty Good Race for the first time, and we did a little bit of running together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;some-warmup-races&#34;&gt;Some warmup races&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ran the first races of my life right before the Pretty Good Race, in order to get a feel for what it was like racing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;run-around-the-square-5k&#34;&gt;Run Around the Square 5K&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My actual first 5K race was the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.runaroundthesquare.com/&#34;&gt;Run Around the Square&lt;/a&gt; in August 2000, just some weeks before the Pretty Good Race. It was &amp;ldquo;disastrous&amp;rdquo;, because I was completely inexperienced:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
I guess I went too fast, because before I reached the park entrance, I
wasn&#39;t feeling so well, and my right side was beginning to hurt
already.  I didn&#39;t think of myself as going fast, because so many
people were going faster and obviously way ahead.  There was no
crowding problem, because people were getting spread out.

Worse, when I reached the park entrance, I dashed down the steep,
curving hill, passing a lot of people, and almost fell off the trail.
When the uphill came, people started passing me.

I knew I was in trouble when it took me 9 minutes to get to the 1 mile
mark.

As the race progressed, I saw all kinds of people pass me: middle-aged
women, high-schoolers, old men.  It was embarrassing.  I was just
trying to avoid getting sick.  I was moving my feet slowly, and not
pushing off.  The feeling of people passing me was not encouraging.

I ended up grabbing water three times.

I took 18 minutes to get to the 2 mile mark.  At this point, I
believed I would probably take 27 minutes total, and I felt bad.

I didn&#39;t even bother to get in an extra kick when the end was near.  I
just didn&#39;t feel well.  I believe my time was 27:xx.  I took my pulse
right after I ripped off my chip and handed it to someone.  It was
200.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, my time was a very slow 27:23, and I was overambitious in my first race. But that was OK, because the point was to get experience so that in the race that mattered, the Pretty Good Race, hopefully I would do better. I was afraid of finishing dead last in the Pretty Good Race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(For the record, a year later, 2001, I ran 23:19 in this race.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;montour-trail-5k&#34;&gt;Montour Trail 5K&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A week before the Pretty Good Race, I ran in my second 5K race of my life, the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mtchalfmarathon.com/&#34;&gt;Montour Trail 5K&lt;/a&gt;. I did it in 25:30, being much more experienced as a result of the Run Around the Square.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(For the record, a year later, in 2001, I ran the Montour Trail half marathon instead, in 1:47:23, five days after running a 5K race in 21:39. Do the math: in one year I got my 5K time down from 27:23 to 21:39!!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;moment-of-truth-pretty-good-race-2000-http-www-cs-cmu-edu-kalp-pgr-2000-html&#34;&gt;Moment of truth: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~kalp/PGR/2000.html&#34;&gt;Pretty Good Race 2000&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My friends all beat me in the race, some pretty significantly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I finished in 26:26, in agony, in 27th place out of 32 (including the guy who ran backwards the whole way). OK, so I didn&amp;rsquo;t finish in last place after all!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I silently vowed to beat my friends in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~kalp/PGR/2001.html&#34;&gt;2001&lt;/a&gt;. I did. I came in 18th place out of 45, after training really hard for a year to improve my running. My time in 2001 was 22:33, over four minutes faster than in 2000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here I am outsprinting my friend Sungwoo at the finish:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pgr-2001-sungwoo-franklin.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Pretty Good Race 5K, 2001, closeup of Sungwoo and Franklin&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A mutual friend asked me why I was so intent on beating Sungwoo, and asked whether I had something against him. I said no, not at all. It was just a personal challenge, a goal, just like when I first starting running in races, and got beaten by a certain 70-something hunched-over old man repeatedly, I made him a concrete target to surpass in the future, and eventually I did. In this case, I had earlier judged that Sungwoo was closest in speed to me, and therefore I would aim to beat him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;other-years-of-running-the-pretty-good-race&#34;&gt;Other years of running the Pretty Good Race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2000: 26:26 (first time, and 3rd lifetime race)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2001: 22:33 (much better, 23rd race)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2002: did not run, because of half marathon the next day&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2003: did not run, because of half marathon the next day&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2004: simply chose not to run&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2005: 23:16 (little training)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2006: 22:57 (recovered some fitness)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2007: (almost no running this year, health declining)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2008: (almost no running this year, health declining)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2009: 25:52 (almost no running this year, in terrible health)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2010: 26:41 (almost no running this year, in terrible health)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2011: 24:36 (began running again, recovering my health)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-future&#34;&gt;The future&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year, 2012, I aim to get back under 24:00 in the Pretty Good Race, to return to my fitness level of early 2007 before my life was disrupted for half a decade during which I had trouble staying healthy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have done less running so far this year than I would have liked, unfortunately, but just being on the Pretty Good Race course again and feeling great to be out there reminded me to return to a regular running habit. I have three months before the next Pretty Good Race!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;but-why&#34;&gt;But why??&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this blog post I haven&amp;rsquo;t explained why I wanted to run, what my goals were, how they have changed over the years, and why I run now. I will write about those topics in detail later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For now, I&amp;rsquo;ll just say that &lt;strong&gt;I love to run&lt;/strong&gt;. I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t do it if I didn&amp;rsquo;t. (I know people who run but do not love it. I think &lt;a href=&#34;http://jones.wordpress.com/2012/06/04/things-ive-learnt-from-running/&#34;&gt;that is a mistake&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>