<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Gratitude on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/gratitude/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Gratitude on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/gratitude/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>A favorite poem to share as 2013 comes to an end</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/12/22/a-favorite-poem-to-share-as-2013-comes-to-an-end/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Dec 2013 20:12:54 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/12/22/a-favorite-poem-to-share-as-2013-comes-to-an-end/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/immortal-poems.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Immortal Poems of the English Language&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For a party last night, hostess Gina announced some weeks ahead of time that we were to bring &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;a favorite quote, poem, lyric or inspired thought to share as we look forward to 2014 with gratitude&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought this was a really good theme for an end-of-year holiday party. At first I thought maybe I should write a new poem of my own, for the occasion. But I got cold feet and bailed out of that plan. Maybe for another party next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After thinking for a while, I decided I would return to an old favorite: the poetry of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_Blake&#34;&gt;William Blake&lt;/a&gt;. I picked one of my (favorite) poems by him, and planned to recite it and say a few words at the party about what it means to me and how it applies in particular to my thoughts as 2013 comes to an end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that we were all having too much fun at the party just eating and meeting people and talking and then some of us going off to play music together, and &amp;ldquo;forgot&amp;rdquo; about the quote/poem/lyric/thought thing for a while. But it was getting late and Abby and I had to get going at some point, so I reminded Gina about the theme, and she got everyone together and started off herself with a quote from Kafka. That led to some discussion, and then someone else offered a provocative thought, a question to the younger people present. It turned out that this question led to a lot of lively debate, which was great, but also meant that since I didn&amp;rsquo;t want to interrupt it, Abby and I had to quietly excuse ourselves and leave the party. I told Gina I would share my thought later on her party page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Originally I was only going to say a few words, but as long as I&amp;rsquo;m not limited by keeping things very brief, I decided I might as well write a full-fledged post about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-accidental-introduction-to-really-good-poetry&#34;&gt;My accidental introduction to really good poetry&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, I want to say something about an accident that led to my discovering some really good poetry as a child. I was not (and still am not) primarily poetry-oriented (I am music-oriented), but exposure to good stuff led me not to completely ignore poetry through my life. I was 9 years old at the time (my sister 5). We were living in an apartment in Royal Oak, Michigan at the time. One day we discovered a couple of boxes of books out on the sidewalk, obviously put out for trash day. Since our family owned very little, and I was a voracious reader who always had to beg to go to the public library to get books to read, this was like treasure from heaven for us. Linda and I hauled our stash back inside, and sort of divvied it up between the two us. I will probably write more about this stash later, because over the years many of the titles played a huge role in both our lives. &lt;strong&gt;These boxes of books changed our lives in every possible way.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For now, I just want to mention that I came across the poetry of William Blake through one of these volumes that I got from the trash in 1979, &amp;ldquo;Immortal Poems of the English Language&amp;rdquo;. This book was already old and yellow when I got it from the trash then, having been printed in 1952, but they used to make books differently back in the day: really high-quality paper that stands the test of time. I still have this anthology on my book shelf at home. In fact, here&amp;rsquo;s a photo of it:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/immortal-poems.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Immortal Poems of the English Language&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t browse through this book as a 9-year-old because I was interested in poetry. I did it because it was sitting there at home. A child who is at home and bored (this was before computers and video games and iPads, and we didn&amp;rsquo;t even have a working TV at the time: our old 1960s black and white vacuum tube TV had not survived the move to Michigan) will find &lt;em&gt;anything&lt;/em&gt; at least &lt;em&gt;potentially&lt;/em&gt; interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I flipped through the volume looking for short, easy stuff to maybe read. Well, it turns out that a lot of Blake&amp;rsquo;s poetry is in fact really short, and really easy to read, without a lot of complicated words or subordinate phrases or fancy thoughts. (Much later, I realized that simple to read does &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; mean simplistic or &amp;ldquo;for children&amp;rdquo;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t fully understand what I was reading, but at least I got a taste.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;really-enjoying-blake&#34;&gt;Really enjoying Blake&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My teenage years were quite difficult, filled with alienation, loneliness, anger, depression, and poor health. I found some unexpected solace reading Blake&amp;rsquo;s poetry. In fact, it turned out that I embraced the fundamental messages inherent in his work. I have changed my opinions about one thing or another in the decades of my life since, but one constant has been my admiration for William Blake: the man, the poet, the philosopher, the do-it-yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were several poems that really spoke to me then as they do to me now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He means so much to me that one of these poems is actually the &amp;ldquo;secret&amp;rdquo; inspiration for the title and subtitle of this very blog that I started over two years ago. Why is this blog &amp;ldquo;Franklin Chen&amp;rsquo;s grain of sand: infinity in the palm of my hand&amp;rdquo;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Auguries_of_Innocence&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Auguries of Innocence&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/auguries-of-innocence.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Auguries of Innocence&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-poem-for-yesterday-s-party-eternity&#34;&gt;The poem for yesterday&amp;rsquo;s party: &amp;ldquo;Eternity&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that&amp;rsquo;s a complex poem, not the one I was going to share yesterday at the party. The poem for yesterday was a much shorter one, &amp;ldquo;Eternity&amp;rdquo;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
He who binds to himself a joy
Does the winged life destroy;
But he who kisses the joy as it flies
Lives in eternity&#39;s sun rise.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(The old edition I have has &amp;ldquo;bends&amp;rdquo; instead of &amp;ldquo;binds&amp;rdquo;.)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/eternity.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Eternity&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is a very powerful poem. I have not always abided by its advice, but I believe in its wisdom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, the poem is about attachment versus &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Detachment_%28philosophy%29&#34;&gt;detachment&lt;/a&gt;, and eternity versus &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Impermanence&#34;&gt;impermanence&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lesson I have learned the hard way in my life is that being attached to something, whether an idea or a possession or even a memory, leads to suffering, because it contradicts the reality of the world and of human existence. This year has been particularly challenging for me, as I gave up some old, familiar habits and beliefs and activities in order to start new ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is hard to say goodbye to something familiar and comforting, whether it is writing computer programs in a certain language, or taking part in certain music performances because you&amp;rsquo;ve done that for two years and feel a camaraderie with others you have done it with, or giving up or scaling down on a beloved hobby. But then I remember that if we love something, that does not mean we possess it, or that it possesses us. A musical ensemble will continue on without us; we should be happy for it without constantly feeling regret or sadness at moving on. We should be &lt;em&gt;grateful&lt;/em&gt; for what we have given ourselves to in the past, without feeling shackled by it. And that I&amp;rsquo;ve found myself used to thinking or behaving a certain way doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean I need to stay that way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Easier said than done: there are still various things that I know I am still hanging on to that once made sense but now may not. Luckily, I have Abby as a source of input that can offer a point of view that is not just my own self-absorption. OK, I don&amp;rsquo;t always accept her point of view, but I am grateful that she expresses it and offers it as something for me to give myself permission to consider.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of trying to capture and relive a perfect moment, we can look forward to brand new moments. And especially as a new year arrives, we can symbolically renew our sense of freshness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean necessarily throwing out the past; it just means recognizing the past as what it is, rather than as what we wish the future could still be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d like to thank Gina for inviting us to take a moment to reflect on something of our choice as 2013 comes to an end. I wish I could have stayed longer last night to take part in the discussions that apparently lasted quite some time!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thanking the best of all possible worlds</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/11/22/thanking-the-best-of-all-possible-worlds/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Nov 2012 21:55:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/11/22/thanking-the-best-of-all-possible-worlds/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Happy Thanksgiving, everyone!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-Lc7Oc2PreKI/T3U0A6pSPBI/AAAAAAAABxY/iTXcrFFn1sQ/s1600/tumblr_kx61vvQHfG1qz82gvo1_500.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Oppenheimer quote&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Today, on a sunny Thanksgiving, I surprised myself by spontaneously deciding to thank this world, and go as far as to call it &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Best_of_all_possible_worlds&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;the best of all possible worlds&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;m still not entirely sure what I mean by that, but somehow, I &amp;ldquo;believe&amp;rdquo; it; more precisely, it&amp;rsquo;s an &lt;em&gt;attitude&lt;/em&gt; I now have that I have never really had in my life up till now. Even &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/23/every-day-is-thanksgiving/&#34;&gt;a year ago&lt;/a&gt;, I would have thought it silly to adopt such an attitude.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A friend of mine asked, &amp;ldquo;Dr. Pangloss?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, am I being a fool?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;being-dr-pangloss&#34;&gt;Being Dr. Pangloss?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Pangloss is a fictional character from &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Voltaire&#34;&gt;Voltaire&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s satirical novella &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Candide&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Candide&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; that was required reading in high school French. I remember reading that novella in high school, of course: it was a &lt;em&gt;profound&lt;/em&gt; influence on me at the time, instilling a certain cynicism in me that lasted years. Voltaire wrote this novella as a direct attempt to refute &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gottfried_Wilhelm_Leibniz&#34;&gt;Leibniz&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s philosophy of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Best_of_all_possible_worlds&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;best of all possible worlds&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;: Pangloss is a buffoonish character who spouts parodies of Leibniz&amp;rsquo;s reasoning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No question about it, Candide is a wickedly entertaining satire, and Voltaire is a towering figure from the French Enlightenment, one who exposed a lot of hypocrisy and was an advocate of many social reforms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;philosophy-vs-attitude&#34;&gt;Philosophy vs. attitude&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I have over the years come to believe that the Enlightenment emphasis on Reason is not by itself the panacea to the mysteries and problems of life. In particular, I perceive that often, this emphasis leads to arrogance, anger, and selective blindness. There doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem any logical &lt;em&gt;reason&lt;/em&gt; that &lt;em&gt;Reason&lt;/em&gt; should lead to this, but it really happens. It happened to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I have not by any means abandoned &lt;em&gt;reason&lt;/em&gt;, but I have long since abandoned &lt;em&gt;Reason&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, I&amp;rsquo;m going to confess that Leibniz&amp;rsquo;s philosophical work does not make a whole lot of sense to me. So my adopting an &lt;em&gt;attitude&lt;/em&gt; of &amp;ldquo;this is the best of all possible worlds&amp;rdquo; is in no way an endorsement of any belief in Leibniz&amp;rsquo;s philosophical/theological system. And I certainly have also observed that there are people who do accept Leibniz&amp;rsquo;s purported solution to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Problem_of_evil&#34;&gt;problem of evil&lt;/a&gt;, who seem to use it as a way to turn a blind eye to the injustices that still occur in our world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short, I am taking an &lt;em&gt;attitude&lt;/em&gt; that I find helps me function in a positive way in the world, without tying myself to a fully worked out philosophy about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;related-ideas&#34;&gt;Related ideas&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A related idea is &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amor_fati&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;amor fati&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (&amp;ldquo;love of fate&amp;rdquo;), popularized by Nietzsche but coming from &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stoicism&#34;&gt;Stoicism&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Steve Pavlina wrote today about &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.stevepavlina.com/blog/2012/11/this-is-heaven/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;heaven&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;application&#34;&gt;Application&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That I have adopted the &lt;em&gt;optimistic&lt;/em&gt; attitude toward life, after having a mostly &lt;em&gt;pessimistic&lt;/em&gt; one during most of my years, has practical applications. Being &lt;em&gt;grateful&lt;/em&gt; every single day for every positive thing that happens enables me to more easily overcome the negative. My attitude is a choice I have made, and nurtured through various techniques, as mentioned &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/23/every-day-is-thanksgiving/&#34;&gt;last Thanksgiving&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being optimistic does not mean ignoring the negative. It means maintaining the energy to do things, to set things right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have embrace this world as &lt;em&gt;my&lt;/em&gt; world. This is my choice, my attitude. May it be yours as well.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Happy Thanksgiving and a call to action</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/11/24/happy-thanksgiving-and-a-call-to-action/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Nov 2011 10:38:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/11/24/happy-thanksgiving-and-a-call-to-action/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Happy Thanksgiving, everyone! Please take time out to give thanks today, whether out loud or silently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday I wrote about how &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/23/every-day-is-thanksgiving/&#34;&gt;every day is Thanksgiving&lt;/a&gt;. At the end of the post, I wondered about further improving my gratitude practice. I woke up today with a burning desire to take action. I&amp;rsquo;d like to know what you think of my specific ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;gratitude-letters&#34;&gt;Gratitude letters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I first heard about gratitude letters from the fantastic book &lt;a href=&#34;http://chass.ucr.edu/faculty_book/lyubomirsky/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The How of Happiness&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.faculty.ucr.edu/~sonja/index.html&#34;&gt;Sonja Lyubomirsky&lt;/a&gt;. The idea is to directly write a letter of gratitude to an individual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought about this in the context of all the free and open source software I use regularly for work or for personal purposes. I was thinking that I should start taking the time to thank, one by one, each of the developers or teams of such software.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, I follow a lot of blogs. Many of them don&amp;rsquo;t have many followers, so commenting more and offering gratitude would probably be very welcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;gratitude-themed-blog-post&#34;&gt;Gratitude-themed blog post&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps I could reserve one day a week of my blog for the gratitude theme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;gratitude-in-every-blog-post&#34;&gt;Gratitude in every blog post&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or I could find a way to express gratitude in every blog post I write.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;gratitude-tweets&#34;&gt;Gratitude tweets&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe I could tweet gratitude more often. I don&amp;rsquo;t want to annoy my Twitter followers with too much though. And I admit I don&amp;rsquo;t like the length restriction. I guess I don&amp;rsquo;t see as much value in tweeting gratitude as in writing even a decent one-paragraph email to someone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;integrate-into-digital-sabbath&#34;&gt;Integrate into Digital Sabbath&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently I began to observe a little bit of a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/12/starting-a-mini-digital-sabbath/&#34;&gt;Digital Sabbath&lt;/a&gt; on which I do not write a blog post. Maybe I could reserve the day after the Digital Sabbath for a gratitude-oriented post?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;other-ideas&#34;&gt;Other ideas&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lyubomirsky has other ideas, some of which are in &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.beliefnet.com/beyondblue/2010/05/5-ways-to-practice-gratitude-a.html&#34;&gt;this interview&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;your-ideas&#34;&gt;Your ideas&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What ideas do you have about how to integrate more gratitude into your life, starting this Thanksgiving? Or ideas you have about how &lt;em&gt;I&lt;/em&gt; should integrate more gratitude into my life, into my blog?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;postscript&#34;&gt;Postscript&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will be observing an extended Digital Sabbath till the end of the weekend. There will be a lot of turkey, and a lot of friends and family to see again.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Every day is Thanksgiving</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/11/23/every-day-is-thanksgiving/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Nov 2011 23:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/11/23/every-day-is-thanksgiving/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;So tomorrow is &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thanksgiving&#34;&gt;Thanksgiving&lt;/a&gt;, the American holiday that is so unfortunate for turkeys. Thanksgiving is a traditional time for pausing and giving thanks for all that we are grateful for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I briefly considered creating a little list of some of my reasons for thanks and posting the list here. I changed my mind after realizing that for every item I put on the list, I would be omitting a thousand other items and implicitly suggesting they were less important. Therefore, I decided to not have a list at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, let me advocate making &lt;strong&gt;every day&lt;/strong&gt; Thanksgiving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;negativity&#34;&gt;Negativity&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a time in my life when I easily fell into a persistently cynical, negative mood, and thought happiness and gratitude were for chumps who didn&amp;rsquo;t realize how crappy the world was. I would often feel angry about some injustice in the world, or some injustice done to me. I would wish I had more stuff or were smarter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I realized that this attitude was not helpful, so I tried changing it through reasoning, but the results were never long-lasting. Negative emotions would pop up and create a cycle of anger, envy, resentment, greed, etc. I never experienced an overall sense of harmony and acceptance and gratitude.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;happiness-and-gratitude&#34;&gt;Happiness and gratitude&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things started changing when I started reading about happiness and &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Positive_psychology&#34;&gt;positive psychology&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But one of the few sources that really got me on a path of permanent change was a deeply personal, accessible, and &lt;em&gt;practical&lt;/em&gt; book by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.talbenshahar.com/&#34;&gt;Tal Ben-Shahar&lt;/a&gt;, &amp;ldquo;Happier: Learn the Secrets to Daily Joy and Lasting Fulfillment&amp;rdquo;, published in 2007.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the practical suggestions by Ben-Shahar was that of maintaining a &lt;strong&gt;gratitude journal&lt;/strong&gt; regularly. I thought, OK, this sounds cheesy, but I&amp;rsquo;ll give it a shot.  So I got some blank notebooks, and every day before going to bed, I would write down five thoughts of gratitude that I had genuinely observed arising in myself that day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Years later, I am still writing in my gratitude journal every day&lt;/strong&gt;. When packing for travel, the first thing on my packing list is always my gratitude journal. I&amp;rsquo;ve almost never missed a day of writing in my gratitude journal. The couple of times in the past years when I missed a day were when my life was obviously in considerable disorder and just recognizing my omission was enough to get me back the next day. Yes, I write in my gratitude journal even when I have what seems like a really terrible day, because there is always something that could have been worse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Completely unexpectedly, this simple ritual, the gratitude journal, slowly began to change my life. The changes were subtle but real. Just being aware that there is so much good going on in life, even when it is terrible, keeps me from ever sinking into the kind of depression that I was prone to in my younger days. My negative emotions became more controllable, and my overall outlook on life is positive, and instead of just taking for granted all that is good, I have reset myself so that I appreciate what is good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-goes-into-the-gratitude-journal&#34;&gt;What goes into the gratitude journal?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might be wondering what kinds of things I write about in my gratitude journal. As I mentioned, I simply write down what really comes to mind, relatively spontaneously. Some days I have a lot more exciting items rushing to my mind, and other days I have to struggle to find five. I just happen to always put down at least five, for the sake of regularity, and for the sake of deepening my search for little things that I might not have been conscious of during a day but maybe I could appreciate more fully.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few random shorter examples from my gratitude journals of the past years:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Made decent butternut squash and navy bean soup! First time really.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Got in a lot of walking today as exercise and mental relaxation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Got a haircut from Joe.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It was a peaceful, sunny day.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jim Weirich was great at the Pittsburgh Ruby presentation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Had the last red tea bag in the can, refreshing and awakening.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tasty beef fajitas by Abby for dinner.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Had time to catch up on emails with (long-distance) friends.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Made up with Abby after argument.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shoveling snow today was not too tedious.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Someone had extra water for me on the hike.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nothing seems permanently broken after my big fall.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Still sick, but feel better than yesterday.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Caught up on sleep last night.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given my gratitude journal, every day is in a sense Thanksgiving, but I think something is still missing. I am now considering changing things up with the gratitude journal, because sometimes I take the easy way out and repeat myself with similar items that, yes, matter a lot to me, but are a bit mundane. The gratitude journal is like tweeting. I would like to write longer essays giving thanks. On my to-do list for the blog!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>