<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Toilet on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/toilet/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Toilet on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/toilet/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>World Toilet Day is not just another crappy holiday</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/19/world-toilet-day-is-not-just-another-crappy-holiday/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2014 23:41:34 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/19/world-toilet-day-is-not-just-another-crappy-holiday/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;From an excellent blog I follow, Timothy Taylor&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://conversableeconomist.blogspot.com/&#34;&gt;Conversable Economist&lt;/a&gt;, I read his &lt;a href=&#34;http://conversableeconomist.blogspot.com/2014/11/world-toilet-day.html&#34;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; about &lt;a href=&#34;http://worldtoilet.org/&#34;&gt;World Toilet Day&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, every day is some kind of observed day somewhere in the world promoted by someone, but World Toilet Day is not just another crappy commercial holiday. It&amp;rsquo;s about a serious problem, which is that 15 percent of the world population still lives without proper sanitation. Open sanitation, especially in densely populated areas, is a cause of much serious illness (especially to children, who are especially vulnerable). So I&amp;rsquo;m happy about the invention of World Toilet Day in 2001 by the World Toilet Organization global non-profit. It&amp;rsquo;s curious that I hadn&amp;rsquo;t heard about it for thirteen years, but I&amp;rsquo;m grateful Timothy Taylor pointed it out in his blog. Because this is a serious issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I, for one, am grateful to live in the industrialized US where toilets abound everywhere, and even in parks such as my local Frick Park in Pittsburgh, there are port-a-potties in various locations within the park. I used to make fun of my immigrant parents for being strangely fixated on and happy about functioning and clean toilets, but the reality is that their generation and their parents&amp;rsquo; generation in rural Taiwan did not necessarily have this luxury. In fact, even today, apparently, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ketagalanmedia.com/2014/09/03/dreaming-odor-free-bathroom-taiwan/&#34;&gt;the sewage system is not great in Taiwan&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>