<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Blues on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/blues/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Blues on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/blues/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>How I forgot to meditate after sixty days in a row of remembering and what that means</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/01/24/how-i-forgot-to-meditate-after-sixty-days-in-a-row-of-remembering-and-what-that-means/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2015 13:58:29 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/01/24/how-i-forgot-to-meditate-after-sixty-days-in-a-row-of-remembering-and-what-that-means/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I woke up this morning feeling very tired. I also suddenly realized that yesterday, I forgot to set aside time for the daily meditation practice (just ten minutes a day) that I had successfully done for &lt;em&gt;sixty days in a row&lt;/em&gt;, having deliberately started it &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/11/24/report-on-my-first-day-of-stoic-week-2014/&#34;&gt;shortly before Thanksgiving&lt;/a&gt;. I was pretty angry at myself. But I also thought about how it was possible that I slipped after sixty days, and what that means.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-s-my-meditation-schedule&#34;&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s my meditation schedule?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The optimal way to maintain any habit is to make it as rigid and automatic as possible. Several years ago, when I went months at a time without missing a single day, my system was to meditate first thing in the morning, before eating or exercising or anything else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I confess that I still don&amp;rsquo;t have that kind of rigid schedule yet. Much of the time, I do meditate first thing. Other times, I feel pressed for time and want to get some work done. Or I&amp;rsquo;m feeling very hungry and decide to eat breakfast first. But usually I do complete meditation in the morning. Occasionally I &amp;ldquo;forget&amp;rdquo; but then remember well before bedtime, and get it in before sleeping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-my-forgetting-yesterday-says-about-my-life&#34;&gt;What my forgetting yesterday says about my life&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, I was feeling tired when I woke, because of a week of accumulated fatigue from doing many things, including going out last night with Abby for the second week of blues dance class at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.tartanswing.com/&#34;&gt;Tartan Swing&lt;/a&gt; at CMU. Adding an extra evening out every week is requiring some changes in how much other stuff I can get done in evenings, and apparently I have not scaled back enough to make up for that additional commitment; it is always a struggle for me to &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/12/15/thoughts-on-giving-up-an-old-project-to-make-room-for-the-new/&#34;&gt;give up something to make room for something else&lt;/a&gt;, but especially on short notice, since we had not originally planned, in December, to start checking out Tartan Swing this January!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, yesterday was Friday, and I tend to feel I have many things to try to get done on Friday. I ate breakfast immediately, did work stuff, then since I was scheduled to go for a run, I did that. I&amp;rsquo;ve been ramping up on my run distances, and I ran my second longest distance so far this month: the length was the sum of the length of my Monday and Wednesday runs this week! So that took more energy than I am used to yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I came home from work, I was extremely tired and hungry, to the point that I decided I wanted to eat a whole lot of food and do something different, so Abby and I went out for dinner. I came home totally stuffed. In any case, going out was an unscheduled, spontaneous decision, and by the time we came home, none of the whole day had gone according to my usual pattern. And so I somehow forgot to get in meditation before going to bed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;lessons-learned&#34;&gt;Lessons learned&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first lesson is that just because I missed one day of meditation after sixty in a row, that doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean I&amp;rsquo;ve lost everything. I meditated today, and will continue my practice. It&amp;rsquo;s important to recover as quickly as possible, to avoid what has happened to me before, which is to feel ashamed, start identifying (after too many days in a row missed) as a &amp;ldquo;non-meditator&amp;rdquo;, and give up the practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other is that I&amp;rsquo;m definitely overbooked and need to make sure I get rest, and get back on schedule for what I can manage to do. A busy week is coming up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What do you do when you find out that you&amp;rsquo;ve missed a day of meditation, exercise, or some other daily practice? Do you feel bad about yourself? Do you make excuses? Do you examine what is really important? Do you set up a system to prevent having to rely on will power? What is your latest experience of slipping, and how did you deal with it?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Third year at July 3 music party and finally participated in jamming</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/07/03/third-year-at-july-3-music-party-and-finally-participated-in-jamming/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jul 2014 22:11:59 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/07/03/third-year-at-july-3-music-party-and-finally-participated-in-jamming/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;The past two years, Abby and I have gone to an annual July 3 music potluck/party, and we went again this year. Both &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/03/petrified-at-a-music-jam-session-so-i-didnt-play-but-watched-and-listened/&#34;&gt;in 2012&lt;/a&gt; as well as &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/07/03/second-year-at-july-3-music-party-still-only-listening-without-playing/&#34;&gt;in 2013&lt;/a&gt;, I was too intimidated to participate in music jamming, and only watched. This year I was determined to contribute, and I brought my ukulele (which I only started learning &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/08/23/another-unexpected-life-change-one-month-of-learning-to-play-ukulele/&#34;&gt;a month after last year&amp;rsquo;s party&lt;/a&gt;, actually) and my Irish flute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;piano&#34;&gt;Piano&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After my first round of food at the potluck, I went to Susan&amp;rsquo;s piano and played David Raksin&amp;rsquo;s theme from &amp;ldquo;Laura&amp;rdquo;, which I had so botched up last month at the annual Pittsburgh Recorder Society potluck/recital. I play it much better now, although I somehow messed up the final chords today. There were a few people sitting around listening, and they wanted to hear more, but I didn&amp;rsquo;t have any more, so I scurried away to eat more food.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;old-time&#34;&gt;Old time&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As dinner started winding down, the old time musicians started gathering outside to play. I saw fiddles, banjos, and other instruments make an appearance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;blues&#34;&gt;Blues&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inside, the main guy who plays guitar and ukulele unpacked his soprano ukulele, and so I took out my concert ukulele, and two other guys with guitars appeared. Eventually a woman who sang also appeared, as well as a guy on fiddle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I felt very intimidated, because although I&amp;rsquo;ve gotten some experience jamming while on recorder or flute or tin whistle, my ukulele experience &lt;em&gt;without written music&lt;/em&gt; is still very minimal. Nevertheless, I joined in. I fumbled around, and had to ask what key each song was being played in, and even then, I&amp;rsquo;m still quite shaky in anticipating and knowing chord changes beyond the simplest I, IV, V, and some dominant and major 7th chords. I strummed very softly.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/music-2014-07-04/jamming.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Music jamming&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;They&amp;rsquo;re a great bunch, improvising melodic lines at will and even making up lyrics right on the spot, just as they had at the last two years when I only watched. And the singing in harmony was fantastic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby got a little bit of video footage of us at one point:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/zYb1aBioAao&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For two years, I was afraid to join in the music jams at this annual July 3 party. This year I joined in a little bit. If we attend the party again next year, I hope to be in a position to contribute even more! Many thanks to Susan for hosting this annual party!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Second year at July 3 music party: still only listening without playing</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/07/03/second-year-at-july-3-music-party-still-only-listening-without-playing/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jul 2013 22:10:07 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/07/03/second-year-at-july-3-music-party-still-only-listening-without-playing/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/03/petrified-at-a-music-jam-session-so-i-didnt-play-but-watched-and-listened/&#34;&gt;Last year Abby and I went&lt;/a&gt; to a July 3 music potluck/party at Susan&amp;rsquo;s for the first time. We attended again. I brought my flute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again I enjoyed hearing two groups of people playing music. I am not so much into the &amp;ldquo;old time&amp;rdquo; music, however, which the group outside in the backyard was playing, so I hung out inside instead, where I liked much better the blues guitar and ukulele and singing and piano. &lt;em&gt;I would like to join in one day&lt;/em&gt; myself, but today did not feel up to it. I never took out my flute; it didn&amp;rsquo;t seem appropriate for any of the music anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2014-07-04&#34;&gt;(Update of 2014-07-04)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/07/03/third-year-at-july-3-music-party-and-finally-participated-in-jamming/&#34;&gt;my third year&lt;/a&gt; of this annual party, I actually played both piano and ukulele!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Stepping it up at the French and blues jam</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/02/25/stepping-it-up-at-the-french-and-blues-jam/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Feb 2013 23:09:11 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/02/25/stepping-it-up-at-the-french-and-blues-jam/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Last month, I reported on &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/28/my-first-blues-music-jam-happened-after-the-regular-french-music-jam/&#34;&gt;exciting new developments in the local French/blues music jam&lt;/a&gt; that happens approximately once a month. We continued with the excitement this month, playing more complex and difficult tunes that Lisa, John, Donna, and others have been transcribing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, if you are interested in checking out some of our growing French repertoire, take a look at our &lt;a href=&#34;http://drawthedots.com/&#34;&gt;transcriptions&lt;/a&gt;, choosing tunebook &amp;ldquo;Campanule by Gregory Dyke&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Tunes for Mondays by Lisa Tamres&amp;rdquo;. These tunebooks are always in progress, so not everything we know or are working on has been put up yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And if you live in the Pittsburgh area and would like to join in playing with us in the future, contact me!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;french-jam&#34;&gt;French jam&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I arrived somewhat late because I was coming from leaving the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/02/25/openhack-pittsburgh-studying-scala/&#34;&gt;second OpenHack Pittsburgh&lt;/a&gt; early (regrettably); in retrospect, I was trying to squeeze in too much on a Monday evening and should have skipped attending OpenHack Pittsburgh, but I had too much enjoyed &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/21/attending-the-first-openhack-pittsburgh-meeting/&#34;&gt;the first one&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I arrived, Lisa, John, and Allison were already playing together (on fiddle, accordion, piano), and I joined them for two hours of jamming and playing for the dancers who arrived later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was excited to be learning new (to me) music, in various different keys and modes and rhythms, while all still falling in the categories of waltz, mazurka, bourrée, Schottisch. Because of all the different keys, I ended up only playing my modern flute, not ever switching to my Irish flute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We took turns looking through some transcriptions and deciding what to work on, and one song I chose was something called &amp;ldquo;Les Ormeaux&amp;rdquo;. It&amp;rsquo;s a lovely song. Here is a performance of it on accordion I found:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/MxuXoaH5L2k&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;upcoming-french-dance-workshop&#34;&gt;Upcoming French dance workshop&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another French dance workshop is &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.facebook.com/events/161251944027578/&#34;&gt;being held at CMU on Saturday, March 9&lt;/a&gt;. There was discussion of getting a group of us together to play live music for the workshop. This reminded me that it was a year ago that I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/01/23/discovering-french-traditional-dance-in-pittsburgh/&#34;&gt;first became involved in French dance&lt;/a&gt; and also hoped to eventually play music at a workshop. Normally, I would jump at the opportunity to play for the next French dance workshop, taking up the main melody role on flute, but I simply anticipated being too busy to be involved in the next one coming up so soon, so I had to decline to join in. I hope that for the April workshop I&amp;rsquo;ll have more time to commit to joining in, rehearsing, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;blues-jam&#34;&gt;Blues jam&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was exhausted after two hours of the French jam and dance, plus I needed to get home as I promised Abby I would be home before she got back from being driven home from her mandolin practice, so I don&amp;rsquo;t know how the blues jam went. Maybe next month I&amp;rsquo;ll be able to check it out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a great time further exploring French music and continuing to play with Lisa, John, and Allison, whom I&amp;rsquo;ve played with several times now, getting to feel like a solid core group.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My first blues music jam happened after the regular French music jam</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/01/28/my-first-blues-music-jam-happened-after-the-regular-french-music-jam/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jan 2013 23:26:28 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/01/28/my-first-blues-music-jam-happened-after-the-regular-french-music-jam/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s been over two months since the last French music jam, which was in November. I didn&amp;rsquo;t write about it because there was nothing particularly remarkable about it compared to the whole past year of French music jams: there was Lisa, John, Allison, a new fiddler Liz, and Leslie joining us on banjo again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tonight, an addition was made to the program. For some time I had suggested to Lisa that for French/blues dance night, maybe there should be a blues jam in addition to the French jam. She liked that idea, got hold of people she knew who were interested, and so tonight was the first blues jam!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was actually &lt;em&gt;my first full participation in a blues jam&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was very anxious, but I&amp;rsquo;ve grown somewhat used to feeling anxious at least once a month in the past two years pushing myself into unfamiliar territory repeatedly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, there were some changes for the French jam. Here&amp;rsquo;s how the evening went.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;french-jam&#34;&gt;French jam&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this new year of French music jamming, John, Lisa, and others have kicked things off by transcribing some of their favorite tunes by listening to recordings, watching YouTube, or from memory, in order to share so that we can learn and play them. John couldn&amp;rsquo;t make it tonight, ironically, because he was sick, but I was very exciting that we started exploring a lot of new tunes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I showed up, it was just Lisa on fiddle, Allison on piano (she also brought her button accordion), and me. Enough to get going. (I switched between Irish flute and modern flute as needed depending on the key.) Later, Donna also showed up, on fiddle, and Jess showed up, on clarinet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We played for quite some time, including old favorites we already knew, for the dancers, and learning some new tunes. I think we were at it for two hours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;blues-jam&#34;&gt;Blues jam&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As some of the French dance crowd went home and the blues dance crowd came in, the blues jam began. There was Anders on piano, whom I recognized from his having played blues indoors at a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/03/petrified-at-a-music-jam-session-so-i-didnt-play-but-watched-and-listened/&#34;&gt;summer party&lt;/a&gt;; I may have seen him elsewhere also at &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/10/07/my-first-contra-dance-workshop-unexpected-fun./&#34;&gt;contra dance&lt;/a&gt; or something. I met Michael and Billy, who both had guitars and harmonicas. And all three of them were apparently willing to sing!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was really intimidated. I&amp;rsquo;m still totally, utterly a novice at blues, although I started working on that last year. I wasn&amp;rsquo;t even sure whether I shouldn&amp;rsquo;t pack up my flute and go home. After all, I&amp;rsquo;d already spent a lot of time on music this evening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But something happened that made me stay! Allison seemed like she was about to pack up too, but was curious, and stayed. No longer on piano, she was on her button accordion. We both confessed to never having done this before, but stayed on. I thought she was doing quite well. I wasn&amp;rsquo;t doing so well, but I participated in bits. (But no, I did not sing.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for playing for dancers, I think the dancers were sometimes confused by the experiment, because they didn&amp;rsquo;t have their usual iTunes playlist to dance to. Not everything we did was really suitable to the dancing they wanted to do. We&amp;rsquo;ll have to eventually figure out what works for the dancers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically, when it came to my first blues jam experience, I felt sort of the way I did when I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/05/14/playing-french-music-for-first-time-and-dancing-blues-for-first-time/&#34;&gt;first got into playing French music eight months ago&lt;/a&gt;: anxious, uncertain, embarrassed. But if I work at this and get more comfortable and better, the feeling will pass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d like to do more blues jamming. There is a bit of a problem in that this has made for a very long and late evening. I think that&amp;rsquo;s just the nature of the blues music/dance world. I&amp;rsquo;ll have to plan my schedule accordingly if I want to integrate a regular blues jam into my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And of course, I should continue my studies of the blues.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My second French music jam: playing my Irish flute in public for the first time</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/08/27/my-second-french-music-jam-playing-my-irish-flute-in-public-for-the-first-time/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Aug 2012 22:37:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/08/27/my-second-french-music-jam-playing-my-irish-flute-in-public-for-the-first-time/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Tonight I participated for the second time in a new little &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/groups/182324948478861/&#34;&gt;French traditional dance&lt;/a&gt; music jam session that &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/02/my-first-french-music-jam-anxious-but-excited/&#34;&gt;started up in July&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This time, I played not only my &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/baroque-flute/&#34;&gt;Baroque flute&lt;/a&gt; (which happens to be the instrument I&amp;rsquo;ve mostly been playing for the past two months), but also my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/30/got-my-new-casey-burns-small-handed-irish-flute/&#34;&gt;new Irish flute I got a month ago&lt;/a&gt;. I did &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; bring my modern flute at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we did the last time, after we played around for an hour or so, we then played for dancers for another hour. I enjoyed the experience a lot, and was less nervous than I was the first time. I am slowly improving at learning a tune, without a score, while someone is playing it, and then imitating the melodic line or filling in a harmonically sensible line on the fly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;instruments-and-musicians&#34;&gt;Instruments and musicians&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I finally received my Irish flute a month ago and have spent some minutes every day breaking it in at home. Tonight was its &amp;ldquo;debut&amp;rdquo; in public. I enjoyed the louder, stronger sound.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still used the Baroque flute, for key signatures that my keyless Irish flute does not work well for (half-holing is a pain).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also had fiddles, melodeon, guitar, mandolin (not all at the same time, since John was switching between melodeon and mandolin depending on the key of the song, given the limitations of the melodeon), and I felt that the Irish flute was balanced pretty well with the other instruments, better than the Baroque flute did in the first session in July (when it was often drowned out).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We lost some musicians from last time, because one of them left town, and the clarinetist has a class in the evening and therefore cannot arrive till later, when she comes to dance. But we had two new people!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our little French music group is gaining momentum. I&amp;rsquo;m very excited! Also, as the CMU fall semester starts, there are plans to really promote French and other traditional music and dance in the form of an official CMU student organization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2012-09-28&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-09-28)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/28/another-french-music-jam-also-announcing-cats-dance/&#34;&gt;CATS Dance successfully launched in September&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Another terrifying music jam session but I played a little bit of blues and old time</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/07/07/another-terrifying-music-jam-session-but-i-played-a-little-bit-of-blues-and-old-time/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Jul 2012 23:37:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/07/07/another-terrifying-music-jam-session-but-i-played-a-little-bit-of-blues-and-old-time/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/03/petrified-at-a-music-jam-session-so-i-didnt-play-but-watched-and-listened&#34;&gt;Just earlier this week, I went to a music jam where I was afraid to play&lt;/a&gt; and so I didn&amp;rsquo;t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today Abby and I went to another intimidating potluck/jam session, this time hosted by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.appalasia.com/Mimi.htm&#34;&gt;Mimi Jong&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://classic-sculpture.com/&#34;&gt;Susan Wagner&lt;/a&gt;. Mimi had invited Abby, but hadn&amp;rsquo;t yet met me; I knew who she was through having been to an &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.appalasia.com/&#34;&gt;Appalasia&lt;/a&gt; performance with Abby at some point earlier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This time I played a little bit. I almost didn&amp;rsquo;t, but felt that I had to start with something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;lots-of-music&#34;&gt;Lots of music&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was music going on outside in back of the home. Wow. It was fantastic stuff, what everyone was doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was Mimi on &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Erhu&#34;&gt;erhu&lt;/a&gt;, of course. There was a keyboard and sound system set up. People on bass, guitars, drums of all kinds, claves, banjos, violin, singing, you name it. All kinds of music was being jammed to. A lot of Latin music, sung by someone who seemed a native Spanish speaker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recognized a violinist as being someone who had played Baroque violin at a recital I had been at in April.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, there were clearly a lot of professional musicians here and so I felt really intimidated. I did a lot of watching and listening and quite enjoyed experiencing joy and inventiveness unfold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was fascinating seeing Mimi kicking off &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Summertime_(song)&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Summertime&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; on erhu. Hey, why not?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the Latin and Brazilian songs I knew the melodies for, and if I only knew all lyrics and could actually sing, I would have wanted to join in for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;joining-in&#34;&gt;Joining in&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But Mimi encouraged Abby and me to join in. At some point, Abby did join in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of the problem for me, besides the fact that I felt naked and helpless without a music score to read, was that I&amp;rsquo;d brought one case of instruments this time, which included some recorders as well as a Baroque flute, and it didn&amp;rsquo;t seem like any of these instruments was really suitable for the occasion. In my hurry to arrive at the potluck already running late, I had forgotten to bring my modern flute!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did the best I could and took out my Baroque flute and tried joining in. Some old time music came on and I found it not so difficult to do something for that, although nothing I was proud of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I remember mainly is when Mimi started some blues and at some point I came in and gave it a shot, and although I didn&amp;rsquo;t last very long, I got something in that wasn&amp;rsquo;t totally horrible. Somehow that was very liberating, getting those few seconds in for the evening. At least I didn&amp;rsquo;t walk away from the party this evening without playing anything at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Attending this potluck/jam session was an immensely exciting experience for me. I feel like I am truly expanding my musical world, and getting inspired. I too would like to be singing my favorite Latin songs. And I really like blues improvisation. I will start doing these things eventually; they are no longer just remote possibilities, but what I have seen people doing in front of my own eyes and not in an impersonal concert but at a casual, fun party.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-01-28&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-01-28)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Six months later, I participated in &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/28/my-first-blues-music-jam-happened-after-the-regular-french-music-jam/&#34;&gt;my first blues jam&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-09-28&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-09-28)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over a year later, I reported on &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/09/28/an-erhu-player-and-a-tuba-player-at-a-party-said-lets-jam/&#34;&gt;participating in a music jam at another one of these parties with Mimi&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Petrified at a music jam session so I didn&#39;t play but watched and listened</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/07/03/petrified-at-a-music-jam-session-so-i-didnt-play-but-watched-and-listened/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jul 2012 22:35:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/07/03/petrified-at-a-music-jam-session-so-i-didnt-play-but-watched-and-listened/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/02/my-first-french-music-jam-anxious-but-excited&#34;&gt;Just yesterday, I went to a music jam&lt;/a&gt; and was anxious but got over that and participated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today Abby and I went to a &lt;em&gt;very different&lt;/em&gt; one, a potluck/music jam hosted by Susan Waggoner, whom we&amp;rsquo;ve known for a long time through various Pittsburgh music and dance activities. Susan is involved particularly in the Cajun music/dance scene, and was also in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.post-gazette.com/stories/local/neighborhoods-city/accordion-pool-partys-another-use-for-empty-lawrenceville-pool-357459/&#34;&gt;Accordion Pool Party&lt;/a&gt; that Abby played in three years ago, and also has been doing &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/01/23/discovering-french-traditional-dance-in-pittsburgh/&#34;&gt;French dancing&lt;/a&gt; with us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was so &lt;em&gt;terrified&lt;/em&gt; at this party that I didn&amp;rsquo;t play &lt;em&gt;at all&lt;/em&gt;, despite bringing my instruments. I just didn&amp;rsquo;t feel up to it. But I learned a lot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;two-main-groups-of-musicians&#34;&gt;Two main groups of musicians&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that there were a bunch of musicians playing music outside in the back of the home. I wasn&amp;rsquo;t super familiar with what they were playing. Then there were some musicians playing music inside in the living room.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They really knew what they were doing, and were singing and playing by ear, no scores in sight. Without any scores, I had no clue how I could contribute, so I didn&amp;rsquo;t even take out my instruments. This was &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; jamming, not the kind that I did yesterday where most (but not all) of the stuff we did involved songs I had brought scores for or at least had heard before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;old-time-music&#34;&gt;Old time music&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was told by the men and women who were inside that those outside were playing &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Old-time_music&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;old time&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; music. I hadn&amp;rsquo;t been familiar with the term or genre.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby liked being outside, and also has been playing mandolin, so spent time checking out that group. I think she played along some too. It seemed to be mostly fiddlers, with banjo, mandolin, percussion, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I checked it out, but the music happened not to be quite so interesting to me; it moved fast, had a lot of notes, but seemed somewhat monotonous to my taste.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;country-blues-music&#34;&gt;Country blues music&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inside, however, I was really captivated by what was going on. They said that they were playing &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Country_blues&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;country blues&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. I liked the harmonic changes and the rhythmic qualities and improvisation. Guitars, harmonica, piano, singing. I was impressed by how the singers made up entire lyrics on the spot, often very funny or off-color.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I stayed around inside soaking in what was going on, and thought, I could see myself someday playing along.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was really excited to meet more musicians and widen my musical experience at the potluck/jam session. I felt pretty inspired by what I saw going on, music as a really communal, creative experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Noticing the huge gap between what these musicians were able to do and what I am able to do, I know that it takes a long time to get where they are, but I want to have that kind of everyday facility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2012-07-07&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-07-07)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Four days later, we went to another potluck/jam session, and &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/07/another-terrifying-music-jam-session-but-i-played-a-little-bit-of-blues-and-old-time/&#34;&gt;I played a little bit&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-01-28&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-01-28)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seven months later, I participated in &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/28/my-first-blues-music-jam-happened-after-the-regular-french-music-jam/&#34;&gt;my first blues jam&lt;/a&gt;. The pianist there, Anders, was the same one I first saw here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-07-03&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-07-03)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/07/03/second-year-at-july-3-music-party-still-only-listening-without-playing/&#34;&gt;my second year&lt;/a&gt; of this annual party, I still did not feel comfortable enough with the crowd to try to participate musically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2014-07-03&#34;&gt;(Update of 2014-07-03)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/07/03/third-year-at-july-3-music-party-and-finally-participated-in-jamming/&#34;&gt;my third year&lt;/a&gt; of this annual party, I actually played both piano and ukulele!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My first French music jam: anxious but excited</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/07/02/my-first-french-music-jam-anxious-but-excited/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jul 2012 23:45:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/07/02/my-first-french-music-jam-anxious-but-excited/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Tonight I participated for the first time in a new local &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/groups/182324948478861/&#34;&gt;French traditional dance&lt;/a&gt; music jam session that is getting off the ground, organized by Lisa. I was really excited about the formation of our group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How did this come about?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;inspired-by-gregory&#34;&gt;Inspired by Gregory&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What happened was that after &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/05/14/playing-french-music-for-first-time-and-dancing-blues-for-first-time/&#34;&gt;Gregory left us this summer&lt;/a&gt;, I told Lisa that I really wanted to do the kind of thing Gregory had been doing, playing French music for dancers. Lisa was excited about this and thought it would be cool for herself to start playing fiddle again. She found some other people who were interested in playing French music together, and so we met up!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;instruments&#34;&gt;Instruments&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tonight, I played both my &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/baroque-flute/&#34;&gt;Baroque flute&lt;/a&gt; and my modern flute. I didn&amp;rsquo;t really want to play the modern flute, but there were times when we played some music in keys I wasn&amp;rsquo;t comfortable with on Baroque flute. Meanwhile, it will take a long time for the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/06/12/ordered-the-casey-burns-small-handed-irish-flute/&#34;&gt;Irish flute I ordered&lt;/a&gt; to be made and shipped. I really want to use the louder Irish flute when feasible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lisa had her fiddle, and someone else also had a fiddle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A guy brought his melodeon (button accordion), which unfortunately is limited in the keys it can play in. He sometimes used the old upright piano also. There was someone else who also used the piano.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there was someone on clarinet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-it-went&#34;&gt;How it went&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was quite nervous, because much of what we did was not from printed scores, but from people&amp;rsquo;s memories of their favorite tunes. I in fact ended up using my phone to send Lisa a PDF of Gregory&amp;rsquo;s French music score compilation so that she could print it out for some of us!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I quickly noticed that my Baroque flute was being drowned out by the other instruments. So I pulled out my modern flute sometimes in order to be heard more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We went on for quite some time as the dancers arrived and became restless, and then we played for them for about an hour. Actually, I was heard better then, because Lisa and some other musicians gave introductory lessons or themselves wanted to dance. The result was that after a while, it was just Donna on fiddle, John on melodeon, and me on Baroque flute playing for the dancers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s really a joy playing music for people to dance to. I feel like I&amp;rsquo;m starting to fulfill my dream that &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/10/flute-loving-it-again/&#34;&gt;I dared to mention in March: that of being the musician rather than the dancer at a dance&lt;/a&gt;. During his time here in Pittsburgh, I was really inspired by the example of Gregory (who has finished his stay in the country and gone back to Europe) to start learning tunes by ear, ornamenting, and improvising. I&amp;rsquo;m still quite a beginner at this approach to music, but this is what I&amp;rsquo;ve always wanted to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first French music jam and new format for the French dance (live music instead of iTunes) was a great start of something new. We were all so excited that we definitely want to continue doing this. I look forward to continuing to play together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2012-08-27&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-08-27)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And less than two months later, I am &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/08/27/my-second-french-music-jam-playing-my-irish-flute-in-public-for-the-first-time/&#34;&gt;still involved in the new French music jam&lt;/a&gt;, and finally with my own Irish flute!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Playing French music for the first time, and dancing blues for the first time</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/05/14/playing-french-music-for-first-time-and-dancing-blues-for-first-time/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 May 2012 23:44:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/05/14/playing-french-music-for-first-time-and-dancing-blues-for-first-time/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Although I have stopped writing about it, Abby and I have continued to do &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/02/20/enjoying-more-french-dancing-in-pittsburgh/&#34;&gt;French dancing here in Pittsburgh&lt;/a&gt;. Tonight, for the first time, we finally attended the regular Monday night French and blues dance hosted by Lisa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was quite an intense evening for me, both playing French music &lt;em&gt;for the first time&lt;/em&gt; and dancing blues &lt;em&gt;for the first time&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;french-and-blues-social-dance&#34;&gt;French and blues social dance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;French &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; blues night?! What&amp;rsquo;s the connection?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, the story is simply that Lisa and Gregory (and some other dancers) enjoy both French music/dance and blues music/dance, so both types of music and dance are combined into one evening of dancing. Of course, there are people who show up who are only interested in the French or only interested in the blues. The iTunes playlists have a mix of both.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-i-wanted-to-go&#34;&gt;Why I wanted to go&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d never done blues dancing before, and was curious to see it, and maybe learn some and try it with Abby, who is also completely unfamiliar with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also: since Gregory is going back back to Europe soon, I wanted to have an opportunity to see him again before he left, and finally play French music with him. I&amp;rsquo;d never played French music before. When I told him I wanted to come and play with him for the first time, he helpfully sent me a link to his compilation of French tunes, &lt;a href=&#34;http://drawthedots.com/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Campanule&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. I feverishly tried to learn some of them before showing up. That was tricky because I wanted to play the music on my Baroque flute, an instrument that I&amp;rsquo;m &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/04/21/my-first-time-in-a-public-music-jam-intense-fun-with-chris-norman-and-david-greenberg/&#34;&gt;still quite a beginner at&lt;/a&gt;. But I didn&amp;rsquo;t want to use the modern flute for this music; it doesn&amp;rsquo;t produce the kind of sound I like for traditional music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;playing-music-with-gregory&#34;&gt;Playing music with Gregory&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gregory and I spent maybe ten minutes playing some of his compiled music sort of together. This was very hard for me for a number of reasons:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m still pretty bad at Baroque flute, having trouble with fingerings and intonation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t know the tunes very well, and was trying to find them in my printouts of his scores.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;He doesn&amp;rsquo;t even look at the scores, but just plays from memory.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;He doesn&amp;rsquo;t play exactly what was in the scores anyway, but improvises at will.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We were not coordinated, because he repeated sections or measures at will, and we didn&amp;rsquo;t really take turns or something.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t know how to come up with a secondary line or accompaniment on the fly to blend in with Gregory.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As dancers started arriving and Gregory kept on playing, I stopped my feeble attempts at contributing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a way, my attempt to get into playing French music tonight was a &lt;em&gt;failure&lt;/em&gt;, but on the other hand, I actually learned a lot from observing Gregory, and knew what I had to do to be able to function as an actual musician for dancing. I had to memorize tunes, learn them by ear, get myself off the tyranny of printed scores, watch dancers, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;dancing-blues&#34;&gt;Dancing blues&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point, the French dance part of the evening started to end, as the demand for blues rose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There wasn&amp;rsquo;t going to be any blues dance instruction, so Abby and I had a choice. We could just watch, or we could leave. We did do some watching, but I decided I wanted to dance, and so I just started making stuff up. I got the impression that people were basically just leading and following through improvisation similar to what I&amp;rsquo;ve experienced before when I did some Argentine tango (and a bit of Lindy hop and West Coast swing). I rather enjoy that kind of improvisational dancing, but have had little opportunity to participate in it because Abby is not used to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We did do a bit of blues dancing tonight, but it&amp;rsquo;s not clear to me whether we will continue. I&amp;rsquo;m very interested in exploring blues dance further, but Abby seems less interested. People are interested in different activities; that&amp;rsquo;s just a fact of life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This evening highlighted the contrast between my lack of ability to function as a practical musician for dancers and my comfort with improvisation as a dancer. I plan to work toward merging these two worlds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel sad that Gregory is leaving us, because I wanted to start working with him on French music, but his example has inspired me to want to continue playing French music after he is gone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2012-07-02&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-07-02)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And less than two months later, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/02/my-first-french-music-jam-anxious-but-excited/&#34;&gt;I joined Lisa and others in playing French music together, inspired by Gregory&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Enjoying more French dancing in Pittsburgh</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/02/20/enjoying-more-french-dancing-in-pittsburgh/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Feb 2012 01:03:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/02/20/enjoying-more-french-dancing-in-pittsburgh/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A month ago I reported on how Abby and I had our &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/01/23/discovering-french-traditional-dance-in-pittsburgh&#34;&gt;first experience of French traditional dance&lt;/a&gt;. On Saturday, we went again to Skibo Gym at Carnegie Mellon University for another fun session of French dancing from 4:00 to 7:00 PM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had a great time again, and afterwards joined the instructors and some other people in having dinner at &lt;a href=&#34;http://gulliftys.us/&#34;&gt;Gullifty&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;attendance&#34;&gt;Attendance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to some familiar faces, there were many new people we hadn&amp;rsquo;t met before, and I got my office mate John to go too. Abby and I learned some dances that were not taught the last time, and we got to do more of the dances we had learned the last time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The male-female ratio was not so great this time: it would be nice to have more men attend these workshops and dances! If you are male and interested in learning French dance, come next month!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;3-count-bourrée&#34;&gt;3-count bourrée&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last month, we had learned the 2-count bourrée, but this month we also added the 3-count. That&amp;rsquo;s really fast and was a real workout!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;dances-from-last-time&#34;&gt;Dances from last time&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We went over the dances from last time also. Since they were no longer new to me, I felt freer to feel the music more and make the most of enjoying the dances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, in a very simple circle dance, I felt like lifting my body up when we swung our arms upward, and letting my body bend naturally to the &amp;ldquo;1-2-3, down&amp;rdquo; movement. Otherwise, just stepping endlessly like a rigid robot was getting quite boring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last time, I was rather stiff and clumsy at the Schottische, waltz, and mazurka, because I was out of practice in these turning dances. This time I got more into the swing of things and remembered the fun I had doing ballroom dancing over ten years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were two other circle dances from last time that we did again. I really enjoy these partner switching dances. Again, since I knew the moves already, I felt freer to improve my technique and personal expression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;social-dancing&#34;&gt;Social dancing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A familiar musician, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/16/playing-recorder-and-flute-at-the-holiday-ball/&#34;&gt;Donna Isaac&lt;/a&gt;, played fiddle for us, with Gregory on his Irish flute again. I liked the different texture from last month&amp;rsquo;s piano and flute, but I have to confess that missing a bass line made the music harder to dance to. In fact, I ended up starting to hum my own bass line to fill in the harmonies to feel less of a musical omission and help my rhythm while dancing!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again I thank everyone who was at the workshop and dance. It was a great group. I am so happy to be dancing again. I had put it aside for a couple of years after Abby and I got married, but now I envision our making it a regular part of our lives again!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Sorry, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/02/19/why-i-have-not-posted-many-photos-or-videos-recently-exploitation/&#34;&gt;I took no photos or videos this time&lt;/a&gt;. I spent the whole time immersed in dancing!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;dinner-at-gullifty-s&#34;&gt;Dinner at Gullifty&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since people were talking about going to dinner afterwards, and this time Abby and I did not leave the dance early before it ended, we ended up joining six others for dinner. We helped pack stuff up and drove home and walked to Gullifty&amp;rsquo;s. I hadn&amp;rsquo;t been there in at least ten years. It&amp;rsquo;s not my favorite idea of food, but I made the most of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ordered a &amp;ldquo;pierogie burger&amp;rdquo; for dinner. Only in Pittsburgh, ha! It was actually pretty good. It was a burger that had pierogies on top, all encased in a bun. It came with a pickle and fries. Not the kind of food I usually eat, but &amp;ldquo;cheating&amp;rdquo; once in a while is fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, we &amp;ldquo;had&amp;rdquo; to have dessert. Gullifty&amp;rsquo;s is &amp;ldquo;famous&amp;rdquo; for desserts. Abby and I had reservations about continuing our &amp;ldquo;cheating&amp;rdquo; to desserts, but what the heck, we shared a triple chocolate cake. Unfortunately, we got a huge chunk of cake, as the waitress explained that it was the end of the cake so we got probably twice as much as we would ordinarily have received. We ate the whole thing, but I ended up feeling quite sugared out and bloated. That&amp;rsquo;s the punishment for &amp;ldquo;cheating&amp;rdquo; way too much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;blues-and-other-dancing&#34;&gt;Blues and other dancing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People at dinner were talking about needing to take a nap afterwards and then going to a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pittsburghdancecenter.com/&#34;&gt;blues dance&lt;/a&gt; at midnight. That&amp;rsquo;s very late for Abby and me to be dancing! We&amp;rsquo;ve never done blues dancing before but are interested in trying it out sometime (but not if it&amp;rsquo;s too late at night).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dinner gang was also into Lindy hop. I did a little bit of Lindy and swing a decade ago, but never got much into it. Maybe Abby and I should check that out too. I know there&amp;rsquo;s a lot of it here in Pittsburgh. In the past, I&amp;rsquo;ve gone to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.swingpgh.com&#34;&gt;Swing City&lt;/a&gt;. There&amp;rsquo;s the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.coalcountry.org/swingdances.html&#34;&gt;Edgewood Club&lt;/a&gt; also.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m kind of interested in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.chickenswing.com/&#34;&gt;Chicken Swing&lt;/a&gt; because it meets right at Carnegie Mellon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there&amp;rsquo;s West Coast swing in town too, at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pghwcs.com/&#34;&gt;Absolute Ballroom&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a lot of fun dancing with Abby more again, and also with other people, and hanging out at dinner. I am not a dance maniac any more, and time is limited, but I am excited about continuing with Abby to further explore dances we haven&amp;rsquo;t done much of before. It&amp;rsquo;s great exercise and great socializing!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2012-05-14&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-05-14)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three months later, I ended up beginning to &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/05/14/playing-french-music-for-first-time-and-dancing-blues-for-first-time/&#34;&gt;play French music on flutes&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>