<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Calf Sleeves on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/calf-sleeves/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Calf Sleeves on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/calf-sleeves/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Why I feel sad when people congratulate me for finishing the Pittsburgh Marathon</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/05/07/why-i-feel-sad-when-people-congratulate-me-for-finishing-the-pittsburgh-marathon/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 May 2013 11:07:36 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/05/07/why-i-feel-sad-when-people-congratulate-me-for-finishing-the-pittsburgh-marathon/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/medal.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;2013 Pittsburgh Marathon medal&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m on the second day of recovery after &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/05/06/2013-pittsburgh-marathon-my-135th-race-was-my-worst-i-finished/&#34;&gt;my debacle of a Pittsburgh Marathon&lt;/a&gt; two days ago. The recovery has been going very well; I think I&amp;rsquo;ll probably be walking &amp;ldquo;normally&amp;rdquo; (to a point) tomorrow. But meanwhile, I&amp;rsquo;ve been dealing with a lot of anger and sadness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I feel the most angry and sad when people congratulate me for finishing the marathon.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A warning up front: in this post I&amp;rsquo;m going to talk about some things that might give the wrong impression and make you angry, but I assure you that I am just speaking from the heart, and that my own reaction to finishing my marathon has no bearing on how I feel about &lt;em&gt;your&lt;/em&gt; finishing &lt;em&gt;your&lt;/em&gt; marathon, or anyone else&amp;rsquo;s. I simply have certain goals for myself when doing things like marathons, and I don&amp;rsquo;t believe that everyone has or should have the same kinds of goals as I do, and I respect your own goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m also writing this because I think I&amp;rsquo;m speaking not only for myself, but for other runners who might also feel the same way but tiptoe around expressing their feelings, precisely because of the fear of offending those who might take the self-criticism the wrong way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;not-my-first-marathon&#34;&gt;Not my first marathon&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the first thing you have to realize is that this is not my first marathon. It is my second Pittsburgh Marathon. And it is probably the &lt;em&gt;sixth&lt;/em&gt; time I at least mostly run (versus walked) a consecutive 26.2 miles or more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was fairly thrilled to &lt;em&gt;finish&lt;/em&gt; my &lt;em&gt;first&lt;/em&gt; marathon, which was the 2003 Pittsburgh Marathon, even though it was also basically an embarrassing disaster, because it was my first. There is nothing like the first, because before going in, no matter what, you just wonder whether you will finish at all. It is so unknown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;marathon-long-training-run&#34;&gt;Marathon-long training run&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did one or two marathon-long training runs just by myself in Frick Park and Homewood Cemetery in 2006, while trying to toughen myself up for the Rachel Carson Trail Challenge. I did those slowly, so that I experienced none of the suffering from going too fast in my first Pittsburgh Marathon. This was a very important experience for me because I needed to prove to myself that simply going very slowly, I could cover a marathon distance any day of my life by just hopping out of bed without any special training. I wanted to defuse the mystique of the marathon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ended up abandoning doing my own marathon-distance runs, however, because even if I didn&amp;rsquo;t suffer horribly, it still took a long time to fully recover. In fact, I made the mistake of playing in a chess tournament two days after one of these runs and had one of the worst tournaments in my life, in which my brain was deprived of fuel and I could not think. &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ben_Finegold&#34;&gt;Ben Finegold&lt;/a&gt;, I never explained to you why I self-destructed while easily winning a game against your (then) wife in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.uschess.org/msa/XtblMain.php?200607092031.1-12226800&#34;&gt;Columbus Open&lt;/a&gt;, but now you know!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;sammy-s-birthday-run&#34;&gt;Sammy&amp;rsquo;s Birthday Run&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2006, I ran/walked (after completing the Rachel Carson Trail Challenge) Sammy&amp;rsquo;s Birthday Run, covering 27.5 miles before I quit. I was going pretty slow. I was not doing it for time. I was doing it just to finish at least a marathon distance, although I was kind of hoping to get to 30 miles (I stopped because I felt my body had enough and I didn&amp;rsquo;t need more punishment). I didn&amp;rsquo;t time myself, but I know I finished in about &lt;em&gt;5 hours and 15 minutes&lt;/em&gt; (there is a 6 hour time limit for the run, and I arrived about half an hour late for the official start). This was with no carb-loading, any of that stuff. Just showing up an running really slowly, walking some of the uphill sections. I drank some sports drink that I brought, and ate boiled potatoes and pretzels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No cramping up, no suffering (other than increasing fatigue and leg heaviness). Here is what I looked like finishing:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/franklin-finishing-sammys-birthday-run-2006.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin finishing Sammy&amp;#39;s Birthday Run 2006&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In 2008, I did Sammy&amp;rsquo;s Birthday Run again, with even less training and fitness. This time I timed myself. I finished my 27.5 miles in 5:55:22. Hardly a great time, but it was a finish, and without any real suffering except at one moment. At around mile 22, I made the mistake of eating some cookies that someone had brought, and was in instant agony with stomach cramps. I slowed way down for a couple of minutes. Then I sat down for 9 minutes, used the Port-a-pottie, was OK again, and continued. But other than that incident, I had no leg or foot problems. So, basically what I&amp;rsquo;m saying is that &lt;em&gt;for me&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;finishing a marathon distance by simply going slow&lt;/em&gt; is &lt;em&gt;trivial&lt;/em&gt;, and therefore does not give me a sense of accomplishment. &lt;em&gt;For you&lt;/em&gt;, finishing might be nontrivial, in which case you definitely deserve to be proud upon finishing your marathon!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;training&#34;&gt;Training&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So another thing that some people have said is, &amp;ldquo;You should be proud of myself for all the training I put in to finish the marathon!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I&amp;rsquo;m not proud. I&amp;rsquo;m embarrassed and angry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One reason: it is possible that with &lt;em&gt;no training whatsoever&lt;/em&gt;, I could have finished Sunday&amp;rsquo;s marathon in 4:38, with far less suffering. I did an average 10:37 pace for that marathon (including the minutes I spent at the side of the road resting). What if I had just gone into the marathon healthy, without messed up legs and feet and body, fully rested, and simply jogged slowly (for me) at 10:37 pace the whole way?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An even better reason: look at my training record that I&amp;rsquo;ve documented since February. My cramping and slowing down before mile 11 was a total joke. It wasn&amp;rsquo;t training that &lt;em&gt;enabled&lt;/em&gt; me to get past that. It was &lt;em&gt;overtraining&lt;/em&gt; that &lt;em&gt;disabled&lt;/em&gt; my fitness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two months ago, in March, I was &lt;em&gt;barely&lt;/em&gt; starting marathon training. I did a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/09/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings-in-one-12-mile-run/&#34;&gt;12-mile run crossing Pittsburgh bridges 11 times&lt;/a&gt; that was tough for me. I averaged just a bit faster than 10-minute pace. Just a month later, I had already gotten much stronger: I did my hardest run, a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/04/13/my-final-16-mile-long-run-before-pittsburgh-marathon-featured-two-radical-experiments/&#34;&gt;16-mile run&lt;/a&gt;, in 2:27, for an average of 9:11 pace. And I did that in Luna Sandals, with no blisters, no leg cramping, no problems. And without breakfast and without any Gatorade or gel or food during the entire run! And that was just a training run, not a race where I gave it my all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, that 16-mile run was the last time I felt really strong. I screwed things up after that. I could have run the Pittsburgh Marathon that day, probably, and finished in 4:00.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;shoes&#34;&gt;Shoes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I get the impression that some people are questioning my shoe choice, wondering whether wearing Luna Sandals messed up my marathon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This also upsets me, because the last thing I want is for Luna Sandals to get a bad reputation just because I happened to be wearing them when I ran a bad marathon. Fact is, as I explained, I believe the Luna Sandals &lt;em&gt;saved&lt;/em&gt; me from much worse. I had toe cramping wearing non-sandals in all my previous half marathons and marathons. And I have to refer again back to the 16-mile long run that I did in Luna Sandals. I didn&amp;rsquo;t wear these shoes untested in the marathon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;finishing-versus-excelling&#34;&gt;Finishing versus excelling&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem with the marathon is that it is such a public event, and there is so much focus on &amp;ldquo;finishing&amp;rdquo; one. I don&amp;rsquo;t feel good about merely &amp;ldquo;finishing&amp;rdquo; a marathon. Here are some analogies I make to myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m an amateur flutist, and still a beginner, with only two years of serious self-study so far. Suppose I had the opportunity to somehow get put into a professional orchestra, and got assigned to perform a flute concerto. Suppose we did the performance, and after messing everything up and playing quite poorly, we got to the end. Would I feel proud of &amp;ldquo;finishing&amp;rdquo; the performance? This is exactly how I personally feel about what I did in the marathon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some possible modifications to the music program that would make me proud of &amp;ldquo;finishing&amp;rdquo;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Suppose that we took the flute concerto slowly enough that I could get most of the notes and expressiveness in. Then at least it would preserve some integrity that I could be proud of.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Suppose that we chose a much easier and shorter piece that I could actually master, and we played that.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The analogues in the running world:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I could have done the marathon very slowly, like with Sammy&amp;rsquo;s Birthday Run, and run an even pace, with no suffering other than extreme fatigue, and been proud of that.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I could have abandoned the idea of finishing a marathon at all and choose to run half marathon or 5K races that I can run fast and well.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personally, I am far more proud of my fastest 5K, 10K, and half marathon races than of any marathon I have done or ever will do again, because they stand as gems of perfect execution. I would rather do a smaller thing well and completely than a bigger thing badly and sloppily.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nobody ever cheered for me as I performed my greatest feats in the 5K, 10K, and half marathon where I thought I was going to puke or fall apart, but those are the moments I treasure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So in fact, I am abandoning the marathon and returning to trying to improve my performances at shorter distances. You will not be congratulating me as I shave off minutes or seconds from my times, but that&amp;rsquo;s OK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m very emotional right now, and I felt now was as good a time as any to say something about my personal values and goals when it comes to running races, and by extension, to other aspects of my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I actually do feel good about finishing the marathon in one respect: I proved that even if I totally screwed everything up, and deserved all the pain I experienced, and it was all my own fault that I could have avoided, I went on anyway and got the job done. When I realize that this is what people are trying to communicate to me by congratulate me, I am very appreciative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-05-09&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-05-09)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following day, the third day after the marathon, I was able to walk normally and was emotionally recovering as well and was embarrassed by this rant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fourth day, I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/05/09/back-to-what-running-is-really-about-for-me/&#34;&gt;went out for a short run and reflected on what running is really about for me&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2013 Pittsburgh Marathon: my 135th race was the worst I finished, but I did!</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/05/06/2013-pittsburgh-marathon-my-135th-race-was-my-worst-i-finished/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 May 2013 20:23:08 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/05/06/2013-pittsburgh-marathon-my-135th-race-was-my-worst-i-finished/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/runner-of-steel.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin Chen, runner of steel&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/lying-down.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin lying down&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, for my birthday, I ran the Pittsburgh Marathon for the second time. The first time was &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/30/why-and-how-i-am-going-to-run-the-2013-pittsburgh-marathon/&#34;&gt;ten years ago, in 2003&lt;/a&gt;. That was an ordeal in which I had aimed at finishing in 3:30 and in fact run the first half in 1:45, but then faltered badly to struggle to finish in a &lt;a href=&#34;http://runhigh.com/.2003%20Results%20A/R050403AA.html&#34;&gt;chip time of 3:53:25&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My second Pittsburgh Marathon went even worse. I had wanted to finish in 4:00, but instead &lt;a href=&#34;http://results.active.com/events/dicks-sporting-goods-pittsburgh-marathon&#34;&gt;finished in 4:38:21&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was my 135th race in my life, and the worst of them all that I actually finished (I failed to finish one 30K race because of severe illness that should have kept me from going to the start line at all).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s my report on what happened, why, my thankfulness for all the good that came from the experience, and my running plans for the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;coming-back-from-injury-and-burnout&#34;&gt;Coming back from injury and burnout&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it&amp;rsquo;s important to understand that my poor performance did not come from nowhere. I had battled injury and burnout &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/05/04/i-spent-the-past-week-not-knowing-whether-i-could-run-in-the-2013-pittsburgh-marathon-tomorrow/&#34;&gt;for some time&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Logically&lt;/em&gt;, I should not have gone to the start line at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;night-before&#34;&gt;Night before&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got zero sleep the night before the race. Terrible, but my body was probably confused by the carb-loaded diet as well as my insistence on spending the whole day napping because I was so tired. I had felt that I had to do that napping because I was not going to be able to sleep well at night anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;early-morning-on-race-day&#34;&gt;Early morning on race day&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Super early, Abby drove us to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.visitpittsburgh.com/essentials/neighborhoods/north-shore/&#34;&gt;North Shore&lt;/a&gt; to park. Then we napped for a bit before heading to the nearest &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pittsburgh_Light_Rail&#34;&gt;light rail (aka &amp;ldquo;T&amp;rdquo;)&lt;/a&gt; station to wait for a ride downtown:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/go-downtown.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby and I wait for T&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We got downtown finally, I dropped off a bag of post-race flip-flops at Gear Check, time was starting to run out, and I got in line for a Port-a-pottie:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/port-a-potties.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Port-a-potties&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It was 15 minutes before I did what I needed to do. Then I had to quickly head to my corral.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;clothing&#34;&gt;Clothing&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/franklin-before-marathon.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin before marathon&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What I wore:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the &lt;em&gt;same blue singlet&lt;/em&gt; I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/30/why-and-how-i-am-going-to-run-the-2013-pittsburgh-marathon/&#34;&gt;wore in the 2003 Pittsburgh Marathon ten years ago&lt;/a&gt; (my favorite running shirt that I have actually worn for probably at least 70 of my races in over a decade, as well as most of my warm-weather casual runs also!!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Brooks Infiniti Short III that I bought at Elite Runners and Walkers before the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/30/report-on-just-a-short-run-my-first-half-marathon-in-nine-years/&#34;&gt;Just A Short Run half marathon in March&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Luna Sandals (Venado) that I&amp;rsquo;ve been wearing for almost all of my runs in the past month, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/04/13/my-final-16-mile-long-run-before-pittsburgh-marathon-featured-two-radical-experiments/&#34;&gt;maximum distance of 16 miles&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CEP compression calf sleeves, which I had worn just &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/04/20/on-overtraining-and-feeling-injured-two-weeks-before-the-pittsburgh-marathon/&#34;&gt;one other time&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/22/paradox-i-will-observe-the-national-day-of-unplugging-but-just-bought-my-first-smartphone-this-week/&#34;&gt;phone&lt;/a&gt;, in a SPIbelt.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;on my back, I pinned a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/04/20/on-overtraining-and-feeling-injured-two-weeks-before-the-pittsburgh-marathon/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;We are all Boston Marathoners at heart&amp;rdquo; bib&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a long-sleeve T-shirt on top of my singlet, since it was cold (under 50 degrees F?) before the race; the plan was to discard this T-shirt before the race (and hope that people collect it and find a good home for it!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;entering-the-corral&#34;&gt;Entering the corral&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the second race in my life in which I have carried a phone. I planned to use it only in case of emergency, and in order to meet up with Abby afterwards, but as you can see, while I had a chance, I took some photos also.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/corral-c.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Corral C&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I was assigned to corral C because of my estimated finish time of 4:00 that I had written down when signing up for the marathon months ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This was my first mistake.&lt;/em&gt; Given my comeback from injury and inactivity, the truly logical thing for me to have done was to set a very conservative goal of simply finishing the marathon without terrible suffering. Given that I ended up finishing in 4:38, I might as well have moved back into another corral and &lt;em&gt;planned&lt;/em&gt; to finish in the 4:20-4:30 range, in which case I bet I would have done that with minimal pain and suffering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the future, I resolve to face the facts on the ground in any event as strenuous as a marathon. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t make any sense what I did, especially given that I was perfectly smart when &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/30/report-on-just-a-short-run-my-first-half-marathon-in-nine-years/&#34;&gt;in March I did my first half marathon in nine years and ran it conservatively and had a great experience&lt;/a&gt;! I am capable of logical reasoning and have actually executed it in the past. But apparently the marathon puts me into a hyper-emotional frame of mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;pace&#34;&gt;Pace?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, I had chosen not to sign up to follow an &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pittsburghmarathon.com/pace-team&#34;&gt;official pacer&lt;/a&gt;, because on all my long training runs, I had found my own pace by feel, and done well ignoring pacers. My plan was simply to go slow and then get faster. I did look around for pace signs. I only saw one from where I was standing: a sign near the front of the corral for finishing in 3:50. I looked back and saw no other signs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This was my second mistake.&lt;/em&gt; Given that I had not done any serious running for ten days, with my longest run being only two miles, and my last &amp;ldquo;long&amp;rdquo; run was an eleven-mile run fifteen days ago, I should have realized that whatever &amp;ldquo;feel&amp;rdquo; I had for pace was gone, and I should have moved back in the corral till I found a 4:00-finishing pacer, at least (but as mentioned earlier, what I should have done was move into a slower corral altogether and then found a suitable pacer there).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;race-start&#34;&gt;Race start&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a moment of silence for Boston.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Star-Spangled Banner, then the waves began. A photo as mine was approaching the start line, around 7:05 AM:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/start-line.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;About to reach the start line&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Then we went.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;wrong-pace&#34;&gt;Wrong pace&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I honestly thought I was going slow. I was hardly breathing at all. I was going so &amp;ldquo;slow&amp;rdquo; that I pulled out my phone to take some photos. But then I got very confused, because the 3:50 pacer was still in my sight after many minutes:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/early.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Early in the marathon&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I could not process this information. Part of me wanted to slow down, but I felt like I was barely running. Part of me believed that the pacer must be slow, but come on, these pacers are supposed to be reliable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I &lt;em&gt;made the mistake&lt;/em&gt; of not trusting the pacer. It sounds crazy, but I really felt like I was going too slow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;slowing-down&#34;&gt;Slowing down?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point, I lost sight of the pacer, so I felt reassured that I must have slowed down properly. Here&amp;rsquo;s another problem: I did not keep track of my mile splits because the mass of people made it hard for me to actually reliably spot any mile markers on the course; I don&amp;rsquo;t even know how many actually existed.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/bridge.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Crossing bridge&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I even took a photo of myself 40 minutes into the marathon feeling fine.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/franklin-early.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There were spectators on bridges, some of them positioned seemingly precariously.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/spectators-on-bridges.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Spectators on bridge&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At some point I realized that I could see the 3:50 pacer up ahead. I got worried. It was unlikely that I was magically super-fit now. But I didn&amp;rsquo;t feel like slowing down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point I must have started slowing down, because eventually I saw a 3:55 pacer pass me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still, it appears from the alert system that I signed up for (to notify my parents by email, and Abby by text message, and my Facebook friends and Twitter followers), that I did the first 10K (6.2 miles) in 55:29, meaning an average pace of 8:56 and estimated finish time of 3:54:04. That&amp;rsquo;s much faster than the 9:08 pace I had intended for a 4:00 finish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;really-slowing-down&#34;&gt;Really slowing down&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started really slowing down before even reaching the Birmingham Bridge. I knew I was getting into serious trouble. It was crazy, but my left knee was bothering me, and my left quads had started to twitch. So I had gone only about 11 miles and I was already struggling.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/birmingham-bridge.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;On Birmingham Bridge&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You have to understand how &lt;em&gt;nonsensical&lt;/em&gt; it is for me to be having muscle cramping after running only 11 miles at a pace that is actually slow for an 11-mile run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if we assumed, falsely, that I got to mile 11 at the same pace as during my first 6.2 miles (8:56), note that I ran an entire half marathon (13.1 miles) in late March, only in the beginning of marathon training, at an average of 8:28 pace, and was totally fine with no cramping during the race. And after a couple of weeks of further training, I had felt much stronger during a 16-mile run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So basically, it was a cruel joke I played on myself that I was in such poor condition that I was cramping up after 11 miles at a slow pace. I was very angry at myself that I had made a complete &lt;em&gt;travesty&lt;/em&gt; of my marathon, &lt;em&gt;just like in 2003&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;halfway-and-change-of-plan&#34;&gt;Halfway, and change of plan&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I slowed down more in Oakland to keep the left quad twitching under control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the alert system, I got halfway in 1:59:46, average pace of 9:09, and estimated finish time of 3:59:31. But of course, by then, I knew that I was done for. I was just going to continue slowing down and suffering, for &lt;em&gt;over two more hours&lt;/em&gt;, if I finished at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I finally saw the 4:00 pace group pass me, somehow that was a real blow to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At 9:27 AM, not too long after the halfway point, I texted Abby: &amp;ldquo;Severe pain. Very slow, just aim finish. Maybe 4:30.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now my main thought was to focus on making it to Annie (of the Pittsburgh Recorder Society), who was going to watch for me in Highland Park, just before mile 20. I had told her to expect me around 10 AM, and Annie had even posted to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/photo.php?fbid=463404163737512&amp;amp;set=a.368839359860660.86924.330712777006652&amp;amp;type=1&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Recorder Society Facebook page&lt;/a&gt; telling everyone I was running.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was so not going to make it for 10 AM. But I wanted to go slowly enough that I could hold off the quad cramping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;despair&#34;&gt;Despair&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At around 9:49 AM, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.runoverit.com/&#34;&gt;Chris&lt;/a&gt; passed me and said hello. I told him I was doing very badly. He wasn&amp;rsquo;t doing as well as he had hoped, but was moving along, unlike me. Here&amp;rsquo;s a photo I had the presence of mind to take only as he had already gone way ahead (in the blue shirt):&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/chris.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Chris up ahead in blue shirt&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At 9:54 AM, I made a video statement on my phone, just for myself: &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m after mile 17 or something, in Homewood. I&amp;rsquo;m doing really badly, but I&amp;rsquo;m still running, and that&amp;rsquo;s all I can say about that.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/12inzKGZGRU&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/despair.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Despair after mile 17 in Pittsburgh Marathon&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;annie&#34;&gt;Annie&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At 10:11 AM, not yet at Annie&amp;rsquo;s, I was contemplating quitting, because the pains I was experiencing (right quads twitching also, and even my arms and hands, mysteriously, in spots where I had old injuries years ago, plus a really bad blister on my right foot where I had all those skin problems earlier, and less bad but very annoying constant chafing of the Luna Sandals straps) were so terrible. I decided to just take a break at a fluid station and squat and stretch. I texted Abby: &amp;ldquo;Very bad shape. Rested some.&amp;rdquo; I also finally &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/franklin.chen/posts/10201315392704609&#34;&gt;posted to Facebook&lt;/a&gt;, &amp;ldquo;In very bad shape. Trying to finish anyway.&amp;rdquo; I was not actively reading Facebook during the marathon at all, but did notice a lot of notifications, and assumed they were words of encouragement from my friends; I didn&amp;rsquo;t want to read them until I was done, because I felt I might let them down. Abby replied, &amp;ldquo;What is your plan?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At 10:19, I said, &amp;ldquo;Don&amp;rsquo;t know. Walking, blister and cramping.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A note on the blistering and chafing: it got really warm and I got sweaty, so that was part of the problem. I had not run in these sandals in such conditions before: I had mostly run in dry, cold conditions of 35-50 degrees F. Also, I had forgotten about road hazards: there were cups of water and Gatorade all over around the aid stations and my feet were sticky and wet for much of the marathon. It was a rather unpleasant feeling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I kept running/walking. I saw Annie. I decided there and then, seeing her, that I was going to finish, rather than just bail out and crash on her couch or something pathetic like that. I shouted that I was in severe pain but planned to continue on! She took a photo of me, which I knew was going to be on Facebook before too long, so I&amp;rsquo;d better make good on my promise to her!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/franklin-in-highland-park.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin in Highland Park&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At 10:29, I texted Abby: &amp;ldquo;Got to Annie. Running again.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I then focused on just continuing to move, slowing to a walk if I needed to in order to deal with cramping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;mile-22&#34;&gt;Mile 22&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At 10:51, I reached S Aiken, just before mile 22. This is an important point in the course for me, not only because it begins a downhill, but also because it is where my friend Nathaniel cheered me on ten years ago when I was also suffering.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/aiken.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;S Aiken&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;strip-district&#34;&gt;Strip District&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point, I was getting discouraged again and started walking, when I accidentally spotted Deb and Mark watching. Seeing familiar faces among the spectators is definitely helpful! Upon seeing them, I felt ashamed of my walking and my negative thoughts. I went up to them, and they were going to take a picture of me, and I got all determined, and &lt;em&gt;screamed&lt;/em&gt;, &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m going to finish this thing!!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/im-going-to-finish-this-thing.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin determined to finish&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I kept on running, and did not stop, even though I saw many people walking, and also saw many relay runners zooming by. I decided that I was not only going to finish (it was now clear that I could), but that I was going to finish as strong as I could, even though it would count for nothing. I was going to run at the edge of quad twitching, all the way to the end. It was going to hurt far more than if I just ran very slowly to finish, but I didn&amp;rsquo;t come this far just to walk if I could run. I was determined to push.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/franklin-in-strip.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin in Strip District&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As I got closer and closer, I periodically texted Abby the street I had just crossed, so that she would know roughly when I was going to finish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;finish-line&#34;&gt;Finish line&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so I finished. I finished in a state of my quads twitching like firecrackers. I got my medal. I kept on walking. I grabbed a bag of chips and water. I forgot to look for other stuff, like Smiley Cookies (that Abby later said she saw were being handed out). I just wanted to stop the twitching, get my bag from Gear Check, get out of my Luna Sandals into some comfortable, cushioned flip-flops, use a Port-a-potty, and finally find Abby and the &amp;ldquo;CMU tent&amp;rdquo;, which I assumed was just a section of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pittsburghmarathon.com/PCC&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Corporate Challenge Tent&lt;/a&gt;. (I had bought a bracelet for Abby earlier so that she could have access to the tent.)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/after.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;After finishing&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I could barely walk after I started cooling down, because I got stiffer and stiffer. It took me forever to make it to the Finish Line Festival area, and I was so mentally drained that I had to call Abby to have her tell me where the tent was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;videos-update-of-2013-05-23&#34;&gt;Videos (update of 2013-05-23)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburgh.cbslocal.com/2013/05/05/2013-marathon-finish-line-videos/&#34;&gt;Videos of the Pittsburgh Marathon have been posted&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found myself in &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburgh.cbslocal.com/video/8844851-2013-marathon-finish-line-44000-45000/&#34;&gt;one of the sets of videos&lt;/a&gt;, for those who finished in a clock time between 4:40:00 and 4:50:00.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see me at around 4:44:35 and finishing at about 4:44:40 here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&#39;text/javascript&#39; src=&#39;http://CBSPIT.images.worldnow.com/interface/js/WNVideo.js?rnd=998125;hostDomain=video.pittsburgh.cbslocal.com;playerWidth=615;playerHeight=365;isShowIcon=true;clipId=8844851;flvUri=;partnerclipid=;adTag=Sport;advertisingZone=CBS.PITTS%252Fworldnowplayer;enableAds=true;landingPage=;islandingPageoverride=false;playerType=STANDARD_EMBEDDEDscript;controlsType=fixed&#39;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://video.pittsburgh.cbslocal.com&#34; title=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-tent-and-the-pittsburgh-campus-challenge&#34;&gt;The tent and the Pittsburgh Campus Challenge&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I signed up for the Pittsburgh Campus Challenge through Carnegie Mellon University, there was advertised to be &amp;ldquo;gourmet food, private massages, and more&amp;rdquo; in the tent. The reality was actually quite different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby said it was a good thing she made it to the tent before too late (she had gone back to nap in the car after seeing me off), because by 10 AM, half marathoners had eaten much of the food already, and she had remembered to save some for me for later! There was still food left, but much of the good stuff was gone. And it wasn&amp;rsquo;t really &amp;ldquo;gourmet&amp;rdquo;. There was dry fried chicken, rolls, pasta left, as far as I could tell, other than the pancakes Abby had saved from earlier, and  a Panera Bread sandwiches she also saved for me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/abby.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/tent-food.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Tent food&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There was a signup sheet for massage by Massage Envy, however, and a very long wait, as I got my massage after one hour and twenty minutes, which was actually OK because I was so sore I simply needed to be left alone for a while to just eat and eat and rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;cmu-won&#34;&gt;CMU won!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I came into the tent, there was confusion because I didn&amp;rsquo;t have a sticker on my bib indicating that I had access to the tent. Apparently I was supposed to have gotten a sticker at some point, but I don&amp;rsquo;t remember getting instructions about that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When they learned I was with CMU, however, they gave me the prize for CMU winning the Pittsburgh Campus Challenge, to hand over to Pattye at CMU. We beat Pitt!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/pittsburgh-campus-challenge.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Pittsburgh Campus Challenge prize&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;feet&#34;&gt;Feet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My feet were terribly sore. I got one blood-filled blister:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/blister.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Blister on right foot&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But otherwise, the damage was not as bad as I had thought. During the marathon, I had wondered sometimes about all the stickiness I felt on my feet, but it was not blood after all; it was a mixture of energy gel, Gatorade, orange juice, and whatever else was left on the road that got onto my feet:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/feet.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I had two chafing spots from the straps, but they were not serious. All in all, my feet were in much condition after wearing the Luna Sandals than they were ten years ago after wearing standard socks and running shoes. The drawback is that my feet were horribly sore, although after one night of rest, the foot soreness is actually all gone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;one-day-later&#34;&gt;One day later&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I do have a different problem: one day later, numbness in my left foot remains, because I had adjusted my strap for my left foot too tightly, out of fear of it coming off. &lt;em&gt;Overly tight strap was a big mistake.&lt;/em&gt; I did make an adjustment at some point during the race, but I could at least have loosened the strap earlier when I felt discomfort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In all my previous runs, my left foot has never fallen out. I hope the numbness goes away in another day.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/feet-day-after.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;My feet the day after&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;legs&#34;&gt;Legs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My legs were utterly trashed, as might be expected given how I had tortured them for so long. At first, I thought it was just my quads and hamstrings, but once I pulled off the calf sleeves, I realized that my calves were trashed too, but had &lt;em&gt;completely&lt;/em&gt; avoided cramping because of the compression. I count this as a total success for the calf sleeves, because in the marathon ten years ago, my calves were seizing up in the second half, not just my quads. &lt;em&gt;I will always wear calf sleeves in the future in long runs or hikes&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Em of Massage Envy was very helpful in getting me able to sort of walk, so that I could go with Abby back over to the North Shore to our car (I had to walk across the bridge, then waited as she brought the car over).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/massage-envy.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Massage Envy&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Overall, I think wearing the Luna Sandals was the correct decision, despite the drawbacks. I did &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; have toe jamming, toe blistering, toe cramping that I believe I would have had in other footwear. I did not have ankle soreness of any kind. Or shin splints. I did not have any right knee pain at all, just left (and almost certainly because of my fall on Thursday). I could have used more cushioning though. But my order of the thicker Luna Sandals (the new Mono model) has not yet shipped.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;thanks&#34;&gt;Thanks!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a lot to be thankful for even though in some sense this marathon was truly a debacle for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am thankful that this race returned to Pittsburgh after suspension in 2004-2008, as Dick&amp;rsquo;s Sporting Goods rose up to be the title sponsor. I am amazed by how large and popular the Pittsburgh Marathon has become since I last ran it ten years ago. I think it&amp;rsquo;s great that the city has this annual celebration of its neighborhoods and of the running community. The Pittsburgh Marathon is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; just about the marathon, but about just regular fitness running, free workshops on health and exercise, and celebrating a sport that brings everyone together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am thankful to Pattye Stragar for spreading word of the Pittsburgh Campus Challenge through the CMU fitness mailing list.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am thankful to Steel City Road Runners for their well-organized Saturday long runs that got me out during the cold months when I otherwise might have chosen to just sleep in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am thankful to my friends who encouraged me as I progressed through my training and in my discouraging days before the marathon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am thankful to Annie and Deb and Mark for being spectators I saw and knew who gave me additional motivation to keep going.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am thankful to all the spectators and volunteers I don&amp;rsquo;t know who offered cheers, water, orange slices, music, and everything else that reminded me that humanity is caring and helpful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And of course, I am particularly thankful to my wife Abby, who has been so patient these months as I have pursued this marathon thing that she thinks is crazy (OK, I know it is crazy), and helped me every single day. Abby, this whole experience has truly deepened my appreciation of you, and I will never forget what we went through together to make this birthday present happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;did-i-achieve-my-goals&#34;&gt;Did I achieve my goals?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s go back to &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/30/why-and-how-i-am-going-to-run-the-2013-pittsburgh-marathon/&#34;&gt;my blog post from three months ago where I stated my goals for the marathon&lt;/a&gt;. What did I actually achieve?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;maintain a smart pace: failed (totally)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;finish strong: succeeded (insofar as I pushed as hard as I could for the last three miles approximately)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;avoid leg muscle cramping: failed miserably with the quads, succeeded with the calves&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;avoid foot blistering: failed (got one bad blister)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;conquer the hills: neutral (didn&amp;rsquo;t feel particularly bad at hills as such)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it would seem that I basically failed, as far as the marathon itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I think I succeeded, in a larger context:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t expect to be wearing huaraches for a marathon, but I did wear Luna Sandals! I proved to myself it could be done.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As a side effect of marathon training, I got myself into much better shape than I have been in for the past half decade, and did my first half marathon in nine years, and set up exercise habits I hope to make permanent independent of any future marathoning.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Abby&amp;rsquo;s help as I took on the task of training made a profound impression on me.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The outpouring of support from friends was a welcome surprise to me, because in my last Pittsburgh Marathon, I mostly went about it alone, telling only a few people about it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-did-i-fail-so-miserably&#34;&gt;Why did I fail so miserably?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe I failed mostly because I didn&amp;rsquo;t have the proper training. I started too late, I didn&amp;rsquo;t have enough time to more gradually absorb increased training volume, I could have used an extra month or two of more long runs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also did not adapt properly to setbacks that should have led me to change my goals drastically. There was a downward spiral in terms of injury, fatigue, and loss of calm reason.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-next&#34;&gt;What next?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;done-with-the-marathon&#34;&gt;Done with the marathon&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I told Abby that this is it: no more racing marathons again, ever. I mean it. I&amp;rsquo;m facing the reality that this is not the right event for me. I believe I could do a good marathon, but what it would take is not worth the effort. The sacrifices that I made, and Abby made, were considerable. There are other things we could be doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I look forward to our returning to &amp;ldquo;normal&amp;rdquo; life as I recover.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;running&#34;&gt;Running&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, I totally enjoyed getting back into year-round running. I will never go into winter hibernation again. I still have to figure out ideal footwear for the coldest and snow/ice/water-ridden conditions for next winter, of course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;half-marathons&#34;&gt;Half marathons&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Doing Just A Short Run again gave me confidence that I can &amp;ldquo;master&amp;rdquo; the half marathon distance. I would like to continue doing half marathons. I have decided to do the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mtchalfmarathon.com/&#34;&gt;Montour Trail Half Marathon&lt;/a&gt; in September. This means I will have to skip the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~kalp/PGR/&#34;&gt;CMU Pretty Good Race&lt;/a&gt;, which is always held the Friday before this Saturday race, but it&amp;rsquo;s time for me to get back into doing half marathon and 10K and 5K (and even mile) races, distances that I can actually work on being able to run well without wrecking myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heck, I might even run the Pittsburgh Half Marathon a year from now! (Although I don&amp;rsquo;t actually want to think about that for a while.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In isolation, the 2013 Pittsburgh Marathon may be considered to be a total debacle for me, the worst race I&amp;rsquo;ve finished out of the 135 races I&amp;rsquo;ve showed up for in my life. But I&amp;rsquo;m glad I went through the process of training for it, and I&amp;rsquo;m grateful for it as a vehicle of self-discovery: I faced some unpleasant truths about various poor decisions I made. And I&amp;rsquo;m grateful for the opportunity to share my journey with friends and family.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.guardian.co.uk/sport/blog/2012/jun/22/50-olympic-stunning-moments-emil-zatopek&#34;&gt;Emil Zatopek&lt;/a&gt; said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
If you want to run, run a mile. If you want to experience a different life, run a marathon.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-05-09&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-05-09)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second day after the marathon, I was still in physical and emotional pain, and wrote a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/05/07/why-i-feel-sad-when-people-congratulate-me-for-finishing-the-pittsburgh-marathon/&#34;&gt;little rant expressing my disappointment&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third day, I was able to walk normally and was emotionally recovering as well and was embarrassed by my rant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fourth day, I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/05/09/back-to-what-running-is-really-about-for-me/&#34;&gt;went out for a short run and reflected on what running is really about for me&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-12-22&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-12-22)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I just wanted to point out a much healthier attitude and experience of a marathon gone badly: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.letsrun.com/news/2013/11/time-life/&#34;&gt;this is a really beautiful article&lt;/a&gt; that every disappointed racer should read.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recognize that I trapped myself during March and April with increasingly unbalanced expectations of my marathon, and lost all calmness and perspective. I still don&amp;rsquo;t know whether I will run a marathon again, but if I do, I vow to do it with a clear mind and body.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Back from injury: an unexpected fast finish Steel City Road Runners training run</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/04/25/back-from-injury-an-unexpected-fast-finish-steel-city-road-runners-training-run/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Apr 2013 21:55:57 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/04/25/back-from-injury-an-unexpected-fast-finish-steel-city-road-runners-training-run/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/04/20/on-overtraining-and-feeling-injured-two-weeks-before-the-pittsburgh-marathon/&#34;&gt;Five days ago, I reported on feeling overtrained and injured.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, I report on my progress with recovery and continued training for the Pittsburgh Marathon during the first week of my taper period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;recovery&#34;&gt;Recovery&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The good news is that I&amp;rsquo;m bouncing back. I still have a way to go before I feel completely healthy and strong, but I&amp;rsquo;m not doing too badly, considering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;knee&#34;&gt;Knee&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier this week, I did take Sunday off from running (and from wearing Luna Sandals). My left knee was still shaky on Monday, plus I simply felt tired, so I took Monday off as well. Tuesday, my knee was feeling better, so I did an easy 3.5 mile run and called it a day. That really improved my mood, because I was really upset about whether I could run the marathon at all. Wednesday, my knee seemed completely OK, so I ran an easy 4.5 miles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;feet&#34;&gt;Feet&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My left foot skin injuries are healing; two days ago there was still some rawness:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/left-foot-healing.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Left foot healing&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But today, everything is completely scabbed over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My right foot is still problematic with a crack in the dry skin at the big toe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still, I have been back to wearing Luna Sandals since two days ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;new-shorts&#34;&gt;New shorts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All my runs this week have been in a new pair of running shorts that I will probably use for the marathon. I bought this at Elite Runners and Walkers a month ago when picking up my race packet for the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/30/report-on-just-a-short-run-my-first-half-marathon-in-nine-years/&#34;&gt;Just A Short Run half marathon&lt;/a&gt; there, but hadn&amp;rsquo;t gotten around to wearing them yet!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am liking this &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.brooksrunning.com/Infiniti-Short-III/210277,default,pd.html&#34;&gt;Brooks Infiniti Short III&lt;/a&gt; a lot. It seems extremely well-designed. I have not sensed chafing problems, and the pockets for a key and gel seem sturdy. Believe me, I have had all kinds of problems with many running shorts in the past decade, mostly involving chafing, deterioration of materials, and pockets becoming non-functional because of how they are sewn, so I can spot design and quality problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-run&#34;&gt;The run&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, I wanted to do a marathon pace (9-minute pace) run of no more than 6 miles. It turned out that Steel City Road Runners along with &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.truerunner.com/&#34;&gt;True Runner&lt;/a&gt; had organized a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.steelcityrrc.org/events?eventId=675354&amp;amp;EventViewMode=EventDetails&#34;&gt;Thursday evening 6-mile training run&lt;/a&gt;. I almost never run in the evening, but just this once, I decided to check it out, and John joined me also, for our first run together since the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/09/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings-in-one-12-mile-run/&#34;&gt;12-miler that put him out of commission almost two months ago and led him to cancel his Pittsburgh Marathon registration&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was pretty cold, relatively speaking. The temperature was around 50 and getting colder, windier, and it was cloudy and it looked like it might rain (it turned out that near the end of the run, it did drizzle a bit).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;pace&#34;&gt;Pace&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We followed a guy who was supposed to lead a roughly 9-minute pace for 6 miles, doing two 3-mile loops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My impression was that we shot out noticeably faster, and I fell off the pack and just tried to stay in contact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;a-note-on-dense-urban-evening-running&#34;&gt;A note on dense urban evening running&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Running in the Shadyside area at this time of day is stressful, it turns out, because of all the road traffic, the narrow sidewalks, and stop lights. We had to stop more often than I prefer:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/shadyside-run-stopped.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Waiting for light in Shadyside run&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Well, this was a learning experience, reminding me of why I prefer to run in the morning, and in less congested areas such as Beechwood Boulevard or Homewood Cemetery in Squirrel Hill, or Frick or Schenley Park!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;first-loop&#34;&gt;First loop&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite going slower than everyone else in the supposedly 9-minute pace group, I was feeling pretty good, probably finally completely recovered from last week&amp;rsquo;s overtraining. My stride rate was fast and I felt relatively relaxed and efficient, except that I knew we were going faster than I feel I will be able to sustain in the marathon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I saw a guy in front of me wearing calf sleeves. I had forgotten to wear mine. I should wear them more before the marathon in order to make sure to be completely used to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We finished the first loop in around 26:18. Um, that&amp;rsquo;s 8:47 pace. I was right, we were going faster than 9:00 pace. I had in fact wondered why our pacer had slowed down some blocks before we got back to True Runner, and meanwhile most of the rest of us just followed whoever was in front of the pack!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;second-loop&#34;&gt;Second loop&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some people stopped to drink Gatorade or water, but I didn&amp;rsquo;t take any. Then we headed off again. This time, the pace was slower, possibly even a bit slower than 9:00 pace. That was fine with me. But after about a mile, we started going faster and faster. I almost had to laugh. We were going considerably faster than in the first loop even.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pacer eventually fell back and &lt;em&gt;we all just passed him&lt;/em&gt;. Later I reflected on this bizarre group mentality we engaged in. We must have simply ended up following whoever wanted to go fastest. I decided I might as well treat this run as a super fast finish run rather than the steady run I had originally intended. We were clearly going at 8:30 pace and then even faster, down to 8:00 pace and even possibly 7:45 by the end. It was crazy. I felt like I was running in a race. For some reason, everyone decided to push it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We finished the second loop in something like 24:59 (we&amp;rsquo;d done the first loop in 26:18).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That I was able to maintain alert turnover and also speed things up as I felt like it gave me some confidence that I am bouncing back OK from the past two really hard weeks of training. I have one more week of tapering to go before the marathon!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On overtraining and feeling injured two weeks before the Pittsburgh Marathon</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/04/20/on-overtraining-and-feeling-injured-two-weeks-before-the-pittsburgh-marathon/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Apr 2013 22:25:40 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/04/20/on-overtraining-and-feeling-injured-two-weeks-before-the-pittsburgh-marathon/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/04/13/my-final-16-mile-long-run-before-pittsburgh-marathon-featured-two-radical-experiments/&#34;&gt;Last week&amp;rsquo;s 16-mile run with the Steel City Road Runners&lt;/a&gt; was my longest run during the past two months of training for the Pittsburgh Marathon. I knew that it was about time to start &lt;a href=&#34;http://running.competitor.com/2012/08/training/the-art-of-the-marathon-taper_57754&#34;&gt;tapering&lt;/a&gt;, but I felt that because of my relatively low mileage (mostly under 30 miles a week), I should put in one last hard week of training, and then have two weeks of tapering before the marathon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, this week I overdid things and &lt;a href=&#34;http://steelcityrrc.org/scrrcevents?eventId=619965&#34;&gt;today&amp;rsquo;s 11-mile run&lt;/a&gt; was very revealing. I ended that run with a whole slew of real problems that I need to immediately fix, or else I will not be able to even make it to the start line of the marathon in two weeks!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;this-week-s-workouts&#34;&gt;This week&amp;rsquo;s workouts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;monday&#34;&gt;Monday&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/04/19/commuting-on-foot-during-cmu-carnival-week-as-cross-training-for-the-pittsburgh-marathon/&#34;&gt;walking 2 miles to work&lt;/a&gt;, I did a tough &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/02/03/my-favorite-running-workout/&#34;&gt;high-intensity Billat workout&lt;/a&gt; on the CMU track, thinking that having taken Sunday off from running, I was ready to get back into action. After doing about 12 minutes of this workout (after warming up first, of course), I was beat. I was feeling pressure on my knees and shins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically, I was not sufficiently recovered from my 16-miler on Saturday, and I made a mistake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, I walked 2 miles back home from work, with sore legs and feet, and still wearing Luna Sandals all day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;tuesday&#34;&gt;Tuesday&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did an easy 6-mile run, which included 1 mile of running to work, 4 miles of running in Schenley Park on the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/07/running-my-8th-pretty-good-race-5k-dealing-with-disappointment/&#34;&gt;Pretty Good Race course&lt;/a&gt;, and 1 mile on the CMU track. Despite taking this run slowly, I felt rather sore afterwards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;wednesday&#34;&gt;Wednesday&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided to take a day completely off from running, and off from Luna Sandals, to give my legs and feet a rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;thursday&#34;&gt;Thursday&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ran 5 miles in Frick Park.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;friday&#34;&gt;Friday&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did the annual &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/04/19/going-out-too-fast-yet-again-in-my-third-random-distance-run/&#34;&gt;Random Distance Run&lt;/a&gt;. By this time, I was quite looking forward to getting Saturday&amp;rsquo;s run over with and then resting on Sunday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;11-mile-run&#34;&gt;11-mile run&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided to make the Saturday run a kind of dress rehearsal for the marathon. I would wake up at approximately the same time, and dress and eat as though running the marathon, and run at marathon pace, and the only difference would be that I would do 11 miles, not 26.2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I ate some salted, boiled potatoes for breakfast, and took a gel pack to eat right before the run, and planned to take a gel during the run also.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was really cold yet again (temperature below 40F, and I saw some stray snowflakes), even colder than last week, so I substituted a short-sleeve T-shirt and shell and long pants in place of the long-sleeve T-shirt and shorts I wore last Saturday. I still had the glove liners and hat, of course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wore, for the first time, my &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cepcompression.com/1922-Allsports-Sleeves.aspx&#34;&gt;calf sleeves&lt;/a&gt; that had just arrived, and that I plan to wear during the marathon:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/scrr-2013-04-20/cep-compression-calf-sleeves.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;CEP Compression calf sleeves&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;moment-of-silence-for-boston&#34;&gt;Moment of silence for Boston&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The whole week has been very weird for me because the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/04/15/boston-marathon-tragedy-please-avoid-the-news-porn/&#34;&gt;Boston Marathon bombing on Monday has been on my mind&lt;/a&gt;; I did what I could to avoid media coverage of the hunt for the bombers. It turned out that just last night, they caught the remaining official suspect, so that brought a little closure to the whole thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The training run was preceded by a moment of silence for Boston as well as updates on changes to the Pittsburgh Marathon setup for increased security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this run, I wore blue as well as a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.races2remember.com/PrintBib.php?bib=BOSTON2013&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;We are all Boston Marathoners at heart&amp;rdquo; bib&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/scrr-2013-04-20/boston-marathoners-at-heart.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;We are all Boston Marathoners at heart&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-run&#34;&gt;The run&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/scrr-2013-04-20/start.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Waiting to start run&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I intended to try to follow a 9-minute pace group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that the group went out pretty fast. I could not tell whether it felt fast because it really &lt;em&gt;was&lt;/em&gt; faster than 9-minute pace, or because I was so fatigued from my week of training.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point, I did speed up (as I usually seem to do in my runs, starting out slowly before I&amp;rsquo;m all warmed up and ready to go faster). Then the problem was that I didn&amp;rsquo;t know what the route was exactly, once I started passing people! Yes, I got the printed map right before the run, but that&amp;rsquo;s never a great time for me to study and memorize the map, and I hate pulling out the map while running.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;getting-lost&#34;&gt;Getting &amp;ldquo;lost&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At one point when we reached downtown again in Pittsburgh, and we were supposed to eventually cross over north, I asked some runners around me what the route was, and unfortunately, one guy made some assumption and we followed him. Later I learned he made the wrong assumption. In fact, since I ran past him and was following some other people ahead of me, I got myself into more trouble. At one point, I saw someone behind me go right, while the guy ahead of me by a block kept going straight. I immediately smelled that the guy was &lt;em&gt;not part of our group&lt;/em&gt; (lots of people were out running, I could tell), and sure enough, I looked back and everyone was taking a shortcut through someone&amp;rsquo;s back yard to get back to Liberty Avenue and cross the 16th Street Bridge, and so I backtracked and followed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By that time, I was tired and demoralized by all the weird twists and turns the route had become after having reached downtown earlier, and now that I knew where I was, I just slowed down and didn&amp;rsquo;t bother to catch up to any pack again, and took some photos:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/scrr-2013-04-20/bridge.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;View from Sixteenth Street Bridge&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/scrr-2013-04-20/16th-street-bridge.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Crossing Sixteenth Street Bridge&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t really know how far I ran or how fast. It just seemed really intense to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;after-the-run&#34;&gt;After the run&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/scrr-2013-04-20/after.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;After run&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;After the run, I ate two bananas and some cookies and went inside to stretch and inspect the damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;feet&#34;&gt;Feet&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My Luna Sandals:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/scrr-2013-04-20/luna-venado.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Luna Venado&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h4 id=&#34;tops-of-feet&#34;&gt;Tops of feet&lt;/h4&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/scrr-2013-04-20/feet.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Feet&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My right foot felt OK, despite some indentations from tight laces:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/scrr-2013-04-20/right.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Right foot&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But my left foot took a lot of damage, with skin scraped and some blood; the problem was that the strap had been loose, but I had neglected to stop and tighten and readjust it, and as a result, it shifted around and therefore chafed me:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/scrr-2013-04-20/left.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Left foot&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It was good to learn this lesson once and for all: I will be more careful in the future to make sure the laces are tight enough, and also not ignore sensations of chafing, and take the time to stop and readjust if I really have to. I could not have run a full marathon with my left foot being chafed in this fashion for the whole distance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;soles-of-feet&#34;&gt;Soles of feet&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My soles revealed some developing problems from the entire week.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/scrr-2013-04-20/soles.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Soles of feet&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My left sole was basically OK, despite some dry skin that I should really deal with, but my right sole had more serious dry and cracking skin problems. In particular, near my big toe, there was a noticeable crack that caused me discomfort with every step:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/scrr-2013-04-20/right-sole.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Right sole of foot&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;calves&#34;&gt;Calves&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe the calf sleeves did help me, even in just an 11-miler. They were not obtrusive at all as I wore them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;knee&#34;&gt;Knee&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later in the afternoon at home, I noticed that I had developed a debilitating left knee problem. I have no idea what exactly caused it, but the general overtraining had clearly caught up to me. When I put weight on my left leg at certain angles, the pain is excruciating. This particular happens when I go down the stairs. On the other hand, I can control whether I feel pain, by stepping very carefully. Something is loose and out of alignment, clearly. This has happened to me before, so I&amp;rsquo;m not as worried as I could be, but just two weeks away from the marathon, it is not good news.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;recovery-plans&#34;&gt;Recovery plans?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My left knee is my highest priority right now. I am immediately taking a break from running. I will take tomorrow off, and possibly Monday as well. I will do whatever it takes to get the knee all good again, because there is no way I would even go to the start line of the marathon with the knee being as it is today!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really need to fix my feet, and especially the right one. I really dried out my feet by wearing the Luna Sandals exclusively for running (and almost exclusively for walking) in the past week. So I&amp;rsquo;m putting lotion on my feet and deciding to wear socks and cushioned shoes for a while. There&amp;rsquo;s more I&amp;rsquo;m going to have to do for my feet also. I&amp;rsquo;ve never in my life had this dry skin problem before on my feet, because in the past when it&amp;rsquo;s been cold and dry, I&amp;rsquo;ve always worn socks and closed toe shoes, whether of the usual monotoed variety or Vibram FiveFingers. I&amp;rsquo;ve never had my feet so exposed before. Especially, running in temperatures of the 30s with huaraches seemed to cause some of my problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, the next two weeks really are supposed to be tapering for me. I will be running easy and short and slow for the most part, just to maintain some fitness, but do not plan on doing any super hard workouts any more. We all know that the body takes about two weeks to adapt to any training, and so no hard training I do now will have an effect on my performance in the marathon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I yet again pushed myself to the edge and overtrained, and have some real knee and feet problems to solve as quickly as possible. I am so ready to dial down the training and get the marathon over with. I don&amp;rsquo;t want to sound pessimistic or depressed, but that&amp;rsquo;s the reality of how I&amp;rsquo;m feeling at this moment. I hope that within the next couple of days, I&amp;rsquo;ll have recovered from this low point.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Boston Marathon tragedy: please avoid the news porn</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/04/15/boston-marathon-tragedy-please-avoid-the-news-porn/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Apr 2013 19:49:22 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/04/15/boston-marathon-tragedy-please-avoid-the-news-porn/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Since I am a runner (and happening to be in the last stages of training for my second Pittsburgh Marathon, which is coming in less than three weeks), I woke up this morning knowing that it was Boston Marathon day. Also, by sheer coincidence, a fellow Pittsburgher I have never met but follow on Twitter happened to tweet a photo of his running gear while ready to run in Boston, and happened to mention some sock sleeves that he wears that I had never seen before, and I tweeted him for the first time in my life, and I got a reply from him after he finished, and I went and ordered a pair of these &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cepcompression.com/1922-Allsports-Sleeves.aspx&#34;&gt;sock sleeves online&lt;/a&gt;, since I have a tendency toward calf cramping in long distance races.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it was particularly eerie and somewhat personal to me when in the afternoon I heard from my office mate at work that the Boston Marathon had been bombed and people were dead and horribly injured.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first thought was, &lt;strong&gt;this is fucking insane&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My second thought was extreme anger that criminals would do such a thing, and sadness for the runners and spectators who were so victimized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My third thought was, &amp;ldquo;Uh oh, here we go again: time for news porn&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;9-11-and-news&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;9&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;11&lt;/sub&gt; and news&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because I remember &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/September_11_attacks&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;9&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;11&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some excerpts from my journal on September 11, 2001 (at this time in my life I was jotting down journal entries regularly during the waking day):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;11:12: &amp;ldquo;Oh G-d!!!!!!!!!!!  The World Trade Center has been destroyed.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;11:36: &amp;ldquo;Things will never be the same again in this country.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;12:11: &amp;ldquo;Can&amp;rsquo;t let terrorists disrupt my life.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;18:28: &amp;ldquo;Wait, are we attacking Afghanistan??????&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;22:14: &amp;ldquo;Watched some TV footage for the first time.  Disturbing.  Especially people jumping out of the buildings.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;23:31: &amp;ldquo;Other people on &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zephyr_%28protocol%29&#34;&gt;zephyr&lt;/a&gt; [an internal chat system at Carnegie Mellon University] are saying they watched more TV today than all year.  Same with me.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, during this whole time, I did immediately try to call my sister who lived and worked in New York City, and of course failed. She reached me eventually and said she was OK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I realized something that day. I realized that I could not let relentless news porn rule my life. There was no benefit to my seeing again and again footage about the tragic terrorist attacks and all the speculations, the anger, the crying. I did not quit watching TV that evening, but did realize that I was being manipulated in a way that did not help me or help the world, really.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much later, I learned that a high school classmate of mine had died on &lt;sup&gt;9&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;11&lt;/sub&gt;. And a college classmate was across the street when it happened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;news&#34;&gt;News&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point, years later, I did completely quit following news. By this, I mean that I stopped watching news on TV, I stopped reading printed newspapers, and I stopped reading online news sites as well. Seriously. It has improved my life. Periodically I try to spread the message of news avoidance, having seen the damage that following news has done to some family members and friends, without noticeable benefit in return.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, just yesterday on Twitter I retweeted &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.guardian.co.uk/media/2013/apr/12/news-is-bad-rolf-dobelli&#34;&gt;yet another article on news avoidance&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you haven&amp;rsquo;t done the experiment of avoiding news, your first thought might be, &amp;ldquo;Franklin must be an ignoramus who doesn&amp;rsquo;t care about the world or know what goes on in it&amp;rdquo;. But actually, I am not completely ignorant of news: I simply have some filters. I do actively follow blogs, Twitter, Facebook, and Google+, and so I implicitly get a curated summary of whatever news is forwarded around through those channels. I see links and check the headlines, and I can choose to ignore or follow up on the news. And I selectively retweet what I find interesting and &lt;em&gt;useful&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, the social media has for the past couple of hours become overwhelmingly dominated by a lot of emotions over the Boston Marathon terrorist attack, so as I write this, I am imposing a complete blackout on blogs, Twitter, Facebook, and Google+.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;local&#34;&gt;Local&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The local and federal authorities are, I presume, doing what they can to aid the victims and seek out the criminals, and following their every move would not help me be useful. If this tragedy had happened in Pittsburgh, then I would be monitoring the situation much more closely, in case I can actually be of direct aid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;couldn-t-avoid-tv-today&#34;&gt;Couldn&amp;rsquo;t avoid TV today&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, by coincidence, I could not avoid TV today. This evening, I was in the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/10/26/yet-another-haircut-from-joe-always-worth-the-wait/&#34;&gt;barber shop&lt;/a&gt; getting a haircut, and not only could people not refrain from commenting on the tragedy, but he also had the radio on and turned on his TV as well. I refused to look at the TV screen, but could not help repeatedly hearing about body parts being blown off, eardrums being perforated, panic, the audio clips of explosions and screaming, again and again. I remained silent and maintained my composure until my haircut was done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-media-blackout&#34;&gt;A media blackout&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am taking a break from the Web overall for the rest of the evening. Last I checked my social media feeds, they are now all about the Boston Marathon attacks. I cannot help anyone by sitting in front of my computer getting all emotional and confused following all these feeds. I humbly recommend that you consider doing this also.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have not found news porn to be useful in helping me cope with tragedy or in enabling me be of aid to those who need help. Given that, I am opting out of the news frenzy.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>