<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Language on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/language/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Language on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/language/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Why I will always pronounce &#34;GIF&#34; like &#34;gift&#34; and not like &#34;Jif&#34;</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/05/24/why-i-will-always-pronounce-gif-like-gift-and-not-like-jif/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 May 2013 21:40:22 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/05/24/why-i-will-always-pronounce-gif-like-gift-and-not-like-jif/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently Steve Wilhite, the creator of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Graphics_Interchange_Format&#34;&gt;GIF (Graphics Interchange Format)&lt;/a&gt;, tried to settle once and for all the age-old (well, 26-year-old, since the invention of GIF in 1987) question of how to pronounce &amp;ldquo;GIF&amp;rdquo;, claiming that it is &lt;a href=&#34;http://howtopronouncegif.com/&#34;&gt;pronounced as &amp;ldquo;jif&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&#34;The Oxford English Dictionary accepts both pronunciations,&#34; Mr. Wilhite said. &#34;They are wrong. It is a soft ‘G,’ pronounced ‘jif.’ End of story.&#34; 
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, whole &amp;ldquo;debate&amp;rdquo; is kind of silly, because it doesn&amp;rsquo;t really matter how it&amp;rsquo;s pronounced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Or does it?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-first-memories-of-gif&#34;&gt;My first memories of GIF&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was in college in the late 1980s when a friend of mine first introduced me to the world of GIF files. Since he pronounced &amp;ldquo;GIF&amp;rdquo; like &amp;ldquo;gift&amp;rdquo;, I followed suit. Other friends also pronounced it that way, and I simply assumed that was &amp;ldquo;correct&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;mispronunciation&#34;&gt;Mispronunciation?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was in the early 1990s when at my first job, I noticed that a colleague of mine pronounced &amp;ldquo;GIF&amp;rdquo; like &amp;ldquo;Jif&amp;rdquo; instead. I was stunned, of course. Meanwhile, at this very time, there was an uproar over the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Graphics_Interchange_Format#Unisys_and_LZW_patent_enforcement&#34;&gt;patent enforcement by Unisys on the LZW compression algorithm used by GIF&lt;/a&gt;. I was outraged by the development myself, and chose to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.gnu.org/philosophy/gif.html&#34;&gt;minimize use of the GIF format&lt;/a&gt;; I used JPEG and the new PNG formats instead for any new image file creation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was around this time that I learned that the official pronunciation of &amp;ldquo;GIF&amp;rdquo; was supposed to be &amp;ldquo;jif&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;But I didn&amp;rsquo;t care.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I knew that there were people pronouncing it either way, and I was already used to one way, and nobody was enforcing the &amp;ldquo;correct&amp;rdquo; way, and I was rarely even saying the word any more, since I was not using the file format for personal or work purposes. In the past two decades, I don&amp;rsquo;t believe I&amp;rsquo;ve said the word more than a dozen times, but each time, I stubbornly used the &amp;ldquo;gift&amp;rdquo; pronunciation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;ownership&#34;&gt;Ownership?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If everyone were saying &amp;ldquo;jif&amp;rdquo; all the time, I would have changed my pronunciation. This is how language works. The point of language is to communicate with others, and if nobody knew what I was saying because I was pronouncing a word wrong, then I would have to change my pronunciation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;It means little to me what the inventor of the word intended&lt;/em&gt;, because language serves everyone who uses it meaningfully, not just the inventor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When you create something, you don&amp;rsquo;t own it any more. It belongs to the world.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is considered by some to be a controversial point of view, but I think it is philosophically correct &lt;em&gt;as a starting point&lt;/em&gt; of discussion. Yes, sophisticated systems of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Property_rights_%28economics%29&#34;&gt;property rights&lt;/a&gt; have been created and do serve a useful purpose, but always &lt;em&gt;in context of&lt;/em&gt; the fundamental outlook, and as a constraint in the name of greater benefit to society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The continuing debates over American copyright and patent laws, for example, illustrate that these laws are not set in stone but are a result of discussions and compromises among different interests and philosophies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is ironic, of course, that more people seem to care about the pronunciation of &amp;ldquo;GIF&amp;rdquo; than about the old patent controversy surrounding the format. Then again, as a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.law.cornell.edu/wex/patent&#34;&gt;limited monopoly&lt;/a&gt;, the patent on LZW did expire in the US in 2003 (and elsewhere in 2004).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;ownership-of-language&#34;&gt;Ownership of language?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are reading this and are French, I&amp;rsquo;m curious what your view is of ownership of language, because the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Acad%C3%A9mie_fran%C3%A7aise&#34;&gt;Académie française&lt;/a&gt; has officially controlled the French language since 1635, and there is no analogous institution in the US.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;authorial-intent&#34;&gt;Authorial intent?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The debate over &amp;ldquo;GIF&amp;rdquo; may seem trivial, but I think it is a good starting point for those who are interested in issues of ownership and &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Authorial_intent&#34;&gt;authorial intent&lt;/a&gt;, as applied to many more important issues, such as &amp;ldquo;correct&amp;rdquo; interpretation or use of literature, of music, of law. I have been particularly interested in this debate in the context of music, and my attitude comes from grappling with &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/10/rip-charles-rosen/&#34;&gt;Charles Rosen&amp;rsquo;s writings&lt;/a&gt; over the years; as you can imagine, debate over &amp;ldquo;composer&amp;rsquo;s intent&amp;rdquo; can get &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pianostreet.com/smf/index.php?topic=2657.0&#34;&gt;very heated&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dictionaries of English today accept both pronunciations of &amp;ldquo;GIF&amp;rdquo;. Furthermore, some informal polls I have seen even come up with the result that most people who participate in such polls favor my pronunciation. So I will continue using my pronunciation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But really, &lt;a href=&#34;http://stancarey.wordpress.com/2013/05/24/you-can-pronounce-gif-any-way-you-like/&#34;&gt;it doesn&amp;rsquo;t matter how you pronounce &amp;ldquo;GIF&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. The existence of alternate pronunciations of words is not a threat to language. &amp;ldquo;Either&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;tomato&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;GIF&amp;rdquo;: let&amp;rsquo;s call the whole thing off!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/dskTypuEXoM&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>