<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Improvisation on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/improvisation/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Improvisation on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/improvisation/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>How Ornette Coleman changed my life</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/06/12/how-ornette-coleman-changed-my-life/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jun 2015 23:59:40 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/06/12/how-ornette-coleman-changed-my-life/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The legendary jazz musician
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ornette_Coleman&#34;&gt;Ornette Coleman&lt;/a&gt;
recently died at age 85. He had not been on my radar for a long
time. In fact, I never actually listened to much of his music at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, my immediate first thought on hearing this news was, &lt;strong&gt;Ornette
Coleman permanently changed the course of my life&lt;/strong&gt;. How can this be?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;first-reactions-to-ornette-coleman-s-music&#34;&gt;First reactions to Ornette Coleman&amp;rsquo;s music&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2000, during a huge transition in my life that turned everything
upside down, I began experimenting with listening to a lot of kinds of
music I had never experienced before. I was exploring Cuban,
Brazilian, Argentinian music. I was exploring Western classical music
of the 20th century (I had a fairly narrow taste up till then focused
primarily on the Classical 18th century and Romantic 19th century,
with little before or after this range). In jazz, I was expanding
beyond the swing, bebop, hard bop eras of jazz. I frequently reached
areas that made me confused or disgusted. For example, in jazz I got
&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/23/celebrating-the-birthday-of-john-coltrane/&#34;&gt;as far as I could with John Coltrane&lt;/a&gt;
as Coltrane ventured into &amp;ldquo;free jazz&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided to try out Ornette Coleman for another approach to &amp;ldquo;free
jazz&amp;rdquo;, and checked out the album
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Shape_of_Jazz_to_Come&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Shape of Jazz to Come&amp;rdquo; (1959)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;lonely-woman&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Lonely Woman&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Immediately, I was struck by the track
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lonely_Woman_%28composition%29&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Lonely Woman&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. Conventional
concerns such as being strictly &amp;ldquo;in tune&amp;rdquo; were out the window, in
favor of extremely flexibility of pitch and raw, wailing emotional
expression. It showcased Coleman&amp;rsquo;s lyrical side and was easy to
love. OK, not too weird.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/DNbD1JIH344&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;other-tracks&#34;&gt;Other tracks&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But bam, that was just a warmup. For example, check out
&amp;ldquo;Eventually&amp;rdquo;. It&amp;rsquo;s very free indeed, a lot of notes, an expression of
hyperactive motion, conventional tonality unimportant. Still, not too
harsh, and not totally random.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/WoC69lxnS_Y&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, what I really understood from his music was that he was doing
what came naturally to him. It did not feel forced, it was not to
prove a point. He was enjoying what he was doing. This sense of
&lt;em&gt;freedom&lt;/em&gt; really impressed me. It wasn&amp;rsquo;t reaction, it wasn&amp;rsquo;t
rebellion. I respected that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;free-jazz-a-collective-improvisation&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Free Jazz: A Collective Improvisation&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next album I checked out was
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Free_Jazz:_A_Collective_Improvisation&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Free Jazz: A Collective Improvisation&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was a step beyond, and confusing to me because of the
simultaneous playing that often seemed chaotic. I confess to taking no
huge pleasure in attempting to listen to it all at once (note that
apart from lack of conventional structure, it also keeps going on and
on at length). I found it more enjoyable to listen to only a couple of
random minutes, trying to absorb some stretch of order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, although this was not really my thing, it opened up my mind
to &amp;ldquo;why not?&amp;rdquo; Maybe this particular experiment didn&amp;rsquo;t work, but I
could imagine a simpler setting, say, with fewer instruments, in which
collective improvisation could work out better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check it out yourself:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/xbZIiom9rDA&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;something-else&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Something Else!!!!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I checked out
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Something_Else!!!!&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Something Else!!!!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;,
which actually was his first album and closer to bebop and so forth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t have much to say about it, but it&amp;rsquo;s not too confusing to
enjoy, because of still audible ties to some traditional forms and
styles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;freedom&#34;&gt;Freedom&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, I didn&amp;rsquo;t continue exploring Coleman&amp;rsquo;s music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the sense of &lt;em&gt;freedom&lt;/em&gt;, of &lt;em&gt;permission&lt;/em&gt; to ignore boundaries and
go wherever, musically, really affected me. Was what he was doing
&amp;ldquo;jazz&amp;rdquo;? Listening to him, I made up my mind that I was never again
going to get involved in debates about what jazz &amp;ldquo;really is&amp;rdquo; or what
classical music &amp;ldquo;really is&amp;rdquo; or even what music &amp;ldquo;really is&amp;rdquo;. These
labels stopped being meaningful to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That was what I really learned from him and his life. By coincidence,
I just read this Rolling Stone article,
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rollingstone.com/music/news/vernon-reid-on-ornette-coleman-he-set-a-lot-of-people-free-20150612&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Vernon Reid on Ornette Coleman: &amp;lsquo;He set a lot of people free&amp;rsquo;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;,
that echoes exactly what I felt I learned fifteen years ago from my
brief exposure to him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past year or so, there have been times when, alone and not
likely to bother anyone, I pull out my bass recorder (ha, my lowest
instrument) and just go wild, play some melodic shapes, make up
rhythms, go multiphonic, whatever, for the sheer joy of it. And I&amp;rsquo;m
not embarrassed, because I remember Ornette Coleman and he gave us all
permission to express our unconscious in whatever honest way it comes
out. And he gave us permission to accept and encourage each other to
do that, whether or not we personally like or understand everything
that comes out of tapping the unconscious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hadn&amp;rsquo;t expected to think so much upon hearing of Ornette Coleman&amp;rsquo;s
death. But he set an example that I respected deeply, forever changing
not only my perceptions of music but of what musicians can and should
be allowed to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Are you an Ornette Coleman fan or detractor? Did he change your
  life? If so, how exactly?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Third year at July 3 music party and finally participated in jamming</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/07/03/third-year-at-july-3-music-party-and-finally-participated-in-jamming/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jul 2014 22:11:59 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/07/03/third-year-at-july-3-music-party-and-finally-participated-in-jamming/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;The past two years, Abby and I have gone to an annual July 3 music potluck/party, and we went again this year. Both &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/03/petrified-at-a-music-jam-session-so-i-didnt-play-but-watched-and-listened/&#34;&gt;in 2012&lt;/a&gt; as well as &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/07/03/second-year-at-july-3-music-party-still-only-listening-without-playing/&#34;&gt;in 2013&lt;/a&gt;, I was too intimidated to participate in music jamming, and only watched. This year I was determined to contribute, and I brought my ukulele (which I only started learning &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/08/23/another-unexpected-life-change-one-month-of-learning-to-play-ukulele/&#34;&gt;a month after last year&amp;rsquo;s party&lt;/a&gt;, actually) and my Irish flute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;piano&#34;&gt;Piano&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After my first round of food at the potluck, I went to Susan&amp;rsquo;s piano and played David Raksin&amp;rsquo;s theme from &amp;ldquo;Laura&amp;rdquo;, which I had so botched up last month at the annual Pittsburgh Recorder Society potluck/recital. I play it much better now, although I somehow messed up the final chords today. There were a few people sitting around listening, and they wanted to hear more, but I didn&amp;rsquo;t have any more, so I scurried away to eat more food.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;old-time&#34;&gt;Old time&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As dinner started winding down, the old time musicians started gathering outside to play. I saw fiddles, banjos, and other instruments make an appearance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;blues&#34;&gt;Blues&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inside, the main guy who plays guitar and ukulele unpacked his soprano ukulele, and so I took out my concert ukulele, and two other guys with guitars appeared. Eventually a woman who sang also appeared, as well as a guy on fiddle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I felt very intimidated, because although I&amp;rsquo;ve gotten some experience jamming while on recorder or flute or tin whistle, my ukulele experience &lt;em&gt;without written music&lt;/em&gt; is still very minimal. Nevertheless, I joined in. I fumbled around, and had to ask what key each song was being played in, and even then, I&amp;rsquo;m still quite shaky in anticipating and knowing chord changes beyond the simplest I, IV, V, and some dominant and major 7th chords. I strummed very softly.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/music-2014-07-04/jamming.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Music jamming&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;They&amp;rsquo;re a great bunch, improvising melodic lines at will and even making up lyrics right on the spot, just as they had at the last two years when I only watched. And the singing in harmony was fantastic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby got a little bit of video footage of us at one point:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/zYb1aBioAao&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For two years, I was afraid to join in the music jams at this annual July 3 party. This year I joined in a little bit. If we attend the party again next year, I hope to be in a position to contribute even more! Many thanks to Susan for hosting this annual party!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My first time at an English country dance music jam</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/01/25/my-first-time-at-english-country-dance-music-jam/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Jan 2014 19:39:03 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/01/25/my-first-time-at-english-country-dance-music-jam/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Relatively recently, a new English country dance music jam in the Pittsburgh area has been organized by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amarillismusic.com/aboutus.html&#34;&gt;Maro Avakian&lt;/a&gt;, whom I first met through joining in playing for the Holiday Ball &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/16/playing-recorder-and-flute-at-the-holiday-ball/&#34;&gt;two years ago&lt;/a&gt;. I was unable to make it to the first couple of meetings, but finally, on a nasty snowy Saturday, my schedule happened to be open, so I went.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not completely new to English country dance music. It was almost two years ago when I first encountered it, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/31/my-first-sampling-of-english-country-dance-and-contra-dance/&#34;&gt;as a dancer&lt;/a&gt;. As has happened several times now in my life, becoming familiar with the dance got me interested in the &lt;em&gt;music&lt;/em&gt; and in the idea of actually playing the music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that I&amp;rsquo;d already played some of this kind of music for myself as a result of my study of the Baroque flute, because method books I have for the instrument include a good amount of dance music from the era. In any case, the book we use for many tunes is the volume by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.canispublishing.com/&#34;&gt;Peter Barnes&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://mysite.verizon.net/peterabarnes/books.htm&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Barnes Book of English Country Dance Tunes&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, a fine anthology. Actually, I ordered my copy only last week and was lucky it arrived in the mail just in time!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://mysite.verizon.net/peterabarnes/Book1.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;instruments&#34;&gt;Instruments&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had a pretty good turnout given the weather. Apart from Maro on piano, we had people playing flute, Baroque flute, recorders, ukulele, mandolin, percussion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d brought my flute, Baroque flute, and soprano, alto, tenor recorders, but since there were already two others on modern flute and soprano recorder, I ended up playing just the Baroque flute, alto recorder, and tenor recorder. The Baroque flute is pretty hard to play in some of the keys, and also is kind of soft, so I mostly played the alto and tenor recorders. I gradually gravitated toward improvising inner voices with the tenor recorder. I think I will do that in the future also. In addition, I should bring my bass recorder, to add a yet lower instrument to our group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;improvisation&#34;&gt;Improvisation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had great discussions about tips and tricks for improvising lines and filling out chords. Needless to say, I was botching up a lot of stuff as I experimented, but you can&amp;rsquo;t learn if you don&amp;rsquo;t try!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It looks like I have a new musical outlet, English country dance music. I hope to continue participating in it. As with French traditional dance music, I like the improvisational nature of working with a tune with repetition.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Finally learning about Carnatic music</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/10/finally-learning-about-carnatic-music/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2013 23:04:45 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/10/finally-learning-about-carnatic-music/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://f0.bcbits.com/img/a2399391511_2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Sandeep Narayan&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I attended the Thursday CMU music school convocation that featured a &lt;a href=&#34;http://music.cmu.edu/events/267&#34;&gt;lecture/performance by Sandeep Narayan and his brother Nirmal Narayan&lt;/a&gt;. I very much enjoyed the presentation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://sandeepnarayanmusic.com/&#34;&gt;Sandeep Narayan&lt;/a&gt; is a Carnatic musician. &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carnatic_music&#34;&gt;Carnatic music&lt;/a&gt; is the &amp;ldquo;classical&amp;rdquo; music of Southern India. I&amp;rsquo;d never specifically listened to it before, because I&amp;rsquo;d never had an introduction to it so that I would know what to listen for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sandeep is unusual in that he was born and grew up in the US, in Los Angeles, before eventually settling in Chennai, the center of Carnatic music. I imagine he must have faced quite a bit of curiosity and skepticism as one who walks between two worlds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, his introduction to the elements of Carnatic music, along with brief performance excerpts with his brother (Sandeep sang and Nirmal provided percussion backup), was fantastic! It was a very clear introduction to the elements of pitches, scales/modes, rhythms, and different levels of improvisation. It was particularly helpful that he related the different vocabulary to that of Western &amp;ldquo;classical&amp;rdquo; music and jazz.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wish I had been able to attend the free concert he was giving this evening, but in any case, after receiving this introduction, I feel ready to pursue Carnatic music further as a listener. I always feel intimidated and lost when thinking about how to understand a new kind of music; I&amp;rsquo;m not quite adventurous enough to just jump in with a tiny bit of prior background knowledge. Introductions like his go a long way to providing just enough that it is possible to start enjoying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing Sandeep emphasized is how the music is fundamentally based on &lt;em&gt;improvisation&lt;/em&gt;. He joked that his instrumentalist accompanists have to know more about music than he does, because they all have to follow wherever he goes. They have no idea what he is going to do with the musical material, till he is actually doing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is his &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/user/SRNChannel&#34;&gt;YouTube channel&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An erhu player and a tuba player at a party said &#34;Let&#39;s jam&#34;</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/09/28/an-erhu-player-and-a-tuba-player-at-a-party-said-lets-jam/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Sep 2013 22:02:19 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/09/28/an-erhu-player-and-a-tuba-player-at-a-party-said-lets-jam/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I attended a music potluck party tonight. We had been unsure about whether to attend, since I do have the Great Race 10K to run tomorrow and need to avoid staying up too late. So we went with the understanding that we would leave early as needed, in order for me to wind down at home and go to bed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;food&#34;&gt;Food&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I whipped up a large batch of roasted vegetables to bring to the potluck:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/vegetables-2013-09-28.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Roasted vegetables&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;music&#34;&gt;Music&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a lot of eating and chatting, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.appalasia.com/Mimi.htm&#34;&gt;Mimi&lt;/a&gt; was ready to start jamming, and got out her &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Erhu&#34;&gt;erhu&lt;/a&gt;. A guy who had brought a tuba was ready to play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OK, who else was in?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I pulled out my flute. Abby took out her mandolin. It seemed like nobody else (yet) was interested in joining in. (But as we know, the party usually really gets going later in the evening when musicians are involved.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tuba player seemed really into jazz. He asked for requests and started his own rhythmic bass sometimes. I tried to join in with him and Mimi as they led the way. It was pretty hard for me, and frightening, but I did what I could to contribute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At one point, I volunteered to sing and play &amp;ldquo;Has Anybody Seen My Gal?&amp;rdquo; on ukulele, which I did (for the first time by myself outside home), and they followed along. I don&amp;rsquo;t know if that was the first time an erhu, tuba, and ukulele were in action simultaneously!?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;lending-my-flute-out&#34;&gt;Lending my flute out&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point, a guy arrived at the party who wanted to jam. He hadn&amp;rsquo;t yet brought in his trombone, but asked if he could borrow my flute. I recognized him from previous parties, and I had seen him play flute in at least one of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So he borrowed my flute and I sat back and watched and listened. He was a really good improviser. Actually, at the suggestion of the tuba player, who really liked totally free improvisation, the three of them did something I found amazing and beautiful. Starting with some long tones, they created an eerie sonic soundscape together, listening to one another while blending the erhu, tuba, and flute. I was really moved by this display of musicality and feeling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;leaving-early&#34;&gt;Leaving early&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby noted that it was getting &amp;ldquo;late&amp;rdquo; for us, and so we regrettably had to leave. Guests were still coming in and bringing food, even though those of us who had arrived early had filled our stomachs long ago. I got my flute back and packed up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is always a special treat for me when I get to hang around creative, accomplished musicians and get to see them make music spontaneously. I&amp;rsquo;m usually too intimidated in these kinds of situations to join in, but I did briefly tonight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-11-06&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-11-06)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was surprised and saddened to learn from Mimi that just a couple of days ago, the man who had borrowed my flute and played so beautifully, David Olson, &lt;a href=&#34;http://obituaries.triblive.com/listing/231895/David-E-Olson/&#34;&gt;died&lt;/a&gt;. Even in the brief time that I interacted with him at all, just in a handful of music parties, I was struck by his enthusiasm, humor, and graciousness. It is hard to believe that he is gone now, just a month since he was playing my flute. RIP, David.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Finally playing Piazzolla&#39;s &#34;Oblivion&#34; on flute</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/09/13/finally-playing-piazzollas-oblivion-on-flute/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2013 23:49:09 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/09/13/finally-playing-piazzollas-oblivion-on-flute/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Almost a year ago, I almost played Piazzolla&amp;rsquo;s tango &amp;ldquo;Oblivion&amp;rdquo; on flute with piano accompaniment by Henry &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/02/oblivion-obsession-time-to-start-playing-melodica/&#34;&gt;at a party&lt;/a&gt; but I ended up playing melodica instead of flute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having the opportunity to play with Henry again, this time I played it on flute, finally! I had found an oboe and piano arrangement which we used, sight reading it. I think the arranger filled in his own ornamentation into the melodic line. I only used that as a guide. Personally, when I play &amp;ldquo;Oblivion&amp;rdquo;, I improvise my own embellishments on the spot, depending on my mood. I play it very freely: it cries out for self-expression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2014-10-23-some-other-performances-of-oblivion&#34;&gt;(Update of 2014-10-23) Some other performances of &amp;ldquo;Oblivion&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/02/oblivion-obsession-time-to-start-playing-melodica/&#34;&gt;blog post of 2012&lt;/a&gt;, I embedded a lot of my favorite performances I found on YouTube of &amp;ldquo;Oblivion&amp;rdquo;. Here are some more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;flute-cello-piano-trio-mathilde-caldérini-zoé-karlikow-aurèle-marthan&#34;&gt;Flute/cello/piano trio (Mathilde Caldérini, Zoé Karlikow, Aurèle Marthan)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Very beautiful performance, great unity and balance and expression from all three musicians.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/DDCB1GqwL0I&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;7-flute-choir&#34;&gt;7 flute choir&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An unusual 7-flute arrangement, with all parts played by the same person, Manja Thessin! A bonus is that the video is a beautiful demonstration of tango dancing by David and Kim Benitez of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.tangomovement.com/&#34;&gt;Tango Movement&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/qvzgzpft8Xg&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;j-oublie-voice-elena-lydia-stamellou&#34;&gt;J&amp;rsquo;oublie (voice), Elena-Lydia Stamellou&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lovely, pure voice with piano accompaniment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/vfP4UF_1cUY&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;piano-improvisational-gila-goldstein&#34;&gt;Piano, improvisational, Gila Goldstein&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A gorgeous, floating performance, very free, with lovely touches in filling in inner voices and adding drama effectively through contrast, detail, and improvisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/J5meF7u3HpY&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;guitar-duo-katrin-klingeberg-and-sebastián-montes&#34;&gt;Guitar duo, Katrin Klingeberg and Sebastián Montes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What a partnership! A passionate performance with contrasting moods, immense focus, really captures the spirit of the piece.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/gONVtoQaovQ&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;guitar-solo-ryuji-kunimatsu&#34;&gt;Guitar solo, Ryuji Kunimatsu&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wow, one guy on guitar, all by himself, in his own arrangement, beautifully expressive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/2WZBOawjNiQ&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;melodica-and-piano-one-musician-simultaneously-haim-shapira&#34;&gt;Melodica and piano, one musician simultaneously! Haim Shapira&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A novelty item, definitely. There are compromises from trying to arrange to play both melodica and piano at the same time, but this is a fascinating free arrangement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/-R_jdtCACQw&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;piano-solo-arrangement-viktoriya-yermolyeva&#34;&gt;Piano solo arrangement, Viktoriya Yermolyeva&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A very passionate performance on piano by the arranger herself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/w1azi_oJGxY&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;digital-piano-solo-roland-fp4&#34;&gt;Digital piano solo (Roland FP4),&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Really quite good, based on Yermolyeva&amp;rsquo;s arrangement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/_Av7LcGRcd8&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Second year at July 3 music party: still only listening without playing</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/07/03/second-year-at-july-3-music-party-still-only-listening-without-playing/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jul 2013 22:10:07 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/07/03/second-year-at-july-3-music-party-still-only-listening-without-playing/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/03/petrified-at-a-music-jam-session-so-i-didnt-play-but-watched-and-listened/&#34;&gt;Last year Abby and I went&lt;/a&gt; to a July 3 music potluck/party at Susan&amp;rsquo;s for the first time. We attended again. I brought my flute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again I enjoyed hearing two groups of people playing music. I am not so much into the &amp;ldquo;old time&amp;rdquo; music, however, which the group outside in the backyard was playing, so I hung out inside instead, where I liked much better the blues guitar and ukulele and singing and piano. &lt;em&gt;I would like to join in one day&lt;/em&gt; myself, but today did not feel up to it. I never took out my flute; it didn&amp;rsquo;t seem appropriate for any of the music anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2014-07-04&#34;&gt;(Update of 2014-07-04)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/07/03/third-year-at-july-3-music-party-and-finally-participated-in-jamming/&#34;&gt;my third year&lt;/a&gt; of this annual party, I actually played both piano and ukulele!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My first blues music jam happened after the regular French music jam</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/01/28/my-first-blues-music-jam-happened-after-the-regular-french-music-jam/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jan 2013 23:26:28 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/01/28/my-first-blues-music-jam-happened-after-the-regular-french-music-jam/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s been over two months since the last French music jam, which was in November. I didn&amp;rsquo;t write about it because there was nothing particularly remarkable about it compared to the whole past year of French music jams: there was Lisa, John, Allison, a new fiddler Liz, and Leslie joining us on banjo again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tonight, an addition was made to the program. For some time I had suggested to Lisa that for French/blues dance night, maybe there should be a blues jam in addition to the French jam. She liked that idea, got hold of people she knew who were interested, and so tonight was the first blues jam!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was actually &lt;em&gt;my first full participation in a blues jam&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was very anxious, but I&amp;rsquo;ve grown somewhat used to feeling anxious at least once a month in the past two years pushing myself into unfamiliar territory repeatedly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, there were some changes for the French jam. Here&amp;rsquo;s how the evening went.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;french-jam&#34;&gt;French jam&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this new year of French music jamming, John, Lisa, and others have kicked things off by transcribing some of their favorite tunes by listening to recordings, watching YouTube, or from memory, in order to share so that we can learn and play them. John couldn&amp;rsquo;t make it tonight, ironically, because he was sick, but I was very exciting that we started exploring a lot of new tunes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I showed up, it was just Lisa on fiddle, Allison on piano (she also brought her button accordion), and me. Enough to get going. (I switched between Irish flute and modern flute as needed depending on the key.) Later, Donna also showed up, on fiddle, and Jess showed up, on clarinet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We played for quite some time, including old favorites we already knew, for the dancers, and learning some new tunes. I think we were at it for two hours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;blues-jam&#34;&gt;Blues jam&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As some of the French dance crowd went home and the blues dance crowd came in, the blues jam began. There was Anders on piano, whom I recognized from his having played blues indoors at a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/03/petrified-at-a-music-jam-session-so-i-didnt-play-but-watched-and-listened/&#34;&gt;summer party&lt;/a&gt;; I may have seen him elsewhere also at &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/10/07/my-first-contra-dance-workshop-unexpected-fun./&#34;&gt;contra dance&lt;/a&gt; or something. I met Michael and Billy, who both had guitars and harmonicas. And all three of them were apparently willing to sing!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was really intimidated. I&amp;rsquo;m still totally, utterly a novice at blues, although I started working on that last year. I wasn&amp;rsquo;t even sure whether I shouldn&amp;rsquo;t pack up my flute and go home. After all, I&amp;rsquo;d already spent a lot of time on music this evening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But something happened that made me stay! Allison seemed like she was about to pack up too, but was curious, and stayed. No longer on piano, she was on her button accordion. We both confessed to never having done this before, but stayed on. I thought she was doing quite well. I wasn&amp;rsquo;t doing so well, but I participated in bits. (But no, I did not sing.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for playing for dancers, I think the dancers were sometimes confused by the experiment, because they didn&amp;rsquo;t have their usual iTunes playlist to dance to. Not everything we did was really suitable to the dancing they wanted to do. We&amp;rsquo;ll have to eventually figure out what works for the dancers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically, when it came to my first blues jam experience, I felt sort of the way I did when I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/05/14/playing-french-music-for-first-time-and-dancing-blues-for-first-time/&#34;&gt;first got into playing French music eight months ago&lt;/a&gt;: anxious, uncertain, embarrassed. But if I work at this and get more comfortable and better, the feeling will pass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d like to do more blues jamming. There is a bit of a problem in that this has made for a very long and late evening. I think that&amp;rsquo;s just the nature of the blues music/dance world. I&amp;rsquo;ll have to plan my schedule accordingly if I want to integrate a regular blues jam into my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And of course, I should continue my studies of the blues.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mideast Early Music Workshop 2012: a life-changing experience!!</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/07/21/mideast-early-music-workshop-a-life-changing-experience/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Jul 2012 22:43:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/07/21/mideast-early-music-workshop-a-life-changing-experience/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The whole past week (July 15-21, 2012), I attended my first ever music camp, the annual &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mideastearlymusic.addr.com/&#34;&gt;Mideast early music workshop&lt;/a&gt; held at LaRoche College. It totally changed my life!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A big report, with photos and videos:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-i-decided-to-attend&#34;&gt;Why I decided to attend&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have loved music all my life, but never had any private instruction, or any intensive group instruction either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;old&#34;&gt;Old?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After passing age 40, I started thinking about mortality, and making a list of what my biggest regrets in life would be if I died soon. On the &lt;em&gt;very top&lt;/em&gt; of the list was my lifelong regret that I never had the courage to get serious about music. I had made excuse after excuse to downplay following my musical dreams (in part a legacy of my internalizing my parents&amp;rsquo; constant discouragement of music as a &amp;ldquo;waste of time&amp;rdquo;, but also because I was &lt;em&gt;not willing to make the required sacrifices as a very busy adult&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So before I turned 41, I decided to finally start the process of getting serious about music, and in February 2011 (less than one and a half years ago), I started to learn to play &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/recorder/&#34;&gt;recorder&lt;/a&gt; because it was easy to get started on, was new to me (without the baggage of my difficult experiences with flute and piano) and most of all, because of the existence of the Pittsburgh Recorder Society as a friendly place to finally play with other people. I mentioned this in &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/22/byron-janis-on-overcoming-adversity/&#34;&gt;one of my first posts on this blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;first-hearing-of-the-workshop&#34;&gt;First hearing of the workshop&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In March 2011, I went to the meeting of the Pittsburgh Recorder Society &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/26/i-dont-feel-like-practicing-but-im-gonna-do-it-anyway/&#34;&gt;for the first time&lt;/a&gt;. At the April 2011 meeting, Helen passed out flyers for the Mideast workshop. I was interested in it and asked her and others about it, but as a total beginner felt that it was not worth attending until I got much better first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After another year, I did in fact improve significantly on recorder (and musically in general), and therefore &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/31/my-first-sampling-of-english-country-dance-and-contra-dance/&#34;&gt;decided this past March&lt;/a&gt; to attend the workshop. I pegged myself as finally having reached a beginner/intermediate level suitable for benefiting from the workshop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;gary-marcus&#34;&gt;Gary Marcus&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also turns out that just this February, I picked up Gary Marcus&amp;rsquo;s book &lt;a href=&#34;http://garymarcus.com/books/guitarzero.html&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Guitar Zero&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; and read it. It is about his experience finally immersing himself in music at the age of 40. This book helped me decide to attend the workshop this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;instruments&#34;&gt;Instruments&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that you have to choose a primary instrument (from among recorder, viol, and (Baroque) flute), but can also study secondary instruments. I decided that because of my strong interest in flute (both Baroque flute and modern flute), I would choose &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/baroque-flute/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Baroque flute&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; as my primary instrument.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Possible secondary instruments are recorder, viol, harp, voice, and capped reeds (for Renaissance band): I chose &lt;em&gt;recorder&lt;/em&gt; (of course), &lt;strong&gt;but also&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;voice&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was deathly scared of getting into singing, but felt that this was my chance to finally jump into it!! I have &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; sung with anyone before (in elementary and middle school, I basically lip-synced when supposed to sing), and have almost never sung in the presence of any other human being (I believe I sang for Abby once). I had a definitely goal of unobtrusively getting my start in singing here, in an informal group setting, and then moving forward from there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;classes&#34;&gt;Classes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The classes I tentatively planned to take were:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Baroque flute technique&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;recorder consort&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;all-workshop ensemble&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;bass recorder ensemble&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;improvisation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;voice class&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;English country dance&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I expected it to be a pretty intense schedule, and it definitely was!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;evening-before-informal-dinner-at-helen-s&#34;&gt;Evening before: informal dinner at Helen&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Helen hosted dinner at her place for both locals and out-of-towners arriving in town for the workshop. About a dozen of us showed up, and Abby came along. Since most of the attendees and instructors already knew each other for years (decades in most cases!), I found it a great way to start getting to know some people. Yes, this is an &amp;ldquo;old people&amp;rdquo; music camp. At age 42, I was by far the baby of the entire group. It seems that a good number of retired people attend the camp. Some of the instructors are younger than me, but it appeared that all the students were going to be older than me. I have to confess that last year, when I was &amp;ldquo;warned&amp;rdquo; that this was an &amp;ldquo;old people&amp;rdquo; camp, I had reservations, but the fact is, music is for any age, and interestingly, since getting involved in music last year, I have been consistently surprised and delighted by how younger-looking or younger-acting musicians tend to be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;day-1-sunday-july-15&#34;&gt;Day 1: Sunday (July 15)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sunday afternoon, I drove up to LaRoche College to check in and pay the registration balance, and got my key to the dorm room where I would be staying for the week. Mike of the Pittsburgh Recorder Society had agreed to share a room with me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dinner in the LaRoche dining hall was varied and tasty, as I expected given the excellent lunch I had enjoyed at LaRoche during &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/06/09/report-on-the-first-pittsburgh-techfest-2012/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh TechFest in June&lt;/a&gt;! I was starving, having become considerably underweight in the past couple of weeks because of being really busy and stressed, and welcomed the opportunity to chow down. I ate not only a whole lot of healthy food, but also couldn&amp;rsquo;t help myself and ate a cupcake, a cookie, and ice cream also!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;introduction-and-all-workshop-ensemble&#34;&gt;Introduction and all-workshop ensemble&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The introduction to the workshop happened after dinner&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marilyn introduced the workshop, along with the instructors. Marilyn has been the organizer of this workshop for something like 45 years, I believe: wow!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/intro.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Instructors on the left&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/intro2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;The rest of the instructors&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Immediately following the introduction was the first meeting of the all-workshop ensemble. We had substantial-looking spiral-bound books of ensemble music and I wondered how much of it we would go through!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/all-workshop-music.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Book and people ready to play&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;english-country-dance&#34;&gt;English country dance&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After that was the first meeting of English country dance. I was sad not to be dancing with Abby (she was not enrolled in the workshop because this isn&amp;rsquo;t her kind of music), but enjoyed learning something new and getting a bit of exercise. Since it started from scratch, it was less intimidating than &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/31/my-first-sampling-of-english-country-dance-and-contra-dance/&#34;&gt;my first experience with English country dance four months ago&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, given that I was the young baby of the bunch, going a bit slowly was helpful to me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/english-country-dance.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;day-2-monday-july-16&#34;&gt;Day 2: Monday (July 16)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed a fine breakfast, including eggs, sausages, and potatoes, and felt myself regaining some much-needed weight. Also, regarding the dorm rooms: they have air-conditioning, much appreciated given the hot and muggy summer!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;baroque-flute-technique&#34;&gt;Baroque flute technique&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I felt very intimidated in Majbritt&amp;rsquo;s morning Baroque flute technique class. There were six of us in the class, and I was clearly the least experienced. My flute playing (whether modern or flute) is at a beginner&amp;rsquo;s level, as I have been playing for only a few months really. In fact, this is &lt;em&gt;exactly&lt;/em&gt; why I chose flute as my &lt;em&gt;primary&lt;/em&gt; instrument in the workshop: to get good instruction in technique before I progressed too far on my won. Even with recorder, I had to unlearn some bad habits early on that I had developed from working on it myself for a month or so before joining the Pittsburgh Recorder Society!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In class we had a &amp;ldquo;review&amp;rdquo; of basic concepts of Baroque flute technique such as the correct &lt;em&gt;embouchure&lt;/em&gt; adjustments to get the intonation right of all the various notes: for example, the F is sharp unless you adjust the embouchure, and the F-sharp is flat unless you adjust the embouchure in the other way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then we talked about &lt;em&gt;articulation&lt;/em&gt;. One new thing I learned here was to be aware of the &lt;em&gt;end&lt;/em&gt; of a note, very important compared with playing modern instruments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I took a lot of notes, as well as made annotations in the music we got.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;voice-class&#34;&gt;Voice class&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eric taught voice class. There was a good balance of men and women. He handed us spiral-bound books of musical selections.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/voice-eric.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Eric Haas&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/voice-men.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Other men in voice class&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We went through a bunch of songs, and I . It was tremendous fun. I had never in my life sight-sung before (!!!), so I was very nervous. I tried not to let on that I was a total novice (unlike everyone else there). I took a lot of notes on what was tricky and marked up the song book for further study.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The somewhat nerve-wracking thing was that no men were really tenors, and a bunch sang bass, so Eric, Chris, and I sang tenor. I&amp;rsquo;m a baritone, not a tenor: the high notes were scary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;lunch&#34;&gt;Lunch&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I totally stuffed myself for lunch. So much good food.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/monday-lunch.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;recorder-consort&#34;&gt;Recorder consort&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Emily was the instructor for my recorder consort class. I was put into a lower-level class because of being relatively new (having played recorder for less than two years). I didn&amp;rsquo;t mind, because I knew that I had much to learn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Emily focused a lot on things like where to breathe, and in paying attention to others in an ensemble. I learned to write in commas for breathing in music scores (in the flute class, Majbritt also emphasized finding the phrasing and the breathing, and this has been a theme at Pittsburgh Recorder Society meetings as well). I realized that I still had a lot to absorb from these lessons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Emily also told us to find the narrative in any music we played. It&amp;rsquo;s not just isolated notes; music has a push and pull.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;bass-ensemble&#34;&gt;Bass ensemble&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;James (whom I amusingly first encountered online through his &lt;a href=&#34;http://jnote.org/&#34;&gt;fantastic multi-track melodica videos&lt;/a&gt; before finding out that he teaches recorder at the Mideast workshop) led the bass ensemble. I still play bass recorder only very infrequently, so I was nervous, but joined the bass ensemble because I thought it would be fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;improvisation&#34;&gt;Improvisation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alan taught improvisation. I had never actually specifically learned improvisation techniques before, but want to eventually get truly serious about improvisation, so I was excited to take this class, which was quite participatory. He would describe a concept, such as the pentatonic scale, and then have us do something with it. The class was enthusiastic. I was actually pretty moved by how individual everyone&amp;rsquo;s inventiveness was, even doing basic things, and that helped me loosen up as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;medieval-fiddle&#34;&gt;Medieval fiddle&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a whim, I checked out the medieval fiddle class. I borrowed a medieval fiddle to take back to my room after class. (But it would turn out that the instrument had problems, and I had too much other stuff to do, and had never played a string instrument before, so I ended up returning it and not returning to the class.)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/medieval-fiddle.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;A medieval fiddle&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;dinner&#34;&gt;Dinner&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby came up to visit and joined me for dinner while on her way to mandolin orchestra rehearsal, which is actually close by.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ate an ice cream cone, but realizing that I was gaining a lot of weight already after 24 hours at LaRoche, I chose not to eat cake or cupcakes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;all-workshop-ensemble&#34;&gt;All-workshop ensemble&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Intense stuff. I took pages and pages of notes as Eric talked about different styles, phrasing, &amp;ldquo;painting&amp;rdquo;, dissonances, imitation, counterpoint, the significance of words in text, changes in meter, etc. We read through a lot of pieces to work on for the week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;english-country-dance-1&#34;&gt;English country dance&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We learned more stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;study&#34;&gt;Study!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, after all the classes into the evening, I got to spend some hours in my dorm room or across the hall in an empty meeting room used for classes in the day (since sometimes Mike was in the dorm room or going to bed earlier than me) doing what review of my notes I could, as well as practicing for each of my classes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was intense: I had been given so much to learn already after a single day! I was right in choosing to live on site rather than take the commuter option, because the commute from Pittsburgh would have been stressful and time-consuming for me, taking away energy and time I could spend on classes and preparation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;day-3-tuesday-july-17&#34;&gt;Day 3: Tuesday (July 17)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;flute&#34;&gt;Flute&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I learned about &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Notes_in%C3%A9gales&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;inégal&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; for the first time. I hadn&amp;rsquo;t know that this &amp;ldquo;swinging&amp;rdquo; of notes (familiar in jazz) also applied to Baroque music!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We continued our study of articulation. I learned a huge amount about &amp;ldquo;t&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;d&amp;rdquo; and runs of notes as well as leaps. It was very difficult for me to execute all this, so I tried to focus on one aspect at a time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;voice&#34;&gt;Voice&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More work, and a lot of fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;recorder-consort-1&#34;&gt;Recorder consort&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reinforcing the technique points we learned yesterday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;bass-class&#34;&gt;Bass class&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It continued being a challenge for me to alternate between reading bass clef for bass recorder and reading treble clef for it as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;improvisation-1&#34;&gt;Improvisation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Musical structure such as ABA, ABACA (rondo).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;nap-time&#34;&gt;Nap time&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cutting out medieval violin meant having a block of nap time, much-needed!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;dinner-1&#34;&gt;Dinner&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I created a pattern of eating ice cream every day at dinner, and continued to gain weight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;all-workshop-ensemble-singing&#34;&gt;All-workshop ensemble: singing?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the pieces we went through could optionally be sung, so Eric asked us to think of whether we wanted to sing or play an instrument for our performance on Friday. I was intrigued by the option to sing. &amp;ldquo;Ecco l&amp;rsquo;Aurora&amp;rdquo; was very interesting to sing, but also rather challenging to me, with its leaps and modulations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But because of the relative lack of tenor volunteers, I decided I would switch from playing tenor recorder and work on singing it on Friday. I was partly inspired by Chris&amp;rsquo;s example, and also by the guy sitting next to me who decided to sing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;english-country-dance-2&#34;&gt;English country dance&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We learned a new dance, but also started focusing on improving on a particular dance for Friday&amp;rsquo;s performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;study-1&#34;&gt;Study&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was practicing in the empty meeting room until at 11 PM, Charles, whose dorm room was actually right next door, told me he was going to sleep. Oops! If I didn&amp;rsquo;t do English country dance, I could practice earlier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;day-4-wednesday-july-18&#34;&gt;Day 4: Wednesday (July 18)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;flute-1&#34;&gt;Flute&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Very detailed articulation instruction. Also, notes on hemiolas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;master-class&#34;&gt;Master class&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was very excited to attend the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Master_class&#34;&gt;master class&lt;/a&gt;. I had never attended a master class before, actually, although I had seen some videos of the concept.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that Karen had prepared a piece for Baroque flute for the master class, and Mike had prepared a piece for recorder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I took a huge number of notes. For each of them, I first took notes while they played their pieces, then I took more notes as the instructors gave feedback. I found it quite useful to compare what they observed with what I had observed independently (or not noticed at all). The whole experience was tremendously instructive for me, giving me a huge amount of information to apply to my own playing. I don&amp;rsquo;t know if I have the courage to expose myself to scrutiny in public like this. I&amp;rsquo;m certainly appreciative of Karen and Mike doing so!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I noticed some observations in common among the instructors and for both Karen and Mike. The gist of the advice:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;add more variety in &lt;em&gt;articulation&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;play with more &lt;em&gt;freedom&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;find and express the &lt;em&gt;shape&lt;/em&gt; and melodic line&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;look for the meaning of leaps and &lt;em&gt;dissonance&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found these insights profoundly useful, and found it inspiring to see Karen and Mike work to make some changes in their playing in response to the instructors&amp;rsquo; feedback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;karen&#34;&gt;Karen&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Karen prepared one of the twelve &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/12_Fantasias_for_Solo_Flute_%28Telemann%29&#34;&gt;Telemann fantasias for solo flute&lt;/a&gt;, no. 2.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/master-class-karen.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Karen&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/master-class-karen-majbritt.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Majbritt feedback for Karen&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h4 id=&#34;mike&#34;&gt;Mike&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By coincidence, Mike played another of the Telemann fantasias for solo flute, no. 10, but he played it on alto recorder instead of flute.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/master-class-mike.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Mike&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There was a funny moment in which Mike used his leg to play a high F-sharp. Later, Emily and James showed him a good technique hint, preparing the F-sharp by bringing up the leg already in anticipation, and then bringing the head down toward the leg instead of vice versa.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/master-class-mike-james-leg.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Mike raising leg, with James and Emily&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;lunch-1&#34;&gt;Lunch&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After lunch, Mike and I helped Chris move his harpsichord. (Chris drove his own harpsichord up from home and it&amp;rsquo;s used for many sessions at the workshop.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;recorder-consort-2&#34;&gt;Recorder consort&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People had been leaving our recorder consort class one by one; Wednesday, we were down to five! I wondered why this was going on. Admittedly, we were moving slowly through the music, because a couple of us were more on the beginner side and had trouble sight reading, staying with the score, keeping fingerings straight. I myself had silently considered switching, but I found the &amp;ldquo;slower&amp;rdquo; pace an opportunity to really focus on trying to work on various basic things that are more important than &amp;ldquo;getting through&amp;rdquo; a lot of musical selections. I really needed to get down what I was learning about breath, resonance, and intonation, as well as ensemble unity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;free-time&#34;&gt;Free time!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wednesday there is scheduled &amp;ldquo;free time&amp;rdquo; during which there are no classes. I was totally exhausted by this point in the week and napped for two and a half hours!! Then I finally went outside for a 40-minute run, in my new Invisible Shoes (which I wore around daily and got a lot of comments on); I had originally intended to get regular exercise in every day while at camp, but had simply felt overwhelmed by the desire to make the most of my music classes and practice (at least I did do an hour of English country dance every evening).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;white-elephant-sale&#34;&gt;White Elephant Sale&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After dinner, I browsed around at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/White_Elephant_Sale&#34;&gt;White Elephant Sale&lt;/a&gt;. I kicked myself for having totally forgotten to bring some stuff to donate to it. I was amused that Helen managed to get rid of a particular item that she had wanted out of her home for some time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;chris-and-harpsichord&#34;&gt;Chris and harpsichord&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had been so busy that I had not bothered to think about signing up for playing with Chris on harpsichord. Unfortunately, by the time I checked the signup sheet, I saw that it was full (empty slots conflicted with my class time).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/harpsichord-signup.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Chris harpsichord signup sheet&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There were signup sheets all along for other stuff too, such as people wanting to find others to play with. That is actually a large part of the appeal of the workshop. I didn&amp;rsquo;t participate in any of that because as a newcomer, I was focused on exploring classes. But obviously, those who had come to the workshop for years and decades did not necessarily need or want to spend all their time on classes.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/other-signup.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Other signup sheets&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;faculty-concert&#34;&gt;Faculty concert&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another highlight of Wednesday was the faculty concert. This was great. Bagpipes, recorders, Renaissance flutes, Baroque flutes, harpsichord, viola da gamba, even sackbut! It was a real treat to see all our instructors performing.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/bagpipes.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Alan on bagpipes&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/faculty-concert-2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Group&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/faculty-concert-3.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Group&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/faculty-concert-james-majbritt.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;James and Majbritt in duet&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I was intrigued by Emily playing Debussy&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Syrinx&amp;rdquo; on a special tenor recorder.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/emily-syrinx.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Emily playing Syrinx on special tenor recorder&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/chris-harpsichord.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Chris solo on harpsichord&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/faculty-concert-flutes.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Eric, Emily, Majbritt on flutes&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/judith-viol.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Judith on viol&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A short video clip from the faculty concert (I found out that my phone made an unstoppable annoying click when taking video, so I never used my phone again for video after this; other videos I post here came from the camera Abby brought on Friday):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/vpXVEf7NfSw&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;practice&#34;&gt;Practice&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally I got time to practice. There was a lot of stuff to prepare for the Friday concert.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;day-5-thursday-july-19&#34;&gt;Day 5: Thursday (July 19)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;breakfast&#34;&gt;Breakfast&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of the considerable weight gain (approximately &lt;em&gt;four pounds&lt;/em&gt; so far since arrival), I decided to stop eating potatoes (which seemed to be available in some form at every meal).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;flute-2&#34;&gt;Flute&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More technique. Lip and tongue placement, different scales. We finally decided on what to play for the concert, a selection by Dittersdorf. I was one of those on the easiest part, the third part of the trio, playing &amp;ldquo;bass&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;voice-1&#34;&gt;Voice&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We worked through a bunch more selections while continuing to refine the one we had decided to perform on Friday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, it came in really handy this week that I have at least basic competence in French, Italian, Latin, and German, because we sang in all these languages!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;bass&#34;&gt;Bass&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got to class early enough (a rarity, since usually I was rushing from voice class) to take a photo.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/bass-setup.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Mike and James&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;By the way, since I had hardly played bass before coming to this workshop, I hadn&amp;rsquo;t realized that my bass tended to be sharp and I learned I had to keep the head joint pulled out to a certain degree. Useful to finally find that out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;improvisation-2&#34;&gt;Improvisation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We did blues stuff, and Alan pulled out his guitar to give us chords as the rest of us took turns on recorder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;special-mini-class-on-practice-techniques&#34;&gt;Special mini-class on practice techniques&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I attended a one-session class on practice techniques by Emily. I found this tremendously useful and took a lot of notes. Some of the key ideas:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;don&amp;rsquo;t practice a mistake&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;importance of warmup with focus (physical but also mental)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;go slow, do it right&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;break down difficult tasks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it all starts with the mind: first decide and know what you want to accomplish, then figure out the physical means&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;repetition and grouping into units&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;isolation of aspects of technique&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;classify goals as long, medium, and short term&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;all-workshop-ensemble-1&#34;&gt;All-workshop ensemble&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had a shorter session, in order to make more time for the following ad hoc student concert.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eric had singers lined up in front so that we would run through &amp;ldquo;Ecco l&amp;rsquo;Aurora&amp;rdquo; as it was going to be presented on Friday: I stood with Chris for tenor and found it tremendously helpful to have him at my side so that when I was uncertain or got lost, I had someone to anchor back to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instrumentalists were reminded to play as though singing, articulating consistently with the words of the text.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;ad-hoc-student-concert&#34;&gt;Ad hoc student concert&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of participants in the workshop look forward to this as one of their highlights of the experience. I did not sign up to perform for this because I was focused entirely on classes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each selection was short, and there were a whole lot of individuals and groups that came up to present something. Some people had prepared something before the workshop. Others had met up and were playing for the first time together. It was a fun time.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/ad-hoc-audience.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Ad hoc student concert audience&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;practice-1&#34;&gt;Practice&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally at 10 PM I started music practice!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;day-6-friday-july-20-final-day&#34;&gt;Day 6: Friday (July 20), final day&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;flute-3&#34;&gt;Flute&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We reviewed what we were playing for the concert, but also moved on to work some more on music we were not performing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;voice-2&#34;&gt;Voice&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We went over the two pieces we were to perform at the concert, then closed the class with work on some more pieces in the book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;recorder-consort-3&#34;&gt;Recorder consort&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Final review.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;bass-1&#34;&gt;Bass&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We did a lot of intonation adjustment, since many of us were sharp!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;James had particular ideas about performance presentation, and told us to hold up our instruments after we were done playing, watch out for extraneous sucking, and refrain from bringing too much junk (extra clothing, shoe boxes, etc.) with us. Also, we were to bring only the two pages of music we were to play, not binders of all our music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;improvisation-3&#34;&gt;Improvisation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Final class. We did not plan to perform as a group in the concert.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;dinner-2&#34;&gt;Dinner&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby had come up for dinner on Monday. I hadn&amp;rsquo;t seen her since then, and she came up to see the final concert. I was happy she was able to make it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;final-concert&#34;&gt;Final concert&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final student concert showcased what everyone had worked on so hard for the week. Because I took so many classes, I was in several groups that performed. Here are just a sample of photos and videos from the concert. I apologize for not having full coverage, but as I was occupied with performing, after my first performance, I completely stopped messing around with my phone and just focused on enjoying others&amp;rsquo; performances and getting ready to switch in when one of my groups was up! Abby did take some photos and videos, but only when I was involved!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/harps.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/recorder-eric.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/recorder-eric-2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h4 id=&#34;me-in-flute&#34;&gt;Me in flute&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby took this photo of me in Majbritt&amp;rsquo;s flute group:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/flute-majbritt.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h4 id=&#34;me-in-voice-ensemble&#34;&gt;Me in voice ensemble&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eric tuning for the voice ensemble (I&amp;rsquo;m standing next to Chris as usual):&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/voice-tuning.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Clips from our two selections:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/SfptMbkdwsw&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/nF-5ph82sJ4&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Immediately after the voice ensemble performance, Abby commented to me that during performance, I ended up &amp;ldquo;hiding&amp;rdquo; with my score in my hands rising up and up, partially covering my face. Admittedly, I was very nervous, but also, I was trying to cover up my inability to keep a straight face while barking on the tenor dog line!! (For the final all-workshop ensemble performance, I made sure not to hide.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;bass-ensemble-1&#34;&gt;Bass ensemble&lt;/h4&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/bass-final.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.mideastearlymusic.addr.com/P1160081.jpeg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/NY8YQfYErfc&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;concluding-all-workshop-ensemble-performance&#34;&gt;Concluding all-workshop ensemble performance&lt;/h4&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/all-workshop-final.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Me and Chris:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/all-workshop-final-franklin-chris.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.mideastearlymusic.addr.com/P1160084.jpeg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;All-workshop ensemble&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.mideastearlymusic.addr.com/P1160083.jpeg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;All-workshop ensemble&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/CBGZlAWB7BI&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;party&#34;&gt;Party&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a party afterwards with unique tasty treats that Abby and I attended, and she got to meet more of my instructors and classmates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People started to pack up and prepare to leave. It was a long week, but what a fun one!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was, of course, asked whether I planned to come back next year. I said I would like to, but could not yet commit to that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;more-photos&#34;&gt;More photos&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More photos of the whole workshop week can be found &lt;a href=&#34;http://mideastearlymusic.addr.com/newpglogo.htm&#34;&gt;here at the workshop site&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;saturday-at-home-thoughts&#34;&gt;Saturday at home: thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I weighed myself the next day. I&amp;rsquo;d gained a total of &lt;em&gt;seven pounds&lt;/em&gt; in five days. On the one hand, I had gone in underweight, so it was good I finally made up for that, but now I was a bit overweight, as Abby noticed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reflecting on the week, I resolved to put into practice everything I had learned at the workshop. It was going to take time to develop new habits, make use of new awareness, but I now knew of the path forward. Before attending the workshop, I had gotten advice here and there that was useful, and I had read up on things by myself, but there is nothing like being immersed in an environment of total learning, feedback, and collaboration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Attending this workshop has given me fresh concrete direction and musical goals as well as the determination to push on and not settle for anything less than doing what I can to musically express myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;thanks&#34;&gt;Thanks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am grateful to Marilyn, all the instructors (especially those of my classes: Majbritt, Emily, Eric, James, Alan), my classmates (especially Chris for voice, without whom I would have felt lost), the staff of LaRoche College, and the members of the Pittsburgh Recorder Society who first told me of this workshop and also attended (Helen, Annie, Mike, Sam, Maggie who danced with me). Mike was a considerate dorm roommate for the week. And I am particularly grateful that Abby supported me in my quest to improve my musicianship and enabled me to attend the workshop, and also visited me twice for dinner and to see me in the final student concert.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had an amazing time at the Mideast early music workshop. I am going to continue my study of Baroque flute and recorder, and voice as well, and do more with improvisation. Now that I have seen and worked with more really good musicians up front (both instructors and students at the workshop: I noticed that quite a few of the students themselves are actually professional musicians on non-early instruments), I have a much clearer idea of how I want to sound and what kind of technique I need to develop in order to make that into reality. Mostly, I feel that some kind of psychological block has been removed and that I now have real courage where I still didn&amp;rsquo;t have it before attending the workshop: courage to experiment, to fail, to continue.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Another terrifying music jam session but I played a little bit of blues and old time</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/07/07/another-terrifying-music-jam-session-but-i-played-a-little-bit-of-blues-and-old-time/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Jul 2012 23:37:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/07/07/another-terrifying-music-jam-session-but-i-played-a-little-bit-of-blues-and-old-time/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/03/petrified-at-a-music-jam-session-so-i-didnt-play-but-watched-and-listened&#34;&gt;Just earlier this week, I went to a music jam where I was afraid to play&lt;/a&gt; and so I didn&amp;rsquo;t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today Abby and I went to another intimidating potluck/jam session, this time hosted by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.appalasia.com/Mimi.htm&#34;&gt;Mimi Jong&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://classic-sculpture.com/&#34;&gt;Susan Wagner&lt;/a&gt;. Mimi had invited Abby, but hadn&amp;rsquo;t yet met me; I knew who she was through having been to an &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.appalasia.com/&#34;&gt;Appalasia&lt;/a&gt; performance with Abby at some point earlier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This time I played a little bit. I almost didn&amp;rsquo;t, but felt that I had to start with something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;lots-of-music&#34;&gt;Lots of music&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was music going on outside in back of the home. Wow. It was fantastic stuff, what everyone was doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was Mimi on &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Erhu&#34;&gt;erhu&lt;/a&gt;, of course. There was a keyboard and sound system set up. People on bass, guitars, drums of all kinds, claves, banjos, violin, singing, you name it. All kinds of music was being jammed to. A lot of Latin music, sung by someone who seemed a native Spanish speaker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recognized a violinist as being someone who had played Baroque violin at a recital I had been at in April.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, there were clearly a lot of professional musicians here and so I felt really intimidated. I did a lot of watching and listening and quite enjoyed experiencing joy and inventiveness unfold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was fascinating seeing Mimi kicking off &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Summertime_(song)&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Summertime&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; on erhu. Hey, why not?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the Latin and Brazilian songs I knew the melodies for, and if I only knew all lyrics and could actually sing, I would have wanted to join in for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;joining-in&#34;&gt;Joining in&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But Mimi encouraged Abby and me to join in. At some point, Abby did join in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of the problem for me, besides the fact that I felt naked and helpless without a music score to read, was that I&amp;rsquo;d brought one case of instruments this time, which included some recorders as well as a Baroque flute, and it didn&amp;rsquo;t seem like any of these instruments was really suitable for the occasion. In my hurry to arrive at the potluck already running late, I had forgotten to bring my modern flute!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did the best I could and took out my Baroque flute and tried joining in. Some old time music came on and I found it not so difficult to do something for that, although nothing I was proud of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I remember mainly is when Mimi started some blues and at some point I came in and gave it a shot, and although I didn&amp;rsquo;t last very long, I got something in that wasn&amp;rsquo;t totally horrible. Somehow that was very liberating, getting those few seconds in for the evening. At least I didn&amp;rsquo;t walk away from the party this evening without playing anything at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Attending this potluck/jam session was an immensely exciting experience for me. I feel like I am truly expanding my musical world, and getting inspired. I too would like to be singing my favorite Latin songs. And I really like blues improvisation. I will start doing these things eventually; they are no longer just remote possibilities, but what I have seen people doing in front of my own eyes and not in an impersonal concert but at a casual, fun party.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-01-28&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-01-28)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Six months later, I participated in &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/28/my-first-blues-music-jam-happened-after-the-regular-french-music-jam/&#34;&gt;my first blues jam&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-09-28&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-09-28)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over a year later, I reported on &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/09/28/an-erhu-player-and-a-tuba-player-at-a-party-said-lets-jam/&#34;&gt;participating in a music jam at another one of these parties with Mimi&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Petrified at a music jam session so I didn&#39;t play but watched and listened</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/07/03/petrified-at-a-music-jam-session-so-i-didnt-play-but-watched-and-listened/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jul 2012 22:35:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/07/03/petrified-at-a-music-jam-session-so-i-didnt-play-but-watched-and-listened/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/02/my-first-french-music-jam-anxious-but-excited&#34;&gt;Just yesterday, I went to a music jam&lt;/a&gt; and was anxious but got over that and participated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today Abby and I went to a &lt;em&gt;very different&lt;/em&gt; one, a potluck/music jam hosted by Susan Waggoner, whom we&amp;rsquo;ve known for a long time through various Pittsburgh music and dance activities. Susan is involved particularly in the Cajun music/dance scene, and was also in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.post-gazette.com/stories/local/neighborhoods-city/accordion-pool-partys-another-use-for-empty-lawrenceville-pool-357459/&#34;&gt;Accordion Pool Party&lt;/a&gt; that Abby played in three years ago, and also has been doing &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/01/23/discovering-french-traditional-dance-in-pittsburgh/&#34;&gt;French dancing&lt;/a&gt; with us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was so &lt;em&gt;terrified&lt;/em&gt; at this party that I didn&amp;rsquo;t play &lt;em&gt;at all&lt;/em&gt;, despite bringing my instruments. I just didn&amp;rsquo;t feel up to it. But I learned a lot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;two-main-groups-of-musicians&#34;&gt;Two main groups of musicians&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that there were a bunch of musicians playing music outside in the back of the home. I wasn&amp;rsquo;t super familiar with what they were playing. Then there were some musicians playing music inside in the living room.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They really knew what they were doing, and were singing and playing by ear, no scores in sight. Without any scores, I had no clue how I could contribute, so I didn&amp;rsquo;t even take out my instruments. This was &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; jamming, not the kind that I did yesterday where most (but not all) of the stuff we did involved songs I had brought scores for or at least had heard before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;old-time-music&#34;&gt;Old time music&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was told by the men and women who were inside that those outside were playing &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Old-time_music&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;old time&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; music. I hadn&amp;rsquo;t been familiar with the term or genre.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby liked being outside, and also has been playing mandolin, so spent time checking out that group. I think she played along some too. It seemed to be mostly fiddlers, with banjo, mandolin, percussion, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I checked it out, but the music happened not to be quite so interesting to me; it moved fast, had a lot of notes, but seemed somewhat monotonous to my taste.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;country-blues-music&#34;&gt;Country blues music&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inside, however, I was really captivated by what was going on. They said that they were playing &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Country_blues&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;country blues&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. I liked the harmonic changes and the rhythmic qualities and improvisation. Guitars, harmonica, piano, singing. I was impressed by how the singers made up entire lyrics on the spot, often very funny or off-color.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I stayed around inside soaking in what was going on, and thought, I could see myself someday playing along.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was really excited to meet more musicians and widen my musical experience at the potluck/jam session. I felt pretty inspired by what I saw going on, music as a really communal, creative experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Noticing the huge gap between what these musicians were able to do and what I am able to do, I know that it takes a long time to get where they are, but I want to have that kind of everyday facility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2012-07-07&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-07-07)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Four days later, we went to another potluck/jam session, and &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/07/another-terrifying-music-jam-session-but-i-played-a-little-bit-of-blues-and-old-time/&#34;&gt;I played a little bit&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-01-28&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-01-28)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seven months later, I participated in &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/28/my-first-blues-music-jam-happened-after-the-regular-french-music-jam/&#34;&gt;my first blues jam&lt;/a&gt;. The pianist there, Anders, was the same one I first saw here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-07-03&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-07-03)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/07/03/second-year-at-july-3-music-party-still-only-listening-without-playing/&#34;&gt;my second year&lt;/a&gt; of this annual party, I still did not feel comfortable enough with the crowd to try to participate musically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2014-07-03&#34;&gt;(Update of 2014-07-03)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/07/03/third-year-at-july-3-music-party-and-finally-participated-in-jamming/&#34;&gt;my third year&lt;/a&gt; of this annual party, I actually played both piano and ukulele!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My first time in a public music jam: intense fun with Chris Norman and David Greenberg</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/04/21/my-first-time-in-a-public-music-jam-intense-fun-with-chris-norman-and-david-greenberg/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Apr 2012 13:44:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/04/21/my-first-time-in-a-public-music-jam-intense-fun-with-chris-norman-and-david-greenberg/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://fbcdn-sphotos-a.akamaihd.net/hphotos-ak-ash3/544714_10150682065771513_55075526512_9775036_876594193_n.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;David Greenberg and Chris Norman and the rest of us&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Friday evening, Abby and I packed up various musical instruments of ours, and attended an event that I had been eagerly awaiting for over three weeks since I first found out about it from Annie of the local &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.andrew.cmu.edu/user/lukas/pcars/Welcome.html&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh recorder gang&lt;/a&gt;: a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rbsp.org/Jam%20Session%20Flyer.pdf&#34;&gt;jam session open to the public&lt;/a&gt; being offered by &lt;a href=&#34;http://chrisnorman.com/&#34;&gt;Chris Norman&lt;/a&gt;, flutist, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.davidgreenberg.ca/&#34;&gt;David Greenberg&lt;/a&gt;, violinist the day before &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rbsp.org/11-12c6.aspx&#34;&gt;their concert&lt;/a&gt; the next evening to close the current season of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rbsp.org/&#34;&gt;Renaissance and Baroque of Pittsburgh&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was so excited by this opportunity to jam with such esteemed musicians. Norman and Greenberg specialize in playing Irish, Scottish, Cape Breton and Baroque music. I&amp;rsquo;ve come to love playing the rhythmic, danceable music of the old days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I learned a lot from the experience, and would like to share what I learned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;some-photos-of-the-event&#34;&gt;Some photos of the event&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/pages/Pittsburgh-Renaissance-and-Baroque/55075526512&#34;&gt;Facebook page of the Pittsburgh Renaissance and Baroque&lt;/a&gt; has a bunch of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/media/set/?set=a.10150682065546513.394216.55075526512&amp;amp;type=3&#34;&gt;photos of the event&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;ve used a couple of these here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;preparation&#34;&gt;Preparation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;my-instruments&#34;&gt;My instruments&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been spending most of my daily music practice all year working on the modern &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/flute/&#34;&gt;flute&lt;/a&gt;; I have not reported on my progress in over a month because I&amp;rsquo;ve been too busy &lt;em&gt;doing&lt;/em&gt; rather than &lt;em&gt;writing&lt;/em&gt;, but will catch up with the writing sometime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But for this jam session, I had decided very quickly that I was &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; going to be bringing my modern flute to play, because I do prefer to play older music on other instruments; I planned to bring the following instruments instead:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;my &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/tin-whistle/&#34;&gt;tin whistle&lt;/a&gt;, which I bought the week of St. Patrick&amp;rsquo;s Day in March (for a party I haven&amp;rsquo;t written about yet but which radically changed my life)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;an assortment of &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/recorder/&#34;&gt;recorders&lt;/a&gt;: I decided to just bring my soprano and alto&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;my &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/baroque-flute/&#34;&gt;Baroque flute&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, interspersed with my continuing work on the modern flute, I have also done some maintenance practice of tin whistle and recorders. The most difficult challenge was trying to get serious about Baroque flute: the one-keyed flute is &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.oldflutes.com/charts/onekey/index.htm&#34;&gt;very, very, very tricky to play in tune&lt;/a&gt;. Sometimes I wonder whether it&amp;rsquo;s worth the bother. But I tend to be inspired by quirky challenges whose benefit I don&amp;rsquo;t fully understand immediately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ideally, I would own an &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.caseyburnsflutes.com/cat_d.php&#34;&gt;Irish flute&lt;/a&gt;, preferably with a number of keys to aid with intonation and fingering, but given that I don&amp;rsquo;t currently intend to specialize in Irish music, and am still working with the tin whistle anyway, I cannot at all justify buying an Irish flute at this time. So I&amp;rsquo;ve been working on using the related Baroque flute instead, for traditional Irish or Scottish music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;abby-s-instruments&#34;&gt;Abby&amp;rsquo;s instruments&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby started learning mandolin just this year, joining the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pittsburghmandolinsociety.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Mandolin Orchestra&lt;/a&gt;, so I was excited that she decided early on to bring it to the jam session. (And I look forward to seeing her play for the first time in the orchestra&amp;rsquo;s concert on Mother&amp;rsquo;s Day coming up in three weeks!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She also brought a frame drum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-event&#34;&gt;The event!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;arrival&#34;&gt;Arrival&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I arrived a little late, so I scrambled to get ready while a whole bunch of people were already gathered. Many people were sitting in back just to watch and listen, while maybe twenty of us were armed with instruments of all kinds, ready to have some fun!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://fbcdn-sphotos-a.akamaihd.net/hphotos-ak-prn1/541085_10150682067126513_55075526512_9775042_292845062_n.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;We played lots of different instruments&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We ran into half a dozen people we knew from various of our musical circles, including Annie from recorder, a guy Abby knew from mandolin, and some fellow &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/16/playing-recorder-and-flute-at-the-holiday-ball/&#34;&gt;Holiday Ball&lt;/a&gt; musicians.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was intrigued by the couple of people who had actual keyed Irish flutes and eager to hear them play (it would turn out, of course, that they were very, very good).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;music-scores&#34;&gt;Music scores&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So each of us got a packet of around twenty pages of music. We didn&amp;rsquo;t play all of it, of course, but it was a good basis for sight reading along with Chris and David leading the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much of the music went at breakneck pace that I&amp;rsquo;m still not proficient enough to sight reading perfectly, but my (yet unreported) musical adventures in the past month have made me far less self-conscious about perfection and figure out ways to cope:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it&amp;rsquo;s not necessary to play all the notes; in fast music, you can contribute just fine playing only one main note per measure or harmony change&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;you can also substitute a different, easier melodic line that is compatible with the chords&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;since sections are repeated many times, you can add more during repetitions as you feel ready to&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it&amp;rsquo;s not the end of the world to miscalculate sometimes and squeak out a harsh dissonant error; the music just keeps going, so don&amp;rsquo;t look back, only forward&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;learning-by-ear-improvisation&#34;&gt;Learning by ear, improvisation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I expected, much of the time we didn&amp;rsquo;t play music from the handed out scores at all. This was the fun I was anticipating all along (I had not really expected music scores at all, actually).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost half the time, Chris would ask us for music suggestions to offer up &lt;em&gt;by example&lt;/em&gt;, so that the volunteer would play (or sing) the melody, then the rest of us would start &amp;ldquo;learning&amp;rdquo; it by ear and join in and continue with repetitions. I had not anticipated the call for volunteers, else I would have come prepared with some favorite tunes to offer!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some people were more familiar with various tunes being offered up than I was, since they had a lot more experience with Irish, Scottish and other such music than me, so I felt awkward and lost trying to learn and play on the spot, without written music, but it was part of the whole fun, really stretching what I have usually been doing with music (very oriented toward following a written score).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve mentioned before my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/10/flute-loving-it-again/&#34;&gt;poor memory&lt;/a&gt; having a considerable impact on my life, and I worked around it again, given that I could not quickly learn the details of a melody, by just giving up and improvising around the harmony changes instead. I would like to find ways to improve my memory, but for now, I work around my limitations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;a-charming-tangent-involving-an-oboe&#34;&gt;A charming tangent involving an oboe&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it turned out that a young woman among us had come with a Baroque oboe tuned to A415 instead of the modern A440 tuning. This caused confusion, of course, when she tried to play from written scores. I&amp;rsquo;m not sure what she ended up doing: the only choices were to mentally transpose from the written scores (when we were playing music from them) or just ignore the scores and learn by ear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, Chris and David repeatedly wanted to play with her and asked her what music she had on her, and she had a variety of Baroque music scores with her (she said she was actually giving a recital the next day), and so they tried to play some stuff just with her while doing their own mental transposition so that she would get to play without mental transposition! Check out Chris hovering over the score trying to do the really hard work of transposing on the fly:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://fbcdn-sphotos-a.akamaihd.net/hphotos-ak-ash4/s720x720/295215_10150682067841513_395463764_n.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Baroque oboist with Chris and David&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;dancing&#34;&gt;Dancing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Periodically, a number of people got up to dance in the space at the side, especially when we played waltzes. It was nice to see people moving.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://fbcdn-sphotos-a.akamaihd.net/hphotos-ak-ash3/529154_10150682066471513_55075526512_9775039_758574985_n.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;A couple dancing&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;i-m-caught-on-a-photo-playing-baroque-flute&#34;&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m caught on a photo playing Baroque flute&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spent a fair amount of time playing the tin whistle, and some time on my recorders, but in the end gravitated toward the Baroque flute because it was mellower and I could draw less attention to my mistakes by playing it instead!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that a photo was taken that included me when I was playing my Baroque flute. In this photo, you can also see a guy playing tin whistle (this guy also at one point volunteered to sing a tune, and did so with quite a powerful voice, a great rendition).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://fbcdn-sphotos-a.akamaihd.net/hphotos-ak-ash2/35507_10150682067581513_55075526512_9775044_1738151368_n.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;A fellow tin whistle player, and me on Baroque flute&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My posture is really bad here. I need to sit up straight and keep my head over my body rather than straining over my neck. My only excuse is that this photo was probably taken two hours into the jam session when it was almost over, and I was having energy issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-note-on-energy-requirements&#34;&gt;A note on energy requirements&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was totally exhausted after the jam session. After Abby and I drove back home, we both had to eat something. We were starving. We should have taken a snack break at the jam session.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I weighed myself and I had lost weight. The mental demands on me were considerable, and I had really spent myself. Given that I have lost weight before when taking exams in school, or playing in chess tournaments, or doing similar activities that combine both mental demands and personal anxiety, I should have been better prepared with fuel at the event. I get the impression that I burn more energy by thinking hard than by running.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was my first time ever at a public music jam session, and I quite enjoyed it. I am grateful to Chris Norman and David Greenberg, and the Pittsburgh Renaissance and Baroque, for providing it to the community. I am always very happy for opportunities to play music with Abby, and keep remembering how she got me into this particular early traditional dance music world, through our first musical time together at the Holiday Ball.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got self-feedback about musical shortcomings for me to keep working on in order to enjoy future jam sessions, and I learned that I really need food to keep me fueled for optimal musicality!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Flute update: celebrating Bach&#39;s birthday, using a Thumbport, improvising to bossa nova</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/03/21/flute-update-celebrating-bachs-birthday/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Mar 2012 20:57:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/03/21/flute-update-celebrating-bachs-birthday/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s been eleven days since &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/10/flute-loving-it-again/&#34;&gt;my last blog post on my flute progress&lt;/a&gt;. During this time, there have been various changes in my life, including &lt;em&gt;radical&lt;/em&gt; changes in my musical life. It will take me a couple of additional blog posts to discuss these changes, but for now, I&amp;rsquo;ll talk only about today&amp;rsquo;s snapshot of my flute activity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2012-03-12&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-03-12)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had ended up &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/12/quitting-the-cmu-all-university-orchestra-one-of-the-hardest-decisions-in-my-life/&#34;&gt;quitting the CMU AUO&lt;/a&gt;, and then having a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/17/st-patricks-day-party-playing-tin-whistle-and-flute/&#34;&gt;wonderful musical experience a birthday party&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;thumbport&#34;&gt;Thumbport&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.thumbport.com/images/position.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Thumbport&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Today I received a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.thumbport.com/&#34;&gt;Thumbport II&lt;/a&gt; I ordered recently. It&amp;rsquo;s a snap-on device that helps with holding a flute, by making it easier to balance the flute on the right thumb, thereby decreasing rolling of the flute and pressure on the right pinkie finger. I tried it for the first time today and it seems useful. We&amp;rsquo;ll see if it helps a bit with my form and &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/07/flute-taking-a-break-while-clarifying-my-goals/&#34;&gt;injury issues&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;i-celebrated-the-327th-birthday-of-johann-sebastian-bach&#34;&gt;I celebrated the 327th birthday of Johann Sebastian Bach&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t follow celebrity birthdays, but I could not avoid hearing about the birthday of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Johann_Sebastian_Bach&#34;&gt;Johann Sebastian Bach, born in 1685&lt;/a&gt;, thanks to some music blogs I follow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How to celebrate? The last time I celebrated a composer&amp;rsquo;s birthday, it was last October, for Franz Liszt&amp;rsquo;s 200th birthday. Then, I listened to a piece of music by the composer and &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/22/happy-200th-birthday/&#34;&gt;wrote up my impressions of it&lt;/a&gt;. Today, I again had the option to read about Bach or his music, and but I mostly chose to play his music, in order to celebrate as &lt;em&gt;actively&lt;/em&gt; as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;playing-the-cello-suite-no-1-in-g-major-bwv-1007&#34;&gt;Playing the cello suite no. 1 in G major, BWV 1007&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I sight read a bunch of old Bach&amp;rsquo;s music that eventually I should practice seriously to play well, including various minuets and bourrées.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the main piece I sight read was the full &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cello_Suites_(Bach)&#34;&gt;cello suite&lt;/a&gt; no. 1 in G major, using an &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pjb.com.au/mus/arr.html&#34;&gt;arrangement for flute by Peter Billam&lt;/a&gt;. (I had actually obtained this a long time ago intending to play it on alto &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/recorder/&#34;&gt;recorder&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This music is deceptively simple but really quite beautiful. Even visually it is pleasing: check out Bach&amp;rsquo;s handwritten score:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/9/9c/Bachs1a.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Bach cello suite no. 1, first page&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h4 id=&#34;visual-animation&#34;&gt;Visual animation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, you must check out the following unconventional visual animated representation of this music (see the creator&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.chenalexander.com/2011/baroque-bach-cello/&#34;&gt;blog post about its construction&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe src=&#34;http://player.vimeo.com/video/31179423?title=0&amp;amp;byline=0&amp;amp;portrait=0&#34; width=&#34;400&#34; height=&#34;225&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen allowFullScreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://vimeo.com/31179423&#34;&gt;Baroque.me: J.S. Bach - Cello Suite No. 1 - Prelude&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href=&#34;http://vimeo.com/alexanderchen&#34;&gt;Alexander Chen&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&#34;http://vimeo.com&#34;&gt;Vimeo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;bossa-nova&#34;&gt;Bossa nova&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://s3.amazonaws.com/halleonard-closerlook/00843016/00843016FC.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Latin Jazz: 10 Latin Jazz Classics&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Today I also picked up from the public library another play-along score/CD set, this time a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.halleonard.com/product/viewproduct.do?itemid=843016&amp;amp;lid=1&amp;amp;keywords=latin&amp;amp;seriesfeature=JZPLYA&amp;amp;&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Latin jazz&amp;rdquo; collection&lt;/a&gt;. Apart from the famous mambo &amp;ldquo;Ran Kan Kan&amp;rdquo; by Tito Puente, the rest was actually bossa nova, which was what I got it for. Recently I decided to get more into playing jazz and working on improvisation. Since I love the harmonies and tunes of classic bossa nova, I decided this was a good place to get started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a lot of fun playing around with the accompaniment CD. Actually, I would also like to sing this music, but unlike with salsa and bolero, where I am completely comfortable singing in Spanish, I am not proficient in the Portuguese language and it trips me up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I just thought I&amp;rsquo;d provide a short update on some of my current musical activities, until I have time to write about the big changes I&amp;rsquo;ve made in my musical life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-musical-tangent-bach-s-goldberg-variations&#34;&gt;A musical tangent: Bach&amp;rsquo;s Goldberg Variations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In turns out there is a whole series of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.npr.org/blogs/deceptivecadence/148455347/goldberg-week&#34;&gt;posts on the NPR music blog about the Goldberg Variations&lt;/a&gt;. I could not resist dipping into this series, because I am a Goldberg geek. I would like someday to get good enough on piano to play much of it.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Flute: loving it again, remembering why I dance, and how I met my wife!</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/03/10/flute-loving-it-again/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Mar 2012 21:28:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/03/10/flute-loving-it-again/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, after four days of &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/07/flute-taking-a-break-while-clarifying-my-goals&#34;&gt;not even touching my (modern) flute&lt;/a&gt; and having spent the time having fun with my Baroque flute instead, I felt the urge to return to the modern flute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still have not regained the inclination to continue working on the orchestra music I still have to improve a lot on in the coming week, but I rediscovered the joy of simply playing my instrument.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;sound-intonation&#34;&gt;Sound, intonation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The perpetual challenges of getting clean sounds and accurate pitches on the Baroque flute in the past four days have given me an increased appreciation for the modern flute. I picked it up and spent time just trying to make beautiful sounds. Freed from the stress of orchestra practice, I felt much more relaxed on the instrument than I have for a while now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To my surprise (but not really), I have improved considerably on the flute after not playing it for four days. I really needed a break, a consolidation of lessons learned. My production of tones is much improved, and high notes are squeaking less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;music-for-dance&#34;&gt;Music for dance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing I&amp;rsquo;ve truly come to realize is that I particularly enjoy playing rhythmic music suitable for dancing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, every time I attend a dance, and there is live music, I experience a strange internal conflict: I do like to dance, but sometimes, I&amp;rsquo;d rather be on the other side of the dance floor, being the musical performer! The &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; time I&amp;rsquo;ve been on the other side has been at last year&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburghcontra.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Contras and Squares&lt;/a&gt; Holiday Ball.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most recent instance of my wishing I could sometimes stop dancing and just join the musicians has been at the local &lt;a href=&#34;http://coalcountry.org/frenchdance.html&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh French dance workshop and social&lt;/a&gt;, where we&amp;rsquo;ve had live piano, fiddle, and of course, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~gdyke/&#34;&gt;Gregory&lt;/a&gt; on his Irish flute. I wonder whether at some point I might be qualified to play for the event, using either my modern flute or Baroque flute. (By the way, it was held again today, but unfortunately, Abby and I chose not to go because we had too many things to do this weekend.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;remembering-dancing&#34;&gt;Remembering dancing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday I spent time playing along to a score/CD set I&amp;rsquo;ve mentioned before, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/World-Music-Cuba-Flute-play-along/dp/3702465804&#34;&gt;World Music Cuba&lt;/a&gt;. While playing the bolero, cha cha, and mambo pieces in particular, I felt I was returning &amp;ldquo;home&amp;rdquo; in many ways. This was among the first music I heard and saw people dancing to when I was curious and visited the &lt;a href=&#34;http://cmubdc.org/&#34;&gt;CMU Ballroom Dance Club&lt;/a&gt; in 2000, and fell in love with, and learned to dance to. I also played along to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Play-along-Argentina-Flute-World-Music/dp/3702465871&#34;&gt;World Music Argentina&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;some-photos-of-my-ballroom-dance-days&#34;&gt;Some photos of my ballroom dance days&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some photos of me dancing in 2002 with my last dance partner, Amy, before I quit competitive ballroom dancing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here we are at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dcdancesportinferno.com/&#34;&gt;DC DanceSport Inferno&lt;/a&gt; in 2002 doing a hockey stick in international rumba:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/ballroom/dcdi-2002-hockey-stick.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Amy and Franklin at DCDI 2002 in rumba&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And here were are at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://comp.cornelldancesport.org/&#34;&gt;Cornell DanceSport Classic&lt;/a&gt; in 2002 in cha cha, rumba, and tango:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/ballroom/cornell-2002-new-yorker.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Amy and Franklin at Cornell 2002 in cha cha&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/ballroom/cornell-2002-hockey-stick.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Amy and Franklin at Cornell 2002 in rumba&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/ballroom/cornell-2002-tango-promenade.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Amy and Franklin at Cornell 2002 in tango&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;dancing-with-abby&#34;&gt;Dancing with Abby&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But never mind the ballroom dance days. It was through salsa dancing that I met my wife!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;how-i-met-abby&#34;&gt;How I met Abby&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was through dancing that I met Abby in the first place. After quitting dancing in 2003, I never danced again until late 2006, when my friend Jon told me he had recently started salsa dancing (because of a girlfriend who got him into it) and invited me to join him at a free outdoors dance, and I went. Then as I re-entered the Pittsburgh salsa dance scene, I kept running into Abby.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;some-photos-of-us-dancing-salsa&#34;&gt;Some photos of us dancing salsa&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are not many photos of Abby dancing with me, because when I&amp;rsquo;m dancing, I&amp;rsquo;m not holding my camera, but here are some photos a friend took at a big salsa dance weekend at the Palisades in McKeesport in April 2008, a year after we started dating in 2007.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/palisades-2008/abby-franklin.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby and Franklin dancing salsa at Palisades&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/palisades-2008/abby-franklin-hair.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby and Franklin dancing salsa at Palisades, hair flying&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;expression-and-improvisation-in-dance-and-in-music&#34;&gt;Expression and improvisation in dance and in music&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;dance&#34;&gt;Dance&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One reason I gave up ballroom dancing was that I felt there was an overemphasis on &amp;ldquo;syllabus steps&amp;rdquo; (I realize this is an oversimplification of the ballroom dance culture; all very good ballroom dancers go beyond the syllabus mindset). After quitting ballroom dancing, I explored Argentine tango, which is all about improvisation, but I left it because (at the time) it seemed that most of the women in the local scene were very tall, which made dancing awkward for me. I got into salsa because freed from the closed embrace, there was clearly a lot of room for personal improvisation. Ironically, I first got into making stuff up as a result of my imperfect memory: I could never memorize long choreography of step patterns, whether I was doing ballroom dancing or anything else. So I would always make a &amp;ldquo;mistake&amp;rdquo;, then I would make something out of the mistake. I learned that as long as you get back in time with the music, and keep the lead and follow communication strong, there is no such thing really as a mistake. You just keep going, with whatever is happening at the present moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I now have a long-term goal of developing my technique and releasing my inhibitions so that I can improvise musically at will. Yesterday, I played with improvising when playing bolero, cha cha, and tango. It was a lot of fun and profoundly satisfying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;music&#34;&gt;Music&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I actually credit my study of the recorder and the Baroque flute for reawakening me to my dream of free expression and improvisation. Baroque music leaves room for a lot of interpretation of trills and ornamentation and articulation (subject, of course, to &amp;ldquo;good taste&amp;rdquo;). I want to go beyond that, but it has been a great starting point. For some reason, too much exposure to later music (such as Beethoven) had turned me into a score-reader, since such later music has so much already marked up for the performer to simply &lt;em&gt;obey&lt;/em&gt;. The sparse annotations in Renaissance and Baroque music give one much more freedom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am enjoying playing the flute again, now that I know what I really want to do with it. And I would like to merge my dance and music lives, just as Abby has always played the Balkan music she also dances to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2012-03-12&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-03-12)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ended up &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/12/quitting-the-cmu-all-university-orchestra-one-of-the-hardest-decisions-in-my-life/&#34;&gt;quitting the CMU AUO&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2013-01-26&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-01-26)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost a year later, I finally played tangos on flute &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/26/music-i-just-played-for-the-first-time-recorder-sonata-tangos/&#34;&gt;at a party&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2013-03-17&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-03-17)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost exactly a year later, I ended up playing selections from the World Music Cuba book &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/17/finally-doing-some-latin-music-jamming-on-flute/&#34;&gt;at a party&lt;/a&gt;, and improvising freely with two other guys!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>