<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Beatles on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/beatles/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Beatles on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/beatles/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Steel City Ukuleles: a nice session on playing by ear</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/11/06/steel-city-ukuleles-a-nice-session-on-playing-by-ear/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Nov 2013 21:20:29 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/11/06/steel-city-ukuleles-a-nice-session-on-playing-by-ear/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s been three (rather than the usual two, because of the nature of the twice-a-month scheduling) weeks since &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/10/16/steel-city-ukuleles-back-to-plain-good-fun/&#34;&gt;my last meeting of the Steel City Ukuleles&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was definitely starting to miss the group meeting, and was happy to attend &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/Steel-City-Ukuleles/events/132647952/&#34;&gt;tonight&lt;/a&gt;, although I have to confess I did enjoy having more time to work on my own ukulele musical projects (rather than practicing the meetup music).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;playing-by-ear&#34;&gt;Playing by ear&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Renee had volunteered to lead a session including basic practice for &lt;em&gt;playing by ear&lt;/em&gt;, a very important skill that many of us coming from the &amp;ldquo;written score&amp;rdquo; orientation of music need work on. That obviously includes me. I&amp;rsquo;m always astounded when going to jam sessions and seeing and hearing musicians do amazing things who barely read music, for example. The &lt;em&gt;freedom&lt;/em&gt; and flexible facility is just obvious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, we started easy, doing songs with only two chords, then moved to three, then four. We did this in four different keys. For me, amusingly, it was a good thing that I didn&amp;rsquo;t actually know most of the songs, so I had to pick them up in real time (or more accurately, partially in real time, then repair mistaken guesses after fumbling through the first repetition).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I very much appreciated the session on playing by ear. There is no reason I can&amp;rsquo;t work on this by myself at home, of course, using various techniques. I have done some of this, but not as systematically as I should, so after tonight, I decided to spend &lt;em&gt;every&lt;/em&gt; future musical practice session (regardless of instrument) doing something without any written music. I consider playing by ear to be a critical component of what I want to get out of music in my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;beatles&#34;&gt;Beatles&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rest of the time we had a Beatles-themed program of songs. I found these tricky because of the sometimes strange chord changes (&amp;ldquo;strange&amp;rdquo; relative to most of the stuff we play).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;ending-a-little-early&#34;&gt;Ending a little early&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We ended a little early because a subset of us were scheduled to use the time to rehearse for a recording session coming up. (I had not volunteered for this gig when it was announced along with the Ecofest gig that I did do.)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>