<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Sociology on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/sociology/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Sociology on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/sociology/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Some good science-based reading for Election Day, whether or not you voted</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/04/some-good-science-based-reading-for-election-day/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2014 15:41:25 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/04/some-good-science-based-reading-for-election-day/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/11/01/how-i-avoid-demotivating-myself-away-from-voting/&#34;&gt;I voted&lt;/a&gt; today, on Election Day in the US.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/franklinmingchen/15527007380&#34; title=&#34;IMG_20141104_153326 by Franklin Chen, on Flickr&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7496/15527007380_abfb7f5691.jpg&#34; width=&#34;375&#34; height=&#34;500&#34; alt=&#34;IMG_20141104_153326&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, now is as good a time as any for some interesting articles about politics and voting. Here are some that came my way:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;motive-attribution-asymmetry&#34;&gt;Motive attribution asymmetry&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/oliver-burkeman-column/2014/nov/04/get-along-enemies-motive-attribution&#34;&gt;Oliver Burkeman&lt;/a&gt; discusses a study that shows that you argue that your side is motivated by &lt;em&gt;love&lt;/em&gt;, while the other side is motivated by &lt;em&gt;hate&lt;/em&gt;. But since the other side thinks the same, what is the &amp;ldquo;truth&amp;rdquo;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;One of the reasons it’s so hard to accept the notion that our enemies might be motivated by love, I suspect, is because that conclusion seems to suggest that our enemies’ cause must therefore have merit.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Actually, those two issues are completely unrelated.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I agree with this: it is quite possible (I&amp;rsquo;m not saying it&amp;rsquo;s always the case) for someone you disagree with to have the most loving intentions, but simply be &lt;em&gt;mistaken&lt;/em&gt; rather than &lt;em&gt;evil&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;dangers-of-accurate-statistical-prediction-by-data-journalism&#34;&gt;Dangers of accurate statistical prediction by data journalism&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A good article in the Berkeley Journal of Sociology about &lt;a href=&#34;http://berkeleyjournal.org/2014/11/what-should-the-fox-say/&#34;&gt;Nate Silver&amp;rsquo;s statistical journalism&lt;/a&gt; argues that data journalism should focus on understanding rather than prediction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;This extensive use of Big Data for election forecasting passively promotes our current sense of political fatalism.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;If our politicians can’t risk making public appearances or trying to appear human without navigating at least three levels of performative irony, then our political culture has entered a state of structural crisis.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;emotions-of-election-day-asymmetric-hedonic-response&#34;&gt;Emotions of Election Day: asymmetric hedonic response&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://harvardmagazine.com/2014/11/emotions-of-elections-study-todd-rogers&#34;&gt;Harvard Kennedy School research result&lt;/a&gt; on asymmetric hedonic response: after an election, losing makes you far sadder than winning makes you happy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I confess to having been really bummed out fairly often in the past two decades of voting. I&amp;rsquo;ve been trying to be more detached.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;in-praise-of-the-occasional-voter&#34;&gt;In praise of the occasional voter&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, some people make fun of people who do not vote (I never do this; there are often quite rational reasons to avoid voting). Here&amp;rsquo;s an interesting article arguing that the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2014/11/02/upshot/the-vital-role-of-the-occasional-voter.html&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;occasional voter&amp;rdquo; is actually quite valuable&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From an economics point of view, &amp;ldquo;voting is a classic example of a free-rider problem&amp;rdquo; because the possible gain for each individual is so tiny, statistically, that it may not make sense to go out of one&amp;rsquo;s way to vote.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, voting has an interesting cost to the voter: &amp;ldquo;The very act of voting for a given candidate or party ties us mentally to that candidate and inadvertently costs us some measure of our neutrality.&amp;rdquo; This is because we &lt;em&gt;rationalize&lt;/em&gt; what we do in order to resolve our &lt;em&gt;cognitive dissonance&lt;/em&gt; about the apparent pointlessness of voting. We try to fool ourselves into thinking we did something really important. &amp;ldquo;We don’t just choose what we like; we like more and more what we choose.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the &amp;ldquo;occasional voter&amp;rdquo; can be an outsider not subject to cognitive dissonance as much as the regular and party-registered voter, countering partisanship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, it could be argued that partisanship, and the resulting gridlock, is good. But is it? That&amp;rsquo;s another topic entirely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-strange-sameness-of-political-candidates-in-the-face-of-competition&#34;&gt;The strange sameness of political candidates in the face of competition&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Conversable Economist, Timothy Taylor, offered an explanation for &lt;a href=&#34;http://conversableeconomist.blogspot.com/2014/11/the-excessive-sameness-of-politics-and.html&#34;&gt;why politicians end up in the same squishy middle&lt;/a&gt;, based on &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Harold_Hotelling&#34;&gt;Hotelling&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s famous 1929 mathematical model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Mainstream politicians thus face a continual dynamic where they seek to reassure their more ardent partisans that they are on their side, while shading and tacking as needed to pick up voters in the middle.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, if you are interested in more mathematical modeling, check out Scott Page&amp;rsquo;s free MOOC on &amp;ldquo;model thinking&amp;rdquo;, which I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/06/16/review-of-coursera-course-model-thinking/&#34;&gt;reviewed here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;bloggers-reactions-to-election-day&#34;&gt;Bloggers&amp;rsquo; reactions to Election Day&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a blogger I follow, &lt;a href=&#34;http://ayjay.tumblr.com/post/101755797073/and-one-more-note-on-politics&#34;&gt;Alan Jacobs, on his options&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/the-fix/wp/2013/05/09/people-hate-congress-but-most-incumbents-get-re-elected-what-gives/&#34;&gt;People hate Congress, but 90% of incumbents get re-elected&lt;/a&gt;. &amp;ldquo;The message from voters to Congress? Throw the bums out. But not my bum.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope you enjoyed this taste of research results concerning psychology, sociology, and economics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not staying up to watch the returns from today&amp;rsquo;s election. I did what I did, and it&amp;rsquo;s over for me until next May.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Did you learn anything surprising in the links I shared here? Is there anything that will change how you think or behave when it comes to politics?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>