<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Global Climate Change on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/global-climate-change/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Global Climate Change on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/global-climate-change/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Thoughts on an unexpected winter barefoot run</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/01/20/thoughts-on-an-unexpected-winter-barefoot-run/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Jan 2013 08:14:12 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/01/20/thoughts-on-an-unexpected-winter-barefoot-run/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/barefoot-running-winter.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Barefoot running in winter&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, I went on my first ever &lt;em&gt;winter barefoot run&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; what you think; or maybe, it &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; what you think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;sunny-day&#34;&gt;Sunny day&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, there was still some snow on the ground. But it was purely residual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a sunny day. A &lt;em&gt;warm&lt;/em&gt; day, temperature of about 53 degrees F.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Originally I had planned to go for a run like I did a couple of days ago, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/17/winter-running-in-vibram-fivefingers-shoes-revisited/&#34;&gt;in Vibram FiveFingers shoes&lt;/a&gt;. But I changed my mind when I realized just how warm it was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Impulsively, I just hopped out the door in my short-sleeve T-shirt and shorts, and &lt;em&gt;barefoot&lt;/em&gt;, because it seemed that I could. What other winter have I had, during my lifetime spent in the northern United States, when I could go out running barefoot?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-run&#34;&gt;The run&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ended up running less than about three miles, because I faced some annoyances:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the roads and sidewalks were actually pretty cold&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;there was a lot of debris out there (ouch!), left behind after the snow melted; some of it was clearly salt crystals&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;putting-on-shoes&#34;&gt;Putting on shoes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ended up going back home and putting on my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/26/walking-and-running-in-invisible-shoes-a-review&#34;&gt;Xero Shoes (4mm Connect)&lt;/a&gt; that have become my favorite running footwear (when the weather allows; I stopped wearing them last fall shortly after the Great Race 10K, which was &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/30/running-my-10th-great-race-10k-obscene-but-in-a-good-way/&#34;&gt;my first race running in them&lt;/a&gt;). I felt much better wearing these huaraches and went back out to run another three miles.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/xero-shoes-winter.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Xero Shoes 4mm Connect&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;somber-thoughts&#34;&gt;Somber thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a good time running outside as though it were spring or fall, but actually, I get worried every time this winter I am able to do something like this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s not normal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it&amp;rsquo;s not good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wunderground.com/blog/weatherhistorian/comment.html?entrynum=112&#34;&gt;2012 was a record warm year for the continental United States&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s not pleasant contemplating &lt;a href=&#34;http://climate.nasa.gov/&#34;&gt;global climate change&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s been nice being able to run in winter here in Pittsburgh without being all bundled up. But that is a constant reminder to me that something weird has been happening to our planet.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>