<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Health on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/health/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Health on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/health/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>World Toilet Day is not just another crappy holiday</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/19/world-toilet-day-is-not-just-another-crappy-holiday/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2014 23:41:34 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/19/world-toilet-day-is-not-just-another-crappy-holiday/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;From an excellent blog I follow, Timothy Taylor&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://conversableeconomist.blogspot.com/&#34;&gt;Conversable Economist&lt;/a&gt;, I read his &lt;a href=&#34;http://conversableeconomist.blogspot.com/2014/11/world-toilet-day.html&#34;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; about &lt;a href=&#34;http://worldtoilet.org/&#34;&gt;World Toilet Day&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, every day is some kind of observed day somewhere in the world promoted by someone, but World Toilet Day is not just another crappy commercial holiday. It&amp;rsquo;s about a serious problem, which is that 15 percent of the world population still lives without proper sanitation. Open sanitation, especially in densely populated areas, is a cause of much serious illness (especially to children, who are especially vulnerable). So I&amp;rsquo;m happy about the invention of World Toilet Day in 2001 by the World Toilet Organization global non-profit. It&amp;rsquo;s curious that I hadn&amp;rsquo;t heard about it for thirteen years, but I&amp;rsquo;m grateful Timothy Taylor pointed it out in his blog. Because this is a serious issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I, for one, am grateful to live in the industrialized US where toilets abound everywhere, and even in parks such as my local Frick Park in Pittsburgh, there are port-a-potties in various locations within the park. I used to make fun of my immigrant parents for being strangely fixated on and happy about functioning and clean toilets, but the reality is that their generation and their parents&amp;rsquo; generation in rural Taiwan did not necessarily have this luxury. In fact, even today, apparently, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ketagalanmedia.com/2014/09/03/dreaming-odor-free-bathroom-taiwan/&#34;&gt;the sewage system is not great in Taiwan&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why I was so happy to run 5 miles in 63 minutes today when I was doing it in 50 earlier this year</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/08/13/why-i-was-so-happy-to-run-5-miles-in-63-minutes-today-when-i-was-doing-it-in-50-earlier-this-year/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Aug 2013 21:18:29 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/08/13/why-i-was-so-happy-to-run-5-miles-in-63-minutes-today-when-i-was-doing-it-in-50-earlier-this-year/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I went for a run in Frick Park, my usual 5-mile route, which I haven&amp;rsquo;t done in a while. It took me 63 minutes. Earlier this year I was doing it in 50. My fitness is pretty low right now, as &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/08/10/emerging-from-my-three-months-of-illness-self-pitying-and-self-loathing/&#34;&gt;I explained three days ago&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I&amp;rsquo;m happy to be on the upswing. I&amp;rsquo;m getting out there, not pushing too hard, but challenging myself. I have faith that I will get back out of my slump. I have done this before. Other people have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you also have this experience of being happy to do something worse than you used to do it, because you&amp;rsquo;re doing it at all rather than doing nothing?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Emerging from my three months of illness, self-pitying, and self-loathing</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/08/10/emerging-from-my-three-months-of-illness-self-pitying-and-self-loathing/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Aug 2013 08:39:23 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/08/10/emerging-from-my-three-months-of-illness-self-pitying-and-self-loathing/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, I reported on my feelings after &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/08/09/getting-up-when-reality-punches-you-in-the-face-running-the-second-liberty-mile-in-pittsburgh/&#34;&gt;having a very painful and embarrassing performance in the Liberty Mile road race&lt;/a&gt;. I resolved to slowly return myself to health and fitness, starting &lt;em&gt;immediately&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, Leo Babauta wrote a great blog post that really spoke to me, &lt;a href=&#34;http://zenhabits.net/fraud/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Fear of Being Found a Fraud&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. Basically, he writes advice, but he&amp;rsquo;s not perfect, and doesn&amp;rsquo;t always successfully do what he preaches. I periodically have feelings like that, since I write about stuff too and also post &amp;ldquo;advice&amp;rdquo; links on Twitter, Facebook, and Google+. What would people think if they knew I have been failing myself in the past three months?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, I have to be honest. There&amp;rsquo;s no point lying. I sometimes &lt;em&gt;know&lt;/em&gt; what&amp;rsquo;s best and what has worked for me, but don&amp;rsquo;t take my own advice. This in itself is not the big problem. The real problem is the second-order problem, which is that of believing that I&amp;rsquo;m not only imperfect (we all are), but sometimes ending also deciding to give up on myself. That&amp;rsquo;s the worst thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, after health conditions disrupted my &amp;ldquo;normal&amp;rdquo; routines, I ended up not getting back on track when in fact I should and could have, through a gradual process. In a way, I was too proud to &lt;em&gt;adapt to reality&lt;/em&gt;. I was willing to operate under a different, better reality, but given the worse one, I chickened out, and entered a downward spiral of bad habits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;meditation-habit-destroyed&#34;&gt;Meditation habit, destroyed&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/02/01/a-report-on-one-month-of-daily-meditation/&#34;&gt;restarted a daily meditation practice for the new year&lt;/a&gt;, and entered into a 100-day meditation challenge. I encountered setbacks in my first month, but kept bouncing back. I even &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/01/dealing-with-setbacks-during-my-second-month-of-meditation/&#34;&gt;continued into a second month&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then things got worse, and as you can see in the archives to my blog, I &lt;em&gt;never wrote a report for the third month&lt;/em&gt;. According to my &lt;a href=&#34;http://insighttimer.com/&#34;&gt;Insight Timer&lt;/a&gt; journal, I actually did meditate in March almost every day, so I could have written a blog post on that, but I didn&amp;rsquo;t. &lt;em&gt;That was a mistake&lt;/em&gt;. I have found that public updates on progress keep me more accountable to myself; this is why I have written so much about my personal musical activities: not only to share my journey with those who are interested (because they are friends or because they are themselves on their own journeys), but also to keep myself honest about where I&amp;rsquo;ve been, what I still need to do, where I intend to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In April, my meditation practice started to fall apart. I missed April 10 and 11, then 13, 14, 15, then 18, 19, 20, 20, 23, and the rest of the month. In May I was erratic, till after May 13, &lt;em&gt;I completely stopped identifying myself as a &amp;ldquo;meditator&amp;rdquo; and quit&lt;/em&gt;. That&amp;rsquo;s right: I felt so ashamed of myself that I did not meditate between May 14 and August 9 this year. Big mistake, this pointless shame, especially given that I know, empirically, that &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/30/when-i-dont-have-time-to-sit-and-breathe-something-is-wrong-with-my-life/&#34;&gt;when I don&amp;rsquo;t &amp;ldquo;have time&amp;rdquo; to meditate, something is wrong with my life&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;exercise&#34;&gt;Exercise&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, my exercise schedule completely fell apart. &amp;ldquo;Normally&amp;rdquo;, I run every other day and do strength training the other days. None of this has to be a super-long session. Just enough to keep me mentally and physically alert. My strength training has generally been just a simple half-hour &amp;ldquo;core performance&amp;rdquo; type of workout at home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, I lost the habit, partially because marathon training caused me to cut back on strength training and because after the marathon, I took a break from running. The big lesson I learned here is that marathoning is very disruptive to my ordinary life, and I do not plan to ever do a marathon again in my life. But apart from that, I had non-marathon disruptions also, such as the skin rash after a hike that I&amp;rsquo;ve been dealing with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-i-did-today&#34;&gt;What I did today&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Today is the first day of the rest of my life.&lt;/strong&gt; Clean slate, forget the past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I meditated this morning. And I will continue to make this a high priority and do it daily. I must make sure that if I slip, I simply get back on track, rather than feel shame or whatever. It must simply be a habit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I ran yesterday, today was a non-running day. I decided that one way to prevent myself from completely slipping is to have a backup &amp;ldquo;very short&amp;rdquo; workout in case any kind of laziness or disruption causes me to think about just canceling a workout rather than do a longer one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So today was my first experiment with a &lt;a href=&#34;http://medium.com/editors-picks/e4975b151181&#34;&gt;7-minute workout&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s intense, but fast to get over with. I highly recommend checking it out!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are more links to this type of workout:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://journals.lww.com/acsm-healthfitness/Fulltext/2013/05000/HIGH_INTENSITY_CIRCUIT_TRAINING_USING_BODY_WEIGHT_.5.aspx&#34;&gt;Journal paper&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://7minworkoutapp.com/&#34;&gt;Online app&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifehack.org/articles/lifestyle/master-the-7-minute-workout-with-this-video.html&#34;&gt;Lifehack article&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if you&amp;rsquo;re lazy, surely you have 7 minutes a day to squeeze in this little circuit. I did!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-future&#34;&gt;The future&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back to meditating every day, just 10 minutes a day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I&amp;rsquo;m going to take it easy to ramp back up to fitness. I know it&amp;rsquo;s going to take &lt;em&gt;months&lt;/em&gt; to get back to where I was earlier in the year. &lt;em&gt;Patience is a virtue&lt;/em&gt;. I will start small. A little bit of slow running every other day, and the 7-minute workout every other day, to get started, before extending further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was time to stop my descent into endless self-pitying and self-loathing over all the misfortunes that have come my way in the past months. I&amp;rsquo;m taking my life back.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reflections on Food Day</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/10/24/reflections-on-food-day/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Oct 2012 22:38:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/10/24/reflections-on-food-day/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/food-day-2012-breakfast-1.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Soup and veggies&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A year ago I celebrated &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.foodday.org/&#34;&gt;Food Day&lt;/a&gt; for the first time, by sharing &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/24/every-day-is-food-day/&#34;&gt;some reflections on what food means to me&lt;/a&gt;. Today I review my reflections and some more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;buying-food&#34;&gt;Buying food&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I still take care to shop carefully for groceries and make our own tasty meals to eat. Some of our sources:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://kretschmannfarm.com/&#34;&gt;Kretschmann Farm&lt;/a&gt; CSA subscription for local produce&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.localharvest.org/miseras-organic-farm-M14896&#34;&gt;Misera&amp;rsquo;s Organic Farm&lt;/a&gt; for local &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/24/whats-a-nice-acorn-squash-like-you-doing-in-a-pot-of-spicy-lentils/&#34;&gt;chickens&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lewisfamilyfarms.com/&#34;&gt;Lewis Family Farms&lt;/a&gt; for local beef&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://pine-richland.patch.com/articles/stoney-lane-farm-a-little-bit-country-in-suburbia&#34;&gt;Stoney Lane Farm&lt;/a&gt; for local &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/28/thankful-for-the-free-range-orange-yolked-eggs/&#34;&gt;eggs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.traderjoes.com/&#34;&gt;Trader Joe&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.eastendfood.coop/&#34;&gt;East End Food Co-op&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our food choices are based on our concerns for both &lt;em&gt;health&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;sustainability&lt;/em&gt;. Our choices may have an impact on one or the other or both.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;cooking&#34;&gt;Cooking&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I started my blog over a year ago, I had thought I would be posting more about cooking, since I was doing a good amount of it, but as it turned out, during this year (2012), Abby took over almost all of the cooking for us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;diet&#34;&gt;Diet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both Abby and I have experimented in paleo directions in the past year. As a reminder, this doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean that we&amp;rsquo;re just going around chowing down on all the meat we can eat. It does mean that we have&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;considerably increased our consumption of vegetables&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;increased our consumption of various fats and oils&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;reduced our consumption of carbs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-question-of-carbs&#34;&gt;The question of carbs&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What we seemed to discover was that we needed some base level of carbs in order to maintain energy and weight levels. Through experimentation, Abby has focused on getting carbs through potatoes and sweet potatoes primarily, going almost completely off wheat. I, on the other hand, am still hooked on rice; I also still eat some wheat, but frankly, I can tell from the effects that I would probably do best to eliminate it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;rice-disaster&#34;&gt;Rice disaster?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, I wondered about brown rice, and even briefly experimented with &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/07/is-brown-rice-healthy-or-not/&#34;&gt;switching to white rice&lt;/a&gt;. The white rice experiment was a fast failure: the high glycemic index and lack of fiber didn&amp;rsquo;t help me at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More recently, there have been reports of &lt;em&gt;brown rice&lt;/em&gt; in particular having &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.consumerreports.org/cro/magazine/2012/11/arsenic-in-your-food/index.htm&#34;&gt;high levels of arsenic&lt;/a&gt;. This is rather disturbing, and Abby and I have agreed that I need to quickly re-evaluate my consumption of brown rice. I&amp;rsquo;ve committed to trying out some alternative source of calories/fiber.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-breakfast&#34;&gt;My breakfast&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My breakfast has remained fairly &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/01/26/improving-my-breakfast-and-other-meals/&#34;&gt;stable&lt;/a&gt; since &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/23/paleo-diet-experimentation/&#34;&gt;I quit oatmeal&lt;/a&gt;. Basically, I eat&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;veggies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;eggs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;nuts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a prune&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Depending on how I feel and what&amp;rsquo;s available, occasionally I&amp;rsquo;ll eat some bacon or fish, and sometimes I&amp;rsquo;ll add some sweet potatoes or other carbs, but typically that&amp;rsquo;s it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(I stopped the flax seeds, largely out of inconvenience of grinding them!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s what I happened to eat today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/food-day-2012-breakfast-1.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Soup and veggies&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/food-day-2012-breakfast-2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Eggs&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The soup and veggies were leftovers from big batches Abby or I had made earlier:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;my cauliflower leaf soup with garlic, carrots, sweet potatoes, curry powder, extra virgin olive oil&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;my stir-fried cauliflower florets with garlic, green peppers, coconut oil&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Abby&amp;rsquo;s spaghetti squash with onion and other stuff&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And on top of that I also ate two fried eggs with walnuts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-lunch-and-dinner&#34;&gt;My lunch and dinner&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lunch and dinner were combinations of various leftovers, all originally made by Abby (hence my not knowing the exact ingredients):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ground beef stew with green peppers, jalapeno, onion, various seasoning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;slow-cooked chicken with veggies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;leftover kale and onion&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;dinner included sauteed zucchini and other veggies Abby cooked tonight&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;brown rice&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;fasting&#34;&gt;Fasting&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes I deliberately fast for a meal or two. This happens when I just don&amp;rsquo;t feel all that hungry. I treat that as a signal from my body that I don&amp;rsquo;t really need to eat. My experiments have convinced me that &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Intermittent_fasting&#34;&gt;intermittent fasting&lt;/a&gt; helps with fat loss and mental clarity. It also helps me remember to be grateful, when I do eat again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are human beings, not robots. We need food. And food isn&amp;rsquo;t just &amp;ldquo;fuel&amp;rdquo;. It lives or has lived. It is complex. I am grateful to be living in a land of plenty, and that Abby has taken so much care to make varied and tasty dishes for us. But as the recent reports on arsenic reminds me, there is much we must continue to do to prevent the degradation of what we eat.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CMU Fitness Challenge keynote lecture by Vonda Wright: Stay strong at any age</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/01/20/cmu-fitness-challenge-keynote-lecture-by-vonda-wright-stay-strong-at-any-age/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Jan 2012 22:32:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/01/20/cmu-fitness-challenge-keynote-lecture-by-vonda-wright-stay-strong-at-any-age/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://athletics.cmu.edu/athletics/directory/headshots/vonda_wright_hs.jpg?max_height=200&amp;amp;max_width=150&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Dr. Vonda Wright&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I attended a &lt;a href=&#34;http://athletics.cmu.edu/generalnews/2011-2012/vondawright&#34;&gt;much-anticipated talk at CMU&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.drvondawright.com/&#34;&gt;Dr. Vonda Wright&lt;/a&gt; of UPMC in McConomy Auditorium, given to the CMU community as a keynote lecture for the CMU Fitness Challenge I participate in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Dr. Wright is an orthopedic surgeon at UPMC and an author and researcher. She focuses on the master athlete and living a healthy lifestyle, having conducted extensive research on the benefits of remaining active throughout one&amp;rsquo;s lifetime.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a fascinating and inspiring talk! Dr. Wright was a high-energy speaker, very passionate and direct. She spoke on many topics, actually, not just about physical exercise. And she spoke frankly about personal experiences in her life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;focus-on-over-40&#34;&gt;Focus on over 40&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Wright was particularly speaking to the older staff members in attendance. She argued that there was no reason one should not remain strong and vital well into what some might consider old age. She indicated that research showed that significant decline does not need to kick in until the &amp;ldquo;cutoff&amp;rdquo; point of age 70, which is when it seems that even very health people start a significant downward slope.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She said that as someone going on age 45 (she certainly looked a lot more fit than most people that age!), she learned that there is not enough research on active people over age 40, because of a bias in favor of studying young athletes. The result is that people have made wrong assumptions about what it is like to grow older.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Her favorite phrase seems to be &amp;ldquo;bash your bones&amp;rdquo;: she emphasized that weight-bearing exercise is particularly important and stimulating for older people. She showed photos of how inactivity can result in &amp;ldquo;fat in muscle&amp;rdquo; (yuck).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;business-principles&#34;&gt;Business principles&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One interesting perspective she wanted to share was that she urged us to apply &amp;ldquo;business principles&amp;rdquo; to our personal health: after all, if we pay a lot of attention to our careers and jobs, how come we don&amp;rsquo;t treat our own health as a serious job too? Furthermore, it&amp;rsquo;s not just our physical health, narrowly construed: she asked, &amp;ldquo;What do we really want?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without plans, she said, we are just laying bricks, not building a movement. Whatever we take seriously, we must think ahead five to ten years, and do nothing that is not part of the goal. We must learn to say &amp;ldquo;No&amp;rdquo; to what is unimportant. If we focus on what is most important to us, &amp;ldquo;everything else falls into place&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She told a personal story illustrating what she meant. She had an opportunity at one point in her career to just continue working hard and become chair of the department. But she realized she didn&amp;rsquo;t want to be chair and followed her own path instead, choosing what interested her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;books&#34;&gt;Books&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Wright openly promoted &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.drvondawright.com/fitness-author/&#34;&gt;her books&lt;/a&gt; throughout the talk. I made a note to look them up at the library.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought it was great that CMU had Dr. Vonda Wright come give a talk for the CMU Fitness Challenge this year. Many ideas she shared, I found inspirational. And as a master athlete herself, she is a great role model.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is brown rice healthy or not?</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/12/07/is-brown-rice-healthy-or-not/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Dec 2011 23:48:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/12/07/is-brown-rice-healthy-or-not/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been thinking for a year or two now about my relationship with rice, in conjunction with reading about &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/23/paleo-diet-experimentation/&#34;&gt;paleo diets&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;ve been eating rice, white or brown, for most of my life, and am now considering make some further changes to my diet (beyond &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/03/one-of-these-breakfasts-is-not-paleo/&#34;&gt;giving up oatmeal&lt;/a&gt; for an entire month now).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what now with rice?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;white-rice&#34;&gt;White rice&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was a kid, I ate white rice often, because it was something my mother provided for most meals. Actually, it was present for me at almost all meals, until I decided I wanted to eat, all the time, the sweet breakfast cereals I saw on TV.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I went off to college, I drastically changed my diet, being dependent on cafeteria food and also being tempted by opportunities to eat pizza and chicken wings and the like outside of the provided meals. I ate much less rice then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While in grad school at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cmu.edu/&#34;&gt;CMU&lt;/a&gt;, I got back into eating white rice, as a result of developing the habit of eating Indian food for lunch: I would buy lunch from either the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.tasteofindiapittsburgh.com/&#34;&gt;Taste of India&lt;/a&gt; present on campus or from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.srees.com/&#34;&gt;Sree&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/a&gt; food truck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;brown-rice-for-five-years&#34;&gt;Brown rice for five years&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For many years, I kept hearing that brown rice was healthier than white rice, and this advice was based on the idea that white rice has lost many of its nutrients and fiber during the refinement process. But I never ate brown rice because every time I tried making it, it came out unpalatable. Eventually I learned that I was making it wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2006, after hearing too often from a friend that white rice was &amp;ldquo;white death&amp;rdquo;, I took the plunge and bought a fancy Zojirushi Neuro Fuzzy rice cooker, to be able to make good brown rice as well as start eating steel cut oatmeal (which my friend also advocated eating). So it&amp;rsquo;s been over five years since I have been eating a lot of oatmeal (recently stopped) and brown rice (still going). And I have to confess that if one is going to eat steel cut oatmeal or brown rice, the Neuro Fuzzy cooker is the way to go, with its timer functions that make it trivial to generate really good results!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;paleo&#34;&gt;Paleo&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enter the paleo movement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started reading that maybe brown rice isn&amp;rsquo;t so healthy after all.  Sources such as &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.marksdailyapple.com/is-rice-unhealthy/&#34;&gt;Mark Sisson&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&#34;http://perfecthealthdiet.com/&#34;&gt;Jaminets&lt;/a&gt; argue that brown rice is harmful because of phytic acid that binds to nutrients and makes them inaccessible to us. I don&amp;rsquo;t know how true this is. But if it is true, it is worrying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sisson suggests soaking and fermenting brown rice. Having sort of tried this, I was disgusted by the results. Stephan Guyenet suggested a whole complicated-sounding protocol for &lt;a href=&#34;http://wholehealthsource.blogspot.com/2009/04/new-way-to-soak-brown-rice.html&#34;&gt;soaking brown rice&lt;/a&gt;. Looking at the comments gave me a headache.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-now&#34;&gt;What now?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what am I to do?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I eat brown rice in part to get fiber and in part to get (carb) calories. I have experimented with eating less brown rice lately, but am now considering doing an experiment in which I actually give it up for two weeks or so, to see how I feel. Giving up oatmeal has largely been a good thing for me; I rather enjoy eating a lot of veggies and more protein for breakfast. But getting rid of brown rice is much more radical.  Should I really go back to white rice?  I don&amp;rsquo;t know right now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2012-10-24&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-10-24)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Food Day in 2012, I wrote more about some &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/10/24/reflections-on-food-day/&#34;&gt;dilemmas with rice&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Starting a mini Digital Sabbath</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/11/12/starting-a-mini-digital-sabbath/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Nov 2011 09:52:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/11/12/starting-a-mini-digital-sabbath/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been writing at least one blog post a day now for 42 days. I had started the blog bent on making it a real habit to maintain, and felt that forcing myself to write and upload every single day was necessary to keep the momentum going. I&amp;rsquo;m sure I was right, but now that I am confident in my self-discipline to maintain regularity, I am going to relax the arbitrary rule I set for myself, and start observing a mini Digital Sabbath in which I take a day off every week from blogging. I&amp;rsquo;m starting today (considering this little note as equivalent to taking a break).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you observe or considered observing your own Digital Sabbath in this busy, &lt;sup&gt;24&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;7&lt;/sub&gt; world?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why soda bans don&#39;t work</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/11/07/why-soda-bans-dont-work/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Nov 2011 19:13:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/11/07/why-soda-bans-dont-work/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I just saw an article, &lt;a href=&#34;http://well.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/11/07/soda-bans-in-schools-have-limited-benefit/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Soda Bans in Schools Have Limited Impact&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. It boggles my mind that anyone would advocate soda bans in school as a policy in isolation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are my thoughts on the economics and politics, and health and cultural aspects of the issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;economics-101&#34;&gt;Economics 101&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The article describes the empirical results from soda bans:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Students were drinking other sugary beverages instead&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Students were bringing in their own sugary beverages&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;economics&lt;/em&gt; of the situation are obvious:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are plenty of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Substitute_good&#34;&gt;substitute goods&lt;/a&gt; for soda that satisfy students&amp;rsquo; demand for sugary beverages.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Since the school is not a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Monopoly&#34;&gt;monopoly&lt;/a&gt;, and there are plenty of other &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Supply_(economics)&#34;&gt;suppliers&lt;/a&gt; of soda and other sugary beverages outside of school, all that happens is that students buy from another supplier.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basic economic theory has a way to reduce consumption of sugary beverages, of course: a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pigovian_tax&#34;&gt;Pigovian tax&lt;/a&gt; such as the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sin_tax&#34;&gt;sin tax&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cigarette_taxes_in_the_United_States&#34;&gt;cigarettes&lt;/a&gt;. A tax on the entire category of sugary beverages would do the trick. There is reason to believe the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Price_elasticity_of_demand&#34;&gt;price elasticity&lt;/a&gt; is sufficient that such a tax would considerably reduce consumption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;politics-101&#34;&gt;Politics 101&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And such a wide-ranging tax is completely impossible, politically. Even an overall &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Soda_tax&#34;&gt;soda tax&lt;/a&gt; is, I believe, politically impossible. Worse, it would not solve the problem, because as we know from the school example, there are other sugary beverages that pose the very same health problems but are not labeled as &amp;ldquo;soda&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;bigger-picture-of-economics&#34;&gt;Bigger picture of economics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Worse, the &lt;em&gt;problem&lt;/em&gt; as narrowly defined, that of decreasing consumption of sugary beverages, is only the tip of the iceberg when it comes to the bigger picture of public health. People will eat cookies and any number of other less perfect substitutes for sugary beverages anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;beyond-economics-to-health&#34;&gt;Beyond economics to health&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the purported motivation for reducing sugary beverages has been to reduce obesity. Obesity happens for all kinds of reasons. Worse, I don&amp;rsquo;t even like the focus on &lt;em&gt;weight&lt;/em&gt;. Poor health has to do with a lot more than weight. Most people, when thinking about their weight, and try to lose it, don&amp;rsquo;t even apply healthy strategies to lose weight, or even to do so permanently rather than temporarily. I don&amp;rsquo;t believe stopgap politically controversial initiatives can do much to address the real problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;culture-and-a-personal-note&#34;&gt;Culture and a personal note&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am bombarded daily with access to sugary beverages. Every time I go to a lunch seminar or party or reception, cans and bottles of soda, sports beverages, juices, and sweetened teas are provided. Clearly American culture is simply not ready to give up on these beverages. I get the impression that I am in the minority in choosing not to drink them. I have had maybe &lt;em&gt;four or five&lt;/em&gt; cans or bottles of such beverages in the past ten years. I get the impression that a lot of people I see around have had approximately &lt;em&gt;ten thousand&lt;/em&gt; cans or bottles in the past ten years. I don&amp;rsquo;t lecture people on why they should abstain, because it is useless even when directed toward, say, my own parents. I don&amp;rsquo;t know what it will take for the culture to change, or what I can do to help. Right now, I just silently abstain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you have any suggestions of what I could really do to help spread the word that life really might be more enjoyable without consuming sugary beverages all the time?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Every day is Food Day</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/10/24/every-day-is-food-day/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Oct 2011 21:26:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/10/24/every-day-is-food-day/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I found out only yesterday that today is &lt;a href=&#34;http://foodday.org/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Food Day&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I &lt;a href=&#34;http://foodday.org/about-food-day/&#34;&gt;looked up&lt;/a&gt; what it&amp;rsquo;s all about and it seems that October 24 has been designated &lt;em&gt;Food Day&lt;/em&gt;, sponsored by the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cspinet.org/&#34;&gt;Center for Science in the Public Interest&lt;/a&gt;, a nonprofit watchdog group. I looked further, and saw that the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Center_for_Science_in_the_Public_Interest&#34;&gt;Wikipedia entry&lt;/a&gt; is informative, noting controversies concerning the group, especially the vocal opposition from the restaurant, food, and tobacco industries, but from other sources also, including former CSPI members.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anything concerning food policy in this country is, well, political.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not here today to talk about the politics of food (I recommend &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.foodpolitics.com/&#34;&gt;Marion Nestle&lt;/a&gt; as one sober source about it), but about my personal relationship with food. Once upon a time, I knew very little about food, cared little about it, and rarely prepared it myself. But then things changed, and every day became Food Day for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;before-awareness&#34;&gt;Before awareness&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As late as graduate school, I was still eating random junk, and not really cooking for myself. White bread, processed lunch meats. Frozen dinners. Commercial cereal for breakfast, pizza, Chinese take-out. Potato chips, cookies, candy bars. Canned soups. Frozen chicken wings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not much variety, and not very good for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had never once thought about where my food came from, what was in it, and whether it was any good. I just assumed that name-brand tasty goodies at the grocery store must be OK. Food was an impersonal &amp;ldquo;fuel&amp;rdquo; and a source of instant gratification.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-vegetarian-phase&#34;&gt;My vegetarian phase&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Around 1999, I don&amp;rsquo;t remember exactly how it happened (although being around some female grad students who were vegetarian probably had something to do with it), I started learning about food production. In particular, I came across polemical books about the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Prisoned-Chickens-Poisoned-Eggs-Industry/dp/1570670323&#34;&gt;poultry industry&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/MAD-COWBOY-Plain-Cattle-Rancher/dp/0684854465&#34;&gt;meat industry&lt;/a&gt;. These and similar sources of information exposing the conditions of factory farming, the health hazards of the system, and the environmental impact, led me to actually become a vegetarian.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I became a zealous convert to vegetarianism, went to a local &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.vegetariansummerfest.org/&#34;&gt;vegetarian conference&lt;/a&gt;, and even returned a vegan! That lasted only three months. In the end, my vegetarianism lasted only a year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Why I ended vegetarianism, and how I feel about vegetarianism as an idealized diet or societal arrangement, may be the topic for a future blog post.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;lasting-changes&#34;&gt;Lasting changes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, regardless of how my thinking has evolved since my vegetarian days, many side effects still remain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did learn a lot of facts about food production and health (amid stronger vegetarian claims that I do not accept today). This was stuff that surely everyone should learn as a child in school.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was forced to really cook for myself, especially during my vegan phase, which made it much, much harder to eat out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result, my relationship with food was radically transformed. It became one of the centers of my life, rather than something peripheral. After all, I was cooking something almost every other day. And much of it was from the bulk section of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.eastendfood.coop/&#34;&gt;East End Food Co-op&lt;/a&gt;: various rices, chickpeas, lentils, red kidney beans, black beans, you name it. A whole lot of variety to choose from. I got a pressure cooker, a rice cooker, a slower cooker, an immersion blender, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I had spent most of my life up till then in purely intellectual, theoretical pursuits, it was really new to be getting down and dirty physically with raw ingredients and turning them into something. I felt more in touch with my body, and grateful for living in a land of plenty, never needing to go hungry. I enjoyed exploring many new flavors, ethnic cuisines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This all happened in conjunction with other life changes, such as taking up &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/running/&#34;&gt;running&lt;/a&gt; and dancing and losing thirty pounds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once upon a time, food really was the center of human life: you spent much of the day doing what you could to eat something so you could stay alive! In the developed world, we&amp;rsquo;ve removed a lot of the drudgery and uncertainty of finding something to eat (even half a century ago, women had to spend huge amounts of time on feeding their families), and that can&amp;rsquo;t be a bad thing, but we&amp;rsquo;ve also lost touch with our biological, animal natures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not advocating that everyone should spend huge amounts of time on food preparation, but I think that if everyone were simply more aware of the chain of what happens to feed us, and were mindful and grateful when eating anything, the world would be a better place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether Abby is doing the cooking or I am doing the cooking, I remember my mortality and the impermanence of all living things that gave rise to my meal, and consider each day of my life a gift.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, every day is Food Day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;postscript&#34;&gt;Postscript&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A blog post about Food Day is probably not complete with at least some photo and recipe of something recently prepared or eaten, so here is my &lt;em&gt;chicken curry with cauliflower&lt;/em&gt;, based on the recipe in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.notyourmotherscookbook.com/not-your-mothers-slow-cooker-cookbook/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Not Your Mother&amp;rsquo;s Slow Cooker Cookbook&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The photo is not glamorous, but it is a real photo of real food, simple and tasty.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/chicken-curry-cauliflower.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Chicken curry with cauliflower&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Prep time:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;15 minutes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Equipment:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;medium-sized Crock Pot&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;set it on high for 3 hours (original recipe called for low for longer)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ingredients:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2 pounds boneless, skinless chicken thighs (I find thighs are better than breasts, which tend to dry out)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3 tablespoons extra virgin olive oil&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2 medium onions, chopped coarsely&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2 gloves garlic, minced&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1.5 teaspoons ground coriander&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 teaspoon turmeric&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 teaspoon ground cumin (I also tossed in cumin seeds)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 tablespoon ground ginger (was in a hurry, didn&amp;rsquo;t use fresh)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2 teaspoons paprika&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;0.5 teaspoon red chile pepper flakes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;0.5 teaspoon mustard seeds&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;one can of diced tomatoes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;juice of half lemon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 head cauliflower (florets and stems)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;salt&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Procedure:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some olive oil into slow cooker to coat the bottom.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chop up the chicken thighs, not too finely, and brown in skillet with olive oil for a few minutes, remove.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Into the same skillet, cook onions for a few minutes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add the rest of the dry ingredients to the skillet, continue cooking the mixture for a couple of minutes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add the wet ingredients (tomatoes, lemon juice) to the skillet, mix everything up.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Put the chicken into the slow cooker.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scrape the skillet&amp;rsquo;s contents into the slow cooker.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mix stuff up in the slow cooker.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cook for 3 hours.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When done, add salt to taste.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2012-10-24&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-10-24)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Food Day, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/10/24/reflections-on-food-day/&#34;&gt;a year later&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>