<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Walking on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/walking/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Walking on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/walking/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Commuting on foot during CMU Carnival week as cross-training for the Pittsburgh Marathon</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/04/19/commuting-on-foot-during-cmu-carnival-week-as-cross-training-for-the-pittsburgh-marathon/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Apr 2013 22:10:14 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/04/19/commuting-on-foot-during-cmu-carnival-week-as-cross-training-for-the-pittsburgh-marathon/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Last year, I reported on deciding to &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/04/16/one-week-of-commuting-on-foot-because-of-cmu-carnival/&#34;&gt;walk to work and back home during CMU Carnival week in order to avoid the hassles of parking on campus&lt;/a&gt;. This year, I decided to do this again, but with a twist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I considered my commute to be a deliberate part of cross-training for the Pittsburgh Marathon.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/schenley-drive-carnival-week-2013.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Walking on Schenley Drive during CMU Carnival week 2013&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/2YjLH7SIHaQ&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-walk-instead-of-run&#34;&gt;Why walk instead of run?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might think that I would just run to work and back home, but the logistics were too complicated because of clothing, laptop, and other issues. I ran in to work this week just one time; otherwise, I walked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More important, I feel that walking is greatly underrated as a fitness activity. Here is one of many recent articles, for example, reporting that &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.theatlantic.com/health/archive/2013/04/study-walking-can-be-as-good-as-running/274738/&#34;&gt;walking has many underrated health benefits&lt;/a&gt;. Unfortunately, I think the tone of this article is part of the problem: the title is &amp;ldquo;Study: walking can be as good as running&amp;rdquo;, which is just sensationalist drivel. I don&amp;rsquo;t see walking and running as competitors at all. They are just two different activities, with different benefits, really. High-intensity running, for example, does a lot that walking does not do. But walking is less stressful, is slower, takes more time to cover a particular distance, is more meditative and in many cases more sociable (since running paces differ more than walking paces). Both are great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;total-mileage&#34;&gt;Total mileage&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ended up walking about 12 miles total more than I normally walk during the week. Note that this is less than the total of the distances between home and office because when I drive in to work, I have to walk the distance between the parking lot and the office.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;footwear-concerns-over-the-luna-sandals&#34;&gt;Footwear: concerns over the Luna Sandals&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I took the opportunity to put more mileage onto my Luna Sandals, which I&amp;rsquo;ve been wearing for all my running in recent weeks. I figured that the more time I spend on these minimalist sandals, the more prepared I will be for the sustained impact of running the whole Pittsburgh Marathon in them. Also, I needed more time to get used to the lacing system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that the extra 12 miles on my feet really made a difference in how much more stress on my feet I felt during this training week: not just soreness in my soles, but also some issues with drying, cracking skin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;cushioned-shoes&#34;&gt;Cushioned shoes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After yesterday, I decided I needed a break from all the walking, and so on Friday, I drove to work, parking on Circuit Road, and walking less than half a mile to my office from there, and in my &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Rockport-Mens-Westshire-Oxford-Black/dp/B000VRUX54&#34;&gt;Rockport Westshire casual shoes&lt;/a&gt; rather than any minimalist shoes! I did this especially because of the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/04/19/going-out-too-fast-yet-again-in-my-third-random-distance-run/&#34;&gt;Random Distance Run I did in my Luna Sandals&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-mono&#34;&gt;The Mono&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also finally decided to order a pair of thicker Luna Sandals, the new &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lunasandals.com/products/37-mono&#34;&gt;Mono&lt;/a&gt;, which are 12 mm thick rather than the 7 mm of the Venado I&amp;rsquo;m currently wearing:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://s3.amazonaws.com/lunastore/images/279/full.jpg?1357775828&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Luna Sandals, Mono&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a review of these huaraches on &lt;a href=&#34;http://birthdayshoes.com/luna-mono-huaraches-barefoot-sandals-review&#34;&gt;Birthday Shoes&lt;/a&gt;. I will almost certainly &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; be receiving these huaraches in time to break in and use in the Pittsburgh Marathon, but I expect to use them this summer for walking around in and longer runs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was unexpected to me how much more fat burning and soreness for my feet the extra 12 miles of walking this week gave me. I had to eat more just to maintain my weight, and I was so ready to take a break from minimalist shoes. I did decide to order a thicker running sandal for future running and walking.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Walking and running in Invisible Shoes: a review of the Connect</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/07/26/walking-and-running-in-invisible-shoes-a-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jul 2012 21:28:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/07/26/walking-and-running-in-invisible-shoes-a-review/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;For three weeks now, I have been wearing a pair of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.invisibleshoe.com/&#34;&gt;Invisible Shoes&lt;/a&gt; huaraches almost exclusively when walking and running outside. I have worn them daily walking, and I have run in them on roads, on sidewalks, on grass, and in park trails.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a review of the 4mm sole Connect model (I might get a 6mm sole Contact later).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is what the shoes look like with &amp;ldquo;slip-on/slip-off&amp;rdquo; lacing:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/invisible-shoes-connect/without-feet.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/invisible-shoes-connect/bottom.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As you can see, the sole is quite thin, just 4mm:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/invisible-shoes-connect/side-view.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here are some photos of me wearing the shoes:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/invisible-shoes-connect/grass.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/invisible-shoes-connect/asphalt.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-wear-such-a-thin-shoe&#34;&gt;Why wear such a thin shoe?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ten years ago, in 2002, I learned about the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tarahumara_people&#34;&gt;Tarahumara&lt;/a&gt; Native Americans who live in Mexico and are famed for long-distance running. I was fascinated that they chose to run in minimalist huaraches. At the time, I was doing a lot of serious &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/running/&#34;&gt;running&lt;/a&gt;, and perpetually had problems with running shoes. I figured out from trial and error that the more minimalist I got, the more I enjoyed the feel of running and the fewer injuries I received, but I didn&amp;rsquo;t know how minimalist I could really get before the cons outweighed the pros. By 2002, I had gotten as far as wearing racing flats by New Balance and Asics for races and some of my training runs, but no shoe was perfect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had also tried wearing a variety of ordinary sandals for walking and running, but they had all kinds of ergonomic problems that led me to give up on them. The strapping systems, the substantial (by my standards) heels, and the curved &amp;ldquo;arch support&amp;rdquo; all caused discomfort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fast-forward to 2009, when I bought my first pair of Vibram FiveFingers minimalist shoes. These changed my life, being sufficiently minimalist to defeat a number of problems I&amp;rsquo;ve had with traditional mono-toed shoes. As long-time readers of &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/fivefingers/&#34;&gt;this blog know&lt;/a&gt;, I&amp;rsquo;ve been wearing them exclusively for all kinds of activities, ranging from regular everyday walking to running on roads, running on trails, hiking, kayaking, rafting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past year, I have tried a little bit of &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/barefoot-running/&#34;&gt;barefoot running&lt;/a&gt;, but that is still too extreme for me to do often or for a long period of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I decided that now was the time to try to get more minimalist than FiveFingers, toward the &amp;ldquo;barefoot&amp;rdquo; feel, but without the most glaring drawbacks of being barefoot. Luckily, the surprising popularity of &lt;a href=&#34;http://chrismcdougall.com/&#34;&gt;Chris McDougall&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/a&gt; book &amp;ldquo;Born to Run&amp;rdquo; has resulted in a good number of people selling minimalist huaraches for running.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;buying&#34;&gt;Buying&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Barefoot Ted had long sold his version of huaraches, the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lunasandals.com/&#34;&gt;Luna Sandals&lt;/a&gt;. I decided to try, instead, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.invisibleshoe.com/&#34;&gt;Invisible Shoes&lt;/a&gt;, because these are more minimalist than the Luna, which in its classic form has a 6mm sole as well as a foot bed. I may well try the Luna at some point, but my goal for now is to approximate the barefoot feel, rather than pick the best huaraches for serious rugged use, and work up from there. So I went for the 4mm Connect version of the Invisible Shoes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For now, instead of buying a DIY kit, I decided that the simplest hassle-free way to break into huaraches was to buy a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lunasandals.com/&#34;&gt;custom-made&lt;/a&gt; shoe that had the soles cut and punched and laced up, ready to immediately wear. I traced my foot, scanned the trace, and emailed it, and quickly received my pair in the mail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are interested in trying out huaraches, I recommend following this route if the thought of DIY problems might otherwise discourage you. I may go DIY in the future, now that I see the final product.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;tying&#34;&gt;Tying&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question of how to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.invisibleshoe.com/tying/&#34;&gt;tie&lt;/a&gt; laces always pops up. For now, I have not experimented with different methods in order to evaluate what works best for me for secureness and comfort. I have been using the slip-on/slip-off system that came with the shoe, adjusting it as needed when my foot feels too tight or too loose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;walking&#34;&gt;Walking&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I got Invisible Shoes, my regular walking shoes were my Vibram FiveFingers KSO shoes. But once I got the Invisible Shoes, I completely stopped wearing the KSO for everyday walking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;pros&#34;&gt;Pros&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My toes have real freedom. Toe shoes like the Vibram FiveFingers compartmentalize the toes, so although they solve my wide-foot problem, they do not give me total freedom of the whole front of the foot that I like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good ventilation, like being barefoot. FiveFingers get hot in summer, resulting in sweat and sometimes blisters. I don&amp;rsquo;t get blisters walking in Invisible Shoes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the slip-on/slip-off system, I really can slip on and off easily. Since I like going barefoot indoors, it&amp;rsquo;s a plus to be able to slip on and off the shoes so easily.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;cons&#34;&gt;Cons&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is some rubbing at key points on the foot: the knot in the lacing system on top of the foot, and the lacing that passes between the big toe and the second toe. In practice, none of this has been a real problem except when it&amp;rsquo;s raining and my feet get wet, in which case I get chafed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The soles, being so thin, flop around a bit. Occasionally a sole will fold under and cause me to trip, but this happens very rarely. The main problem is mostly social: the flopping sound draws attention; I prefer to walk very silently (which I can do in most closed shoes).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The thinness of the soles also result in my feet getting very hot when I&amp;rsquo;m just standing for a period of time on hot asphalt or concrete (this is the same problem as I have when going barefoot). So standing at a street intersection waiting for a long light or in a parking lot while putting stuff into a car is not so pleasant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The thinness of the soles means walking over rough terrain is not always pleasant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that all the problems with the thinness of the soles might not be present if I had the 6mm sole rather than the 4mm sole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;running&#34;&gt;Running&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Disclaimer: I have run only four or five times in these shoes so far, so I will accumulate more experience as I continue to run in them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;pros-1&#34;&gt;Pros&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Running in these shoes on the roads and sidewalks is predictable and pleasant, very much like running barefoot. I am considering doing more tests to determine whether to run a road race 5K or 10K in these shoes! I have not run at race pace in these shoes yet. I may need to adjust lacing systems in order to feel confident about running at maximum speed without a flopping or lace-loosening problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;cons-1&#34;&gt;Cons&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is sole flopping when running. Actually there is less flopping than when walking, though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Running in the trails has not worked too smoothly. The 4mm sole really is quite thin for trail running. I noticed this when running in Frick Park, where some of the trails are more rocky than others. I also noticed this even when running in &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/06/18/walking-the-scenic-route-through-schenley-park-to-work/&#34;&gt;Schenley Park on the Pretty Good Race course&lt;/a&gt;, where the downhill section had me periodically hitting rocks harder than comfortable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is also the annoyance of stuff getting between the foot and the sole when running in the trails. Since I don&amp;rsquo;t like stopping, I&amp;rsquo;ve tried to simply flex my foot to let the material slide back out during the next couple of strides, and this mostly works. But I got one blister during a run on the trails, possibly because of loose material that got between my foot and the sole that I didn&amp;rsquo;t bother completely shaking out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 4mm Connect model of Invisible Shoes is great for walking around in. For running, I need to do more tests to find out how they hold up in more demanding conditions of speed and terrain. I would also like to compare the 4mm Connect model with the 6mm Contact model.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Walking the scenic route through Schenley Park to work</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/06/18/walking-the-scenic-route-through-schenley-park-to-work/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Jun 2012 22:08:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/06/18/walking-the-scenic-route-through-schenley-park-to-work/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Two months ago, I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/04/16/one-week-of-commuting-on-foot-because-of-cmu-carnival/&#34;&gt;spent a whole week&lt;/a&gt; commuting to work at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cmu.edu/&#34;&gt;Carnegie Mellon University&lt;/a&gt; by walking instead of driving, because of the annoyances of parking during Carnival week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because I enjoyed that experience so much, since then, I have walked to/from work at least once a week! Usually my route has included either Forbes Avenue or Schenley Drive, but once I went on other roads through Schenley Park.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last week I started making the trails of Schenley Park part of my walk. This adds probably half a mile to the walk (for a total of just less than 2.5 miles from home to work); time efficiency was why I had not taken this indirect route before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some photos of my walk to CMU last week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;going-barefoot-to-schenley-park&#34;&gt;Going barefoot to Schenley Park&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went barefoot the entire way from home to Schenley Park.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/commute-schenley-park/barefoot.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Barefoot&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Reaching the Schenley Park sign on Hobart Street:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/commute-schenley-park/hobart.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Schenley Park sign on Hobart Street&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;About to enjoy barefoot running on the grass to cross Beacon Street and Bartlett Street to reach the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.examiner.com/article/schenley-park-bartlett-street-playground&#34;&gt;Bartlett Playground&lt;/a&gt;. Note that the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.tour.pitt.edu/tour-080.html&#34;&gt;Cathedral of Learning&lt;/a&gt; is visible in the background.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/commute-schenley-park/beacon-bartlett-grass.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Grass at Hobart Street and Beacon Street&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Arriving at the Bartlett Shelter sign:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/commute-schenley-park/bartlett-shelter.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Sign for Bartlett Shelter&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Right behind the playground is the entrance to the Panther Hollow Trail:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/commute-schenley-park/bartlett-panther-hollow-trail.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Sign for Panther Hollow Trail&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;panther-hollow-trail-to-schenley-park-cafe-and-visitor-center&#34;&gt;Panther Hollow Trail to Schenley Park Cafe and Visitor Center&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This section of the Panther Hollow Trail that I followed all the way to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pittsburghparks.org/schenleyparkcafe&#34;&gt;Schenley Park Cafe and Visitor Center&lt;/a&gt; is the all-downhill section of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~kalp/PGR/&#34;&gt;Pretty Good Race 5K&lt;/a&gt; course that I ran on to &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/06/06/i-celebrated-national-running-day-in-schenley-park-remembering-how-i-began-to-run-13-year-ago/&#34;&gt;celebrate National Running Day on June 6&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My apologies to the barefoot purists, but I immediately found the trail too rough for my bare feet and put on my Vibram FiveFingers KSO shoes:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/commute-schenley-park/vibram-fivefingers-kso.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Vibram FiveFingers KSO shoes on Panther Hollow Trail&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A typical view while running downhill on the Panther Hollow Trail for about 0.9 mile:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/commute-schenley-park/panther-hollow-trail-downhill.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Panther Hollow Trail going downhill&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A sign at the base of the steps that lead up to the Schenley Park Cafe and Visitor Center. I appreciate the renovations in the Pittsburgh parks in the past several years that include such features as the new signs that I think help visitors a lot.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/commute-schenley-park/steps-sign.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Schenley Park sign at base of steps&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Finally out of the trail:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/commute-schenley-park/schenley-park-cafe-and-visitor-center.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Schenley Park Cafe and Visitor Center&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;across-flagstaff-hill-to-my-office-at-carnegie-mellon-university&#34;&gt;Across Flagstaff Hill to my office at Carnegie Mellon University&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A view of Phipps Conservatory as well as the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.tour.pitt.edu/tour-080.html&#34;&gt;Cathedral of Learning&lt;/a&gt; in the distance:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/commute-schenley-park/phipps-cathedral.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Phipps Conservatory&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One is probably not supposed to do so, but I climbed up the stone border (about four feet high) to enter Flagstaff Hill. The more circuitous route to my office would be to take Schenley Drive, which curves around, but it&amp;rsquo;s shorter (and also more scenic and strenuous) to go up the hill directly and steeply, and then descend.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/commute-schenley-park/flagstaff-hill.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Flagstaff Hill&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Taking in the view of the Cathedral of Learning against the lovely blue sky, while running through the grass on Flagstaff Hill:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/commute-schenley-park/cathedral-of-learning-from-flagstaff-hill.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Cathedral of Learning visible from Flagstaff Hill&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My office is barely visible through the trees as I descend:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/commute-schenley-park/office-through-trees.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Office visible through trees&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A convenient path to Frew Street:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/commute-schenley-park/path-to-frew-street.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Path to Frew Street&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At my office building:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/commute-schenley-park/office-building.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;My office building&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a lot of fun on a nice day to walk to work the &amp;ldquo;long&amp;rdquo; way that goes through the trails of Schenley Park and also Flagstaff Hill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am so grateful that Pittsburgh is friendly and stimulating for walking in. And, of course, I am grateful that &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mary_Schenley&#34;&gt;Mary Schenley&lt;/a&gt; donated the land to Pittsburgh way back that became Schenley Park.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>One week of commuting on foot because of CMU Carnival</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/04/16/one-week-of-commuting-on-foot-because-of-cmu-carnival/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Apr 2012 19:57:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/04/16/one-week-of-commuting-on-foot-because-of-cmu-carnival/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This week, the Morewood Parking Lot, where I have an annual parking permit for commuting to work at Carnegie Mellon University, is being used for the annual &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.contrib.andrew.cmu.edu/~sc0v/&#34;&gt;CMU Spring Carnival&lt;/a&gt;, so this year I opted for the new possibility opened up by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cmu.edu/parking/&#34;&gt;CMU Parking Services&lt;/a&gt; to volunteer to not park in my lot, in order to reduce demand for parking. In return, I get a $50 credit toward my parking fee.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/walk-home-from-cmu/morewood-lot-carnival.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(A photo from the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.contrib.andrew.cmu.edu/~sc0v/webcam.html&#34;&gt;CMU Carnival live webcam&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So today I walked two miles to work and another two back home, taking about thirty minutes each way at a fairly brisk pace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why was I so eager to volunteer?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-pain-of-parking-during-carnival-week&#34;&gt;The pain of parking during Carnival week&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been paying for parking in the Morewood Lot for over a decade (with only one year in which I parked in the East Campus Garage). Every year, parking during Carnival week is a nightmare. Since the lower lot is closed, the result is that the rest of the lot fills quickly and you end up having to park in the East Campus Garage, spending over five minutes (according to my actual measurements) to drive up to the top and be guided to park somewhere, if you&amp;rsquo;re lucky. I already hate parking in the East Campus Garage, for a variety of reasons, and the added congestion and time only makes the experience worse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-do-i-drive-to-and-park-at-work-at-all&#34;&gt;Why do I drive to and park at work at all?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have, of course, walked (or run) to work occasionally in the past, but it was not a regular habit, given that I pay for an expensive parking spot. I like to drive to work because of the conveniences:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;not as exposed to the elements (cold, hot, snow, rain, etc.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;saves &amp;ldquo;a lot of&amp;rdquo; time: ten minutes to get to work rather than thirty (actually, this is false: the driving time may be ten minutes from home to getting out of parked car, and then it takes another ten minutes to walk from the lot to my office, for a total of twenty minutes)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;much easier to haul stuff around, such as books and printouts and glass Pyrex containers for my lunches&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;in a typical week I need to drive somewhere immediately after work, e.g., a Meetup event on the North Shore or some other such place&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;goal-force-myself-to-do-more-walking&#34;&gt;Goal: force myself to do more walking&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do some running approximately every other day, but I haven&amp;rsquo;t been doing much plain old walking (sadly, I have not even done long hikes in the woods recently). I decided it would be a good opportunity to see what happens (mentally and physically) if I walk two miles to work, and two miles back home, every day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-not-run-instead-of-walk&#34;&gt;Why not run instead of walk?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have run to work in the past, but only when I had a way to deal with the following issues:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;change of clothing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;hauling my stuff (easier to do when walking)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-not-take-the-bus&#34;&gt;Why not take the bus?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I work at CMU, I get &amp;ldquo;free&amp;rdquo; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.portauthority.org/&#34;&gt;city bus&lt;/a&gt; service. I take the bus quite infrequently; there is a stop a block away from my home, so it is definitely always an option.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I have hated buses all my life, since riding them as a kid in New York City, and riding them elsewhere. In high school, I often chose to walk rather than ride a bus. In college, I also chose to walk rather than ride a bus; sometimes I would even walk an entire hour to get from one end of campus to the next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why I don&amp;rsquo;t like buses:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;air pollution: I have a strong belief that there is a lot of carbon monoxide and other noxious gases in and around buses that are why I feel nauseous whenever I am on a bus&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;waiting: I have lived in some places such as Pittsburgh where bus service leaves much to be desired, with long waits; I have observed in the past that by running, I can already go a mile before I see any bus going where I want to go, catching up to me!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;overcrowding: it&amp;rsquo;s not entirely predictable whether you can even get onto a bus that arrives&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;passivity: if it&amp;rsquo;s not going to save me much time, and has down sides, I might as well be active and walk!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-not-ride-my-bike&#34;&gt;Why not ride my bike?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be frank, I think of bike riding in Pittsburgh as scary. Things are much, much better now than they used to be, but I just don&amp;rsquo;t feel comfortable riding my bike around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe some day I&amp;rsquo;ll change my mind, but not right now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;should-i-try-my-old-razor-kick-scooter&#34;&gt;Should I try my old Razor kick scooter?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.razor.com/&#34;&gt;Razor&lt;/a&gt; kick scooter that I bought over a decade ago when it suddenly became a big fad. I had plans to use it for various purposes (including working my leg muscles around a track), but actually never got around to using it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am considering trying it out to supplement walking to work, but have some reservations. We&amp;rsquo;ll see whether I try it out this week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;some-photos-of-today-s-walk-home&#34;&gt;Some photos of today&amp;rsquo;s walk home&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feared that a thunderstorm might hit this evening (it did not), so I walked pretty quickly home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Schenley Drive is the most direct way to get into Squirrel Hill, where I live. Amusingly, my boss passed me on his bike while I was walking along:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/walk-home-from-cmu/walking-home-on-schenley-drive.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Residential Squirrel Hill arrives right after the golf course:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/walk-home-from-cmu/darlington-murdoch.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Going down Murray Avenue:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/walk-home-from-cmu/south-on-murray-ave.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I felt great (if sweaty) after my quick walk home tonight. I have tended to feel tired when coming home from work. It may be that all I really need is a nice walk to give me some air and circulation before dinner time. I look forward to doing more walking the rest of this week.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>