<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Carnegie Mellon University on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/carnegie-mellon-university/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Carnegie Mellon University on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/carnegie-mellon-university/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>How I forgot to meditate after sixty days in a row of remembering and what that means</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/01/24/how-i-forgot-to-meditate-after-sixty-days-in-a-row-of-remembering-and-what-that-means/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2015 13:58:29 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/01/24/how-i-forgot-to-meditate-after-sixty-days-in-a-row-of-remembering-and-what-that-means/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I woke up this morning feeling very tired. I also suddenly realized that yesterday, I forgot to set aside time for the daily meditation practice (just ten minutes a day) that I had successfully done for &lt;em&gt;sixty days in a row&lt;/em&gt;, having deliberately started it &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/11/24/report-on-my-first-day-of-stoic-week-2014/&#34;&gt;shortly before Thanksgiving&lt;/a&gt;. I was pretty angry at myself. But I also thought about how it was possible that I slipped after sixty days, and what that means.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-s-my-meditation-schedule&#34;&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s my meditation schedule?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The optimal way to maintain any habit is to make it as rigid and automatic as possible. Several years ago, when I went months at a time without missing a single day, my system was to meditate first thing in the morning, before eating or exercising or anything else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I confess that I still don&amp;rsquo;t have that kind of rigid schedule yet. Much of the time, I do meditate first thing. Other times, I feel pressed for time and want to get some work done. Or I&amp;rsquo;m feeling very hungry and decide to eat breakfast first. But usually I do complete meditation in the morning. Occasionally I &amp;ldquo;forget&amp;rdquo; but then remember well before bedtime, and get it in before sleeping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-my-forgetting-yesterday-says-about-my-life&#34;&gt;What my forgetting yesterday says about my life&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, I was feeling tired when I woke, because of a week of accumulated fatigue from doing many things, including going out last night with Abby for the second week of blues dance class at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.tartanswing.com/&#34;&gt;Tartan Swing&lt;/a&gt; at CMU. Adding an extra evening out every week is requiring some changes in how much other stuff I can get done in evenings, and apparently I have not scaled back enough to make up for that additional commitment; it is always a struggle for me to &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/12/15/thoughts-on-giving-up-an-old-project-to-make-room-for-the-new/&#34;&gt;give up something to make room for something else&lt;/a&gt;, but especially on short notice, since we had not originally planned, in December, to start checking out Tartan Swing this January!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, yesterday was Friday, and I tend to feel I have many things to try to get done on Friday. I ate breakfast immediately, did work stuff, then since I was scheduled to go for a run, I did that. I&amp;rsquo;ve been ramping up on my run distances, and I ran my second longest distance so far this month: the length was the sum of the length of my Monday and Wednesday runs this week! So that took more energy than I am used to yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I came home from work, I was extremely tired and hungry, to the point that I decided I wanted to eat a whole lot of food and do something different, so Abby and I went out for dinner. I came home totally stuffed. In any case, going out was an unscheduled, spontaneous decision, and by the time we came home, none of the whole day had gone according to my usual pattern. And so I somehow forgot to get in meditation before going to bed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;lessons-learned&#34;&gt;Lessons learned&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first lesson is that just because I missed one day of meditation after sixty in a row, that doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean I&amp;rsquo;ve lost everything. I meditated today, and will continue my practice. It&amp;rsquo;s important to recover as quickly as possible, to avoid what has happened to me before, which is to feel ashamed, start identifying (after too many days in a row missed) as a &amp;ldquo;non-meditator&amp;rdquo;, and give up the practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other is that I&amp;rsquo;m definitely overbooked and need to make sure I get rest, and get back on schedule for what I can manage to do. A busy week is coming up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What do you do when you find out that you&amp;rsquo;ve missed a day of meditation, exercise, or some other daily practice? Do you feel bad about yourself? Do you make excuses? Do you examine what is really important? Do you set up a system to prevent having to rely on will power? What is your latest experience of slipping, and how did you deal with it?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>For Martin Luther King, Jr. Day: some black American voices that spoke to me recently</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/01/19/for-martin-luther-king-jr-day-some-black-american-voices-that-spoke-to-me-recently/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2015 20:58:34 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/01/19/for-martin-luther-king-jr-day-some-black-american-voices-that-spoke-to-me-recently/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I believe today was the first time in my life I&amp;rsquo;ve officially celebrated &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Martin_Luther_King,_Jr._Day&#34;&gt;Martin Luther King, Jr. Day&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means many things to me as an American (I am an Asian-American, son of immigrants).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;mlk-day-became-an-official-holiday-at-work-finally&#34;&gt;MLK Day became an official holiday at work, finally&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, I didn&amp;rsquo;t go to work today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year, 2015, was the year that MLK Day finally became an &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cmu.edu/leadership/president-suresh/presidential-communications/2014/2014-08-21.html&#34;&gt;official university holiday at Carnegie Mellon University&lt;/a&gt;! Our new president, Subra Suresh, decided to finally end the weird CMU tradition of observing MLK Day only as a half-day holiday for students, and turning it into a full-day holiday for everyone (see &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cmu.edu/cipi/news-events/2014/140114_Frazer-2014-MLK-Keynote-Address.html&#34;&gt;2014&amp;rsquo;s schedule of events&lt;/a&gt; for an example of how things used to be). I am proud of President Suresh for taking the step of turning MLK Day into a full holiday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;some-recent-black-american-voices-i-heard&#34;&gt;Some recent black American voices I heard&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The media frenzy over the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shooting_of_Michael_Brown&#34;&gt;shooting last year in Ferguson&lt;/a&gt; may have ended, but I have not forgotten &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/11/27/report-on-my-fourth-day-of-stoic-week-2014/&#34;&gt;my vow last year to begin engaging more publicly in discussions about race in America&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I&amp;rsquo;m starting off small, by linking to eloquent, heartfelt writings I&amp;rsquo;ve read and saved in the past year (independent of Ferguson, just part of what comes my way online) by black Americans who shared their various life experiences so that those of us who are not black can better understand what they have dealt with in their lives in the US. I&amp;rsquo;ve deliberately chosen articles by high achievers to highlight what still remains even after doing all the &amp;ldquo;right&amp;rdquo; things to try to live as normally as possible as a black American.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-price-of-black-ambition-http-www-vqronline-org-essays-articles-2014-10-price-black-ambition&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.vqronline.org/essays-articles/2014/10/price-black-ambition&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The price of black ambition&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an essay by a black female writer, Roxane Gay, daughter of Haitian immigrants, whose life was marked by great ambition and hard work. She kept hoping that it would be enough to overcome racism. She writes, &amp;ldquo;I have come to realize how much I have, throughout my life, bought into the narrative of this alluring myth of personal responsibility and excellence.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-other-side-of-diversity-http-medium-com-ericajoy-the-other-side-of-diversity-1bb3de2f053e&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://medium.com/@ericajoy/the-other-side-of-diversity-1bb3de2f053e&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The other side of diversity&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This poignant essay by a black woman discusses what it has been like to work in a predominantly white male tech community, thereby facing the dilemmas of minority status in two dimensions (race, gender). She has found it challenging to simply be who she wants to be, &amp;ldquo;&amp;hellip;a black woman who happens to work in the tech industry&amp;rdquo;, rather than something additional seemingly expected of her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;i-taught-my-black-kids-that-their-elite-upbringing-would-protect-them-from-discrimination-i-was-wrong-http-www-washingtonpost-com-posteverything-wp-2014-11-06-i-taught-my-black-kids-that-their-elite-upbringing-would-protect-them-from-discrimination-i-was-wrong&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.washingtonpost.com/posteverything/wp/2014/11/06/i-taught-my-black-kids-that-their-elite-upbringing-would-protect-them-from-discrimination-i-was-wrong/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;I taught my black kids that their elite upbringing would protect them from discrimination. I was wrong.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article by Lawrence Otis Graham talks about how he and his wife tried to shelter their children from racial discrimination by giving them an upper-middle-class upbringing. &amp;ldquo;My wife and I, both African Americans, constitute one of those Type A couples with Ivy League undergraduate and graduate degrees who, for many years, believed that if we worked hard and maintained great jobs, we could insulate our children from the blatant manifestations of bigotry that we experienced as children in the 1960s and ’70s.&amp;rdquo; Especially check out the detailed &amp;ldquo;rules&amp;rdquo; of behavior that they taught their children in hope that they would not be mistakenly targeted through racial profiling!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;mlk-s-letter-from-a-birmingham-jail-http-www-africa-upenn-edu-articles-gen-letter-birmingham-html&#34;&gt;MLK&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.africa.upenn.edu/Articles_Gen/Letter_Birmingham.html&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Letter from a Birmingham jail&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I want to simply quote MLK himself from his brilliant essay, &amp;ldquo;Letter from a Birmingham jail&amp;rdquo;. The key to his work, often forgotten or deliberately obscured, is this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
I must confess that over the past few years I have been gravely disappointed with the white moderate. I have almost reached the regrettable conclusion that the Negro&#39;s great stumbling block in his stride toward freedom is not the White Citizen&#39;s Counciler or the Ku Klux Klanner, but the white moderate, who is more devoted to &#34;order&#34; than to justice; who prefers a negative peace which is the absence of tension to a positive peace which is the presence of justice; who constantly says: &#34;I agree with you in the goal you seek, but I cannot agree with your methods of direct action&#34;; who paternalistically believes he can set the timetable for another man&#39;s freedom; who lives by a mythical concept of time and who constantly advises the Negro to wait for a &#34;more convenient season.&#34; Shallow understanding from people of good will is more frustrating than absolute misunderstanding from people of ill will. Lukewarm acceptance is much more bewildering than outright rejection.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Political &amp;ldquo;moderation&amp;rdquo; is often praised and held up as superior to &amp;ldquo;extremism&amp;rdquo;, but in fact, the &amp;ldquo;moderate&amp;rdquo; is often a large part of the problem when it comes to change and doing the right thing. I have more to say about this general topic, but not right now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, read the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.africa.upenn.edu/Articles_Gen/Letter_Birmingham.html&#34;&gt;whole letter&lt;/a&gt;, one of the most brilliant examples of the art and science of that rhetoric I have ever seen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I observed MLK Day today by reviewing writings by black Americans and rereading MLK&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Letter from a Birmingham jail&amp;rdquo;. In the US, we still have a long way to go in race relations, but we continue to make progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How did you observe MLK Day today? What is on your mind today? Did you participate in a reading or a march? Do you oppose what MLK did and believe there should be no holiday in his honor? Or do you feel he didn&amp;rsquo;t do enough, that nonviolence didn&amp;rsquo;t work?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Observing Constitution Day with &#34;The Supreme Court and Privacy: The Fourth Amendment in the Digital Age&#34;</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/09/17/observing-constitution-day-with-the-supreme-court-and-privacy-the-fourth-amendment-in-the-digital-age/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2014 21:54:01 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/09/17/observing-constitution-day-with-the-supreme-court-and-privacy-the-fourth-amendment-in-the-digital-age/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have a habit of observing Constitution Day every year by attending a presentation at CMU and thinking about issues relating to the Constitution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year (2013), &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/09/17/on-not-celebrating-constitution-day-this-year&#34;&gt;I was too disheartened to observe Constitution Day but wrote a little bit about why&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year, I returned because the topic for discussion sounded interesting: &lt;a href=&#34;http://thebridge.cmu.edu/organization/SLO/calendar/details/466499&#34;&gt;Mary Jo Miller gave a talk &amp;ldquo;The Supreme Court and Privacy: The Fourth Amendment in the Digital Age&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; in the Posner Center. (Miller is a Staff Attorney for the Pennsylvania State Education Association and an adjunct professor in Carnegie Mellon&amp;rsquo;s Social and Decision Sciences Department.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/franklinmingchen/15274305882&#34; title=&#34;IMG_20140917_163751 by Franklin Chen, on Flickr&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3836/15274305882_f0eaf5d8fb.jpg&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; height=&#34;375&#34; alt=&#34;IMG_20140917_163751&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-fourth-amendment-http-en-wikipedia-org-wiki-fourth-amendment-to-the-united-states-constitution&#34;&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fourth_Amendment_to_the_United_States_Constitution&#34;&gt;fourth amendment&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
The right of the people to be secure in their persons, houses, papers, and effects, against unreasonable searches and seizures, shall not be violated, and no warrants shall issue, but upon probable cause, supported by oath or affirmation, and particularly describing the place to be searched, and the persons or things to be seized.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mary Jo Miller gave an entertaining and instructive talk in which she discussed various rulings by the Supreme Court involving interpretations of the fourth amendment in various circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, she reminded us that the fourth amendment came about because of the colonialists&amp;rsquo; bad experiences with England when arbitrary searches of people&amp;rsquo;s home happened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then she argued that although it is popularly held that there is a &amp;ldquo;conservative&amp;rdquo; (&amp;ldquo;originalist&amp;rdquo;) wing of the Supreme Court (typified currently by Scalia) and a &amp;ldquo;liberal&amp;rdquo; (&amp;ldquo;living Constitution&amp;rdquo;) wing (typified in the past by Stevens), on fourth amendment issues, they are not always split. In fact, she gave examples of where the Court was unanimous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The primary concern by the Court has been to respect (in the absence of probable cause) the doctrine that &amp;ldquo;each man&amp;rsquo;s home is his castle&amp;rdquo;. Miller gave examples involving surveillance of a marijuana grower&amp;rsquo;s home through a heat detector, as well as examining the contents of a drug dealer&amp;rsquo;s cell phone, as being judged a violation of fourth amendment rights because of what can be considered one&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;home&amp;rdquo;: a cell phone is actually a computer containing much of one&amp;rsquo;s possession, so it is in fact one&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;home&amp;rdquo; and requires a proper warrant in order to search it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s about the &amp;ldquo;exclusionary rule&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;fruits of the poison tree&amp;rdquo;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/franklinmingchen/15271576131&#34; title=&#34;IMG_20140917_164820 by Franklin Chen, on Flickr&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5596/15271576131_6c4a8f4d5f.jpg&#34; width=&#34;375&#34; height=&#34;500&#34; alt=&#34;IMG_20140917_164820&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-about-the-nsa&#34;&gt;What about the NSA?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After almost an hour, I had to leave, and therefore did not stay for questions and answers. I would have asked about what the current thinking is by the Court about NSA surveillance. When is information far enough removed that it is no longer considered one&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;home&amp;rdquo;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did enjoy this year&amp;rsquo;s Constitution Day observance at CMU. Mary Jo Miller gave an excellent talk discussing various Supreme Court rulings and different aspects of the fourth amendment.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sometimes the best speech is the one you didn&#39;t have time to prepare</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/05/29/sometimes-the-best-speech-is-the-one-you-didnt-have-time-to-prepare/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 May 2014 21:57:45 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/05/29/sometimes-the-best-speech-is-the-one-you-didnt-have-time-to-prepare/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I went to something like my twelfth &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.hss.cmu.edu/&#34;&gt;CMU Dietrich College of Humanities and Social Sciences&lt;/a&gt; staff appreciation lunch (I&amp;rsquo;ve lost track). Basically, they feed you, recognize people who have worked some multiple of five years, and hold a raffle for ten cash prizes topping out at $100 (I won $75 last year). It&amp;rsquo;s a pleasant annual social event, but one whose details I don&amp;rsquo;t really remember from one year to the next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this year was different. I will not forget this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;where-s-the-dean&#34;&gt;Where&amp;rsquo;s the dean?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The current dean, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.stat.cmu.edu/GSS/lehoczky.html&#34;&gt;John Lehoczky&lt;/a&gt;, who always gives out the awards during the staff appreciation lunch, was nowhere to be found. This was especially mysterious because he was to be honored with a gift today, since he is stepping down as dean after fourteen years, to return to his duties as professor of statistics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;food&#34;&gt;Food&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lunch was pretty good, for me anyway. I had steak, potatoes, steamed vegetables, and salad, and topped off with some coffee and cake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/dietrich-appreciation-lunch-2014-05-29/lunch.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Lunch&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/dietrich-appreciation-lunch-2014-05-29/cake.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Coffee and cake&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I was surprised by the absence of vegetarian entrees. I myself am not vegetarian, but I know many people who are, or are almost-vegetarian, and I enjoy vegetarian options, so I am always sensitive to the variety of food options at events. Vegetarians at this lunch today had to make do by loading up on only simple salad and steamed vegetables.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;dean-lehoczky-appears&#34;&gt;Dean Lehoczky appears&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, after everyone was done eating, Dean Lehoczky appeared.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He explained that last night he had been working on some fancy speech for us, but then his wife had an accident and he took her to the hospital and they had some adventures there. After they finally returned home, he decided to scrap his plans for his speech.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, he gave a little talk that is the only one of his that I expect to remember in the past decade of this annual event (I have no memory of what he even said last year, for example). It was hilarious, and it was just him telling a story highlighting the humor in all the situations that arose after the accident last night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I guarantee you that I will &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; forget this story he told, as long as I live, it was so funny and personal. I will remember this story for decades. Up till this moment, John Lehoczky was to me just some guy I saw around at events. I don&amp;rsquo;t remember anything he might have said at any ceremonial speech I may have attended by him. But after yesterday, I saw a really funny guy who shared a personal story at his last staff appreciation lunch. The first thing when I got home from work was to tell Abby the story.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/dietrich-appreciation-lunch-2014-05-29/lehoczky.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;John Lehoczky&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re going to give a speech, why not make it unique and interesting, rather than formal and boilerplate? It worked, by accident, for John Lehoczky in his final moments as dean of the CMU Dietrich College of Humanities and Social Sciences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When you have to speak in public, how do you feel about your obligation? Do you fall back on some impersonal formula based on some template, since nobody really cares anyway? Or do you tell a story, and make it interesting? Do you care if anyone cares?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Copland&#39;s Appalachian Spring danced by the orchestra musicians: confronting my memories of boredom four years ago</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/05/28/coplands-appalachian-spring-danced-by-the-orchestra-musicians-confronting-my-memories-of-boredom-four-years-ago/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2014 22:23:26 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/05/28/coplands-appalachian-spring-danced-by-the-orchestra-musicians-confronting-my-memories-of-boredom-four-years-ago/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I follow Greg Sandow&amp;rsquo;s blog on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.artsjournal.com/sandow/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;future of classical music&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. He posted an &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.artsjournal.com/sandow/2014/05/essential-video.html&#34;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; that got me thinking: he was all excited about an unorthodox performance of Aaron Copland&amp;rsquo;s half-hour-long &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Appalachian_Spring&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Appalachian Spring&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; by the University of Maryland Symphony Orchestra in which the students of the orchestra actually moved around and danced as well as played their instruments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a confession to make: back almost four years ago, in November 2010, I went to a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cmu.edu/news/archive/2010/November/nov15_cmunightwithpso.shtml&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Carnegie Mellon Night at the Symphony&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; in which &amp;ldquo;Appalachian Spring&amp;rdquo; was on the program. &lt;strong&gt;I got very bored during the piece.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing to remember is that the orchestra suite was actually arranged by Copland from his original piece that was an actual ballet for Martha Graham! So it&amp;rsquo;s actually kind of unnatural to experience this music &amp;ldquo;purely&amp;rdquo; as music. To me the suite is rather long and redundant without some kind of &amp;ldquo;story&amp;rdquo; to go along with it. So I watched the video of the orchestra-danced performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was definitely more interesting seeing action. At the same time, I got bored eventually anyway, after about 15 minutes. But I lasted longer with the physical action. However, I was also distracted by thoughts of how difficult it must have been for the orchestra to pull this off. I mean, marching band is one thing, but this is an orchestra and there was a ton of choreography and it&amp;rsquo;s not just marching.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s interesting that a commenter on Sandow&amp;rsquo;s blog criticized the
effort, writing: &lt;em&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s nicely done, I suppose, if you must do this
sort of thing. But when I go to an orchestral concert, I&amp;rsquo;m there for
the music, not for this sort of thing. To me, this doesn&amp;rsquo;t tell the
audience &amp;ldquo;this music is worth your time and attention,&amp;rdquo; it tells them
&amp;ldquo;we have so little faith that you’ll enjoy the music that we feel
compelled to trick it out with distractions.&amp;rdquo; I used to sing in a
chorus that was fond of &amp;ldquo;chorusography,&amp;rdquo; and it annoyed me as a
performer, too.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What do you think? Do you like this idea or does it annoy you?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Judge for yourself:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/jGSctM_8K_E&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How a homemade ice cream cookie sandwich touched my heart seven years ago</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/05/21/how-a-homemade-ice-cream-cookie-sandwich-touched-my-heart-seven-years-ago/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2014 20:09:43 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/05/21/how-a-homemade-ice-cream-cookie-sandwich-touched-my-heart-seven-years-ago/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Today&amp;rsquo;s was Carnegie Mellon University&amp;rsquo;s annual &amp;ldquo;staff picnic&amp;rdquo;. Basically, they provide some reasonable food in the University Center, including a variety of sandwiches and wraps (with many good vegetarian selections, by the way), and salads, and ice cream billed as &amp;ldquo;homemade ice cream sandwiches&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The menu in recent years has been pretty good, and stayed the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ate a single one of the ice cream cookie sandwiches, which was plenty! There were several different configurations: this time, I chose the chocolate ice cream sandwiched by chocolate chip cookies:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/cmu-staff-picnic-ice-cream-top.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Top view&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/cmu-staff-picnic-ice-cream-side.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Side view&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-big-disappointment-seven-years-ago-then-an-unexpected-surprise&#34;&gt;A big disappointment seven years ago, then an unexpected surprise&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The funny thing is that even as I enjoyed the staff appreciation lunch, my colleagues and I still remember a disappointment from seven years ago, when because of budget cuts and/or bad judgment, CMU put on a staff picnic that went horrifically wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically, they barely had enough food for everyone, there was no potato salad, and there was no ice cream at all! It was an insult to be &amp;ldquo;appreciated&amp;rdquo; in this manner: it would have been better to cancel the event than hold one that everyone would grumble about for seven years. I think only since last year did people really start forgetting about that one incident. Time heals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, however, I still remember the incident if only because of a counterbalancing incident that happened just a few hours later, after work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seven years ago, when I had only recently started dating Abby, she had invited me to come after work to her friend&amp;rsquo;s place for a little party the same day as the CMU staff picnic, so I went. I arrived complaining to her that I had not received my annual ice cream sandwich (in previous years of the CMU staff picnic, they always provided standard-brand ice cream sandwiches, nothing special, but at least something). It turned out that there was ice cream present at the party, and also cookies, so Abby just combined a pat of ice cream with two cookies and presented it to me! Although the ice cream melted quickly and so the &amp;ldquo;sandwich&amp;rdquo; didn&amp;rsquo;t work so well after all, the gesture was funny and kind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know it&amp;rsquo;s a tiny little thing to do, but it really touched my heart seven years ago. It was a surprise, unexpected, and just very sweet. It&amp;rsquo;s one of those memories that, when it pops up (spontaneously or because Abby reminds me, as she did tonight when I told her about eating a chocolate one this year rather than a vanilla one), makes me smile. There I was, disappointed by how CMU apparently didn&amp;rsquo;t care enough to truly &amp;ldquo;appreciate&amp;rdquo; its staff, and then there was Abby, making a little treat for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our fifth anniversary of marriage is coming up soon. It&amp;rsquo;s been easy to start forgetting the early moments from when we first met, but I&amp;rsquo;ve decided that it&amp;rsquo;s important to keep remembering and remain grateful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CMU must have gotten a lot of feedback from the debacle seven years ago, because the staff picnic went back to normal, and then eventually even improved further. In the past couple of years, they got away from the boring burgers and hot dogs entirely, and went to a much more healthy and interesting menu. Meanwhile, Abby still surprises me sometimes with a treat of some kind, such as when packing lunch for us when we got for a day of hiking. Life is the little things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How do you react to either negative or positive surprises? Which do you remember more, after the passage of time?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is there a grounding problem in empirical computational linguistics?</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/05/13/is-there-a-grounding-problem-in-empirical-computational-linguistics/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2014 20:28:29 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/05/13/is-there-a-grounding-problem-in-empirical-computational-linguistics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I saw an announcement for a lunch talk at CMU with the intriguing title &amp;ldquo;Theoretical and Practical Grounding in Empirical Computational Linguistics&amp;rdquo;, by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cl.uni-heidelberg.de/~riezler/&#34;&gt;Stefan Riezler&lt;/a&gt; of Heidelberg University.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abstract: &lt;strong&gt;Philosophy of science has pointed out a circularity problem in empirical sciences that arises if all known measuring procedures for a quantity of a theory presuppose the validity of this theory. We discuss how this problem relates to empirical computational linguistics, and define a criterion of T-non-theoretical grounding as guidance to avoid such circularities. We exemplify how this criterion can be met by crowdsourcing, task-related data annotation, or data in the wild. In particular, we illustrate the benefits of grounded learning in the area of statistical machine translation, e.g., by grounding machine translation in semantic parsing and in cross-lingual information retrieval.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/nlp-2014-05-13/presentation.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I attended the talk because of my long-standing interest in the philosophy of science, a subject I spent a lot of time studying in college (although my degree was in physics).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-problem&#34;&gt;The problem&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When using machine learning, there is a fundamental issue of whether one can run around in circles during feature discovery. For example, if you have labeled data, and you train a system, and then claim to find useful features which are actually just equivalent to what you were given, then there is a problem. Your system may not generalize to unseen data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Riezler opened with a simple example of the circularity problem of grounding in science involving Archimedean statics. Suppose you measure mass through use of a balance scale. Then how do you evaluate an empirical claim about the theory of Archimedean statics? If you use a balance scale, there is a circularity in the use of &lt;a href=&#34;http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/theoretical-terms-science/&#34;&gt;theoretical terms&lt;/a&gt;. Is there a way out? Yes, there is: use a different theory to &lt;em&gt;ground&lt;/em&gt; your terms: make a distinction, for a theory T, between T-theoretical and T-non-theoretical terms, and make a correspondence (some kind of &amp;ldquo;transfer&amp;rdquo;), so that non-circular progress can actually be made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his talk, Riezler presented methods of learning for machine translation that he claimed to be free of the circularity problem. One method is &amp;ldquo;naive&amp;rdquo; coders (rather than expert coders) and crowdsourcing. Another is semantic parsing in which evaluation is based on a real-world task, getting the right answer according to a gold standard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;questions&#34;&gt;Questions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some interesting questions were posed by the audience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;isn-t-circularity-only-a-problem-for-science-but-not-for-engineering-systems&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Isn&amp;rsquo;t circularity only a problem for science, but not for engineering systems?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Answer: a system that fails to generalize is a problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;how-can-we-know-if-we-are-doing-it-wrong&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;How can we know if we are doing it wrong?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Answer: talk to a social scientist!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;cookies&#34;&gt;Cookies&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cookies were available as part of lunch. In accordance with my promise, here are photos of two I ate:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/nlp-2014-05-13/cookie1.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/nlp-2014-05-13/cookie2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They were big. I should probably have eaten just the first one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not a working computational linguist, and it&amp;rsquo;s been over a decade since the only course I&amp;rsquo;ve taken in computational linguistics at CMU (in 2003), so I can&amp;rsquo;t pretend that I entirely followed the presentation, but I found interesting his attempt to apply philosophical considerations toward generating new ways to tackle empirical computational linguistics, and hope more people take philosophy seriously in the field of machine learning in general. I have an impression that some practitioners just sling data and numbers around, but may not be aware of the pitfalls of the grounding problem.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>&#34;Time to Taste the World&#34;: thoughts on expanding my food tastes as an adult</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/03/21/time-to-taste-the-world-thoughts-on-expanding-my-food-tastes-as-an-adult/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Mar 2014 21:37:07 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/03/21/time-to-taste-the-world-thoughts-on-expanding-my-food-tastes-as-an-adult/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This evening, right after work, I attended an event called &amp;ldquo;Time to Taste the World&amp;rdquo;, organized by Carnegie Mellon University&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cmu.edu/dietrich/modlang/student-organizations/mlsac.html&#34;&gt;Modern Languages Student Advisory Council&lt;/a&gt; for the Department of Modern Languages. It was an informal event featuring some food selections followed by a German film that I opted not to watch, since I needed to go home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were three tables of food, one for &amp;ldquo;Asian&amp;rdquo;, another for &amp;ldquo;Mediterranean&amp;rdquo;, and another for &amp;ldquo;European&amp;rdquo;. Obviously, only a very tiny fraction of the world was actually represented in this event, and the selections were mostly not very exciting, but it was interesting and even jarring going from one table to another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/time-to-taste-the-world-2014/mediterranean.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Mediterranean&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/time-to-taste-the-world-2014/asian.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Asian&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/time-to-taste-the-world-2014/european.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;European&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that standard CMU catering cookies were also provided.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did try a bit of everything, including stuff I less frequently encounter. Unexpectedly, the experience of hopping from one table to another, and sampling every single item, led me to reflect on how unfamiliar some of these items were to me until later in life, and how my taste in food has expanded considerably in my &lt;em&gt;30s and 40s&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;linking-my-history-of-eating-to-time-to-taste-the-world&#34;&gt;Linking my history of eating to &amp;ldquo;Time to Taste the World&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Most of what I like to eat now is what I never ate or knew existed before I was 30 years old&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This probably goes against &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.theguardian.com/lifeandstyle/wordofmouth/2013/jan/29/changing-tastes-food-and-aging&#34;&gt;most people&amp;rsquo;s eating histories&lt;/a&gt;, but heck, I&amp;rsquo;m a late bloomer, because for various reasons, I had very limited life experiences until my 30s and even more so, my 40s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For fun, I decided to think back about when it was that I first ate or even encountered, each of the items I sampled in &amp;ldquo;Time to Taste the World&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;mediterranean-table&#34;&gt;Mediterranean table&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pita bread: OK, I suppose I probably encountered this first in college, when the dorm cafeteria provided it and I used it to eat with tuna fish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grape leaves stuffed with rice: first time encountered and eaten was as a grad student at CMU in 1997, age 27, from Sree&amp;rsquo;s food truck, actually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hummus: also discovered in Pittsburgh upon arrival in 1997.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Baba ghanoush: also discovered in Pittsburgh upon arrival in 1997.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, I still love grape leaves and hummus. Baba ghanoush I still find a bit harsh and biting, but happily eat it in small quantities at a time. By the way, I should note that I discovered olive oil in 1997 also. At first its strong taste and appearance were confusing to me, but I got used to them, and have been using olive oil since as part of my everyday cooking, in fact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;asian-table&#34;&gt;Asian table&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OK, my parents were immigrants from Taiwan, so these foods have never been unfamiliar to me!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spring rolls: my mother makes them sometimes, and of course much better than the commercial frozen ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chicken wings: some of my favorite childhood food memories involve my mother&amp;rsquo;s chicken wings with soy sauce and ginger. Still my favorite flavor of wings!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Noodle dishes: again, my mother makes this stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.npr.org/2011/08/08/139033757/babys-palate-and-food-memories-shaped-before-birth&#34;&gt;our initial food tastes are actually formed in the womb&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;european-table&#34;&gt;European table&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OK, this is the stuff that I&amp;rsquo;m least familiar with, find overall least appealing, and still encounter surprises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was some &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gorgonzola&#34;&gt;gorgonzola&lt;/a&gt; cheese appetizer thing that I&amp;rsquo;ve had before, and I had some here, but it&amp;rsquo;s not really my thing. I don&amp;rsquo;t think I ever ate something like this until my 30s. The taste and texture is interesting. Not my favorite thing to eat, but I could have a little bit now and then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was also &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prosciutto&#34;&gt;prosciutto&lt;/a&gt; wrapped around some cheesy stuff, something I think I never tried until my 40s. Again, it still tastes weird to me, but I can eat it if I have to. It&amp;rsquo;s not revolting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main thing is that I have historically &lt;em&gt;fundamentally&lt;/em&gt; disliked all dairy. I emerged into the world seemingly hating milk: I don&amp;rsquo;t like the taste, I don&amp;rsquo;t like the smell. I was forced to drink milk as a toddler and basically accepted that I was supposed to drink it, and that it was the only thing to go with cereal, so I tolerated it all the way till I went to college. Then in freshman year in college, I came down with severe puzzling health problems, and finally found out by accident (upon missing breakfast for a couple of days) that cutting out my usual breakfast cereal with milk completely solved my problems: I was simply &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lactose_intolerance&#34;&gt;lactose intolerant&lt;/a&gt;. I cut down significantly on dairy consumption (which for me was only milk for cereal, and cheese on pizza).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point in my late 30s, I found that my lactose intolerance had let up, and with care I could eat some forms of dairy without having problems. Cheese on pizza is OK, if it&amp;rsquo;s not &amp;ldquo;extra thick&amp;rdquo;. Cheese in a serving of lasagna is typically not OK, in the quantities provided. Also, in my late 30s I began developing a taste for hard cheeses, which smell less bad to me, and happen to also have far less lactose, and so I do enjoy eating some hard cheeses occasionally: my favorite is &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gruy%C3%A8re_cheese&#34;&gt;Gruyère&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is some food awkwardness at home, because I&amp;rsquo;m married to Abby, who comes from the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nature.com/news/archaeology-the-milk-revolution-1.13471&#34;&gt;dairy-loving peoples&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;m perpetually having to tolerate the odor of dairy of all kinds at home. This is &lt;em&gt;quite difficult&lt;/em&gt; for me, but such is life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;notes-on-more-recent-food-adventures&#34;&gt;Notes on more recent food adventures&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I explored a tremendous amount of new food when I went vegetarian (for several months) at age 29, and got serious for the first time in my life, about cooking for myself. All kinds of bean, lentils, unfamiliar nuts, spices, herbs, vegetables such as kale, etc. Although I didn&amp;rsquo;t stay vegetarian long, that phase of my life resulted in the biggest explosion in my food taste diversity ever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I didn&amp;rsquo;t even touch beets until my mid-30s, when I was &amp;ldquo;forced&amp;rdquo; to because they came in my &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.kretschmannfarm.com/&#34;&gt;farm subscription box&lt;/a&gt;. A whole bunch of other unfamiliar vegetables have come my way through my annual subscription since I began it. The latest was celeriac, which I had never even heard of until it started showing up in our farm box last year. I figured out stuff to do with it, and I like it! It&amp;rsquo;s fantastic continuing to discover new stuff to cook and eat. Life is not boring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m even learning to eat &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brussels_sprout&#34;&gt;Brussels sprouts&lt;/a&gt;. My initial experiences in my 30s made me want to vomit, but there are ways to cook these to make them much more palatable, and in the past couple of years, I have enough tolerable experiences that I can see myself trying them more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;cookies&#34;&gt;Cookies&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did eat some cookies at the event, but only three, in accordance with &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/03/16/pittsburgh-recorder-society-something-new-recently-recording-our-practice-sessions/&#34;&gt;my recent findings about how many I should eat at a time&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/time-to-taste-the-world-2014/cookie1.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Cookie 1&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/time-to-taste-the-world-2014/cookie2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Cookie 2&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/time-to-taste-the-world-2014/cookie3.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Cookie 3&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s never too late to try new foods. You might be surprised and enjoy something new. And if you don&amp;rsquo;t like it, you don&amp;rsquo;t have to keep eating it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m very grateful to have had the opportunity to try new foods now and then, and add to my enjoyment of life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many thanks to the Modern Languages Department at CMU for sponsoring this little event! I hope many of the students attending it got some exposure to new foods that they will remember for the rest of their lives.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Geeking out at the annual CMU psychology holiday party: beauty and selling out</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/12/02/geeking-out-at-the-annual-cmu-psychology-holiday-party/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2013 20:31:24 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/12/02/geeking-out-at-the-annual-cmu-psychology-holiday-party/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;At the annual &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.psy.cmu.edu/&#34;&gt;CMU psychology department&lt;/a&gt; holiday party this year, the featured entertainment is the pub quiz, which my office team has come in second place basically every year since its existence. (Although we never win, we believe that if we accumulate the standings over the years, we are clearly first: our consistent second place performance clearly beats the wild variance of any of the other teams&amp;rsquo; performances.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a movie trivia category that we did very well in. Given a graphic, we were to determine the film title represented by the graphic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, one of the images had everyone confused and silent, except for me, it seemed:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/math-quiz.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Math quiz&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-answer&#34;&gt;The answer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer was immediately obvious to me, certifying me as the math geek in the department. Understandably, most psychology department people are not math geeks; but I&amp;rsquo;m not a psychologist, but a programmer, and my college degree is in physics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer is, of course, &amp;ldquo;Beauty and the Beast&amp;rdquo;, because &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Euler%27s_identity&#34;&gt;Euler&amp;rsquo;s identity&lt;/a&gt; is the &amp;ldquo;most beautiful equation&amp;rdquo; in all of mathematics. There is simply no doubt about this; it is so amazing and wondrous that if you&amp;rsquo;ve studied mathematics seriously, contemplating this equation is like seeing God or something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And &amp;ldquo;666&amp;rdquo; is, by contrast, the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Number_of_the_beast&#34;&gt;mark of the beast&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-genuine-most-beautiful-equation-in-mathematics&#34;&gt;The genuine &amp;ldquo;most beautiful&amp;rdquo; equation in mathematics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I have to add a disclaimer: Euler&amp;rsquo;s identity as we know it is &lt;em&gt;not really&lt;/em&gt; the most beautiful equation. It has a real flaw: it uses pi (&lt;em&gt;π&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/14/for-real-geeks-today-is-not-pi-day-but-half-tau-day/&#34;&gt;pi is a terrible mistake in the history of mathematics&lt;/a&gt;. The correct equation, had history adopted &lt;a href=&#34;http://tauday.com/&#34;&gt;tau instead of pi&lt;/a&gt;, would have been more beautiful:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://img.spikedmath.com/comics/fact-005-embrace-the-tau.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Euler with tau&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(Images from &lt;a href=&#34;http://spikedmath.com/fact-005.html&#34;&gt;Spiked Math&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, Euler&amp;rsquo;s identity as we know it is &lt;em&gt;not quite&lt;/em&gt; the most beautiful equation. But it could be, if we all embraced tau.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;back-to-reality&#34;&gt;Back to reality&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I wasn&amp;rsquo;t going to get any points for the team by snidely answering the question with the nonexistent film title &amp;ldquo;Half Beauty and the Beast&amp;rdquo;. What can I say, I swallowed my pride and sold out to score an important point for our team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given how easily I sold out, it is clear that a hundred years from now, we&amp;rsquo;ll all still be using pi instead of tau.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2014-05-09&#34;&gt;(Update of 2014-05-09)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is an interesting video reporting on brain research into the experience of &amp;ldquo;mathematical beauty&amp;rdquo; (both in mathematicians and non-mathematicians):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe id=&#34;dit-video-embed&#34; width=&#34;640&#34; height=&#34;360&#34;
src=&#34;http://snagplayer.video.dp.discovery.com/855979/snag-it-player.htm?auto=no&#34;
frameborder=&#34;0&#34; scrolling=&#34;no&#34; allowtransparency=&#34;true&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A fine trumpet recital by Erin Yanacek</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/11/25/a-fine-trumpet-recital-by-erin-yanacek/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Nov 2013 22:24:39 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/11/25/a-fine-trumpet-recital-by-erin-yanacek/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://static.erinyanacek.com/img/home_page_new_photo_3.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Erin Yanacek&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I attended a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.music.cmu.edu/events/282&#34;&gt;graduate trumpet recital&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&#34;http://erinyanacek.com/&#34;&gt;Erin Yanacek&lt;/a&gt;, in which she performed works of Robert Planel, Camille Saint-Saens, George Enescu, Franz Joseph Haydn, and Herbert L. Clarke.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2014-07-28&#34;&gt;(Update of 2014-07-28)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Erin has posted a video of the Herbert L. Clarke work from her recital:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/oBV4u360Ats&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-little-about-erin&#34;&gt;A little about Erin&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I first encountered Erin, without yet knowing who she was, from &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/04/29/attending-my-first-cmu-baroque-ensemble-concert/&#34;&gt;attending a CMU Baroque Ensemble Concert for the first time over a year ago&lt;/a&gt;. Then, some months later, without knowing the name or connecting it with anyone I had seen before, I saw a heartfelt article she wrote for a new blog on the arts, &lt;a href=&#34;http://musedialogue.org/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Muse Dialogue&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://musedialogue.org/2013/02/11/seeking-the-love-of-music-that-i-once-felt/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Seeking the love of music that I once felt&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. Then I bumped into her at a party Abby and I attended, and I finally connected the dots. It also turned out that she is a serious runner, and we&amp;rsquo;ve accidentally crossed paths while both running in the trails of Frick Park. And she&amp;rsquo;s also a cyclist and has done the wildly difficult Pittsburgh &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dannychew.com/dd_11.html&#34;&gt;Dirty Dozen&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, if you&amp;rsquo;re a fan of Pittsburgh&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rivercitybrass.org/&#34;&gt;River City Brass&lt;/a&gt;, you may have seen her recently, as she is now a cornet player there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;it-s-about-the-music&#34;&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s about the music&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I rather enjoy Erin&amp;rsquo;s playing. She&amp;rsquo;s a versatile and sensitive musician, adept at different styles and different moods, exploring and showcasing what the trumpet can express. Whether it&amp;rsquo;s pure brilliance, classical elegance, tender and lyrical romanticism, or jazzy/bluesy attitude and rhythm, I&amp;rsquo;m pretty impressed by the range of what Erin can do using a trumpet to communicate. Erin&amp;rsquo;s program was a tasty sampler of trumpet delight. I especially like the way she shapes phrases, really making the instrument sing and speak.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pittsburgh is blessed to have Erin as part of the local community of excellent musicians, and I hope to continue seeing her perform when I can! Check her out.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Chamber music concert at CMU featured Bach&#39;s Goldberg Variations arranged for string trio</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/11/19/chamber-music-concert-at-cmu-featured-bachs-goldberg-variations-arranged-for-string-trio/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Nov 2013 23:04:37 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/11/19/chamber-music-concert-at-cmu-featured-bachs-goldberg-variations-arranged-for-string-trio/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.cmu.edu/news/stories/archives/2013/november/images/chamber-recital_400x340.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;David Harding, Noah Bendix-Balgley, Lorna McGhee, Amit Peled&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I attended a special &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cmu.edu/news/stories/archives/2013/november/nov8_chambermusic.html&#34;&gt;chamber music concert at CMU&lt;/a&gt; that featured some truly excellent musicians.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-musicians&#34;&gt;The musicians&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was particularly interested in seeing &lt;a href=&#34;http://trioverlaine.com/bios/lorna-mcghee/&#34;&gt;Lorna McGhee&lt;/a&gt;, the current principal flute of the Pittsburgh Symphony Orchestra, and violinist &lt;a href=&#34;http://noahbendixbalgley.com/&#34;&gt;Noah Bendix-Balgley&lt;/a&gt;, the concertmaster, both of whom are relatively recent additions to the orchestra. The other two musicians, also fantastic, were violist and CMU professor &lt;a href=&#34;http://trioverlaine.com/bios/david-harding/&#34;&gt;David Harding&lt;/a&gt; and cellist &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amitpeled.com/&#34;&gt;Amit Peled&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;mozart-s-flute-quartet-no-1-in-d-major&#34;&gt;Mozart&amp;rsquo;s flute quartet no. 1 in D major&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lorna McGhee played in the first part of the program, which was Mozart&amp;rsquo;s first flute quartet. I was very curious how she would approach the work, because I&amp;rsquo;m very picky nowadays about the performance of music from the 18th century or earlier, which I far prefer to be both on period instruments and in period style. The typical &amp;ldquo;modern&amp;rdquo; performance I can no longer enjoy, because of stylistic anachronisms that in my mind invalidate the beauty and freshness of early music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed the quartet&amp;rsquo;s performance of the Mozart. The playing was crisp, lively, and transparent. There was little to quibble with in Lorna McGhee&amp;rsquo;s performance: she played with verve, sensitivity, and clarity. In some phrases she held a legato longer than I would like, but overall I quite liked the performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;bach-s-goldberg-variations-arranged-for-string-trio-by-dmitry-sitkovetsky&#34;&gt;Bach&amp;rsquo;s Goldberg Variations arranged for string trio by Dmitry Sitkovetsky&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bulk of the program was devoted to a performance by the string trio of the entire Goldberg Variations by Bach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past quarter century, I&amp;rsquo;ve listened to countless performances of the Goldberg Variations on all kinds of keyboard instrument, including harpsichord, fortepiano, and modern piano, but until tonight, I hadn&amp;rsquo;t bothered listening to Sitkovetsky&amp;rsquo;s arrangement for string trio that came out several years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought it worked out pretty well tonight, with the three string players working really hard to create dynamism and contrast along with unity in this monumental work. I couldn&amp;rsquo;t help but think that it&amp;rsquo;s actually harder to pull off as a trio than as a solo keyboard piece. What was particularly interesting was visually seeing and hearing (in the different tonal qualities) all the different voices in the music. They are there in the original version, of course, but experiencing the spatial separation just made me even more amazed by Bach&amp;rsquo;s creation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I appreciate the time the four musicians took to perform in this chamber music recital free to the public, and thank you, CMU, for bringing them in for these invigorating performances of Mozart and Bach!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Finally learning about Carnatic music</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/10/finally-learning-about-carnatic-music/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2013 23:04:45 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/10/finally-learning-about-carnatic-music/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://f0.bcbits.com/img/a2399391511_2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Sandeep Narayan&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I attended the Thursday CMU music school convocation that featured a &lt;a href=&#34;http://music.cmu.edu/events/267&#34;&gt;lecture/performance by Sandeep Narayan and his brother Nirmal Narayan&lt;/a&gt;. I very much enjoyed the presentation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://sandeepnarayanmusic.com/&#34;&gt;Sandeep Narayan&lt;/a&gt; is a Carnatic musician. &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carnatic_music&#34;&gt;Carnatic music&lt;/a&gt; is the &amp;ldquo;classical&amp;rdquo; music of Southern India. I&amp;rsquo;d never specifically listened to it before, because I&amp;rsquo;d never had an introduction to it so that I would know what to listen for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sandeep is unusual in that he was born and grew up in the US, in Los Angeles, before eventually settling in Chennai, the center of Carnatic music. I imagine he must have faced quite a bit of curiosity and skepticism as one who walks between two worlds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, his introduction to the elements of Carnatic music, along with brief performance excerpts with his brother (Sandeep sang and Nirmal provided percussion backup), was fantastic! It was a very clear introduction to the elements of pitches, scales/modes, rhythms, and different levels of improvisation. It was particularly helpful that he related the different vocabulary to that of Western &amp;ldquo;classical&amp;rdquo; music and jazz.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wish I had been able to attend the free concert he was giving this evening, but in any case, after receiving this introduction, I feel ready to pursue Carnatic music further as a listener. I always feel intimidated and lost when thinking about how to understand a new kind of music; I&amp;rsquo;m not quite adventurous enough to just jump in with a tiny bit of prior background knowledge. Introductions like his go a long way to providing just enough that it is possible to start enjoying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing Sandeep emphasized is how the music is fundamentally based on &lt;em&gt;improvisation&lt;/em&gt;. He joked that his instrumentalist accompanists have to know more about music than he does, because they all have to follow wherever he goes. They have no idea what he is going to do with the musical material, till he is actually doing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is his &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/user/SRNChannel&#34;&gt;YouTube channel&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>9 things you could be doing in Pittsburgh on Saturday, October 5</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/04/9-things-you-could-be-doing-in-pittsburgh-on-saturday-october-5/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2013 00:46:44 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/04/9-things-you-could-be-doing-in-pittsburgh-on-saturday-october-5/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m always frustrated at this time of year because there are so many events of interest to me in Pittsburgh that seem to happen on the first weekend of October. Since I cannot attend all of them, I figured I might as well attempt a public service and mention some of them so that if you are in the Pittsburgh area, maybe you can go and enjoy what I can&amp;rsquo;t attend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So here are 9 of the probably dozens of cool things you could be doing tomorrow, Saturday, October 5, 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;free-concert-allegheny-city-ragtime-orchestra&#34;&gt;Free concert: Allegheny City Ragtime Orchestra&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re interested in ragtime or Latin music, check out &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.shadysideacademy.org/page.cfm?p=12541&#34;&gt;this concert by the Allegheny City Ragtime Orchestra&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some articles in anticipation of it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.post-gazette.com/stories/ae/music/preview-ragtime-orchestra-connects-with-history-705929/&#34;&gt;Post-Gazette&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://triblive.com/aande/music/4763900-74/ragtime-music-concert&#34;&gt;Trib&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I wanted to go, but finally decided that we have too many other activities earlier in the day and need to just stay home and unwind in the evening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;free-conference-podcamp-pittsburgh-8&#34;&gt;Free conference: PodCamp Pittsburgh 8&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 8th annual &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.podcamppittsburgh.com/&#34;&gt;PodCamp Pittsburgh&lt;/a&gt; should be good. If you have any interest in using social media for personal or professional purposes, you should check it out. Interesting talks, opportunities to just socialized and learn new things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I attended in 2010, 2011, 2012, and will attend again for the fourth year. Unfortunately, I will only be able to attend the afternoon sessions. But I didn&amp;rsquo;t want to completely miss it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that PodCamp completely changed my life. For example, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/21/one-month-anniversary-of-my-blog/&#34;&gt;I started this blog in 2011 because of my second PodCamp&lt;/a&gt;, and I became serious about using social media in general, and that led to a total transformation of my life as I learned about local activities and made new friends. (Unfortunately, I didn&amp;rsquo;t get around to finishing my draft reports about my experience at last year&amp;rsquo;s PodCamp 7.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;pittsburgh-south-side-slopes-step-trek&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh South Side Slopes Step Trek&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The annual &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.southsideslopes.org/steptrek/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh South Side Slopes Step Trek&lt;/a&gt; is another event you can attend tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/08/my-god-its-full-of-stairs-pittsburgh-step-trek-2011/&#34;&gt;blog coverage two years ago&lt;/a&gt; as well as my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/09/25/why-you-should-go-out-to-the-pittsburgh-south-side-slopes-step-trek/&#34;&gt;recent update&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, Abby and I will be missing it this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;run-shadyside-5k&#34;&gt;Run Shadyside 5K&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you like to run in races, a fine race is the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.runshadyside.com/&#34;&gt;Run Shadyside 5K&lt;/a&gt;. Fast and flat, with a pancake breakfast and festivities afterwards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not running in it this year, just because I have too many other things to do already for the rest of the day, but here&amp;rsquo;s my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/01/run-shadyside-5k-outrunning-mickey-mouse-and-lending-a-trumpet/&#34;&gt;report from two years ago&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;free-5th-annual-wilkins-school-community-center-ecofest-in-regent-square&#34;&gt;Free: 5th annual Wilkins School Community Center Ecofest in Regent Square&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/ecofest-2013.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;5th annual Wilkins School Community Center Ecofest in Regent Square&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Interested in green living? Check out the &lt;a href=&#34;http://foresthills-regentsquare.patch.com/groups/around-town/p/ecofest-encourages-recycling-green-living&#34;&gt;5th annual Wilkins School Community Center Ecofest in Regent Square&lt;/a&gt;. Abby has regularly attended for the clothing swap. There will also be food, information, and entertainment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that this year, I will also be attending, to perform as a new member of the Steel City Ukuleles. &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/08/23/another-unexpected-life-change-one-month-of-learning-to-play-ukulele/&#34;&gt;I just started playing the ukulele a bit over two months ago&lt;/a&gt;, and have been working hard to help put on an entertaining show!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;ll be performing around 11:30 AM to 12:30 PM. If you come, say hello!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;cmu-donut-dash-2-mile-race&#34;&gt;CMU Donut Dash 2 mile race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, if you are into weird running events, there is the &lt;a href=&#34;http://cmudonutdash.org/&#34;&gt;Carnegie Mellon University Donut Dash&lt;/a&gt;, a 2 mile event serving as a fundraiser for the Children&amp;rsquo;s Hospital of Pittsburgh of UPMC. This is not an event I have ever done, and not one I intend to do, but what the heck, some of you might love this sort of thing!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;national-chess-day-gateway-open-tournament-at-the-pittsburgh-chess-club&#34;&gt;National Chess Day: Gateway Open tournament at the Pittsburgh Chess Club&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did you know that it&amp;rsquo;s time for &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nationalchessday.com/&#34;&gt;National Chess Day&lt;/a&gt;? There will be a tournament at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburghcc.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Chess Club&lt;/a&gt;, the 56th annual Gateway Open. Yes, chess in Pittsburgh has a long and illustrious history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;pittsburgh-perl-workshop&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Perl Workshop&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are a Perl programmer, the &lt;a href=&#34;http://pghpw.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Perl Workshop&lt;/a&gt; is back &lt;a href=&#34;http://pghpw.org/ppw2013/&#34;&gt;this year&lt;/a&gt;. Registration is already closed, so it&amp;rsquo;s not so helpful right now for me to mention it, but in case you didn&amp;rsquo;t know it existed, watch for it next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;ninth-thing&#34;&gt;Ninth thing?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, I guess I miscounted. But there are a whole lot more than nine things to do in Pittsburgh tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, if you are interested in some free stuff to do, there&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.radworkshere.org/interior.php?pageID=64&#34;&gt;RADical Days&lt;/a&gt; listing a whole bunch of stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s no shortage of stuff to do in this great city of Pittsburgh at any time or day of year. I think it&amp;rsquo;s unfortunate that many things I like to do happen to repeatedly fall on the first Saturday of the year, but I&amp;rsquo;m not complaining about an embarrassment of riches. Go out and take advantage of what I can&amp;rsquo;t.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>First rehearsal for my first ukulele gig: dealing with anxiety</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/09/26/first-rehearsal-for-my-first-ukulele-gig/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Sep 2013 23:09:23 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/09/26/first-rehearsal-for-my-first-ukulele-gig/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s now officially &lt;em&gt;two months&lt;/em&gt; since &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/08/23/another-unexpected-life-change-one-month-of-learning-to-play-ukulele/&#34;&gt;I started learning to play ukulele&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s hard to believe, but two months ago, I was still struggling to play three chords: I could play C, of course, but had trouble with G7, and had even worse trouble with F: I had no finger strength or dexterity and could not arch my fingers and everything was a painful buzz, and I could spend only five minutes a day practicing because of the pain on my uncalloused fingers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And after just over a month of playing, and joining the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/Steel-City-Ukuleles/&#34;&gt;Steel City Ukuleles&lt;/a&gt;, I had volunteered to &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/09/04/my-second-meeting-of-the-steel-city-ukuleles/&#34;&gt;perform in a gig for Ecofest in Regent Square&lt;/a&gt;, as a way to force myself to maintain momentum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this week, just in time, I got my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/09/23/finally-got-a-nice-new-ukulele-mainland-classic-mahogany-concert/&#34;&gt;brand new concert-sized ukulele&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/ecofest-2013-rehearsal-1.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;First Ecofest rehearsal&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The gig is in just over a week. I attended my first rehearsal with extreme anxiety. I was even thinking about bailing out instead of attending. Here&amp;rsquo;s why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;new-music-for-me&#34;&gt;New music for me&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/steel-city-ukuleles-bound-thing-1.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/steel-city-ukuleles-bound-thing-2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I went into rehearsal with basically &lt;em&gt;none&lt;/em&gt; of the songs we were going to perform. So it was basically a sight reading and singing session for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One reason is that I was waiting to get the official bound compilation of performance songs that we were to receive at the first rehearsal, which we did. I had not requested to get one ahead of time, because I was too busy all week anyway to make good use of it if I had possessed it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, it turns out that many of these songs are already familiar and played by most of the other members of the performance group; they are part of the general repertoire, for previous years&amp;rsquo; Ecofests as well as for other gigs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;new-performance-group-for-me&#34;&gt;New performance group for me&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that breaking into a performance group for the first time always involves an initial learning curve because there are those who already know everything inside and out. I still have very vivid memories of other times in my life when I have entered a performance group and felt lost for a while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was briefly in marching band, during the 9th grade in high school. As a new freshman, I was unfamiliar with the repertoire, the choreography, etc. It was a tricky experience for all us freshmen, of course, amidst the 10th, 11th, and 12th graders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, over a decade ago, for a couple of years I was a member of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://cmubdc.org/&#34;&gt;Carnegie Mellon University ballroom dance club&lt;/a&gt;, and I was on both the competition team as well as the formation team. I&amp;rsquo;d made ballroom dancing the main focus of my life, throwing myself into lessons and competition and being in performances with the formation team while still a beginner. I improved my dancing significantly and quickly as a result of jumping in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And more recently, I have been performing in a small &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/09/playing-music-on-recorders-at-a-phipps-conservatory-candlelight-evening/&#34;&gt;recorder quartet/quintet at winter holiday time&lt;/a&gt;. Practicing so that I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t totally flub everything always took a huge amount of work for me, but the side effect was that I really improved my recorder playing and musicianship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I know firsthand the benefits of just jumping in and being around very experienced team members who are inspirational to emulate and learn from, and to exert some healthy pressure on myself not to let the team down!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;listening-watching&#34;&gt;Listening, watching&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of what I did during rehearsal was listening and watching, while doing what I could to keep up and go and make dozens of mistakes everywhere. (It&amp;rsquo;s particularly important to boldly make those mistakes and write down what to work on for homework.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was no way I was going to be able to play everything at first sight. In fact, that&amp;rsquo;s not even the right way to think about the situation. This isn&amp;rsquo;t classical music where you really do &amp;ldquo;sight read&amp;rdquo;. This is music where almost everything is transmitted &lt;em&gt;by ear&lt;/em&gt;. Not knowing the melodies, and not having an actual score, I have to listen and figure out where the melodic lines roughly are, and where the chord changes are. I have to learn what the prevailing strum rhythms and breaks and mood the group has largely decided on. The goal is to learn how to blend in and contribute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t do much extended &lt;em&gt;singing&lt;/em&gt; during this rehearsal. But we have two more rehearsals after this one, so it was not necessary to get everything down right away. I would, of course, be doing my own homework, looking up YouTube videos, in between official rehearsals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For consistency, I found it very useful to focus my listening on one person at a time to emulate. Usually that person was Sunny, because she is leading us. Sometimes that was Adam, because I was sitting near him and because as a strong male voice, I could follow him especially in songs where we had male and female voices split.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fact that there were over a dozen of us in the group for this gig was very helpful to me, because it meant that there was much less pressure on me to get everything right. I don&amp;rsquo;t always have to sing, or sing everything. I don&amp;rsquo;t always have to play the tricky chord progressions that I&amp;rsquo;m not ready yet to get right. I can leave stuff out judiciously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;half-the-songs&#34;&gt;Half the songs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In two hours, we covered half the songs we planned to play at Ecofest. I felt there was still a huge amount of work for me to do in order to really contribute to the group, but no longer felt helpless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-cost-of-excellence&#34;&gt;The cost of excellence&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still think it&amp;rsquo;s a little crazy that I jumped into committing to performing when still a beginner at ukulele, but in the past couple of years, I have learned that shorter, tighter learning and creating cycles considerably speed up the improvement process, provided that one actually puts in the hard work on a daily basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s been a huge cost, unfortunately. I have let some things slide while focusing on ukulele in the past two months. For example, I have been playing chess very poorly. Last week, I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/09/26/the-chess-improver-the-psychology-of-not-winning-the-won-game/&#34;&gt;drew a game that I should have won&lt;/a&gt;. And just two days ago, disaster struck: in my fatigue, I lost a game I should have won. If I had known I was going to have ukulele take over my life outside of work, I would have chosen &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; to play in the current chess tournament.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now as in the past couple of years, I have chosen to sacrifice my chess performance when other things come up. This is why I rarely play chess tournaments any more: I hate playing worse than I am actually capable of playing. As I mentioned two weeks ago, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/09/15/saying-no-on-not-playing-in-the-pittsburgh-chess-league-this-season-for-the-cmu-tartans/&#34;&gt;I had anticipated becoming busy in November&lt;/a&gt;, but I had not anticipated being so busy now already, in September!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sunny led a great rehearsal for our Ecofest gig coming up. I really like some of these songs we&amp;rsquo;re working on, and left feeling that after more work, we can sound really good and have a lot of fun at the gig!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On not celebrating Constitution Day this year, 2013</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/09/17/on-not-celebrating-constitution-day-this-year/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2013 08:42:26 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/09/17/on-not-celebrating-constitution-day-this-year/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;For several years, I&amp;rsquo;ve made a habit of observing &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Constitution_Day_(United_States)&#34;&gt;Constitution Day&lt;/a&gt; by attending the annual exhibit and lecture at CMU. Last year I reported on &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/18/is-constitution-day-constitutional/&#34;&gt;an interesting session about the very invention of Constitution Day&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://events.web.cmu.edu/ecal/event/137831259599848837&#34;&gt;This year&lt;/a&gt;, the program for the event &lt;a href=&#34;http://cmlibblog.wordpress.com/2013/08/13/constitution-day-celebration/&#34;&gt;held at the Posner Center&lt;/a&gt; at CMU read:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
David Harris, distinguished faculty scholar and professor of law at the University of Pittsburgh School of Law, will deliver a keynote speech titled &#34;How Will America Be Remembered? A Constitution Day Journey Into the Future&#34; at approximately 3:30 p.m. Light refreshments will be served. An original copy of the Bill of Rights will be on display.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ended up deciding not to attend today, for several reasons. One is that I have a lot of stuff to get done at work right now. But even if that weren&amp;rsquo;t the case, my heart was not into celebrating Constitution Day this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-will-america-be-remembered&#34;&gt;How will America be remembered?&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/6/60/Edward_Snowden-2.jpg/199px-Edward_Snowden-2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Because the story is still far from over, I haven&amp;rsquo;t said much on my blog about the events that have been unfolding for some months now since &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_Snowden&#34;&gt;Edward Snowden&lt;/a&gt; exposed information about the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2013_mass_surveillance_disclosures&#34;&gt;surveillance activities of the National Security Agency&lt;/a&gt;. He &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.theguardian.com/world/2013/jul/12/edward-snowden-full-statement-moscow&#34;&gt;explained his actions as justified by the violation of the 4th and 5th Amendments to the Constitution&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
The 4th and 5th Amendments to the Constitution of my country, Article 12 of the Universal Declaration of Human Rights, and numerous statutes and treaties forbid such systems of massive, pervasive surveillance. While the US Constitution marks these programs as illegal, my government argues that secret court rulings, which the world is not permitted to see, somehow legitimize an illegal affair. These rulings simply corrupt the most basic notion of justice -- that it must be seen to be done. The immoral cannot be made moral through the use of secret law.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I do a Web search for &amp;ldquo;Edward Snowden&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Constitution&amp;rdquo;, I mostly find pro-Snowden articles that affirm his point of view of the NSA programs as being unconstitutional. Here is &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.newsworks.org/index.php/blogs/brandywine-to-broad/item/56244-nsa-leaks-by-edward-snowden-threaten-constitutional-self-government&#34;&gt;one exception&lt;/a&gt; you may wish to read.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find it interesting that much of the media coverage of Edward Snowden&amp;rsquo;s actions do not actually reference his claim of unconstitutionality, but focus on other matters, such as the nature of his education or possible ulterior motives for leaking, or whether his actions may prove harmful to national security or other interests. These may be interesting and important questions, but sidestep his primary claim and stated motive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;too-early-to-tell&#34;&gt;Too early to tell&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did not attend the &lt;a href=&#34;http://wesa.fm/post/us-constitution-224-years-later-why-it-endures&#34;&gt;David Harris&lt;/a&gt;, although it might have been interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think Snowden&amp;rsquo;s actions and their repercussions will add an extra twist to the age-old question of whether the Constitution is to be interpreted under &amp;ldquo;original intent&amp;rdquo; or as a &amp;ldquo;living document&amp;rdquo;, and even whether the Constitution should be &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2012/12/31/opinion/lets-give-up-on-the-constitution.html&#34;&gt;abandoned&lt;/a&gt;, if interpretations either way simply come to be seen as purely political game-playing to justify &amp;ldquo;constitutional&amp;rdquo; as simply meaning &amp;ldquo;what I like&amp;rdquo;. The most interesting thing right now is that prominent voices on both the &amp;ldquo;left&amp;rdquo; and the &amp;ldquo;right&amp;rdquo; (the libertarian wing) have united in denouncing the activities of the NSA as unconstitutional.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not a political blog, and political theory is not my main area of interest or advocacy, but I thought it would be useful to make a few observations about current events for Constitution Day.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>