<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Music on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/music/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Music on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/music/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Accidentally discovering and performing some music by Brazilian composer Ernesto Nazareth: Coração que Sente</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/12/29/accidentally-discovering-and-performing-some-music-by-brazilian-composer-ernesto-nazareth-cora%C3%A7%C3%A3o-que-sente/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Dec 2015 23:05:10 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/12/29/accidentally-discovering-and-performing-some-music-by-brazilian-composer-ernesto-nazareth-cora%C3%A7%C3%A3o-que-sente/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In November, I fell in love with some music I accidentally discovered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What happened was that I was looking for some music for &lt;em&gt;flute&lt;/em&gt; and
&lt;em&gt;guitar&lt;/em&gt; to play, with me on flute and one of my friends on guitar, and
I did a simple search in the
&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/30/free-to-the-people-since-1895/&#34;&gt;local library&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://librarycatalog.einetwork.net/&#34;&gt;online catalog&lt;/a&gt;, and at the top
sorted by date was
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.halleonard.com/product/viewproduct.action?itemid=49044167&amp;amp;&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Brazilian folk tunes for flute and guitar&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;,
which came with a CD of sample performance tracks,
so I picked it up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What followed was a series of explorations that resulted in unexpected
changes in my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;exploring-the-brazilian-music-in-the-score-book&#34;&gt;Exploring the Brazilian music in the score book&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I listened to some tracks on the CD of this book of arrangements and
found the music (Brazilian polkas, tangos, waltzes) really
enchanting. Most of the music was by a composer
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ernesto_Nazareth&#34;&gt;Ernesto Nazareth&lt;/a&gt;,
who lived 1863-1934. I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t call this music &amp;ldquo;folk tunes&amp;rdquo;: it&amp;rsquo;s
a sophisticated combination of popular and classical styles using
catchy dance rhythms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m a real sucker for waltzes, so at first I thought I would pick one
of the beautiful waltzes to choose to suggest to play with a partner
on guitar. It came down to &amp;ldquo;Confidências&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;Coração que Sente&amp;rdquo;
(English translation: &amp;ldquo;Heart that Feels&amp;rdquo;). The
latter was much easier and shorter, as I learned while sight reading
through it with the CD track, so I thought I was done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;finding-astounding-performances-of-coração-que-sente-on-youtube&#34;&gt;Finding astounding performances of &amp;ldquo;Coração que Sente&amp;rdquo; on YouTube&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking for performances of the piece on YouTube to get an idea of
how people play it, I immediately entered a strange new world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, I learned that the original music was for
&lt;em&gt;piano&lt;/em&gt;. OK. Then, while listening to and/or watching a dozen or so
videos of performances of this piece (OK, I was obsessed), I found a
huge variety of interpretations, and some of them spoke to me more
than others. Some I found light and boring. The ones that interested
me were the ones that were extremely intense and probing. You might
think this music was just fluff, but I found a dark undercurrent
behind it that spoke to me, in that its different sections (the piece
is roughly in rondo form) present clear emotional contrasts, with
longing, melancholy, and manic excitement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;arthur-moreira-lima&#34;&gt;Arthur Moreira Lima&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A very intense performance I found was by a pianist named
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arthur_Moreira_Lima&#34;&gt;Arthur Moreira Lima&lt;/a&gt;
in 1975, used after the fact as soundtrack on YouTube for a silent
film using footage from 1929. What an odd pairing!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lima goes all out in Romantic expressiveness, with extensive rubato
and dynamic and rhythmic flexibility. It was completely different from
the relatively straight, danceable version on the flute/guitar CD
demo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have to listen to his performance (ignore the film or watch it, as
you wish):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Mmjt8RrfXtA&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;joão-carlos-assis-brasil&#34;&gt;João Carlos Assis Brasil&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even more extreme than Lima was this weird guy João Carlos Assis
Brasil, who is apparently so unknown in the English-speaking world
that Wikipedia doesn&amp;rsquo;t have an entry on him, although I found this
random
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bach-cantatas.com/Bio/Assis-Brasil-Joao-Carlos.htm&#34;&gt;pieced-together bio&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His live performance here from 2013 is the single most extreme, yet
deepest, interpretation of this waltz I found (he adds his own
ornamentation). I was deeply moved by it. (Warning, bad sound
quality.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/iG_o94sU1tE&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;other-good-performances&#34;&gt;Other good performances&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://pt.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fernanda_Chaves_Canaud&#34;&gt;Fernanda Canaud&lt;/a&gt;,
with a very expressive performance (including her own extensive
embellishments), uses drastic changes in articulation and tempo for
contrast. I particularly liked how naturally she seemed to express her
personality through the piece:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/-DfOYvNCaqk&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://pt.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maria_Teresa_Madeira&#34;&gt;Maria Theresa Madeira&lt;/a&gt;
captures well the moods of the different sections of the piece; I
really like the rhythmic alertness and drive throughout:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/eeztzLsF6Cc&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some random YouTube guy named Ilton, playing a really crappy upright
piano, but with amazing rhythmic expression that I totally love (if he
played this on a good piano, I would consider his interpretation one
of my favorites, period):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/b-gYk_YUoIM&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://lucianoalves.com.br/&#34;&gt;Luciano Alves&lt;/a&gt;, 2013, in an elegant
performance:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/y8LchR8Mi5Y&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://pt.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marcelo_Bratke&#34;&gt;Marcelo Bratke&lt;/a&gt; in a
relaxed, easygoing, dream interpretation with a lilt (but after all
the intense interpretations, I find this tame, I confess):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Pn5vYhfQYHs&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-performance-that-made-me-decide-to-learn-and-play-the-piece&#34;&gt;The performance that made me decide to learn and play the piece&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I spent a lot of time listening to and watching performances of the
piece, but one performance was the one that made me decide to go learn
and play the piece! It was this one by some random guy Marcelo Chiarella:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/QaQL9VlJy8s&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why? Because I could &lt;em&gt;relate to&lt;/em&gt; his playing:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;He wasn&amp;rsquo;t some famous pro pianist, as far as I could tell.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The sound quality was good and the recording was as though I were
standing right there, made me feel like I was in his home, and
nobody else there.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I could see his hands up close.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I liked various things he did with expression (especially when he
&lt;em&gt;wasn&amp;rsquo;t&lt;/em&gt; pedaling).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I knew that I could be much more expressive and personal
(remember, the title in English translation is &amp;ldquo;Heart that feels&amp;rdquo;)
while playing this piece &lt;em&gt;solo&lt;/em&gt;, on piano, than in a flute/guitar
duet. So I decided to go for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;finding-an-official-free-score&#34;&gt;Finding an official free score&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had to find a score. Luckily, it turned out that there was some
big
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ernestonazareth150anos.com.br/&#34;&gt;150-year anniversary celebration for Ernesto Nazareth&lt;/a&gt;
in 2013, and I found an official &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ernestonazareth150anos.com.br/files/uploads/work_elements/work_43/coracao_que_sente_piano.pdf&#34;&gt;free PDF score&lt;/a&gt; on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ernestonazareth150anos.com.br/works/view/43&#34;&gt;page for the piece&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That page also had a story about the title of the piece and why it was
composed. It was in Portuguese, so I tried with the help of Google
Translate to translate it (I only studied Portuguese for several weeks
many years ago), and pieced together (I hope I didn&amp;rsquo;t get this too
wrong) that Nazareth dedicated it to a student of his, Gabriella
Crauz, who had showed great emotion as Nazareth described the last
days of a dying nephew, as though she had been there herself
experiencing what he experienced as he saw the sights in the city one
last time. (If you know Portuguese, please correct me if I got the
story wrong.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This story only added to the sense I already had that this seemingly
simple piece hid a depth of emotion that some performers already
revealed for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-performance-of-coração-que-sente&#34;&gt;My performance of &amp;ldquo;Coração que Sente&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I started working on the piece, I had to decide where and when to
perform it. It turned out that I learned that friends who mean a lot
to me decided to move. This was really tough news to me, and they have
always invited me and Abby to their December holiday party, where I
play music, so I decided that I was going to perform the piece at
their (now farewell) party and openly dedicate my performance to them,
because they are human beings of deep feeling, hence &amp;ldquo;Heart that
feels&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I performed the piece at the party the day after Christmas. In my
nervousness, I completely lost my train of thought a couple of times
and botched things up inexplicably (I had gone through the piece with
no errors so many times at home), but I made it through, and my
gesture was appreciated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I then decided to quickly record myself at home soon after (and still
botched some things up), so here I am. This is for Henry and Gina:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34;
src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/VBOS9btMUPI&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;
allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;other-music-by-ernesto-nazareth&#34;&gt;Other music by Ernesto Nazareth&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spent all this time talking about just one piece by Nazareth, but he
wrote much more, and more substantial pieces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I totally love Fernanda Canaud&amp;rsquo;s performance of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ernestonazareth150anos.com.br/works/view/133&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Batuque&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, &amp;ldquo;Coração
que Sente&amp;rdquo;, and
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ernestonazareth150anos.com.br/works/view/136&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Odeon&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;
(the performance of &amp;ldquo;Coração que Sente&amp;rdquo; is very different from the one
I posted above: more inward, refined, beautiful rather than super-dramatic):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/U6WaAgRWqaw&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is Nazareth playing his own pieces in recordings from 1912-1930:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/eZS3bDNJEUY&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a one-hour special documentary video &amp;ldquo;Nazareth Revisitado&amp;rdquo;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/TJAT3pJJR6M&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-note-on-the-english-language-oriented-web&#34;&gt;A note on the English-language-oriented Web&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found a whole world of music and musicians that barely register in
the English-language-oriented part of the Web. Most of what I found
when trying to look up Nazareth or various Brazilian pianists was in
Portuguese. So it&amp;rsquo;s been really humbling to remember that many in the
English-speaking world might not even know about all these Brazilian
composers and musicians who are not big enough stars to warrant
international fame.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am grateful for accidentally discovering an entire world of
Brazilian music and performers of it through my search in the local
library catalog for music to play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am grateful for friends who inspire me by their examples as human
beings of genuine and great feeling.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How Ornette Coleman changed my life</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/06/12/how-ornette-coleman-changed-my-life/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jun 2015 23:59:40 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/06/12/how-ornette-coleman-changed-my-life/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The legendary jazz musician
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ornette_Coleman&#34;&gt;Ornette Coleman&lt;/a&gt;
recently died at age 85. He had not been on my radar for a long
time. In fact, I never actually listened to much of his music at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, my immediate first thought on hearing this news was, &lt;strong&gt;Ornette
Coleman permanently changed the course of my life&lt;/strong&gt;. How can this be?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;first-reactions-to-ornette-coleman-s-music&#34;&gt;First reactions to Ornette Coleman&amp;rsquo;s music&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2000, during a huge transition in my life that turned everything
upside down, I began experimenting with listening to a lot of kinds of
music I had never experienced before. I was exploring Cuban,
Brazilian, Argentinian music. I was exploring Western classical music
of the 20th century (I had a fairly narrow taste up till then focused
primarily on the Classical 18th century and Romantic 19th century,
with little before or after this range). In jazz, I was expanding
beyond the swing, bebop, hard bop eras of jazz. I frequently reached
areas that made me confused or disgusted. For example, in jazz I got
&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/23/celebrating-the-birthday-of-john-coltrane/&#34;&gt;as far as I could with John Coltrane&lt;/a&gt;
as Coltrane ventured into &amp;ldquo;free jazz&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided to try out Ornette Coleman for another approach to &amp;ldquo;free
jazz&amp;rdquo;, and checked out the album
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Shape_of_Jazz_to_Come&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Shape of Jazz to Come&amp;rdquo; (1959)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;lonely-woman&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Lonely Woman&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Immediately, I was struck by the track
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lonely_Woman_%28composition%29&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Lonely Woman&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. Conventional
concerns such as being strictly &amp;ldquo;in tune&amp;rdquo; were out the window, in
favor of extremely flexibility of pitch and raw, wailing emotional
expression. It showcased Coleman&amp;rsquo;s lyrical side and was easy to
love. OK, not too weird.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/DNbD1JIH344&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;other-tracks&#34;&gt;Other tracks&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But bam, that was just a warmup. For example, check out
&amp;ldquo;Eventually&amp;rdquo;. It&amp;rsquo;s very free indeed, a lot of notes, an expression of
hyperactive motion, conventional tonality unimportant. Still, not too
harsh, and not totally random.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/WoC69lxnS_Y&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, what I really understood from his music was that he was doing
what came naturally to him. It did not feel forced, it was not to
prove a point. He was enjoying what he was doing. This sense of
&lt;em&gt;freedom&lt;/em&gt; really impressed me. It wasn&amp;rsquo;t reaction, it wasn&amp;rsquo;t
rebellion. I respected that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;free-jazz-a-collective-improvisation&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Free Jazz: A Collective Improvisation&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next album I checked out was
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Free_Jazz:_A_Collective_Improvisation&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Free Jazz: A Collective Improvisation&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was a step beyond, and confusing to me because of the
simultaneous playing that often seemed chaotic. I confess to taking no
huge pleasure in attempting to listen to it all at once (note that
apart from lack of conventional structure, it also keeps going on and
on at length). I found it more enjoyable to listen to only a couple of
random minutes, trying to absorb some stretch of order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, although this was not really my thing, it opened up my mind
to &amp;ldquo;why not?&amp;rdquo; Maybe this particular experiment didn&amp;rsquo;t work, but I
could imagine a simpler setting, say, with fewer instruments, in which
collective improvisation could work out better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check it out yourself:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/xbZIiom9rDA&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;something-else&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Something Else!!!!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I checked out
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Something_Else!!!!&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Something Else!!!!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;,
which actually was his first album and closer to bebop and so forth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t have much to say about it, but it&amp;rsquo;s not too confusing to
enjoy, because of still audible ties to some traditional forms and
styles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;freedom&#34;&gt;Freedom&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, I didn&amp;rsquo;t continue exploring Coleman&amp;rsquo;s music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the sense of &lt;em&gt;freedom&lt;/em&gt;, of &lt;em&gt;permission&lt;/em&gt; to ignore boundaries and
go wherever, musically, really affected me. Was what he was doing
&amp;ldquo;jazz&amp;rdquo;? Listening to him, I made up my mind that I was never again
going to get involved in debates about what jazz &amp;ldquo;really is&amp;rdquo; or what
classical music &amp;ldquo;really is&amp;rdquo; or even what music &amp;ldquo;really is&amp;rdquo;. These
labels stopped being meaningful to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That was what I really learned from him and his life. By coincidence,
I just read this Rolling Stone article,
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rollingstone.com/music/news/vernon-reid-on-ornette-coleman-he-set-a-lot-of-people-free-20150612&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Vernon Reid on Ornette Coleman: &amp;lsquo;He set a lot of people free&amp;rsquo;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;,
that echoes exactly what I felt I learned fifteen years ago from my
brief exposure to him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past year or so, there have been times when, alone and not
likely to bother anyone, I pull out my bass recorder (ha, my lowest
instrument) and just go wild, play some melodic shapes, make up
rhythms, go multiphonic, whatever, for the sheer joy of it. And I&amp;rsquo;m
not embarrassed, because I remember Ornette Coleman and he gave us all
permission to express our unconscious in whatever honest way it comes
out. And he gave us permission to accept and encourage each other to
do that, whether or not we personally like or understand everything
that comes out of tapping the unconscious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hadn&amp;rsquo;t expected to think so much upon hearing of Ornette Coleman&amp;rsquo;s
death. But he set an example that I respected deeply, forever changing
not only my perceptions of music but of what musicians can and should
be allowed to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Are you an Ornette Coleman fan or detractor? Did he change your
  life? If so, how exactly?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Revisiting Bach&#39;s Air on G String, from a singing and dancing viewpoint</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/06/10/revisiting-bachs-air-on-g-string-from-a-singing-and-dancing-viewpoint/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jun 2015 23:46:26 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/06/10/revisiting-bachs-air-on-g-string-from-a-singing-and-dancing-viewpoint/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Three years ago, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/14/passion-of-bachs-air-on-the-g-string-three-different-interpretations/&#34;&gt;I wrote a post comparing three very different
performance styles&lt;/a&gt;
for Johann Sebastian Bach&amp;rsquo;s famous music,
&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Air_on_the_G_String&#34;&gt;Air on G String&lt;/a&gt;
and indicating which I preferred.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have received an unexpected number comments over the years, and
thought it was time to write an update of my thoughts in response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Primarily, I am responding to those who (correctly) criticized the
unfortunately chosen exemplar of the style that I preferred. I tried
to find better versions that might illustrate my perceptions. I also
integrated some thoughts based on how I perceive music as a singer and
as a dancer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;better-than-the-rushed-croatian-baroque-ensemble-s-performance&#34;&gt;Better than the rushed Croatian Baroque Ensemble&amp;rsquo;s performance?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I agreed quickly with the first commenters that the Croatian
ensemble&amp;rsquo;s performance was too perfunctory, even downright brutal and
unpleasant in various ways. I wish I had
chosen a better example of what I actually &lt;em&gt;like&lt;/em&gt; rather than &lt;em&gt;prefer
to the other two versions&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I searched YouTube for period-style performances that are
closer to what I envision than either the Croatian ensemble&amp;rsquo;s or
Koopman&amp;rsquo;s. It proved impossible for me to find a perfect performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-period-performance-i-like-more-christopher-hogwood&#34;&gt;A period performance I like more: Christopher Hogwood&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like this version by the late &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christopher_Hogwood&#34;&gt;Christopher Hogwood&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s Academy of
Ancient Music:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/nrtdhH8_47k&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a sweetness and &lt;em&gt;bouncy lightness&lt;/em&gt; to this version that I
like, but it is also somewhat anemic. Personally, I would play up more
contrast and fullness of sound and passion, but the overall tempo and
breathing to this version seems right to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;voices-of-music-richer-sound&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Voices of Music&amp;rdquo;: richer sound&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Voices of Music&amp;rdquo; here in a good performance:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/pzlw6fUux4o&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like the richness of sound in this performance. I miss the lighter,
more bouncy feeling that Hogwood brought out though. This performance
is a bit too legato for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;i-care-about-singing&#34;&gt;I care about singing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I approach this music from the viewpoint of singing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bouncy lightness is very important to me, along with the rhythmic
characterization. I feel this music as a song (it is an &amp;ldquo;air&amp;rdquo;, after
all), and I cannot help singing along when I hear it. Therefore, when
it&amp;rsquo;s taken too slow for me to sing and make it to natural breathing
points in phrases, that considerably lessens my pleasure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;yehudi-menuhin-solo-violin&#34;&gt;Yehudi Menuhin, solo violin&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s an interesting old black and white video of a performance by a young Yehudi Menuhin on violin with
accompaniment. It&amp;rsquo;s not a period performance, but moves along at a
decent &amp;ldquo;singing&amp;rdquo; tempo, as befits violin, that singing instrument.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34;
src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/08bDiKXW0gg&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;
allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I confess that I rather like this performance for its virtues,
although it distorts Bach&amp;rsquo;s music by so emphasizing just the musical
line, at the expense of the balance of the other voices and the
essential character of the dissonances among the voices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;more-menuhin-but-as-conductor&#34;&gt;More Menuhin, but as conductor&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s Yehudi Menuhin not as violin soloist but as conductor of the
Bath Festival Orchestra in 1960. Again, not a period performance, but
he takes the music briskly, and has the violins create sufficient
phrase delineations that I feel the music alertly as though it sings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s direct and clear, maybe not the most subtle and warm,
but I like it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/kaBAE4stNIo&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;dancing-is-possible-too&#34;&gt;Dancing is possible too&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also like to dance to expressive music. A pioneer of modern dance,
Doris Humphrey, famously choreographed a dance to a slowish
performance of this music:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/NjwJyaSIRqY&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not how I would dance to it, because I feel the music
differently. Surprisingly, I could find few examples on YouTube of
dancing to this music. I may consider choreographing a dance myself as
a project to express my own personal vision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing I would like to mention is that I feel that the &lt;em&gt;walking bass&lt;/em&gt;
is very important in this music and gives it the impetus. When played
too slow, the walking bass no longer feels like it&amp;rsquo;s walking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel this music in my legs, not just in my lungs. Yes, I have
actually hummed it to myself while walking in time to the bass
leisurely in the local park. There is a limit to how &amp;ldquo;leisurely&amp;rdquo; I can
walk without feeling frustrated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;ice-dancing&#34;&gt;Ice dancing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found this somewhat frenetic but nevertheless beautiful ice dancing
performance from the 1992 World Figure Skating Championships:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/1JjbwtM_E3g&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;recorder-quartet&#34;&gt;Recorder quartet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A final performance to enjoy: the Japanese &amp;ldquo;Sekishi Recorder Quartet&amp;rdquo;
playing their hearts out in 2009. I think it&amp;rsquo;s lovely: impeccable
phrasing, transparency,
and rich ensemble balance and tone. (As a twist, the melody line performer adds
his own ornamentations.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/pRRRK0UClNs&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was inspired by the accumulated comments on my previous post on
Bach&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Air on G String&amp;rdquo; that I decided to flesh out my thoughts by
using more example performances, as well as relate the orchestral
music to singing and dancing. I hope you have enjoyed these
explorations. There is no single &amp;ldquo;right&amp;rdquo; way to experience music, but
I wanted to share how I experience it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;ve read my previous post, does this one help clarify where
  I&amp;rsquo;m coming from with my musical values? Do you dance
  or sing? Does this affect how you perceive this piece of music and
  like to perform it or hear it performed?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The many faces of &#34;Stella by Starlight&#34;</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/06/01/the-many-faces-of-stella-by-starlight/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jun 2015 01:08:23 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/06/01/the-many-faces-of-stella-by-starlight/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently I got obsessed with the classic 1944 jazz standard
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stella_by_Starlight&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Stella by Starlight&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought I&amp;rsquo;d share some very different interpretations of this music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;harry-james-1947&#34;&gt;Harry James, 1947&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the original version, not jazz, but slow, sentimental, lush: a
sentimental serenade perfect for dancing foxtrot to. Pretty good, if
you like &amp;ldquo;oldies&amp;rdquo;. And if you don&amp;rsquo;t like oldies, you need to hear this
anyway, to understand why the piece was so interesting: there is
inherently beautiful harmonic movement and color that would attract
jazz musicians to adopt this tune and transform it, and they still
continue to do that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/TjRMLqb6Sgs&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;miles-davis-quintet-1964&#34;&gt;Miles Davis quintet, 1964&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A really quirky version that starts with a slow intro before everyone
starts swinging, and then it goes fragmented again, and then the cycle
continues with all kinds of different ideas. Ten minutes long.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Riok08Y_ri4&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;tito-puente-around-1983&#34;&gt;Tito Puente, around 1983?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tito Puente and his Latin jazz band,
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michel_Camilo&#34;&gt;Michel Camilo&lt;/a&gt; on
piano. Puente himself starts off soloing on vibraphone: beautiful,
haunting rhythmic playing. Later, there is an electric guitar
solo. But mostly, this whole performance is melodic, and with its
steady and standard Afro-Cuban rhythmic drive, utterly danceable for
salsa. Something different!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the performance that inspired me to write this blog post,
because I&amp;rsquo;d never encountered this version before, but it was so
enchanting. From foxtrot original to salsa&amp;hellip; who would have thought?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34;
src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/xJF5BRuRtVo&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;
allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;chet-baker-quartet-1987&#34;&gt;Chet Baker quartet, 1987&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Live video footage from Tokyo. Baker is near the end of his tragic
life. He starts off with a fragmentary approach, and makes use of
long-held but gently played notes that creates soft but extended
dissonances against what&amp;rsquo;s going on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34;
src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/qq8oHYWHji8&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;
allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;learn-jazz-standards&#34;&gt;Learn Jazz Standards&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A wonderful backing track from &amp;ldquo;Learn Jazz Standards&amp;rdquo;, not for
listening to but playing against:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34;
src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/XR6KDWrn2ew&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;
allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One day I&amp;rsquo;ll take up the challenge of improvising an own performance
of &amp;ldquo;Stella by Starlight&amp;rdquo;, but I have to confess that right now it
seems too hard for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love &amp;ldquo;Stella by Starlight&amp;rdquo;. It will endure forever as a jazz
standard, I&amp;rsquo;m sure. I hope you like it too.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Discovering the Eolina, a beautiful musical instrument</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/02/18/discovering-the-eolina-a-beautiful-musical-instrument/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2015 20:56:18 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/02/18/discovering-the-eolina-a-beautiful-musical-instrument/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I just discovered a musical instrument that was new to me, the
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.melodicaworld.com/post_reviews/ballone-burini-eolina-45/&#34;&gt;Eolina&lt;/a&gt;,
which has a surprisingly beautiful sound, given that it is a form of
melodica, which although a perfectly fine instrument I enjoy playing,
does not have the loveliest, most refined sound.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I encountered the Eolina through my following the
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/user/GerardvanR&#34;&gt;YouTube channel&lt;/a&gt; of Gerard
van Reenen, who is just some random musician I found on YouTube at some
point in the past couple of years through some music search that I
have now completely forgotten.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His specialty is playing duets with himself, by playing a wind
instrument with one hand while accompanying himself on a
keyboard instrument. Remarkably, he often makes this work quite well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what exactly is an Eolina, and what does it sound like?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;example-a-handel-sonata-performed-on-eolina-and-organ&#34;&gt;Example: a Handel sonata performed on Eolina and organ&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out Gerard van Reenen&amp;rsquo;s self-duet on Eolina and organ of George
Frideric Handel&amp;rsquo;s sonata in B-flat major, HWV 377. I really like this
performance, showcasing his musicality on both instruments, and the
expressiveness of the Eolina, which is an upscale melodica made of
wood rather than plastic and therefore has more subtlety and
smoothness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/zNvV5WXRP1Q&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;another-example&#34;&gt;Another example&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was so curious about the Eolina that I tried to find other uses of
it on YouTube.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some musicians performing Piazzolla&amp;rsquo;s tango &amp;ldquo;Oblivion&amp;rdquo;, with
one of them playing an Eolina:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34;
src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/U0h39B6blVE&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;
allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Over two years ago,
&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/02/oblivion-obsession-time-to-start-playing-melodica/&#34;&gt;I had attempted to play &amp;ldquo;Oblivion&amp;rdquo; on my cheap melodica&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;d
love to have access to an Eolina sometime!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I always enjoy discovering a new musical instrument, and the Eolina
counts as one, even if it is just a wooden melodica.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Had you heard of or heard an Eolina before you read this blog post?
  What do you think of the sound? What do you think of melodicas in
  general? They are not so commonly used except as teaching
  instruments for children, so does that affect your perception?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thoughts on Cuba while watching Cuban musicians performing the 1947 bolero &#34;La gloria eres tú&#34;</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/12/13/thoughts-on-cuba-while-watching-cuban-musicians-performing-the-1947-bolero-la-gloria-eres-tu/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Dec 2014 21:01:47 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/12/13/thoughts-on-cuba-while-watching-cuban-musicians-performing-the-1947-bolero-la-gloria-eres-tu/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t expect to be thinking so much about Cuba today. It all started with a random musical itch I was scratching.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;la-comparsa-and-the-wooden-flute-headjoint&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;La comparsa&amp;rdquo; and the wooden flute headjoint&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I was in a Latin music mood as I was playing my flute at home, and started looking up flute versions of music on YouTube for fun and inspiration. One piece that came to mind was the famous &amp;ldquo;La comparsa&amp;rdquo;, by Cuban composer &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ernesto_Lecuona&#34;&gt;Ernesto Lecuona&lt;/a&gt;. Last year when Bebo Valdés died, I wrote about being moved by the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/22/rip-bebo-valdes/&#34;&gt;reunion of Bebo with his son Chucho in a tearful duet performance of this piece on two pianos&lt;/a&gt;, and thinking about their separation as Bebo abandoned his family to flee Cuba for Sweden while his son stayed behind to become one of Cuba&amp;rsquo;s great musicians.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found a really quirky Latin jazz performance of &amp;ldquo;La comparsa&amp;rdquo; on YouTube by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.chipboaz.com/blog/2014/07/10/cuban-flautist-bobby-ramirez-releases-jazz-flute/&#34;&gt;Cuban-American&lt;/a&gt; jazz flutist &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bobbyramirez.com/&#34;&gt;Bobby Ramirez&lt;/a&gt; and Puerto Rican &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.negronistrio.com/&#34;&gt;Jose Negroni&lt;/a&gt; on keyboard:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/4Nro7myJ6Nw&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ramirez on flute was unfortunately out of tune with the keyboard, but what I noticed was his wooden headjoint. I&amp;rsquo;ve never seen the old traditional Cuban wooden &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.descarga.com/cgi-bin/db/archives/Article15&#34;&gt;Charanga flute&lt;/a&gt;, but do see flutists playing the modern Boehm flute with a wooden headjoint for a different sound. In fact, I love and prefer wooden flutes, but they are expensive and I own only one, a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/30/got-my-new-casey-burns-small-handed-irish-flute/&#34;&gt;Casey Burns Irish flute&lt;/a&gt;. So just for the fun of it (I can&amp;rsquo;t really justify the investment right now), I decided to search the Web for makers of wooden headjoints.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;juan-novo-wooden-flute-headjoints&#34;&gt;Juan Novo wooden flute headjoints&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the top Web hits was &lt;a href=&#34;http://jnovoheadjoints.com/&#34;&gt;Juan Novo&lt;/a&gt;. It had the benefit of having an embedded YouTube video with the caption &amp;ldquo;This musician appreciated Mr. Novo’s craftsmanship so much, that this song was dedicated to him.&amp;rdquo; So I checked out the video. Indeed, the young woman playing the flute said, &amp;ldquo;Está para Juan Novo&amp;rdquo;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/kBzrwhpVvDE&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, I noticed that Juan Novo&amp;rsquo;s biography said he was sent from Cuba to the US all alone by his parents in 1962 to &lt;a href=&#34;http://jnovoheadjoints.com/about-juan-novo/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;escape the rampant communist indoctrination&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;la-gloria-eres-tú&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;La gloria eres tú&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was captivated not so much by the flute playing, but by the beautiful singing, of the young woman in this video of the classic bolero &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cancioneros.com/nc/2806/0/la-gloria-eres-tu-jose-antonio-mendez&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;La gloria eres tú&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; written by Cuban composer &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.encaribe.org/es/article/jose-antonio-mendez-garcia/1296&#34;&gt;José Antonio Méndez&lt;/a&gt; in 1947. I was really touched by her clear, unexaggerated but free expression and style, especially in light of much more famous performances of the song in my memory:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;La gloria eres tú&amp;rdquo; is one of my favorite boleros (&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/08/10/rip-eydie/&#34;&gt;my favorite being &amp;ldquo;Sabor a mî&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;) of all time. For comparison:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;luis-miguel&#34;&gt;Luis Miguel&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first exposure to &amp;ldquo;La gloria eres tú&amp;rdquo; was, like probably many others of my generation or younger worlwide, through the revival of the bolero by Mexican pop star &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Luis_Miguel&#34;&gt;Luis Miguel&lt;/a&gt; in the 1990s and onwards. I have all his bolero albums, a result of taking up Latin ballroom dancing in 2000 and hearing him singing in much of the music we practiced, performed, and competed to, including my first discovery of &amp;ldquo;Sabor a mî&amp;rdquo;, which was also on the 1997 album &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Romances_%28Luis_Miguel_album%29&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Romances&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. Luis Miguel is a great musician, I will continue to admit, but in time I drew away from his high-powered, slick performances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here he is live, from his 2000 DVD &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vivo_%28Luis_Miguel_album%29&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Vivo&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, which was the last thing I bought by him before backing away from his work:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/GNldCVbD4b4&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;olga-guillot&#34;&gt;Olga Guillot&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, the gold standard for &amp;ldquo;La gloria eres tú&amp;rdquo; is the performance by Cuban &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Olga_Guillot&#34;&gt;Olga Guillot&lt;/a&gt;, the &amp;ldquo;queen of the bolero&amp;rdquo;. (In 1961, she was yet another musician who fled Cuba.) I like how she alternates between different moods, starting out gently and almost like a prayer, but then gets more and more passionate. She very quickly changes the color of her voice and dynamics. For me it&amp;rsquo;s still the greatest performance of this bolero:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/xEAOX2nxsEo&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;elena-burke&#34;&gt;Elena Burke&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another recording I have of the bolero is from an album by Cuban singer &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elena_Burke&#34;&gt;Elena Burke&lt;/a&gt;. She has her own style, with a low voice, and more staccato delivery:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/yuHpvIvukOg&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elena died in Havana in 2002. Her daughter &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Malena_Burke&#34;&gt;Malena&lt;/a&gt; came to Miami in the US in 1995 with her family. Here is Malena Burke performing the bolero with Arturo Sandoval on piano:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/2_LxxwXda8Y&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Malena Burke&amp;rsquo;s oldest daughter &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lena_Burke&#34;&gt;Lena&lt;/a&gt; is also a musician, a pianist and singer, and has worked with Gloria Estefan and others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s Lena singing the famous 1929 bolero-son &lt;a href=&#34;http://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/L%C3%A1grimas_negras&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Lágrimas negras&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; with Bebo Valdés and others. This is such a weird combo, with her being sixty years younger than Bebo and stylistically very &amp;ldquo;American pop&amp;rdquo;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/x56VtBF6iGo&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;arturo-sandoval&#34;&gt;Arturo Sandoval&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arturo_Sandoval&#34;&gt;Arturo Sandoval&lt;/a&gt;, he defected from Cuba to the US in 2000. I discovered him initially when his biographical film &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/For_Love_or_Country:_The_Arturo_Sandoval_Story&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;For Love or Country&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; about his life before defection came out, and I saw him perform in the Three Rivers Arts Festival in Pittsburgh in 2002.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a Latin jazz version by Arturo Sandoval on flugelhorn, from his 1994 album &amp;ldquo;Tenderly&amp;rdquo;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/AZW15092fx4&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;where-is-blau-colonial-cayo-coco&#34;&gt;Where is Blau Colonial Cayo Coco?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So there were many thoughts and questions already in my mind as a result of listening to this old Cuban bolero, as a result of my remembering past performances by musicians who had left Cuba. When I hear classic boleros, I think about old Cuba, the culture and society that produced this kind of music and musicians, the political upheaval, the consequences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But back to that little band Nucay, captured presumably on a phone outside on a windy day by a random tourist who posted the video on YouTube in 2010. What has life been like for the members of Nucay, and for the charming young flutist/singer?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, what and where is &amp;ldquo;Blau Colonial Cayo Coco&amp;rdquo;? Apparently it&amp;rsquo;s a resort now named just &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cayocococuba.net/hotel_colonialcayococo.html&#34;&gt;Colonial Cayo Coco&lt;/a&gt; on the island of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cayo_Coco&#34;&gt;Cayo Coco&lt;/a&gt; that is part of Cuba. In particular, this place was designed to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cubahotelreservation.com/hotel.asp?hotel_code=sctblacolonial&#34;&gt;look like a village&lt;/a&gt;. This kind of thing makes me uncomfortable. I guess tourists fly in to pretend to have a nice &amp;ldquo;village&amp;rdquo; experience, while the hired musicians are probably paid to look and act the part.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;nucay&#34;&gt;Nucay&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I looked up more performances on YouTube by this band Nucay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;oye-como-va-cha-cha&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Oye como va&amp;rdquo;, cha-cha&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The caption for this video reads, &amp;ldquo;Ramon Almeida and daughter Arleytis [sic] lead this wonderful group of talented Cuban musicians.&amp;rdquo; So now we have some names. I presume the leader with maracas is the father? (Later I determined his daughter&amp;rsquo;s name is actually &amp;ldquo;Arletis&amp;rdquo;: read on.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was a fine performance of the classic cha-cha &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oye_Como_Va&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Oye coma va&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; written by &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tito_Puente&#34;&gt;Tito Puente&lt;/a&gt; in 1963. No, Puente was not Cuban; he was born in New York and was a big force in creating the mambo/salsa scene in the US in the 1950s. A great Latin jazz musician. I should have gone to see him perform live when he was in Pittsburgh in 2000 before he died. His music was great for listening to as well as dancing to; I still remember practicing my dancing to the first album of his I bought, &amp;ldquo;Mambo Birdland&amp;rdquo; (which has an &amp;ldquo;Oye como va&amp;rdquo; track).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I&amp;rsquo;ll confess that hearing performances of this work over a decade ago inspired me to think about taking up flute again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arletis did a fine job on flute here, jazzing things up:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/l4uWBPD7y70&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;ay-maria-merengue&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Ay Maria!&amp;rdquo;, merengue&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The musicians seem to be having fun; how could one not, given the catchy music and all of them singing? I really enjoyed flute action by Arletis in this upbeat classic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Merengue_music&#34;&gt;merengue&lt;/a&gt; is not Cuban, but comes from the Dominican Republic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/tAgVVL_ZTmI&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;sabor-a-mî&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Sabor a mî&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My favorite bolero, performed well. The caption reads &amp;ldquo;Cuban Music with the help of young percussionist from Quebec&amp;rdquo;, but this is wrong: &lt;a href=&#34;http://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sabor_a_m%C3%AD_%28canci%C3%B3n%29&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Sabor a mî&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; was composed in 1959 by a Mexican composer, &lt;a href=&#34;http://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/%C3%81lvaro_Carrillo&#34;&gt;Álvaro Carrillo&lt;/a&gt;. These distinctions matter to me: &amp;ldquo;Latin&amp;rdquo; music is not all the same, any more than the people or the distinct cultures are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/RmOIKdY3LYw&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;some-salsa-song&#34;&gt;Some salsa song&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is some salsa song; I&amp;rsquo;m afraid I cannot identify it offhand, the way I did the other songs. I&amp;rsquo;d have to try to transcribe the lyrics and hope that a Web search finds something, but have my doubts when it comes to salsa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I loved the father-daughter musical interplay here, with Ramón singing and Arletis on flute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/sAMdEezxYJs&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;summary-of-nucay&#34;&gt;Summary of Nucay&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OK, so Nucay is a pretty good band and plays a lot of classics to please the tourists. What else?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;arletis-almeida-sentirse-asi&#34;&gt;Arletis Almeida, &amp;ldquo;Sentirse Asi&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that a search for more Nucay material on YouTube reveals the following slick, professionally produced video uploaded by someone in 2012, promoting Arletis Almeida as a singer, with the caption &amp;ldquo;Arletis Almeida, flutist of Grupo Nucay in Cayo Coco Cuba, with her original song Sentirse Asi written by her father and band member Ramon Almeida&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, she is almost unrecognizable to me, very much made up and glamorous and placed in an urban nightlife setting, with shots of handsome men, alcohol, cigarettes. The contrast between this angsty, sensualized persona and the cheerful flutist playing at Colonial Cayo Coco with her father was quite jarring to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The singing is beautiful, and the song actually breaks out into a standard bolero accompaniment. It&amp;rsquo;s really something hearing bolero singing of this quality from a young person today. My overall feeling when hearing either this newly composed bolero or the classic music in the earlier videos is this: there&amp;rsquo;s some kind of time bubble that can still happen in the world, for better or for worse (a subject bigger than this blog post), and Nucay and Arletis Almeida illustrate it. Here in the US, no young people sing in this way. The many influences from pop, hip hop, and much more result in much more &amp;ldquo;fusion&amp;rdquo;. You saw that above in Lena Burke&amp;rsquo;s singing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/P1PZhDtCmLM&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;thoughts-on-cuba&#34;&gt;Thoughts on Cuba&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After watching this video, I wonder what has become of Arletis Almeida. Does she still play flute? Has she embarked on some kind of lounge career? Who knows? She&amp;rsquo;s in Cuba. Cuba is a world away. It took tourists to make her name even register on the Web, through the links to the YouTube videos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve waited for decades for an end to the senseless &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_States_embargo_against_Cuba&#34;&gt;embargo of Cuba&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;ve already run out of space here to even begin talking about the politics of the Cold War, about the human cost of isolating Cuba. Cuba, a place with a complicated history, but once an advanced nation by any standard, filled with culture, music classical and popular, home of world chess champion &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jos%C3%A9_Ra%C3%BAl_Capablanca&#34;&gt;Capablanca&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;con-los-años-que-me-quedan-and-nostalgia&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Con los años que me quedan&amp;rdquo; and nostalgia&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For some reason, I was reminded of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gloria_Estefan&#34;&gt;Gloria Estefan&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s music video of the bolero &amp;ldquo;Con los años que me quedan&amp;rdquo; from her nostalgic 1993 album &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mi_Tierra&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Mi Tierra&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s an odd kind of nostalgia, given that her parents fled Cuba when she was young. She made this album to embrace her Cuban heritage. But what world is portrayed here? Something like the world the tourists at Cayo Cayo hope to see? And what is Arletis trying to do as she sings boleros today?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, it&amp;rsquo;s definitely a beautiful song, and Estefan sings it soulfully:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/l6LjNOYvhMk&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2014-12-17&#34;&gt;(Update of 2014-12-17)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Totally by coincidence, news has come of the apparent &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2014/12/18/world/americas/us-cuba-relations.html&#34;&gt;plan by President Obama to normalize relations with Cuba&lt;/a&gt; after half a century. I cannot process this news right now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Life for Arletis and her father may well change one day in interesting ways.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The single greatest performance of Bach&#39;s Goldberg Variations: Pierre Hantaï with rhythmic drive and life</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/05/the-single-greatest-performance-of-bachs-goldberg-variations-pierre-hantai/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2014 22:32:07 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/05/the-single-greatest-performance-of-bachs-goldberg-variations-pierre-hantai/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been listening to JS Bach&amp;rsquo;s Goldberg Variations for a quarter of a century now. I haven&amp;rsquo;t actually said much about this piece on this blog, although I did mention attending a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/11/19/chamber-music-concert-at-cmu-featured-bachs-goldberg-variations-arranged-for-string-trio/&#34;&gt;concert featuring a string trio arrangement of it a year ago&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a favorite recording, out of probably a dozen recordings I have heard since a college friend introduced me to the piece performed by Glenn Gould on piano . Several years ago I discovered my true favorite, upon encountering &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pierre_Hanta%C3%AF&#34;&gt;Pierre Hantaï&lt;/a&gt; on harpsichord in a CD recording.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-hantaï-stands-out-for-me&#34;&gt;Why Hantaï stands out for me&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given that there are plenty of other performances that I consider worthy, why is Hantaï&amp;rsquo;s by far my favorite?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;sustained intensity (many performances have me getting bored and sleepy)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;rhythmic&lt;/em&gt; drive is always there; the music never droops&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;subtlety and shape to all phrasing and contrast&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;no distractions of self-absorption (many performances have certain kinds of oddities that are magnified when spread out over an hour or more)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;nice harpsichord sound&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: I once didn&amp;rsquo;t like harpsichord, and always preferred a piano when possible, but now I actually prefer Bach&amp;rsquo;s music on harpsichord, because of the nature of articulation and decay and how dissonances are more delicious on this instrument.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a treat I just found by accident: a video of Hantaï performing the Goldberg Variations. Watch it if you care about the Goldberg Variations at all!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/9NYqiKm3gng&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you are already a fan of the Goldberg Variations, what is your favorite performance, and why? Also, does it matter to you whether piano or harpsichord is used?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lessons to learn from pianist Dejan Lazić&#39;s attempt to remove a critic&#39;s bad review</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/02/lessons-to-learn-from-pianist-dejan-lazics-attempt-to-remove-a-critics-bad-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Nov 2014 17:25:32 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/02/lessons-to-learn-from-pianist-dejan-lazics-attempt-to-remove-a-critics-bad-review/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I never heard of the pianist Dejan Lazić until a news article about him started circulating: he was upset about a 2010 review of a concert of his, written by a Washington Post critic. Because a link to this review appeared high in Web searches of his name, he asked the Washington Post to remove the review under the EU&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Right_to_be_forgotten&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;right to be forgotten&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; law. The result: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.washingtonpost.com/news/the-intersect/wp/2014/10/31/pianist-asks-the-washington-post-to-remove-a-concert-review-under-the-e-u-s-right-to-be-forgotten-ruling/&#34;&gt;this article in the Washington Post about the situation&lt;/a&gt; that came to my attention from music blogs I follow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t have much to add to the commentary about the important questions about politics or philosophy regarding the &amp;ldquo;right to be forgotten&amp;rdquo;; there are very complex questions there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, Lazić claimed he has a right to control his public image, to make the Web reflect the &amp;ldquo;truth&amp;rdquo; about his concert performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what about unintended consequences?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;unintended-consequences&#34;&gt;Unintended consequences&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously, one could argue that the law has resulted in unintended consequences in people trying to use the law for more than what it was in spirit aimed to do, which was to protect people from defamation or a past that no longer reflects who they are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main unintended consequence, however, as far as I&amp;rsquo;m concerned, is what Alex Ross said without words, in his &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.therestisnoise.com/2014/11/the-unfortunate-mr-lazi%C4%87.html&#34;&gt;blog post here with a screen shot&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically, what Lazić did is to make himself a household name, with one of the top Web search hits now being exactly the article about him trying to remove an article. Talk about going meta! He has pretty much guaranteed that he will be known for possibly the rest of his career as &amp;ldquo;the guy who was upset by a negative review and tried to have it taken down&amp;rdquo;. I don&amp;rsquo;t think he intended for that to happen. This article about his trying to remove a bad review is surely going to be the top hit for his name now!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many actions have unintended consequences, if you didn&amp;rsquo;t think far enough ahead or have contingency plans. And even if you are powerful enough and arrogant enough to think you have everything figured out, and don&amp;rsquo;t consider what &lt;em&gt;reaction&lt;/em&gt; you might get from your action, and entire chains of actions and reactions, then something further down the road can still wreck everything you tried to start; for example, the Iraq War and the entire &amp;ldquo;War on Terror&amp;rdquo; has destabilized Iraq and the entire Middle East, and has created more terrorists than existed before it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t think there was any realistic scenario under which a lone pianist looking for fame could have killed that bad review in a major newspaper. An obscure pianist could kill a bad review in an obscure blog, probably. But once you are big enough, anything you do is news in itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;ignore-negative-reviews&#34;&gt;Ignore negative reviews&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would advise Dejan Lazić to focus on making good music, getting more positive reviews from many sources. It is definitely possible that critics can kill a career, and certainly in the past, vicious powerful critics have silenced musicians, but in today&amp;rsquo;s world, people do know to look at more than one source of trusted information. I for one would not rely solely on one random Washington Post music critic&amp;rsquo;s review of a musician to determine whether to give that musician&amp;rsquo;s work a listen: actually, I would just go look for audio or video samples to &lt;em&gt;hear for myself&lt;/em&gt;. The world is different now than when the critics really did have more power than they have now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you are a musician, do you agree with what Lazić tried to do? If so, why?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you are a music fan, how seriously do you take the top negative hits when you search for an unfamiliar musician?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I just saw and heard the most amazing performance of Schumann&#39;s Fantasy for piano by Alexandre Moutouzkine</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/08/28/i-just-saw-and-heard-the-most-amazing-performance-of-schumanns-fantasy-for-piano-by-alexandre-moutouzkine/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Aug 2014 23:42:37 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/08/28/i-just-saw-and-heard-the-most-amazing-performance-of-schumanns-fantasy-for-piano-by-alexandre-moutouzkine/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My single favorite work of music by Robert Schumann is his &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fantasie_in_C_%28Schumann%29&#34;&gt;Fantasie in C for piano&lt;/a&gt;, Op. 17. I was introduced to this piece in a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/05/07/happy-birthday-johannes-brahms/&#34;&gt;course for non-musicians I took first semester of freshman year in college&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have to confess that in the past two decades since discovering that piece, I never found a perfect performance of it, although Sviatoslav Richter&amp;rsquo;s came close, and I remember rushing to buy it when it was reissued on CD (back when one had to wait to transition from LPs). But I always felt something was missing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I just accidentally discovered the performance of a lifetime, captured in &lt;em&gt;video&lt;/em&gt; on YouTube. Why did I like this one so much?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;youtube-accidental-find&#34;&gt;YouTube accidental find&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just last week I had a YouTube accidental find, of &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/08/21/discovering-the-beautiful-keyboard-playing-of-robert-hill-by-accident-on-youtube-changed-my-life/&#34;&gt;Robert Hill&lt;/a&gt;. I had another find now, while not even searching for Schumann. Somehow my YouTube sidebar popped up a suggestion to check out a performance of Schumann&amp;rsquo;s Fantasie in C for piano by some random dude named Alexandre Moutouzkine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The YouTube video appeared to be highly rated, and was recorded live at a piano competition in 2011. &lt;em&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m a sucker for live performances with actual video&lt;/em&gt;, so I checked it out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;alexandre-moutouzkine&#34;&gt;Alexandre Moutouzkine&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First impressions are important. Well, I was hooked after just twenty seconds, because he was playing it the way I hear it in my mind! The lyrical flow and phrasing and drama got me hooked. Not square, but freely emotional, yet under control. My experience was also much enhanced by seeing him in action, as he moved his body completely in sync with the music, as though his entire being was part of the instrument. I&amp;rsquo;m not a fan of musicians who move a lot but don&amp;rsquo;t actually add to the musical expression, but it seemed like this guy was the real deal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before a minute was up, I was already totally entranced by his fluidity of tempo and dynamic contrast. He was maxing out on emotional expression in just the way that I&amp;rsquo;ve always wanted to hear and see this piece performed. Schumann wrote this in a dark period of life when it was not clear he would ever get to marry Clara Wieck (which he eventually did).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll stop with the blow-by-blow, but just say that I was sitting on the edge of my seat at home for half an hour while he performed the entirety of this piece. I was not disappointed. It was like the spirit of Schumann had entered him and he was showing how Schumann felt. The final movement, the slow movement, was particularly lovely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A bit of nitpicking: of course there were some botched notes, but it would be stupid to focus on that; more seriously, the second movement (fiendishly difficult to play, admittedly) was not as solid as it could have been. But I loved the first and third movements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;video-vs-just-audio&#34;&gt;Video vs. just audio?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My experience does leave me with some questions. Is it possible that I am actually &lt;em&gt;deceived&lt;/em&gt; about the quality of interpretation because there was video and I saw the performer up close? What if there were video of Richter available? Would it change my mind about him either positively or negatively? Some naysayers would argue we should do some kind of blind comparison. But I don&amp;rsquo;t think that. Because I perform music now as an amateur, and prefer attending live performances of music, I understand now (as I did not when I merely collected audio recordings and listened) that the &amp;ldquo;music&amp;rdquo; does not just exist on paper or as audio, but as the full performance context, and seeing video helps a lot in filling in that context.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This issue has come up this year &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.henle.de/blog/en/2014/03/31/listeners-are-also-only-human/&#34;&gt;in the news&lt;/a&gt;, and I may write more about it in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some naysayers in the YouTube comments decry the physical emoting by Alexandre Moutouzkine, but I do not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am ready to admit that at least part of what was missing for me in listening to Sviatoslav Richter was that I did not &lt;em&gt;see&lt;/em&gt; him, but only heard him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;listen-for-yourself&#34;&gt;Listen for yourself&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the video.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/mGgya_-xvdo&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;more-about-alexandre-moutouzkine&#34;&gt;More about Alexandre Moutouzkine&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only after watching the video did I do a Web search on this young guy. He&amp;rsquo;s 34 now and here&amp;rsquo;s a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alexandre_Moutouzkine&#34;&gt;Wikipedia page about him&lt;/a&gt;. Definitely someone to keep an eye on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;performances-by-sviatoslav-richter&#34;&gt;Performances by Sviatoslav Richter&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to compare (but only audio, no video), here is Sviatoslav&amp;rsquo;s classic 1961 studio recording (the one I&amp;rsquo;ve treasured for decades):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/CEjhA3QVdJA&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s also a 1959 Prague live recording, which I was not aware of till looking Richter up on YouTube just now; it does have more of a sense of freedom than the studio recording:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/FzmTmOUb9Sw&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;video-footage-of-richter-in-action&#34;&gt;Video footage of Richter in action&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is video footage of Richter in action in other music. I particularly like this video of Richter playing Brahms&amp;rsquo; intermezzo in E minor, Op. 116, No. 5. You can see Richter rocking rhythmically to the music as he plays it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/wSsobHfa37A&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was very pleased to have discovered Alexandre Moutouzkine&amp;rsquo;s live performance of Schumann&amp;rsquo;s Fantasie in C for piano. Time will tell whether I will always consider it as amazing as I do now, but it really touched my heart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Do you consider it important to experience music live and/or visually? Or do you think that is just a distraction and the best way to experience music is privately through pure audio?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Discovering the beautiful keyboard playing of Robert Hill by accident on YouTube changed my life</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/08/21/discovering-the-beautiful-keyboard-playing-of-robert-hill-by-accident-on-youtube-changed-my-life/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2014 22:14:23 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/08/21/discovering-the-beautiful-keyboard-playing-of-robert-hill-by-accident-on-youtube-changed-my-life/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.mh-freiburg.de/typo3temp/_processed_/csm_prof.-dr.-robert-hill_c7981b16bc.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Robert Hill&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Recently, I completely accidentally discovered a fascinating musician, &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Hill_%28musician%29&#34;&gt;Robert Hill&lt;/a&gt;, on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/user/earlymus&#34;&gt;YouTube&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story is as you might expect: I heard a piece of music, and wanted to find some performance of it by somebody, anybody on YouTube as long as it had a decent user rating (yes, I find ratings actually useful when checking out unfamiliar music), and I happened to come across some random guy&amp;rsquo;s performance, and it was so fascinating that I looked at other uploads of his, subscribed to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/user/earlymus&#34;&gt;his YouTube channel&lt;/a&gt;, and looked him up on the Web to find out who he was!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s especially great that he regularly uploads new videos to his YouTube channel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So who is Robert Hill, and why do I like his performances so much that I&amp;rsquo;m recommending that you check them out?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-i-found-robert-hill&#34;&gt;How I found Robert Hill&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The short story is that I just heard someone playing, on piano, Johann Sebastian Bach&amp;rsquo;s Allemande from the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/French_Suites_%28Bach%29&#34;&gt;French Suite&lt;/a&gt; no. 4 in E-flat, BWV 815.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note that I actually have had very little interest in much of Bach&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Works_for_keyboard_by_J.S._Bach&#34;&gt;keyboard music&lt;/a&gt; and have almost completely ignored them for decades&lt;/em&gt;; there are only two exceptions: the Goldberg Variations and some of the Well-Tempered Clavier.  In particular, I have not listened to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/French_Suites_%28Bach%29&#34;&gt;French Suites&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/English_Suites_%28Bach%29&#34;&gt;English Suites&lt;/a&gt;, or &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Partitas_for_keyboard_%28Bach%29&#34;&gt;Partitas&lt;/a&gt; at all!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But because I just accidentally heard this Allemande played live, and liked it, I wanted to hear it again when I got home, and so I went to YouTube to find it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found a lot of performances online, of course, but I&amp;rsquo;m a sucker for the unusual, so I was particularly interested when I saw in the search results a link to some guy, Robert Hill, performing it on an unusual instrument I had never heard of in my life, a &amp;ldquo;lute-harpsichord&amp;rdquo;. And it got well over a hundred thumb-up ratings and only one thumb-down, so of course I was going to check it out!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I watched the video, and was &lt;em&gt;totally blown away&lt;/em&gt; by the beauty of the performance:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The instrument has a gorgeous sound.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Robert Hill played very expressively, with the full freedom and emotion that treasure.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Structurally, I could hear the different voices and phrases with total clarity because of how he plays.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This single performance made me think that I needed to give old Bach another shot and check out more of his keyboard music.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Listen for yourself (it&amp;rsquo;s less than two minutes long):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/woh8UHdjl1M&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;who-is-robert-hill&#34;&gt;Who is Robert Hill?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did a Web search on Robert Hill and found &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Hill_%28musician%29&#34;&gt;information about him&lt;/a&gt;. He is an American keyboard instrument performer (especially early keyboard instruments such as harpsichord, clavichord, lute-harpsichord, fortepiano) and musicologist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had to search hard to find an actual Web site of his own, and it&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://robert-hill.tripod.com/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. It basically looks like it hasn&amp;rsquo;t been updated since around 2001, which is also his last recording time period on his &lt;a href=&#34;http://robert-hill.tripod.com/id11.html&#34;&gt;discography&lt;/a&gt;. At some point he must have decided to just share his music through YouTube. He is a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mh-freiburg.de/lehrende/person/details/hill/&#34;&gt;music professor in Freiburg&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I just mentioned, my fascination with the performances of Robert Hill comes from his &lt;em&gt;expressiveness&lt;/em&gt;, which comes about from adjustments of tempo, rhetorical gestures, ornamentation, rhythmic sense. He plays a lot more expressively than many keyboard musicians do today, and I like that. I now believe that I was turned off by much of Bach&amp;rsquo;s keyboard music not because of Bach, but because of the relatively bland performances his music has received, especially from modern pianists. Bach was an emotional man living in an emotional age (the Baroque era of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Doctrine_of_the_affections&#34;&gt;affect&lt;/a&gt;), and I feel blessed that musicians like Robert Hill are taking this seriously. There are others, of course, besides him, but I think his performances have a particular edge to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;regular-harpsichord&#34;&gt;Regular harpsichord&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is an example of Robert Hill playing regular harpsichord.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;bach-s-allemande-from-the-partita-in-d-major-bwv-828&#34;&gt;Bach&amp;rsquo;s Allemande from the Partita in D major, BWV 828&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I discovered this beautiful, haunting work of music by Bach for the first time, by sheer accident, when browsing Hill&amp;rsquo;s YouTube channel (live performance from 1997):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/oEoqPSFklkE&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I cannot believe I went four decades without ever having heard this piece in my life. Now I can&amp;rsquo;t get it out of my head.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hill did some extreme things in this performance (tempo modifications and hesitations) that are not to my taste, but I applaud him for having the courage to play from the heart, because much of what he did spoke to mine! He lives dangerously. Maybe that&amp;rsquo;s why he only posts live recording clips to YouTube now rather than make CDs?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;fortepiano&#34;&gt;Fortepiano&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He also plays fortepiano, which is a fascinating instrument I love. I have mentioned my first experience with a fortepiano in college in a blog post earlier this year celebrating the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/03/08/happy-300th-birthday-carl-philipp-emanuel-bach/&#34;&gt;300th birthday of Johann Sebastian&amp;rsquo;s son Carl Philipp Emanuel&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;cpe-bach-s-fantasie-in-f-sharp-minor&#34;&gt;CPE Bach&amp;rsquo;s Fantasie in F-sharp minor&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heck, I had to check out Hill&amp;rsquo;s performance of my favorite CPE Bach keyboard work. In my earlier blog post, I had praised Andreas Staier&amp;rsquo;s performance I discovered in college, but now having heard Hill&amp;rsquo;s, I have another favorite (live from April 2014). This totally plays up Hill&amp;rsquo;s maximally emotive expressive style:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/LOT_nUPvE98&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;js-bach-well-tempered-clavier-selections&#34;&gt;JS Bach: Well-Tempered Clavier selections&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was fascinating to find Hill performing JS Bach on fortepiano; I had never heard anyone playing JS Bach on fortepiano before. I love that he experiments with different styles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The famous WTC I, Prelude in C major, in a fluid, beautiful Romantic-style (vs. Baroque-style) performance he just uploaded a couple of days ago:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/jiBQD0vV5qI&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A totally gorgeous Romantic-style interpretation of the slow Bach WTC I, Prelude in C# minor:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/9iGj4U7nqqY&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love how he makes full use of the expressive possibilities of the fortepiano (power and dynamics and sustain).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;beethoven-s-moonlight-sonata&#34;&gt;Beethoven&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Moonlight&amp;rdquo; sonata&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, he plays Beethoven too, on fortepiano.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that Beethoven did call it &amp;ldquo;sonata quasi fantasia&amp;rdquo; so it should be played freely &amp;ldquo;like a fantasy&amp;rdquo;, freely, and he does this. If you&amp;rsquo;ve only heard it played more &amp;ldquo;squarely&amp;rdquo;, check this out. In this case, I prefer a more subtle freedom than the exaggerated gestures Hill provides, because I feel he disrupts the rhythmic flow too much, so I consider his experiment not a full success, but still, I respect his willingness to go all out:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/6gpmZsqOzZs&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;pianoforte&#34;&gt;Pianoforte!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, of course Robert Hill plays the modern piano too. And I love what he does with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;brahms&#34;&gt;Brahms&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hill brings out the different voices very well, the counterpoint through the thick textures of Brahms. These are truly beautiful performances of some of &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/05/07/happy-birthday-johannes-brahms/&#34;&gt;my favorite piano music of all time, Brahms&amp;rsquo; intermezzi&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A passionate performance of Op. 117, No. 2 in B-flat minor:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/U_rlk4H-DQ0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And Op. 119, No. 1 in B minor (some favorite performances of which I discussed in &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/05/07/happy-birthday-johannes-brahms/&#34;&gt;my blog post last year&lt;/a&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/NOpe_KvXQzA&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is one of the most emotionally raw performances I have ever heard of this intermezzo. Hill makes the most of the suspensions, silences, dissonances, and clashing lines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Discovering the musical performances of Robert Hill on keyboard instruments has been one of the happy surprises of my life this year. Not only has he provided me listening pleasure, but also has sharpened my conception of what the music he plays is about and how to express it. He has forever changed my expectation from myself of how I should play music. I expect that from now on, I will never again hold back from &amp;ldquo;weird&amp;rdquo; interpretations that I feel come from my heart and mind. I don&amp;rsquo;t expect that all my experiments will succeed, but seeing someone else try, and publicly, how can I not do likewise?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Have you recently discovered a musician who has changed your hearing and/or your own playing? Who was it and what did you learn?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The growth of loyalty after seventeen years</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/07/22/the-growth-of-loyalty-after-seventeen-years/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2014 21:44:11 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/07/22/the-growth-of-loyalty-after-seventeen-years/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Tonight I finally got a haircut.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For two weeks I&amp;rsquo;d been looking for my &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/barber/&#34;&gt;barber&lt;/a&gt; Joe, of Harry&amp;rsquo;s Barber Shoppe in Squirrel Hill; I was due for my haircut. I&amp;rsquo;d called Joe&amp;rsquo;s phone number from work in the afternoon. I&amp;rsquo;d driven by on the way home (the shop is just a block away from home). I&amp;rsquo;d taken a walk on Saturday to see if he was open. No sign of him. I was worried. I began imagining the worst.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not kidding when I tell people that I don&amp;rsquo;t know what I&amp;rsquo;d do without Joe to cut my hair. He&amp;rsquo;s been the only one to cut my hair in the past seventeen years, apart from that one time he broke his hand and was out of commission for a while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first thought when I wondered whether Joe was OK was, if he was gone, I would miss not only a great cut (after the first couple of times in 1997, he figured out how to do things just the way I like), but also some kind of relationship. Since Joe is a lot older than me, I know that one day I will have to find a new barber; I was just thinking that when that day comes, I don&amp;rsquo;t want just a haircut, but I want some kind of relationship. Joe doesn&amp;rsquo;t just cut my hair. He asks me how my life is going; he was there before I was married, and now he inquires about Abby, whom he&amp;rsquo;s met, that time when I was waiting so long for my turn that she walked over and brought me dinner. He knows the structure of my head and the properties of my hair more than I do. We take turns guessing who&amp;rsquo;s singing the songs on his favorite radio station; I&amp;rsquo;ve absorbed some of his oldies into my consciousness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;lucky&#34;&gt;Lucky&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The whole haircut experience is about much more than my walking out with less hair. That&amp;rsquo;s why I was relieved to find him accidentally after an evening run in Frick Park that ended with my spotting in the distance the light in Joe&amp;rsquo;s shop and stopping by and seeing him there. It was already late in the evening, nearly 8:00 PM already, but he said he would take me (he was finishing up one guy in the chair), so I ran back home to change out of my running gear and get my wallet and return to the shop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joe said he was OK. He&amp;rsquo;s continued to have back trouble and reduced his work, but he&amp;rsquo;s still around. It does not even occur to me to get angry with him for causing me to look for him for two weeks. I&amp;rsquo;m simply grateful he&amp;rsquo;s OK and able to work and cheerful. He thanks me for being patient and returning to him again and again. That is all. The rest is philosophical banter about what is important in life, and chuckling to myself as I easily identify &amp;ldquo;drunky&amp;rdquo; Dean Martin on the radio singing &amp;ldquo;Ain&amp;rsquo;t That a Kick in the Head?&amp;rdquo; Such a dated song, I think, but it has a certain charm and who else could sing it in perfect character besides Dean Martin?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/2zBszbgkH8g&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;questions&#34;&gt;Questions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Are you loyal to someone who cuts your hair? What would you do (or have done) if that person is no longer present in your life?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The one thing I remember Lorin Maazel for</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/07/13/the-one-thing-i-remember-lorin-maazel-for/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Jul 2014 19:36:07 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/07/13/the-one-thing-i-remember-lorin-maazel-for/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;RIP, &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lorin_Maazel&#34;&gt;Lorin Maazel&lt;/a&gt;. A music conductor of fame and longevity has died (at age 84), generating no shortage of obituaries, such as &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2014/07/14/arts/music/lorin-maazel-brilliant-intense-and-enigmatic-conductor-dies-at-84.html&#34;&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Very often famous people die without my really having known much about them, and of course, this case was no exception. But this post isn&amp;rsquo;t about what I didn&amp;rsquo;t know, but what I do know, and &lt;em&gt;remember&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-ring-without-words&#34;&gt;The &amp;ldquo;Ring&amp;rdquo; Without Words&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lorin Maazel may have had a long and illustrious career, but actually, I don&amp;rsquo;t believe I have listened to a single of his recordings (I never saw him in performance) other than one, his &amp;ldquo;Ring Without Words&amp;rdquo; purely orchestral arrangement of Richard Wagner&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Der_Ring_des_Nibelungen&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Ring&amp;rdquo; cycle of operas&lt;/a&gt; that fits in a CD-length 75-minute &amp;ldquo;summary&amp;rdquo; of the epic operatic cycle (which takes more like 17 hours for a complete performance, spread out over four separate operas).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So he touched my life in a single, unusual, but quite &lt;em&gt;positive&lt;/em&gt; way. Ironically, the example obituary I mentioned does not even mention this work of Maazel&amp;rsquo;s. This illustrates that obituaries hardly tell the whole story of the contributions of someone to people&amp;rsquo;s lives. They may tell what is most prestigious or most scandalous, but may miss interesting quirky projects that have less measurable impact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-story&#34;&gt;My story&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://ecx.images-amazon.com/images/I/51lK9-us16L._SY300_.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;The Ring Without Words&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In my senior year of college, I came across a CD in the campus library on the Telarc label of Maazel&amp;rsquo;s recording of the &amp;ldquo;Ring Without Words&amp;rdquo;. At the time, I knew fairly little about Richard Wagner or his music, but I was intrigued by the concept, since I was &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; an opera fan, and didn&amp;rsquo;t mind trying out what some immediately criticized as a gimmicky &amp;ldquo;Reader&amp;rsquo;s Digest&amp;rdquo; concept by Maazel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I very much enjoyed the recording and listened to clips here and there without the &amp;ldquo;guilt&amp;rdquo; or confusion of choosing and listening to selected portions of recordings of the actual original operas. Basically, I appreciated Maazel&amp;rsquo;s role as a curator and summarizer that brought in curious new listeners like me. I still believe there is a role for &amp;ldquo;popularizers&amp;rdquo; of &amp;ldquo;classical music&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I just looked on YouTube and found this very short clip of a performance by Maazel of the &amp;ldquo;Ring Without Words&amp;rdquo;, so you can check it out to get an idea of how it works:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/h9ObRSy3D1E&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;authorial-intent&#34;&gt;Authorial intent&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I mentioned last year in &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/05/22/reflections-on-richard-wagners-200th-birthday/&#34;&gt;my post for Wagner&amp;rsquo;s 200th birthday&lt;/a&gt; that I had, before encountering Maazel&amp;rsquo;s CD, tried to watch the Metropolitan Opera&amp;rsquo;s four-evening TV broadcast in the summer of the &amp;ldquo;Ring&amp;rdquo; cycle and found it hard going. My overall philosophy was, and is, that &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/05/24/why-i-will-always-pronounce-gif-like-gift-and-not-like-jif/&#34;&gt;authorial intent is overrated&lt;/a&gt;. Fact is, if we were really serious about authorial intent, Wagner actually originally &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parsifal#The_ban_on_Parsifal_outside_Bayreuth&#34;&gt;forbade his opera &amp;ldquo;Parsifal&amp;rdquo; from being performed anywhere except in Bayreuth&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not saying we shouldn&amp;rsquo;t respect to one degree or other a composer&amp;rsquo;s original setting or wishes. Actually, I&amp;rsquo;m probably more respectful than most other people, because of my involvement with early music! I&amp;rsquo;m just saying that alternative arrangements and excerpts are always possible, and as long as they do not misrepresent themselves, I have no problem with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;pittsburgh&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might expect me to say something how Maazel turned the Pittsburgh Symphony Orchestra into a world-class orchestra, but actually, I moved to Pittsburgh in 1997 after Maazel had just left, so when I started attending PSO concerts, it was &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/06/08/heinz-hall-memories-at-the-pittsburgh-symphony-being-shocked-out-of-my-mind-upon-experiencing-prokofievs-second-piano-concerto-for-the-first-time/&#34;&gt;under Mariss Jansons&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the &lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.pittsburghsymphony.org/2014/07/statement-on-the-death-of-former-pittsburgh-symphony-orchestra-music-director-lorin-maazel/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Symphony Orchestra&amp;rsquo;s official statement on the passing of Lorin Maazel&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever else Lorin Maazel may have done in his life, one thing he did was bring Wagner to people like me, through his &amp;ldquo;Ring Without Words&amp;rdquo;. I am grateful he carried out this project. Also, more indirectly, he shaped the Pittsburgh Symphony Orchestra into the world-class orchestra it was by the time I moved to Pittsburgh, so I benefited from something he did that I never personally saw.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Third year at July 3 music party and finally participated in jamming</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/07/03/third-year-at-july-3-music-party-and-finally-participated-in-jamming/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jul 2014 22:11:59 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/07/03/third-year-at-july-3-music-party-and-finally-participated-in-jamming/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;The past two years, Abby and I have gone to an annual July 3 music potluck/party, and we went again this year. Both &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/03/petrified-at-a-music-jam-session-so-i-didnt-play-but-watched-and-listened/&#34;&gt;in 2012&lt;/a&gt; as well as &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/07/03/second-year-at-july-3-music-party-still-only-listening-without-playing/&#34;&gt;in 2013&lt;/a&gt;, I was too intimidated to participate in music jamming, and only watched. This year I was determined to contribute, and I brought my ukulele (which I only started learning &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/08/23/another-unexpected-life-change-one-month-of-learning-to-play-ukulele/&#34;&gt;a month after last year&amp;rsquo;s party&lt;/a&gt;, actually) and my Irish flute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;piano&#34;&gt;Piano&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After my first round of food at the potluck, I went to Susan&amp;rsquo;s piano and played David Raksin&amp;rsquo;s theme from &amp;ldquo;Laura&amp;rdquo;, which I had so botched up last month at the annual Pittsburgh Recorder Society potluck/recital. I play it much better now, although I somehow messed up the final chords today. There were a few people sitting around listening, and they wanted to hear more, but I didn&amp;rsquo;t have any more, so I scurried away to eat more food.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;old-time&#34;&gt;Old time&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As dinner started winding down, the old time musicians started gathering outside to play. I saw fiddles, banjos, and other instruments make an appearance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;blues&#34;&gt;Blues&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inside, the main guy who plays guitar and ukulele unpacked his soprano ukulele, and so I took out my concert ukulele, and two other guys with guitars appeared. Eventually a woman who sang also appeared, as well as a guy on fiddle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I felt very intimidated, because although I&amp;rsquo;ve gotten some experience jamming while on recorder or flute or tin whistle, my ukulele experience &lt;em&gt;without written music&lt;/em&gt; is still very minimal. Nevertheless, I joined in. I fumbled around, and had to ask what key each song was being played in, and even then, I&amp;rsquo;m still quite shaky in anticipating and knowing chord changes beyond the simplest I, IV, V, and some dominant and major 7th chords. I strummed very softly.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/music-2014-07-04/jamming.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Music jamming&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;They&amp;rsquo;re a great bunch, improvising melodic lines at will and even making up lyrics right on the spot, just as they had at the last two years when I only watched. And the singing in harmony was fantastic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby got a little bit of video footage of us at one point:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/zYb1aBioAao&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For two years, I was afraid to join in the music jams at this annual July 3 party. This year I joined in a little bit. If we attend the party again next year, I hope to be in a position to contribute even more! Many thanks to Susan for hosting this annual party!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Celebrating the 150th birthday of my favorite second-rate composer: Richard Strauss</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/06/11/celebrating-the-150th-birthday-of-my-favorite-second-rate-composer-richard-strauss/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jun 2014 17:22:01 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/06/11/celebrating-the-150th-birthday-of-my-favorite-second-rate-composer-richard-strauss/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;So it&amp;rsquo;s the 150th birthday of Richard Strauss, the German composer who famously declared himself a &amp;ldquo;first-class second-rate composer&amp;rdquo;, since he considered himself not in the rank of Mozart and Beethoven.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, I would certainly consider him one of the great composers of all time, because of his innovative explorations of color, and the tension between counterpoint and tonality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a tour of some of my favorite performances of his music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-first-discovery-of-richard-strauss-also-sprach-zarathustra&#34;&gt;My first discovery of Richard Strauss: &amp;ldquo;Also sprach Zarathustra&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Probably like everyone else born after 1968, the first time I heard any music by Strauss was surely while watching the 1968 film &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2001:_A_Space_Odyssey_%28film%29&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;2001: A Space Odyssey&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. I watched it sometime in the 1980s. Kubrick took the opening &amp;ldquo;Sunrise&amp;rdquo; of Strauss&amp;rsquo;s 1896 symphonic poem [Also sprach Zarathustra](&amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Also_sprach_Zarathustra_%28Richard_Strauss%29&amp;quot;&#34;&gt;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Also_sprach_Zarathustra_%28Richard_Strauss%29&amp;quot;&lt;/a&gt;) as the opening musical theme of the film:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/e-QFj59PON4&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It took years until I actually learned this music wasn&amp;rsquo;t composed for the film, but was a fragment of something old, and had a name. At some point, I finally heard the whole piece, on the radio. And then I listened to it more deeply in college, as I grappled with Strauss&amp;rsquo;s playing with tonality, using B major against C major in the piece to contrast humanity with the universe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;ve only heard the opening fanfare, you must listen to the whole piece. It&amp;rsquo;s a story in itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A video of Mariss Jansons conducting this work:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/Y9QxaJLt7EA&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-second-discovery-im-abendrot&#34;&gt;My second discovery: &amp;ldquo;Im Abendrot&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In college, I watched the 1990 film &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wild_at_Heart_%28film%29&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Wild at Heart&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; with friends as it came out. I was wowed by the opening music theme and wondered what that gorgeous music was. Well, it turned out to be the beginning of Richard Strauss&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Im Abendrot&amp;rdquo;, one of his &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Four_Last_Songs&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Four Last Songs&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; composed in 1948 when he was 84 years old.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out the opening of the film, if you haven&amp;rsquo;t seen it before or don&amp;rsquo;t remember:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/JHNEL1H5_b0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The music clip from that film was an excerpt from one sung by Jessye Norman, conducted by Kurt Masur. It turns out that she sang it really slowly, and I prefer the music as a whole to go more quickly, in the context of it being a whole song, not just an instrumental introduction. Here is a classic recording by Gundula Janowitz in 1973 conducted by Herbert von Karajan that may be my favorite one of this beautiful song, which is about reflections on approaching death: &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;We have gone through sorrow and joy hand in hand; now let us rest from our wanderings above the silent land.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Listen to the whole thing:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/6YD_8E4ZVxY&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find it marvelous and touching that Richard Strauss continued to give the world the gift of lovely music in his old age.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;some-youthful-music-piano-sonata-in-b-minor&#34;&gt;Some youthful music: piano sonata in B minor&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, for something completely different: a piano sonata he wrote at age 16, in 1880. (Yes, 1880. One thing to remember about Richard Strauss is just how long he lived, and how many eras of musical and political change he survived through.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Glenn Gould was a big champion of Richard Strauss, and I&amp;rsquo;m grateful he recorded a bunch of his Strauss&amp;rsquo;s piano music. Obviously, this youthful piano music is not among Strauss&amp;rsquo;s greatest work (it tends to be very repetitious, not yet fully individualist and economical), but it still has its charm, as a transitional late Romantic attempt of the 19th century. I can&amp;rsquo;t possibly listen to the whole thing without falling asleep, but it&amp;rsquo;s interesting to click around to get a glimpse of where he was coming from:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/xemgqKGl9VE&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;his-masterpiece-at-the-end-metamorphosen-for-23-solo-strings&#34;&gt;His masterpiece at the end: Metamorphosen for 23 solo strings&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1944, near the end of his life, 64 years after the last musical selection I linked to, Strauss composed his final masterpiece, &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metamorphosen&#34;&gt;Metamorphosen&lt;/a&gt;, which he subtitled &amp;ldquo;in memoriam&amp;rdquo;. &amp;ldquo;In memory&amp;rdquo; of what? He refused to say, so there is debate about this: it could be a statement of mourning over the Dresden destruction in World War II, or could be a more abstract statement about the horrors of war in general. See this &lt;a href=&#34;http://csosoundsandstories.org/strauss-reflecting-on-his-artistic-life-in-metamorphosen/&#34;&gt;recent article&lt;/a&gt; for more discussion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is my favorite music by him. It is a feat of emotional contrast and expression, and gorgeous orchestration, writing for strings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a wonderful video of Nathalie Stutzmann conducting Metamorphosen:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/3X9asrefuSg&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;other-work&#34;&gt;Other work&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have completely omitted any mention of &lt;em&gt;decades&lt;/em&gt; of Strauss&amp;rsquo;s most prominent masterpieces, because, ironically, most of them do not speak to me. I realize that by saying this, I am saying that Strauss is a problem for me: much of his music leaves me cold, however technically brilliant they might be. So I do not love that music. I remember him for his accomplished, nostalgic later work that I actually love.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conducting&#34;&gt;Conducting&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Richard Strauss was influential as a conductor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;his-own-music&#34;&gt;His own music&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a video clip of Richard Strauss conducting his own music in 1944:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/doJVlS7nn_g&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;mozart&#34;&gt;Mozart&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Strauss loved Mozart. Here he is in a 1926 recording of Mozart&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Jupiter&amp;rdquo; symphony, no. 41:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/lF7QxBkmlXE&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s not a great performance (I do not like the sloppiness or the rushing), but it is interesting how &amp;ldquo;modern&amp;rdquo; it sounds, in that it takes a brisk tempo and focuses on overall structural integrity and drive. Apparently he did not treat recording as a serious activity, however, so one cannot extrapolate from this recording how his live performances sounded in general.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;controversies&#34;&gt;Controversies&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two controversies over Strauss: one is over music and one is over politics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Musically, Strauss for a long time was considered to have fallen into conservatism, as he began as a radical innovator but did not follow through: he rejected the 20th century developments in atonality and serialism. I am not sure how entirely fair it is to level this charge against him, since he lived so long that one could not expect him to stay a radical forever. I also do not believe musical conservatism is necessarily horrible. Not everyone has the temperament or desire to be perpetually be on the cutting edge. I am perfectly happy that he wrote the &amp;ldquo;conservative&amp;rdquo; Metamorphosen and Four Last Songs that only he, who had lived half his life through the late Romantic era in the 19th century, could have created the way that they are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Politically, there are charges of his conveniently &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2002/01/06/arts/music-richard-strauss-and-hitler-s-reich-jupiter-in-hell.html&#34;&gt;going along with the Nazi regime&lt;/a&gt; for his own career gain. He is not alone, of course, in being a German musician under a cloud for not fleeing Germany or actively opposing Hitler. So there will always be &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dw.de/richard-strauss-and-musical-seduction/a-17695663&#34;&gt;discussion of this aspect of his life&lt;/a&gt;. I think it&amp;rsquo;s clear that he had no Nazi ideological convictions, but was a career opportunist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Richard Strauss&amp;rsquo;s 150th birthday, I decided to celebrate the music of his that I love most, and share it here. I hope you have checked out some of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Do you like the music of Richard Strauss? If so, what are your favorite pieces by him? Are they among those I mentioned, or those I did not? What do you think about him as a person?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Copland&#39;s Appalachian Spring danced by the orchestra musicians: confronting my memories of boredom four years ago</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/05/28/coplands-appalachian-spring-danced-by-the-orchestra-musicians-confronting-my-memories-of-boredom-four-years-ago/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2014 22:23:26 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/05/28/coplands-appalachian-spring-danced-by-the-orchestra-musicians-confronting-my-memories-of-boredom-four-years-ago/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I follow Greg Sandow&amp;rsquo;s blog on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.artsjournal.com/sandow/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;future of classical music&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. He posted an &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.artsjournal.com/sandow/2014/05/essential-video.html&#34;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; that got me thinking: he was all excited about an unorthodox performance of Aaron Copland&amp;rsquo;s half-hour-long &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Appalachian_Spring&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Appalachian Spring&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; by the University of Maryland Symphony Orchestra in which the students of the orchestra actually moved around and danced as well as played their instruments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a confession to make: back almost four years ago, in November 2010, I went to a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cmu.edu/news/archive/2010/November/nov15_cmunightwithpso.shtml&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Carnegie Mellon Night at the Symphony&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; in which &amp;ldquo;Appalachian Spring&amp;rdquo; was on the program. &lt;strong&gt;I got very bored during the piece.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing to remember is that the orchestra suite was actually arranged by Copland from his original piece that was an actual ballet for Martha Graham! So it&amp;rsquo;s actually kind of unnatural to experience this music &amp;ldquo;purely&amp;rdquo; as music. To me the suite is rather long and redundant without some kind of &amp;ldquo;story&amp;rdquo; to go along with it. So I watched the video of the orchestra-danced performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was definitely more interesting seeing action. At the same time, I got bored eventually anyway, after about 15 minutes. But I lasted longer with the physical action. However, I was also distracted by thoughts of how difficult it must have been for the orchestra to pull this off. I mean, marching band is one thing, but this is an orchestra and there was a ton of choreography and it&amp;rsquo;s not just marching.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s interesting that a commenter on Sandow&amp;rsquo;s blog criticized the
effort, writing: &lt;em&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s nicely done, I suppose, if you must do this
sort of thing. But when I go to an orchestral concert, I&amp;rsquo;m there for
the music, not for this sort of thing. To me, this doesn&amp;rsquo;t tell the
audience &amp;ldquo;this music is worth your time and attention,&amp;rdquo; it tells them
&amp;ldquo;we have so little faith that you’ll enjoy the music that we feel
compelled to trick it out with distractions.&amp;rdquo; I used to sing in a
chorus that was fond of &amp;ldquo;chorusography,&amp;rdquo; and it annoyed me as a
performer, too.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What do you think? Do you like this idea or does it annoy you?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Judge for yourself:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/jGSctM_8K_E&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>