<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Temple Run on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/temple-run/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Temple Run on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/temple-run/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Thoughts upon uninstalling &#34;Temple Run 2&#34; from my phone</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/05/16/thoughts-upon-uninstalling-temple-run-2-from-my-phone/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 May 2014 20:37:34 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/05/16/thoughts-upon-uninstalling-temple-run-2-from-my-phone/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have a confession to make.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/thumb/c/c4/TempleRun.jpg/150px-TempleRun.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Temple Run logo&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Two years ago, when I finally got my first &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/22/paradox-i-will-observe-the-national-day-of-unplugging-but-just-bought-my-first-smartphone-this-week/&#34;&gt;smartphone&lt;/a&gt;, I downloaded a free game, &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Temple_Run&#34;&gt;Temple Run&lt;/a&gt;, and quickly became a bit obsessed with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was the first computer game I had played in &lt;em&gt;twenty years&lt;/em&gt;, actually; although in college I played a fair number of games (including actual physical arcade games in the basement of the college dining hall), including &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dark_Castle&#34;&gt;Dark Castle&lt;/a&gt;, which I commandeered friends&amp;rsquo; Macs to play (I owned only an Apple IIe in college, for word processing purposes), the last time I played computer games was in grad school twenty years ago, when I conquered a Mac game called &amp;ldquo;Kung Fu Chivalry&amp;rdquo;. Somehow, after actually winning that game, I totally lost interest in playing computer games again (despite being annoyed about never finishing &amp;ldquo;Beyond Dark Castle&amp;rdquo;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I noticed that my reaction time and coordination were quite rusty after twenty years away from this kind of game, and was determined to get good at Temple Run. I was really bad for a while, but then everything started falling into place, and I got good enough that I got a bit bored. I forgot about the game for a long time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Months later, &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Temple_Run_2&#34;&gt;Temple Run 2&lt;/a&gt; came out, and I got that, and deleted the original Temple Run. The graphics were much better and the action was more interesting, but again, I got good enough that I got bored. Eventually I stopped playing the game. It&amp;rsquo;s probably been almost a year since I last played it, actually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I still had it on my phone, just in case I got &amp;ldquo;bored&amp;rdquo; or wanted to check up on my reaction time to see if I had retained my improvements. I never did end up playing it again though. Finally, I just deleted it, to free up space on my phone and to commit to saying goodbye to the game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thoughts flashed through my mind as I deleted the game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;we-are-always-choosing-how-to-spend-our-time-we-must-own-our-choices&#34;&gt;We are always choosing how to spend our time; we must own our choices&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I felt guilty every time I played the game on the phone (or the iPad, on which I had also installed the game, but I didn&amp;rsquo;t play it often on that). Part of me thought it was a waste of time. Part of me rationalized that I was &amp;ldquo;training&amp;rdquo; my brain and fingers to improve my overall reaction time and motor coordination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t like feeling guilty about anything&lt;/em&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;d rather just &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; the thing in all good conscience, or &lt;em&gt;not do&lt;/em&gt; it at all. At some point, I resolved the dissonance for good by no longer playing the game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;i-noticed-how-i-had-let-the-smartphone-intrude-on-my-life&#34;&gt;I noticed how I had let the smartphone intrude on my life&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously, upon getting my first smartphone, I was excited by all the things I could do that I couldn&amp;rsquo;t do before. I could check my email anywhere, read my RSS feeds, Facebook, etc. I even loaded up some of my books onto the phone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found myself pulling out the phone to play the game when I was &amp;ldquo;bored&amp;rdquo; while riding in a car or something. Then I realized that I was missing the scenery, or just plain quiet time away from technology. Eventually, I decided to minimize the use of my phone when away from home or work, where I&amp;rsquo;m already in front of a computer most of the time already anyway. Yes, I can spend several hours without checking my phone for email (especially if I&amp;rsquo;m in the middle of nowhere with no reception).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;i-got-sucked-in-by-fear-of-losing-my-accumulated-wealth&#34;&gt;I got sucked in by fear of losing my accumulated &amp;ldquo;wealth&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I took so long to delete the game because I kept thinking that if I ever wanted to keep playing, I had racked up a lot of points and &amp;ldquo;unlocked&amp;rdquo; various powers, so I wanted to keep all that &amp;ldquo;just in case&amp;rdquo;. So keeping the game wasn&amp;rsquo;t even really about my enjoyment of it any more; I just liked the &amp;ldquo;wealth&amp;rdquo; I had accumulated. I was hoarding what was really worthless. The only thing I could do with my unlocked powers was continue playing the game to earn more powers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-was-once-fun-and-useful-may-become-stale&#34;&gt;What was once fun and useful may become stale&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still believe that it was worth spending some time playing the game. It really did improve my mental functioning to a degree. But there were no further benefits to be gained. It is worth periodically evaluating whether old activities or habits are still doing us any good, even if they once did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had my fun with Temple Run, learned some things about myself along the way, and now am done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How do you feel when you uninstall a favorite game or app, or declutter in some other way? Do you feel sadness? Relief? Regret? Pride?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>