<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Smiley Cookie on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/smiley-cookie/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Smiley Cookie on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/smiley-cookie/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Pittsburgh Pirates: it was not to be</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/09/pittsburgh-pirates-it-was-not-to-be/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Oct 2013 23:54:12 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/09/pittsburgh-pirates-it-was-not-to-be/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;At work today, there was a little celebration in honor of the bizarre winning streak of the Pittsburgh Pirates (&amp;ldquo;let&amp;rsquo;s go Bucs!&amp;rdquo;). I&amp;rsquo;ve lived in Pittsburgh for sixteen years now, so it&amp;rsquo;s been pretty weird seeing the Pirates doing so well. I don&amp;rsquo;t follow baseball these days, but I&amp;rsquo;ve been to a handful of games over the years: each time but once, we lost. It was kind of a sad sight, because almost every time I went to a game, there were so few fans out there.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/bucco-cookie.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Bucco Cookie&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed having my first &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.smileycookie.com/pittsburgh-pirates-cookie.html&#34;&gt;Bucco Cookie&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the Bucs lost tonight, so it was not meant to be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wonder how excited everyone will be next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remember as a kid in Michgan watching the Pirates (on TV) win the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/1979_World_Series&#34;&gt;1979 World Series&lt;/a&gt;, thanks to Willie Stargell. To be honest, that&amp;rsquo;s what first put the word &amp;ldquo;Pittsburgh&amp;rdquo; into my vocabulary!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2013 Pittsburgh Marathon: my 135th race was the worst I finished, but I did!</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/05/06/2013-pittsburgh-marathon-my-135th-race-was-my-worst-i-finished/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 May 2013 20:23:08 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/05/06/2013-pittsburgh-marathon-my-135th-race-was-my-worst-i-finished/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/runner-of-steel.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin Chen, runner of steel&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/lying-down.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin lying down&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, for my birthday, I ran the Pittsburgh Marathon for the second time. The first time was &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/30/why-and-how-i-am-going-to-run-the-2013-pittsburgh-marathon/&#34;&gt;ten years ago, in 2003&lt;/a&gt;. That was an ordeal in which I had aimed at finishing in 3:30 and in fact run the first half in 1:45, but then faltered badly to struggle to finish in a &lt;a href=&#34;http://runhigh.com/.2003%20Results%20A/R050403AA.html&#34;&gt;chip time of 3:53:25&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My second Pittsburgh Marathon went even worse. I had wanted to finish in 4:00, but instead &lt;a href=&#34;http://results.active.com/events/dicks-sporting-goods-pittsburgh-marathon&#34;&gt;finished in 4:38:21&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was my 135th race in my life, and the worst of them all that I actually finished (I failed to finish one 30K race because of severe illness that should have kept me from going to the start line at all).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s my report on what happened, why, my thankfulness for all the good that came from the experience, and my running plans for the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;coming-back-from-injury-and-burnout&#34;&gt;Coming back from injury and burnout&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it&amp;rsquo;s important to understand that my poor performance did not come from nowhere. I had battled injury and burnout &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/05/04/i-spent-the-past-week-not-knowing-whether-i-could-run-in-the-2013-pittsburgh-marathon-tomorrow/&#34;&gt;for some time&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Logically&lt;/em&gt;, I should not have gone to the start line at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;night-before&#34;&gt;Night before&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got zero sleep the night before the race. Terrible, but my body was probably confused by the carb-loaded diet as well as my insistence on spending the whole day napping because I was so tired. I had felt that I had to do that napping because I was not going to be able to sleep well at night anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;early-morning-on-race-day&#34;&gt;Early morning on race day&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Super early, Abby drove us to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.visitpittsburgh.com/essentials/neighborhoods/north-shore/&#34;&gt;North Shore&lt;/a&gt; to park. Then we napped for a bit before heading to the nearest &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pittsburgh_Light_Rail&#34;&gt;light rail (aka &amp;ldquo;T&amp;rdquo;)&lt;/a&gt; station to wait for a ride downtown:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/go-downtown.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby and I wait for T&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We got downtown finally, I dropped off a bag of post-race flip-flops at Gear Check, time was starting to run out, and I got in line for a Port-a-pottie:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/port-a-potties.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Port-a-potties&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It was 15 minutes before I did what I needed to do. Then I had to quickly head to my corral.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;clothing&#34;&gt;Clothing&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/franklin-before-marathon.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin before marathon&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What I wore:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the &lt;em&gt;same blue singlet&lt;/em&gt; I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/30/why-and-how-i-am-going-to-run-the-2013-pittsburgh-marathon/&#34;&gt;wore in the 2003 Pittsburgh Marathon ten years ago&lt;/a&gt; (my favorite running shirt that I have actually worn for probably at least 70 of my races in over a decade, as well as most of my warm-weather casual runs also!!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Brooks Infiniti Short III that I bought at Elite Runners and Walkers before the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/30/report-on-just-a-short-run-my-first-half-marathon-in-nine-years/&#34;&gt;Just A Short Run half marathon in March&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Luna Sandals (Venado) that I&amp;rsquo;ve been wearing for almost all of my runs in the past month, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/04/13/my-final-16-mile-long-run-before-pittsburgh-marathon-featured-two-radical-experiments/&#34;&gt;maximum distance of 16 miles&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CEP compression calf sleeves, which I had worn just &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/04/20/on-overtraining-and-feeling-injured-two-weeks-before-the-pittsburgh-marathon/&#34;&gt;one other time&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/22/paradox-i-will-observe-the-national-day-of-unplugging-but-just-bought-my-first-smartphone-this-week/&#34;&gt;phone&lt;/a&gt;, in a SPIbelt.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;on my back, I pinned a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/04/20/on-overtraining-and-feeling-injured-two-weeks-before-the-pittsburgh-marathon/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;We are all Boston Marathoners at heart&amp;rdquo; bib&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a long-sleeve T-shirt on top of my singlet, since it was cold (under 50 degrees F?) before the race; the plan was to discard this T-shirt before the race (and hope that people collect it and find a good home for it!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;entering-the-corral&#34;&gt;Entering the corral&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the second race in my life in which I have carried a phone. I planned to use it only in case of emergency, and in order to meet up with Abby afterwards, but as you can see, while I had a chance, I took some photos also.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/corral-c.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Corral C&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I was assigned to corral C because of my estimated finish time of 4:00 that I had written down when signing up for the marathon months ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This was my first mistake.&lt;/em&gt; Given my comeback from injury and inactivity, the truly logical thing for me to have done was to set a very conservative goal of simply finishing the marathon without terrible suffering. Given that I ended up finishing in 4:38, I might as well have moved back into another corral and &lt;em&gt;planned&lt;/em&gt; to finish in the 4:20-4:30 range, in which case I bet I would have done that with minimal pain and suffering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the future, I resolve to face the facts on the ground in any event as strenuous as a marathon. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t make any sense what I did, especially given that I was perfectly smart when &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/30/report-on-just-a-short-run-my-first-half-marathon-in-nine-years/&#34;&gt;in March I did my first half marathon in nine years and ran it conservatively and had a great experience&lt;/a&gt;! I am capable of logical reasoning and have actually executed it in the past. But apparently the marathon puts me into a hyper-emotional frame of mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;pace&#34;&gt;Pace?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, I had chosen not to sign up to follow an &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pittsburghmarathon.com/pace-team&#34;&gt;official pacer&lt;/a&gt;, because on all my long training runs, I had found my own pace by feel, and done well ignoring pacers. My plan was simply to go slow and then get faster. I did look around for pace signs. I only saw one from where I was standing: a sign near the front of the corral for finishing in 3:50. I looked back and saw no other signs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This was my second mistake.&lt;/em&gt; Given that I had not done any serious running for ten days, with my longest run being only two miles, and my last &amp;ldquo;long&amp;rdquo; run was an eleven-mile run fifteen days ago, I should have realized that whatever &amp;ldquo;feel&amp;rdquo; I had for pace was gone, and I should have moved back in the corral till I found a 4:00-finishing pacer, at least (but as mentioned earlier, what I should have done was move into a slower corral altogether and then found a suitable pacer there).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;race-start&#34;&gt;Race start&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a moment of silence for Boston.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Star-Spangled Banner, then the waves began. A photo as mine was approaching the start line, around 7:05 AM:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/start-line.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;About to reach the start line&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Then we went.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;wrong-pace&#34;&gt;Wrong pace&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I honestly thought I was going slow. I was hardly breathing at all. I was going so &amp;ldquo;slow&amp;rdquo; that I pulled out my phone to take some photos. But then I got very confused, because the 3:50 pacer was still in my sight after many minutes:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/early.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Early in the marathon&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I could not process this information. Part of me wanted to slow down, but I felt like I was barely running. Part of me believed that the pacer must be slow, but come on, these pacers are supposed to be reliable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I &lt;em&gt;made the mistake&lt;/em&gt; of not trusting the pacer. It sounds crazy, but I really felt like I was going too slow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;slowing-down&#34;&gt;Slowing down?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point, I lost sight of the pacer, so I felt reassured that I must have slowed down properly. Here&amp;rsquo;s another problem: I did not keep track of my mile splits because the mass of people made it hard for me to actually reliably spot any mile markers on the course; I don&amp;rsquo;t even know how many actually existed.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/bridge.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Crossing bridge&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I even took a photo of myself 40 minutes into the marathon feeling fine.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/franklin-early.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There were spectators on bridges, some of them positioned seemingly precariously.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/spectators-on-bridges.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Spectators on bridge&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At some point I realized that I could see the 3:50 pacer up ahead. I got worried. It was unlikely that I was magically super-fit now. But I didn&amp;rsquo;t feel like slowing down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point I must have started slowing down, because eventually I saw a 3:55 pacer pass me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still, it appears from the alert system that I signed up for (to notify my parents by email, and Abby by text message, and my Facebook friends and Twitter followers), that I did the first 10K (6.2 miles) in 55:29, meaning an average pace of 8:56 and estimated finish time of 3:54:04. That&amp;rsquo;s much faster than the 9:08 pace I had intended for a 4:00 finish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;really-slowing-down&#34;&gt;Really slowing down&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started really slowing down before even reaching the Birmingham Bridge. I knew I was getting into serious trouble. It was crazy, but my left knee was bothering me, and my left quads had started to twitch. So I had gone only about 11 miles and I was already struggling.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/birmingham-bridge.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;On Birmingham Bridge&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You have to understand how &lt;em&gt;nonsensical&lt;/em&gt; it is for me to be having muscle cramping after running only 11 miles at a pace that is actually slow for an 11-mile run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if we assumed, falsely, that I got to mile 11 at the same pace as during my first 6.2 miles (8:56), note that I ran an entire half marathon (13.1 miles) in late March, only in the beginning of marathon training, at an average of 8:28 pace, and was totally fine with no cramping during the race. And after a couple of weeks of further training, I had felt much stronger during a 16-mile run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So basically, it was a cruel joke I played on myself that I was in such poor condition that I was cramping up after 11 miles at a slow pace. I was very angry at myself that I had made a complete &lt;em&gt;travesty&lt;/em&gt; of my marathon, &lt;em&gt;just like in 2003&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;halfway-and-change-of-plan&#34;&gt;Halfway, and change of plan&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I slowed down more in Oakland to keep the left quad twitching under control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the alert system, I got halfway in 1:59:46, average pace of 9:09, and estimated finish time of 3:59:31. But of course, by then, I knew that I was done for. I was just going to continue slowing down and suffering, for &lt;em&gt;over two more hours&lt;/em&gt;, if I finished at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I finally saw the 4:00 pace group pass me, somehow that was a real blow to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At 9:27 AM, not too long after the halfway point, I texted Abby: &amp;ldquo;Severe pain. Very slow, just aim finish. Maybe 4:30.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now my main thought was to focus on making it to Annie (of the Pittsburgh Recorder Society), who was going to watch for me in Highland Park, just before mile 20. I had told her to expect me around 10 AM, and Annie had even posted to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/photo.php?fbid=463404163737512&amp;amp;set=a.368839359860660.86924.330712777006652&amp;amp;type=1&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Recorder Society Facebook page&lt;/a&gt; telling everyone I was running.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was so not going to make it for 10 AM. But I wanted to go slowly enough that I could hold off the quad cramping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;despair&#34;&gt;Despair&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At around 9:49 AM, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.runoverit.com/&#34;&gt;Chris&lt;/a&gt; passed me and said hello. I told him I was doing very badly. He wasn&amp;rsquo;t doing as well as he had hoped, but was moving along, unlike me. Here&amp;rsquo;s a photo I had the presence of mind to take only as he had already gone way ahead (in the blue shirt):&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/chris.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Chris up ahead in blue shirt&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At 9:54 AM, I made a video statement on my phone, just for myself: &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m after mile 17 or something, in Homewood. I&amp;rsquo;m doing really badly, but I&amp;rsquo;m still running, and that&amp;rsquo;s all I can say about that.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/12inzKGZGRU&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/despair.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Despair after mile 17 in Pittsburgh Marathon&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;annie&#34;&gt;Annie&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At 10:11 AM, not yet at Annie&amp;rsquo;s, I was contemplating quitting, because the pains I was experiencing (right quads twitching also, and even my arms and hands, mysteriously, in spots where I had old injuries years ago, plus a really bad blister on my right foot where I had all those skin problems earlier, and less bad but very annoying constant chafing of the Luna Sandals straps) were so terrible. I decided to just take a break at a fluid station and squat and stretch. I texted Abby: &amp;ldquo;Very bad shape. Rested some.&amp;rdquo; I also finally &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/franklin.chen/posts/10201315392704609&#34;&gt;posted to Facebook&lt;/a&gt;, &amp;ldquo;In very bad shape. Trying to finish anyway.&amp;rdquo; I was not actively reading Facebook during the marathon at all, but did notice a lot of notifications, and assumed they were words of encouragement from my friends; I didn&amp;rsquo;t want to read them until I was done, because I felt I might let them down. Abby replied, &amp;ldquo;What is your plan?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At 10:19, I said, &amp;ldquo;Don&amp;rsquo;t know. Walking, blister and cramping.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A note on the blistering and chafing: it got really warm and I got sweaty, so that was part of the problem. I had not run in these sandals in such conditions before: I had mostly run in dry, cold conditions of 35-50 degrees F. Also, I had forgotten about road hazards: there were cups of water and Gatorade all over around the aid stations and my feet were sticky and wet for much of the marathon. It was a rather unpleasant feeling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I kept running/walking. I saw Annie. I decided there and then, seeing her, that I was going to finish, rather than just bail out and crash on her couch or something pathetic like that. I shouted that I was in severe pain but planned to continue on! She took a photo of me, which I knew was going to be on Facebook before too long, so I&amp;rsquo;d better make good on my promise to her!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/franklin-in-highland-park.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin in Highland Park&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At 10:29, I texted Abby: &amp;ldquo;Got to Annie. Running again.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I then focused on just continuing to move, slowing to a walk if I needed to in order to deal with cramping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;mile-22&#34;&gt;Mile 22&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At 10:51, I reached S Aiken, just before mile 22. This is an important point in the course for me, not only because it begins a downhill, but also because it is where my friend Nathaniel cheered me on ten years ago when I was also suffering.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/aiken.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;S Aiken&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;strip-district&#34;&gt;Strip District&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point, I was getting discouraged again and started walking, when I accidentally spotted Deb and Mark watching. Seeing familiar faces among the spectators is definitely helpful! Upon seeing them, I felt ashamed of my walking and my negative thoughts. I went up to them, and they were going to take a picture of me, and I got all determined, and &lt;em&gt;screamed&lt;/em&gt;, &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m going to finish this thing!!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/im-going-to-finish-this-thing.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin determined to finish&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I kept on running, and did not stop, even though I saw many people walking, and also saw many relay runners zooming by. I decided that I was not only going to finish (it was now clear that I could), but that I was going to finish as strong as I could, even though it would count for nothing. I was going to run at the edge of quad twitching, all the way to the end. It was going to hurt far more than if I just ran very slowly to finish, but I didn&amp;rsquo;t come this far just to walk if I could run. I was determined to push.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/franklin-in-strip.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin in Strip District&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As I got closer and closer, I periodically texted Abby the street I had just crossed, so that she would know roughly when I was going to finish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;finish-line&#34;&gt;Finish line&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so I finished. I finished in a state of my quads twitching like firecrackers. I got my medal. I kept on walking. I grabbed a bag of chips and water. I forgot to look for other stuff, like Smiley Cookies (that Abby later said she saw were being handed out). I just wanted to stop the twitching, get my bag from Gear Check, get out of my Luna Sandals into some comfortable, cushioned flip-flops, use a Port-a-potty, and finally find Abby and the &amp;ldquo;CMU tent&amp;rdquo;, which I assumed was just a section of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pittsburghmarathon.com/PCC&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Corporate Challenge Tent&lt;/a&gt;. (I had bought a bracelet for Abby earlier so that she could have access to the tent.)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/after.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;After finishing&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I could barely walk after I started cooling down, because I got stiffer and stiffer. It took me forever to make it to the Finish Line Festival area, and I was so mentally drained that I had to call Abby to have her tell me where the tent was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;videos-update-of-2013-05-23&#34;&gt;Videos (update of 2013-05-23)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburgh.cbslocal.com/2013/05/05/2013-marathon-finish-line-videos/&#34;&gt;Videos of the Pittsburgh Marathon have been posted&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found myself in &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburgh.cbslocal.com/video/8844851-2013-marathon-finish-line-44000-45000/&#34;&gt;one of the sets of videos&lt;/a&gt;, for those who finished in a clock time between 4:40:00 and 4:50:00.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see me at around 4:44:35 and finishing at about 4:44:40 here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&#39;text/javascript&#39; src=&#39;http://CBSPIT.images.worldnow.com/interface/js/WNVideo.js?rnd=998125;hostDomain=video.pittsburgh.cbslocal.com;playerWidth=615;playerHeight=365;isShowIcon=true;clipId=8844851;flvUri=;partnerclipid=;adTag=Sport;advertisingZone=CBS.PITTS%252Fworldnowplayer;enableAds=true;landingPage=;islandingPageoverride=false;playerType=STANDARD_EMBEDDEDscript;controlsType=fixed&#39;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://video.pittsburgh.cbslocal.com&#34; title=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-tent-and-the-pittsburgh-campus-challenge&#34;&gt;The tent and the Pittsburgh Campus Challenge&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I signed up for the Pittsburgh Campus Challenge through Carnegie Mellon University, there was advertised to be &amp;ldquo;gourmet food, private massages, and more&amp;rdquo; in the tent. The reality was actually quite different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby said it was a good thing she made it to the tent before too late (she had gone back to nap in the car after seeing me off), because by 10 AM, half marathoners had eaten much of the food already, and she had remembered to save some for me for later! There was still food left, but much of the good stuff was gone. And it wasn&amp;rsquo;t really &amp;ldquo;gourmet&amp;rdquo;. There was dry fried chicken, rolls, pasta left, as far as I could tell, other than the pancakes Abby had saved from earlier, and  a Panera Bread sandwiches she also saved for me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/abby.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/tent-food.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Tent food&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There was a signup sheet for massage by Massage Envy, however, and a very long wait, as I got my massage after one hour and twenty minutes, which was actually OK because I was so sore I simply needed to be left alone for a while to just eat and eat and rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;cmu-won&#34;&gt;CMU won!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I came into the tent, there was confusion because I didn&amp;rsquo;t have a sticker on my bib indicating that I had access to the tent. Apparently I was supposed to have gotten a sticker at some point, but I don&amp;rsquo;t remember getting instructions about that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When they learned I was with CMU, however, they gave me the prize for CMU winning the Pittsburgh Campus Challenge, to hand over to Pattye at CMU. We beat Pitt!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/pittsburgh-campus-challenge.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Pittsburgh Campus Challenge prize&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;feet&#34;&gt;Feet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My feet were terribly sore. I got one blood-filled blister:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/blister.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Blister on right foot&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But otherwise, the damage was not as bad as I had thought. During the marathon, I had wondered sometimes about all the stickiness I felt on my feet, but it was not blood after all; it was a mixture of energy gel, Gatorade, orange juice, and whatever else was left on the road that got onto my feet:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/feet.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I had two chafing spots from the straps, but they were not serious. All in all, my feet were in much condition after wearing the Luna Sandals than they were ten years ago after wearing standard socks and running shoes. The drawback is that my feet were horribly sore, although after one night of rest, the foot soreness is actually all gone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;one-day-later&#34;&gt;One day later&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I do have a different problem: one day later, numbness in my left foot remains, because I had adjusted my strap for my left foot too tightly, out of fear of it coming off. &lt;em&gt;Overly tight strap was a big mistake.&lt;/em&gt; I did make an adjustment at some point during the race, but I could at least have loosened the strap earlier when I felt discomfort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In all my previous runs, my left foot has never fallen out. I hope the numbness goes away in another day.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/feet-day-after.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;My feet the day after&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;legs&#34;&gt;Legs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My legs were utterly trashed, as might be expected given how I had tortured them for so long. At first, I thought it was just my quads and hamstrings, but once I pulled off the calf sleeves, I realized that my calves were trashed too, but had &lt;em&gt;completely&lt;/em&gt; avoided cramping because of the compression. I count this as a total success for the calf sleeves, because in the marathon ten years ago, my calves were seizing up in the second half, not just my quads. &lt;em&gt;I will always wear calf sleeves in the future in long runs or hikes&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Em of Massage Envy was very helpful in getting me able to sort of walk, so that I could go with Abby back over to the North Shore to our car (I had to walk across the bridge, then waited as she brought the car over).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/massage-envy.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Massage Envy&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Overall, I think wearing the Luna Sandals was the correct decision, despite the drawbacks. I did &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; have toe jamming, toe blistering, toe cramping that I believe I would have had in other footwear. I did not have ankle soreness of any kind. Or shin splints. I did not have any right knee pain at all, just left (and almost certainly because of my fall on Thursday). I could have used more cushioning though. But my order of the thicker Luna Sandals (the new Mono model) has not yet shipped.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;thanks&#34;&gt;Thanks!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a lot to be thankful for even though in some sense this marathon was truly a debacle for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am thankful that this race returned to Pittsburgh after suspension in 2004-2008, as Dick&amp;rsquo;s Sporting Goods rose up to be the title sponsor. I am amazed by how large and popular the Pittsburgh Marathon has become since I last ran it ten years ago. I think it&amp;rsquo;s great that the city has this annual celebration of its neighborhoods and of the running community. The Pittsburgh Marathon is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; just about the marathon, but about just regular fitness running, free workshops on health and exercise, and celebrating a sport that brings everyone together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am thankful to Pattye Stragar for spreading word of the Pittsburgh Campus Challenge through the CMU fitness mailing list.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am thankful to Steel City Road Runners for their well-organized Saturday long runs that got me out during the cold months when I otherwise might have chosen to just sleep in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am thankful to my friends who encouraged me as I progressed through my training and in my discouraging days before the marathon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am thankful to Annie and Deb and Mark for being spectators I saw and knew who gave me additional motivation to keep going.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am thankful to all the spectators and volunteers I don&amp;rsquo;t know who offered cheers, water, orange slices, music, and everything else that reminded me that humanity is caring and helpful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And of course, I am particularly thankful to my wife Abby, who has been so patient these months as I have pursued this marathon thing that she thinks is crazy (OK, I know it is crazy), and helped me every single day. Abby, this whole experience has truly deepened my appreciation of you, and I will never forget what we went through together to make this birthday present happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;did-i-achieve-my-goals&#34;&gt;Did I achieve my goals?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s go back to &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/30/why-and-how-i-am-going-to-run-the-2013-pittsburgh-marathon/&#34;&gt;my blog post from three months ago where I stated my goals for the marathon&lt;/a&gt;. What did I actually achieve?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;maintain a smart pace: failed (totally)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;finish strong: succeeded (insofar as I pushed as hard as I could for the last three miles approximately)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;avoid leg muscle cramping: failed miserably with the quads, succeeded with the calves&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;avoid foot blistering: failed (got one bad blister)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;conquer the hills: neutral (didn&amp;rsquo;t feel particularly bad at hills as such)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it would seem that I basically failed, as far as the marathon itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I think I succeeded, in a larger context:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t expect to be wearing huaraches for a marathon, but I did wear Luna Sandals! I proved to myself it could be done.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As a side effect of marathon training, I got myself into much better shape than I have been in for the past half decade, and did my first half marathon in nine years, and set up exercise habits I hope to make permanent independent of any future marathoning.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Abby&amp;rsquo;s help as I took on the task of training made a profound impression on me.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The outpouring of support from friends was a welcome surprise to me, because in my last Pittsburgh Marathon, I mostly went about it alone, telling only a few people about it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-did-i-fail-so-miserably&#34;&gt;Why did I fail so miserably?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe I failed mostly because I didn&amp;rsquo;t have the proper training. I started too late, I didn&amp;rsquo;t have enough time to more gradually absorb increased training volume, I could have used an extra month or two of more long runs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also did not adapt properly to setbacks that should have led me to change my goals drastically. There was a downward spiral in terms of injury, fatigue, and loss of calm reason.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-next&#34;&gt;What next?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;done-with-the-marathon&#34;&gt;Done with the marathon&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I told Abby that this is it: no more racing marathons again, ever. I mean it. I&amp;rsquo;m facing the reality that this is not the right event for me. I believe I could do a good marathon, but what it would take is not worth the effort. The sacrifices that I made, and Abby made, were considerable. There are other things we could be doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I look forward to our returning to &amp;ldquo;normal&amp;rdquo; life as I recover.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;running&#34;&gt;Running&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, I totally enjoyed getting back into year-round running. I will never go into winter hibernation again. I still have to figure out ideal footwear for the coldest and snow/ice/water-ridden conditions for next winter, of course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;half-marathons&#34;&gt;Half marathons&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Doing Just A Short Run again gave me confidence that I can &amp;ldquo;master&amp;rdquo; the half marathon distance. I would like to continue doing half marathons. I have decided to do the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mtchalfmarathon.com/&#34;&gt;Montour Trail Half Marathon&lt;/a&gt; in September. This means I will have to skip the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~kalp/PGR/&#34;&gt;CMU Pretty Good Race&lt;/a&gt;, which is always held the Friday before this Saturday race, but it&amp;rsquo;s time for me to get back into doing half marathon and 10K and 5K (and even mile) races, distances that I can actually work on being able to run well without wrecking myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heck, I might even run the Pittsburgh Half Marathon a year from now! (Although I don&amp;rsquo;t actually want to think about that for a while.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In isolation, the 2013 Pittsburgh Marathon may be considered to be a total debacle for me, the worst race I&amp;rsquo;ve finished out of the 135 races I&amp;rsquo;ve showed up for in my life. But I&amp;rsquo;m glad I went through the process of training for it, and I&amp;rsquo;m grateful for it as a vehicle of self-discovery: I faced some unpleasant truths about various poor decisions I made. And I&amp;rsquo;m grateful for the opportunity to share my journey with friends and family.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.guardian.co.uk/sport/blog/2012/jun/22/50-olympic-stunning-moments-emil-zatopek&#34;&gt;Emil Zatopek&lt;/a&gt; said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
If you want to run, run a mile. If you want to experience a different life, run a marathon.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-05-09&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-05-09)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second day after the marathon, I was still in physical and emotional pain, and wrote a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/05/07/why-i-feel-sad-when-people-congratulate-me-for-finishing-the-pittsburgh-marathon/&#34;&gt;little rant expressing my disappointment&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third day, I was able to walk normally and was emotionally recovering as well and was embarrassed by my rant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fourth day, I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/05/09/back-to-what-running-is-really-about-for-me/&#34;&gt;went out for a short run and reflected on what running is really about for me&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-12-22&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-12-22)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I just wanted to point out a much healthier attitude and experience of a marathon gone badly: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.letsrun.com/news/2013/11/time-life/&#34;&gt;this is a really beautiful article&lt;/a&gt; that every disappointed racer should read.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recognize that I trapped myself during March and April with increasingly unbalanced expectations of my marathon, and lost all calmness and perspective. I still don&amp;rsquo;t know whether I will run a marathon again, but if I do, I vow to do it with a clear mind and body.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Report on Just A Short Run: my first half marathon in nine years!</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/03/30/report-on-just-a-short-run-my-first-half-marathon-in-nine-years/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Mar 2013 15:06:18 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/03/30/report-on-just-a-short-run-my-first-half-marathon-in-nine-years/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;(Updated 2013-05-09 with official race videos!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until today, I had not run a half marathon in nine years. This distance had given me a lot of trouble the five times I did it in 2001-2004. So I was very anxious about running &lt;a href=&#34;http://eliterunners.com/just-a-short-run/&#34;&gt;Just A Short Run&lt;/a&gt; this morning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s why I feared it, and how I ended up unexpectedly pleased with the experience, including finishing over four minutes faster than my goal time.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/just-a-short-run-2013/franklin.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin done&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;past-participation-in-just-a-short-run&#34;&gt;Past participation in Just A Short Run&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was the fifth time I participated in Just A Short Run. This race began in 2001, when &lt;a href=&#34;http://eliterunners.com/running-shoes-pittsburgh/about-running-store/&#34;&gt;Kevin Smith&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href=&#34;http://eliterunners.com/&#34;&gt;Elite Runners and Walkers&lt;/a&gt; created in in memory of his younger brother who died of leukemia, to &lt;a href=&#34;http://eliterunners.com/just-a-short-run-about/&#34;&gt;support the Leukemia and Lymphoma Society&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/ipDidl-_qpM&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until today I have done the Just A Short Run four times:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;5K in 2001&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;half marathon in 2002&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;30K in 2003 (my only DNF in my life, because I went into it sick)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;5K in 2004&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;past-half-marathons&#34;&gt;Past half marathons&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have only once ever partly successfully executed a half marathon race, and even then, some things went rather wrong. Here&amp;rsquo;s a summary of what went wrong in each of my half marathons up till today:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;ikea-montour-trail-half-marathon-2001&#34;&gt;Ikea Montour Trail half marathon, 2001&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was my very first half marathon, after having run some good 5K races earlier in the year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went out too fast (because of an initial downhill that got me too excited), and paid the price. I finished in 1:47:23. My splits for the 13.1 miles:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;6:31.94&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;7:59.53&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;8:09.44&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;8:16.53&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;8:16.99&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;8:19.28&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;8:19.64&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;7:44.85&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;8:01.41&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;8:23.29&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;8:28.72&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;8:42.36&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;9:17.34&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;0:49.85&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was just struggling in the last miles, and very demoralized. I almost collapsed on my buddy Jude&amp;rsquo;s shoulder after I finished. Also, I had major blisters during the race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;just-a-short-run-half-marathon-2002&#34;&gt;Just A Short Run half marathon, 2002&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did this race without any real training at all, just because it was there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got blisters in the race, and also had to deal with weird existential thoughts like &amp;ldquo;Why am I running this?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I finished in 1:49:34, but actually, the course was found to be long by about a tenth of a mile, so that number does not mean much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;ikea-montour-trail-half-marathon-2002&#34;&gt;Ikea Montour Trail half marathon, 2002&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got my revenge in this race, actually training hard specifically for the distance, doing long intervals and a lot of tempo and race-pace runs. Overall I did very well, finishing in 1:38:48, but the experience was marred by some serious problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ran mile 4 too fast, but since I was carefully monitoring on my watch, I slowed down for mile 5. Still, one pays the price eventually for going too fast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, I still was not fueling consistently. I erred by taking both water and energy drink, resulting in dilution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In mile 12, my calves started cramping up and I had to stop at one point. I lost about half a minute because of this. In mile 13, I had to run conservatively to avoid cramps. It was very frustrating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, after I finished, while getting on the shuttle bus, I cramped up quite severely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;ikea-montour-trail-half-marathon-2003&#34;&gt;Ikea Montour Trail half marathon, 2003&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A total disaster. I finished in 1:45:32, which is 7:44 slower than the previous year. This was while having a 5K fitness similar to the previous year&amp;rsquo;s. Something just went wrong. I felt sluggish throughout, and I cramped up in mile 10. And I had digestive problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;chamber-classic-half-marathon-2004&#34;&gt;Chamber Classic half marathon, 2004&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1:46:12. No real training for it, just did it because it was there and I had not been able to do the Montour Trail one. A fiasco, in which I struggled with my usual problems (slowing down in the final miles, cramping).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;preparation&#34;&gt;Preparation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did not go into this race truly prepared to &lt;em&gt;race&lt;/em&gt; the half marathon. I know what it takes to race a half marathon for time: long tempo and race-pace runs, long intervals. I have done little of that so far this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My hardest training run so far has been &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/16/18-miles-in-vibram-fivefingers-training-for-the-pittsburgh-marathon/&#34;&gt;16 miles with the Steel City Road Runners, two weeks ago, on an 18 mile course&lt;/a&gt;. I did not truly taper for the half marathon race, although this week including the race I have a reduced mileage of 25 (easy 6, easy 3, speed ladder 3, and then the race).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather, what I am really training for is the Pittsburgh Marathon, but I felt that I should do a half marathon race in order to get a taste of what it is like to run in a long race. I have been doing long runs every week for a while now, so running the half marathon distance is not a problem: the challenge for me was to figure out if I could partially &lt;em&gt;race&lt;/em&gt; it, to find my limits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I wanted to fix the problems I had in my previous half marathons:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;blistering&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;going out too fast&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;slowing way down&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;cramping&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;digestive problems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;blistering&#34;&gt;Blistering&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Solving the problem of blistering has been trivial for me since I switched to wearing Vibram FiveFingers shoes. I just don&amp;rsquo;t get serious blisters any more; my feet have adapted completely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, I just got my Luna Sandals two days ago, but have not run in them yet. Friends helpfully convinced me that it would be crazy to wear them in the race without any actual test of them (I knew that, but just needed validation).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the &lt;em&gt;first half marathon&lt;/em&gt; I&amp;rsquo;m running in Vibram FiveFingers. Up till now, the longest distance I&amp;rsquo;ve raced in FiveFingers has been &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/25/blistered-but-blissful-in-the-burgh/&#34;&gt;10K, when I was still getting blistered by the Bikila LS&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;going-out-too-fast&#34;&gt;Going out too fast&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By not treating this as an all-out race whose goal is to minimize time, I could afford to run more conservatively and plan on negative-splitting. I decide to target a time of 1:55:00 (reasonable given &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/03/my-first-steel-city-road-runners-winter-5k-race/&#34;&gt;my recent 5K&lt;/a&gt; time of 25:11), with the idea of speeding up if it felt right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;slowing-way-down&#34;&gt;Slowing way down&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I consciously carb-loaded for this half marathon and had a race fueling plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;cramping&#34;&gt;Cramping&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have no idea how to really solve this problem. I think I must be genetically predisposed to cramping. People like to claim electrolyte deficiency is the cause, but I don&amp;rsquo;t believe this at all, because I have tried loading up on electrolytes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;digestive-problems&#34;&gt;Digestive problems&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have concluded that it is safest to avoid Gatorade and the like on the course because people mix it in funny proportions. Sticking with predictable gels and water is my new plan. One gel before starting the race, and then one gel every 45 minutes after that (which in the case of a half marathon means two gels on the course).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, I used to drink too much water, resulting in sloshing in the stomach. So I drink less now during a race, and drink more well before it starts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-route&#34;&gt;The route&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;iframe id=&#34;mapmyfitness_route&#34; src=&#34;http://snippets.mapmycdn.com/routes/view/embedded/24782?width=560&amp;height=400&amp;elevation=true&amp;info=true&amp;line_color=E60f0bdb&amp;rgbhex=DB0B0E&amp;distance_markers=1&amp;unit_type=imperial&amp;map_mode=TERRAIN&amp;last_updated=2006-03-10T16:46:31-05:00&#34; height=&#34;590px&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: right; padding-right: 20px;&#34;&gt;&lt;a target=&#34;_blank&#34; href=&#34;http://mapmyrun.com/routes/create/&#34;&gt;Create Maps&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a target=&#34;_blank&#34; href=&#34;http://mapmyrun.com/routes/&#34;&gt;search&lt;/a&gt; from 80 million at &lt;a href=&#34;http://mapmyrun.com&#34;&gt;MapMyRun&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

Note the big hill at the beginning. Control of effort going up and down hills is critical, to avoid bad spikes in energy usage.

## The race

Here are the [official race results](http://www.runhigh.com/2013RESULTS/R033013AA.html).

### Start


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/just-a-short-run-2013/announcements.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Announcements&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


I started out with the 1:55:00 finish pacer (8:47 pace):


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/just-a-short-run-2013/pacer.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;My initial pacer&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


Going up the big hill, however, he totally lost me, as I slowed down to avoid prematurely feeling the burn. In fact, a slower pacer even passed me. No problem.

On the downhill, I quickly started regaining ground. I think after around three miles, I had caught up to the original 8:47 pacer, and then that was feeling too slow for me, so I passed him for good, and never saw a pacer again in the race.

### Gatorade error

I made an error at one of the aid stations when I mistaken grabbed Gatorade and threw it in my face. I got stickiness all over my face and the front of my jacket and fingers. It was really disgusting, actually. I will be more careful in the future to ask what stuff is before taking a cup.

Otherwise, I stuck well to my plan of taking water and two gels during the entire half marathon. Note that the race provided [e-Gel](http://www.cranksports.com/products/eGel/), which I had not had before. If I were seriously racing this half marathon, obviously I would have bought and tried this stuff on long runs ahead of time.

### Passing people

The thing about Just A Short Run is that people are running different races and therefore are at different paces, and also in such a huge race, there are always those who are inexperienced and go out too fast and slow down. What this means, in practice, is that if you are running evenly (or for a negative split, like I was doing), you will be needing to pass people constantly. It is very important to be a good judge of your own pace, because otherwise you might think you are doing OK, while the reality is you&#39;re following someone who is slowing down.

I like to target someone who looks faster than me and then try to keep up with him or her. I did this repeatedly in the race.

At one point I asked a guy what his pace was, and he said 8:30. I was feeling good, so eventually I passed him. I realized at that moment that I was going to be able to run considerably faster than 1:55:00, despite my very slow start.

### Last five miles

I maintained speed in the last 5 miles of the race; I might even have gone faster, but without the data, I cannot tell, since when fatigue sets in, effort does not equal actual pace. I was definitely getting tired, but I kept pushing, trying to pretend I was running a 10K race or something. I thought that I just might have a shot at finishing under 1:50:00. I didn&#39;t, but that&#39;s OK. I finished in 1:50:52.

The official [split data](http://www.runhigh.com/2013RESULTS/R033013AF.html) shows that I did the last 5 miles in 42:03, which is about 8:25 pace. Since I averaged 8:28 pace for the whole race, I clearly ran faster in the last 5 miles than in the first 8.1 miles.

If I had known what I was capable of, I could have run faster and more evenly from the start, and finished faster, but that was quite explicitly *not* the goal today. The goal was to finish strong, which I did.

## SPIbelt

This was my first time running a race wearing a SPIbelt. It did not cause me any trouble at all; I barely noticed it. I will wear it during the Pittsburgh Marathon, in order to have my phone on me in case of emergency. I did not use my phone during the race, only before and after it, but it&#39;s always nice to know that I can directly contact Abby if something goes wrong.

## Cramping

I did a little bit of a final sprint across the finish line. The moment I crossed was the moment when I felt both of my calves start to twitch. I realized that I almost crossed the line to full-on cramping, and decided to keep moving. I grabbed a banana and ate it while jogging slowly, and planning to jog off the heaviness in my calves.

Then disaster struck: I stubbed my right toes on the ground and instantly two of my toes cramped up and my lower right calf also cramped up. I ripped off my shoe and luckily, after about twenty seconds, I was OK again. I decided it was unsafe to keep moving, and I went upstairs in the North Park Boat House to just keep warm and stretch in a safe environment. I did not cramp up again.

So I have not entirely solved the cramping problem. Apparently sprinting was enough to push me over the edge. Also, closed-toe shoes are a problem because my toes inevitably get at least somewhat jammed in the course of running in closed-toe shoes. This is why I want to test out the Luna Sandals, which may completely prevent toe jamming and cramping. As for my calves, I don&#39;t know, maybe I just need to do more hard longer runs in order to get them accustomed to the lactic acid buildup or something.

## Post-race eating

My stomach was entirely OK during the race. No water sloshing, no indigestion, no gnawing hunger. I was hungry after finishing, of course.


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/just-a-short-run-2013/food.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Post-race food&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


I made some mistakes after finishing, however. I ate not only a banana, but also a bagel, a Smiley Cookie, a little bag of chips, and a little bag of cookies. I believe I should have excluded the bag of cookies and the chips, and saved the Smiley Cookie for later. I had some digestive discomfort (nothing serious though) for a while after everything I ate. I will remember next time. After a 5K or 10K, I can eat anything, but apparently, after a half marathon, digestion is trickier.

But it is hard not to gobble up a Smiley Cookie:


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/just-a-short-run-2013/smiley-cookie.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Smiley Cookie&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


At home, I ended up deciding to eat familiar leftovers rather than going out to a buffet as I had originally thought of doing with Abby.

## Feet

My feet were sore, but actually, less sore than after each of my long runs in the past month. I think I&#39;ve become more efficient. No knee pain either. After the race, just general inflammation. I think I&#39;ll be OK tomorrow.


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/just-a-short-run-2013/shoes.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Vibram FiveFingers Bikila LS&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/just-a-short-run-2013/feet.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin&amp;#39;s feet&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/just-a-short-run-2013/soles.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin&amp;#39;s soles of feet&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


I did get one small blister, on my right pinkie toe, but I didn&#39;t actually notice it until I was home and took a shower.

## What does all this mean for the marathon?

This [race time predictor](http://www.runnersworld.co.uk/general/rws-race-time-predictor/1681.html) suggests that given that I ran a half marathon in 1:50:52, I can do a full marathon in 3:51:08. I am, frankly, skeptical that I can go under 4:00:00 at all a month from now. I know I want to be conservative in the marathon, and I rather doubt I will be able to negative-split it, and I still have concerns about late-stage cramping or other physical deterioration. We shall see how my training progresses. I am going to start adding &#34;quality&#34; work in the form of interval training in order to toughen up.

## Thanks

Many thanks to my wife Abby, who dropped me off at the race and picked me up after visiting her parents in the vicinity, saving me driving and parking hassles! And thanks to all my friends who have been supportive while I&#39;ve been so nervous for weeks about this race!

I like to thank [Elite Runners and Walkers](http://eliterunners.com/) for putting on a really well-organized race. The instructions were very clear, volunteers giving out water, Gatorade, and gels were everywhere, there was plenty of post-race food, bag check was convenient, and everything seemed to go smoothly. I would like to take this opportunity to say that without Elite Runners and Walkers, I do not know where I would be as a runner. Back over a decade ago, when I started running, the Internet was not what it is now. I got information about running from books and magazines and word of mouth more than anything else. I was told about the new store Elite Runners and Walkers and I got some of my first running shoes and clothing there. I even bought my very first pair of Vibram FiveFingers KSO shoes there, in 2009, before minimalist shoes suddenly became more mainstream and available in other stores, and last year when I got some rips in those first Vibram FiveFingers shoes, I got a new pair of KSO shoes through them also. And the races they put on in the winter and spring are great: I used to run their [Spring Thaw](http://eliterunners.com/events/annual-spring-thaw/) as well as Just A Short Run. And when picking up my race packet at the store this week, Abby and I bought some more shirts and shorts in preparation for summer!

## Conclusion

This was my slowest half marathon ever, but one of the most satisfying, and one of the best-executed, given my actual fitness level, which is substantially lower than that of a decade ago. I may consider *really* racing a half marathon in the fall. Meanwhile, I definitely found the successful completion of this half marathon to be a confidence booster for the upcoming Pittsburgh Marathon. Yes, there is no real comparison between the two distances, but it&#39;s just the fact that this is a long race at all, compared to, say, a 5K or 10K.

## Race videos are out! (Update of 2013-05-09)

### From start to 1:30:00

#### Start

I couldn&#39;t find myself in the half marathon start, because it&#39;s too congested.

#### Additional loop 1

I found myself arriving under &#34;Additional loops&#34; at 27:09 on the clock to begin the first of two 5-mile loops.

(To jump immediately to the spot, click [here](http://youtu.be/BukDHKvc7rk?t=12m50s).)

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/BukDHKvc7rk&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I crossed the start line after 21 seconds, I really ran 26:48 for the first 3.1 miles (average 8:39 pace).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;additional-loop-2&#34;&gt;Additional loop 2&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, watch me cross &amp;ldquo;Additional loops&amp;rdquo; at around 1:09:09 on the clock, which means I did 5 miles in 42:00 (average 8:24 pace).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(To jump immediately to the spot, click &lt;a href=&#34;http://youtu.be/BukDHKvc7rk?t=46m11s&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;from-1-31-00-to-3-21-00&#34;&gt;From 1:31:00 to 3:21:00&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;sprint-finish&#34;&gt;Sprint finish&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Watch my sprint finish from clock time around 1:51:03 to finish at 1:51:12 (my chip time was 1:50:51, meaning I crossed the start line after 21 seconds), which means I did the last 5 miles in 42:03, almost exactly the same time as I did the first 5-mile loop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(To jump immediately to the spot, click &lt;a href=&#34;http://youtu.be/wdjy7eLUlwQ?t=15m41s&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/wdjy7eLUlwQ&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;from-3-23-00-to-4-07-00&#34;&gt;From 3:23:00 to 4:07:00&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was already done, so I am not in this video.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/t4Zwv-tSLVM&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2014-03-09&#34;&gt;(Update of 2014-03-09)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2014, I did not set a goal to run a spring half marathon, so I did not train in the winter months for one, and so I am sadly missing Just A Short Run. Maybe there&amp;rsquo;s still time for me to get back into regular running and aim to do a half marathon in the fall.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Running my 10th Great Race 10K: &#34;obscene but in a good way&#34;</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/09/30/running-my-10th-great-race-10k-obscene-but-in-a-good-way/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Sep 2012 19:08:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/09/30/running-my-10th-great-race-10k-obscene-but-in-a-good-way/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/great-race-2012/great-race-expo.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Great Race quilt&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Today I ran in Pittsburgh&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://rungreatrace.com/&#34;&gt;Great Race 10K&lt;/a&gt; for the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/25/blistered-but-blissful-in-the-burgh/&#34;&gt;tenth time in my life&lt;/a&gt;. For various reasons, I performed a number of experiments for this tenth running of the race, doing things I&amp;rsquo;ve never done before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the race, I heard someone say, as I passed him:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
...obscene... but in a good way!
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It made my day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll explain what might have triggered this reaction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;preparation-and-uncertainty&#34;&gt;Preparation and uncertainty&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/07/running-my-8th-pretty-good-race-5k-dealing-with-disappointment/&#34;&gt;Pretty Good Race 5K&lt;/a&gt;, I was so tired out from my effort that I totally lost the desire to run. Plus my left foot was hurting more again. I ended up not running a single step for two weeks. This meant, of course, that there was no way I was going to go after the goal of beating last year&amp;rsquo;s time in the Great Race 10K.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, there was the question of whether I should even run the Great Race at all this year! Until almost the last minute, Abby and I agreed that if I did not feel up for running it at all, I would just sell my registration. Part of me felt bad about the possibility of breaking &amp;ldquo;tradition&amp;rdquo; and not running the race; I have stubbornly run it while horribly sick in some years! At the same time, it&amp;rsquo;s not really the end of the world if I miss a race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;change-of-purpose-and-plan-enter-the-invisible-shoes&#34;&gt;Change of purpose and plan: enter the Invisible Shoes!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eventually, after my two-week absence from running, my left foot injury resolved itself, and I started running again. The plan was to start road running (since I prefer to trail running) in preparation for the Great Race. The problem is that I actually don&amp;rsquo;t like wearing my road running Vibram FiveFingers shoes, my Bikila LS shoes. In fact, since my taste in footwear has become more and more minimalist over time, the Bikila LS shoes seem like a step totally in the wrong direction. I got them last year really only for the purpose of road racing, since the KSO blisters me and the KSO Trek is for the trails.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just to start running again, I began going out for 2-3 mile casual runs in my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/26/walking-and-running-in-invisible-shoes-a-review/&#34;&gt;Invisible Shoes&lt;/a&gt; that I&amp;rsquo;d been wearing all summer for walking, and sometimes for running. I enjoyed my short runs in these huaraches.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/great-race-2012/invisible-shoes-rolled.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Invisible Shoes rolled up&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Given that I was just getting back into running after such a long break, I never ran more than 3 miles during any of my runs leading up to the Great Race. And I never wore anything other than the Invisible Shoes. So that led me to the idea that since I wasn&amp;rsquo;t going to be able to achieve a goal of running super fast this year, I could set a &lt;em&gt;different goal&lt;/em&gt; for myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My new goal: &lt;em&gt;run the Great Race 10K in 4mm huaraches&lt;/em&gt;. More specifically, I wanted to see how my joints and muscles would hold up, as well as my feet and skin. Also, I&amp;rsquo;d never run fast in huaraches before, so this would also be an experiment in running fast in them. I had every intention of running pretty fast: I simply expected that I would not be able to run as fast as if I were running more protected shoes, because of many factors such as flopping soles and more pounding, resulting in my going more conservatively than if I had already experimented and knew what the limits were.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, originally I had planned to run a 5K race sometime in the huaraches; I had never planned to suddenly run a 10K in them without running a 5K first!! Also, I was going to run this 10K without having run more than 3 miles at a time in an entire month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;last-minute-panic-and-recovery&#34;&gt;Last minute panic and recovery&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Friday, I was coming down with a sore throat, and my boss said he and his son were both sick (they were both signed up for the Great Race this year). Now I was totally uncertain about whether I was going to run on Sunday. I tried to get healthy, and on Saturday, was feeling more stable, although a sore throat kept lingering, and picked up my race packet. Luckily, I was feeling great this morning, with no sign of a sore throat, so apparently my &amp;ldquo;placebos&amp;rdquo; worked (sleep, healthy food, various supplements). I canceled all my Saturday plans (such as going to a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/28/another-french-music-jam-also-announcing-cats-dance/&#34;&gt;French dance workshop&lt;/a&gt;) in order to rest up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other concern was the weather forecast. All week it seemed like it was going to rain sometime this morning. I&amp;rsquo;ve run in rain before, raced in rain before. I can do it. But the last time I ran in Invisible Shoes in the rain, I got into trouble. So now what? I simply decided I was going to deal with rain if it happened. Yet another variable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-race&#34;&gt;The race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;to-eat-or-not-to-eat&#34;&gt;To eat or not to eat?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One experiment I did today that I deem a big success: &lt;em&gt;I ate almost nothing before the race&lt;/em&gt;. I ate a bunch of almonds when I was leaving the house, but that was it. In the past, I always ate something more substantial before a race. Rationally, it does not make sense, but for some reason, I always felt that I should eat a mini-meal. This was completely irrational, a weird clinging behavior I engaged in: after all, when I casually go running in the morning, I do it before breakfast! So why should race day be any different? We human beings have enough fuel stored in our bodies. It&amp;rsquo;s true that when I go for a run of over, say, 8 miles, I get hungry, and like to either have a snack on me to eat, or have eaten right before going on the run, but when it comes to 5K and 10K races, clearly there is no need for me to eat before the race. Experience has shown that it only makes me feel sluggish. So from now on, &lt;em&gt;no more mini-meals before a race of 10K or shorter&lt;/em&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;shoes&#34;&gt;Shoes&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/great-race-2012/franklin-before.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin wearing Invisible Shoes and race number 1853&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/great-race-2012/feet-before.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin wearing Invisible Shoes&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As usual, I jogged a mile from home to the start line as my warmup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;beginning&#34;&gt;Beginning&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The temperature was in the low 50s F: ideal racing temperature, not too cold. Under 50, I would have worn a long-sleeve T-shirt instead of a short-sleeve one. As it was, since I anticipated rain, I did not wear my usual singlet but instead a standard short-sleeve T-shirt. It was not yet raining, thankfully!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some guy stepped on my right toes with his shoes as he wandered through the crowd. I was upset by this and hoped that my toes were OK. They were sore for a few minutes but then I forgot about them and was OK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within the first few minutes, I saw Don Slusser ahead of me; last year I had tracked him and then passed him at the end of the race. This year, he was obviously going much slower, thanks to his shot knees, so I passed him early on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I saw my boss standing on his street corner watching the race. I asked why he wasn&amp;rsquo;t running and he said he was too sick. It&amp;rsquo;s too bad he had to miss the race yet again, after missing it last year because of another commitment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My huaraches seemed to be working pretty well as I ran faster than I had ever run in them. I rather enjoyed being able to feel the ground, as though I were fully barefoot. At 4mm, running with these is pretty close to being barefoot, much closer than wearing Vibram FiveFingers shoes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wasn&amp;rsquo;t paying much attention to any glances or stares at my feet, or remarks people may have been making, although a few runners did directly ask me about my &amp;ldquo;flip flops&amp;rdquo;, with an attitude ranging from incredulity to amusement to admiration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;middle&#34;&gt;Middle&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Near halfway through the race, it started raining fairly steadily. I had to periodically wipe the water away from my eyes. Well, it was in the forecast. One thing I can say is that I was never in danger of overheating in this race! There have been instances of the Great Race in warm conditions under a sun, when even in a singlet I got very warm and had to dump water over my head: ha, today I got free water on my head constantly!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I started the race further back than I usually do, there were very few people running at exactly my pace. I was always either passing or being passed by people. This is one thing annoying about big races where people can cross the start mat at very different times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, at one point, a guy came to be in front of me who was running approximately my pace, so that I was almost a constant distance from him. On downhills I would tend to overtake him, but then he would come back. We would be mostly together for approximately the last two miles. At one point when I slowly passed him, I think I heard him say, &amp;ldquo;That&amp;rsquo;s obscene&amp;hellip; but in a good way!&amp;rdquo; I believe that comment was directed at me and my footwear, and I kind of took it as a compliment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;end&#34;&gt;End&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The water puddles were starting to get to me, as I had earlier feared. I did not feel confident about running any faster than I already was, given the road conditions and the way my huaraches were slipping around. And my toes were getting sore from the pounding. Normally, in the end of a race, I turn it on and try to use up the remaining energy I have, but today, I just did not feel confident in my footing. I continued going reasonably fast, but did not put in any finishing sprint at all. Even if I had wanted to, it would have been difficult, because of so many slower people in front of me. This is a direct consequence of my lining up at the start line far further back than I usually do: what happens is that slower people who started further up are in the way for the entirety of the race!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I did turn it on just enough to pass that guy I had been more or less with for two miles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;result&#34;&gt;Result&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My chip time was 48:23, not too bad given my footwear experimentation and lack of conditioning and failure to go all out in the final mile; last year&amp;rsquo;s time was 47:46. Next year, I would like to go under 47:00. I should be able to do that if I maintain a regular running regimen. 2006 was the last year that I went under 47:00.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;after-the-race&#34;&gt;After the race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got some water, was given two Smiley Cookies, and ate a bagel and a banana also. I hopped on the shuttle bus back to the start line (the ride took 30 minutes), then walked 25 minute (1.5 miles) back home in the cold. In the future, I don&amp;rsquo;t want to do this walk. I should park my car near the start line the night before, so that I can hop off the bus and drive home. It&amp;rsquo;s no fun to be walking so long in the cold when you&amp;rsquo;re tired and you&amp;rsquo;re not sure what the condition of your feet are, except that they hurt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are my feet after I got home:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/great-race-2012/feet-after.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin&amp;#39;s bare feet after race, at home&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It turns out that I got only one blister, and it was exactly where I got a blister last time I ran in the rain in the huaraches: between my first two toes. There was some roughing up of the callouses on the balls of my feet (from wearing the huaraches all summer), but otherwise, my feet were OK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After some more hours of recovery, I was feeling fine. No joint pain whatsoever, no muscle soreness whatsoever, none of that stuff. Even last year I had some stiffness when I got off the shuttle bus. My conclusion is that truly minimalist footwear trains me to land in such a way as to minimize problems to my body. No shin splints, no ankle soreness, no knee pain, no hip pain, no shot quads, no cramping calves, nothing. Just a blister, and toes and forefoot that were sore for a while but right now no longer are. It&amp;rsquo;s amazing what &lt;em&gt;no cushioning for the feet at all&lt;/em&gt; did to prevent the problems I used to face when running. I am so completely sold that I will look into running more races in huaraches, and in optimizing my lacing in order to prevent the flopping limitation and that one blister spot. I am consider going up to the 6mm sole from the 4mm sole, with the idea that 6mm would be more solid for racing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another thought: assuming a race with no rain or extreme cold or hot surfaces, I should run a race &lt;em&gt;barefoot&lt;/em&gt; sometime next year. I&amp;rsquo;ll think about this. I know people who have done this. Why not? Barefoot, one does not have to worry about blisters caused from laces, or sole flopping, or water slipping. One may have other worries instead, but knowing a course ahead of time can help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;photos&#34;&gt;Photos&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Official photos of me in action, including beating the guy I mentioned, are &lt;a href=&#34;http://orders.islandphoto.com/RACE/Proofs.aspx#26561404-00002-0026&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, but since they are copyrighted, I have not inserted them directly into my report here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Running My Ninth Pittsburgh Great Race 10K: Blistered but Blissful in the &#39;Burgh</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/09/25/blistered-but-blissful-in-the-burgh/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Sep 2011 15:28:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/09/25/blistered-but-blissful-in-the-burgh/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m temporarily using a walking stick right now, because of bad blisters I got on my right foot this morning. But I am very happy today, and it was a &lt;a href=&#34;http://rungreatrace.com/&#34;&gt;Great&lt;/a&gt; day in the &amp;lsquo;Burgh.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/franklin-finishing-great-race-10k-2011.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin finishing Great Race 10K (photo by Abby)&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/great-race-2011-official/0020.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin giving it all he has&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/great-race-2011-official/0093.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin crossing finish line&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/great-race-2011-official/0094.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin over finish line&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/great-race-2011-official/0072.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin stopping his watch&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have now run the Pittsburgh &lt;a href=&#34;http://rungreatrace.com/&#34;&gt;Great Race&lt;/a&gt; 10K nine times now, beginning in 2000: I have only missed 2003 (the year it was canceled), 2009, and 2010. I have run it in all kinds of conditions (both in terms of weather and my physical state). There is no other race I have run for so many years, so it is always special to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But beyond that, today&amp;rsquo;s race was special because Abby participated in it, for the first time. She did not run the 10K, but did run the 5K (and took the photo of me above nearing the finish line). She just started running in races with me this year, and I am very proud of her for getting into running! Having once been a non-runner, it gives me great pleasure to encourage others to take up this wonderful form of exercise.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/abby-before-great-race-5k-2011.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby in Oakland before Great Race 5K start&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Of course, right after catching my breath and finding Abby, my first instinct was to ask her, &amp;ldquo;Where are the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.eatnpark.com/smiley.asp&#34;&gt;Smiley Cookies&lt;/a&gt;?&amp;rdquo; I limped over to pick one up, even as sweat was still dripping down my face, and eagerly gobbled it!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/franklin-great-race-2011-smiley-cookie.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin with Smiley Cookie after race&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;tradition&#34;&gt;Tradition&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Great Race is a wonderful Pittsburgh tradition. It is not only thrilling to be on the Boulevard of the Allies heading downtown getting a fine view of our city (although the uphill during mile 5 of the race is admittedly tough), but the sight of so many people participating in this event is heartwarming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/great-race-2011-crowd.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/great-race-2011-crowd-2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-great-race-stats&#34;&gt;My Great Race stats&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was also very happy about my finish time. I had a plan to break 48:00 this year, and I succeeded handily (all times mentioned are &amp;ldquo;chip times&amp;rdquo;, not &amp;ldquo;gun times&amp;rdquo;). My time was, of course, not one of my fastest times in this race (my fastest time was 42:49 nine years ago), but it was faster than my time in 2008. The last three years of my life have been very tough for me physically, so I have enjoyed starting to get back into shape this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s my record in the Great Race 10K over the years:
&lt;table style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 15px&#34;&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;th style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px; font-size: 1.1em&#34;&gt;Year&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;th style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px; font-size: 1.1em&#34;&gt;Chip time&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;th style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px; font-size: 1.1em&#34;&gt;Comment&lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;2000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;53:53&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;First time ever ran more than 3 miles continuously at all!&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;2001&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;45:02&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;Lost weight, trained seriously.&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;2002&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;42:49&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;Trained really hard.&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;2003&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;(not held)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;2004&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;45:36&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;Very sick, but was preregistered, and didn&amp;rsquo;t want to break tradition.&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;2005&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;46:49&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;Was too busy to train.&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;2006&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;46:55&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;Again untrained. Slower and slower.&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;2007&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;47:11&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;Not trained at all; extreme pain halfway, but kept going.&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;2008&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;49:12&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;Not trained at all, left shin hurting, unmotivated.&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;2009&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;(did not run)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;Too untrained to even think of running.&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;2010&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;(did not run)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;Too untrained to even think of running.&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;2011&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;47:46&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;Lightly trained, but put in a genuine effort on race day.&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;details-of-the-race&#34;&gt;Details of the race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My splits (for each mile, then the final 0.22 mile) are below. I tried to run an even effort (till the final mile, when I simply tried to keep going hard despite the pain), accounting for the changes in elevation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;7:40.73&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;7:07.52&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;8:09.14&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;7:23.90&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;8:24.08&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;7:29.08&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1:31.03&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One trick I try to use in a race is to pick someone ahead of me who is running just a bit faster than what I feel I can hold, and see if I can slowly catch up (and maybe overtake eventually). In the Great Race, this is hard to do because there are so many runners, and people starting at different times, so there is always a lot of passing and slowing down going on, unlike in smaller races where things get spread out and you know people are basically running at the pace they can hold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have to work harder in these big races to maintain my own sense of pace. I do this by &amp;ldquo;feel&amp;rdquo;: having run in races from a mile up to the marathon, I know what a sustainable pace feels like. 5K pace gives me a burning, pukey sensation, for example, while half-marathon pace is not at all pukey. 10K pace is in between: uncomfortable but tolerable, till the final mile when I just do whatever I can without completely falling apart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;don-slusser&#34;&gt;Don Slusser&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it was after around two miles that I noticed ahead of me &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.newsandsentinel.com/page/content.detail/id/538234.html&#34;&gt;Don Slusser&lt;/a&gt;, a local legend in the running scene. OK, he is not at all what he used to be, and has had a lot of knee surgeries, but still, I felt it was an honor to be see him out there still running.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As long as Don was still ahead of me, he was going to be my target. He pulled away from me slightly over the next three miles, but was always in my sight. So in the final mile, I finally blasted past him. Then somehow he passed me at one point downtown, and that pushed me to pick up the pace again and finish ahead of him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After he finished, I went up to him and shook his hand. He probably has no idea who I am or why I respect him or how he helped provide focus for me in my own attempt to run as well as I could today, but what can I say, it was a spontaneous gesture on my part. I salute you, Don: you and your wife Tammy have done much for the Pittsburgh running community and I am grateful for that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-note-on-shoes&#34;&gt;A note on shoes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the second race in which I&amp;rsquo;ve run in my &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.vibramfivefingers.com/products/Five-Fingers-BikilaLS-Mens.htm&#34;&gt;Bikila LS&lt;/a&gt; shoes (the first race was &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/23/happiness-is-finishing-39th-of-43-men-in-a-race/&#34;&gt;three days ago&lt;/a&gt;). Unfortunately, these shoes tend to give me blisters if I run over three miles and fast. I&amp;rsquo;ve run a slow eight miles before without blisters, but going fast, and in warm weather, my feet sweat and chafing happens. These shoes are nice but have a ventilation problem. I have never had any problems with my &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.vibramfivefingers.com/products/Five-Fingers-KSO-Trek-Mens.htm&#34;&gt;KSO Trek&lt;/a&gt; shoes that I use for trail running and hiking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see in the photo above that Abby wore her &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.vibramfivefingers.com/products/five-fingers-komodo-sport-ls-mens.htm&#34;&gt;KomodoSport LS&lt;/a&gt; shoes in the race. Wearing &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.vibramfivefingers.com/&#34;&gt;Vibram FiveFingers&lt;/a&gt; shoes for walking, hiking, and running has really improved our lives. (More on that in a later blog post.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;photo-update-on-september-28-2011&#34;&gt;Photo update on September 28, 2011&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some official photos from Island Photography have appeared online. I have to confess that my original plan was to try to spot the cameras and try to look good for any photos of me that might be taken. Unfortunately, I was in such pain in the final mile of the race that I had tunnel vision and could not really perceive anything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve added some of these photos to the beginning of this blog post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2012-09-30&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-09-30)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following year, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/30/running-my-10th-great-race-10k-obscene-but-in-a-good-way/&#34;&gt;I ran in the Great Race again&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>