<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Dvd on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/dvd/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Dvd on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/dvd/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>On re-experiencing VHS tapes again</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/16/on-re-experiencing-vhs-tapes-again/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Nov 2014 21:27:49 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/16/on-re-experiencing-vhs-tapes-again/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I stopped serious study of ballroom dance sometime around 2003, over ten years ago, because I was discouraged by not finding a maximally compatible dance partner. I ended up closing the chapter of my life that started in 2000 when ballroom dance consumed almost all of my time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently I brought up several boxes of ballroom dance instruction videos from those days, with the idea that even though I&amp;rsquo;m not longer doing ballroom dancing with anyone any more (Abby is not very interested in ballroom dance), I might find it enjoyable to continue developing my dance skills and use the videos as part of exercise also. Almost all of these videos are VHS tapes. I have almost no dance videos on DVD, as I was very late in acquiring a DVD player: actually, one day, my mother bought me a DVD player because she was tired of visiting me and having no way to watching any DVDs she brought!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had mixed emotions and memories as I started going through these videos again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-was-i-late-to-cds-and-dvds&#34;&gt;Why was I late to CDs and DVDs?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier in life, I was very late in getting a CD player also; I bought only &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/09/12/rip-ray-dolby-yes/&#34;&gt;cassette tapes&lt;/a&gt; and LPs until late in college, around 1990, when I finally buckled to pressure and bought a CD player. I am generally not an early adopter of technology. I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/22/paradox-i-will-observe-the-national-day-of-unplugging-but-just-bought-my-first-smartphone-this-week/&#34;&gt;bought my first smartphone in 2012&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why the resistance to technology? Partly it&amp;rsquo;s just a matter of cost. But more fundamentally, I worried about the long-term durability of digital media. It turns out that I shouldn&amp;rsquo;t have worried quite so much, because backing up has turned out to be quite feasible and inexpensive. But in the early days of CDs and DVDs, I was not going to be ripping them and storing them on super-expensive hard drives, so my worry was about the physical media of CDs and DVDs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;was-i-was-right-about-the-disadvantages-of-digital-media&#34;&gt;Was I was right about the disadvantages of digital media?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that I was partially right. Some of my old CDs and DVDs did become unplayable after a decade or two, but very few.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bigger problem is that Abby and I sometimes check out DVDs from the public library and find that they have enough scratches that when watching a film we often miss entire minutes and scenes because of damaged playback! This has happened so many times that I question the value of ever checking out a DVD from the library again that looks even a little scratched. What a waste!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The advantage of analog media such as LPs and cassette tapes and VHS tapes is that in some ways they are more fault tolerant. I remember the old days of splicing tape, for example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But actually, analog media get corrupted easily enough by magnetism, mold, etc. I do have tapes that are unplayable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The killer feature of digital media was always indexing and random access. It&amp;rsquo;s a real hassle not being able to skip from one dance lesson to the next, or get a table of contents, in these dance videos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s far less efficient using VHS videos for instruction than indexed digital media. That said, I see why people stream video these days rather than buy or borrow DVDs; physical digital media are fragile. But what would libraries do if they stopped acquiring and serving CDs and DVDs?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>