<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Run Shadyside on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/run-shadyside/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Run Shadyside on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/run-shadyside/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>9 things you could be doing in Pittsburgh on Saturday, October 5</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/04/9-things-you-could-be-doing-in-pittsburgh-on-saturday-october-5/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2013 00:46:44 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/04/9-things-you-could-be-doing-in-pittsburgh-on-saturday-october-5/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m always frustrated at this time of year because there are so many events of interest to me in Pittsburgh that seem to happen on the first weekend of October. Since I cannot attend all of them, I figured I might as well attempt a public service and mention some of them so that if you are in the Pittsburgh area, maybe you can go and enjoy what I can&amp;rsquo;t attend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So here are 9 of the probably dozens of cool things you could be doing tomorrow, Saturday, October 5, 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;free-concert-allegheny-city-ragtime-orchestra&#34;&gt;Free concert: Allegheny City Ragtime Orchestra&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re interested in ragtime or Latin music, check out &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.shadysideacademy.org/page.cfm?p=12541&#34;&gt;this concert by the Allegheny City Ragtime Orchestra&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some articles in anticipation of it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.post-gazette.com/stories/ae/music/preview-ragtime-orchestra-connects-with-history-705929/&#34;&gt;Post-Gazette&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://triblive.com/aande/music/4763900-74/ragtime-music-concert&#34;&gt;Trib&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I wanted to go, but finally decided that we have too many other activities earlier in the day and need to just stay home and unwind in the evening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;free-conference-podcamp-pittsburgh-8&#34;&gt;Free conference: PodCamp Pittsburgh 8&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 8th annual &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.podcamppittsburgh.com/&#34;&gt;PodCamp Pittsburgh&lt;/a&gt; should be good. If you have any interest in using social media for personal or professional purposes, you should check it out. Interesting talks, opportunities to just socialized and learn new things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I attended in 2010, 2011, 2012, and will attend again for the fourth year. Unfortunately, I will only be able to attend the afternoon sessions. But I didn&amp;rsquo;t want to completely miss it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that PodCamp completely changed my life. For example, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/21/one-month-anniversary-of-my-blog/&#34;&gt;I started this blog in 2011 because of my second PodCamp&lt;/a&gt;, and I became serious about using social media in general, and that led to a total transformation of my life as I learned about local activities and made new friends. (Unfortunately, I didn&amp;rsquo;t get around to finishing my draft reports about my experience at last year&amp;rsquo;s PodCamp 7.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;pittsburgh-south-side-slopes-step-trek&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh South Side Slopes Step Trek&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The annual &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.southsideslopes.org/steptrek/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh South Side Slopes Step Trek&lt;/a&gt; is another event you can attend tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/08/my-god-its-full-of-stairs-pittsburgh-step-trek-2011/&#34;&gt;blog coverage two years ago&lt;/a&gt; as well as my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/09/25/why-you-should-go-out-to-the-pittsburgh-south-side-slopes-step-trek/&#34;&gt;recent update&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, Abby and I will be missing it this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;run-shadyside-5k&#34;&gt;Run Shadyside 5K&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you like to run in races, a fine race is the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.runshadyside.com/&#34;&gt;Run Shadyside 5K&lt;/a&gt;. Fast and flat, with a pancake breakfast and festivities afterwards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not running in it this year, just because I have too many other things to do already for the rest of the day, but here&amp;rsquo;s my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/01/run-shadyside-5k-outrunning-mickey-mouse-and-lending-a-trumpet/&#34;&gt;report from two years ago&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;free-5th-annual-wilkins-school-community-center-ecofest-in-regent-square&#34;&gt;Free: 5th annual Wilkins School Community Center Ecofest in Regent Square&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/ecofest-2013.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;5th annual Wilkins School Community Center Ecofest in Regent Square&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Interested in green living? Check out the &lt;a href=&#34;http://foresthills-regentsquare.patch.com/groups/around-town/p/ecofest-encourages-recycling-green-living&#34;&gt;5th annual Wilkins School Community Center Ecofest in Regent Square&lt;/a&gt;. Abby has regularly attended for the clothing swap. There will also be food, information, and entertainment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that this year, I will also be attending, to perform as a new member of the Steel City Ukuleles. &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/08/23/another-unexpected-life-change-one-month-of-learning-to-play-ukulele/&#34;&gt;I just started playing the ukulele a bit over two months ago&lt;/a&gt;, and have been working hard to help put on an entertaining show!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;ll be performing around 11:30 AM to 12:30 PM. If you come, say hello!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;cmu-donut-dash-2-mile-race&#34;&gt;CMU Donut Dash 2 mile race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, if you are into weird running events, there is the &lt;a href=&#34;http://cmudonutdash.org/&#34;&gt;Carnegie Mellon University Donut Dash&lt;/a&gt;, a 2 mile event serving as a fundraiser for the Children&amp;rsquo;s Hospital of Pittsburgh of UPMC. This is not an event I have ever done, and not one I intend to do, but what the heck, some of you might love this sort of thing!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;national-chess-day-gateway-open-tournament-at-the-pittsburgh-chess-club&#34;&gt;National Chess Day: Gateway Open tournament at the Pittsburgh Chess Club&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did you know that it&amp;rsquo;s time for &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nationalchessday.com/&#34;&gt;National Chess Day&lt;/a&gt;? There will be a tournament at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburghcc.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Chess Club&lt;/a&gt;, the 56th annual Gateway Open. Yes, chess in Pittsburgh has a long and illustrious history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;pittsburgh-perl-workshop&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Perl Workshop&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are a Perl programmer, the &lt;a href=&#34;http://pghpw.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Perl Workshop&lt;/a&gt; is back &lt;a href=&#34;http://pghpw.org/ppw2013/&#34;&gt;this year&lt;/a&gt;. Registration is already closed, so it&amp;rsquo;s not so helpful right now for me to mention it, but in case you didn&amp;rsquo;t know it existed, watch for it next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;ninth-thing&#34;&gt;Ninth thing?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, I guess I miscounted. But there are a whole lot more than nine things to do in Pittsburgh tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, if you are interested in some free stuff to do, there&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.radworkshere.org/interior.php?pageID=64&#34;&gt;RADical Days&lt;/a&gt; listing a whole bunch of stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s no shortage of stuff to do in this great city of Pittsburgh at any time or day of year. I think it&amp;rsquo;s unfortunate that many things I like to do happen to repeatedly fall on the first Saturday of the year, but I&amp;rsquo;m not complaining about an embarrassment of riches. Go out and take advantage of what I can&amp;rsquo;t.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Fineview Stepathon 2012: Pittsburgh&#39;s grueling urban trail race</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/10/06/the-fineview-stepathon-2012-pittsburghs-grueling-urban-trail-race/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Oct 2012 23:07:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/10/06/the-fineview-stepathon-2012-pittsburghs-grueling-urban-trail-race/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://thenorthsidechronicle.com/UserFiles/Image/stepathon.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Stepathon steps&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Today I ran in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.thenorthsidechronicle.com/2061_php?calendarDate=2012-10-04&#34;&gt;annual&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://stepathon.org/&#34;&gt;Fineview Stepathon&lt;/a&gt;, a truly unique and grueling 5-mile race held in &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fineview_(Pittsburgh)&#34;&gt;Fineview&lt;/a&gt;, a neighborhood in the North Side of Pittsburgh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was not the first time I&amp;rsquo;d run the Stepathon: I&amp;rsquo;d actually done a shorter version of it (supposedly a 5K, but clearly much shorter given how quickly I finished it) in 2006. Originally, I wasn&amp;rsquo;t sure I was going to run another race this year after the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/30/running-my-10th-great-race-10k-obscene-but-in-a-good-way/&#34;&gt;Great Race&lt;/a&gt;, but after telling my buddy Chris about the Stepathon, and his getting excited about the concept, I decided to commit to doing it with him, rain or shine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Note that there was a short 2.5 mile option available, but only six people took it this year.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Web site&amp;rsquo;s description only gives a hint of what this event is like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Are you a runner, about to run the Great Race?   An urban explorer?  A fitness nut?  Or just a masochist?  How fast should you pace yourself, going up a stairway that rises out of view?  How fast can you go?  One thing for sure, the harder you fight the steps, the harder they fight back!  We saved the best for last... the legendary Rising Main stairway.  High as a 17-story building, disorienting as it leans this way and that, your legs feeling like jelly as you near the top... The Stepathon, ready to chew you up and spit you out!
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, the registration form says:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Challenging course includes 12 public staircases over 1600 steps.  Vertical climb 400 feet.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s my report on this fantastic event!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;course&#34;&gt;Course&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The course includes stairways, sidewalk steps, road sections, trail sections, grassy sections, bridges. It&amp;rsquo;s really something else. With all the turns, it was very helpful indeed that signs were put up and arrows drawn on the ground where useful, and several volunteers out on the course also, who pointed the way. I really appreciated the number of volunteers in the Stepathon who made it go smoothly. They not only pointed the way, but gave encouragement, and there were water stations also along the course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a &lt;a href=&#34;https://maps.google.com/maps/ms?hl=en&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;t=h&amp;amp;msa=0&amp;amp;msid=113997026750504519105.000482f8ae0315f705efc&amp;amp;ll=40.46334,-80.002184&amp;amp;spn=0.011428,0.018239&amp;amp;z=15&amp;amp;source=embed&#34;&gt;detailed map of the course&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And here are &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/groups/110502898969170/photos/&#34;&gt;photos from the past&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;preparation&#34;&gt;Preparation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t prepare for this event at all. I had no goal but to do my best and pace myself well. Real preparation, of course, would have involved doing a lot of &lt;strong&gt;stair-climbing&lt;/strong&gt;. It is the case that I &lt;em&gt;almost never&lt;/em&gt; take an elevator or escalator, but take the stairs instead, wherever I go, but I&amp;rsquo;m talking about actual stair-climbing training, of the form I used to engage in, during winter, when I did the summer &lt;a href=&#34;http://rachelcarsontrails.org/rct/challenge&#34;&gt;Rachel Carson Trail Challenge&lt;/a&gt; three years in a row. Of course, the place for such training is the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.tour.pitt.edu/tour-080.html&#34;&gt;Cathedral of Learning&lt;/a&gt;. Once a week, I&amp;rsquo;d do 36 floors, elevation gain of 440 feet, in one straight shot up, no rest: it was a &lt;a href=&#34;http://alltrails.com/events/2010/11/cathedral-of-learning-steps-2&#34;&gt;great workout&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;pre-race&#34;&gt;Pre-race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;food&#34;&gt;Food&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as in the Great Race, I continued my policy of not eating before the race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;clothing&#34;&gt;Clothing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was drizzling rain, but the temperature wasn&amp;rsquo;t too bad. I wore a long-sleeve moisture-wicking shirt, long running pants, my Vibram FiveFingers Bikila LS shoes, and the brand new Great Race cap that was given to all participants of the Great Race this year. This was the first time I&amp;rsquo;d ever worn a cap during a race; I didn&amp;rsquo;t want water getting into my eyes (as happened actually during the Great Race). I also wore some light gloves; in particular, I expected to try to hold onto some cold and wet stairway handrails!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chris also wore his Great Race cap. Since this was a smaller race, with 70 participants, this was the first time in a race we were at a start line together. In the huge July 4 Brentwood 5K race, which was his first 5K race, we didn&amp;rsquo;t start together, and in the even more huge Great Race, his first 10K race, I never even saw him at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I saw some people wearing the yellow Great Race long-sleeve shirts they were also given to all Great Race participants. I still haven&amp;rsquo;t worn mine yet. I wasn&amp;rsquo;t going to wear an unfamiliar shirt for the first time when doing a race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;pep-talk&#34;&gt;Pep talk&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The race director warned us of the hazards in store for us, and told us to be especially careful on the slippery wooden steps and in the trails. There were lots of jokes going around about dragging our broken bodies from the steps. I enjoyed the lighthearted mood. Hey, we all signed the waivers about the dangers of this event!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;description-of-the-race&#34;&gt;Description of the race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;stairs-and-trails&#34;&gt;Stairs and trails&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We started off running on the road for a bit before turning onto the first stairway. Chris was way ahead of me, but I was trying to pace myself for what lay ahead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After doing a bit of &amp;ldquo;running&amp;rdquo; up the stairs, I quickly realized that I was wasting my energy. I started just walking up the stairs instead. The plan was to walk up all stairways, but descend quickly, and run fast on the roads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, I was trying to pull myself up with my arms using the handrails, but it turns out that some handrail sections are missing or &lt;em&gt;loose&lt;/em&gt;. Yup, we were warned!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point, we started going off into the trails. Unfortunately, I had &amp;ldquo;forgotten&amp;rdquo; that there might be mud issues, and I was annoyed that I had worn my Bikila LS shoes instead of my KSO Trek shoes, which would have been much better in these conditions. I had to slow down a lot to avoid slipping and falling in the muddy trails.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I noticed that I was a lot faster descending steps than many people, so I started passing people during the descents. At some point, I caught up to Chris and passed him. But not too long after that, we entered a grassy section of the course, outside the fenced baseball field. I &lt;em&gt;knew&lt;/em&gt; that this was going to be treacherous, so I tried to grab with my right hand onto the fence as I ran, but still, at some point there was a drop and I slipped and fell hard, right on my butt. I picked myself up, luckily not really injured (although I had some hip pain for a day or two after the race), and kept going. After the race, Chris said he had seen me going down. Thanks to the indentation I made in the ground with my body, others behind me knew where not to step!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;roads&#34;&gt;Roads&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did do a good bit of running on the roads, but actually, a lot of walking too, because there were such steep hills along some of the roads. Here&amp;rsquo;s my rule of thumb in these kinds of races: if by walking hard I can keep up with someone who is running up a hill, clearly I am saving more energy than my competitor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;bridges&#34;&gt;Bridges&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were various bridges, but most amusing was the bridge over I-279. When was the last time I ran in a race that crossed an interstate highway? Um, never?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-garden-hose&#34;&gt;The garden hose&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the big stair climb near the end, I noticed while pulling myself up the handrails that one entire section was not only missing, but replaced seamlessly with a &lt;em&gt;garden hose&lt;/em&gt;. Hilarious, but not safe! I didn&amp;rsquo;t touch the hose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;fear-of-getting-lost&#34;&gt;Fear of getting lost&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite all the volunteers and signs and drawn arrows, there were times when I feared getting lost. This proved detrimental to my running speed. During much of the last half hour of the race, I was basically with a pack of two other people, with nobody else in sight ahead of us, and we were taking turns leading. This was fine when I wasn&amp;rsquo;t leading (typically, they were faster than me on the stairs and trails, while I was faster on the roads), but when a long stretch of road came up and I was clearly able to go faster, I was afraid to go as fast as I really could, in case I missed a turn. If I had genuinely prepared for this race, I would have studied and memorized the course map before doing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result of my not going all out when I was clearly strong enough to on the roads, by the time I saw the finish line approaching, no amount of sprinting on my part could get me to catch up with my two closest competitors. I was slightly annoyed with myself for not having applied optimal race tactics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;results&#34;&gt;Results&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://runhigh.com/2012RESULTS/R100612GB.html&#34;&gt;results of the race&lt;/a&gt; show that I finished in 27th place out of 70, in a time of 59:31. The two people I was running in a pack with for much of the second half of the race came in 8 seconds and 4 seconds earlier than me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I cheered Chris on as he came in some minutes later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;post-race&#34;&gt;Post-race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a view from the finish:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://bbbigdawgs.weebly.com/uploads/4/4/9/1/4491611/5685188_orig.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Welcome to Fineview&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://bbbigdawgs.weebly.com/uploads/4/4/9/1/4491611/5390106_orig.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;View from finish&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(It&amp;rsquo;s probably too hard to see my &amp;ldquo;indentation&amp;rdquo; in the ground in this photo outside the fenced ball field where I fell!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a little band playing some &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Old-time_music&#34;&gt;old-time music&lt;/a&gt;. That was a nice touch to this event. I always appreciate it when post-race festivities include some music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many refreshments were available: muffins, fruit, coffee, etc. I was pretty hungry after almost an hour of running (and on an empty stomach), and devoured some muffins and fruit. No coffee for me, though: I need to wind down, not wind up, after a race!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t pay much attention to the raffle prizes being given away, so who knows, I might have missed winning something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I picked up my race bag and a coaster. After I was done eating and chatting with Chris, I was getting cold and walked back to the start line and back to my car to drive home. It was kind of funny going backwards along part of the course, down the rights, down the steps, back to the start line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;other-events-that-took-place-today&#34;&gt;Other events that took place today&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sadly, today was also the day for two other annual events that were on different days last year: the Pittsburgh Step Trek and the Run Shadyside 5K.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I had to miss both of them. Generally, given the choice between doing something that I have enjoyed recently and doing something new (or very old), I will almost always choose what I did least recently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;pittsburgh-step-trek&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Step Trek&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, Abby and I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/08/my-god-its-full-of-stairs-pittsburgh-step-trek-2011/&#34;&gt;did the annual Pittsburgh Step Trek&lt;/a&gt;, which is a self-guided, noncompetitive event that actually gives a similar feel to the Fineview Stepathon, in that it is an exploration of a Pittsburgh neighborhood that has a lot of hills and nooks and crannies, and of course a lot of stairways. This year I was unable to do the Step Trek because of another commitment in the afternoon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.post-gazette.com/stories/local/neighborhoods-city/pittsburgh-steptrek-provides-a-different-view-of-city-656542/&#34;&gt;local writeup of this year&amp;rsquo;s event&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;run-shadyside-5k&#34;&gt;Run Shadyside 5K&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, since it fell on a different day, I also &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/01/run-shadyside-5k-outrunning-mickey-mouse-and-lending-a-trumpet/&#34;&gt;ran the Run Shadyside 5K&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s a nice event, but fast and flat and crowded is not as exciting as a quirky, small Stepathon!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a great time in this year&amp;rsquo;s Fineview Stepathon, and I was delighted to have introduced Chris to this event. This was one of the &lt;em&gt;most fun&lt;/em&gt; races in my life! I&amp;rsquo;m grateful for all the work the volunteers did to get the route ready, handle registration, direct the race, point out directions, give us water, and provide music and food for us at the end. I totally want to do this again next year, even if schedule conflicts arise again. And I hope that maybe I&amp;rsquo;ll do some targeted training in order to really conquer &amp;ldquo;man versus steps&amp;rdquo;!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Run Shadyside 5K: Outrunning Mickey Mouse and Lending a Trumpet</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/10/01/run-shadyside-5k-outrunning-mickey-mouse-and-lending-a-trumpet/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Oct 2011 09:47:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/10/01/run-shadyside-5k-outrunning-mickey-mouse-and-lending-a-trumpet/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My alarm starts blaring at 6:30 AM on a cold, dark Saturday morning, and I&amp;rsquo;m tired and sleepy, and briefly wonder why I preregistered on Wednesday to run today&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.runshadyside.com/&#34;&gt;Run Shadyside 5K&lt;/a&gt; race. But a commitment is a commitment, so I get, check the weather forecast, get dressed, eat something, and head off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Little do I know that today I will just manage to outrun Mickey Mouse, far exceed my race time goal, and lend someone my trumpet that has been lying around unused!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/franklin-and-mickey-mouse-eric.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin and Eric after the race&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;pre-race&#34;&gt;Pre-race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since it was cold, in the 40s, and there was a possibility it could rain (although things looked clear), I wore a long-sleeve shirt and gloves and a hat along with my shorts and Bikila LS shoes (this was the third race in which I used these shoes).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After my successful &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/25/blistered-but-blissful-in-the-burgh/&#34;&gt;Great Race 10K&lt;/a&gt; toughened me up, I was ready to run a &amp;ldquo;fast&amp;rdquo; 5K race. I had run a 5K in August in 24:36, and another in September in 24:36, but these were mostly off-road and hilly, so I expected that I should definitely go under 24:00 in this mostly flat road race, I targeted 23:30 as an ambitious goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing you have to realize is that I hadn&amp;rsquo;t run a decent 5K in years, so my goal was to really gut it out in this one. My fastest 5K was in 2003, in 20:37. I slowed down gradually to 22:04 in 2007, but later in 2007, as my life entered turmoil, I slowed to 23:30, then 24:39 in 2008, 25:20 in 2009, and 26:41 in 2010. So I have been using races this year as a gauge of my gradual &amp;ldquo;comeback&amp;rdquo; to my former level of fitness (taking aging into account, of course).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-race&#34;&gt;The race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/QslAbd-_TsA&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The gun went off and the race played out for me as most largish races do: I took care not to go out too fast, but a lot of people always act otherwise and pass me like crazy during the first minutes of the race. I just &lt;a href=&#34;http://sethgodin.typepad.com/seths_blog/2011/09/run-your-own-race.html&#34;&gt;run my own race&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a mile, things were mostly settled down. I noticed a guy ahead of me wearing a hat with Mickey Mouse ears.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mickey-mouse-ears-hat-profile.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Mickey Mouse ears hat&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, the gap between the guy and me was ever so slowly increasing. I decided at that moment that with two miles to go, I was going to do what I could to beat this guy. This goal was going to be the single purpose of my life for the next 15 minutes (approximately).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To motivate myself even further, I used the mind trick of publicly proclaiming my goal. I know this technique is &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ted.com/talks/derek_sivers_keep_your_goals_to_yourself.html&#34;&gt;controversial&lt;/a&gt; and can backfire, but I think it depends on context. Every time I found myself running side by side with someone (whether someone I was passing or someone who had caught up to me), I told him that I was going to catch Mickey Mouse. Somehow saying that always gave me a bit of energy each time, and I would pass the guy I just talked with and not look back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I pushed really hard but for the whole second mile had still not yet closed the gap with Mickey Mouse. Sometimes I could not even see him, but I always made sure to find him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Around halfway through the third mile, I started closing on Mickey Mouse. For the first time in the race, I was totally confident that I had what it took to beat him. I finally overtook him when the finish line was in sight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;final-sprint&#34;&gt;Final sprint&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that was not all. I saw the clock and was surprised to find that I was going to come in well under 23:00!  In the excitement, I decided to go wild.  I &lt;strong&gt;screamed&lt;/strong&gt;, as though I were dying, as I launched into a big sprint to pass probably a dozen people as I stumbled over the finish line in something like 22:46.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Man, that was cathartic. This is only the second time I have ever screamed in a race (and I have run in well over a hundred in the past decade). I had let out a scream during a sprint finish at the Pretty Good Race 5K in September, but it was a short scream, not this prolonged seconds-long one that I let out today. I supposed that in the past decade I used to be too shy to do a thing like that, but it felt so good today that I may do it in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was reminded of how in karate class I was instructed on how important it was to use the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kiai&#34;&gt;kiai&lt;/a&gt; shout as a projection of energy. But then I reflected, my scream was not objectively the best way to end a race. If I had enough energy to scream, then I should have been able to run faster before that point, so a smarter race would have been to push even harder before the somewhat wasteful sprint. Nevertheless, at the very moment today, the scream seemed the thing to do, for psychological reasons, at least.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;post-race&#34;&gt;Post-race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mickey Mouse came in seconds later. I went up to him and shook his hand, then grabbed some water and food and started walking back to my car (parked almost a mile away), since I needed to cool down from the race, and wanted to get my camera and warm clothing to bring back to the post-race party.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the way back from my car, I saw Mickey Mouse, but without the ears. He was walking with his family and I approached him and had his mother take a photo of us. His name is &lt;a href=&#34;http://ericbrockmeyer.com/&#34;&gt;Eric&lt;/a&gt; and he said he wasn&amp;rsquo;t the only one with Mickey Mouse ears: a bunch of Disney Research people were all wearing them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got back to the post-race party and happened to see a guy I know from lots of previous races in the past decade, Ron Romanoff, and had him take a photo of me:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-shadyside-2011-franklin.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin after Run Shadyside 5K 2011&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;bumping-into-ben-paul&#34;&gt;Bumping into Ben Paul&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-shadyside-2011-festivities.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Festivities after Run Shadyside 5K 2011&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-shadyside-2011-pancakes.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Pancakes after Run Shadyside 5K 2011&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I saw a sign for pancakes, and suddenly realized that I had totally forgotten about the post-race pancake breakfast. I put away the half-eaten bagel I was munching on and headed toward the pancakes, and whom did I see but &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.communiteach.com/post/10818529188&#34;&gt;Ben Paul&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-shadyside-2011-ben-paul.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Ben Paul with coffee after Run Shadyside 5K 2011&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I had first met and talked with Ben at &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/22/starting-a-new-web-site/&#34;&gt;PodCamp Pittsburgh&lt;/a&gt;, although I had heard his name much earlier since he was one of the founders of &lt;a href=&#34;http://communiteach.com/&#34;&gt;CommuniTeach&lt;/a&gt;. CommuniTeach is a really great concept, providing a way for people who want to learn stuff, or teach it, or both, to get together. Back in June, Abby and I had attended a CommuniTeach session on &lt;a href=&#34;http://communiteach.com/learnitss.php?glid=151&#34;&gt;fermentation&lt;/a&gt;. We learned to make kefir and sauerkraut and experiment with various fermented veggie combinations involving radishes, carrots, zucchini, onion, fennel seeds, you name it. Since July (when our first batch was ready), we&amp;rsquo;ve been enjoying tasty fermented veggies to complement our meals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are curious about teaching or learning anything in the Pittsburgh area, I highly recommend that you sign up on &lt;a href=&#34;http://communiteach.com/&#34;&gt;CommuniTeach&lt;/a&gt; and check it out! I also find the &lt;a href=&#34;http://twitter.com/#!/CommuniTeach&#34;&gt;@CommuniTeach&lt;/a&gt; very useful to follow, and there is also a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.facebook.com/pages/CommuniTeach/99389138220&#34;&gt;Facebook site&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;music&#34;&gt;Music&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I mentioned to Ben that I&amp;rsquo;d been reading about him from the links that he&amp;rsquo;s posted. I&amp;rsquo;d just learned that he played melodica, and I said that I have a melodica too, but have not been playing it. I said I was also learning accordion recently. I asked him about ukulele, since he had mentioned it somewhere, and he suggested that a bunch of us find a way to teach ourselves together. I pointed out that unfortunately, I was already focusing a lot of my musical time on playing recorder and for now my ukulele goals are on hold. He couldn&amp;rsquo;t believe I played recorder, since he hates the sound, ha! I happened to mention that I had too many instruments I didn&amp;rsquo;t play, such as a trumpet. He got excited, because he needs a trumpet to play, and I offered to lend him mine. So we decided that he could meet up at my place to pick it up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We looked at the posted race results and Ben couldn&amp;rsquo;t find himself listed. He was pretty bummed about that. It was his first race! It turned out that he had not attached the race chip to his shoe, but it was still attached to his race number on his shirt. Oops. Nevertheless, in case anyone ever doubts it: I hereby declare myself as a witness to Ben Paul having run his first race today in Shadyside!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;trumpet-finally-finds-a-happy-player&#34;&gt;Trumpet finally finds a happy player!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s Ben with my trumpet. Enjoy playing it, Ben!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/ben-paul-with-franklins-trumpet.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Ben Paul with Franklin&amp;#39;s trumpet&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;rain&#34;&gt;Rain&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It started raining outside just as Ben left with the trumpet. I am &lt;em&gt;so&lt;/em&gt; grateful that it did not rain during the race! I was prepared to deal with it (I have run cold half marathons during which it rained the whole time), but it would not have been so much fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2012-10-06&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-10-06)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following year, sadly, I did not do Run Shadyside again, because of a schedule conflict with &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/10/06/the-fineview-stepathon-2012-pittsburghs-grueling-urban-trail-race/&#34;&gt;the Fineview Stepathon that I did instead&lt;/a&gt;. We&amp;rsquo;ll have to see what the schedules are for 2013.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>