<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Jazz on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/jazz/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Jazz on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/jazz/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>How Ornette Coleman changed my life</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/06/12/how-ornette-coleman-changed-my-life/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jun 2015 23:59:40 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/06/12/how-ornette-coleman-changed-my-life/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The legendary jazz musician
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ornette_Coleman&#34;&gt;Ornette Coleman&lt;/a&gt;
recently died at age 85. He had not been on my radar for a long
time. In fact, I never actually listened to much of his music at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, my immediate first thought on hearing this news was, &lt;strong&gt;Ornette
Coleman permanently changed the course of my life&lt;/strong&gt;. How can this be?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;first-reactions-to-ornette-coleman-s-music&#34;&gt;First reactions to Ornette Coleman&amp;rsquo;s music&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2000, during a huge transition in my life that turned everything
upside down, I began experimenting with listening to a lot of kinds of
music I had never experienced before. I was exploring Cuban,
Brazilian, Argentinian music. I was exploring Western classical music
of the 20th century (I had a fairly narrow taste up till then focused
primarily on the Classical 18th century and Romantic 19th century,
with little before or after this range). In jazz, I was expanding
beyond the swing, bebop, hard bop eras of jazz. I frequently reached
areas that made me confused or disgusted. For example, in jazz I got
&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/23/celebrating-the-birthday-of-john-coltrane/&#34;&gt;as far as I could with John Coltrane&lt;/a&gt;
as Coltrane ventured into &amp;ldquo;free jazz&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided to try out Ornette Coleman for another approach to &amp;ldquo;free
jazz&amp;rdquo;, and checked out the album
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Shape_of_Jazz_to_Come&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Shape of Jazz to Come&amp;rdquo; (1959)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;lonely-woman&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Lonely Woman&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Immediately, I was struck by the track
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lonely_Woman_%28composition%29&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Lonely Woman&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. Conventional
concerns such as being strictly &amp;ldquo;in tune&amp;rdquo; were out the window, in
favor of extremely flexibility of pitch and raw, wailing emotional
expression. It showcased Coleman&amp;rsquo;s lyrical side and was easy to
love. OK, not too weird.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/DNbD1JIH344&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;other-tracks&#34;&gt;Other tracks&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But bam, that was just a warmup. For example, check out
&amp;ldquo;Eventually&amp;rdquo;. It&amp;rsquo;s very free indeed, a lot of notes, an expression of
hyperactive motion, conventional tonality unimportant. Still, not too
harsh, and not totally random.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/WoC69lxnS_Y&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, what I really understood from his music was that he was doing
what came naturally to him. It did not feel forced, it was not to
prove a point. He was enjoying what he was doing. This sense of
&lt;em&gt;freedom&lt;/em&gt; really impressed me. It wasn&amp;rsquo;t reaction, it wasn&amp;rsquo;t
rebellion. I respected that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;free-jazz-a-collective-improvisation&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Free Jazz: A Collective Improvisation&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next album I checked out was
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Free_Jazz:_A_Collective_Improvisation&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Free Jazz: A Collective Improvisation&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was a step beyond, and confusing to me because of the
simultaneous playing that often seemed chaotic. I confess to taking no
huge pleasure in attempting to listen to it all at once (note that
apart from lack of conventional structure, it also keeps going on and
on at length). I found it more enjoyable to listen to only a couple of
random minutes, trying to absorb some stretch of order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, although this was not really my thing, it opened up my mind
to &amp;ldquo;why not?&amp;rdquo; Maybe this particular experiment didn&amp;rsquo;t work, but I
could imagine a simpler setting, say, with fewer instruments, in which
collective improvisation could work out better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check it out yourself:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/xbZIiom9rDA&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;something-else&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Something Else!!!!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I checked out
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Something_Else!!!!&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Something Else!!!!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;,
which actually was his first album and closer to bebop and so forth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t have much to say about it, but it&amp;rsquo;s not too confusing to
enjoy, because of still audible ties to some traditional forms and
styles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;freedom&#34;&gt;Freedom&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, I didn&amp;rsquo;t continue exploring Coleman&amp;rsquo;s music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the sense of &lt;em&gt;freedom&lt;/em&gt;, of &lt;em&gt;permission&lt;/em&gt; to ignore boundaries and
go wherever, musically, really affected me. Was what he was doing
&amp;ldquo;jazz&amp;rdquo;? Listening to him, I made up my mind that I was never again
going to get involved in debates about what jazz &amp;ldquo;really is&amp;rdquo; or what
classical music &amp;ldquo;really is&amp;rdquo; or even what music &amp;ldquo;really is&amp;rdquo;. These
labels stopped being meaningful to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That was what I really learned from him and his life. By coincidence,
I just read this Rolling Stone article,
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rollingstone.com/music/news/vernon-reid-on-ornette-coleman-he-set-a-lot-of-people-free-20150612&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Vernon Reid on Ornette Coleman: &amp;lsquo;He set a lot of people free&amp;rsquo;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;,
that echoes exactly what I felt I learned fifteen years ago from my
brief exposure to him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past year or so, there have been times when, alone and not
likely to bother anyone, I pull out my bass recorder (ha, my lowest
instrument) and just go wild, play some melodic shapes, make up
rhythms, go multiphonic, whatever, for the sheer joy of it. And I&amp;rsquo;m
not embarrassed, because I remember Ornette Coleman and he gave us all
permission to express our unconscious in whatever honest way it comes
out. And he gave us permission to accept and encourage each other to
do that, whether or not we personally like or understand everything
that comes out of tapping the unconscious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hadn&amp;rsquo;t expected to think so much upon hearing of Ornette Coleman&amp;rsquo;s
death. But he set an example that I respected deeply, forever changing
not only my perceptions of music but of what musicians can and should
be allowed to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Are you an Ornette Coleman fan or detractor? Did he change your
  life? If so, how exactly?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The many faces of &#34;Stella by Starlight&#34;</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/06/01/the-many-faces-of-stella-by-starlight/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jun 2015 01:08:23 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/06/01/the-many-faces-of-stella-by-starlight/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently I got obsessed with the classic 1944 jazz standard
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stella_by_Starlight&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Stella by Starlight&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought I&amp;rsquo;d share some very different interpretations of this music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;harry-james-1947&#34;&gt;Harry James, 1947&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the original version, not jazz, but slow, sentimental, lush: a
sentimental serenade perfect for dancing foxtrot to. Pretty good, if
you like &amp;ldquo;oldies&amp;rdquo;. And if you don&amp;rsquo;t like oldies, you need to hear this
anyway, to understand why the piece was so interesting: there is
inherently beautiful harmonic movement and color that would attract
jazz musicians to adopt this tune and transform it, and they still
continue to do that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/TjRMLqb6Sgs&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;miles-davis-quintet-1964&#34;&gt;Miles Davis quintet, 1964&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A really quirky version that starts with a slow intro before everyone
starts swinging, and then it goes fragmented again, and then the cycle
continues with all kinds of different ideas. Ten minutes long.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Riok08Y_ri4&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;tito-puente-around-1983&#34;&gt;Tito Puente, around 1983?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tito Puente and his Latin jazz band,
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michel_Camilo&#34;&gt;Michel Camilo&lt;/a&gt; on
piano. Puente himself starts off soloing on vibraphone: beautiful,
haunting rhythmic playing. Later, there is an electric guitar
solo. But mostly, this whole performance is melodic, and with its
steady and standard Afro-Cuban rhythmic drive, utterly danceable for
salsa. Something different!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the performance that inspired me to write this blog post,
because I&amp;rsquo;d never encountered this version before, but it was so
enchanting. From foxtrot original to salsa&amp;hellip; who would have thought?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34;
src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/xJF5BRuRtVo&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;
allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;chet-baker-quartet-1987&#34;&gt;Chet Baker quartet, 1987&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Live video footage from Tokyo. Baker is near the end of his tragic
life. He starts off with a fragmentary approach, and makes use of
long-held but gently played notes that creates soft but extended
dissonances against what&amp;rsquo;s going on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34;
src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/qq8oHYWHji8&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;
allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;learn-jazz-standards&#34;&gt;Learn Jazz Standards&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A wonderful backing track from &amp;ldquo;Learn Jazz Standards&amp;rdquo;, not for
listening to but playing against:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34;
src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/XR6KDWrn2ew&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;
allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One day I&amp;rsquo;ll take up the challenge of improvising an own performance
of &amp;ldquo;Stella by Starlight&amp;rdquo;, but I have to confess that right now it
seems too hard for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love &amp;ldquo;Stella by Starlight&amp;rdquo;. It will endure forever as a jazz
standard, I&amp;rsquo;m sure. I hope you like it too.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thoughts on Cuba while watching Cuban musicians performing the 1947 bolero &#34;La gloria eres tú&#34;</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/12/13/thoughts-on-cuba-while-watching-cuban-musicians-performing-the-1947-bolero-la-gloria-eres-tu/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Dec 2014 21:01:47 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/12/13/thoughts-on-cuba-while-watching-cuban-musicians-performing-the-1947-bolero-la-gloria-eres-tu/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t expect to be thinking so much about Cuba today. It all started with a random musical itch I was scratching.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;la-comparsa-and-the-wooden-flute-headjoint&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;La comparsa&amp;rdquo; and the wooden flute headjoint&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I was in a Latin music mood as I was playing my flute at home, and started looking up flute versions of music on YouTube for fun and inspiration. One piece that came to mind was the famous &amp;ldquo;La comparsa&amp;rdquo;, by Cuban composer &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ernesto_Lecuona&#34;&gt;Ernesto Lecuona&lt;/a&gt;. Last year when Bebo Valdés died, I wrote about being moved by the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/22/rip-bebo-valdes/&#34;&gt;reunion of Bebo with his son Chucho in a tearful duet performance of this piece on two pianos&lt;/a&gt;, and thinking about their separation as Bebo abandoned his family to flee Cuba for Sweden while his son stayed behind to become one of Cuba&amp;rsquo;s great musicians.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found a really quirky Latin jazz performance of &amp;ldquo;La comparsa&amp;rdquo; on YouTube by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.chipboaz.com/blog/2014/07/10/cuban-flautist-bobby-ramirez-releases-jazz-flute/&#34;&gt;Cuban-American&lt;/a&gt; jazz flutist &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bobbyramirez.com/&#34;&gt;Bobby Ramirez&lt;/a&gt; and Puerto Rican &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.negronistrio.com/&#34;&gt;Jose Negroni&lt;/a&gt; on keyboard:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/4Nro7myJ6Nw&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ramirez on flute was unfortunately out of tune with the keyboard, but what I noticed was his wooden headjoint. I&amp;rsquo;ve never seen the old traditional Cuban wooden &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.descarga.com/cgi-bin/db/archives/Article15&#34;&gt;Charanga flute&lt;/a&gt;, but do see flutists playing the modern Boehm flute with a wooden headjoint for a different sound. In fact, I love and prefer wooden flutes, but they are expensive and I own only one, a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/30/got-my-new-casey-burns-small-handed-irish-flute/&#34;&gt;Casey Burns Irish flute&lt;/a&gt;. So just for the fun of it (I can&amp;rsquo;t really justify the investment right now), I decided to search the Web for makers of wooden headjoints.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;juan-novo-wooden-flute-headjoints&#34;&gt;Juan Novo wooden flute headjoints&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the top Web hits was &lt;a href=&#34;http://jnovoheadjoints.com/&#34;&gt;Juan Novo&lt;/a&gt;. It had the benefit of having an embedded YouTube video with the caption &amp;ldquo;This musician appreciated Mr. Novo’s craftsmanship so much, that this song was dedicated to him.&amp;rdquo; So I checked out the video. Indeed, the young woman playing the flute said, &amp;ldquo;Está para Juan Novo&amp;rdquo;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/kBzrwhpVvDE&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, I noticed that Juan Novo&amp;rsquo;s biography said he was sent from Cuba to the US all alone by his parents in 1962 to &lt;a href=&#34;http://jnovoheadjoints.com/about-juan-novo/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;escape the rampant communist indoctrination&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;la-gloria-eres-tú&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;La gloria eres tú&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was captivated not so much by the flute playing, but by the beautiful singing, of the young woman in this video of the classic bolero &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cancioneros.com/nc/2806/0/la-gloria-eres-tu-jose-antonio-mendez&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;La gloria eres tú&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; written by Cuban composer &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.encaribe.org/es/article/jose-antonio-mendez-garcia/1296&#34;&gt;José Antonio Méndez&lt;/a&gt; in 1947. I was really touched by her clear, unexaggerated but free expression and style, especially in light of much more famous performances of the song in my memory:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;La gloria eres tú&amp;rdquo; is one of my favorite boleros (&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/08/10/rip-eydie/&#34;&gt;my favorite being &amp;ldquo;Sabor a mî&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;) of all time. For comparison:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;luis-miguel&#34;&gt;Luis Miguel&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first exposure to &amp;ldquo;La gloria eres tú&amp;rdquo; was, like probably many others of my generation or younger worlwide, through the revival of the bolero by Mexican pop star &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Luis_Miguel&#34;&gt;Luis Miguel&lt;/a&gt; in the 1990s and onwards. I have all his bolero albums, a result of taking up Latin ballroom dancing in 2000 and hearing him singing in much of the music we practiced, performed, and competed to, including my first discovery of &amp;ldquo;Sabor a mî&amp;rdquo;, which was also on the 1997 album &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Romances_%28Luis_Miguel_album%29&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Romances&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. Luis Miguel is a great musician, I will continue to admit, but in time I drew away from his high-powered, slick performances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here he is live, from his 2000 DVD &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vivo_%28Luis_Miguel_album%29&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Vivo&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, which was the last thing I bought by him before backing away from his work:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/GNldCVbD4b4&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;olga-guillot&#34;&gt;Olga Guillot&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, the gold standard for &amp;ldquo;La gloria eres tú&amp;rdquo; is the performance by Cuban &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Olga_Guillot&#34;&gt;Olga Guillot&lt;/a&gt;, the &amp;ldquo;queen of the bolero&amp;rdquo;. (In 1961, she was yet another musician who fled Cuba.) I like how she alternates between different moods, starting out gently and almost like a prayer, but then gets more and more passionate. She very quickly changes the color of her voice and dynamics. For me it&amp;rsquo;s still the greatest performance of this bolero:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/xEAOX2nxsEo&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;elena-burke&#34;&gt;Elena Burke&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another recording I have of the bolero is from an album by Cuban singer &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elena_Burke&#34;&gt;Elena Burke&lt;/a&gt;. She has her own style, with a low voice, and more staccato delivery:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/yuHpvIvukOg&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elena died in Havana in 2002. Her daughter &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Malena_Burke&#34;&gt;Malena&lt;/a&gt; came to Miami in the US in 1995 with her family. Here is Malena Burke performing the bolero with Arturo Sandoval on piano:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/2_LxxwXda8Y&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Malena Burke&amp;rsquo;s oldest daughter &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lena_Burke&#34;&gt;Lena&lt;/a&gt; is also a musician, a pianist and singer, and has worked with Gloria Estefan and others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s Lena singing the famous 1929 bolero-son &lt;a href=&#34;http://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/L%C3%A1grimas_negras&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Lágrimas negras&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; with Bebo Valdés and others. This is such a weird combo, with her being sixty years younger than Bebo and stylistically very &amp;ldquo;American pop&amp;rdquo;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/x56VtBF6iGo&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;arturo-sandoval&#34;&gt;Arturo Sandoval&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arturo_Sandoval&#34;&gt;Arturo Sandoval&lt;/a&gt;, he defected from Cuba to the US in 2000. I discovered him initially when his biographical film &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/For_Love_or_Country:_The_Arturo_Sandoval_Story&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;For Love or Country&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; about his life before defection came out, and I saw him perform in the Three Rivers Arts Festival in Pittsburgh in 2002.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a Latin jazz version by Arturo Sandoval on flugelhorn, from his 1994 album &amp;ldquo;Tenderly&amp;rdquo;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/AZW15092fx4&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;where-is-blau-colonial-cayo-coco&#34;&gt;Where is Blau Colonial Cayo Coco?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So there were many thoughts and questions already in my mind as a result of listening to this old Cuban bolero, as a result of my remembering past performances by musicians who had left Cuba. When I hear classic boleros, I think about old Cuba, the culture and society that produced this kind of music and musicians, the political upheaval, the consequences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But back to that little band Nucay, captured presumably on a phone outside on a windy day by a random tourist who posted the video on YouTube in 2010. What has life been like for the members of Nucay, and for the charming young flutist/singer?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, what and where is &amp;ldquo;Blau Colonial Cayo Coco&amp;rdquo;? Apparently it&amp;rsquo;s a resort now named just &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cayocococuba.net/hotel_colonialcayococo.html&#34;&gt;Colonial Cayo Coco&lt;/a&gt; on the island of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cayo_Coco&#34;&gt;Cayo Coco&lt;/a&gt; that is part of Cuba. In particular, this place was designed to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cubahotelreservation.com/hotel.asp?hotel_code=sctblacolonial&#34;&gt;look like a village&lt;/a&gt;. This kind of thing makes me uncomfortable. I guess tourists fly in to pretend to have a nice &amp;ldquo;village&amp;rdquo; experience, while the hired musicians are probably paid to look and act the part.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;nucay&#34;&gt;Nucay&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I looked up more performances on YouTube by this band Nucay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;oye-como-va-cha-cha&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Oye como va&amp;rdquo;, cha-cha&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The caption for this video reads, &amp;ldquo;Ramon Almeida and daughter Arleytis [sic] lead this wonderful group of talented Cuban musicians.&amp;rdquo; So now we have some names. I presume the leader with maracas is the father? (Later I determined his daughter&amp;rsquo;s name is actually &amp;ldquo;Arletis&amp;rdquo;: read on.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was a fine performance of the classic cha-cha &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oye_Como_Va&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Oye coma va&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; written by &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tito_Puente&#34;&gt;Tito Puente&lt;/a&gt; in 1963. No, Puente was not Cuban; he was born in New York and was a big force in creating the mambo/salsa scene in the US in the 1950s. A great Latin jazz musician. I should have gone to see him perform live when he was in Pittsburgh in 2000 before he died. His music was great for listening to as well as dancing to; I still remember practicing my dancing to the first album of his I bought, &amp;ldquo;Mambo Birdland&amp;rdquo; (which has an &amp;ldquo;Oye como va&amp;rdquo; track).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I&amp;rsquo;ll confess that hearing performances of this work over a decade ago inspired me to think about taking up flute again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arletis did a fine job on flute here, jazzing things up:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/l4uWBPD7y70&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;ay-maria-merengue&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Ay Maria!&amp;rdquo;, merengue&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The musicians seem to be having fun; how could one not, given the catchy music and all of them singing? I really enjoyed flute action by Arletis in this upbeat classic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Merengue_music&#34;&gt;merengue&lt;/a&gt; is not Cuban, but comes from the Dominican Republic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/tAgVVL_ZTmI&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;sabor-a-mî&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Sabor a mî&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My favorite bolero, performed well. The caption reads &amp;ldquo;Cuban Music with the help of young percussionist from Quebec&amp;rdquo;, but this is wrong: &lt;a href=&#34;http://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sabor_a_m%C3%AD_%28canci%C3%B3n%29&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Sabor a mî&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; was composed in 1959 by a Mexican composer, &lt;a href=&#34;http://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/%C3%81lvaro_Carrillo&#34;&gt;Álvaro Carrillo&lt;/a&gt;. These distinctions matter to me: &amp;ldquo;Latin&amp;rdquo; music is not all the same, any more than the people or the distinct cultures are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/RmOIKdY3LYw&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;some-salsa-song&#34;&gt;Some salsa song&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is some salsa song; I&amp;rsquo;m afraid I cannot identify it offhand, the way I did the other songs. I&amp;rsquo;d have to try to transcribe the lyrics and hope that a Web search finds something, but have my doubts when it comes to salsa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I loved the father-daughter musical interplay here, with Ramón singing and Arletis on flute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/sAMdEezxYJs&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;summary-of-nucay&#34;&gt;Summary of Nucay&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OK, so Nucay is a pretty good band and plays a lot of classics to please the tourists. What else?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;arletis-almeida-sentirse-asi&#34;&gt;Arletis Almeida, &amp;ldquo;Sentirse Asi&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that a search for more Nucay material on YouTube reveals the following slick, professionally produced video uploaded by someone in 2012, promoting Arletis Almeida as a singer, with the caption &amp;ldquo;Arletis Almeida, flutist of Grupo Nucay in Cayo Coco Cuba, with her original song Sentirse Asi written by her father and band member Ramon Almeida&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, she is almost unrecognizable to me, very much made up and glamorous and placed in an urban nightlife setting, with shots of handsome men, alcohol, cigarettes. The contrast between this angsty, sensualized persona and the cheerful flutist playing at Colonial Cayo Coco with her father was quite jarring to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The singing is beautiful, and the song actually breaks out into a standard bolero accompaniment. It&amp;rsquo;s really something hearing bolero singing of this quality from a young person today. My overall feeling when hearing either this newly composed bolero or the classic music in the earlier videos is this: there&amp;rsquo;s some kind of time bubble that can still happen in the world, for better or for worse (a subject bigger than this blog post), and Nucay and Arletis Almeida illustrate it. Here in the US, no young people sing in this way. The many influences from pop, hip hop, and much more result in much more &amp;ldquo;fusion&amp;rdquo;. You saw that above in Lena Burke&amp;rsquo;s singing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/P1PZhDtCmLM&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;thoughts-on-cuba&#34;&gt;Thoughts on Cuba&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After watching this video, I wonder what has become of Arletis Almeida. Does she still play flute? Has she embarked on some kind of lounge career? Who knows? She&amp;rsquo;s in Cuba. Cuba is a world away. It took tourists to make her name even register on the Web, through the links to the YouTube videos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve waited for decades for an end to the senseless &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_States_embargo_against_Cuba&#34;&gt;embargo of Cuba&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;ve already run out of space here to even begin talking about the politics of the Cold War, about the human cost of isolating Cuba. Cuba, a place with a complicated history, but once an advanced nation by any standard, filled with culture, music classical and popular, home of world chess champion &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jos%C3%A9_Ra%C3%BAl_Capablanca&#34;&gt;Capablanca&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;con-los-años-que-me-quedan-and-nostalgia&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Con los años que me quedan&amp;rdquo; and nostalgia&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For some reason, I was reminded of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gloria_Estefan&#34;&gt;Gloria Estefan&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s music video of the bolero &amp;ldquo;Con los años que me quedan&amp;rdquo; from her nostalgic 1993 album &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mi_Tierra&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Mi Tierra&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s an odd kind of nostalgia, given that her parents fled Cuba when she was young. She made this album to embrace her Cuban heritage. But what world is portrayed here? Something like the world the tourists at Cayo Cayo hope to see? And what is Arletis trying to do as she sings boleros today?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, it&amp;rsquo;s definitely a beautiful song, and Estefan sings it soulfully:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/l6LjNOYvhMk&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2014-12-17&#34;&gt;(Update of 2014-12-17)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Totally by coincidence, news has come of the apparent &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2014/12/18/world/americas/us-cuba-relations.html&#34;&gt;plan by President Obama to normalize relations with Cuba&lt;/a&gt; after half a century. I cannot process this news right now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Life for Arletis and her father may well change one day in interesting ways.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Review of edX 8.01x: Jazz Appreciation</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/04/04/review-of-edx-8-dot-01x-jazz-appreciation/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2014 22:13:47 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/04/04/review-of-edx-8-dot-01x-jazz-appreciation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.edx.org/sites/default/files/course/image/banner/jazz_608x211.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Course banner&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;By coincidence, it is now &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.smithsonianjazz.org/&#34;&gt;Jazz Appreciation Month&lt;/a&gt;, which is observed every April. So it is fitting that I just completed the free MOOC from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.edx.org/&#34;&gt;edX&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.edx.org/course/utaustinx/utaustinx-ut-8-01x-jazz-appreciation-1149&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Jazz Appreciation&amp;rdquo;, UT.8.01X&lt;/a&gt;, through UT Austin, taught by Jeffrey Hellmer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Intro video:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/dp9I1cM0fGA&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was good and bad in this course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-survey&#34;&gt;A survey&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This course was a low-stress way to get a little survey of jazz. I&amp;rsquo;ve never formally studied jazz nor systematically read up on its history, so all that I know comes purely from random personal listening, more than anything else. I don&amp;rsquo;t consider myself a &amp;ldquo;true&amp;rdquo; jazz aficionado; I know a whole lot more about classical music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought it was a good idea to start with 1950s hard bop rather than go in chronological order through history, and then work backwards and forwards from there, because of the accessibility and typicality of the jazz from this era.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I liked how the instructor illustrated concepts at the piano, and brought up issues of artistic differences without judgment and getting into controversies that still exist today. He basically said, you don&amp;rsquo;t have to like everything you hear in this course, but know how to identify and compare the stylistic features and goals. There&amp;rsquo;s a reason musicians chose to go in the directions they did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;cerego-quizzes&#34;&gt;Cerego quizzes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Cerego quiz platform was the most annoying thing about the course. I thought it was counterproductive busywork. In fact, I can&amp;rsquo;t believe I tolerated it just to complete the course; it was a waste of time to have done so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You had to demonstrate &amp;ldquo;mastery&amp;rdquo; of isolated facts, through identifying musical snippets, classifying the eras of musicians, memorizing what instruments they played, etc. I can see some point in some mastery of some facts, but the sheer repetition and shallowness of the concept bothered me. It got to the point where I made a game of identifying a musical selection based on hearing the first quarter second of its audio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-i-learned&#34;&gt;What I learned&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, I didn&amp;rsquo;t learn that much from the course, because I&amp;rsquo;ve already done my share of listening to jazz. I filled in a few gaps, but not in any deep way. Unfortunately, a course like this must be shallow. You might learn a few names, hear some musical snippets, and then it&amp;rsquo;s purely up to you to go investigate more if you want to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-drawback-of-a-survey-course&#34;&gt;The drawback of a survey course&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not sure whether to recommend a course like this if you&amp;rsquo;re interested in learning more about jazz. I believe it may be more enjoyable and instructive to simply pick a few favorite artists and listen deeply. A shallow survey simply cannot do much. I feel this way about survey courses on any subject, whether ballroom dancing, programming languages, or cooking. It&amp;rsquo;s best to just go deep, and then later fill in gaps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-followup&#34;&gt;My followup&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, one thing I did do as a result of this course was that the instructor mentioned resources such as &lt;a href=&#34;http://tedgioia.com/&#34;&gt;Ted Gioia&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s writings on jazz, and so I went and read his book from 1988, &lt;a href=&#34;http://tedgioia.com/TheImperfectArt.html&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Imperfect Art&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. I loved it, and it clarified for me some things I had been thinking about regarding the nature of jazz. I may write about this later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t actually read much music criticism any more, but if you want to read about jazz, Ted Gioia is definitely one guy to read. For example, check out his recent article &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.thedailybeast.com/articles/2014/03/18/music-criticism-has-degenerated-into-lifestyle-reporting.html&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Music criticism has degenerated into lifestyle reporting&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Finally learning about Carnatic music</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/10/finally-learning-about-carnatic-music/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2013 23:04:45 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/10/finally-learning-about-carnatic-music/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://f0.bcbits.com/img/a2399391511_2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Sandeep Narayan&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I attended the Thursday CMU music school convocation that featured a &lt;a href=&#34;http://music.cmu.edu/events/267&#34;&gt;lecture/performance by Sandeep Narayan and his brother Nirmal Narayan&lt;/a&gt;. I very much enjoyed the presentation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://sandeepnarayanmusic.com/&#34;&gt;Sandeep Narayan&lt;/a&gt; is a Carnatic musician. &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carnatic_music&#34;&gt;Carnatic music&lt;/a&gt; is the &amp;ldquo;classical&amp;rdquo; music of Southern India. I&amp;rsquo;d never specifically listened to it before, because I&amp;rsquo;d never had an introduction to it so that I would know what to listen for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sandeep is unusual in that he was born and grew up in the US, in Los Angeles, before eventually settling in Chennai, the center of Carnatic music. I imagine he must have faced quite a bit of curiosity and skepticism as one who walks between two worlds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, his introduction to the elements of Carnatic music, along with brief performance excerpts with his brother (Sandeep sang and Nirmal provided percussion backup), was fantastic! It was a very clear introduction to the elements of pitches, scales/modes, rhythms, and different levels of improvisation. It was particularly helpful that he related the different vocabulary to that of Western &amp;ldquo;classical&amp;rdquo; music and jazz.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wish I had been able to attend the free concert he was giving this evening, but in any case, after receiving this introduction, I feel ready to pursue Carnatic music further as a listener. I always feel intimidated and lost when thinking about how to understand a new kind of music; I&amp;rsquo;m not quite adventurous enough to just jump in with a tiny bit of prior background knowledge. Introductions like his go a long way to providing just enough that it is possible to start enjoying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing Sandeep emphasized is how the music is fundamentally based on &lt;em&gt;improvisation&lt;/em&gt;. He joked that his instrumentalist accompanists have to know more about music than he does, because they all have to follow wherever he goes. They have no idea what he is going to do with the musical material, till he is actually doing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is his &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/user/SRNChannel&#34;&gt;YouTube channel&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>RIP Marian McPartland of Piano Jazz</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/08/23/rip-marian-mcpartland-of-piano-jazz/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Aug 2013 22:30:35 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/08/23/rip-marian-mcpartland-of-piano-jazz/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marian_McPartland&#34;&gt;Marian McPartland&lt;/a&gt;, longtime host of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.npr.org/series/15773266/marian-mcpartland-s-piano-jazz&#34;&gt;NPR&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Piano Jazz&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; on the radio, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.npr.org/blogs/therecord/2013/08/21/161653933/marian-mcpartland-piano-jazz-host-has-died&#34;&gt;has died&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really enjoyed dipping into her radio program over the years, hearing her play hearing her guests play, listening to the conversations. The main impression I always had was alertness and &lt;em&gt;warmth&lt;/em&gt;. RIP.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pittsburgh JazzLive International Festival 2013: dancing salsa to Eddie Palmieri</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/06/08/pittsburgh-jazzlive-international-festival-2013-dancing-salsa-to-eddie-palmieri/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Jun 2013 22:57:23 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/06/08/pittsburgh-jazzlive-international-festival-2013-dancing-salsa-to-eddie-palmieri/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/eddie-palmieri-2013-06-08/stage.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Music stage&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Abby and I went downtown in Pittsburgh to check out the great Eddie Palmieri and his salsa orchestra, one of the main attractions of &lt;a href=&#34;http://pressroom.trustarts.org/2013/04/02/pittsburgh-jazzlive-international-festival-2013-artist-biographies/&#34;&gt;this year&amp;rsquo;s Pittsburgh JazzLive International Festival&lt;/a&gt;. Although I have a number of Eddie Palmieri&amp;rsquo;s music recordings, this was the first time I saw him live.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We arrived later than intended, so the place was already packed. There were guards for a taped-off seating section in front of the stage, apparently reserved for VIPs. However, we were asked if we were dancers, and we said yes, so they let us into the dancing area, which was already pretty packed with hardcore Pittsburgh salsa fans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;some-videos&#34;&gt;Some videos&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/CMbDlkG1wOE&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see some of us local dancers here (Abby and I were dancing further from the stage):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/sDqcweoCqL0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More footage here from another source here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/O1OH5lgXBs8&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/PsCZLx21Gnw&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I admit to being slightly disappointed (but not surprised at all) that Palmieri and friends did not display as much jazz virtuosity as they possess (and which you can find in their more &amp;ldquo;Latin jazz&amp;rdquo; vs. &amp;ldquo;salsa&amp;rdquo; work). They played tamer improvisations, as they were playing primarily for dancing here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;crowded&#34;&gt;Crowded&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/eddie-palmieri-2013-06-08/stage2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Music stage&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Because it got more and more crowded, and also the music was rather loud anywhere near the stage, at some point we left the designated dancing section and exited. We continued dancing for a bit on a side street off Penn Ave. Eventually we had enough and decided to wander off to Point State Park for a cool-down walk and to check out other acts for the Three Rivers Arts Festival (which the jazz portion is a subset of).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;point-state-park&#34;&gt;Point State Park&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fountain:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/eddie-palmieri-2013-06-08/fountain.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A curiosity that we saw at the bridge to Point State Park was &lt;a href=&#34;http://changjinlee.net/floating_echo/index.html&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Floating Echo&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, a translucent floating Buddha as public art:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/eddie-palmieri-2013-06-08/buddha.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was good to get out there and dance with Abby. I had been feeling really tired all day, but insisted on getting out of the house and was glad I did. I felt it was particularly important to do something with Abby this weekend, because last weekend, after &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/06/01/report-on-the-second-pittsburgh-techfest-2013/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh TechFest and my health problems that led to going to urgent care&lt;/a&gt;, I had to bail out of a planned hike together on Sunday, and Abby went to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/pittsburghhikers/events/117891642/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Getting wet at Ohiopyle hike&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; alone, without me, her first hike of the entire year (because of her breaking her foot in winter).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Singing and playing tango and jazz at an unexpected music party</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/04/12/singing-and-playing-tango-and-jazz-at-an-unexpected-music-party/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Apr 2013 23:20:59 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/04/12/singing-and-playing-tango-and-jazz-at-an-unexpected-music-party/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/bob-party-2013-04-12/henry-franklin.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Henry and Franklin performing El Choclo&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I suddenly got email from Henry on a Friday afternoon while I was at work. He invited me to join him at some guy&amp;rsquo;s party in the evening to play some tangos, since the party was going to have an &amp;ldquo;Argentina&amp;rdquo; theme. My first thought was that Abby was not going to be able to go, and I myself had made plans to rest up before my very important training run Saturday morning for the Pittsburgh Marathon, but the opportunity to meet some new musicians and other people, and express my love for passionate tango music, made me decide, after consulting with Abby, to attend the party.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The good news was that I had done some tango music earlier, so there was some reuse possible. Last year, I had finally worked up the courage to do some singing, and rather enjoyed singing classic traditional tango in particular, such as &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/11/17/a-childhood-dream-come-true-i-am-now-finally-singing-for-real/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Por una Cabeza&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. And this year, I had finally given a shot at playing &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/26/music-i-just-played-for-the-first-time-recorder-sonata-tangos/&#34;&gt;tango on flute&lt;/a&gt;, playing both &amp;ldquo;El Choclo&amp;rdquo; as well as &amp;ldquo;Por una Cabeza&amp;rdquo; (as a flute-violin duet).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bad news was that someone else was already going to play &amp;ldquo;Por una Cabeza&amp;rdquo; on violin, so that left me with only one other tango I had played with Henry before, &lt;a href=&#34;http://joanveronica.hubpages.com/hub/The-Tango-La-Cumparsita-El-Choclo-and-Mi-Buenos-Aires-Querido&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;El Choclo&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, whose contrasts of staccato/legato and minor/major, with a lot of room for rubato and ornamental bravado quite appeal to me.. I wanted a tango to sing, and by sheer coincidence, I knew exactly which tango I always wanted to sing, but had only half-sung it to myself in private: this was &lt;a href=&#34;http://joanveronica.hubpages.com/hub/Outstanding-Tango-selection-Mi-Buenos-Aires-Querido-Uno-and-Caminito&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Uno&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, by &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mariano_Mores&#34;&gt;Mariano Mores&lt;/a&gt; from 1943.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;uno&#34;&gt;Uno&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By coincidence, only a couple of days ago, the Spanish actress/singer &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sara_Montiel&#34;&gt;Sara Montiel&lt;/a&gt; died, and in her memory I rewatched and &lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/100967806642012078047/posts/6xV5iasmXxj&#34;&gt;reposted&lt;/a&gt; a video clip of her singing &amp;ldquo;Uno&amp;rdquo; in a film:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/5Z7rHztinaM&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe that I first came across &amp;ldquo;Uno&amp;rdquo; by accident when some years ago I found Montiel&amp;rsquo;s performance while searching for other tangos. In any case, it was love at first hearing, and made it to my list of tangos I wanted to sing some day. I&amp;rsquo;d put off this project for some good reasons, but today I decided I wanted to give it a shot!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I hastily found a score, printed out the lyrics, and after eating dinner at home after work, and just an hour or so before the party, I worked on being able to sing the Spanish lyrics without completely stumbling over myself. Most songs in Spanish I can sing with no problem, but &amp;ldquo;Uno&amp;rdquo; features a huge number of words in the lyrics, which means there are considerable challenges:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;pronouncing Spanish at basically spoken speed (I&amp;rsquo;m not that fluent yet)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;breaking up the words into logical and emotional groupings at speed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;singing Spanish in the face of many, many instances of word pairs with vowels in between&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I knew I wasn&amp;rsquo;t going to get everything perfect in time in less than half an hour of determining where to break things up and where to link things, and actually doing this fluently, so I was nervous, but I&amp;rsquo;ve learned that when it comes to music, perfect technique is not the most important thing; I felt I could reasonably well convey the emotional content of this song despite imperfections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-party&#34;&gt;The party&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a great party, with food, music, and conversation, and I was excited to meet a whole bunch of new people of all ages. I hope the next time Bob and his wife host another music party, Abby will be able to attend too!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before the musical part of the party began, Henry and I spent about five minutes in the basement, with him on the upright piano down there, and me singing, trying to read through &amp;ldquo;Uno&amp;rdquo; together so that it would be at least halfway presentable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We performed &amp;ldquo;El Choclo&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Uno&amp;rdquo; near the end of the program (since we were last minute additions that didn&amp;rsquo;t make it onto the printed program). I was physically shaking while doing both of them, because I was in front of a completely new crowd of people and just wasn&amp;rsquo;t as prepared as I would have preferred. But it was a friendly crowd, and the audience seemed to enjoy our music-making. I was happy to have contributed something to the &amp;ldquo;Argentina&amp;rdquo; theme with some authentic Golden Age tango music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What was really enjoyable about this music party was that so many of the guests participated in performing something: young and old, amateur and professional. This welcoming atmosphere was wonderful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;jazz-improvisation&#34;&gt;Jazz, improvisation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the official music program ended, some people continued to jam. This guy I met, Keith, was particularly interesting to me, as he is a wind player, and played both soprano saxophone and flute on the program, and then after the program, was doing jazz standards on alto saxophone. I was so inspired by this that I decided I wanted to do some jazz also. I bring a little binder of music nowadays when I go to musical parties, just in case, and happened to have on me &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jazzstandards.com/compositions-0/sweetlorraine.htm&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Sweet Lorraine&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, which I had never played before other than to myself with a CD track. So I got Henry to the piano so that we could just go for it and improvise to the chord changes. We totally got into it and I really enjoyed the jamming. I really enjoy nothing more than improvisation, and appreciate that Henry is game for doing this with me, as when we were doing it with Latin jazz (bolero and cha cha) &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/17/finally-doing-some-latin-music-jamming-on-flute/&#34;&gt;last month&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had tremendous fun attending Bob&amp;rsquo;s party, seeing so many people sing or play an instrument, all of us sharing our love of music together. I was very inspired by everyone who contributed something of their unique soul there, and I feel like this is what life is all about.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>RIP Bebo Valdés, master pianist of Cuban music</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/03/22/rip-bebo-valdes/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Mar 2013 20:08:56 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/03/22/rip-bebo-valdes/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.billboard.com/files/styles/promo_650/public/media/bebo-chucho-valdes-650-430.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Bebo and Chucho&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I just heard about the death of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bebo_Vald%C3%A9s&#34;&gt;Bebo Valdés&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.npr.org/blogs/ablogsupreme/2013/03/22/175080694/bebo-vald-s-giant-of-cuban-music-is-dead?ft=1&amp;amp;f=1039&#34;&gt;at age 94 in Sweden&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I discovered this Cuban musician a decade ago, when, as a big fan of Latin (especially Cuban) dance and music, I bought the documentary &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Calle_54&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Calle 54&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; when it came out. I had heard the playing of his son &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chucho_Vald%C3%A9s&#34;&gt;Chucho&lt;/a&gt; and was very curious how Bebo&amp;rsquo;s playing might differ. The father had a more old-fashioned style, of course. But he was good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most moving scene in the entire film was that of father and son playing together, on two pianos, improvising on the famous Cuban song &amp;ldquo;La Comparsa&amp;rdquo; by &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ernesto_Lecuona&#34;&gt;Ernesto Lecuona&lt;/a&gt;. The communication between them and the interplay and contrasts were quite fascinating and touching to me. They got very emotional during their session and I could not help being moved to tears myself. The scene made me think about the story of Bebo&amp;rsquo;s decision to leave Cuba for Sweden, abandoning his family, and how he met up again with Chucho for this documentary! For me, reflecting on my own relationship with my father over the years (who is still very much alive and well; I see him once or twice a year, and will see him again soon), the scene was electric.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-bebo-chucho-scene-from-calle-54&#34;&gt;The Bebo/Chucho scene from &amp;ldquo;Calle 54&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/enblfWLM4n0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some highlights:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At the beginning, Bebo starts off with flourishes and then the theme, while Chucho provides a little bit of harmonic filler.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Then Chucho starts adding more countermelody.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At 2:01, they smile at each other as Bebo changes the key and lets Chucho take charge. Bebo goes into a lot of elaborate, passionate ornamentation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At 2:46, when the melody goes from minor to major, this is when things start getting intense: watch the two looking at each other with increasing emotion.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At 3:39, Bebo signals to slow things down. They end, slyly without a harmonic resolution. Then Chucho gets up and hugs his father.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rest in peace, Bebo Valdés.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Finally doing some Latin music jamming on flute; also Irish and French</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/03/17/finally-doing-some-latin-music-jamming-on-flute/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Mar 2013 23:36:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/03/17/finally-doing-some-latin-music-jamming-on-flute/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;St. Patrick&amp;rsquo;s Day weekend means, of course, a party at Henry&amp;rsquo;s. Last year Abby and I even went to two of his St. Patrick&amp;rsquo;s Day parties! At the first, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/17/st-patricks-day-party-playing-tin-whistle-and-flute/&#34;&gt;I played tin whistle for the first time&lt;/a&gt;, and I played some easy recorder music &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/30/a-delayed-st-patricks-day-party-playing-tin-whistle-and-alto-recorder/&#34;&gt;at the second&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year, I reflected on how far I&amp;rsquo;ve come musically, and as usual, wanted to do something new and challenging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;irish-music&#34;&gt;Irish music&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I brought my tin whistle and Irish flute ready to jam. It turned out that Barbara had come with violin ready for some Irish jamming also. When she went at it with Henry on piano, she ended up playing &amp;ldquo;Danny Boy&amp;rdquo; (&amp;ldquo;Londonderry Air&amp;rdquo;) as one selection. Unfortunately, I had planned on playing it on flute, &amp;ldquo;redeeming&amp;rdquo; myself after being terrible on flute a year ago &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/17/st-patricks-day-party-playing-tin-whistle-and-flute/&#34;&gt;when I tried it&lt;/a&gt;, so since she had already done it, I quietly scrapped my original plan. No problem: there were many other things to play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Barbara joined me and Henry in some jigs, reels, and waltzes that I pulled out, some of which I did on tin whistle and some of which I did on Irish flute. That was fun, if pretty exhausting: lots and lots of notes, not so easy to just plain sight read. But of course, nobody has to play all the notes. That&amp;rsquo;s the beauty of this music. There never were official notes anyway; these are traditional tunes with a certain recognizable rhythm and shape and harmonic movement, but everyone does the notes differently anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;french-music&#34;&gt;French music&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d asked Vasili to learn on accordion &amp;ldquo;Les Ormeaux&amp;rdquo;, which I had learned just recently &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/02/25/stepping-it-up-at-the-french-and-blues-jam/&#34;&gt;at a French jam&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s not actually a traditional tune, but it&amp;rsquo;s a great one. Unfortunately, it turned out that Vasili had learned it in a different key from the one I was using on modern flute, so one of us (him) transposed on the fly to try to match, and the result therefore wasn&amp;rsquo;t as good as it could have been. Next time! Anyway, Abby and I jammed with Vasili on stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;latin-music&#34;&gt;Latin music&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;bolero&#34;&gt;Bolero&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The musical highlight for me was my debut in playing Latin, or more specifically, Cuban music. I fell in love with this music when I was &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/10/flute-loving-it-again/&#34;&gt;introduced to Latin ballroom dance back in 2000&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started off with an unnamed bolero from a World Music Cuba book I had first encountered &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/02/22/flute-progress-still-hanging-in-there/&#34;&gt;a year ago when I was just barely playing flute&lt;/a&gt;. I got on flute and Henry enthusiastically improvised along on piano and we took a couple of turns. That was great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I pulled out &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pbs.org/buenavista/music/songs/dos_gardenias.html&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Dos Gardenias&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, one of my favorite boleros of all time (and the bolero is one of my favorite musical genres). (By the way, I am working on being ready to sing this and other boleros before too long, making my debut as a bolero singer.) Again, more fun opportunities for inventiveness for Henry and me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;buena-vista-social-club&#34;&gt;Buena Vista Social Club&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, I first encountered &amp;ldquo;Dos Gardenias&amp;rdquo; through Ibrahim Ferrer of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Buena_Vista_Social_Club_%28album%29&#34;&gt;Buena Vista Social Club&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/5pKW7qvYSHU&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Buena Vista Social Club&amp;rdquo; was a very important music recording to me. At a time in my life around thirteen years ago when I was trying to explore Latin music and asked around for suggestions, my grad school classmate Andrej recommended this CD to me and my musical world was changed forever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;cha-cha&#34;&gt;Cha cha&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I pulled out an unnamed cha cha from the World Music Cuba book. We really went wild for this one, especially since Chad, one of Henry&amp;rsquo;s piano students (and a fine improviser) decided to join us and sat at the piano with Henry as both of them played with me and we kept going and going and I became very excited and inspired along with them. Wow. That was one of the most intense musical experiences I&amp;rsquo;ve ever had. It was frightening (didn&amp;rsquo;t know when I&amp;rsquo;d hit the limits of my technique or inventiveness) and exhilarating at the same time. When I was done, I was sweating from all the effort. Abby said she&amp;rsquo;d never seen me so animated before playing music, since she&amp;rsquo;s only ever seen me play Baroque and other such music mainly, or Irish and French. Well, Latin jazz is different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;chess&#34;&gt;Chess&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point in the evening, I needed a break from playing music and from socializing and decided to rest. However, it turned out that my &amp;ldquo;rest&amp;rdquo; consisted of relaxing in a chair while closing my eyes and&amp;hellip; &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/17/my-second-ever-blindfold-chess-game/&#34;&gt;playing blindfold chess&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2014-03-16&#34;&gt;(Update of 2014-03-16)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I couldn&amp;rsquo;t make it to Henry&amp;rsquo;s St. Patrick Day party in 2014. I felt sad about this, but our other plans made earlier made it impractical to try to attend.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Special treat: Dutch jazz trumpeter Eric Vloeimans performed in Pittsburgh!</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/12/19/special-treat-dutch-jazz-trumpeter-eric-vloeimans-performed-in-pittsburgh/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Dec 2012 23:42:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/12/19/special-treat-dutch-jazz-trumpeter-eric-vloeimans-performed-in-pittsburgh/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.pghcitypaper.com/imager/b/original/1596939/9540/music2_50.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Eric Vloeimans&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A while ago, I heard through a fantastic &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pghcitypaper.com/pittsburgh/jazz-goes-dutch/Content?oid=1596938&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh City paper article&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/Pittsburgh-Jazz-Fan-Meetup-Group/events/93376692&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Jazz Fan meetup&lt;/a&gt; about Dutch jazz trumpeter &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ericvloeimans.com/&#34;&gt;Eric Vloeimans&lt;/a&gt; coming to Pittsburgh to perform as part of an &amp;ldquo;international progressive jazz trio&amp;rdquo; including himself, German &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.florianweber.net/&#34;&gt;Florian Weber&lt;/a&gt; on piano, and Syrian &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.kinanazmeh.com&#34;&gt;Kinan Azmeh&lt;/a&gt; on clarinet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had never heard of these musicians before, but the article intrigued me enough to do some research, and Abby and I ended up attending his concert.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;i-did-research&#34;&gt;I did research&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the great things about this era, I think, is that you can learn something about musicians&amp;rsquo; work before deciding to invest in attending a concert. Things were much less certain before the whole Internet; you had to be deeply connected to some community of people that gave you information and advice, and it was harder to randomly hear about and explore new things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Upon checking out &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/user/ericvloeimans&#34;&gt;Eric Vloeimans&amp;rsquo;s YouTube channel&lt;/a&gt; for samples of his work, I decided that I was intrigued by his music, and I loved his contrasts, moving between loud, wild improvisation and a soft lyrical style, but always with beautiful tone. Also, I liked that he comes from the classical world and is interested in all kinds of music and brings it all together to create his own style.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;attending-the-concert-in-pittsburgh&#34;&gt;Attending the concert in Pittsburgh&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby mostly thinks jazz is chaotic, so I didn&amp;rsquo;t know whether I could convince her to go to the concert with me, but found this lyrical side of Vloeimans to show her:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/3Y0izaxU8YQ?list=UUuNCeR2oWKiCdcGZ4NwZv2w&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I got a pair of tickets, and Abby and I went to the trio&amp;rsquo;s concert in the First Unitarian Church. Attendance was, as I expected, sparse. Sadly, this kind of music is not so popular here in Pittsburgh. On the plus side, the small audience made the whole experience feel very intimate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, I loved the concert. This being a jazz program with many different experiments, of course there were moments or ideas that did not work for me, but overall, I was inspired by what the three created together on the spot, working with all they had from pre-agreed themes and technique, and the demands of the moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The concert warmed up with a lyrical piece that showed off Vloeimans&amp;rsquo;s classical training.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things got going right after that, with the second piece starting out with an atonal intro by Weber on piano, and then rhythmically ended up being some kind of tango. Vloeimans is a very physically expressive performer. He started stamping his feet in rhythm while playing, and at some point both Weber and Vloeimans were going at it physically, adding vocalizations to the mix. Great energy and fun!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Azmeh on clarinet then played a lovely duet with Vloeimans on trumpet. I could see how attentive they were to each other as they created a dialogue on the spot, combining turn-taking with simultaneous improvisation. It was an unusual combination of sound to me, the clarinet-trumpet duet. Azmeh also being classically trained, you could hear the working out in real time of subtle contrapuntal and harmonic ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then all three played together as a trio. This used a backdrop of minimalist repetition and literally made their performance sound like a train ride of industrial sounds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then came Azmeh with a long clarinet solo as intro into a piece that unfolded finally into a trio. I loved the meditative and exploratory quality of the solo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then came something very animated, which sounded like it was based on Cuban rhythms, but also somehow sounded Asian. Things got really animated, and Weber started hitting at the piano, and of course Vloeimans was stamping his feet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After that, something that sounded Jewish. Weber prepared the piano and made it sound tinny.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, they closed with telling a story about an encounter with Hindustani music in India, and then launching into music created as a result of that inspiration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a great evening of music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;for-more&#34;&gt;For more&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of what Vloeimans and Weber did came from their album &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Live-Concertgebouw-Vloeimans-Florian-Weber/dp/B005H4T9XI&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Live at the Concertgebouw&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, which &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.allaboutjazz.com/live-at-the-concertgebouw-eric-vloeimans-challenge-records-review-by-john-kelman.php&#34;&gt;you may want to check out&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2014-08-06&#34;&gt;(Update of 2014-08-06)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was looking up the trio again and found this video that gives a good idea of some of the kind of thing they did when they were in Pittsburgh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/WqlJmWd5j3g&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Attending the annual Pitt Jazz Seminar for the first time: day 2</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/11/03/attending-the-annual-pitt-jazz-seminar-for-the-first-time/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Nov 2012 20:52:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/11/03/attending-the-annual-pitt-jazz-seminar-for-the-first-time/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.music.pitt.edu/sites/default/files/jazz-2012-cropped.jpg?1350921512&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;42nd Pitt Jazz Seminar poster&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/11/02/attending-the-annual-pitt-jazz-seminar-for-the-first-time-day-1/&#34;&gt;Yesterday&lt;/a&gt;, I attended some morning sessions of the annual Pitt Jazz Seminar. I went back for more today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-tribute-to-miles&#34;&gt;A tribute to Miles&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;randy-brecker-http-randybrecker-com-trumpet&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://randybrecker.com/&#34;&gt;Randy Brecker&lt;/a&gt;, trumpet&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I liked how Randy Brecker talked about how he got into music. He listened to a lot of records as a kid, and at some point he started improvising during piano solos, by ear. He started with ballads (by Miles, Chet, etc.) and played with his brother &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.michaelbrecker.com/&#34;&gt;Michael&lt;/a&gt; (who sadly died some years ago).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;lew-soloff-http-www-lewsoloff-com-trumpet&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lewsoloff.com/&#34;&gt;Lew Soloff&lt;/a&gt;, trumpet&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lew Soloff came from a very different world. He stopped piano lessons at ten because his teachers did not emphasize &lt;em&gt;music&lt;/em&gt;, but &amp;ldquo;holding the hand a certain way&amp;rdquo;. He wanted trumpet because it was &lt;em&gt;shiny&lt;/em&gt;. Ha! Reminded me that it doesn&amp;rsquo;t matter why you start doing something; often you have a perhaps superficial reason, and find deeper reasons later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His uncle emphasized the importance of &lt;em&gt;practice&lt;/em&gt; and admonished him for being interested in too many things. Some tips on mental attitudes: never say &amp;ldquo;I can&amp;rsquo;t&amp;rdquo;, and also drop your &lt;em&gt;ego&lt;/em&gt;: learn from your peers. So in one summer, he went from last chair to first chair, practicing one and a half hours each day!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lew had a classical music training and therefore at first was scared to improvise. He had to overcome that fear. He also had to learn to articulate in &amp;ldquo;doodle tongue&amp;rdquo; rather than in the classical way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He said he eventually became open to all kinds of music, where in the past he was closed. He has a different take than Duke Ellington&amp;rsquo;s famous quote, &amp;ldquo;There are two kinds of music, good music and the other kind&amp;rdquo;: instead, Lew likes to think that the two kinds are the &lt;em&gt;honest&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;dishonest&lt;/em&gt;. I like this formulation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Randy piped in saying that he became musically open because that was just the way things were in Philadelphia, where there are so many styles.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Advice: when learning ballads, first play them &lt;em&gt;without&lt;/em&gt; improvisation, focusing on purity and honesty, and expressing emotion as though singing. Learn the lyrics and understand them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;artistry-in-rhythm-winard-harper-http-www-winardharper-com-drums&#34;&gt;Artistry in rhythm: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.winardharper.com/&#34;&gt;Winard Harper&lt;/a&gt;, drums&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Winard Harper spoke of coming from a musical family and playing at clubs by the time he was five years old. He emphasized the importance of relationships in making music come together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He&amp;rsquo;s really into an African instrument that I never heard of before called a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Balafon&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;balafon&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. More generally, he is interested in all kinds of world music, whether from Africa, Australia, Japan. He urged everyone to honor tradition, learn history, and do a lot of playing and listening. &amp;ldquo;The more you know, the more you can use&amp;rdquo;. He summed up with the message that as a drummer, when jamming, you have to face all kinds of situations, drums that are not yours, etc., and you have to learn to deal, because it&amp;rsquo;s not about you but about music. Sounds wise no matter what instrument we play!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-piano-in-jazz-george-cables-http-georgecables-com&#34;&gt;The piano in jazz: &lt;a href=&#34;http://georgecables.com/&#34;&gt;George Cables&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;George Cables emphasized that jazz is living music, through which everyone can become a &amp;ldquo;co-composer&amp;rdquo; through arranging and improvising.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a pianist, he didn&amp;rsquo;t want to be a soloist so much as a good side man. He was most inspired by Wynton Kelly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Musically, he emphasized that the piano is a percussion instrument. He also gave a history lesson on the piano in jazz, starting from Scott Joplin and moving forward from there. He said the progression was toward &amp;ldquo;freeing the bass&amp;rdquo;, allowing the left hand to do a lot more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(I had to leave this session a little early because I wanted to make it to a special recorder concert elsewhere in town.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found it very interesting and useful attending Pitt Jazz Seminar sessions these past two days, featuring very different musicians on different instruments, getting a broad perspective on how they operate and what they value and what they have to teach. I hope to continue attending this annual event!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Attending the annual Pitt Jazz Seminar for the first time: day 1</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/11/02/attending-the-annual-pitt-jazz-seminar-for-the-first-time-day-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Nov 2012 23:53:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/11/02/attending-the-annual-pitt-jazz-seminar-for-the-first-time-day-1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.music.pitt.edu/sites/default/files/jazz-2012-cropped.jpg?1350921512&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;42nd Pitt Jazz Seminar poster&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This year I decided to attend events of the 42nd annual &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.music.pitt.edu/events/november-3-2012-42nd-annual-jazz-se120813&#34;&gt;Pitt Jazz Seminar&lt;/a&gt; for the first time. I&amp;rsquo;ve never had any instruction in jazz, and frankly have only a little bit of experience trying to play it myself, so I enjoyed the opportunity to attend presentations by great performers who could talk about what they do, where they&amp;rsquo;ve come from, and demonstrate their craft.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went in to Pitt campus on a Friday morning to learn from some master musicians.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;yotam-silbertein-http-yotammusic-com-guitar&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://yotammusic.com/&#34;&gt;Yotam Silbertein&lt;/a&gt;, guitar&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought it was interesting that an Israeli musician, Yotam Silbertein, kicked off the morning of seminars. Of course, as he emphasized in his talk, jazz is an international phenomenon. It happens in Israel, it happens in Japan, it happens in Europe. It may have started off in the United States, but it is everywhere now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, he did eventually have to head to New York, the place to be. He even speaks English with a New York style accent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He emphasized that it&amp;rsquo;s necessary to go where the action is and learn from the best.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;javon-jackson-http-www-javonjackson-com-tenor-saxophone&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.javonjackson.com/&#34;&gt;Javon Jackson&lt;/a&gt;, tenor saxophone&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Javon Jackson spoke a lot about being a professional in music: how you behave, how you work with others, and develop a career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, he pointed out that he wears a suit because it projects a professional image.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;that-s-it-for-the-day&#34;&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s it for the day&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was another session later in the afternoon, but I skipped it because I needed to return to work.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Singing and playing bossa nova favorite &#34;Chega de Saudade&#34; at Dunkin&#39; Donuts for J-Jam</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/10/28/singing-and-playing-bossa-nova-favorite-chega-de-saudade-at-dunkin-donuts-for-j-jam/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Oct 2012 00:54:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/10/28/singing-and-playing-bossa-nova-favorite-chega-de-saudade-at-dunkin-donuts-for-j-jam/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/j-jam-2012-10-28/5.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;CMU Klezmer Band performing&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Yesterday evening, I ended up unexpectedly &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/10/27/singing-an-irish-ballad-as-an-asian-pirate-at-a-halloween-belly-dance-hafla/&#34;&gt;singing alone in public for the first time in my life&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This evening, I ended up unexpectedly singing again, with guitarist &lt;a href=&#34;http://cantorben.com/&#34;&gt;Cantor Ben Rosner&lt;/a&gt; accompanying me: the first time in my life singing with an accompanist for the general public, and the first time I&amp;rsquo;ve worked with a guitarist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had just met for the first time this evening, and had only a minute ahead of time to agree on a suitable tempo and have him quickly sight read chords before we just launched into the music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had not come to the local Dunkin&amp;rsquo; Donuts in Squirrel Hill expecting to &lt;em&gt;sing&lt;/em&gt; at all, actually! What happened?!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-story-behind-the-jam-session-at-dunkin-donuts&#34;&gt;The story behind the jam session at Dunkin&amp;rsquo; Donuts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby had recently just met a new guy playing in the [Pittsburgh Mandolin Orchestra], &lt;a href=&#34;http://cantorben.wix.com/cantor-benjamin-rosner&#34;&gt;Cantor Ben Rosner&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bethshalompgh.org/&#34;&gt;Congregation Beth Shalom&lt;/a&gt; in Squirrel Hill. He was passing out flyers advertising a music jam session he was organizing, &amp;ldquo;J-Jam&amp;rdquo;, to be held tonight in the local Dunkin&amp;rsquo; Donuts, which happens to be &lt;a href=&#34;http://triblive.com/home/1926901-74/hill-squirrel-dunkin-donuts-kosher-pittsburgh-says-area-jewish-restaurant&#34;&gt;the only Dunkin&amp;rsquo; Donuts in the area that is certified kosher&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apparently this was not the first &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.thejewishchronicle.net/view/full_story/19127215/article-Open-mic-night-draws-Jewish-performers-to-Dunkin%E2%80%99-Donuts?instance=news_special_coverage_right_column&#34;&gt;Jewish community oriented music jam held at Dunkin&amp;rsquo; Donuts&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-01-16&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-01-16)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;J-Jam now has its own &lt;a href=&#34;http://jjampgh.webs.com/&#34;&gt;official Web site&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.facebook.com/jjamPGH&#34;&gt;Facebook page&lt;/a&gt;. Check them out!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;deciding-to-participate&#34;&gt;Deciding to participate&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I hear about music jams, I get excited as well as nervous. I always feel that I wish I were a much better musician than I am now, so that I don&amp;rsquo;t always feel that I&amp;rsquo;m the &lt;em&gt;worst&lt;/em&gt; one at these events, but at the same time, I learn so much from just being out there, both to enjoy hearing other musicians, and to study how they do what they do, and in turn try to provide something of my own soul to other musicians and the audience as well. It&amp;rsquo;s like being naked; it&amp;rsquo;s still really tough for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I was intrigued because, well, Dunkin&amp;rsquo; Donuts should be pretty low key, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had spread the word to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.andrew.cmu.edu/user/lukas/pcars/Welcome.html&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Recorder Society&lt;/a&gt; mailing list, but nobody seemed up for participating, except Chuck said he was interested in coming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;preparation&#34;&gt;Preparation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had no time whatsoever to &amp;ldquo;prepare&amp;rdquo; for this music jam. We exchanged some emails only earlier today, in which I mentioned some music I might play, if a suitable accompanist were available. These emails were exchanged as Abby and I were at the second day of &lt;a href=&#34;http://podcamppittsburgh.com/pcpgh-7-sessions-sunday/&#34;&gt;PodCamp Pittsburgh 7&lt;/a&gt; all day. When we came home from PodCamp Pittsburgh, all we could do was crash with a long nap, eat dinner, and frantically pack up our instruments. I brought along a little binder of stuff I might play. I had told Ben that I could play stuff like Baroque flute sonata movements or bossa nova or tango or Cuban bolero.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby has been performing in music groups longer than I have, so she has her own selections at hand for her tamburas whenever desired.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;at-j-jam&#34;&gt;At J-Jam&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dunkin&amp;rsquo; Donuts was amazingly crowded. There were people of all ages, from toddlers to the elderly, sitting around listening to the live music and enjoying kosher food. It was pretty loud in there. I immediately decided that I would not play Baroque flute here. (I had brought it along with my Irish flute, modern flute, and soprano and alto recorders.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since we had arrived an hour and a half past the begin time of the music jam, we had missed no shortage of performances already, I was sure. There were musicians singing and playing guitar and cello; I saw who I presumed to be Ben Rosner accompanying on mandolin at the time:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/j-jam-2012-10-28/1.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Musicians in the middle of performing&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;meeting-ben-and-deciding-what-to-do&#34;&gt;Meeting Ben and deciding what to do&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/j-jam-2012-10-28/2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Patrons in Dunkin&amp;#39; Donuts&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;After the current musicians&amp;rsquo; set, Ben came up to Abby and me, and said we could play after a couple more groups had their turn. He asked what I wanted to play. We took a few seconds to flip through that stuff I had brought, and decided to play one of the bossa nova songs I had brought, &amp;ldquo;Chega de Saudade&amp;rdquo;: he would sight read the chords and accompany me. I chose &amp;ldquo;Chega de Saudade&amp;rdquo; because I had given a shot at it spontaneously &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/21/my-first-time-singing-bossa-nova-also-a-temporary-farewell-to-baroque-flute/&#34;&gt;at a party a month ago&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I immediately made an interesting decision: although I had originally intended to play the melody on flute, and then launch into a jazzy improvisation before concluding, I decided, based on having just &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/10/27/singing-an-irish-ballad-as-an-asian-pirate-at-a-halloween-belly-dance-hafla/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;sung&lt;/em&gt; yesterday as a pirate&lt;/a&gt;, that I was in the mood to sing, and a lot of people had been singing all evening, so I wanted to do that too. And it seemed that a voice would carry well over the conversations of the Dunkin&amp;rsquo; Donuts patrons. So I would sing the song, in Portuguese of course, and then switch into flute improvisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;a-lot-of-good-music-i-heard&#34;&gt;A lot of good music I heard&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was really impressed by the soulful performances of everyone who showed up to sing and play instruments. Really high quality stuff.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/j-jam-2012-10-28/3.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;I-forgot-her-name&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So I heard a lot of traditional songs and Klezmer (in fact, the &lt;a href=&#34;http://cmuklezmer.weebly.com/index.html&#34;&gt;CMU Klezmer Band&lt;/a&gt; was there). Not what I usually listen to or encounter, but it was really great soaking in the different kinds of music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When one of the CMU Klezmer Band guys, the clarinetist, passed out lyrics to a particularly popular song, I even sang along, stumbling through Yiddish for the first time in my life!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/j-jam-2012-10-28/4.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;CMU Klezmer Band waiting for turn&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.boulevardoftheallies.com/&#34;&gt;Joel&lt;/a&gt;, the J-Jam co-organizer who was handling the sound system throughout, performed one of his own compositions, and then one of his young guitar students performed along with him.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/j-jam-2012-10-28/7.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Joel and student&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;familiar-faces&#34;&gt;Familiar faces&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I saw a number of familiar people. In Pittsburgh, if you meet someone for the first time, it seems that there are already a lot of connections through other people you already know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Roz, whom &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/24/roaring-like-a-lion-on-a-saturday-morning/&#34;&gt;I last saw over a year ago when she was trying to sell accordions&lt;/a&gt; did some singing with the CMU Klezmer Band.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://betterfly.com/75586018&#34;&gt;Cindy Harris&lt;/a&gt;, who played autoharp so beautifully at &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/28/another-french-music-jam-also-announcing-cats-dance/&#34;&gt;one of the French music jams I&amp;rsquo;ve gone to&lt;/a&gt; did some solo pieces on autoharp:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/j-jam-2012-10-28/8.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Cindy Harris on autoharp&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At some point, Chuck from Pittsburgh recorder showed up. He wasn&amp;rsquo;t here to play, but came to watch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;abby-played-while-ben-and-i-figured-stuff-out&#34;&gt;Abby played while Ben and I figured stuff out&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Abby took her turn playing some pieces solo on tambura, Ben and I ducked to the back of the store for a minute so that we could agree on a tempo as well as have him sight read the chord progressions of &amp;ldquo;Chega de Saudade&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;ben-and-me&#34;&gt;Ben and me&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ben and I returned, and set up quickly (we were the last set for the night other than a guy who was going to play some solo violin to close).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I felt pretty awkward trying to sing &amp;ldquo;Chega de Saudade&amp;rdquo; for the first time in public, and in front of a microphone, while trying to read the Portuguese lyrics off a printout I had. (Note to self: I need to memorize these lyrics once and for all.) Ben and I had a go at it, and of course we made some mistakes, but that was expected. Then came time for me to grab my flute and improvise. Under pressure, I was less creative and accurate than I am when just improvising at home, unfortunately, but I&amp;rsquo;ll learn in time to deal with the difference in setting. Also, I botched up a place to return to, so there was confusion for a moment as Ben and I found a way to gracefully end somewhere!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;just-me&#34;&gt;Just me&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided to play one more piece, solo, that I thought I would do a lot better than the bossa nova experiment, so I got my Irish flute and chose spontaneously, while flipping through my binder, to play &amp;ldquo;Waltz in the House&amp;rdquo; by Emile Benoit. I love this beautiful song, and learned it half a year ago at my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/04/21/my-first-time-in-a-public-music-jam-intense-fun-with-chris-norman-and-david-greenberg/&#34;&gt;first public jam session&lt;/a&gt;, when I was playing on Baroque flute at the time. But of course, tonight I chose to play it on Irish flute, and I played it with the best feeling and sonority I had in me, having played it for my own pleasure and for my baby nephew many times, always with the inflections and ornamentations I feel at the moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People seemed to like this last piece I played. I also got a lot of comments afterwards on the beauty of the tone of my &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.caseyburnsflutes.com/&#34;&gt;wooden Irish flute&lt;/a&gt;; yes, it is a lovely instrument.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-next-j-jam&#34;&gt;The next J-Jam&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next J-Jam is already scheduled for Sunday, December 16. I hope Ben and I can come up with good stuff to play together, and with more preparation!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you love music and can make it to J-Jam, please come on over to Dunkin&amp;rsquo; Donuts in Squirrel Hill then! And if you would like to perform something, email Cantor Ben Rosner at the email address in the flyer below:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/j-jam-2012-10-28/flyer-for-2012-12-16.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Flyer for J-Jam 2012-12-16&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;next&#34;&gt;Next?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m still rather unsatisfied with my singing. I&amp;rsquo;m going to work hard on getting my singing into better shape. The next music jam I&amp;rsquo;m in, I absolutely plan to be ready to sing much better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for the jazz improvisation, that&amp;rsquo;s going to take me even longer to get to where I want it. That&amp;rsquo;s going to be a major project, since I have been living mostly in the classical music world lately. But I know for sure that jazz is one place I want to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I had a great time at our first J-Jam, both listening and performing! It&amp;rsquo;s a fantastic Squirrel Hill community event that I hope will continue regularly, and I&amp;rsquo;m grateful to Joel and Ben for organizing it and spreading the word to have people come over to listen and perform, and I was inspired by the wonderful performances by everyone who came to share their love of music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I look forward to participating again!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2012-12-16&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-12-16)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did not perform in or even attend &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.facebook.com/events/347798348651757/&#34;&gt;J-Jam on December 16&lt;/a&gt; after all! It quickly became clear in early December, after I met up with Ben to play together, that I was getting way too busy with many other things, and even if I hadn&amp;rsquo;t been, Ben himself was busy too, such that we had no opportunity to get together again anyway to work on something to play. Furthermore, the time conflicted with the monthly meeting of the Pittsburgh Recorder Society, which I hate to miss, so I did not even show up at J-Jam in December just to watch and listen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-02-10&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-02-10)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did not perform in the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/02/10/attending-j-jam-in-squirrel-hill-but-not-playing-music-in-it/&#34;&gt;February 2013 J-Jam&lt;/a&gt; either, but did attend.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Celebrating the birthday of John Coltrane, the Beethoven of jazz</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/09/23/celebrating-the-birthday-of-john-coltrane/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Sep 2012 00:44:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/09/23/celebrating-the-birthday-of-john-coltrane/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://userserve-ak.last.fm/serve/252/50664911.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;John Coltrane&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So today is the birthday of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Coltrane&#34;&gt;John Coltrane&lt;/a&gt; (1926-1967), a towering figure in the history of jazz like no other. Several years ago, in a moment of inspiration, I quipped to a friend that while it was clear to me that &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charlie_Parker&#34;&gt;Charlie Parker&lt;/a&gt; the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mozart&#34;&gt;Mozart&lt;/a&gt; of jazz, it was even more clear that Coltrane was the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beethoven&#34;&gt;Beethoven&lt;/a&gt; of jazz.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What did I mean by that remark? I meant it on philosophical, historical, and musical levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;mozart-to-beethoven-parker-to-coltrane&#34;&gt;Mozart to Beethoven; Parker to Coltrane&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mozart refined the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Classical_period_(music)&#34;&gt;Classical style&lt;/a&gt; inherited from Haydn and became a most admired practitioner of it; Mozart was accused (perhaps only fictionally) of writing &amp;ldquo;too many notes&amp;rdquo; in his music.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Beethoven started off in the Classical tradition and then went beyond that in his &amp;ldquo;middle&amp;rdquo; period, and then even further beyond that in his &amp;ldquo;late&amp;rdquo; period, to the point where he became completely unique and an existential challenge (to emulate or reject) to all future composers of Western art music.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Charlie Parker refined &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bebop&#34;&gt;bebop&lt;/a&gt; in jazz, which, among other things, involved packing in quite a lot of notes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Coltrane started off in the bebop tradition and then went beyond that along with Miles Davis and others, and then even further beyond that, to the point of challenging notions of what jazz even was or should be.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as I find Beethoven in his late period to be among the most sublime, yet most bizarre music of the entire history of Western art music, and was a hard act to follow, so too Coltrane. Just as many composers after Beethoven judged that he ruined Western art music permanently, so did many jazz musicians react in the same way toward Coltrane.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-coltrane-sampler&#34;&gt;A Coltrane sampler&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a lot of good music by Coltrane I could discuss for pages and pages. Look up popular examples such as &amp;ldquo;My Favorite Things&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;A Love Supreme&amp;rdquo;, for example. But for today, I celebrated not with those favorites (which I do love), but a different set:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;giant-steps-1960&#34;&gt;Giant Steps (1960)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Giant Steps&amp;rdquo; features some of the most amazing yet fluid improvisation I have ever encountered, and I love this video someone created to show transcribed notes. This is a classic that I never tire of listening to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/2kotK9FNEYU&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;vigil-1965&#34;&gt;Vigil (1965)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Vigil&amp;rdquo; is intense and even almost chaotic. It makes strange sense to me, a flow, an expression. I love it, although I don&amp;rsquo;t watch it very often; I have to be in the right mood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/5UHZaqG87N0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;ascension-1965&#34;&gt;Ascension (1965)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OK, &amp;ldquo;Ascension&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;makes no sense to me&lt;/em&gt;, and is not something I enjoy trying to listen to. You be the judge, but he lost me here. I&amp;rsquo;m just speaking the truth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/tgrQhBTDfhk&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-beethoven-sampler&#34;&gt;A Beethoven sampler&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For kicks, even though I&amp;rsquo;m not celebrating Beethoven today, here are examples of my favorite late Beethoven.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;diabelli-variations-http-en-wikipedia-org-wiki-diabelli-variations-1819&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Diabelli_Variations&#34;&gt;Diabelli Variations&lt;/a&gt; (1819)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Truly amazing set of theme and variations for the piano, taking the listener to alternate realities before returning back to earth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/wctoxElV8Os&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;große-fuge-http-en-wikipedia-org-wiki-gro-c3-9fe-fuge-1825&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gro%C3%9Fe_Fuge&#34;&gt;Große Fuge&lt;/a&gt; (1825)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nobody at this point in history was writing stuff like this. Beethoven just went wild and created this dissonant, difficult, and emotionally cathartic movement. Amazing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/XEZXjW_s0Qs&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>