<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Chris Norman on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/chris-norman/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Chris Norman on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/chris-norman/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Another exciting concert at Bar Marco: Chris Norman and the Chatham Baroque playing a tasty assortment of dynamic music</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/02/28/another-exciting-concert-at-bar-marco-chris-norman-and-the-chatham-baroque-playing-a-tasty-assortment-of-dynamic-music/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Feb 2013 23:47:52 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/02/28/another-exciting-concert-at-bar-marco-chris-norman-and-the-chatham-baroque-playing-a-tasty-assortment-of-dynamic-music/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Just this week, Annie of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/PittsburghRecorderSociety&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Recorder Society&lt;/a&gt; sent out email reminding us of upcoming musical performances of interest, including some by the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.chathambaroque.org/&#34;&gt;Chatham Baroque&lt;/a&gt; joined by visiting &lt;a href=&#34;http://chrisnorman.com/&#34;&gt;Chris Norman&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://chrisnorman.com/images/home_feature.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Chris Norman&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When I heard that Chris Norman was coming, I frantically started rethinking my schedule for the week, because I really wanted to see him playing his wooden flutes. He has been one of my primary musical heroes since I first encountered him at a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/04/21/my-first-time-in-a-public-music-jam-intense-fun-with-chris-norman-and-david-greenberg/&#34;&gt;public music jam session last year&lt;/a&gt; sponsored by the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rbsp.org/&#34;&gt;Renaissance and Baroque of Pittsburgh&lt;/a&gt;. That day was one of the most important days of my life, which I will never forget, because not only did I see and hear a real master, but also was encouraged to participate myself in playing music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve always also been a big fan of Chatham Baroque, for their lively, alert performances of the standard repertoire as well as &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/10/04/chatham-baroque-thoughts-on-playing-new-non-baroque-music-on-baroque-instruments/&#34;&gt;new collaborations and projects&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I managed to attend one of this week&amp;rsquo;s concerts, and I was not disappointed!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-i-rarely-attend-concerts&#34;&gt;Why I rarely attend concerts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, a reminder: nowadays, I rarely attend concerts (or even listen to recorded music). &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/02/i-love-music-but-rarely-listen-to-it-now/&#34;&gt;I explained why over a year ago&lt;/a&gt;: time is limited (on weekdays and particularly on weekends). Furthermore, when I do attend concerts, I am much pickier about what I attend, because when I think about it, in the past I have often been disappointed by concerts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;bar-marco-and-nature-of-music-venues&#34;&gt;Bar Marco and nature of music venues&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing I came to realize is that the standard &amp;ldquo;classical music&amp;rdquo; concert is not to my taste. First of all, the programs tend to be very long, such as two hours with an intermission, which, frankly, taxes both my attention span as well as takes up an entire block of time in an evening. Second, and most important actually, is that there is a sense of &amp;ldquo;distance&amp;rdquo; and even formality in the standard concert. This is reinforced by certain choices of clothing and demeanor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: I&amp;rsquo;m speaking as one who did not grow up in &amp;ldquo;classical music&amp;rdquo; culture, but only really discovered and fell in love with Western art music upon &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/10/rip-charles-rosen/&#34;&gt;attending college&lt;/a&gt;. So there have always been things about the culture that initially struck me as strange, and are probably at least partially responsible for the relative lack of popularity of the music among younger people (just peek into the average classical music concert hall and you&amp;rsquo;ll see geezers and middle-aged people).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I rather enjoyed the use of Bar Marco last fall as non-traditional music venue, where &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/11/14/classical-revolution-pittsburghs-aquitango-delivers-passionate-traditional-tango/&#34;&gt;I saw AquiTango performing, and sat up close&lt;/a&gt; and enjoyed the relative intimacy and informality of the occasion. Not only that, but from a technical, performance point of view (now that I play music myself), it is extremely educational for me to be up front seeing what the musicians do and relating to it and learning from it, whether it&amp;rsquo;s cues and signals among them or details of physical technique. This is stuff you can&amp;rsquo;t get sitting far away in a big concert hall, and you certainly can&amp;rsquo;t get at all from audio recordings or even videos really. You have to be there, anticipating, thinking actively, hearing the breaths, seeing the faces, in real time. Music is not just sound, not just wave forms or digital bits. It&amp;rsquo;s a live, active creation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I jumped at the opportunity to see &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.showclix.com/event/3745641&#34;&gt;Chris Norman and Chatham Baroque also at Bar Marco&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This venue has its limitations, of course. Primarily, the bar downstairs is very noisy, and it would be nice if there were a barrier to avoid the noise and music blasting downstairs from so easily being heard upstairs. That said, for the most part I wasn&amp;rsquo;t too bothered by the noise, because I sat up front very near the musicians, and so when they were playing, I didn&amp;rsquo;t hear the noise. But in moments of dead silence the distraction was real. I would suggest putting up a temporary barrier at the stairway during performances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-music&#34;&gt;The music&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A single hour of musical selections was presented (a good length for me; as I mentioned earlier, two hours is a very long time).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;scottish-baroque-james-osvald&#34;&gt;Scottish Baroque: James Osvald&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The concert started out with a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scottish_Baroque_music&#34;&gt;Scottish Baroque&lt;/a&gt; sonata by &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_Oswald_%28composer%29&#34;&gt;James Osvald&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was interested to actually see Scottish Baroque music being performed live because up till now, I had only &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/08/finally-performing-some-sonatas-for-baroque-flute/&#34;&gt;played it without listening to it, through a &amp;ldquo;Baroque Around the World&amp;rdquo; series of books&lt;/a&gt;. And I had played it on flute, even though the music was clearly geared toward violin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;instruments&#34;&gt;Instruments&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chris played the same keyed wooden &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.oldflutes.com/classical.htm&#34;&gt;classical flute&lt;/a&gt; for the most part through the concert, although in the slow movement of just this sonata he switched to a deeper alto flute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout the concert, Andrew Fouts played Baroque violin, while Patrician Halverson played different sizes of viola da gamba, and Scott Pauley played theorbo as well as a banjo and a Baroque guitar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;no-program-notes&#34;&gt;No program notes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were no program notes for this concert, by the way: &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/11/on-not-reading-concert-program-notes/&#34;&gt;just how I like it&lt;/a&gt;! Instead, Chris introduced each piece before he and Chatham Baroque performed it. I liked how he added colorful and humorous touches to his brief introductions. &lt;em&gt;All concerts should work this way&lt;/em&gt;. Long program notes are as pointless, in my opinion, as voluminous printed slides at a lecture: they are only a distraction from the presentation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;american-old-time-music&#34;&gt;American old-time music&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then they switched things up and played some American &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Old-time_music&#34;&gt;old-time music&lt;/a&gt;, including &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Man_of_Constant_Sorrow&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Man of Constant Sorrow&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. It was interesting hearing Baroque instruments used for this kind of music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chris was really in his element playing this folk music. He became very expressive and walked around and stamped his feet. You can&amp;rsquo;t experience this kind of concentration and passion just sitting at home listening to some CD or music file: you had to be there, up front! This is what I want to live when I attend a concert.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;back-to-scottish-baroque-william-mcgibbon&#34;&gt;Back to Scottish Baroque: William McGibbon&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another name familiar to me (because of having played on flute one of his sonatas) came up, the Scottish Baroque composer &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_McGibbon&#34;&gt;William McGibbon&lt;/a&gt;. Apparently the composer was inspired by the Italian style and incorporated into his piece, a sonata in the style of Corelli. I think it&amp;rsquo;s important to remember that even back in the 18th century, musicians were eager to learn from their counterparts in remote places in the world. Think of how much effort it took to visit or get word of what was going on in Italy, from Scotland!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;maritime-canada&#34;&gt;Maritime Canada&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then we entered the world of Chris&amp;rsquo;s own heritage: he is from &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Music_of_the_Maritimes&#34;&gt;Maritime Canada&lt;/a&gt;. He did some singing in French as well as flute playing. It was the first time I had ever heard him sing, and it sounded similar to Cajun singing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;back-to-osvald&#34;&gt;Back to Osvald&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then we returned to Osvald, for the &amp;ldquo;Hawthorn&amp;rdquo; sonata. I was very curious to hear this because I had never heard it played, but had &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/08/finally-performing-some-sonatas-for-baroque-flute/&#34;&gt;played it myself on Baroque flute with Henry on piano&lt;/a&gt;, and run into problems because it was clearly meant for violin, given the crazy fast jig movement at the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that Chris took a break and sat out most of this sonata, ha! I enjoyed the opportunity to observe how Andrew on Baroque violin would play the first movement, to compare his style and choice of ornamentations with what I&amp;rsquo;ve done myself. He played it rather differently than how I play it. This is one of the fascinating things I like about Baroque music: there is a good deal of personal choice in how we feel and interpret it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To my amusement, Chris did come in for the brief but crazy fast jig that was the third movement, showing off his triple-tonguing chops on flute. Whew!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;scottish-smallpipes&#34;&gt;Scottish smallpipes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We ended with Chris pulling out his &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scottish_smallpipes&#34;&gt;Scottish smallpipes&lt;/a&gt; and playing on them. I had never seen this instrument before and was fascinated. In contrast to mouth-blown bagpipes, these are played with the arms only. A vigorous conclusion to the concert!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;afterwards&#34;&gt;Afterwards&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I chatted with Chris Norman a little afterwards. He seemed to recognize me from the jam session a year ago; that surprised me since I was just some quiet guy in the crowd who was still quite a beginner and didn&amp;rsquo;t play all that much. Anyway, I told him I was inspired by that jam session to not only play more traditional music of the kind that he plays (I got into Irish and French, buying myself an &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/irish-flute/&#34;&gt;Irish flute&lt;/a&gt;), but also improving my technique considerably on &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/baroque-flute/&#34;&gt;Baroque flute&lt;/a&gt;. I asked him about his new work on making wooden flutes; I thought it was really cool that he not only plays them, but now makes them too, and why not, if you&amp;rsquo;re interested in the engineering aspects of creating the kind of sounds you want? This utter physicality of (non-digital) music is something that I&amp;rsquo;ve come to particularly appreciate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a really great time at the concert at Bar Marco by Chris Norman and Chatham Baroque. I left inspired again to continue my own music-making and improve on it and incorporate my own personality into it, the way these fine musicians do. It was an hour well-spent.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My first time in a public music jam: intense fun with Chris Norman and David Greenberg</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/04/21/my-first-time-in-a-public-music-jam-intense-fun-with-chris-norman-and-david-greenberg/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Apr 2012 13:44:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/04/21/my-first-time-in-a-public-music-jam-intense-fun-with-chris-norman-and-david-greenberg/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://fbcdn-sphotos-a.akamaihd.net/hphotos-ak-ash3/544714_10150682065771513_55075526512_9775036_876594193_n.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;David Greenberg and Chris Norman and the rest of us&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Friday evening, Abby and I packed up various musical instruments of ours, and attended an event that I had been eagerly awaiting for over three weeks since I first found out about it from Annie of the local &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.andrew.cmu.edu/user/lukas/pcars/Welcome.html&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh recorder gang&lt;/a&gt;: a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rbsp.org/Jam%20Session%20Flyer.pdf&#34;&gt;jam session open to the public&lt;/a&gt; being offered by &lt;a href=&#34;http://chrisnorman.com/&#34;&gt;Chris Norman&lt;/a&gt;, flutist, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.davidgreenberg.ca/&#34;&gt;David Greenberg&lt;/a&gt;, violinist the day before &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rbsp.org/11-12c6.aspx&#34;&gt;their concert&lt;/a&gt; the next evening to close the current season of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rbsp.org/&#34;&gt;Renaissance and Baroque of Pittsburgh&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was so excited by this opportunity to jam with such esteemed musicians. Norman and Greenberg specialize in playing Irish, Scottish, Cape Breton and Baroque music. I&amp;rsquo;ve come to love playing the rhythmic, danceable music of the old days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I learned a lot from the experience, and would like to share what I learned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;some-photos-of-the-event&#34;&gt;Some photos of the event&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/pages/Pittsburgh-Renaissance-and-Baroque/55075526512&#34;&gt;Facebook page of the Pittsburgh Renaissance and Baroque&lt;/a&gt; has a bunch of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/media/set/?set=a.10150682065546513.394216.55075526512&amp;amp;type=3&#34;&gt;photos of the event&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;ve used a couple of these here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;preparation&#34;&gt;Preparation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;my-instruments&#34;&gt;My instruments&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been spending most of my daily music practice all year working on the modern &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/flute/&#34;&gt;flute&lt;/a&gt;; I have not reported on my progress in over a month because I&amp;rsquo;ve been too busy &lt;em&gt;doing&lt;/em&gt; rather than &lt;em&gt;writing&lt;/em&gt;, but will catch up with the writing sometime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But for this jam session, I had decided very quickly that I was &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; going to be bringing my modern flute to play, because I do prefer to play older music on other instruments; I planned to bring the following instruments instead:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;my &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/tin-whistle/&#34;&gt;tin whistle&lt;/a&gt;, which I bought the week of St. Patrick&amp;rsquo;s Day in March (for a party I haven&amp;rsquo;t written about yet but which radically changed my life)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;an assortment of &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/recorder/&#34;&gt;recorders&lt;/a&gt;: I decided to just bring my soprano and alto&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;my &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/baroque-flute/&#34;&gt;Baroque flute&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, interspersed with my continuing work on the modern flute, I have also done some maintenance practice of tin whistle and recorders. The most difficult challenge was trying to get serious about Baroque flute: the one-keyed flute is &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.oldflutes.com/charts/onekey/index.htm&#34;&gt;very, very, very tricky to play in tune&lt;/a&gt;. Sometimes I wonder whether it&amp;rsquo;s worth the bother. But I tend to be inspired by quirky challenges whose benefit I don&amp;rsquo;t fully understand immediately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ideally, I would own an &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.caseyburnsflutes.com/cat_d.php&#34;&gt;Irish flute&lt;/a&gt;, preferably with a number of keys to aid with intonation and fingering, but given that I don&amp;rsquo;t currently intend to specialize in Irish music, and am still working with the tin whistle anyway, I cannot at all justify buying an Irish flute at this time. So I&amp;rsquo;ve been working on using the related Baroque flute instead, for traditional Irish or Scottish music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;abby-s-instruments&#34;&gt;Abby&amp;rsquo;s instruments&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby started learning mandolin just this year, joining the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pittsburghmandolinsociety.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Mandolin Orchestra&lt;/a&gt;, so I was excited that she decided early on to bring it to the jam session. (And I look forward to seeing her play for the first time in the orchestra&amp;rsquo;s concert on Mother&amp;rsquo;s Day coming up in three weeks!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She also brought a frame drum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-event&#34;&gt;The event!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;arrival&#34;&gt;Arrival&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I arrived a little late, so I scrambled to get ready while a whole bunch of people were already gathered. Many people were sitting in back just to watch and listen, while maybe twenty of us were armed with instruments of all kinds, ready to have some fun!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://fbcdn-sphotos-a.akamaihd.net/hphotos-ak-prn1/541085_10150682067126513_55075526512_9775042_292845062_n.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;We played lots of different instruments&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We ran into half a dozen people we knew from various of our musical circles, including Annie from recorder, a guy Abby knew from mandolin, and some fellow &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/16/playing-recorder-and-flute-at-the-holiday-ball/&#34;&gt;Holiday Ball&lt;/a&gt; musicians.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was intrigued by the couple of people who had actual keyed Irish flutes and eager to hear them play (it would turn out, of course, that they were very, very good).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;music-scores&#34;&gt;Music scores&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So each of us got a packet of around twenty pages of music. We didn&amp;rsquo;t play all of it, of course, but it was a good basis for sight reading along with Chris and David leading the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much of the music went at breakneck pace that I&amp;rsquo;m still not proficient enough to sight reading perfectly, but my (yet unreported) musical adventures in the past month have made me far less self-conscious about perfection and figure out ways to cope:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it&amp;rsquo;s not necessary to play all the notes; in fast music, you can contribute just fine playing only one main note per measure or harmony change&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;you can also substitute a different, easier melodic line that is compatible with the chords&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;since sections are repeated many times, you can add more during repetitions as you feel ready to&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it&amp;rsquo;s not the end of the world to miscalculate sometimes and squeak out a harsh dissonant error; the music just keeps going, so don&amp;rsquo;t look back, only forward&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;learning-by-ear-improvisation&#34;&gt;Learning by ear, improvisation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I expected, much of the time we didn&amp;rsquo;t play music from the handed out scores at all. This was the fun I was anticipating all along (I had not really expected music scores at all, actually).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost half the time, Chris would ask us for music suggestions to offer up &lt;em&gt;by example&lt;/em&gt;, so that the volunteer would play (or sing) the melody, then the rest of us would start &amp;ldquo;learning&amp;rdquo; it by ear and join in and continue with repetitions. I had not anticipated the call for volunteers, else I would have come prepared with some favorite tunes to offer!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some people were more familiar with various tunes being offered up than I was, since they had a lot more experience with Irish, Scottish and other such music than me, so I felt awkward and lost trying to learn and play on the spot, without written music, but it was part of the whole fun, really stretching what I have usually been doing with music (very oriented toward following a written score).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve mentioned before my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/10/flute-loving-it-again/&#34;&gt;poor memory&lt;/a&gt; having a considerable impact on my life, and I worked around it again, given that I could not quickly learn the details of a melody, by just giving up and improvising around the harmony changes instead. I would like to find ways to improve my memory, but for now, I work around my limitations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;a-charming-tangent-involving-an-oboe&#34;&gt;A charming tangent involving an oboe&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it turned out that a young woman among us had come with a Baroque oboe tuned to A415 instead of the modern A440 tuning. This caused confusion, of course, when she tried to play from written scores. I&amp;rsquo;m not sure what she ended up doing: the only choices were to mentally transpose from the written scores (when we were playing music from them) or just ignore the scores and learn by ear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, Chris and David repeatedly wanted to play with her and asked her what music she had on her, and she had a variety of Baroque music scores with her (she said she was actually giving a recital the next day), and so they tried to play some stuff just with her while doing their own mental transposition so that she would get to play without mental transposition! Check out Chris hovering over the score trying to do the really hard work of transposing on the fly:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://fbcdn-sphotos-a.akamaihd.net/hphotos-ak-ash4/s720x720/295215_10150682067841513_395463764_n.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Baroque oboist with Chris and David&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;dancing&#34;&gt;Dancing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Periodically, a number of people got up to dance in the space at the side, especially when we played waltzes. It was nice to see people moving.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://fbcdn-sphotos-a.akamaihd.net/hphotos-ak-ash3/529154_10150682066471513_55075526512_9775039_758574985_n.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;A couple dancing&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;i-m-caught-on-a-photo-playing-baroque-flute&#34;&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m caught on a photo playing Baroque flute&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spent a fair amount of time playing the tin whistle, and some time on my recorders, but in the end gravitated toward the Baroque flute because it was mellower and I could draw less attention to my mistakes by playing it instead!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that a photo was taken that included me when I was playing my Baroque flute. In this photo, you can also see a guy playing tin whistle (this guy also at one point volunteered to sing a tune, and did so with quite a powerful voice, a great rendition).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://fbcdn-sphotos-a.akamaihd.net/hphotos-ak-ash2/35507_10150682067581513_55075526512_9775044_1738151368_n.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;A fellow tin whistle player, and me on Baroque flute&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My posture is really bad here. I need to sit up straight and keep my head over my body rather than straining over my neck. My only excuse is that this photo was probably taken two hours into the jam session when it was almost over, and I was having energy issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-note-on-energy-requirements&#34;&gt;A note on energy requirements&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was totally exhausted after the jam session. After Abby and I drove back home, we both had to eat something. We were starving. We should have taken a snack break at the jam session.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I weighed myself and I had lost weight. The mental demands on me were considerable, and I had really spent myself. Given that I have lost weight before when taking exams in school, or playing in chess tournaments, or doing similar activities that combine both mental demands and personal anxiety, I should have been better prepared with fuel at the event. I get the impression that I burn more energy by thinking hard than by running.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was my first time ever at a public music jam session, and I quite enjoyed it. I am grateful to Chris Norman and David Greenberg, and the Pittsburgh Renaissance and Baroque, for providing it to the community. I am always very happy for opportunities to play music with Abby, and keep remembering how she got me into this particular early traditional dance music world, through our first musical time together at the Holiday Ball.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got self-feedback about musical shortcomings for me to keep working on in order to enjoy future jam sessions, and I learned that I really need food to keep me fueled for optimal musicality!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>