<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>University Of Pittsburgh on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/university-of-pittsburgh/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in University Of Pittsburgh on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/university-of-pittsburgh/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Neil Newton on the harmonic structure of atonal music</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/11/neil-newton-on-the-harmonic-structure-of-atonal-music/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2013 21:01:43 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/11/neil-newton-on-the-harmonic-structure-of-atonal-music/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.music.pitt.edu/sites/default/files/story-images/neil_newton-600.jpg?1401301354&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I attended a fascinating and illuminating lecture by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.music.pitt.edu/faculty/newton&#34;&gt;Neil Newton&lt;/a&gt; at the University of Pittsburgh with the title &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.music.pitt.edu/events/lecture-neil-newton-university-pitt130925&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;The Inner Life of Harmonies: An Examination of the Middle Voice in Pop, Classical, and Early Post-Tonal Music&lt;/em&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The big question I&amp;rsquo;ve sometimes asked myself is, what is &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Atonality&#34;&gt;atonal&lt;/a&gt; music anyway? How do we make sense of it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neil Newton provided what seemed to me an interesting explanation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;atonal-music-is-not-random-but-has-order&#34;&gt;Atonal music is not random but has order!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m very interested in &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Atonality&#34;&gt;atonal&lt;/a&gt; music because of how, when successful, when I enjoy it and it somehow &amp;ldquo;makes sense&amp;rdquo; (which it does not always), it falls between the boundaries of order and chaos, like a dream. Also, I should emphasize that I like to make a clear distinction between truly atonal music and the serial (&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Twelve-tone_technique&#34;&gt;twelve-tone&lt;/a&gt;) music that Schönberg invented after he became dissatisfied with his atonal experiments. Serial music, unlike atonal music, is very strictly organized through a mathematical system; atonal music was its &amp;ldquo;freer&amp;rdquo; predecessor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t listen much to atonal music, but there is some atonal music &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/25/thank-you-glenn-gould/&#34;&gt;I have mentioned enjoying, by Schönberg&lt;/a&gt;. So it was with great interest that I attended this lecture trying to explain how atonal music can be understood not as being devoid of traditional harmonic relationships, but rather as embodying a different kind of relationship, a different kind of order. It is not random or chaotic, just ordered differently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;substitution-of-a-different-kind-of-order&#34;&gt;Substitution of a different kind of order&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main idea Newton explored was that of finding a replacement for the dominant-tonic relationship that is key in tonal music for &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tension_%28music%29&#34;&gt;tension&lt;/a&gt; and resolution&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;charge and discharge&amp;rdquo; (his preferred terminology). For example, he argues that the interval of a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tritone&#34;&gt;tritone&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;code&gt;ic6&lt;/code&gt;) in conjunction with &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Voice_leading&#34;&gt;voice leading&lt;/a&gt; can be used to generate functional movement and therefore build up structural significance that is analogous to the kind of structure significance that exists in tonal music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Particularly interesting to me was how Newton used statistical analysis to look for correlations and patterns in the music he studied and justify his thesis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, he unifies his ideas with application to other &amp;ldquo;weird&amp;rdquo; musical phenomenon, such as that found in many pop and rock songs that violate the traditional tonal system. (The music of the Beatles, for example, was quite marked in its oddity.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For details, check out Newton&amp;rsquo;s paper, &lt;a href=&#34;http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/musa.12018/abstract&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;An Aspect of Functional Harmony in Schoenberg&amp;rsquo;s Early Post-Tonal Music&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. I don&amp;rsquo;t pretend to understand more than a fraction of what he tries to show, since I am just an amateur musician, not a trained theorist, but the overview and audio examples he gave in his lecture gave me a glimpse of what he&amp;rsquo;s doing, and I was happy to have attended.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2014-05-28&#34;&gt;(Update of 2014-05-28)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Pitt music department blog &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.music.pitt.edu/blog/neil-newton-schoenberg140528&#34;&gt;just mentioned Newton&amp;rsquo;s work&lt;/a&gt; and provided a link to an &lt;a href=&#34;http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/enhanced/doi/10.1111/musa.12018/&#34;&gt;enhanced HTML version of his paper&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it&amp;rsquo;s great that serious work continues in trying to understand what lies underneath music that we intuitively enjoy but find odd because it doesn&amp;rsquo;t obey the usual expectations of traditional tonality.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Attending the annual Pitt Jazz Seminar for the first time: day 2</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/11/03/attending-the-annual-pitt-jazz-seminar-for-the-first-time/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Nov 2012 20:52:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/11/03/attending-the-annual-pitt-jazz-seminar-for-the-first-time/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.music.pitt.edu/sites/default/files/jazz-2012-cropped.jpg?1350921512&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;42nd Pitt Jazz Seminar poster&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/11/02/attending-the-annual-pitt-jazz-seminar-for-the-first-time-day-1/&#34;&gt;Yesterday&lt;/a&gt;, I attended some morning sessions of the annual Pitt Jazz Seminar. I went back for more today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-tribute-to-miles&#34;&gt;A tribute to Miles&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;randy-brecker-http-randybrecker-com-trumpet&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://randybrecker.com/&#34;&gt;Randy Brecker&lt;/a&gt;, trumpet&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I liked how Randy Brecker talked about how he got into music. He listened to a lot of records as a kid, and at some point he started improvising during piano solos, by ear. He started with ballads (by Miles, Chet, etc.) and played with his brother &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.michaelbrecker.com/&#34;&gt;Michael&lt;/a&gt; (who sadly died some years ago).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;lew-soloff-http-www-lewsoloff-com-trumpet&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lewsoloff.com/&#34;&gt;Lew Soloff&lt;/a&gt;, trumpet&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lew Soloff came from a very different world. He stopped piano lessons at ten because his teachers did not emphasize &lt;em&gt;music&lt;/em&gt;, but &amp;ldquo;holding the hand a certain way&amp;rdquo;. He wanted trumpet because it was &lt;em&gt;shiny&lt;/em&gt;. Ha! Reminded me that it doesn&amp;rsquo;t matter why you start doing something; often you have a perhaps superficial reason, and find deeper reasons later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His uncle emphasized the importance of &lt;em&gt;practice&lt;/em&gt; and admonished him for being interested in too many things. Some tips on mental attitudes: never say &amp;ldquo;I can&amp;rsquo;t&amp;rdquo;, and also drop your &lt;em&gt;ego&lt;/em&gt;: learn from your peers. So in one summer, he went from last chair to first chair, practicing one and a half hours each day!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lew had a classical music training and therefore at first was scared to improvise. He had to overcome that fear. He also had to learn to articulate in &amp;ldquo;doodle tongue&amp;rdquo; rather than in the classical way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He said he eventually became open to all kinds of music, where in the past he was closed. He has a different take than Duke Ellington&amp;rsquo;s famous quote, &amp;ldquo;There are two kinds of music, good music and the other kind&amp;rdquo;: instead, Lew likes to think that the two kinds are the &lt;em&gt;honest&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;dishonest&lt;/em&gt;. I like this formulation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Randy piped in saying that he became musically open because that was just the way things were in Philadelphia, where there are so many styles.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Advice: when learning ballads, first play them &lt;em&gt;without&lt;/em&gt; improvisation, focusing on purity and honesty, and expressing emotion as though singing. Learn the lyrics and understand them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;artistry-in-rhythm-winard-harper-http-www-winardharper-com-drums&#34;&gt;Artistry in rhythm: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.winardharper.com/&#34;&gt;Winard Harper&lt;/a&gt;, drums&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Winard Harper spoke of coming from a musical family and playing at clubs by the time he was five years old. He emphasized the importance of relationships in making music come together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He&amp;rsquo;s really into an African instrument that I never heard of before called a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Balafon&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;balafon&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. More generally, he is interested in all kinds of world music, whether from Africa, Australia, Japan. He urged everyone to honor tradition, learn history, and do a lot of playing and listening. &amp;ldquo;The more you know, the more you can use&amp;rdquo;. He summed up with the message that as a drummer, when jamming, you have to face all kinds of situations, drums that are not yours, etc., and you have to learn to deal, because it&amp;rsquo;s not about you but about music. Sounds wise no matter what instrument we play!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-piano-in-jazz-george-cables-http-georgecables-com&#34;&gt;The piano in jazz: &lt;a href=&#34;http://georgecables.com/&#34;&gt;George Cables&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;George Cables emphasized that jazz is living music, through which everyone can become a &amp;ldquo;co-composer&amp;rdquo; through arranging and improvising.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a pianist, he didn&amp;rsquo;t want to be a soloist so much as a good side man. He was most inspired by Wynton Kelly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Musically, he emphasized that the piano is a percussion instrument. He also gave a history lesson on the piano in jazz, starting from Scott Joplin and moving forward from there. He said the progression was toward &amp;ldquo;freeing the bass&amp;rdquo;, allowing the left hand to do a lot more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(I had to leave this session a little early because I wanted to make it to a special recorder concert elsewhere in town.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found it very interesting and useful attending Pitt Jazz Seminar sessions these past two days, featuring very different musicians on different instruments, getting a broad perspective on how they operate and what they value and what they have to teach. I hope to continue attending this annual event!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Attending the annual Pitt Jazz Seminar for the first time: day 1</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/11/02/attending-the-annual-pitt-jazz-seminar-for-the-first-time-day-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Nov 2012 23:53:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/11/02/attending-the-annual-pitt-jazz-seminar-for-the-first-time-day-1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.music.pitt.edu/sites/default/files/jazz-2012-cropped.jpg?1350921512&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;42nd Pitt Jazz Seminar poster&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This year I decided to attend events of the 42nd annual &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.music.pitt.edu/events/november-3-2012-42nd-annual-jazz-se120813&#34;&gt;Pitt Jazz Seminar&lt;/a&gt; for the first time. I&amp;rsquo;ve never had any instruction in jazz, and frankly have only a little bit of experience trying to play it myself, so I enjoyed the opportunity to attend presentations by great performers who could talk about what they do, where they&amp;rsquo;ve come from, and demonstrate their craft.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went in to Pitt campus on a Friday morning to learn from some master musicians.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;yotam-silbertein-http-yotammusic-com-guitar&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://yotammusic.com/&#34;&gt;Yotam Silbertein&lt;/a&gt;, guitar&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought it was interesting that an Israeli musician, Yotam Silbertein, kicked off the morning of seminars. Of course, as he emphasized in his talk, jazz is an international phenomenon. It happens in Israel, it happens in Japan, it happens in Europe. It may have started off in the United States, but it is everywhere now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, he did eventually have to head to New York, the place to be. He even speaks English with a New York style accent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He emphasized that it&amp;rsquo;s necessary to go where the action is and learn from the best.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;javon-jackson-http-www-javonjackson-com-tenor-saxophone&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.javonjackson.com/&#34;&gt;Javon Jackson&lt;/a&gt;, tenor saxophone&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Javon Jackson spoke a lot about being a professional in music: how you behave, how you work with others, and develop a career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, he pointed out that he wears a suit because it projects a professional image.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;that-s-it-for-the-day&#34;&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s it for the day&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was another session later in the afternoon, but I skipped it because I needed to return to work.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>