<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Ludwig Van Beethoven on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/ludwig-van-beethoven/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Ludwig Van Beethoven on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/ludwig-van-beethoven/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Discovering the beautiful keyboard playing of Robert Hill by accident on YouTube changed my life</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/08/21/discovering-the-beautiful-keyboard-playing-of-robert-hill-by-accident-on-youtube-changed-my-life/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2014 22:14:23 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/08/21/discovering-the-beautiful-keyboard-playing-of-robert-hill-by-accident-on-youtube-changed-my-life/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.mh-freiburg.de/typo3temp/_processed_/csm_prof.-dr.-robert-hill_c7981b16bc.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Robert Hill&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Recently, I completely accidentally discovered a fascinating musician, &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Hill_%28musician%29&#34;&gt;Robert Hill&lt;/a&gt;, on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/user/earlymus&#34;&gt;YouTube&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story is as you might expect: I heard a piece of music, and wanted to find some performance of it by somebody, anybody on YouTube as long as it had a decent user rating (yes, I find ratings actually useful when checking out unfamiliar music), and I happened to come across some random guy&amp;rsquo;s performance, and it was so fascinating that I looked at other uploads of his, subscribed to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/user/earlymus&#34;&gt;his YouTube channel&lt;/a&gt;, and looked him up on the Web to find out who he was!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s especially great that he regularly uploads new videos to his YouTube channel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So who is Robert Hill, and why do I like his performances so much that I&amp;rsquo;m recommending that you check them out?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-i-found-robert-hill&#34;&gt;How I found Robert Hill&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The short story is that I just heard someone playing, on piano, Johann Sebastian Bach&amp;rsquo;s Allemande from the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/French_Suites_%28Bach%29&#34;&gt;French Suite&lt;/a&gt; no. 4 in E-flat, BWV 815.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note that I actually have had very little interest in much of Bach&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Works_for_keyboard_by_J.S._Bach&#34;&gt;keyboard music&lt;/a&gt; and have almost completely ignored them for decades&lt;/em&gt;; there are only two exceptions: the Goldberg Variations and some of the Well-Tempered Clavier.  In particular, I have not listened to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/French_Suites_%28Bach%29&#34;&gt;French Suites&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/English_Suites_%28Bach%29&#34;&gt;English Suites&lt;/a&gt;, or &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Partitas_for_keyboard_%28Bach%29&#34;&gt;Partitas&lt;/a&gt; at all!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But because I just accidentally heard this Allemande played live, and liked it, I wanted to hear it again when I got home, and so I went to YouTube to find it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found a lot of performances online, of course, but I&amp;rsquo;m a sucker for the unusual, so I was particularly interested when I saw in the search results a link to some guy, Robert Hill, performing it on an unusual instrument I had never heard of in my life, a &amp;ldquo;lute-harpsichord&amp;rdquo;. And it got well over a hundred thumb-up ratings and only one thumb-down, so of course I was going to check it out!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I watched the video, and was &lt;em&gt;totally blown away&lt;/em&gt; by the beauty of the performance:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The instrument has a gorgeous sound.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Robert Hill played very expressively, with the full freedom and emotion that treasure.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Structurally, I could hear the different voices and phrases with total clarity because of how he plays.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This single performance made me think that I needed to give old Bach another shot and check out more of his keyboard music.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Listen for yourself (it&amp;rsquo;s less than two minutes long):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/woh8UHdjl1M&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;who-is-robert-hill&#34;&gt;Who is Robert Hill?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did a Web search on Robert Hill and found &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Hill_%28musician%29&#34;&gt;information about him&lt;/a&gt;. He is an American keyboard instrument performer (especially early keyboard instruments such as harpsichord, clavichord, lute-harpsichord, fortepiano) and musicologist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had to search hard to find an actual Web site of his own, and it&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://robert-hill.tripod.com/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. It basically looks like it hasn&amp;rsquo;t been updated since around 2001, which is also his last recording time period on his &lt;a href=&#34;http://robert-hill.tripod.com/id11.html&#34;&gt;discography&lt;/a&gt;. At some point he must have decided to just share his music through YouTube. He is a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mh-freiburg.de/lehrende/person/details/hill/&#34;&gt;music professor in Freiburg&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I just mentioned, my fascination with the performances of Robert Hill comes from his &lt;em&gt;expressiveness&lt;/em&gt;, which comes about from adjustments of tempo, rhetorical gestures, ornamentation, rhythmic sense. He plays a lot more expressively than many keyboard musicians do today, and I like that. I now believe that I was turned off by much of Bach&amp;rsquo;s keyboard music not because of Bach, but because of the relatively bland performances his music has received, especially from modern pianists. Bach was an emotional man living in an emotional age (the Baroque era of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Doctrine_of_the_affections&#34;&gt;affect&lt;/a&gt;), and I feel blessed that musicians like Robert Hill are taking this seriously. There are others, of course, besides him, but I think his performances have a particular edge to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;regular-harpsichord&#34;&gt;Regular harpsichord&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is an example of Robert Hill playing regular harpsichord.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;bach-s-allemande-from-the-partita-in-d-major-bwv-828&#34;&gt;Bach&amp;rsquo;s Allemande from the Partita in D major, BWV 828&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I discovered this beautiful, haunting work of music by Bach for the first time, by sheer accident, when browsing Hill&amp;rsquo;s YouTube channel (live performance from 1997):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/oEoqPSFklkE&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I cannot believe I went four decades without ever having heard this piece in my life. Now I can&amp;rsquo;t get it out of my head.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hill did some extreme things in this performance (tempo modifications and hesitations) that are not to my taste, but I applaud him for having the courage to play from the heart, because much of what he did spoke to mine! He lives dangerously. Maybe that&amp;rsquo;s why he only posts live recording clips to YouTube now rather than make CDs?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;fortepiano&#34;&gt;Fortepiano&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He also plays fortepiano, which is a fascinating instrument I love. I have mentioned my first experience with a fortepiano in college in a blog post earlier this year celebrating the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/03/08/happy-300th-birthday-carl-philipp-emanuel-bach/&#34;&gt;300th birthday of Johann Sebastian&amp;rsquo;s son Carl Philipp Emanuel&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;cpe-bach-s-fantasie-in-f-sharp-minor&#34;&gt;CPE Bach&amp;rsquo;s Fantasie in F-sharp minor&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heck, I had to check out Hill&amp;rsquo;s performance of my favorite CPE Bach keyboard work. In my earlier blog post, I had praised Andreas Staier&amp;rsquo;s performance I discovered in college, but now having heard Hill&amp;rsquo;s, I have another favorite (live from April 2014). This totally plays up Hill&amp;rsquo;s maximally emotive expressive style:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/LOT_nUPvE98&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;js-bach-well-tempered-clavier-selections&#34;&gt;JS Bach: Well-Tempered Clavier selections&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was fascinating to find Hill performing JS Bach on fortepiano; I had never heard anyone playing JS Bach on fortepiano before. I love that he experiments with different styles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The famous WTC I, Prelude in C major, in a fluid, beautiful Romantic-style (vs. Baroque-style) performance he just uploaded a couple of days ago:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/jiBQD0vV5qI&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A totally gorgeous Romantic-style interpretation of the slow Bach WTC I, Prelude in C# minor:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/9iGj4U7nqqY&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love how he makes full use of the expressive possibilities of the fortepiano (power and dynamics and sustain).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;beethoven-s-moonlight-sonata&#34;&gt;Beethoven&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Moonlight&amp;rdquo; sonata&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, he plays Beethoven too, on fortepiano.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that Beethoven did call it &amp;ldquo;sonata quasi fantasia&amp;rdquo; so it should be played freely &amp;ldquo;like a fantasy&amp;rdquo;, freely, and he does this. If you&amp;rsquo;ve only heard it played more &amp;ldquo;squarely&amp;rdquo;, check this out. In this case, I prefer a more subtle freedom than the exaggerated gestures Hill provides, because I feel he disrupts the rhythmic flow too much, so I consider his experiment not a full success, but still, I respect his willingness to go all out:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/6gpmZsqOzZs&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;pianoforte&#34;&gt;Pianoforte!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, of course Robert Hill plays the modern piano too. And I love what he does with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;brahms&#34;&gt;Brahms&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hill brings out the different voices very well, the counterpoint through the thick textures of Brahms. These are truly beautiful performances of some of &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/05/07/happy-birthday-johannes-brahms/&#34;&gt;my favorite piano music of all time, Brahms&amp;rsquo; intermezzi&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A passionate performance of Op. 117, No. 2 in B-flat minor:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/U_rlk4H-DQ0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And Op. 119, No. 1 in B minor (some favorite performances of which I discussed in &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/05/07/happy-birthday-johannes-brahms/&#34;&gt;my blog post last year&lt;/a&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/NOpe_KvXQzA&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is one of the most emotionally raw performances I have ever heard of this intermezzo. Hill makes the most of the suspensions, silences, dissonances, and clashing lines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Discovering the musical performances of Robert Hill on keyboard instruments has been one of the happy surprises of my life this year. Not only has he provided me listening pleasure, but also has sharpened my conception of what the music he plays is about and how to express it. He has forever changed my expectation from myself of how I should play music. I expect that from now on, I will never again hold back from &amp;ldquo;weird&amp;rdquo; interpretations that I feel come from my heart and mind. I don&amp;rsquo;t expect that all my experiments will succeed, but seeing someone else try, and publicly, how can I not do likewise?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Have you recently discovered a musician who has changed your hearing and/or your own playing? Who was it and what did you learn?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Are you familiar with the Nutcracker story? Check out ETA Hoffmann&#39;s other creepy tales!</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/12/27/are-you-familiar-with-the-nutcracker-story-check-out-eta-hoffmanns-other-creepy-tales/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Dec 2013 19:15:36 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/12/27/are-you-familiar-with-the-nutcracker-story-check-out-eta-hoffmanns-other-creepy-tales/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s the season when many of us either watch for the first time a production of the ballet &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Nutcracker&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Nutcracker&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, or remember having seen it at some point, or remember some non-ballet production of the story (I personally still remember seeing some children&amp;rsquo;s adaptation of it when I was young).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But how many of you have actually read the original story by the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/German_Romanticism&#34;&gt;German Romantic&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/E._T._A._Hoffmann&#34;&gt;ETA Hoffmann&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Nutcracker_and_the_Mouse_King&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Nutcracker and the Mouse King&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.press.uchicago.edu/dms/ucp/books/jacket/0226/34/0226347893.jpeg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Tales of ETA Hoffmann&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;eta-hoffmann-a-forgotten-writer&#34;&gt;ETA Hoffmann, a forgotten writer?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was reminded of the creepy tales of Hoffmann when this &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.npr.org/2013/12/25/257139160/the-dark-roots-of-the-nutcracker-and-the-man-who-wrote-it&#34;&gt;article about him came my way&lt;/a&gt;. It suggested that people don&amp;rsquo;t know about him any more. I don&amp;rsquo;t know how true that is, but because he is one of my all-time favorite writers, I decided to do my part to help promote the work of this fascinating 19th century writer. He wrote not only amazing fiction, but also wrote on philosophy and music: in particular, as this article notes, he was one of the first critics who welcomed the strange figure of Ludwig van Beethoven when Beethoven came on the scene and freaked everyone out with his revolutionary new music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;first-encounter&#34;&gt;First encounter&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first time I heard of ETA Hoffmann was purely a result of hearing a musical excerpt from &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jacques_Offenbach&#34;&gt;Jacques Offenbach&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s opera, &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Tales_of_Hoffmann&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Les contes d&amp;rsquo;Hoffmann&amp;rdquo; (&amp;ldquo;The tales of Hoffmann&amp;rdquo;)&lt;/a&gt;. This was when I was in high school.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OK, I have never watched this opera or listened to it, except for the famous &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Belle_nuit,_%C3%B4_nuit_d%27amour&#34;&gt;Barcarolle&lt;/a&gt;. So basically, I only knew that there was someone whose name was Hoffmann and wrote some &amp;ldquo;tales&amp;rdquo; that were used in an opera. That was all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;second-encounter&#34;&gt;Second encounter&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My second encounter was when I was in college and learning to like the music of Mozart and Beethoven. I came across the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/10/rip-charles-rosen/&#34;&gt;book by the late Charles Rosen, &amp;ldquo;The Classical Style&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, and early on in the book, Rosen mentioned this music critic who so loved Mozart that he changed one of his names from &amp;ldquo;Friedrich&amp;rdquo; to &amp;ldquo;Amadeus&amp;rdquo; (hence our knowing him as ETA Hoffmann rather than ETF Hoffmann)! So that was intriguing. I looked at some of his writing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-fine-english-translation-of-selected-stories&#34;&gt;A fine English translation of selected stories&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I immersed myself more in the music of the era, I grew increasingly interested in the philosophy developing that would later be called &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/German_Romanticism&#34;&gt;German Romanticism&lt;/a&gt;. I began reading Fichte, Schlegel, Jean Paul, Kleist, Hölderlin, Jean Paul, Hegel, Goethe, and other figures of the period. I even took a course in German. And of course I ran into ETA Hoffmann again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I bought &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.press.uchicago.edu/ucp/books/book/chicago/T/bo3627741.html&#34;&gt;this really good English translation of selected stories of his&lt;/a&gt; and was not disappointed.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.press.uchicago.edu/dms/ucp/books/jacket/0226/34/0226347893.jpeg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Tales of ETA Hoffmann&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I looked online and there are more recent English translations since my college days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The stories are really surreal, raising many questions about humanity and reality. And yes, they are pretty disturbing too: I will confess to having had nightmares based on the stories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;ve read Edgar Allan Poe, think of Hoffmann the fiction writer as a much, much superior German analogue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-golden-pot&#34;&gt;The Golden Pot&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you read only one story by Hoffmann, I suppose it would have to be &amp;ldquo;The Golden Pot&amp;rdquo;. It&amp;rsquo;s long and vivid, although in the end I could not really make coherent sense of it. It&amp;rsquo;s a weird fantasy and has a lot of funny elements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s an &lt;a href=&#34;http://gutenberg.net.au/ebooks06/0605801h.html&#34;&gt;English translation online&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-sandman&#34;&gt;The Sandman&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story that really got under my skin, however, was &amp;ldquo;The Sandman&amp;rdquo;. Very dark.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s an &lt;a href=&#34;http://germanstories.vcu.edu/hoffmann/sand_e.html&#34;&gt;English translation online&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was interesting to be reminded of the stories of ETA Hoffmann at this time of year. Check some out if you haven&amp;rsquo;t read any before. I have to confess they&amp;rsquo;re not for everyone, and at this point in my life I am less interested in (and more wary of) this kind of Romantic literature, because I consider it &amp;ldquo;unhealthy&amp;rdquo;, frankly, along with other aspects of German Romanticism in general, but I can&amp;rsquo;t deny the guy was a genius.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;questions-for-you&#34;&gt;Questions for you&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;ve read some of Hoffmann&amp;rsquo;s stories before, which ones are your favorites? Why? Do you think they&amp;rsquo;re still as interesting now as when coming out from a mindset of the beginnings of Romanticism in the 19th century, or do they feel dated to you?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>RIP Charles Rosen, pianist and scholar</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/12/10/rip-charles-rosen/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Dec 2012 22:07:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/12/10/rip-charles-rosen/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://yalepress.yale.edu/yupbooks/images/full13/9780300126402.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Charles Rosen, cover of &amp;#34;Music and Sentiment&amp;#34;&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
This book was written from the conviction that understanding music does not come from memorizing an esoteric code. ([Charles Rosen, *Music and Sentiment*, 2010](http://yalepress.yale.edu/yupbooks/book.asp?isbn=9780300126402).)
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, I heard that the noted pianist and musical scholar &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles_Rosen&#34;&gt;Charles Rosen&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.npr.org/blogs/deceptivecadence/2012/12/10/166876593/remembering-charles-rosen-a-prodigious-pianist-and-polymath&#34;&gt;died at 85 yesterday&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://s.wsj.net/public/resources/images/OB-VQ187_rosen6_EV_20121210175859.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Charles Rosen&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I type these words while his book of this year (2012), &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.hup.harvard.edu/catalog.php?isbn=9780674047525&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Freedom and the Arts&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; is visible on my book shelf next to my computer: I had taken it out of the library a while back. I own copies of several of his previous books, starting with his famous [&amp;ldquo;The Classical Style&amp;rdquo;] which was my introduction to his thinking about music. I also own a number of his piano recordings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Put simply, &lt;strong&gt;Charles Rosen changed the entire course of my life&lt;/strong&gt;. Without him, my life would have been completely different, and I would have been a completely different person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t actually remember exactly how I came across Rosen&amp;rsquo;s writings. Here is what I remember about the context.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;freshman-year-in-college&#34;&gt;Freshman year in college&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve mentioned before that I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/09/taking-up-flute-again-after-decades/&#34;&gt;entered freshman year in college having very little musical background&lt;/a&gt;, either as a listener or as a performer, but in order to fulfill a core requirement, in my first semester took an &amp;ldquo;easy&amp;rdquo; music appreciation course called &amp;ldquo;Piano Music of the 19th Century&amp;rdquo;. I also made a new friend in my dorm during freshman week, who happened to be a big fan of Mozart and lent me some of his recordings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, freshman year in college was the year when I fell in love with music all over again, having mostly ignored it after my middle school disasters in music class and band class. Because I made some new friends (from my math and science classes) who were heavily into classical music, I ended up listening to their collections and getting into it myself. Since one of them was a fan of Mozart and the other of Beethoven, it was natural that I became very familiar with music of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Classical_period_(music)&#34;&gt;Classical period&lt;/a&gt;, focused on the late 18th century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;accidental-discovery-of-rosen&#34;&gt;Accidental discovery of Rosen&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point before sophomore year, I must have seen Rosen&amp;rsquo;s book &amp;ldquo;The Classical Style&amp;rdquo; in a local book store and browsed it and found it sufficiently engaging and approachable to buy it. I liked that he combined both readable text as well as excerpts from scores and actual music theoretic analysis. In order to understand better the analysis, of course, I had to learn some music theory, and I eventually ended up taking a two-semester &amp;ldquo;non-majors&amp;rdquo; course on music theory. But the book was readable even without much theoretical knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;making-me-think&#34;&gt;Making me think&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What Rosen&amp;rsquo;s book did for me was that it made me &lt;em&gt;think&lt;/em&gt; about music, and also about a lot more than music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d had a year in college of listening to a lot of music for enjoyment, but felt I wanted to &lt;em&gt;understand&lt;/em&gt; more of what I &lt;em&gt;felt&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;experienced&lt;/em&gt; intuitively. Rosen explained things about how the Classical era&amp;rsquo;s music was very different from the Baroque that preceded it and also very different from the Romantic era&amp;rsquo;s that followed it. He talked about musical forms and structures, the emergent harmonic language, as well as contemporary changes in society, in philosophy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I came away from the book with a much better understanding of various ongoing debates about composer &amp;ldquo;intent&amp;rdquo;, about whether some music is &amp;ldquo;better&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;more advanced&amp;rdquo; than others, about whether old music should be played on modern instruments, about culture in general. I didn&amp;rsquo;t necessarily adopt Rosen&amp;rsquo;s opinions about things, but enjoyed that he provided reasons for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;other-books&#34;&gt;Other books&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the years, I picked up several new books by Rosen as they appeared. Here are examples of what I learned from two of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;frontiers-of-meaning&#34;&gt;Frontiers of Meaning&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 1994 slim volume &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Frontiers-Meaning-Charles-Rosen/dp/187108265X&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Frontiers of Meaning&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; was interesting because Rosen argued that music has &amp;ldquo;meaning&amp;rdquo; and offered his own personal story about changes in his musical taste and understanding. The big message was that if we don&amp;rsquo;t understand a piece of music, we would do well &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; to immediately dismiss it as junk or noise, but try to understand it on its own terms, and maybe even end up actually enjoying it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rosen notes that although he found the string quartets of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/B%C3%A9la_Bart%C3%B3k&#34;&gt;Béla Bartók&lt;/a&gt; harsh and incomprehensible at first, he came to like one of them a lot. He still never ended up liking a different one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, the takeaway message from the book was that if we want to enjoy life, and enjoy as much music as we can, we should open ourselves up to new possibilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;arnold-schönberg&#34;&gt;Arnold Schönberg&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another memorable book was a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Arnold-Schoenberg-Charles-Rosen/dp/0226726436&#34;&gt;1996 book on Arnold Schönberg&lt;/a&gt; that was really fascinating in its discussion of this controversial composer and theoretician. Rosen portrayed Schönberg as a unifier of the past as well as creator of the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I&amp;rsquo;ve &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/25/thank-you-glenn-gould/&#34;&gt;mentioned before&lt;/a&gt;, I still do not enjoy much of Schönberg&amp;rsquo;s music, but thanks to Rosen, I understand where he was coming from, and I think that is important. I also better understand why I like the music of his I like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;recordings&#34;&gt;Recordings&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the years, I went out of my way to obtain some rare recordings of Charles Rosen himself playing piano, such as the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Late-Piano-Sonatas-Charles-Rosen/dp/B00000291P&#34;&gt;late Beethoven piano sonatas&lt;/a&gt;, to test how his interpretations matched what I imagined they would be, from his discussions in his books. I was surprised by some interpretive decisions, and not all of them &amp;ldquo;worked&amp;rdquo; for me, but I felt a sense of satisfaction that here was a guy who not only thought about and wrote about music, but performed it also.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;some-obituaries&#34;&gt;Some obituaries&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2012/12/11/arts/music/charles-rosen-pianist-polymath-and-author-dies-at-85.html&#34;&gt;New York Times&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.guardian.co.uk/music/2012/dec/10/charles-rosen&#34;&gt;Guardian&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.wsj.com/speakeasy/2012/12/10/master-of-piano-and-prose/&#34;&gt;Wall Street Journal&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.artsjournal.com/slippeddisc/2012/12/death-of-a-great-musical-mind.html&#34;&gt;Norman Lebrecht&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;breadth&lt;/em&gt; of Charles Rosen&amp;rsquo;s interests and knowledge was one of the most appealing features of his work: he talked about music theory, piano performance, art, philosophy. I&amp;rsquo;ll miss his presence as an analyst and cultural commentator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-03-11&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-03-11)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An entertaining &lt;a href=&#34;http://standpointmag.co.uk/music-march-13-a-fusion-of-piano-and-cerebellum-norman-lebrecht-charles-rosen&#34;&gt;article by Norman Lebrecht&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-05-22&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-05-22)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In light of future discussions of the influence of Charles Rosen on my thought, I felt I should mention that what he introduced me to was a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Modernism_%28music%29&#34;&gt;modernist&lt;/a&gt; sensibility that, while unapologetic, was also honest and not rigid or doctrinaire. I respected that, given my ambivalence about the modernist philosophy and attitude, an ambivalence I still have two decades after first reading him (I do not consider myself a modernist). As mentioned, this modernist sensibility is at odds with aspects of Romanticism, which had been my default sensibility until I started immersing myself in the music of the Classical era.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Celebrating the birthday of John Coltrane, the Beethoven of jazz</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/09/23/celebrating-the-birthday-of-john-coltrane/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Sep 2012 00:44:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/09/23/celebrating-the-birthday-of-john-coltrane/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://userserve-ak.last.fm/serve/252/50664911.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;John Coltrane&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So today is the birthday of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Coltrane&#34;&gt;John Coltrane&lt;/a&gt; (1926-1967), a towering figure in the history of jazz like no other. Several years ago, in a moment of inspiration, I quipped to a friend that while it was clear to me that &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charlie_Parker&#34;&gt;Charlie Parker&lt;/a&gt; the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mozart&#34;&gt;Mozart&lt;/a&gt; of jazz, it was even more clear that Coltrane was the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beethoven&#34;&gt;Beethoven&lt;/a&gt; of jazz.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What did I mean by that remark? I meant it on philosophical, historical, and musical levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;mozart-to-beethoven-parker-to-coltrane&#34;&gt;Mozart to Beethoven; Parker to Coltrane&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mozart refined the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Classical_period_(music)&#34;&gt;Classical style&lt;/a&gt; inherited from Haydn and became a most admired practitioner of it; Mozart was accused (perhaps only fictionally) of writing &amp;ldquo;too many notes&amp;rdquo; in his music.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Beethoven started off in the Classical tradition and then went beyond that in his &amp;ldquo;middle&amp;rdquo; period, and then even further beyond that in his &amp;ldquo;late&amp;rdquo; period, to the point where he became completely unique and an existential challenge (to emulate or reject) to all future composers of Western art music.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Charlie Parker refined &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bebop&#34;&gt;bebop&lt;/a&gt; in jazz, which, among other things, involved packing in quite a lot of notes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Coltrane started off in the bebop tradition and then went beyond that along with Miles Davis and others, and then even further beyond that, to the point of challenging notions of what jazz even was or should be.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as I find Beethoven in his late period to be among the most sublime, yet most bizarre music of the entire history of Western art music, and was a hard act to follow, so too Coltrane. Just as many composers after Beethoven judged that he ruined Western art music permanently, so did many jazz musicians react in the same way toward Coltrane.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-coltrane-sampler&#34;&gt;A Coltrane sampler&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a lot of good music by Coltrane I could discuss for pages and pages. Look up popular examples such as &amp;ldquo;My Favorite Things&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;A Love Supreme&amp;rdquo;, for example. But for today, I celebrated not with those favorites (which I do love), but a different set:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;giant-steps-1960&#34;&gt;Giant Steps (1960)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Giant Steps&amp;rdquo; features some of the most amazing yet fluid improvisation I have ever encountered, and I love this video someone created to show transcribed notes. This is a classic that I never tire of listening to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/2kotK9FNEYU&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;vigil-1965&#34;&gt;Vigil (1965)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Vigil&amp;rdquo; is intense and even almost chaotic. It makes strange sense to me, a flow, an expression. I love it, although I don&amp;rsquo;t watch it very often; I have to be in the right mood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/5UHZaqG87N0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;ascension-1965&#34;&gt;Ascension (1965)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OK, &amp;ldquo;Ascension&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;makes no sense to me&lt;/em&gt;, and is not something I enjoy trying to listen to. You be the judge, but he lost me here. I&amp;rsquo;m just speaking the truth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/tgrQhBTDfhk&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-beethoven-sampler&#34;&gt;A Beethoven sampler&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For kicks, even though I&amp;rsquo;m not celebrating Beethoven today, here are examples of my favorite late Beethoven.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;diabelli-variations-http-en-wikipedia-org-wiki-diabelli-variations-1819&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Diabelli_Variations&#34;&gt;Diabelli Variations&lt;/a&gt; (1819)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Truly amazing set of theme and variations for the piano, taking the listener to alternate realities before returning back to earth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/wctoxElV8Os&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;große-fuge-http-en-wikipedia-org-wiki-gro-c3-9fe-fuge-1825&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gro%C3%9Fe_Fuge&#34;&gt;Große Fuge&lt;/a&gt; (1825)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nobody at this point in history was writing stuff like this. Beethoven just went wild and created this dissonant, difficult, and emotionally cathartic movement. Amazing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/XEZXjW_s0Qs&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>