<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Tanja Djelevic on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/tanja-djelevic/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Tanja Djelevic on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/tanja-djelevic/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Notes on exercising while sick or tired</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/01/25/notes-on-exercising-while-sick-or-tired/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Jan 2013 19:42:50 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/01/25/notes-on-exercising-while-sick-or-tired/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I was a bit sick this past week, a result of overexerting myself on various projects the previous week, and also Abby herself getting sick. We have been basically fine since Thursday, but I was feeling pretty bad Sunday through Tuesday in particular.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question always comes up, when I am sick or just plain tired, &amp;ldquo;What should I do to recover as efficiently as possible?&amp;rdquo; After trial and error over the years, I&amp;rsquo;ve come to realize I have to do a couple of things:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get more &lt;em&gt;sleep&lt;/em&gt;, whatever it takes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Eat only nutritious food, no junk.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Take some supplements such as vitamin C, B, zinc, fish oil (I don&amp;rsquo;t know if this is just a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.medscape.com/viewarticle/776832&#34;&gt;placebo effect&lt;/a&gt;, but it doesn&amp;rsquo;t matter because it seems to work, I end up believing, and therefore by the placebo effect it does work).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Start canceling lower-priority near-term engagements in order to free up rest time. (In retrospect, I should have bailed out of going to the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/21/attending-the-first-openhack-pittsburgh-meeting/&#34;&gt;first OpenHack Pittsburgh meeting&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get some kind of exercise.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s the exercise that gets tricky sometimes. When one is low on energy and weakened, what should one do, if anything at all? Here are some thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-even-exercise-at-all&#34;&gt;Why even exercise at all?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A long time ago, whenever I felt sick or tired, I would use that as a reason to just shut down and not get any exercise. I had the idea that I needed to &amp;ldquo;rest&amp;rdquo;, and any activity would only weaken me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that being completely sedentary is not actually &amp;ldquo;rest&amp;rdquo;. It is actually quite harmful. Lying around or sitting around all the time is, even for those of us who are healthy, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/sitting/AN02082&#34;&gt;unnatural and damaging&lt;/a&gt;. The way our bodies work actually changes when we are immobile. Granted, if we are seriously, seriously ill, and cannot move, then that is reality, but if we are ill but able to move, then there is a question of what we can do that helps rather than hinders recovery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;breaking-down&#34;&gt;Breaking down&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I take it for granted (and from experience) that when we&amp;rsquo;re sick, we shouldn&amp;rsquo;t just push through everything we would do if we were not. The reason is that normal levels of intense exercise deliberately does some controlled breaking down of the body in order for it to adapt and grow back stronger, but if we&amp;rsquo;re weak, we may not be strong enough to withstand the breaking down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I assume that we want to dial down the intensity in some way while retaining restorative effects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;walking-works-for-me&#34;&gt;Walking works for me&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find that walking (if you&amp;rsquo;re able to walk) is probably the ideal way of getting circulation when not feeling up to running or lifting weights. It&amp;rsquo;s low impact, you breathe more, and you can change the pace and intensity at very fine increments at will. So, if I do nothing else, I&amp;rsquo;ll get in a walk, even if it&amp;rsquo;s just around the block.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;running-sometimes-doesn-t-work-for-me&#34;&gt;Running sometimes doesn&amp;rsquo;t work for me&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find that it&amp;rsquo;s sometimes tricky to run when sick. The main problem is that there is a kind of threshold below which running feels inefficient to me. If you&amp;rsquo;re running a lot slower than usual, that is inefficient and increases pounding on the joints. I&amp;rsquo;d rather walk than run much slower than usual. So I haven&amp;rsquo;t run since &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/20/thoughts-on-an-unexpected-winter-barefoot-run/&#34;&gt;my barefoot run outside on Saturday&lt;/a&gt;. Now that I&amp;rsquo;m well again, I&amp;rsquo;m quite ready to resume running. I&amp;rsquo;d rather run when I&amp;rsquo;m excited to do it and feel that it will benefit me, instead of slogging through an inefficient and possibly form-disrupting run just because I&amp;rsquo;m &amp;ldquo;supposed&amp;rdquo; to run. As &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/14/i-love-medicine-balls-video-review-gaiam-fit-ball-workout/&#34;&gt;Tanja Djelevic&lt;/a&gt; recently wrote, &lt;a href=&#34;http://tanjadjelevic.com/blog/2013/01/22/for-the-purpose-of-living-loud/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;To be a slave to the work out regimen, and have hardcore guilt for missing a work out, is in every way detrimental.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, there are definitely times when I&amp;rsquo;ve run through a minor cold or something. It all depends. When the weather is really friendly (which it hasn&amp;rsquo;t been since real winter came immediately to Pittsburgh), it&amp;rsquo;s easy to just go out for a walk and have it turn into an easy run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;strength-training-partially&#34;&gt;Strength training, partially&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Usually, when I&amp;rsquo;m sick, I don&amp;rsquo;t feel like doing a whole lot of strength training. In fact, I&amp;rsquo;ve tested myself and when I&amp;rsquo;m sick, my pullups suffer considerably.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I&amp;rsquo;ve noticed that doing short bursts of &amp;ldquo;easier&amp;rdquo; exercises is quite helpful in getting the metabolism up and preventing the quick decline that happens if you just stop doing everything for too long. I do pushups every day (partially as a result of my 2013 decision to &amp;ldquo;earn&amp;rdquo; every square of chocolate I eat by first doing pushups just before eating it; as of today, I am earning my chocolate with 26 pushups). I don&amp;rsquo;t care how many I do: the point is to do something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-cathedral-of-learning-stair-climb-what-to-do-about-that&#34;&gt;My Cathedral of Learning stair climb: what to do about that?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been reporting regularly on my Cathedral of Learning 36-floor stair climb regimen &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/19/why-ive-chosen-to-perform-only-two-repetitions-of-the-cathedral-of-learning-stair-climb/&#34;&gt;lately&lt;/a&gt;. So what happened to my routine this week when I was not feeling well?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, I was supposed to do it Monday, and I was feeling queasy enough that I decided to completely bail out of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, Wednesday I was feeling much better, and decided that I wanted to do a reduced workout. I decided that after weeks of doing two repetitions, I was going to do &lt;em&gt;just one&lt;/em&gt;. But since I was feeling on the upswing, I felt that I was strong enough to gut out doing that one repetition relatively &lt;em&gt;fast&lt;/em&gt; (not all out fast, but pretty fast going one step at a time).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did it the fastest I&amp;rsquo;ve done so far this year, in 7:20. That&amp;rsquo;s 42 seconds faster than my fastest time yet in any of the stair climbs I&amp;rsquo;ve done so far this year. I was quite exhausted afterwards, and lay down panting for over three minutes (yes, I let the timer keep running to see when I would be able to breathe normally again). Doing the stair climb at this level of intensity to me feels considerably harder than &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/08/17/the-inaugural-liberty-mile-a-review-of-pittsburghs-first-road-mile-race/&#34;&gt;running an all-out mile race&lt;/a&gt;. Stair climbing is very different from (non-hilly) running, totally burning my quads and jacking up my heart rate way, way up (I didn&amp;rsquo;t measure it but I could feel it).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Afterwards, I felt pretty good and happy to have gotten myself out of my health slump.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;stair-racing-the-sport&#34;&gt;Stair racing, the sport?!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, here&amp;rsquo;s a great article a friend just sent me today about &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2013/01/27/magazine/stair-racing-a-sport-to-make-an-ironman-whimper.html&#34;&gt;stair racing, the sport&lt;/a&gt;. I had no idea there was actually a whole worldwide professional stair racing scene!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out the Empire State Building race:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/9iSGOUTz3QA&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;prevention&#34;&gt;Prevention&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, it&amp;rsquo;s better to prevent getting sick or tired in the first place. Here&amp;rsquo;s a great article on having &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sean-johnson.com/2013/01/22/why-you-need-more-margin-in-your-life/&#34;&gt;more &amp;ldquo;margin&amp;rdquo; in your life&lt;/a&gt; that I recently encountered. I plan to track and report on how I improve my margin in my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When my body is not functioning so well because of illness or fatigue, I try to figure out how to recover, and I&amp;rsquo;ve found that some types and levels of exercise are very helpful to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do you do to keep in shape when you are feeling sick or tired? Do you have your own specific plan B, or do you wing it, or do you follow the regular plan anyway?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I love medicine balls: including a video review: Gaiam Fit Ball Workout</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/12/14/i-love-medicine-balls-video-review-gaiam-fit-ball-workout/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Dec 2011 23:58:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/12/14/i-love-medicine-balls-video-review-gaiam-fit-ball-workout/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I love medicine balls. But once upon a time, I didn&amp;rsquo;t even know what a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Medicine_ball&#34;&gt;medicine ball&lt;/a&gt; was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two months ago, I mentioned my gradual movement away from formal gyms and exercise machines toward &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/17/the-joys-of-convict-conditioning-bodyweight-exercising/&#34;&gt;less technological ways to exercise&lt;/a&gt;. One of the &amp;ldquo;gadgets&amp;rdquo; I do use is a medicine ball.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, I am reviewing an intense exercise video that I started using just two years ago that involves a medicine ball, the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Gaiam-05-52846-Fit-Ball-Workout/dp/B0012K1BM8&#34;&gt;Gaiam Fit Ball Workout&lt;/a&gt; with instructor &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.tanjadjelevic.com/&#34;&gt;Tanja Djelevic&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://ecx.images-amazon.com/images/I/5110kWIORpL._SL500_AA300_.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Photo of Gaiam Fit Ball Workout kit&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I give this &lt;strong&gt;&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;5&lt;/sub&gt; stars&lt;/strong&gt; and here&amp;rsquo;s why!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;i-m-reviewing-the-first-workout-only-for-now&#34;&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m reviewing the first workout only, for now&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am only reviewing the first workout on the DVD, the &amp;ldquo;fit ball workout&amp;rdquo;. I have never done the other two workouts, the &amp;ldquo;abs workout&amp;rdquo; and the &amp;ldquo;partner workout&amp;rdquo;. I happen not to be a fan of abs-specific workouts (a later blog post will explain why), and I have yet to ask Abby whether she is interested in trying the partner workout.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;equipment-which-medicine-ball&#34;&gt;Equipment: which medicine ball?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two years ago, I started out with the 4 pound medicine ball and to my surprise, found myself humbled by it initially (after having spent too many years not working my upper body). Eventually the 4 pound ball became too easy and I bought a 6 pound ball, which I use now. I would advise starting easy and building up, making sure that whatever weight you are using, you only use a weight that you can sustain with good form for 25 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are no points for &amp;ldquo;showing off&amp;rdquo; and handling a heavier ball with poor form. There are also no points for going through the motions with a ball that is far too light to offer the resistance and burn you want to feel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m at the point where the 6 pound ball is a bit easy for some parts of the workout and still challenging for others. So I should probably move to an 8 pound ball soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;instructor&#34;&gt;Instructor&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tanja Djelevic is a fantastic instructor. Her instructions and suggestions and reminders on form are quite clear and enthusiastic, without being annoying. I cannot overstate how important it is, when evaluating an exercise video, to make sure the instructor is someone you can really feel reaching out to you from the TV or computer screen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-movements-full-range-of-motion&#34;&gt;The movements: full range of motion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &amp;ldquo;fit ball workout&amp;rdquo; is 25 minutes of nonstop intensity with a lot of different movements. I like that it works a full range of motion for many muscles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are reaches for the arms that I feel improved my posture and flexibility and aligned my shoulders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are core twists that should be done with care (I once did such twists carelessly and hurt my back).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are lunges and plies that will have you feeling the burn in your quads, glutes, and calves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The figure-eights and circles for the arms while holding the ball are great for shoulders and surrounding muscles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The throws are explosive and one of the great things about using a medicine ball.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The wood chops with the medicine ball I enjoy a lot, very dynamic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pushups are, well, pushups, but with an interesting dimension: by rolling the ball from one side to another while doing pushups, you get to work on core stability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The plank and other stationary poses are good for the abs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;warmup-and-cooldown&#34;&gt;Warmup and cooldown&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The warmup and cooldown are all too brief for my taste, but are decent if extended on both ends by a longer warmup and a longer cooldown (with more stretching of all the leg muscles, especially).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using the 25-minute medicine ball workout periodically over the past two years has not only added muscle to my entire upper body, and expanded my chest, but also improved my posture, balanced my left and right sides of my body, and generated some weight loss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not a workout I would do every day or even every other day. The reason is that doing the workout as is (without modification) involves endurance levels of repetition that I find beneficial in small doses but unenjoyable and less beneficial in larger doses. I like to mix up my workouts so that I get sessions in which I move much heavier weight but with fewer reps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have tried out other videos by Tanja Djelevic and will review them in the future. You might want to check out &lt;a href=&#34;http://tanjadjelevic.com/blog/&#34;&gt;her blog&lt;/a&gt; and subscribe to it: she likes talking about the whole picture of health of mind and body. Exercise isn&amp;rsquo;t and shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be some kind of mechanical operation treating the body as a machine. It&amp;rsquo;s something joyful that taps into our being fully alive, and you can tell from her instruction that Tanja embodies this attitude, and I appreciate it.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>