<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Appalachian Spring on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/appalachian-spring/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Appalachian Spring on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/appalachian-spring/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Copland&#39;s Appalachian Spring danced by the orchestra musicians: confronting my memories of boredom four years ago</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/05/28/coplands-appalachian-spring-danced-by-the-orchestra-musicians-confronting-my-memories-of-boredom-four-years-ago/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2014 22:23:26 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/05/28/coplands-appalachian-spring-danced-by-the-orchestra-musicians-confronting-my-memories-of-boredom-four-years-ago/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I follow Greg Sandow&amp;rsquo;s blog on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.artsjournal.com/sandow/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;future of classical music&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. He posted an &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.artsjournal.com/sandow/2014/05/essential-video.html&#34;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; that got me thinking: he was all excited about an unorthodox performance of Aaron Copland&amp;rsquo;s half-hour-long &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Appalachian_Spring&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Appalachian Spring&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; by the University of Maryland Symphony Orchestra in which the students of the orchestra actually moved around and danced as well as played their instruments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a confession to make: back almost four years ago, in November 2010, I went to a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cmu.edu/news/archive/2010/November/nov15_cmunightwithpso.shtml&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Carnegie Mellon Night at the Symphony&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; in which &amp;ldquo;Appalachian Spring&amp;rdquo; was on the program. &lt;strong&gt;I got very bored during the piece.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing to remember is that the orchestra suite was actually arranged by Copland from his original piece that was an actual ballet for Martha Graham! So it&amp;rsquo;s actually kind of unnatural to experience this music &amp;ldquo;purely&amp;rdquo; as music. To me the suite is rather long and redundant without some kind of &amp;ldquo;story&amp;rdquo; to go along with it. So I watched the video of the orchestra-danced performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was definitely more interesting seeing action. At the same time, I got bored eventually anyway, after about 15 minutes. But I lasted longer with the physical action. However, I was also distracted by thoughts of how difficult it must have been for the orchestra to pull this off. I mean, marching band is one thing, but this is an orchestra and there was a ton of choreography and it&amp;rsquo;s not just marching.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s interesting that a commenter on Sandow&amp;rsquo;s blog criticized the
effort, writing: &lt;em&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s nicely done, I suppose, if you must do this
sort of thing. But when I go to an orchestral concert, I&amp;rsquo;m there for
the music, not for this sort of thing. To me, this doesn&amp;rsquo;t tell the
audience &amp;ldquo;this music is worth your time and attention,&amp;rdquo; it tells them
&amp;ldquo;we have so little faith that you’ll enjoy the music that we feel
compelled to trick it out with distractions.&amp;rdquo; I used to sing in a
chorus that was fond of &amp;ldquo;chorusography,&amp;rdquo; and it annoyed me as a
performer, too.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What do you think? Do you like this idea or does it annoy you?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Judge for yourself:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/jGSctM_8K_E&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>