<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Cathedral Of Learning on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/cathedral-of-learning/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Cathedral Of Learning on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/cathedral-of-learning/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Climbing the Cathedral of Learning to get to the Harvard Classics</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/10/22/climbing-the-cathedral-of-learning-to-get-to-the-harvard-classics/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Oct 2014 23:12:24 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/10/22/climbing-the-cathedral-of-learning-to-get-to-the-harvard-classics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I recently learned that the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Harvard_Classics&#34;&gt;Harvard Classics&lt;/a&gt;, a 51-volume set of classic writings first published in 1909, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.openculture.com/2014/03/the-harvard-classics-download-all-51-volumes-as-free-ebooks.html&#34;&gt;are now available for free download as ebooks&lt;/a&gt;. This isn&amp;rsquo;t really news, but was just something that appeared on my radar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What relevance such an ancient collection has today is an interesting question, especially in light of the fact that a century ago the concept of what was of interest in the history of the &amp;ldquo;world&amp;rdquo; was fairly narrow, but not something I&amp;rsquo;m discussing right now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a hunch where I could find a physical copy of the Harvard Classics. I tested my hunch:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/franklinmingchen/15415427937&#34; title=&#34;IMG_20141022_113213 by Franklin Chen, on Flickr&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5607/15415427937_62f9d10eae.jpg&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; height=&#34;375&#34; alt=&#34;IMG_20141022_113213&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;sightings&#34;&gt;Sightings&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have seen this type of material (including, of course sets of encyclopedias) in many places, including personal homes: dusty, hardly opened volumes handed down generation after generation, perhaps, or acquired at bargain prices from library or garage sales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But most interesting to me is seeing it in public places. In particularly, I suddenly had the suspicion (or unconscious memory) that the 36th floor of the Cathedral of Learning at Pitt, which has book shelves of many old books, might have the Harvard Classics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;climbing-the-cathedral&#34;&gt;Climbing the Cathedral&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/franklinmingchen/15601416745&#34; title=&#34;IMG_20141022_114120 by Franklin Chen, on Flickr&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3932/15601416745_5c49f2fbdf.jpg&#34; width=&#34;375&#34; height=&#34;500&#34; alt=&#34;IMG_20141022_114120&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I used my curiosity to stop by the Cathedral of Learning near lunch time and climb to the 36th floor, a curious form of exercise I hadn&amp;rsquo;t engaged in for quite some time, maybe almost a year by now. I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/04/i-had-no-choice-but-to-barefoot-climb-the-cathedral-of-learning/&#34;&gt;took off my shoes and socks&lt;/a&gt; and jacket, and stuffed them in my backpack before beginning the ascent. I am currently out of shape and started feeling nauseous probably around the 25th floor, but made it to the top:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/franklinmingchen/15415427937&#34; title=&#34;IMG_20141022_113213 by Franklin Chen, on Flickr&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5607/15415427937_62f9d10eae.jpg&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; height=&#34;375&#34; alt=&#34;IMG_20141022_113213&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There they were, the Harvard Classics!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/franklinmingchen/15601416115&#34; title=&#34;IMG_20141022_113305 by Franklin Chen, on Flickr&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3944/15601416115_470d900851.jpg&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; height=&#34;375&#34; alt=&#34;IMG_20141022_113305&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Physically old books have a durability and charm to them. Here&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;The Pilgrim&amp;rsquo;s Progress&amp;rdquo;, a book I actually acquired &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/12/22/a-favorite-poem-to-share-as-2013-comes-to-an-end&#34;&gt;by accident at age 9 along with many others&lt;/a&gt; but never really read (I tried but it was too confusing, despite the illustrations):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/franklinmingchen/15598756521&#34; title=&#34;IMG_20141022_113328 by Franklin Chen, on Flickr&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5615/15598756521_c5fe055973.jpg&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; height=&#34;375&#34; alt=&#34;IMG_20141022_113328&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-note-on-the-elevator-modernization-project&#34;&gt;A note on the &amp;ldquo;elevator modernization project&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After I climb to the top of the Cathedral of Learning, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/11/03/the-dilemma-of-how-to-descend-the-cathedral-of-learning-once-at-the-top/&#34;&gt;I have to choose whether to take an elevator down&lt;/a&gt;, and this time was no exception.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that an elevator appeared quickly before I had to decide whether to just walk down 36 floors, so I hopped in with some other people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I heard a lot of complaints about elevator waits thanks to elevators being out of service. People talked about waiting &lt;em&gt;fifteen to twenty minutes&lt;/em&gt; before giving up sometimes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I kept my mouth shut about the fact that it only takes far less time to either ascend or descend the entire Cathedral on the stairs; this is not a nation of walkers, and everyone has personal reasons not to take the stairs. There are many good reasons to improve accessibility between all the floors of the Cathedral for all people, and I have found the elevators unreliable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Getting back to the bottom, I saw a sign that explained the situation: there is an &amp;ldquo;elevator modernization project&amp;rdquo; in progress to try to considerably improve the elevator situation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/franklinmingchen/15577746826&#34; title=&#34;IMG_20141022_113740 by Franklin Chen, on Flickr&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3944/15577746826_4ee00263a0.jpg&#34; width=&#34;375&#34; height=&#34;500&#34; alt=&#34;IMG_20141022_113740&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found the Harvard Classics where I expected to find them! I will continue to climb the Cathedral in the future to see what other oldies exist up there. I am particularly interested in encyclopedias and &amp;ldquo;world history&amp;rdquo; books, having seen some really old ones in the past that were fascinating in either their short-sighted parochial nature or in their far-sighted prophetic correctness. I will report on what I find that might be particularly noteworthy.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The dilemma of how to descend the Cathedral of Learning once at the top</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/11/03/the-dilemma-of-how-to-descend-the-cathedral-of-learning-once-at-the-top/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Nov 2013 09:34:44 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/11/03/the-dilemma-of-how-to-descend-the-cathedral-of-learning-once-at-the-top/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, right after I left one of the sessions of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.music.pitt.edu/events/43rd-annual-jazz-seminar-concert130813&#34;&gt;annual Pittsburgh Jazz Seminar&lt;/a&gt; at the William Pitt Union, I immediately crossed the street to the Cathedral of Learning, in order to climb up to the 36th floor (I last climbed the Cathedral &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/10/29/an-early-start-on-cathedral-of-learning-stair-climbing/&#34;&gt;three days ago&lt;/a&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/cathedral-2013-11-02.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;View of Cathedral of Learning&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I took off my shoes, stuffed my jacket into my backpack, and went up at an &amp;ldquo;easy&amp;rdquo; pace, taking about nine minutes:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/cathedral-2013-11-02-at-top.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;View from 36th floor window of Cathedral of Learning&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Then I faced the usual dilemma of how to get back down, except this time, the dilemma was magnified because of my time constraints: I really needed to get down and out &lt;em&gt;quickly&lt;/em&gt;, in order to make it to an important appointment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;choices-and-tradeoffs&#34;&gt;Choices and tradeoffs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;elevator-down&#34;&gt;Elevator down&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One option is to take one of the elevators down. This is what I&amp;rsquo;ve almost always done ever since doing the Cathedral of Learning stair climb.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, whether this is time-effective depends a lot on various factors, such as whether Pitt classes are being held, Pitt students are roaming around, or tourists are roaming around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that Saturday afternoon is a bad time to be taking the elevator. There were hordes of students as well as tourists throughout the building, and especially the tourists at the top floor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, I had noticed on the ground floor earlier that some of the elevators were out of service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/10/29/an-early-start-on-cathedral-of-learning-stair-climbing/&#34;&gt;three days ago I had a bad experience with the elevator&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;taking-the-stairs-down&#34;&gt;Taking the stairs down&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other option is to take the stairs back down, all the way. This option is one I take so rarely that I don&amp;rsquo;t even remember when I last did it. I probably did it once earlier this year, but have no specific memory of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The drawback of taking the stairs down is the extra impact on the body.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But since I needed to descend as quickly as possible, I felt I had no choice but to take the stairs. In fact, I not only used the stairs, but ran down all the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It wasn&amp;rsquo;t hard (thank you, gravity!), although it got boring and weird after a while, because it feels like forever going down 36 floors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-day-after&#34;&gt;The day after&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought everything was OK, but this morning, the day after, I woke up with a serious case of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Delayed_onset_muscle_soreness&#34;&gt;DOMS&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My &lt;em&gt;calves&lt;/em&gt; were totally tight and trashed. Oops. Maybe I could have prevented this by stretching after running down yesterday, but I had no time, and had to make my appointment. Or maybe I just plain overdid things, not being conditioned at all to running down so many steps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I&amp;rsquo;m suffering, but no permanent damage done, of course: I will be OK after a day or two.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-next&#34;&gt;What next?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So does this mean that the next time I climb the Cathedral, I will stick to the elevator?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, &lt;em&gt;no&lt;/em&gt;. I take the experience as a challenge:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;First, I want to defeat my sense of boredom going down, just as I&amp;rsquo;ve managed to defeat it on the way up. I will find something meditative and aesthetic about the process of descending the steps.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Clearly my soreness showed that my calves were insufficiently conditioned. The solution to that is not to avoid running down the steps, but to &lt;em&gt;keep doing it&lt;/em&gt;, in a smarter way. Therefore, my plan now is that on any final repetition of the Cathedral stair climb, I will take the stairs back down, rather than the elevator, regardless of elevator congestion concerns.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An accidental case of trashed calves during a workout has led me to treat it as a learning experience and a challenge to overcome in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2014-10-22&#34;&gt;(Update of 2014-10-22)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/10/22/climbing-the-cathedral-of-learning-to-get-to-the-harvard-classics/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;elevator modernization project&amp;rdquo; started in September 2014 and makes it even more attractive to just walk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An early start on Cathedral of Learning stair climbing</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/29/an-early-start-on-cathedral-of-learning-stair-climbing/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Oct 2013 19:18:47 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/29/an-early-start-on-cathedral-of-learning-stair-climbing/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;After work today, I had gone to the Carnegie Library of Pittsburgh, main branch in Oakland, to pick up some books, when I looked across Forbes Avenue and saw the Pitt Cathedral of Learning. Primed by Becky&amp;rsquo;s message today about forming a team again for the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lung.org/pledge-events/pa/pittsburgh-climb-fy14/&#34;&gt;Fight for Air Climb at One Oxford Centre in downtown Pittsburgh, for next March&lt;/a&gt;, I suddenly decided to do the 36-floor stair climb of the Cathedral of Learning to &amp;ldquo;officially&amp;rdquo; begin my training for that event!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/cathedral-2013-10-29.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Cathedral of Learning&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m getting an early start this year on training for the Fight for Air Climb: last year, I didn&amp;rsquo;t even think about that event until I saw a poster for it during &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/28/meditations-on-climbing-the-36-floors-of-the-pitt-cathedral-of-learning/&#34;&gt;my first Cathedral climb in years, right after Christmas&lt;/a&gt;. So I&amp;rsquo;m going to have an additional two months of training.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;going-up&#34;&gt;Going up&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, in addition to my not having done the Cathedral climb in probably over half a year, I was wearing my work clothing and shoes and a backpack full of heavy books, so the climb was rather strenuous and sweaty. I even &amp;ldquo;forgot&amp;rdquo; to go to the 36th floor and got off at the 35th instead (no big deal).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/cathedral-2013-10-29-near-top.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;View out of 35th floor window&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;going-back-down&#34;&gt;Going back down&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once at the top, I didn&amp;rsquo;t stop to rest, because I wanted to get home quickly for dinner. Unfortunately, lots of people were already on the elevator when it came down from 36, and after I got on at 35, we kept on stopping to pick up others, and I felt very uncomfortable being sweaty and packed into the elevator near the back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-11-03&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-11-03)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/11/03/the-dilemma-of-how-to-descend-the-cathedral-of-learning-once-at-the-top/&#34;&gt;Three days later, I did the Cathedral climb again, and did take the stairs, but experienced a surprise.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A comeback from Pittsburgh Marathon overtraining</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/04/06/comeback-from-pittsburgh-marathon-overtraining/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Apr 2013 15:59:23 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/04/06/comeback-from-pittsburgh-marathon-overtraining/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Last week I reported on running Just A Short Run, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/30/report-on-just-a-short-run-my-first-half-marathon-in-nine-years/&#34;&gt;my first half marathon in nine years&lt;/a&gt;. One very real concern I had &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/03/my-first-steel-city-road-runners-winter-5k-race/&#34;&gt;when I put this race on my calendar a month ago&lt;/a&gt; was that recovery from it might interfere with my marathon training. Although I did not race Just A Short Run all out, I did put in a hard effort, and sure enough I did end up having a really tough training week afterwards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the overtraining this week was partly my doing. Here I explain how I ended up feeling like I was falling apart, and how I recovered and felt pretty good during today&amp;rsquo;s long run.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/wow-run.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Pittsburgh Marathon Warmup on Walnut run&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;after-the-half-marathon&#34;&gt;After the half marathon&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned in my report, I had some issues after the race: my right lower calf/Achilles area seized up for a bit, and also my right second and third toes did as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sure enough, a day later, I was feeling very sore in my right lower calf and second toe. I should mention that I have &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Morton%27s_toe&#34;&gt;Morton&amp;rsquo;s toe&lt;/a&gt; on both feet, although my left second toe is only barely longer than the big toe, while it is my right second toe that is noticeably longer than the big toe and therefore has a real tendency to cause me some problems:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mortons-toe.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;My Morton&amp;#39;s toes&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So I did take a day off running after the half marathon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;monday-trying-to-be-careful&#34;&gt;Monday: trying to be careful&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But even on Monday, I was still feeling sore. I decided that I should do some light running anyway, to avoid two days off completely from running.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, I very much wanted to finally start running in my new Luna Sandals, which I had received last week but put aside because of the half marathon. These are the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lunasandals.com/products/33-venado&#34;&gt;Venado with ATS laces and MGT footbed&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/lunastore/images/255/full.jpg?1351720427&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Luna Sandals: Venado, ATS laces, MGT footbed&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I ended up running just an easy 2 miles on the treadmill in the morning in my Vibram FiveFingers Bikila LS shoes, and then after work, running 1.5 miles in the Luna Sandals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;tuesday-new-shoes&#34;&gt;Tuesday: new shoes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tuesday, I was still not yet completely recovered either from the half marathon, but I felt I was ready to go for a normal run. I decided to do a real run in the Luna Sandals and did 5 miles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I encountered various problems while trying out the Luna Sandals, beginning to break them in. I got chafed in various places from the straps and buckle:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/luna-sandals-2013-04-02/feet.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Feet chafed&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/luna-sandals-2013-04-02/side.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Side view&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/luna-sandals-2013-04-02/wearing.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Feet in&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/luna-sandals-2013-04-02/heel.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;View of heel&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And it was tricky keeping the sandals on at all. I fidgeted a lot with the laces to try to keep my heels from slipping. I kept on having problems with my right heel slipping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, although my calf was healing up, I was more worried about my right second toe, which seemed sore and sensitive. I noticed that my tendency to impact the second toe (after all, it is my longest toe) was causing trouble. I had not really encountered any problems until after the half marathon, but the intensity of that effort, and the fact that my Bikila LS shoes were getting worn down at the toes, must have exposed this biomechanical weakness finally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;wednesday-overexcited&#34;&gt;Wednesday: overexcited&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wednesday, I was excited about running, and used the Luna Sandals again. I still had slippage and chafing issues, but figured that there was a break-in process. The soles were starting to shape to my feet, for example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, I accidentally (because of taking impromptu routes in Homewood Cemetery) ran 9 miles when I had originally intended to run more like 7.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My second toe was startling to tingle and really complain: even normal walking triggered pain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;thursday-admission-of-overtraining&#34;&gt;Thursday: admission of overtraining&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thursday was one of those days when I truly &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/14/three-questions-to-ask-yourself-when-you-dont-feel-like-doing-your-scheduled-workout/&#34;&gt;had to ask myself three questions&lt;/a&gt;. I was simply feeling &lt;em&gt;exhausted&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I forced myself to completely take Thursday off from running (or strength training, for that matter), while evaluating my situation. This was no longer just about my toe, but about my overall fatigue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, I had to fix this toe problem somehow, and soon, because I had a long run planned for Saturday. So I observed myself closely while walking. I noticed that I had a tendency to do a weird retracting motion on the toe when walking, a motion I do not use on my left foot. I questioned the purpose of this reflex. I found that I could &lt;em&gt;choose&lt;/em&gt; not to perform the retracting motion. It was difficult to make this choice, but if I really focused, I could control how I &lt;em&gt;used&lt;/em&gt; my foot. I remembered lessons from &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alexander_technique&#34;&gt;Alexander technique&lt;/a&gt; about observing and unlearning habits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, I discovered the reason my right hip has sometimes felt sore: my right hip has sagged in my posture. I also found that correcting this shifted the balance of weight on my right foot, and alleviated the pressure on my second toe, shifting more weight where it should be, more toward the big toe under the ball of the foot. These were very interesting discoveries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, I felt so tired that I decided to go ahead and cancel my Sunday plan to play in the final round of the Pittsburgh Chess League season; I had really wanted to put in one final appearance for our team, after not having actually played for us since &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/11/11/pittsburgh-chess-league-round-3-back-to-chess-after-a-month-off/&#34;&gt;last November&lt;/a&gt;, because something kept on coming up every month since then, but I had little confidence that I would be mentally alert on Sunday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;friday-still-playing-it-safe&#34;&gt;Friday: still playing it safe&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Friday, I was feeling energetic enough to run, but I forced myself to take another day off for the sake of my right toe. It was not easy, but I reminded myself that &lt;em&gt;not being able to do my long run&lt;/em&gt; was not worth one more missed day of training.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of running, I did one rep of the Cathedral of Learning stair climb, just to get some activity in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;saturday-my-14-mile-long-run&#34;&gt;Saturday: my 14-mile long run&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saturday morning, I felt my right toe had recovered sufficiently that I was going to be OK doing my planned long run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Steel City Road Runners had a 10-mile run lined up starting in Shadyside after a program of dynamics warmups by Dr. Vonda Wright, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pittsburghmarathon.com/wow.asp&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Warmup on Walnut&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, outside of sponsor &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.truerunner.com/&#34;&gt;True Runner&lt;/a&gt;. My plan was to skip that program, but create a 14-mile run by running 2 miles from home to the Shadyside point and then joining the group run and then running 2 miles back home afterwards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is the 10-mile loop:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe id=&#34;mapmyfitness_route&#34; src=&#34;http://snippets.mapmycdn.com/routes/view/embedded/187175578?width=560&amp;height=400&amp;elevation=true&amp;info=true&amp;line_color=E60f0bdb&amp;rgbhex=DB0B0E&amp;distance_markers=1&amp;unit_type=imperial&amp;map_mode=TERRAIN&amp;last_updated=2013-04-01T09:44:11-04:00&#34; height=&#34;590px&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: right; padding-right: 20px;&#34;&gt;&lt;a target=&#34;_blank&#34; href=&#34;http://mapmyrun.com/routes/create/&#34;&gt;Create Maps&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a target=&#34;_blank&#34; href=&#34;http://mapmyrun.com/routes/&#34;&gt;search&lt;/a&gt; from 80 million at &lt;a href=&#34;http://mapmyrun.com&#34;&gt;MapMyRun&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;my-goal&#34;&gt;My goal&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My goal for this long run was to make it a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mcmillanrunning.com/index.php/articlePages/article/2&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;fast finish long run&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. In particular, in planning my run, I had noted that the last 5 miles of the course involved a steady uphill as well as a steeper uphill through Oakland on Forbes Avenue. In the 2003 Pittsburgh Marathon ten years ago, this uphill had proved a bit discouraging to me (because I had, frankly, gone out too fast). In any case, for psychological and physiological reasons, I wanted to do this whole uphill fast and strong in this particular workout. In the actual marathon in a month, of course, I don&amp;rsquo;t plan to run it as fast, but I did want to remember the landmarks and mental state of doing something difficult but in a relaxed way. I wanted to focus on applying my newly discovered knowledge about my posture and stride asymmetry and &amp;ldquo;run tall&amp;rdquo; up the hill, with balanced hips, while monitoring my right second toe to make sure it did not get battered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was still not comfortable with the Luna Sandals, so I fell back to the shoes I&amp;rsquo;ve been wearing for almost all of my runs in the past three months, the Bikila LS shoes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;showed-up-late&#34;&gt;Showed up late&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, I strangely miscalculated my departure from home to run 2 miles to Aiken Avenue and Walnut Street, and showed up 4 minutes late, just as runners were already heading off. I grabbed a printed map and picked up the pace so that I could try to catch up to the 10:00 pace group. I did, realizing of course that I was making my task in the final miles of my run more difficult as a result.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;conquering-the-oakland-hill&#34;&gt;Conquering the Oakland hill&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I managed the Oakland hill pretty well, being very focused. I continued going hard all the way back to True Runner in Shadyside. Near the end, I felt my calves getting tight, just as in the half marathon last week when my right calf seized up after I was walking after the finish line. I thought it was very useful to have triggered this exact sensation and knowing where it was, because it meant that maybe I would be able to train my body to accept that state of fatigue (after running 12 miles) and continue. Also, the feeling cleared up fairly quickly after I stopped to walk, so I think last week the real trigger was my pointless little sprint near the end. If I avoid any sprinting during the marathon, I might well be able to avoid cramping. At least, that is the plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;a-decision-about-gatorade&#34;&gt;A decision about Gatorade&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I drank some more Gatorade back at Walnut Street, then ran home. I was really quite tired by this point and my stomach wasn&amp;rsquo;t feeling so great. I ate some actual food and eventually recovered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During this run, no gels were provided, so I drank Gatorade as my only fuel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is my final conclusion, solidifying a thought I had last week in the half marathon: &lt;em&gt;Gatorade is bad for me&lt;/em&gt;, and I should &lt;em&gt;completely&lt;/em&gt; avoid it in future runs and in the Pittsburgh Marathon! It was good to learn this for sure now. In fact, it is quite possible that some of the issues I had in the 2003 Pittsburgh Marathon were a result of Gatorade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GU gel works OK for me, but according to the official &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburghmarathon.com/Course.asp&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Marathon fluid station table&lt;/a&gt;, GU is provided only starting at mile 9.7. Therefore, I am going to pack some gels to ingest during the first 10 miles of the marathon! I will &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; drink any Gatorade!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After some ill-advised overtraining and injury this week after my half marathon, I forced myself to take two days off to recover, and used the time to diagnose possible causes of my biomechanical problems. I found some good hypotheses and possible solutions, and managed a high quality &amp;ldquo;fast finish long run&amp;rdquo; and am optimistic about my continuing training for the Pittsburgh Marathon.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The final Cathedral of Learning stair climb before the Fight for Air Climb</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/03/20/the-final-cathedral-of-learning-stair-climb-before-the-fight-for-air-climb/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Mar 2013 21:53:02 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/03/20/the-final-cathedral-of-learning-stair-climb-before-the-fight-for-air-climb/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Today, members of Team Ferlee met for a final stair climb at the Cathedral of Learning before we race in the Fight for Air Climb.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I originally had not planned to attend, because I am still in a state of recovery from all the running I&amp;rsquo;ve been doing, and had hoped to rest up till tomorrow before doing my own final stair climb. In fact, because I had not intended on a stair climb, I had done a run this morning already as my exercise for the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But circumstances made it most convenient for me to meet up with Becky in order to give her a final donation check as well as receive items to use for agreed-upon team costumes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-workout&#34;&gt;The workout&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out it was just Becky, Bill, and me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite starting from a condition of fatigue, I ended up doing four reps again. This was my most intense workout yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The three of us started with one rep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bill and I both did a crazy fast second rep: he did 6:49, which is a lot faster than the 7:26 he did &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/10/now-at-four-reps-of-the-cathedral-of-learning-stair-climb/&#34;&gt;ten days ago&lt;/a&gt;. I went close to all-out, but without knowing for sure when I could start my final sprint. Still, I finished in 7:06, a lot faster than the approximately 7:36 of ten days ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the third rep, I went at a fairly fast pace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my fourth rep, I did a series of intervals of sprints in order to figure out how long I could go into a full run. My conclusion was that I could not do more than five floors without my quads turning into jelly. That was good to find out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-next&#34;&gt;What next?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am completely beat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No more stair climbing tomorrow or Friday, because Saturday is the big day!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is unfortunate I left the fine-tuning of speed to the final week before the race, so I won&amp;rsquo;t get the full benefits of a serious training program, but optimizing the race was never of high priority to me, after all.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Only one easy rep of the Cathedral of Learning stair climb</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/03/17/only-one-easy-rep-of-the-cathedral-of-learning-stair-climb/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Mar 2013 23:55:52 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/03/17/only-one-easy-rep-of-the-cathedral-of-learning-stair-climb/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Team Ferlee met up yet again for a Cathedral of Learning stair climb workout.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I originally had not planned to even attend this time, for more than one reason:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;recovery from the crazy tough 18 mile Steel City Road Runners training run yesterday, of which I actually ran around 16 miles&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;having a Pittsburgh Recorder Society meeting to attend&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;having a St. Patrick&amp;rsquo;s Day party to attend after the recorder society meeting&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I missed not having seen the team since &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/10/now-at-four-reps-of-the-cathedral-of-learning-stair-climb/&#34;&gt;last week, when I crazily did four reps&lt;/a&gt;. I decided to show up briefly just to say hello before rushing off to the recorder society meeting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, I couldn&amp;rsquo;t help myself, and ended up doing one leisurely rep before leaving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That was actually probably a good thing to have done, because I left feeling less sore and tired. It&amp;rsquo;s definitely true in my experience that the day after a hard workout (as in my 16 mile run), one should resist the temptation to just be sedentary, and instead do something easy that increases circulation and warms the body in order to speed healing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s kind of funny to refer to an &amp;ldquo;easy&amp;rdquo; rep of doing a 36-floor stair climb, but in reality, after these months of gradual buildups, going up once at a leisurely pace is not actually hard for me at all any more. That&amp;rsquo;s encouraging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The team was amused I did this in my dress shirt and slacks (I did take off my socks and shoes and jacket and carried them in my hands while going up), but this is, after all, how I got started just before New Year!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;six-days-left&#34;&gt;Six days left&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are only six more days left till the Fight for Air Climb. I haven&amp;rsquo;t trained as much for this event as I would have liked, because my priority has been Pittsburgh Marathon training, but at some point this week I need to do some last-minute speed work in order to get at least some race sharpness for the Fight for Air Climb.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Now at four reps of the Cathedral of Learning stair climb!</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/03/10/now-at-four-reps-of-the-cathedral-of-learning-stair-climb/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Mar 2013 21:07:54 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/03/10/now-at-four-reps-of-the-cathedral-of-learning-stair-climb/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today I joined a Team Ferlee group stair climb workout at the Cathedral of Learning for the second time. &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/02/24/finally-doing-the-cathedral-of-learning-stair-climb-as-part-of-team-ferlee/&#34;&gt;Two weeks ago&lt;/a&gt; I did two reps and ten floors total.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am still in recovery from doing yesterday a really tough 12 mile Steel City Road Runners training run for the Pittsburgh Marathon, so I didn&amp;rsquo;t know what exactly I planned to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that thanks to Bill, with whom I finally climbed for the first time today, I did more than I had originally intended. In retrospect, I probably shouldn&amp;rsquo;t have, but I did, so what&amp;rsquo;s done is done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s what happened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-workout&#34;&gt;The workout&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The team did the first two reps sort of together, which meant not very fast for Bill or me. That was fine. I like socializing and going easy to warm up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the third rep, Bill decided he wanted to do a fast one, so he timed himself. I tried to follow him, but in my depleted condition had no plan to kill myself to overtake him. I just wanted to test an honest genuinely fast, but not all out, third rep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He ended up doing the third rep in 7:26, his new personal record. I did not time myself, but finished probably about ten seconds behind him, I gathered, so I did around 7:36. This was clearly the fastest I&amp;rsquo;ve also done one rep of the stair climb, not that I&amp;rsquo;ve been timing myself much in the past months (check out &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/19/why-ive-chosen-to-perform-only-two-repetitions-of-the-cathedral-of-learning-stair-climb/&#34;&gt;my reports from two months ago&lt;/a&gt;, when I timed myself just to get an idea of my baseline).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-fourth-rep&#34;&gt;My fourth rep&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone was done after the third rep, but I decided to hang around to do one last rep by myself, since I felt strangely OK even after the hard third rep; recovery from that seemed rather quick. The marathon training I&amp;rsquo;ve been doing has clearly helped with my endurance for stair climbing as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I did an untimed fourth rep just because I could.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having done four reps with good form is starting to give me confidence that in two weeks, I&amp;rsquo;ll be able to put in a good all-out effort in the Fight for Air Climb.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Finally moving up from two to three Cathedral of Learning reps</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/03/04/finally-moving-up-from-two-to-three-cathedral-of-learning-reps/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Mar 2013 22:46:38 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/03/04/finally-moving-up-from-two-to-three-cathedral-of-learning-reps/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s been over a week since my last Cathedral of Learning stair climb, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/02/24/finally-doing-the-cathedral-of-learning-stair-climb-as-part-of-team-ferlee/&#34;&gt;which I did with other members of Team Ferlee&lt;/a&gt;. Apart from being very busy generally, I&amp;rsquo;ve been focusing on getting my Pittsburgh Marathon training going.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But today after work I had some time to squeeze in a stair climb workout. I ended up finally going to &lt;em&gt;three&lt;/em&gt; full reps! The reason I felt ready to do this was that I have started to find it easier to recover from two reps, and also I have found ways to reduce my boredom, by really getting deep into monitoring the physical sensations of stair climbing: not only the details of efficiently lifting my leg and pushing up, but also even how to make turns effectively. I appreciate the subtleties of stair climbing much more than I did when I started out. So I am now mentally prepared to do more than two reps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-times&#34;&gt;My times&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;9:09, then 4:13 recovery&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;9:12, then 3:26 recovery&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;8:52&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was very conservative in going slower than usual and taking a fairly long recovery, but my goal was to get in three solid reps, with the final rep being fastest. Also, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/03/my-first-steel-city-road-runners-winter-5k-race/&#34;&gt;having just run a 5K race yesterday&lt;/a&gt;, technically today was supposed to be an &amp;ldquo;easy&amp;rdquo; workout day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Doing three reps of the Cathedral stair climb wasn&amp;rsquo;t too bad. I can see myself doing the reps faster and with less recovery time in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Finally doing the Cathedral of Learning stair climb as part of Team Ferlee</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/02/24/finally-doing-the-cathedral-of-learning-stair-climb-as-part-of-team-ferlee/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Feb 2013 18:01:42 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/02/24/finally-doing-the-cathedral-of-learning-stair-climb-as-part-of-team-ferlee/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have not been doing a lot of Cathedral of Learning stair climbing in the past month, because of life getting in the way. I did do a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/25/notes-on-exercising-while-sick-or-tired/&#34;&gt;fast single rep while tired&lt;/a&gt;, and then &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/31/doing-an-unexpected-workout/&#34;&gt;another single rep when short on time&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/02/02/an-unexpected-afternoon-tour-9-miles-of-running/&#34;&gt;a single rep in the middle of a long run&lt;/a&gt;, but that was it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, however, I started getting back into things. It&amp;rsquo;s been hard motivating myself to do the Cathedral of Learning stair climb, in part because I don&amp;rsquo;t inherently enjoy doing more than one rep. But now, I am part of an official &lt;em&gt;team&lt;/em&gt; for the Fight for Air Climb! This makes all the difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;team-ferlee&#34;&gt;Team Ferlee&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that a month ago, Chris, upon learning the Bill and I wanted to do the Fight for Air Climb, told us his coworker Becky had created a team and was looking for people to join it. So I joined it, but had been too busy, for a long time, to actually meet my fellow team members to train at the Cathedral.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But today, I finally carved out time to meet on a Sunday afternoon. I met Becky for the first time, as well as Natacha and the two Jennifers. (Bill was the only one who couldn&amp;rsquo;t make it.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have exactly a month before racing the actual Fight for Air Climb.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-workout&#34;&gt;The workout&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The plan was to do one rep and then an extra ten floors after going back down by elevator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have not been doing the stair climb for speed at all, so I was happy to do the first rep at my usual &amp;ldquo;comfortable&amp;rdquo; pace. Since each of us had a different pace, we regrouped at the top after everyone arrived. Then we took the elevator down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since we were to do just ten floors more, I decided to try to race up, to start some serious training finally. Up till now, I was just putting in a rep here or there, without doing any sprinting. I tried to &amp;ldquo;sprint&amp;rdquo; ten floors. It turns out that I can&amp;rsquo;t go all out (running two steps up a time) for ten entire floors. That&amp;rsquo;s good data to have, because in the actual race in a month, I want to know exactly how long a sprint I can actually sustain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;more-than-two-reps&#34;&gt;More than two reps!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other team members were done for the day for this workout and left.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But now that I was &amp;ldquo;warmed up&amp;rdquo;, I decided to stick around to do another full rep by myself, which I did. So this was actually the &lt;em&gt;first time in my life&lt;/em&gt; I did more than two reps: I did two reps and ten floors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over a month ago, I wrote about my deliberately &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/19/why-ive-chosen-to-perform-only-two-repetitions-of-the-cathedral-of-learning-stair-climb/&#34;&gt;limiting myself to just two repetitions of the Cathedral of Learning stair climb&lt;/a&gt;. The situation has changed now. It is time to not only add on more endurance, but also add more speed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was great to meet the team and socialize and get in some exercise also. I left feeling more motivated to continue training and meeting up. The sprint also changed things up and reminded me that it has always been part of the plan to sharpen up before race day.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An unexpected afternoon tour: 9 miles of running, 1 Cathedral of Learning stair climb, 2 chess tournaments</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/02/02/an-unexpected-afternoon-tour-9-miles-of-running/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Feb 2013 17:41:31 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/02/02/an-unexpected-afternoon-tour-9-miles-of-running/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I had an amusing, completely impromptu Saturday afternoon tour in which I ran nine miles (including a couple of miles with a friend I&amp;rsquo;ve never actually seen running before or run with before), did one repetition of the Cathedral of Learning stair climb, and visited two different chess tournaments in Pittsburgh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As of Friday evening, I had only planned to go for a run on Saturday. Here&amp;rsquo;s how I ended up on my unexpected tour instead.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/cathedral-of-learning-full.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Cathedral of Learning&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;i-did-not-run-in-the-morning&#34;&gt;I did not run in the morning&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier in the week, since I had just &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/30/why-and-how-i-am-going-to-run-the-2013-pittsburgh-marathon/&#34;&gt;signed up for the 2013 Pittsburgh Marathon&lt;/a&gt;, I had considered to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.steelcityrrc.org/scrrcevents?eventId=582142&amp;amp;EventViewMode=2&amp;amp;CalendarViewType=1&amp;amp;SelectedDate=2/16/2013&#34;&gt;early Saturday morning training run&lt;/a&gt; of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.steelcityrrc.org/&#34;&gt;Steel City Road Runners&lt;/a&gt;, but by yesterday, had felt that I didn&amp;rsquo;t want to get up early on Saturday, and also it was going to be very cold, possible as low as 10 degrees F, and I felt more comfortable running near 20 degrees F as well as close to home so that I could bail out during my own long run and get back home and warm if needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have not run more than 5 miles continuously in a while. I anticipated running at least 7 miles out in the cold, depending on how I felt. I was certain that I would not run as long as 12 miles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By afternoon, it was over 20 degrees F, so I felt fairly comfortable going out for an extended run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;chess-tournament-1-a-delayed-pittsburgh-chess-club-championship-round-3-game&#34;&gt;Chess tournament 1: a delayed Pittsburgh Chess Club Championship round 3 game&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OK, so I was exaggerating: I did not visit two complete chess tournaments on my tour. I did visit the final unplayed game of round 3 in the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/02/04/pittsburgh-chess-club-championship-2013-round-3-attack-defense-and-sacrifices/&#34;&gt;current Pittsburgh Chess Club Championship&lt;/a&gt; that is played Tuesday nights. The game was between Kurt Wallnau and Peter Jansen, and had been postponed because Kurt couldn&amp;rsquo;t make it on Tuesday. This game was important because likely the winner would be my opponent for round 4 on Tuesday, because of my current perfect score of three wins in the first three rounds so far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that shortly before I was about to go for a run in the afternoon, I got word from Kurt that he was about to play his rescheduled game with Peter at the Pittsburgh Chess Club. So I thought I would run there from home (just a bit over a mile away) to stop by and take a look before continuing on with my run.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/wallnau-jansen.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Wallnau-Jansen from round 3&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When I arrived, the game had barely begun, so I just immediately went back out to continue running.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;chess-tournament-2-2013-pa-state-game-75-championship-http-www-pitt-edu-schach-chesspa-wpastate-htm&#34;&gt;Chess tournament 2: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pitt.edu/~schach/ChessPA/wpastate.htm&#34;&gt;2013 PA State Game/75 Championship&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Originally I had planned to maybe run in Homewood Cemetery for a bit, but I suddenly changed my mind after running for a while and decided to check out the tournament in progress at the William Pitt Union, the 2013 PA State Game/75 Championship. So I ran into Oakland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But as I approached, staring me in the face was the Cathedral of Learning.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/cathedral-of-learning-on-run.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Cathedral of Learning&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;cathedral-of-learning-stair-climb&#34;&gt;Cathedral of Learning stair climb&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suddenly I decided that I would do something I had never done before, which was to do the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/31/doing-an-unexpected-workout/&#34;&gt;Cathedral of Learning stair climb&lt;/a&gt; right after having run a couple of miles. An interesting circuit!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I did one repetition of the 36 floors. I experimented with just continuing to run up the stairs, but quickly found that this was completely unsustainable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As another experiment, I did not just sit down and rest after finishing the stair climb. I stayed on my feet and immediately got on the elevator back down and out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went across the street to the chess tournament in progress. The games in the round were mostly done, so there wasn&amp;rsquo;t that much to see:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/2013-pa-state-game-75.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;2013 PA State Game/75 Championship&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;run-with-jason&#34;&gt;Run with Jason&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I ran back to the Pittsburgh Chess Club in Squirrel Hill to see what was going on there. Kurt and Peter had reached a very strange and unclear position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was planning to go back out to run some more before coming back to the club again when I spotted Jason, a chess club regular whom I have known since winter 2005 when he was one of the first people I met, in addition to &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/18/round-6-of-pittsburgh-chess-club-tournament-playing-pragmatically/&#34;&gt;Jeff&lt;/a&gt;, during my first visits to the Pittsburgh Chess Club. (He also happens to have started playing in chess tournaments again for the first time in several years!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I joked to him, &amp;ldquo;How come you weren&amp;rsquo;t out running with me?&amp;rdquo; and he said that actually, he was about to go out running again, having run &amp;ldquo;a couple of hours&amp;rdquo; &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/27/how-to-gut-out-the-tough-workout/&#34;&gt;in Frick Park&lt;/a&gt; in the morning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m still amazed that Jason so quickly became an &lt;a href=&#34;http://ultrasignup.com/results_participant.aspx?fname=Jason&amp;amp;lname=Maruccio&amp;amp;age=36&#34;&gt;ultrarunner&lt;/a&gt;. A couple of years ago we&amp;rsquo;d gone on some hikes together, and he said he was not a runner. After I hiked the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rachelcarsontrails.org/rct/challenge&#34;&gt;Rachel Carson Trail Challenge&lt;/a&gt; three years in a row, he got excited about signing up for the first time. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rachelcarsontrails.org/rct/challenge/rctc08/volunteers&#34;&gt;Abby and I volunteered&lt;/a&gt; at an aid station for the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rachelcarsontrails.org/rct/challenge/rctc08&#34;&gt;2008 Rachel Carson Trail Challenge&lt;/a&gt;, and greeted Jason as he came through our aid station. Little did I know that he would continue doing not only the Rachel Carson Trail Challenge again and again, but other endurance hikes as well. Eventually, he decided to start running, and he never looked back, and became a full-blown ultrarunner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So Jason went out for a run on the roads in Schenley Park for a couple of miles. It was out first ever run together, actually, and the first time I had ever seen him running. (We haven&amp;rsquo;t hiked together in years.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We came back to the chess club, and I saw that the Wallnau-Jansen game was still in a very strange, complex state, and I decided it was time to go home for the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;back-home&#34;&gt;Back home&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On my way back home, I started feeling really cold and hungry and tired and sore (despite having eaten a banana and some nuts an hour earlier that I had brought with me). The temperature was still around 25F, not terribly cold, but clearly I had taxed my body with my adventures. My toes were blistering and cramping up because of my footwear (I still have to really solve the problem of what shoes to wear for winter running).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was grateful to get home, eat and stretch, shower, and warm back up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did some calculations and I ran a total of about 9 miles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes it&amp;rsquo;s fun to just go and have unplanned adventures.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Doing an unexpected workout</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/01/31/doing-an-unexpected-workout/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Jan 2013 21:53:49 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/01/31/doing-an-unexpected-workout/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;After work, I had originally planned to do the Cathedral of Learning stair climb &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/25/notes-on-exercising-while-sick-or-tired/&#34;&gt;as I have been doing for some weeks now&lt;/a&gt;, stuffing my coat and sweater jacket and shoes and socks into my backpack, before heading to the Carnegie Library of Pittsburgh to pick up some items, but was running late, so I resigned myself to skipping the workout and just picking up the library items and heading home for dinner; the stair climb would have to wait for another day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But after picking up 18 pounds of books from the library, I saw a message from Abby saying that she was out for a walk and would be home later, so I decided that I had time to do one repetition of the stair climb. The &amp;ldquo;problem&amp;rdquo; was that I had a fully loaded backpack of books.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No problem. The situation just gave me an &lt;em&gt;opportunity&lt;/em&gt; for an &lt;em&gt;unexpected&lt;/em&gt; workout: doing the 36-floor stair climb with an extra 18 pounds of weight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I went and did it. The main annoyance was having to keep my shoes on and having to hold my coat and sweater jacket with my arms while going up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I did it, and felt really great afterwards, getting in a nice workout before dinner and successfully completing a new challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When things don&amp;rsquo;t go as planned, often it pays to come up with a different plan.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Notes on exercising while sick or tired</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/01/25/notes-on-exercising-while-sick-or-tired/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Jan 2013 19:42:50 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/01/25/notes-on-exercising-while-sick-or-tired/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I was a bit sick this past week, a result of overexerting myself on various projects the previous week, and also Abby herself getting sick. We have been basically fine since Thursday, but I was feeling pretty bad Sunday through Tuesday in particular.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question always comes up, when I am sick or just plain tired, &amp;ldquo;What should I do to recover as efficiently as possible?&amp;rdquo; After trial and error over the years, I&amp;rsquo;ve come to realize I have to do a couple of things:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get more &lt;em&gt;sleep&lt;/em&gt;, whatever it takes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Eat only nutritious food, no junk.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Take some supplements such as vitamin C, B, zinc, fish oil (I don&amp;rsquo;t know if this is just a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.medscape.com/viewarticle/776832&#34;&gt;placebo effect&lt;/a&gt;, but it doesn&amp;rsquo;t matter because it seems to work, I end up believing, and therefore by the placebo effect it does work).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Start canceling lower-priority near-term engagements in order to free up rest time. (In retrospect, I should have bailed out of going to the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/21/attending-the-first-openhack-pittsburgh-meeting/&#34;&gt;first OpenHack Pittsburgh meeting&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get some kind of exercise.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s the exercise that gets tricky sometimes. When one is low on energy and weakened, what should one do, if anything at all? Here are some thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-even-exercise-at-all&#34;&gt;Why even exercise at all?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A long time ago, whenever I felt sick or tired, I would use that as a reason to just shut down and not get any exercise. I had the idea that I needed to &amp;ldquo;rest&amp;rdquo;, and any activity would only weaken me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that being completely sedentary is not actually &amp;ldquo;rest&amp;rdquo;. It is actually quite harmful. Lying around or sitting around all the time is, even for those of us who are healthy, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/sitting/AN02082&#34;&gt;unnatural and damaging&lt;/a&gt;. The way our bodies work actually changes when we are immobile. Granted, if we are seriously, seriously ill, and cannot move, then that is reality, but if we are ill but able to move, then there is a question of what we can do that helps rather than hinders recovery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;breaking-down&#34;&gt;Breaking down&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I take it for granted (and from experience) that when we&amp;rsquo;re sick, we shouldn&amp;rsquo;t just push through everything we would do if we were not. The reason is that normal levels of intense exercise deliberately does some controlled breaking down of the body in order for it to adapt and grow back stronger, but if we&amp;rsquo;re weak, we may not be strong enough to withstand the breaking down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I assume that we want to dial down the intensity in some way while retaining restorative effects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;walking-works-for-me&#34;&gt;Walking works for me&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find that walking (if you&amp;rsquo;re able to walk) is probably the ideal way of getting circulation when not feeling up to running or lifting weights. It&amp;rsquo;s low impact, you breathe more, and you can change the pace and intensity at very fine increments at will. So, if I do nothing else, I&amp;rsquo;ll get in a walk, even if it&amp;rsquo;s just around the block.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;running-sometimes-doesn-t-work-for-me&#34;&gt;Running sometimes doesn&amp;rsquo;t work for me&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find that it&amp;rsquo;s sometimes tricky to run when sick. The main problem is that there is a kind of threshold below which running feels inefficient to me. If you&amp;rsquo;re running a lot slower than usual, that is inefficient and increases pounding on the joints. I&amp;rsquo;d rather walk than run much slower than usual. So I haven&amp;rsquo;t run since &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/20/thoughts-on-an-unexpected-winter-barefoot-run/&#34;&gt;my barefoot run outside on Saturday&lt;/a&gt;. Now that I&amp;rsquo;m well again, I&amp;rsquo;m quite ready to resume running. I&amp;rsquo;d rather run when I&amp;rsquo;m excited to do it and feel that it will benefit me, instead of slogging through an inefficient and possibly form-disrupting run just because I&amp;rsquo;m &amp;ldquo;supposed&amp;rdquo; to run. As &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/14/i-love-medicine-balls-video-review-gaiam-fit-ball-workout/&#34;&gt;Tanja Djelevic&lt;/a&gt; recently wrote, &lt;a href=&#34;http://tanjadjelevic.com/blog/2013/01/22/for-the-purpose-of-living-loud/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;To be a slave to the work out regimen, and have hardcore guilt for missing a work out, is in every way detrimental.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, there are definitely times when I&amp;rsquo;ve run through a minor cold or something. It all depends. When the weather is really friendly (which it hasn&amp;rsquo;t been since real winter came immediately to Pittsburgh), it&amp;rsquo;s easy to just go out for a walk and have it turn into an easy run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;strength-training-partially&#34;&gt;Strength training, partially&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Usually, when I&amp;rsquo;m sick, I don&amp;rsquo;t feel like doing a whole lot of strength training. In fact, I&amp;rsquo;ve tested myself and when I&amp;rsquo;m sick, my pullups suffer considerably.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I&amp;rsquo;ve noticed that doing short bursts of &amp;ldquo;easier&amp;rdquo; exercises is quite helpful in getting the metabolism up and preventing the quick decline that happens if you just stop doing everything for too long. I do pushups every day (partially as a result of my 2013 decision to &amp;ldquo;earn&amp;rdquo; every square of chocolate I eat by first doing pushups just before eating it; as of today, I am earning my chocolate with 26 pushups). I don&amp;rsquo;t care how many I do: the point is to do something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-cathedral-of-learning-stair-climb-what-to-do-about-that&#34;&gt;My Cathedral of Learning stair climb: what to do about that?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been reporting regularly on my Cathedral of Learning 36-floor stair climb regimen &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/19/why-ive-chosen-to-perform-only-two-repetitions-of-the-cathedral-of-learning-stair-climb/&#34;&gt;lately&lt;/a&gt;. So what happened to my routine this week when I was not feeling well?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, I was supposed to do it Monday, and I was feeling queasy enough that I decided to completely bail out of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, Wednesday I was feeling much better, and decided that I wanted to do a reduced workout. I decided that after weeks of doing two repetitions, I was going to do &lt;em&gt;just one&lt;/em&gt;. But since I was feeling on the upswing, I felt that I was strong enough to gut out doing that one repetition relatively &lt;em&gt;fast&lt;/em&gt; (not all out fast, but pretty fast going one step at a time).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did it the fastest I&amp;rsquo;ve done so far this year, in 7:20. That&amp;rsquo;s 42 seconds faster than my fastest time yet in any of the stair climbs I&amp;rsquo;ve done so far this year. I was quite exhausted afterwards, and lay down panting for over three minutes (yes, I let the timer keep running to see when I would be able to breathe normally again). Doing the stair climb at this level of intensity to me feels considerably harder than &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/08/17/the-inaugural-liberty-mile-a-review-of-pittsburghs-first-road-mile-race/&#34;&gt;running an all-out mile race&lt;/a&gt;. Stair climbing is very different from (non-hilly) running, totally burning my quads and jacking up my heart rate way, way up (I didn&amp;rsquo;t measure it but I could feel it).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Afterwards, I felt pretty good and happy to have gotten myself out of my health slump.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;stair-racing-the-sport&#34;&gt;Stair racing, the sport?!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, here&amp;rsquo;s a great article a friend just sent me today about &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2013/01/27/magazine/stair-racing-a-sport-to-make-an-ironman-whimper.html&#34;&gt;stair racing, the sport&lt;/a&gt;. I had no idea there was actually a whole worldwide professional stair racing scene!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out the Empire State Building race:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/9iSGOUTz3QA&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;prevention&#34;&gt;Prevention&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, it&amp;rsquo;s better to prevent getting sick or tired in the first place. Here&amp;rsquo;s a great article on having &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sean-johnson.com/2013/01/22/why-you-need-more-margin-in-your-life/&#34;&gt;more &amp;ldquo;margin&amp;rdquo; in your life&lt;/a&gt; that I recently encountered. I plan to track and report on how I improve my margin in my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When my body is not functioning so well because of illness or fatigue, I try to figure out how to recover, and I&amp;rsquo;ve found that some types and levels of exercise are very helpful to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do you do to keep in shape when you are feeling sick or tired? Do you have your own specific plan B, or do you wing it, or do you follow the regular plan anyway?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why I&#39;ve chosen to perform only two repetitions of the Cathedral of Learning stair climb</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/01/19/why-ive-chosen-to-perform-only-two-repetitions-of-the-cathedral-of-learning-stair-climb/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Jan 2013 11:05:28 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/01/19/why-ive-chosen-to-perform-only-two-repetitions-of-the-cathedral-of-learning-stair-climb/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Four times now in the past two weeks, I have done exactly &lt;em&gt;two&lt;/em&gt; repetitions, no less and no more, of the 36-floor Cathedral of Learning stair climb.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A friend of mine who also started the stair climbing, inspired by my one-repetition initial climb before New Year, was very excited about immediately going to two, and then after that, going to three reps. I, on the other hand, have chosen to stay at exactly two. So yesterday I did two, as planned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s why I&amp;rsquo;ve chosen to stay at exactly two.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-question-of-goals&#34;&gt;The question of goals&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even before we begin an exercise program at all, we should be very clear and explicit about our goals. It is impossible to effectively and efficiently &lt;em&gt;achieve&lt;/em&gt; our goals if they are too vague or casual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes we expend all our &amp;ldquo;serious&amp;rdquo; energy on school or work or family, but do not carry out the same discipline when working on our goals outside the really big ones that in some sense are forced upon us. Typically, in these bigger, institutionalized realms, once we get involved at all, they have their own built-in feedback mechanisms to prevent us from totally slacking off (although of course there are workaholics who ignore their family as well as those whose highest priority is leaving the office at 5 PM sharp in order to get to the real business of having dinner with the family).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having specific goals enables we to break down into &lt;em&gt;action&lt;/em&gt; steps, supported by theory and practical experience and know-how.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Example questions we have to answer about our goals:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;short term or long term?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;appearance or function?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;specific or general?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, my overall goal in exercise is always &lt;em&gt;general&lt;/em&gt;, not tied to a specific event, but I always have secondary and tertiary increasingly specific goals, that I try to make as consistent as possible with the general goal, and exploit as rewards and milestones along the way for motivation and calibration. So for example, regarding my brand new stair-climbing component of my exercise regimen:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;primary: achieve and maintain lifelong functional core strength, power, vitality&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;secondary: get in better condition to enjoy tough, hilly runs and hikes here in Western Pennsylvania&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;tertiary: perform well in my very first &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lung.org/pledge-events/pa/pittsburgh-climb-fy13/&#34;&gt;Fight for Air Climb&lt;/a&gt; competitive event in March&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hill and stair climbing has always been a weakness of mine, so this is the year when I am going to systematically improve it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;analysis-of-goals&#34;&gt;Analysis of goals&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given my goals, we see that there is a mix of possible &amp;ldquo;zones&amp;rdquo; to target. I want both endurance and power. I&amp;rsquo;m not planning to do hilly ultramarathons, so maximizing endurance is not of interest. Therefore, I am not even thinking about building up to ten reps of the Cathedral of Learning stair climb.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I want to achieve a certain amount of endurance, for the long runs and hikes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But for the shorter term, I want to optimize for the Fight for Air Climb, which is only &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lung.org/pledge-events/pa/pittsburgh-climb-fy13/local/event-information.html&#34;&gt;45 floors (897 steps)&lt;/a&gt;. Given that, doing one fast rep of the Cathedral stair climb simulates best that particular event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-process-of-conditioning&#34;&gt;The process of conditioning&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then there&amp;rsquo;s the question of how to build up to where I want to be. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t happen all at once. Progress is gradual. The muscles need to grow and become efficient. How best to train?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve chosen to do two repetitions in order to simultaneously build up endurance and power, neither maximally, while in the early stages of training. My plan is to get enough endurance from this that I can then transition to more targeted training. In particular, I expect &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; to move up to three reps, but instead, to either drop &lt;em&gt;down&lt;/em&gt; to one rep, or instead change the parameters entirely, training anaerobically with sprints upward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-record-so-far&#34;&gt;The record so far&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s my history so far for the two-rep workout that I began this year:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/04/i-had-no-choice-but-to-barefoot-climb-the-cathedral-of-learning/&#34;&gt;2013-01-04&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;9:02&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;about 16:00 recovery&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;8:58&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/07/primantis-and-the-cathedral-of-learning/&#34;&gt;2013-01-07&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;9:07&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;10:42 recovery&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;8:54&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/14/three-questions-to-ask-yourself-when-you-dont-feel-like-doing-your-scheduled-workout/&#34;&gt;2013-01-14&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;8:47&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;8:39 recovery&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;8:21&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2013-01-18 (yesterday)

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;8:46&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;5:56 recovery&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;8:02&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In four workouts so far this month, I have made improvements while adhering to some deliberate constraints:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I have always taken it &amp;ldquo;easy&amp;rdquo; during the first rep.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I have focused on making the second rep not only faster than the first rep, but faster in absolute time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I have focused on shortening the recovery time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m going to stick to two repetitions until I reach an inflection point at which point I will make some big change. Staying with two allows me to gauge my progress along certain dimensions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is your preference when you work out? What variables do you change and monitor? Number of repetitions? Recovery time? Increase in distance? Increase in speed? Increase in weight load? And why? What are your goals?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-03-04&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-03-04)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over a month later, I finally moved up to &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/04/finally-moving-up-from-two-to-three-cathedral-of-learning-reps/&#34;&gt;three reps&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-03-10&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-03-10)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/10/now-at-four-reps-of-the-cathedral-of-learning-stair-climb/&#34;&gt;four reps&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A gradual progression made the improvement seem natural rather than painful and forced.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Three questions to ask yourself when you don&#39;t feel like doing your scheduled workout</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/01/14/three-questions-to-ask-yourself-when-you-dont-feel-like-doing-your-scheduled-workout/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Jan 2013 21:28:04 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/01/14/three-questions-to-ask-yourself-when-you-dont-feel-like-doing-your-scheduled-workout/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;If, like me, you believe that you should get regular exercise, you probably have some kind of intention, or better yet, a concrete &lt;em&gt;plan&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;schedule&lt;/em&gt;, for achieving it. However, if you are like me, you are human and fallible, and also deal with unpredictable periods of stress or overwork or fatigue or laziness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is about three questions I ask myself when I am supposed to be doing a workout, but don&amp;rsquo;t feel like it. I hope this checklist will be helpful to you as it is to me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/cathedral-of-learning-two-reps/franklin-after-two-reps.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin after two reps up the Cathedral of Learning&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-cathedral-of-learning-stair-climb-plan&#34;&gt;My Cathedral of Learning stair climb plan&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One week ago, a Monday, I reported on the last time I did the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/07/primantis-and-the-cathedral-of-learning/&#34;&gt;36-floor stair climb up the Cathedral of Learning at Pitt&lt;/a&gt;. My expectation was to continue doing the stair climb twice a week, ramping up the difficulty each time in a suitable way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that last Thursday, I was &amp;ldquo;supposed to&amp;rdquo; do the stair climb.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I was going to do it Friday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I was going to do it Saturday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I was going to do it Sunday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did it today, Monday, finally. But let&amp;rsquo;s examine why I didn&amp;rsquo;t do it earlier, and why I did it today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-three-questions&#34;&gt;The three questions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The questions I ask myself honestly, when skipping a planned workout, are the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Should I do it no matter what, because I promised to?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Am I really too busy or tired, such that it would harm me if I pushed myself?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If I am busy or tired, should I make room for the workout by dropping some other commitment, because I will benefit from the workout?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;different-answers-every-day&#34;&gt;Different answers every day?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Thursday, I really was exhausted. I&amp;rsquo;d done a lot of programming all day, and had made a commitment to attend the very first &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/pittsburgh-scala-meetup&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Scala meetup&lt;/a&gt; gathering. I&amp;rsquo;d also done a really intense workout on Wednesday at the CMU gym, including rowing, weights, and treadmill running. So it was easy for me to justify taking a rest day: &lt;em&gt;recovery&lt;/em&gt; is a very important component of an exercise program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Friday, I should have been OK, except that I ran out of time and energy because I was very busy with various things, and had an early evening commitment to attend to. It is important to note that I had every intention of getting in the stair climb in the morning on Friday, and failed only because I lost a couple of hours in the morning as a result of completely unexpected things that came my way. As a result, I really was too tired. Also, I had not in fact fully recovered from my monster workout on Wednesday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Saturday, I recovered and would have gone for the Cathedral climb, but as you can guess, the loss of momentum started catching up with me. It was very warm outside, near 70F, and so I decided I should take advantage of the weather and go for a run outside instead of doing an indoor stair climb. This was a great decision to make, so I don&amp;rsquo;t regret it at all. Call it &amp;ldquo;productive procrastination&amp;rdquo;: I didn&amp;rsquo;t make progress on the Cathedral stair climb plan, but did get in a beneficial &lt;em&gt;substitute&lt;/em&gt;; if you&amp;rsquo;re going to procrastinate on something, you might as well do something genuinely useful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Sunday, I had an excuse again. My legs were actually quite sore from the road run I suddenly went and did on Saturday. I judged that I &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; do the stair climb, but that it would probably be more beneficial to me if I delayed it. Here I made a judgment call, remembering the purpose of my exercise program: it is to make me stronger, not tear me down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;today&#34;&gt;Today&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, Monday, I ran out of excuses. Was I physically able to do the climb? Yes. Was I way too tired or busy? No. OK, I am always busy, but some kinds of busy are different from other kinds. What was left? Sheer laziness. I recognized that the only excuse I had left was that &lt;em&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t actually particularly like climbing the 36 floors of the Cathedral twice&lt;/em&gt;. Some people seem to love doing this sort of thing, but I don&amp;rsquo;t really like it. I&amp;rsquo;ve learned to be mindful and present while doing it, just as with &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/01/05/how-to-enjoy-treadmill-running-treat-it-as-a-meditative-practice/&#34;&gt;treadmill running&lt;/a&gt;, but it&amp;rsquo;s not my favorite thing to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So after work, I dutifully trudged over to the Cathedral and made up my mind to enjoy the task. I planned to do two reps as I had done a week ago, with a goal of shortening the time for each rep as well as shortening the recovery between the two reps. As with last week, I went in my work clothing and backpack, stuffing my jacket and my shoes and socks (I only do the stair climb &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/04/i-had-no-choice-but-to-barefoot-climb-the-cathedral-of-learning/&#34;&gt;barefoot now&lt;/a&gt;), and proceeding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;first-rep&#34;&gt;First rep&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During my first rep, my legs quickly felt like they were burning, and I felt discouraged and frustrated, but I kept going, attempting to find a rhythm. There were a couple of other people, all wearing actual athletic shorts and shoes, in the stairways, but we were all pretty spread out, mostly, so I didn&amp;rsquo;t have to deal with passing anyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I finished in 8:47 (last week my first rep was in 9:07).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;recovery&#34;&gt;Recovery&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was really beat after the first rep. My quads and calves were burning and I was gasping for air. I rested for a while looking out the window.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/cathedral-of-learning-two-reps/franklin-after-two-reps.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Floor 36 panoramic view&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I waited till my breathing was back under control and my leg muscles were no longer completely burning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last week, I took a break of 10:42, but this week, my recovery break was 8:39.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;second&#34;&gt;Second&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the second rep, somehow I felt more peaceful, less anxious, and although I felt the burn, I accepted it. I even perceived that I had acquired a rhythm and was almost dancing up the steps. I experienced a kind of joy, a oneness with the stairway, with its unique changes in the height and number of steps, the turns, and the number of turns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I finished in 8:21, a surprise (last week I did the second rep in 8:54 after a recover period of two minutes longer).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Strangely, after I finished the second rep, I found that I felt pretty good. After several seconds, I was able to walk around normally. I don&amp;rsquo;t know exactly how to explain that after the second rep, I felt in much better condition than after the first rep. Maybe my body warmed up. Or maybe I simply became more efficient during the second time up, using less energy. Or maybe my mind was playing tricks on me because of endorphins?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, I finished the workout feeling energized and really glad that I didn&amp;rsquo;t give into laziness, and that I actually in the end had a fascinating, stimulating experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sorry, this does not mean I am going to do three reps the next time! The thought of that still frightens me. I plan to stick with just two reps for a bit longer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We all have moments when we don&amp;rsquo;t feel like doing what we planned to do and had good reasons for the original plan. When that happens, it is useful to ask three questions, rather than thoughtlessly make assumptions and go to an extreme of either being too lazy or too driven. In the end, the point is not to be able to boast of having followed some schedule, but to actually make sustainable progress. So far, I have been happy with how my Cathedral of Learning stair climbing has gone, despite the irregularities in following the plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What are you doing this year that frustrates you even though you want to see it through? What are your personal strategies for dealing with wanting to slack off?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Primanti&#39;s and the Cathedral of Learning</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/01/07/primantis-and-the-cathedral-of-learning/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Jan 2013 21:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/01/07/primantis-and-the-cathedral-of-learning/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today I was scheduled to do the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/04/i-had-no-choice-but-to-barefoot-climb-the-cathedral-of-learning/&#34;&gt;Cathedral of Learning stair climb again, two repetitions like last time&lt;/a&gt;. Since I had stayed later at work than expected, I was hungry already, so I decided I would go do the two reps and then eat a lot of food.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;John was still around at work too and he was interested in doing two reps for the first time (years ago we&amp;rsquo;d periodically done one), so we went. We had a plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;two-reps&#34;&gt;Two reps&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did both reps barefoot this time, and with a fully stuffed backpack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided to lead the way with a slightly slow pace, in order to guarantee we would go faster during the second rep. We saw two people in shorts doing reps also. Both John and I were in street clothing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first rep we did in 9:07 (on Friday, alone, I had done 9:02).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This time I timed the break, because this is actually important information for the future when comparing improvement. We took a random break of 10:42 before doing the second rep, which we did in 8:54 (at some point before floor 31, we had an opportunity to overtake the other two people, who were on their third rep, and so I decided to just kick it up a notch for the rest of the way up).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-progression-plan&#34;&gt;My progression plan&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;John liked going two steps up at a time, but I am still on one by one, because it&amp;rsquo;s easier on my quads. My intuition tells me that a good cadence is important for efficiency, and until my quads are strong enough, I cannot keep a good cadence going up two steps at a time. Right now I&amp;rsquo;m focusing on simply getting some endurance and efficiency, and increasing the number of reps. After maybe two or three weeks of this, I will work on powering up two steps at a time over maybe no more than ten floors at a time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was amused to see the man wearing one of the old Rachel Carson Trail Challenge T-shirts that I also have, from 2008 (when I was a volunteer, not a participant as I was in 2005-2007). Also, the woman said she had done the Fight for Air Climb last year and placed third in the women&amp;rsquo;s division, I think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;primanti-s&#34;&gt;Primanti&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then we went to &lt;a href=&#34;http://primantibros.com/&#34;&gt;Primanti&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/a&gt; in Oakland, as planned. I stuffed myself with a huge roast beef sandwich, my usual order when I go there (just a couple of times a year).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I heard recently that Primanti&amp;rsquo;s may be &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wpxi.com/news/news/local/primanti-bros-receives-investment-hopes-expanding-/nTmGP/&#34;&gt;expanding nationwide&lt;/a&gt;. Cool! Why should the Pittsburgh area be the only one privileged to enjoy the huge &amp;ldquo;fully loaded&amp;rdquo; sandwiches with fries and cole slaw inside?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/primantis-roast-beef-oakland.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Primanti&amp;#39;s roast beef sandwich&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>