<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Pittsburgh Camerata on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/pittsburgh-camerata/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Pittsburgh Camerata on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/pittsburgh-camerata/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>My first bobblehead doll: guess who?</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/09/20/my-first-bobblehead-doll-guess-who/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Sep 2012 09:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/09/20/my-first-bobblehead-doll-guess-who/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/j-s-bach-bobblehead.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Johann Sebastian Bach bobblehead&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I now own my first &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bobblehead&#34;&gt;bobblehead doll&lt;/a&gt;! Abby was reluctant to let me take him home, but I argued that he would inspire me in the playing of his music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So &lt;em&gt;who&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;pittsburgh-music-alliance-launch-party&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Music Alliance launch party&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;about&#34;&gt;About&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburghmusicalliance.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Music Alliance&lt;/a&gt; had a launch party that Abby and I attended, held at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.contemporarycraft.org/&#34;&gt;Contemporary Craft&lt;/a&gt; in the Strip.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Pittsburgh Music Alliance is a new collaboration of five Pittsburgh music organizations for the purpose of increasing their audience:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bachchoirpittsburgh.org/&#34;&gt;Bach Choir of Pittsburgh&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pittsburghcamerata.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Camerata&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.chathambaroque.org/&#34;&gt;Chatham Baroque&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rbsp.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Renaissance and Baroque&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pittsburghchambermusic.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Chamber Music Society&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can find more information on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/PittsburghMusicAlliance&#34;&gt;Facebook page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;food-and-information-tables&#34;&gt;Food and information tables&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/189232_472125132808229_857638441_n.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Food and tables&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As we wandered around at the party, we sampled the food and checked out the tables of the five organizations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(There are &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/media/set/?set=a.472125112808231.106189.197956923558386&amp;amp;type=3&#34;&gt;photos of the party here&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;live-music&#34;&gt;Live music&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/199595_10151047722351513_1243992903_n.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Recorder quartet&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We arrived in time to see my &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/recorder/&#34;&gt;recorder&lt;/a&gt; friends perform as a recorder quartet, playing a variety of selections. Fred, Helen, Mike, and Annie were delightful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Afterwards, members of the five music organizations took turns performing for us. Unfortunately, the acoustic situation was quite poor amidst the party conversations going on everywhere, but I enjoyed watching the people who sang and played for us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-bobbleheads&#34;&gt;The bobbleheads&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We saw approximately ten bobbleheads, each in its unopened box, sitting around. I got very excited. It turned out that they were being given away. I secretly always wanted one since seeing my friend Henry with one on top of his piano; he had one of Beethoven:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/beethoven-bobblehead.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Beethoven bobblehead&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;By the bobbleheads, there was a sheet saying something like, &amp;ldquo;Name a piece I wrote and you can take me home.&amp;rdquo; It seemed that nobody was really enforcing this, but when I offered to take one, I said the bobblehead would help me as I worked on the composer&amp;rsquo;s [flute sonatas]().&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;notes-on-johann-sebastian-bach-s-flute-sonatas&#34;&gt;Notes on Johann Sebastian Bach&amp;rsquo;s flute sonatas&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The composer whose bobblehead I got was, of course, &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/johann-sebastian-bach/&#34;&gt;Johann Sebastian Bach&lt;/a&gt;, a hero of mine in the past year during which I&amp;rsquo;ve gradually fallen in love with Baroque music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-instrument&#34;&gt;What instrument?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am faced with a conundrum when trying to play Bach&amp;rsquo;s flute sonatas: &lt;em&gt;what instrument should I use to play this music?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the case of his son, &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carl_Philipp_Emanuel_Bach&#34;&gt;CPE Bach&lt;/a&gt;, two months ago in a recital &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/28/my-first-appearance-on-a-music-recital-program/&#34;&gt;I played a movement of CPE Bach&amp;rsquo;s solo flute sonata&lt;/a&gt; using a modern flute. I feel that the nature of CPE Bach&amp;rsquo;s music, more dramatic and agitated, makes the modern flute a reasonable instrument for the piece; I feel that it is definitely reasonable to play the music on a Baroque flute instead, but that I actually prefer it on modern flute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Plus, CPE Bach&amp;rsquo;s music is much easier to play on modern flute.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, Johann Sebastian Bach&amp;rsquo;s flute sonatas, although I prefer them on Baroque flute than to modern flute, are much harder to play on Baroque flute. It turns out that I dislike almost all recordings I&amp;rsquo;ve come across of this music on modern flute, with one exception: the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pahudbach.com/&#34;&gt;recordings&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/emmanuel-pahud/&#34;&gt;Emmanuel Pahud&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;my-decision&#34;&gt;My decision&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve made an unpleasant decision. I work on the slow, easy movements of the flute sonatas on Baroque flute, and I don&amp;rsquo;t currently work on the harder movements at all. I&amp;rsquo;m still far worse on Baroque flute than on modern flute, and those fast movements are beyond me on Baroque flute. And I don&amp;rsquo;t really want to play the music on modern flute. This is just my personal choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a great time at the Pittsburgh Music Alliance season launch party. It was inspiring to see my recorder friends playing, and to see others in the early music community performing with enthusiasm. (Seeing people singing as an ensemble even got me thinking about getting into that sometime maybe.) If you enjoy fresh, vital performances of early music, check out the five organizations mentioned!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I&amp;rsquo;m grateful to now be the proud owner of a Johann Sebastian Bach bobblehead doll. Every time I see him, I remember that I must play his music with verve and soul, because he&amp;rsquo;s watching.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>