<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Philosophy on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/philosophy/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Philosophy on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/philosophy/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Report on my final day of Stoic Week 2014: the view from above</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/30/report-on-my-final-day-of-stoic-week-2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2014 22:16:07 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/30/report-on-my-final-day-of-stoic-week-2014/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s the seventh and final day of Stoic Week 2014! I am very glad I participated in the daily readings and reflections. I&amp;rsquo;ve made so many positive changes in my life already. Now it&amp;rsquo;s time to stick to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;health&#34;&gt;Health&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been spending all of the Thanksgiving long holiday weekend catching up on sleep. I have a meditation habit now and today it was warm out and I went for a run and ended up doing five miles in Frick Park. This is the longest distance I&amp;rsquo;ve run in months!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;nature-providence-the-larger-whole&#34;&gt;Nature, providence, the larger whole&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is fitting that today&amp;rsquo;s theme is the Stoic view of humanity as being embedded in something bigger, call it &amp;ldquo;nature&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;providence&amp;rdquo;. Part of why I enjoy running in the trails of Frick Park is that in its own small way, the experience puts me in touch &lt;em&gt;directly&lt;/em&gt; with something bigger than us; I encounter dogs, chipmunks, trees, creeks, leaves, mud, and even deer (not today, but Abby and I saw one during our hike there yesterday).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I honestly feel more whole and alive when I see more of nature, and not in some self-conscious sentimental way. It&amp;rsquo;s more subtle than that. And there&amp;rsquo;s nothing sentimental about those steep hills that make me gasp for air when I climb them. But I sure appreciate the cleaner air in the park than on the main urban roads of Pittsburgh! And I remember where air comes from and how fragile its quality and composition is. The big picture matters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am grateful for the organizers of Stoic Week for putting it on again this year. Here is something I&amp;rsquo;ve decided to do, to keep its spirit alive indefinitely: I will continue to explore various interpretations of Stoicism (note that I don&amp;rsquo;t feel compelled to buy into any particular school or even call myself a Stoic at all), as well as other philosophy (for example, the Zen I had begun looking into years ago) on a daily basis, to keep my mind always focused on applying principles of practical living.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Did you hear about Stoic Week this year? If you did, why did you choose to participate in it, or more interestingly, choose not to?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Report on my sixth day of Stoic Week 2014: preparing for adversity</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/29/report-on-my-sixth-day-of-stoic-week-2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Nov 2014 18:37:25 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/29/report-on-my-sixth-day-of-stoic-week-2014/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I guess death is the ultimate adversity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;whose-death-and-how-and-what-next&#34;&gt;Whose death and how and what next?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I fear death. Not only for myself, but for Abby, for her parents, for my parents, for our friends. We knew older people who have died even this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today&amp;rsquo;s Stoic theme, &amp;ldquo;preparing for adversity&amp;rdquo;, is particularly relevant to us because not only are our parents aging and already actively preparing for &amp;ldquo;what next&amp;rdquo; if they were to die or get sick and incapacitated, and trying to talk to us about such things, but also because being married, we need to have clear plans and instructions in case one of us suddenly goes. We are not invincible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;decluttering&#34;&gt;Decluttering&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing that makes us anxious is that there&amp;rsquo;s too much clutter in the house, and also clutter in the form of many random online accounts that we need to keep track of. We&amp;rsquo;ve seen how deaths in our families have caused a lot of trouble to survivors because of unfinished business, stuff left behind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel that part of preparing &lt;em&gt;mentally&lt;/em&gt; for adversity is preparing &lt;em&gt;in reality&lt;/em&gt; for adversity. I would have much more peace of mind if I knew that everything would continue as smoothly as possible at home and at work if I suddenly died.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So today I continued on a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/19/really-taking-up-the-challenge-of-minimalism/&#34;&gt;long-interrupted project&lt;/a&gt; of decluttering at home. I dug up old college course notes, exercise log books from a decade ago, and other stuff I just don&amp;rsquo;t need. Dozens of books I no longer read. I filled boxes of stuff to recycle or have Abby donate to the library. I am committed to leaving nothing accidental behind if I die, only what is purposeful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, we don&amp;rsquo;t have wills or the like yet. Time to get cracking on that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;adversity-more-generally&#34;&gt;Adversity, more generally&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel that &amp;ldquo;negative thinking&amp;rdquo; is very useful and that I could do more of it. As a software developer, anticipating failure modes helps me write better and more confident code. Playing chess, I know firsthand that wishful thinking results in big crashes when things don&amp;rsquo;t go your way. Teaching chess, I like to set up unpleasant situations and have the student struggle (in a safe, low stakes environment) to defend, as practice for real tournament chess when the strength to deal with the unexpected is a key to success in competition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;daily-habits&#34;&gt;Daily habits&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, I did meditate and exercise (more dumbbell and body weight strength training) today. Recall that yesterday I had a setback. The advantage of having once had a successful exercise routine is that when I think clearly, I am prepared for adversity, having faced it before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I appreciate the curious technique of envisioning and simulating future catastrophe in order to enable acting more calmly today. Figuring out death seems the ultimate challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How do you feel about the technique of deliberately imagining bad things? Does this seem perverse to you? Or useful?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Report on my fifth day of Stoic Week 2014: action and the reserve clause</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/28/report-on-my-fifth-day-of-stoic-week-2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2014 23:20:43 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/28/report-on-my-fifth-day-of-stoic-week-2014/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I had some setbacks today, the fifth day of Stoic Week, but dealt with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-coconut-oil-accident-yesterday-at-thanksgiving-party&#34;&gt;A coconut oil accident yesterday at Thanksgiving party&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the time we left &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/11/27/report-on-my-fourth-day-of-stoic-week-2014/&#34;&gt;yesterday&amp;rsquo;s Thanksgiving party&lt;/a&gt; in the evening, I wasn&amp;rsquo;t feeling so well. I had blamed eating that one cookie and also drinking a bit of spicy warm cider, but as unpleasant symptoms developed (you don&amp;rsquo;t need to know the details), I immediately knew what must have happened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A bit of history, years ago I experimented with &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/01/26/improving-my-breakfast-and-other-meals/&#34;&gt;using coconut oil&lt;/a&gt; but found that I could tolerate only a little bit, and in fact quickly decided to just not use it any more in cooking, after some incidents in which I experienced very unpleasant symptoms after a meal and found out that Abby had used a good amount of coconut oil in cooking. We had her limit the use of coconut oil in cooking anything I was to eat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it had been quite some time since I experienced those symptoms, but unfortunately, I suffered for over twelve hours with poor sleep overnight, and can only conclude that a large mount of coconut oil was used in Thanksgiving dinner!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-system-temporarily-wrecked-illustrating-today-s-theme&#34;&gt;My system temporarily wrecked, illustrating today&amp;rsquo;s theme&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I not only woke up late in the morning today, but was also still suffering physically, was hungry nonetheless, and grouchy. Normally I try to start my day with meditation, but I just wanted to eat breakfast. Abby had gotten up hours before me and was annoyed I had gotten up late, and snapped at me while I was bleary-eyed and trying to start eating breakfast. I snapped back, and she got very upset and disappeared.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While eating, I recognized that I had gone totally non-Stoic, and so after I finished eating and reading today&amp;rsquo;s theme on &amp;ldquo;action and the reserve clause&amp;rdquo;, I immediately went to meditate for ten minutes before talking with her again, in a much calmer mood, explaining what had been happening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went back to napping, and then before lunch time, after my final visit to the toilet, I finally felt like my coconut oil disaster was truly over and I could start my day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I felt I had &amp;ldquo;failed&amp;rdquo; in that, contrary to Stoic teaching, I had let my physical distress take over my mind and everything I was doing. I could have dealt better with my situation, acting the best I could despite my circumstance rather than giving into my foul mood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &amp;ldquo;reserve clause&amp;rdquo; in Stoicism refers to how we &lt;em&gt;act&lt;/em&gt; even though we may not like what has happened or what might happen. I did not start the morning with this attitude.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;exercise&#34;&gt;Exercise&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I eventually made up, but it really bothered me that I had started off the day so badly. I was also feeling like my muscles were trashed from yesterday&amp;rsquo;s workout (and party play with the two sisters). Later in the afternoon, we went for a hike in Frick Park and both felt better. I considered that my &amp;ldquo;exercise&amp;rdquo; for the day, a lower-intensity day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a setback in my practice of Stoicism but recovered, with even more appreciation for daily reading and study to get back on track.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How do you deal with setbacks? Do you have a system, a philosophical principle, to keep you on track?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Report on my fourth day of Stoic Week 2014: virtue and relationships with others</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/27/report-on-my-fourth-day-of-stoic-week-2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2014 21:47:45 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/27/report-on-my-fourth-day-of-stoic-week-2014/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today was Thanksgiving in the US, a surprisingly appropriate day to be in the middle of observing Stoic Week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;thanksgiving-dinner&#34;&gt;Thanksgiving dinner&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/11/27/report-on-my-third-day-of-stoic-week-2014/&#34;&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve reported on yesterday&amp;rsquo;s theme&lt;/a&gt; of self-discipline and simplicity. At Thanksgiving dinner this year, I decided for the very first time to limit what I ate. I&amp;rsquo;ve always overeaten in the past, with poor results. It was just something I did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year, I did not eat any of the cake or pumpkin pie that was offered. For dessert (after the turkey etc.), I limited myself to one scoop of pistachio gelato and one cookie. Actually, I ended up regretting that cookie, because it was more substantial and sugary than I expected, so I&amp;rsquo;ve made a note to watch myself with the cookies. The gelato I may not have needed, but I enjoyed it all the more knowing it was the one main dessert I was allowing myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;fourth-day-of-health-habits&#34;&gt;Fourth day of health habits&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s my fourth day now of daily meditation and exercise. Actually, I overdid it on the exercise today, but not intentionally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been increasing the intensity of my short (seven-minute or so) daily workouts every day, lifting heavier weights and working more muscles. What I didn&amp;rsquo;t expect was that at the Thanksgiving party, two young sisters (of ages around five and two) were bored and wanted to play, and I rather exerted myself. The older one was the ringleader. We played at scaring each other and I pretended to be sitting on the couch sleeping and suddenly spring up and boo or growl, and I accidentally pulled something in my right arm during one of these explosive, sudden movements. I also pulled my left shoulder when the two challenged me to lift them repeatedly, and the older one (tall for her age) was heavier than I expected and not so easy to repeatedly lift, given that I&amp;rsquo;d already had a workout in the morning at home. All in good fun, but left me a bit overextended.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;on-today-s-theme&#34;&gt;On today&amp;rsquo;s theme&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find sensible the Stoic teaching of developing our &amp;ldquo;natural affection&amp;rdquo;, and expanding outward from ourselves. I feel I have been the beneficiary of much good from many people in my life and am grateful for this. The Thanksgiving dinner that Abby and I went to today is one we have attended for some years now. The hosts I met through Abby, who met them (and other dinner guests) through music and dance circles. I appreciate and deeply admire the generosity that they have shown us and to many others. I look up to them as role models for the kind of genuine affection that human beings can display and share, not only with immediate family or closest friends but outward to larger communities (such as local music communities) and beyond.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tragic shooting and death that happened this year in &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shooting_of_Michael_Brown&#34;&gt;Ferguson, Missouri&lt;/a&gt; has been in the news for some months now, and this week the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shooting_of_Michael_Brown#Announcement_of_no_bill&#34;&gt;grand jury decided not to indict&lt;/a&gt;. I haven&amp;rsquo;t commented in public or in private on any of these events, or on any of the commentary about them, but I do not dismiss what has happened as irrelevant to my life. In fact, I feel that what has happened has been so important, in the biggest possible picture of what has been going on in American history for a long time, that I cannot afford to lightly spew sound bites about it. I do ask myself, how can I best talk about what I am feeling? How can I make a positive difference, in the Stoic &amp;ldquo;cosmopolitan&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;love of all humanity&amp;rdquo;? I don&amp;rsquo;t know the answer yet, but I know what is not the answer: fanning the flames of passion. But simply being silent is also not the answer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2015-01-19&#34;&gt;(Update of 2015-01-19)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wrote something in &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2015/01/19/for-martin-luther-king-jr-day-some-black-american-voices-that-spoke-to-me-recently/&#34;&gt;observation of Martin Luther King, Jr. Day&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I take seriously the Stoic call that we are ethically responsible for more than just ourselves, that we are to develop ourselves outward (not just on inner virtues) and work to honestly consider all human beings our brothers and sisters. I see how I have been treated in such a way by others through my life and aspire to expand beyond myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How do you feel about cosmopolitanism? Do you feel it is naive, that it is best to just look out after family and clan? If you have been following the Ferguson tragedy, do you easily choose a simple &amp;ldquo;side&amp;rdquo;, an &amp;ldquo;us&amp;rdquo; versus &amp;ldquo;them&amp;rdquo;?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Report on my third day of Stoic Week 2014: self-discipline and Stoic simplicity</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/27/report-on-my-third-day-of-stoic-week-2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2014 11:03:44 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/27/report-on-my-third-day-of-stoic-week-2014/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There is a reason I&amp;rsquo;m a little late in reporting on my third day of Stoic Week 2014: the theme, self-discipline and simplicity, had me cut short my intended plan of writing and publishing my thoughts at the end of each day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;health-and-self-control&#34;&gt;Health and self-control&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today&amp;rsquo;s reading for Stoic Week 2014 had us reflect on the importance of physical health and self-control in our daily routine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the third day in a row, I did a morning ten-minute sitting meditation, and noticed that my posture and breathing have improved. It took three days to notice this. It will take weeks to notice even more improvements; I know this because I&amp;rsquo;m a backslider, rather than one completely new to meditation. I imagine it must be much harder for a newcomer to adopt a practice like this where patience is required in order to experience the benefits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also kicked it up a notch with exercise. I mentioned in &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/11/25/report-on-my-second-day-of-stoic-week-2014/&#34;&gt;yesterday&amp;rsquo;s report&lt;/a&gt; that I need to do more weight training. I&amp;rsquo;m on that now. I&amp;rsquo;m making exercise a priority for the next several months in my life, at least.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve still been pretty good about refraining from unhealthy snacks. On &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/11/24/report-on-my-first-day-of-stoic-week-2014/&#34;&gt;day one&lt;/a&gt;, I noted that my work colleague brought back snacks from his first trip to Asia and I chose not to eat any of them. I opened up the bag of chips, but ate only a couple of them (in the past I have given into temptations, when confronted with a bag of chips, to eat the whole bag) and stashed the rest away. (By the way, the chips were unexceptional, tasting not much different than ordinary American potato chips, and the ingredients list was scary, with many weird chemicals included.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;sleep&#34;&gt;Sleep&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I haven&amp;rsquo;t been good with my sleep habits. I tend to stay up too late on the computer, for example. Abby wants me to have a &amp;ldquo;computer off plan&amp;rdquo; for my daily routine, but I&amp;rsquo;ve found this difficult because I like to work on personal projects (such as writing) on the computer and I find the time in the evening. I know the benefits of the &amp;ldquo;natural&amp;rdquo; life, and I&amp;rsquo;m sure Stoics would promote being a morning person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the point of this report isn&amp;rsquo;t to talk about becoming a morning person, or even so much about sleep. It&amp;rsquo;s about self-control. The reality is, yesterday when I came home from work, I was very tired. &amp;ldquo;Sleep when sleepy&amp;rdquo; is so logical and natural, yet I find that American culture does not value sleep. It seems countercultural to sleep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, I decided to simplify the evening and choose to stay off the computer (hence not writing this article). Apart from Wednesday evening being designed &amp;ldquo;us night&amp;rdquo; for Abby and me anyway, I decided that before sleeping, I would read (physical books and paper printouts) instead of use the computer, until ready to sleep. I did end up sleeping earlier. I did miss having the use of the computer to look up stuff that would have been helpful in my reading, but for this evening, at least, it was a tradeoff in favor of simplicity rather than stimulation. I&amp;rsquo;ll have to think about how to arrange my life differently if I want to continue to be more targeted in using the computer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Self-discipline and simplicity are not popular in American culture, which prizes maximization and stimulation. I don&amp;rsquo;t find it easy to maintain self-discipline, and am grateful to Stoic Week to remind me of its benefits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Is your gut impression of Stoic teachings that they want to take the fun out of your life, or that they are a guide to the truly good life? What is the balance you purposefully adopt between self-indulgence and renunciation?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Report on my second day of Stoic Week 2014: mindfulness</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/25/report-on-my-second-day-of-stoic-week-2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2014 23:50:38 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/25/report-on-my-second-day-of-stoic-week-2014/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, I reported on my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/11/24/report-on-my-first-day-of-stoic-week-2014/&#34;&gt;first day of Stoic Week 2014&lt;/a&gt;. Today, the second day&amp;rsquo;s theme was &amp;ldquo;Stoic mindfulness&amp;rdquo;. This is similar to the Buddhist teaching on mindfulness, and is basically a sound psychological observation that &amp;ldquo;You are just an impression and not at all the thing you claim to represent&amp;rdquo;: our thoughts and feelings are one thing but what we do about them is another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found it particularly useful to remember this today, because Tuesdays present an interesting challenge for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;chess&#34;&gt;Chess&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Tuesday nights, I have been playing in the latest 6-round current Tuesday night &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburghcc.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Chess Club&lt;/a&gt; tournament, one round every Tuesday. Tonight was round 4. I had experienced an extremely painful loss last week in round 3 when I was &lt;em&gt;not mindful&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://chessimprover.com/blockading-to-defend-when-things-get-tough/&#34;&gt;got carried away by emotions&lt;/a&gt;: I had an overwhelming advantage during an attack on my opponent&amp;rsquo;s King, but I allowed my excitement to cloud my judgment, make poor moves, and then worse, after I managed to recover and had the opportunity to survive with a draw, &lt;em&gt;and saw this&lt;/em&gt;, I passed it up out of wishful thinking that I could continue an attack, so I ended up losing. In chess, I face the stark reality that most losses at my level in local competition (where I am typically the top-rated player) are due to faulty psychology, rather than lack of sufficient understanding and skill. A loss of &lt;em&gt;objectivity&lt;/em&gt; (which all athletes and other performers under high pressure) is the reason we fail. Mindfulness directly addresses this all-too-human flaw.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;continuing-habits-from-yesterday&#34;&gt;Continuing habits from yesterday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, I noted that I began meditating and exercising again, because it was in my power to do so. I have continued. It&amp;rsquo;s been tricky to get going again, because my body is out of whack, but I remember to do what I can, no more, with faith that incremental progress will pay off. Instead of running, I did a &lt;a href=&#34;http://well.blogs.nytimes.com/projects/workouts/&#34;&gt;7-minute workout&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;ve lost a lot of strength over the years and plan to regain it. I have dumbbells lying around the house from when I was using them a decade ago; it&amp;rsquo;s time to get back to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;tonight-s-chess-game&#34;&gt;Tonight&amp;rsquo;s chess game&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I won a decent game tonight at the chess tournament. It was the third last to finish, taking almost four hours. I&amp;rsquo;ve played against my opponent many times before over the years, mostly winning, but the last time I played him, he held me to a draw, despite a 500-rating-point difference (which is huge). One thing that sometimes happens in tournament chess is overconfidence when facing someone who is on paper much weaker, or fear because of a past bad result. Mindfulness teaches us that although historical facts are facts, we should distance ourselves from distracting feelings about them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As in many hard-fought chess games, I experienced a range of emotions during the game. First of all, in the opening, although I was doing OK, I was frustrated that I allowed a certain kind of position I ordinarily do not allow, because of an oversight. Instead of kicking myself, I focused to do what I could with what I had, assessing that even though I did not want that position, it was actually still OK for me. (Actually, computer analysis afterwards showed that I was more than OK, so I was still more pessimistic than warranted during the game.) In the middlegame, I emerged with an advantage, but then faced a curious choice. My opponent gave me an opportunity to win some material (a Rook for a Bishop and Pawn) at the expense of destroying my Pawn structure and therefore creating good chances for a draw. At the time, I saw no better winning try, so I went for it, deciding that, unlike last week, I was going to settle for a draw if my opponent could prove he could defend; I simply made sure to play soundly and not recklessly. It turned out that he cracked eventually and I won. I was pleased that I remained psychologically strong in the game and was rewarded accordingly. (For those of you interested in the technical details of the game, I will be annotating it in an upcoming article I will write for &lt;a href=&#34;http://chessimprover.com/category/franklin-chen/&#34;&gt;my weekly column in The Chess Improver&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;heavy-traffic&#34;&gt;Heavy traffic&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another thing: when driving home from work to eat dinner before the chess game, I noticed that the traffic was unusually bad. Mindfulness is always helpful when facing stressful situations like this. I was upset with myself for not anticipating apparent pre-Thanksgiving-holiday traffic and therefore being pressed for time to get home and eat dinner before playing chess. I decided to let go of my self-annoyance because it wasn&amp;rsquo;t going to help me get home any sooner and would just sap my mental energy I needed for my game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mindfulness is something I&amp;rsquo;ve had prior experience in trying to adopt well before I even read about Stoicism. But having a daily theme and reading during Stoic Week has been surprisingly helpful in keeping me aware.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Are you familiar with the concept of mindfulness and the scientific underpinnings of it? If so, do you deliberately practice it? Do you have misgivings about it?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Report on my first day of Stoic Week 2014</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/24/report-on-my-first-day-of-stoic-week-2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2014 22:30:51 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/24/report-on-my-first-day-of-stoic-week-2014/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Last year, I heard about the first Stoic Week, &lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.exeter.ac.uk/stoicismtoday/stoic-week-2013/&#34;&gt;Stoic Week 2013&lt;/a&gt;, but did not participate because I was distracted at the time and did not feel like focusing. This week, I decided it was time to sign up for &lt;a href=&#34;http://modernstoicism.com/course/view.php?id=5&#34;&gt;Stoic Week 2014&lt;/a&gt;, and I did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-my-interest-in-stoicism&#34;&gt;Why my interest in Stoicism?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve mentioned Stoicism only briefly in my blog: once in 2012 when &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/11/22/thanking-the-best-of-all-possible-worlds/&#34;&gt;thinking about Thanksgiving&lt;/a&gt; and once earlier this year after &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/01/17/hiroo-onoda-and-the-six-million-dollar-man/&#34;&gt;rewatching an old TV episode&lt;/a&gt;. As I mentioned, it was in 2011, upon reading a book on Stoicism, that I made some major changes in my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that a couple of weeks ago, I decided to make major changes in my life again, but not while thinking about Stoicism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over a year ago, my meditation practice fell apart, and I never really regained it. As a result, my thoughts and habits have become disordered, I have felt. For example, I stopped writing regularly for my blog. I spent too much time on Facebook and Twitter instead, being distracted, annoyed, and worse, behaving in ways that I later came to feel counterproductive. I did &amp;ldquo;quit&amp;rdquo; Facebook in July, and also &amp;ldquo;quit&amp;rdquo; Twitter some weeks ago (part of the big life changes I set in motion), but still, I have felt ungrounded. I decided Stoic Week 2014 would be a good opportunity for me to return to the contemplative life that Buddhism and Stoicism in their different ways aspire to and that I had forgotten.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-i-did-the-first-day-of-stoic-week-2014&#34;&gt;What I did the first day of Stoic Week 2014&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, as I started the first day of Stoic Week 2014, I began by meditating ten minutes, Zen style. &lt;em&gt;This was my first meditation session in weeks&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I read the assigned text for today in the Stoic Week handbook, on &amp;ldquo;What is in our power?&amp;rdquo; A basic principle of Stoicism is that we should know what is under our control and what is not, and summarily refuse to dwell on or resent what is not under our control, and focus on making good decisions about what is under our control. A very simple but powerful concept, especially in a world in which it is easy to get annoyed or angry about many things we hear about in the news or encounter in our daily lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My exercise habit has been very spotty for months now. Well, today I reflected that, what the hell, it is completely under my control whether I choose to exercise or not, so why am I wasting this precious freedom? Some people don&amp;rsquo;t have this freedom. Others, including prisoners in jail, have little freedom but make use of what they have, and &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/17/the-joys-of-convict-conditioning-bodyweight-exercising/&#34;&gt;they exercise&lt;/a&gt;! It happened to be warm outside today, so I really had no excuse. I went for a run in Frick Park. It was short, less than three miles long, but I went. &lt;em&gt;This was my first run in weeks&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was my turn to cook today at home, so I made a substantial beef casserole dish. Abby has (rightfully) complained in the past when I didn&amp;rsquo;t completely clean up after cooking. Well, today I thought to myself that it is completely within my control whether I choose to attend to the details of cleanup as much as I attend to the details of using our skillets and baking pans. So I cleaned up as well as I could.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have not been feeling very well physically for weeks now since an incident involving emergency dental work that somehow resulted in complications. I am still in recovery. OK, so it is not under my control that I am not in good health right now. But what is under my control? After lunch I took a nap, because I felt like I needed it. I have been skimping on naps, but this is stupid, because I know that sleep is the best restorative practice when ill. It is under my control whether I choose to set aside time to sleep as needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At work, a colleague just came back from his first trip in Asia. He gave me samples of some odd snacks: chips, cookies, and candy. In recent months, I would have opened them up and eaten them on the spot. Indeed, I have been having problems with eating too many snacks for no rational reason. Today, I decided that it is up to me whether I choose to give in to random cravings or temptations, and so I chose to put the snacks aside for later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After work, I went to a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/Pittsburgh-Code-Supply/events/210396972/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Code and Supply Build Night&lt;/a&gt;, where food was served. Apart from a Thanksgiving dinner (!), some kind of cake lurked around. I took one glance, and chose not to even look at it again until leaving (when it was already all eaten).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leaving Build Night, I found myself annoyed that it was taking forever for the pedestrian light to change, but caught myself and observed that, first of all, the cycle is as it is, beyond my control; and second, I had mistakenly assumed that someone had pressed the button, so it was my fault I had to wait so long. I pressed the button and eventually got to cross. Next, while driving home, I made the mistake of driving behind a bus, which kept stopping. I got annoyed, not by the bus, but by myself, for mistakenly driving on the wrong street rather than the other one that does not have this problem; I got annoyed that I was too lazy to make a U-turn on the street I was parked on in order to get to that other street. But I stopped myself when I realized that what was done was done, and I simply had to endure the rest of the drive home behind the bus because it was not going to save any more time if I detoured around it late in the game: the best I can do is to be more careful in the future when making choices while driving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I felt I improved my life today by keeping in mind the fundamental Stoic principle of observing what is not under my control and what is under my control. I look forward to continuing to adopt this outlook for the rest of the week, and beyond that.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ransoms, hypocrisy, and bourgeois virtues</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/14/ransoms-hypocrisy-and-bourgeois-virtues/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2014 22:18:36 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/14/ransoms-hypocrisy-and-bourgeois-virtues/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I saw a provocative article, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nybooks.com/blogs/nyrblog/2014/nov/12/case-for-paying-ransoms/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Case for Paying Ransoms&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, that argued that noted that European hostages of terrorist groups, unlike American and British hostages, tend to be returned alive, thanks to European governments paying ransoms. The US and UK governments, however, have a public policy of not negotiating with terrorists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It appears that &amp;ldquo;governments like the Spanish, the French, and the Italian, have simply found other, more clandestine and covert ways of making such payments, through sudden increases in aid budgets and the like. The next move these governments make is simply to &lt;em&gt;deny&lt;/em&gt; that such payments have been made.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this brings up a dilemma (which of course comes up in action films all the time):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Is it better to (a) remain morally consistent, refuse negotiation and ransom payment to an allegedly evil organization, but watch your citizens get beheaded? Or (b) sign up to a principled agreement not to negotiate with &#34;terrorists,&#34; but then negotiate nonetheless, pay a large amount of money to release the citizens of your country, and simply deny the fact publicly?
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;in-praise-of-hypocrisy&#34;&gt;In praise of hypocrisy?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The article argued for the second choice, which is to be hypocritical and deny negotiation while actually engaging it: &amp;ldquo;The effectiveness of the strategy depends on the fact that it is not openly acknowledged, and indeed that it is repeatedly repudiated in official statements and in international agreements by the governments in question.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When reading this, I was not particularly shocked, because hypocrisy is everywhere and is quite official. In fact, almost all American news and political discourse revolves around hypocrisy. This is apparent when it comes to sex scandals, corporate payola, NSA domestic surveillance, complaints about government spending, railing against privatization of education while sending one&amp;rsquo;s own children to private schools, and so on. I get the impression that Americans give much more priority to the &lt;em&gt;appearance&lt;/em&gt; of &amp;ldquo;moral outrage&amp;rdquo; than other people in the world. Nobody wants to be pointed out as a hypocrite, it seems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trouble is that hypocrisy is arguably the single most important bourgeois &amp;ldquo;virtue&amp;rdquo;, the collective decision to look the other way when confronted with something disturbing, to make a euphemism of it if it is seen at all. The &amp;ldquo;liberal&amp;rdquo;, tolerant society depends to a great deal on hypocrisy. This is how &amp;ldquo;tolerance&amp;rdquo; works: claiming to believe one thing while not acting entirely consistently with that claim. For example, religious tolerance was hard won: remember when &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Know_Nothing&#34;&gt;Catholicism were considered anti-American by many&lt;/a&gt;? Was the solution really that Protestants decided Catholicism was OK after all? In part, perhaps, but also in part a result of hypocrisy. Remember when &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.today.com/id/4224452/ns/today-entertainment/t/mel-gibson-says-his-wife-could-be-going-hell/&#34;&gt;Mel Gibson said his (then) wife was doomed to go to hell&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A certain level of hypocrisy seems necessary for a liberal society. Many people who claim to believe abortion is baby murder tend to still be OK eating at a restaurant owned by someone who believes otherwise. Many &amp;ldquo;progressive&amp;rdquo; programmers seem to have no problem with buying Apple products despite suspect sweatshop labor practices at Foxconn. And so forth: in fact, capitalism itself is reliant on hypocrisy to stay alive. If people bought and sold mostly with their supposed moral conscience rather than with their wallets, markets would fall apart. Overall, nobody cares whether the gas station owner is doing drugs, beating his wife, or hates their ethnicity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is there an alternative to hypocrisy that doesn&amp;rsquo;t just lead back to all-out wars among every possible faction believing in their principles so strongly that they are willing to die and kill for them? I don&amp;rsquo;t know. I just know that on some uncomfortable level, &lt;em&gt;complaining about hypocrisy is the essence of hypocrisy itself&lt;/em&gt;. This may just be how human beings have to operate. But we&amp;rsquo;re not supposed to openly admit that, are we? It would be like going to your dear friend&amp;rsquo;s parents&amp;rsquo; home for dinner and then screaming at them for being animal killers for serving meat if you&amp;rsquo;re an ethical vegetarian. That would be such &lt;em&gt;bad manners&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How do you feel about hypocrisy? Do you acknowledge its social value? Do you admit to it yourself? Do you call out those you consider hypocrites?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2014-11-19&#34;&gt;(Update of 2014-11-19)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nybooks.com/blogs/nyrblog/2014/nov/19/ransoms-real-cost/&#34;&gt;critique&lt;/a&gt; of the original article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2014-12-05&#34;&gt;(Update of 2014-12-05)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a related topic, here is an interesting &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.theguardian.com/news/2014/dec/04/-sp-case-against-human-rights&#34;&gt;critique of &amp;ldquo;human rights&amp;rdquo; by Eric Posner&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is there a grounding problem in empirical computational linguistics?</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/05/13/is-there-a-grounding-problem-in-empirical-computational-linguistics/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2014 20:28:29 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/05/13/is-there-a-grounding-problem-in-empirical-computational-linguistics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I saw an announcement for a lunch talk at CMU with the intriguing title &amp;ldquo;Theoretical and Practical Grounding in Empirical Computational Linguistics&amp;rdquo;, by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cl.uni-heidelberg.de/~riezler/&#34;&gt;Stefan Riezler&lt;/a&gt; of Heidelberg University.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abstract: &lt;strong&gt;Philosophy of science has pointed out a circularity problem in empirical sciences that arises if all known measuring procedures for a quantity of a theory presuppose the validity of this theory. We discuss how this problem relates to empirical computational linguistics, and define a criterion of T-non-theoretical grounding as guidance to avoid such circularities. We exemplify how this criterion can be met by crowdsourcing, task-related data annotation, or data in the wild. In particular, we illustrate the benefits of grounded learning in the area of statistical machine translation, e.g., by grounding machine translation in semantic parsing and in cross-lingual information retrieval.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/nlp-2014-05-13/presentation.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I attended the talk because of my long-standing interest in the philosophy of science, a subject I spent a lot of time studying in college (although my degree was in physics).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-problem&#34;&gt;The problem&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When using machine learning, there is a fundamental issue of whether one can run around in circles during feature discovery. For example, if you have labeled data, and you train a system, and then claim to find useful features which are actually just equivalent to what you were given, then there is a problem. Your system may not generalize to unseen data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Riezler opened with a simple example of the circularity problem of grounding in science involving Archimedean statics. Suppose you measure mass through use of a balance scale. Then how do you evaluate an empirical claim about the theory of Archimedean statics? If you use a balance scale, there is a circularity in the use of &lt;a href=&#34;http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/theoretical-terms-science/&#34;&gt;theoretical terms&lt;/a&gt;. Is there a way out? Yes, there is: use a different theory to &lt;em&gt;ground&lt;/em&gt; your terms: make a distinction, for a theory T, between T-theoretical and T-non-theoretical terms, and make a correspondence (some kind of &amp;ldquo;transfer&amp;rdquo;), so that non-circular progress can actually be made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his talk, Riezler presented methods of learning for machine translation that he claimed to be free of the circularity problem. One method is &amp;ldquo;naive&amp;rdquo; coders (rather than expert coders) and crowdsourcing. Another is semantic parsing in which evaluation is based on a real-world task, getting the right answer according to a gold standard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;questions&#34;&gt;Questions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some interesting questions were posed by the audience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;isn-t-circularity-only-a-problem-for-science-but-not-for-engineering-systems&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Isn&amp;rsquo;t circularity only a problem for science, but not for engineering systems?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Answer: a system that fails to generalize is a problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;how-can-we-know-if-we-are-doing-it-wrong&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;How can we know if we are doing it wrong?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Answer: talk to a social scientist!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;cookies&#34;&gt;Cookies&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cookies were available as part of lunch. In accordance with my promise, here are photos of two I ate:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/nlp-2014-05-13/cookie1.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/nlp-2014-05-13/cookie2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They were big. I should probably have eaten just the first one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not a working computational linguist, and it&amp;rsquo;s been over a decade since the only course I&amp;rsquo;ve taken in computational linguistics at CMU (in 2003), so I can&amp;rsquo;t pretend that I entirely followed the presentation, but I found interesting his attempt to apply philosophical considerations toward generating new ways to tackle empirical computational linguistics, and hope more people take philosophy seriously in the field of machine learning in general. I have an impression that some practitioners just sling data and numbers around, but may not be aware of the pitfalls of the grounding problem.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hiroo Onoda and the Six Million Dollar man: what does it mean to know how to die or live?</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/01/17/hiroo-onoda-and-the-six-million-dollar-man/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2014 22:50:24 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/01/17/hiroo-onoda-and-the-six-million-dollar-man/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A news article just came my way that fascinated me: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.washingtonpost.com/world/asia_pacific/hiroo-onoda-japanese-soldier-who-hid-in-philippine-jungle-for-29-years-dies-at-91/2014/01/17/7016d806-7f8b-11e3-93c1-0e888170b723_story.html&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Hiroo Onoda, Japanese soldier who hid in Philippine jungle for 29 years, dies at 91&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, I had long heard of &amp;ldquo;stragglers&amp;rdquo; who did not realize that a war or persecution was over and kept fighting or fleeing, away from &amp;ldquo;civilization&amp;rdquo;, unaware of how the rest of the world was changing. The most recent case of that I read about was a really moving story, astonishing and sad, about an Old Believer &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.smithsonianmag.com/history/for-40-years-this-russian-family-was-cut-off-from-all-human-contact-unaware-of-world-war-ii-7354256/&#34;&gt;Russian family that hid out for forty years&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in the case of this Japanese soldier, although I had not earlier read about his particular story, I instantly remembered an old TV episode I watched as a young child that was an astoundingly memorable episode, whose details are etched in my mind. This was &lt;a href=&#34;http://bionic.wikia.com/wiki/The_Last_Kamikaze&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Last Kamikaze&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, an episode of &amp;ldquo;The Six Million Dollar Man&amp;rdquo; TV series that I watched religiously back in the day. This episode was about a Japanese straggler from World War II. &lt;strong&gt;It changed my life forever.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-last-kamikaze&#34;&gt;The Last Kamikaze&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amazingly, I found the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dailymotion.com/video/xtp86d_the-six-million-dollar-man-the-last-kamikaze-jan-19-1975_shortfilms&#34;&gt;whole episode online&lt;/a&gt;. You may want to watch this episode before reading my spoilers below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe frameborder=&#34;0&#34; width=&#34;480&#34; height=&#34;270&#34; src=&#34;http://www.dailymotion.com/embed/video/xtp86d&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dailymotion.com/video/xtp86d_the-six-million-dollar-man-the-last-kamikaze-jan-19-1975_shortfilms&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;The Six Million Dollar Man&amp;ndash;The Last Kamikaze&amp;hellip;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;i&gt;by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dailymotion.com/dwyerjoss&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;dwyerjoss&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;discussion-with-spoilers&#34;&gt;Discussion, with spoilers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It made a profound impact on me when I watched it over 30 years ago. First, there was the exciting action aspect, of course (all the booby traps in the jungle). But mostly, it was in some sense my first exposure to something from Japanese culture, in particular regarding notions of &amp;ldquo;honor&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OK, it was just TV, and American 1970s TV at a time when there weren&amp;rsquo;t a lot of Asians even being portrayed at all, but in retrospect, it wasn&amp;rsquo;t bad at all. I was confused by the attempted &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Seppuku&#34;&gt;seppuku&lt;/a&gt;, and my parents had to explain what that was about (not being Japanese, but actually living during World War II in Taiwan under Japanese rule and remembering the Allies defeating Japan).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;death-and-life&#34;&gt;Death and life&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the real climax of the episode was when Steve Austin intervenes in the attempt and saves the character Kuroda, saying &amp;ldquo;You have shown that you know how to die. Now for the sake of your enemies, show me that you know how to live.&amp;rdquo; I reflected on what it might mean to &amp;ldquo;know how to die&amp;rdquo; or to &amp;ldquo;know how to live&amp;rdquo;. In that moment of the TV episode, &lt;em&gt;my life was changed forever&lt;/em&gt;. I was around seven years old at the time. I suppose you could say I lost my &amp;ldquo;innocence&amp;rdquo; at that exact moment in time; I became a philosopher then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought a lot about life and death after that episode. What is the meaning of life, or of death? And most of all, what do we choose, and why do we choose? What is honor?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My questioning may have begun at seven, but it has not yet ended. I do not have the final answer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that one TV episode got me started on a lifelong philosophical journey. When I was older, I studied the Christian Bible, which is all about exploring what it means to live and die: Jesus dying and living again, and the command to be &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=Romans%206&#34;&gt;dead to sin but alive in Christ&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, there is also the controversial choice of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Socrates&#34;&gt;Socrates&lt;/a&gt; to commit suicide, which I read various conflicting opinions about: when I had just finished high school, the book &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ifstone.org/trial_of_socrates.php&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Trial of Socrates&amp;rdquo; by I.F. Stone came out&lt;/a&gt; that was very provocative and turned me against Socrates, whom I had earlier considered a hero, from reading Plato&amp;rsquo;s dialogues about him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was also bothered but fascinated by the lore that &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gautama_Buddha&#34;&gt;Gautama Buddha&lt;/a&gt; deliberately ate rotting food in order not to offend his host, and died as a result.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And what of the controversial mass suicide by Jews at &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Masada&#34;&gt;Masada&lt;/a&gt;? Or that of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Self-immolation&#34;&gt;self-immolating&lt;/a&gt; Buddhist monks in Vietnam?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In college, I took a philosophy course by &lt;a href=&#34;http://philosophy.columbia.edu/directories/faculty/frederick-neuhouser&#34;&gt;Frederick Neuhouser&lt;/a&gt; and studied Nietzsche, who had his character Zarathustra say, &lt;a href=&#34;http://4umi.com/nietzsche/zarathustra/21&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Die at the right time&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. I was profoundly affected by the challenges that Nietzsche threw at his readers. That course changed my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Very recently, Stoicism has become popularized as a living philosophy for today, with proponents such as &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ttbook.org/book/transcript/transcript-william-irvine-stoic-life&#34;&gt;William Irvine&lt;/a&gt;, who talks about &amp;ldquo;contemplation of death&amp;rdquo;. I very much enjoyed his book &lt;a href=&#34;http://global.oup.com/academic/product/a-guide-to-the-good-life-9780195374612&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;A Guide to the Good Life: the Ancient Art of Stoic Joy&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; not long after it came out; reading it in early 2011, I changed the course of my life. (Don&amp;rsquo;t forget that &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Seneca_the_Younger&#34;&gt;Seneca&lt;/a&gt; was also forced to commit suicide.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am fascinated by deliberate, reasoned decisions about life and death.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hiroo Onoda and the Six Million Dollar man: what does it mean to know how to die or live?</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/01/17/hiroo-onoda-and-the-six-million-dollar-man/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2014 22:50:24 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/01/17/hiroo-onoda-and-the-six-million-dollar-man/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A news article just came my way that fascinated me: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.washingtonpost.com/world/asia_pacific/hiroo-onoda-japanese-soldier-who-hid-in-philippine-jungle-for-29-years-dies-at-91/2014/01/17/7016d806-7f8b-11e3-93c1-0e888170b723_story.html&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Hiroo Onoda, Japanese soldier who hid in Philippine jungle for 29 years, dies at 91&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, I had long heard of &amp;ldquo;stragglers&amp;rdquo; who did not realize that a war or persecution was over and kept fighting or fleeing, away from &amp;ldquo;civilization&amp;rdquo;, unaware of how the rest of the world was changing. The most recent case of that I read about was a really moving story, astonishing and sad, about an Old Believer &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.smithsonianmag.com/history/for-40-years-this-russian-family-was-cut-off-from-all-human-contact-unaware-of-world-war-ii-7354256/&#34;&gt;Russian family that hid out for forty years&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in the case of this Japanese soldier, although I had not earlier read about his particular story, I instantly remembered an old TV episode I watched as a young child that was an astoundingly memorable episode, whose details are etched in my mind. This was &lt;a href=&#34;http://bionic.wikia.com/wiki/The_Last_Kamikaze&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Last Kamikaze&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, an episode of &amp;ldquo;The Six Million Dollar Man&amp;rdquo; TV series that I watched religiously back in the day. This episode was about a Japanese straggler from World War II. &lt;strong&gt;It changed my life forever.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-last-kamikaze&#34;&gt;The Last Kamikaze&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amazingly, I found the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dailymotion.com/video/xtp86d_the-six-million-dollar-man-the-last-kamikaze-jan-19-1975_shortfilms&#34;&gt;whole episode online&lt;/a&gt;. You may want to watch this episode before reading my spoilers below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe frameborder=&#34;0&#34; width=&#34;480&#34; height=&#34;270&#34; src=&#34;http://www.dailymotion.com/embed/video/xtp86d&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dailymotion.com/video/xtp86d_the-six-million-dollar-man-the-last-kamikaze-jan-19-1975_shortfilms&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;The Six Million Dollar Man&amp;ndash;The Last Kamikaze&amp;hellip;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;i&gt;by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dailymotion.com/dwyerjoss&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;dwyerjoss&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;discussion-with-spoilers&#34;&gt;Discussion, with spoilers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It made a profound impact on me when I watched it over 30 years ago. First, there was the exciting action aspect, of course (all the booby traps in the jungle). But mostly, it was in some sense my first exposure to something from Japanese culture, in particular regarding notions of &amp;ldquo;honor&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OK, it was just TV, and American 1970s TV at a time when there weren&amp;rsquo;t a lot of Asians even being portrayed at all, but in retrospect, it wasn&amp;rsquo;t bad at all. I was confused by the attempted &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Seppuku&#34;&gt;seppuku&lt;/a&gt;, and my parents had to explain what that was about (not being Japanese, but actually living during World War II in Taiwan under Japanese rule and remembering the Allies defeating Japan).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;death-and-life&#34;&gt;Death and life&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the real climax of the episode was when Steve Austin intervenes in the attempt and saves the character Kuroda, saying &amp;ldquo;You have shown that you know how to die. Now for the sake of your enemies, show me that you know how to live.&amp;rdquo; I reflected on what it might mean to &amp;ldquo;know how to die&amp;rdquo; or to &amp;ldquo;know how to live&amp;rdquo;. In that moment of the TV episode, &lt;em&gt;my life was changed forever&lt;/em&gt;. I was around seven years old at the time. I suppose you could say I lost my &amp;ldquo;innocence&amp;rdquo; at that exact moment in time; I became a philosopher then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought a lot about life and death after that episode. What is the meaning of life, or of death? And most of all, what do we choose, and why do we choose? What is honor?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My questioning may have begun at seven, but it has not yet ended. I do not have the final answer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that one TV episode got me started on a lifelong philosophical journey. When I was older, I studied the Christian Bible, which is all about exploring what it means to live and die: Jesus dying and living again, and the command to be &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=Romans%206&#34;&gt;dead to sin but alive in Christ&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, there is also the controversial choice of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Socrates&#34;&gt;Socrates&lt;/a&gt; to commit suicide, which I read various conflicting opinions about: when I had just finished high school, the book &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ifstone.org/trial_of_socrates.php&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Trial of Socrates&amp;rdquo; by I.F. Stone came out&lt;/a&gt; that was very provocative and turned me against Socrates, whom I had earlier considered a hero, from reading Plato&amp;rsquo;s dialogues about him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was also bothered but fascinated by the lore that &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gautama_Buddha&#34;&gt;Gautama Buddha&lt;/a&gt; deliberately ate rotting food in order not to offend his host, and died as a result.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And what of the controversial mass suicide by Jews at &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Masada&#34;&gt;Masada&lt;/a&gt;? Or that of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Self-immolation&#34;&gt;self-immolating&lt;/a&gt; Buddhist monks in Vietnam?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In college, I took a philosophy course by &lt;a href=&#34;http://philosophy.columbia.edu/directories/faculty/frederick-neuhouser&#34;&gt;Frederick Neuhouser&lt;/a&gt; and studied Nietzsche, who had his character Zarathustra say, &lt;a href=&#34;http://4umi.com/nietzsche/zarathustra/21&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Die at the right time&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. I was profoundly affected by the challenges that Nietzsche threw at his readers. That course changed my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Very recently, Stoicism has become popularized as a living philosophy for today, with proponents such as &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ttbook.org/book/transcript/transcript-william-irvine-stoic-life&#34;&gt;William Irvine&lt;/a&gt;, who talks about &amp;ldquo;contemplation of death&amp;rdquo;. I very much enjoyed his book &lt;a href=&#34;http://global.oup.com/academic/product/a-guide-to-the-good-life-9780195374612&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;A Guide to the Good Life: the Ancient Art of Stoic Joy&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; not long after it came out; reading it in early 2011, I changed the course of my life. (Don&amp;rsquo;t forget that &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Seneca_the_Younger&#34;&gt;Seneca&lt;/a&gt; was also forced to commit suicide.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am fascinated by deliberate, reasoned decisions about life and death.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why I hate calling myself &#34;pragmatic&#34; but do</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/06/30/why-i-hate-calling-myself-pragmatic-but-do/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Jun 2013 22:57:55 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/06/30/why-i-hate-calling-myself-pragmatic-but-do/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;For many years, I resisted calling myself &amp;ldquo;pragmatic&amp;rdquo;, even though the evolution of my personal philosophy as well as my concrete actions have for much longer been one that broadly should be called pragmatism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The thing is that for much of my life, I was &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; a pragmatist in &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; sense of the word. I think it was only about twenty years ago that I began my journey toward some of the characteristics of pragmatism, both in the broad popular sense and in the philosophical sense, and it was only in the past couple of years that I&amp;rsquo;ve finally embraced the adjective as an accurate description of my attitude toward not only &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pragmatism&#34;&gt;philosophical issues&lt;/a&gt; (about which I will not say more in this post), but also to living and decision-making.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was dragged kicking and screaming into the world of pragmatism, because for some reason, I was born with a propensity for everything that is not pragmatic. I&amp;rsquo;ve taken the official &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Myers-Briggs_Type_Indicator&#34;&gt;Myers-Briggs Type Indicator&lt;/a&gt; a couple of times, including the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MBTI_Step_II&#34;&gt;MBTI Step II&lt;/a&gt;, and each time I come out as &lt;strong&gt;INFP&lt;/strong&gt;, which some call the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.personalitypage.com/INFP.html&#34;&gt;Idealist&lt;/a&gt;, ha! (Note: I don&amp;rsquo;t actually take the MBTI terribly seriously, but mention it because a lot of people know about it.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;false-pragmatism&#34;&gt;False &amp;ldquo;pragmatism&amp;rdquo;?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main reason I resist the word &amp;ldquo;pragmatic&amp;rdquo; is that all my life, I have seen it used by people to justify anything in the world they do, usually in conjunction with calling critics &amp;ldquo;idealistic&amp;rdquo; or some other such name. The word therefore not only lost its meaning for me, but even acquired a negative connotation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Very often, for example, someone in power will use the word &amp;ldquo;pragmatic&amp;rdquo; in order to shut out dissent and maintain the status quo, as though considering &amp;ldquo;other&amp;rdquo; ideas or implementing them is &lt;em&gt;by itself&lt;/em&gt; suspect. My personal definition of &amp;ldquo;pragmatic&amp;rdquo; includes objectively weighing costs and benefits, opportunities and risks. So when I hear someone &lt;em&gt;emotionally&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;angrily&lt;/em&gt; calling himself a &amp;ldquo;pragmatist&amp;rdquo;, I completely discount that person, whether it&amp;rsquo;s a politician justifying not taking a stand or whether it&amp;rsquo;s a bureaucracy unwilling to experiment with some changes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, I have found that a lot of people who call themselves &amp;ldquo;pragmatic&amp;rdquo; have a very cynical view of human nature and don&amp;rsquo;t believe in people, don&amp;rsquo;t believe in possibilities. So &amp;ldquo;pragmatic&amp;rdquo; for them means not speaking up about injustice, discouraging their children from pursuing some &amp;ldquo;impractical&amp;rdquo; talent, etc. For me, a real pragmatist wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be negative all the time about change or risk, but would confront it head on and look at &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; sides, not just the side that conveniently maintains the status quo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We see people lie and cheat all the time in the name of pragmatism, justifying what they do by simply stating that everyone else is doing, that you can&amp;rsquo;t beat the system so you should learn how to win for yourself within it, etc. I think it&amp;rsquo;s a dangerous slippery slope if you rightfully see and acknowledge the negatives in the world but then decide that the correct thing to do is always to just play along. Is this &amp;ldquo;idealistic&amp;rdquo;? I don&amp;rsquo;t think so. I think the pragmatic thing to do is to pick your fights, rather than not fight at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;idealism&#34;&gt;Idealism&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another reason I have resisted the word &amp;ldquo;pragmatic&amp;rdquo; is that I was once academic-oriented. It turns out that I was very badly suited to academia, in large part precisely because I have pragmatic interests and priorities that I finally concluded are hard to shoehorn into an academic environment. But a lot of people I do respect for the quality of their work and their desire to change the world for the better are in fact academic in nature, and are idealists fighting the good fight. I respect this so much that I wanted to be one of them. So it was one of those situations in which I lacked the courage to be my true self. I faced a lot of cognitive dissonance when I was in academia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, I&amp;rsquo;m writing this post because sometimes I wonder whether I still &amp;ldquo;pass&amp;rdquo; as an idealist, even over a decade after leaving academia permanently. I decided it was about time for me to officially come out as a pragmatist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everything that I think and do these days comes from a pragmatic point of view, and so I&amp;rsquo;ve decided to embrace that rather than half-hide it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reflections on Richard Wagner&#39;s 200th birthday: beautiful music without a future</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/05/22/reflections-on-richard-wagners-200th-birthday/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 May 2013 08:14:55 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/05/22/reflections-on-richard-wagners-200th-birthday/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A couple of days ago, I was driving and had the radio on and heard Richard Wagner&amp;rsquo;s prelude to act 1 of his opera &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Die_Meistersinger_von_N%C3%BCrnberg&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Die Meistersinger&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, and was transported into the lush musical world that is so uniquely Wagner: seductive orchestral colors, chromatic harmony, melodic motifs, fine storytelling, stirring climaxes, and in this particular musical excerpt, ironic yet clever use of counterpoint. I had to pull over for a while to finish listening to the prelude and fully enjoy the &lt;em&gt;guilty&lt;/em&gt; rush of emotional excitement in this fun but over-the-top piece. Why the guilt?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;controversy&#34;&gt;Controversy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The controversial music composer &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_Wagner&#34;&gt;Richard Wagner&lt;/a&gt; was born 200 years ago. In keeping with the media&amp;rsquo;s love of arbitrarily nice round numbers and anniversaries, there&amp;rsquo;s a lot of commentary about celebrations of his birthdays or reasons &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; to celebrate. Here are just a few articles that came up during a Web search:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.washingtonpost.com/entertainment/music/germany-celebrates-200th-birthday-of-composer-richard-wagner/2013/05/22/b8f93924-c2b2-11e2-9642-a56177f1cdf7_story.html?tid=pm_entertainment_pop&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Germany celebrates 200th birthday of Richard Wagner, Hitler&amp;rsquo;s favorite composer&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://fullcomment.nationalpost.com/2013/05/22/barbara-kay-if-you-must-listen-to-wagner-do-it-in-private/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;If you must listen to Wagner, do it in private&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.towntopics.com/wordpress/2013/05/22/whistling-in-the-dark-on-wagners-200th-birthday/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Whistling in the dark on Wagner&amp;rsquo;s 200th birthday&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://jessicamusic.blogspot.com/2013/05/dear-richard-i-need-to-tell-you.html&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Dear Richard, I need to tell you something&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.newyorker.com/online/blogs/culture/2013/05/wagner-bicentennial-birthday-music-recordings.html&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;A Wagner birthday roast&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;None of this commentary actually addresses my mixed feelings about Wagner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;wagner-s-anti-semitism&#34;&gt;Wagner&amp;rsquo;s anti-Semitism?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much of the commentary touches upon Wagner&amp;rsquo;s anti-Semitism and Adolf Hitler&amp;rsquo;s use of Wagner in Germany for Nazi purposes. I will &lt;em&gt;not be discussing&lt;/em&gt; these (important) issues because others already do, and because I tend toward the view that people are imperfect and I would like to be able to assess their important and good work even if they could be judged as unpleasant or downright evil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;love-the-music-hate-the-man&#34;&gt;Love the music, hate the man?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I also do not agree with the sentiment of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.independent.co.uk/voices/comment/on-the-200th-anniversary-of-wagners-birth-lets-learn-to-love-the-music--yet-still-hate-the-man-8614155.html&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Let&amp;rsquo;s learn to love the music, yet still hate the man&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. I don&amp;rsquo;t think there is a total separation between Wagner&amp;rsquo;s music and everything else about him. In Wagner&amp;rsquo;s case, in particular, he specifically designed his music around a certain philosophy about the world, about &lt;em&gt;art&lt;/em&gt;. And that is what I really find interesting and unsettling, somewhat along the lines of Friedrich Nietzsche&amp;rsquo;s critique of his one-time friend, &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Case_of_Wagner&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Case of Wagner&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nietzsche_contra_Wagner&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Nietzsche contra Wagner&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;music-and-philosophy&#34;&gt;Music and philosophy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wagner&amp;rsquo;s philosophizing about the nature of and purpose of music embraced the notion of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gesamtkunstwerk&#34;&gt;Gesamtkunstwerk&lt;/a&gt;, the &amp;ldquo;total work of art&amp;rdquo;, that would unify all the arts, hence his development of his form of opera, the &amp;ldquo;music drama&amp;rdquo;, whose purpose was to unify music, poetry, theater in a grand and serious spectacle to inspire the audience. He proposed the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Music_of_the_Future&#34;&gt;Zukunftsmusik&lt;/a&gt;, or &amp;ldquo;music of the future&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;modernism&#34;&gt;Modernism?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Wagner&amp;rsquo;s day in the late 19th century, there was &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/War_of_the_Romantics&#34;&gt;fierce rivalry among the German Romantics&lt;/a&gt; on the direction of musical evolution. Roughly, there was the camp of Johannes Brahms (whose &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/05/07/happy-birthday-johannes-brahms/&#34;&gt;birthday I celebrated a few weeks ago&lt;/a&gt;, considered &amp;ldquo;conservative&amp;rdquo;, and the camp of Wagner, which considered itself &amp;ldquo;modern&amp;rdquo;. Aspects of this &amp;ldquo;war&amp;rdquo; seem quaint and exaggerated now, and Brahms has been &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.economist.com/node/367351&#34;&gt;re-evaluated&lt;/a&gt; in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/1996/09/29/arts/old-brahms-a-modernist-in-more-ways-than-one.html&#34;&gt;recent&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.americansymphony.org/concert_notes/the-other-voice-of-johannes-brahms&#34;&gt;decades&lt;/a&gt;, and the big tent of Western art music has historically learned from both camps&amp;rsquo; methods and sensibilities, but Wagner, at least, took very seriously his own self-importance and self-promotion as an artist/philosopher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An interesting question to me is, what is Wagner&amp;rsquo;s relationship to &lt;em&gt;modernism&lt;/em&gt;, both in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Modernism_%28music%29&#34;&gt;musical sense&lt;/a&gt; and in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Modernism&#34;&gt;more general sense&lt;/a&gt;, typically applied to the late 19th century and early 20th century trends in literature, art, architecture, and society that are still relevant today?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;tristan&#34;&gt;Tristan&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.guardian.co.uk/friday_review/story/0,,381181,00.html&#34;&gt;harmonic and other innovations&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tristan_und_Isolde&#34;&gt;Tristan und Isolde&lt;/a&gt; in 1865 (it is arguable that Franz Liszt was the real innovator first) can be considered the beginning of modernism in music (in the sense of dissolution of Western tonality). Check out this performance of the beginning of the prelude to act 1 along with a score annotated with harmonic analysis:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/Pwk3BKipjtQ&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s my favorite full performance of the prelude as well as the final sung Liebestod, by the great Wilhelm Furtwngler conducting and Kirsted Flagstad singing. It truly blew my mind when I first discovered and heard this music while in college.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/SQO7QIgNvA0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;who-claims-modernism&#34;&gt;Who claims modernism?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the modernist &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Second_Viennese_School&#34;&gt;Second Viennese School&lt;/a&gt; under Arnold Schnberg liked to claim Brahms as one of their own, and in even more revisionism recently, there have been attempts to situate &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.upress.umn.edu/book-division/books/modernism-after-wagner&#34;&gt;Wagner as the inspiration for modernism in the larger sense&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(A few of my notes about Schnberg &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/25/thank-you-glenn-gould/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Also, it is too large a topic for now, but I plan to write more later about modernism and postmodernism and post-postmodernism in music, in the context of today&amp;rsquo;s music and in my own experience of music, whether listening or performing.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;wagner-s-legacy&#34;&gt;Wagner&amp;rsquo;s legacy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe Wagner failed, that his philosophy was a dead end, and that his music was a dead end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This despite the fact that, of course, he changed the course of Western musical history, both by provoking the modernist backlash against his theatricalism and chromaticism, while paving the way for, say, Mahler and Bruckner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have enjoyed and continue to occasionally listen again to marvelous music by Wagner, but &lt;em&gt;not in the way he intended&lt;/em&gt;. I have never attended a performance of one of his operas. I have only seen (on TV or video) or listened to bits of his operas that are sung (rather than purely instrumental excerpts). Two decades ago, I did try to watch the mammoth &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Der_Ring_des_Nibelungen&#34;&gt;Ring cycle&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/1990/06/18/arts/review-television-taking-the-17-hour-plunge-with-wagner-s-ring-at-the-met.html&#34;&gt;broadcast on TV by the Metropolitan Opera&lt;/a&gt; over four long evenings, but my attention span allowed me to only drift in and out of consciousness periodically during that attempt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps most damning of all is that shortly after that TV experience, I rather enjoyed listening to Lorin Maazel&amp;rsquo;s album, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/music/dp/B000003CUJ&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Ring Without Words&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, basically showing that for me, Wagner totally failed as a philosopher, because I like his music best without the &amp;ldquo;poetry&amp;rdquo; (his lyrics, which he wrote himself, don&amp;rsquo;t make much sense to me) and without the on-stage drama.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even then, I cannot listen to his music much without feeling unclean. There is a sense in which I cannot separate his music from his philosophy and his wider artistic and cultural aims. Even if he had not been an anti-Semite, there should be controversy over him and his legacy. There is a sense in which I agree with some of the old-fashioned concerns about his music: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.guardian.co.uk/music/2013/may/22/wagner-bad-for-your-mental-health&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Wagner as mental health menace?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. In Nietzsche&amp;rsquo;s words, Wagner and his music are &lt;em&gt;decadent&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2014-07-13&#34;&gt;(Update of 2014-07-13)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/07/13/what-i-remember-lorin-maazel-for/&#34;&gt;RIP, Lorin Maazel&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;music-is-powerful&#34;&gt;Music is powerful&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it&amp;rsquo;s pretty delicious decadence. Last month a friend splurged on going to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://ringcycle.metoperafamily.org/&#34;&gt;Metropolitan Opera&amp;rsquo;s performance of the Ring&lt;/a&gt;, and I decided to indulge in listening to Siegfried&amp;rsquo;s funeral march in &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/G%C3%B6tterd%C3%A4mmerung&#34;&gt;Gtterdmmerung&lt;/a&gt;. As usual, the experience left me in tears. Wagner, master psychologist, master manipulator of emotions, master composer, weaving the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leitmotif&#34;&gt;leitmotifs&lt;/a&gt;, summing up the whole tragic story of the Ring:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/L8wHteSOwW4&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And for sheer &lt;em&gt;hypnotism&lt;/em&gt;, listen to Furtwngler again, with the prelude to act 1 of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lohengrin_%28opera%29&#34;&gt;Lohengrin&lt;/a&gt;. Close your eyes, turn out the lights, and listen. Beautiful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/I_m7PN5sn1U&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More hypnosis: prelude to act 1 of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parsifal&#34;&gt;Parsifal&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;ve chosen an old Furtwngler performance again:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/EZhSUX5Ix68&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;back-to-die-meistersinger&#34;&gt;Back to Die Meistersinger&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, to end where I started, with the prelude to act 1 of Die Meistersinger that I happened to enjoy on the radio, here is Furtwngler again, conducting a performance of it live. &lt;strong&gt;Warning: this is a video of a live performance in 1942 in Germany with swastikas in the background, so you may not wish to view this.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/3rM96_RS1Os&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, this video is totally creepy, but I thought it would be appropriate to close on this jarring note. Die Meistersinger was, after all, Wagner&amp;rsquo;s telling of a story to glorify old Germany, and was a favorite opera of the Nazis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(And the subject of Furtwngler, a conductor I have many mixed feelings about, will have to wait for another blog post as well.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I cannot help but admire and be affected by Wagner&amp;rsquo;s music, but at the same time feel that his entire philosophy and aim was bankrupt. I&amp;rsquo;ve touched on only a little bit of how I have come to feel this, since the larger issues go beyond Wagner, but I don&amp;rsquo;t yet have complete thoughts and rationales to offer at this time. As with the towering figure of Beethoven, his musical and cultural legacy is still controversial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;postscript&#34;&gt;Postscript&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided I wanted to end more positively. My favorite piece of Wagner&amp;rsquo;s is one that was actually always intended to be purely instrumental and is self-contained, not just an excerpt: the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Siegfried_Idyll&#34;&gt;Siegfried Idyll&lt;/a&gt;. Oh wait, again we all subvert his intention anyway, because he composed it for his wife Cosima&amp;rsquo;s birthday (what a beautiful present to wake up to in the morning) and only ever intended it to be performed privately!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furtwngler again:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/_jlzEFg-zkY&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2014-07-11&#34;&gt;(Update of 2014-07-11)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I just saw yet another article about &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.newrepublic.com/article/118331/forbidden-music-michael-haas-reviewed-james-loeffler&#34;&gt;Wagner and anti-Semitism&lt;/a&gt;. The topic never goes anyway, and I don&amp;rsquo;t think it should. That said, I don&amp;rsquo;t personally have anything to add to the discussion, but offer the link if you feel you need to engage further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2015-01-14&#34;&gt;(Update of 2015-01-14)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I saw yet another (and excellent) article &lt;a href=&#34;http://mosaicmagazine.com/essay/2015/01/wagner-and-the-jews/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Wagner and the Jews&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reflections on Richard Wagner&#39;s 200th birthday: beautiful music without a future</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/05/22/reflections-on-richard-wagners-200th-birthday/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 May 2013 08:14:55 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/05/22/reflections-on-richard-wagners-200th-birthday/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A couple of days ago, I was driving and had the radio on and heard Richard Wagner&amp;rsquo;s prelude to act 1 of his opera &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Die_Meistersinger_von_N%C3%BCrnberg&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Die Meistersinger&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, and was transported into the lush musical world that is so uniquely Wagner: seductive orchestral colors, chromatic harmony, melodic motifs, fine storytelling, stirring climaxes, and in this particular musical excerpt, ironic yet clever use of counterpoint. I had to pull over for a while to finish listening to the prelude and fully enjoy the &lt;em&gt;guilty&lt;/em&gt; rush of emotional excitement in this fun but over-the-top piece. Why the guilt?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;controversy&#34;&gt;Controversy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The controversial music composer &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_Wagner&#34;&gt;Richard Wagner&lt;/a&gt; was born 200 years ago. In keeping with the media&amp;rsquo;s love of arbitrarily nice round numbers and anniversaries, there&amp;rsquo;s a lot of commentary about celebrations of his birthdays or reasons &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; to celebrate. Here are just a few articles that came up during a Web search:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.washingtonpost.com/entertainment/music/germany-celebrates-200th-birthday-of-composer-richard-wagner/2013/05/22/b8f93924-c2b2-11e2-9642-a56177f1cdf7_story.html?tid=pm_entertainment_pop&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Germany celebrates 200th birthday of Richard Wagner, Hitler&amp;rsquo;s favorite composer&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://fullcomment.nationalpost.com/2013/05/22/barbara-kay-if-you-must-listen-to-wagner-do-it-in-private/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;If you must listen to Wagner, do it in private&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.towntopics.com/wordpress/2013/05/22/whistling-in-the-dark-on-wagners-200th-birthday/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Whistling in the dark on Wagner&amp;rsquo;s 200th birthday&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://jessicamusic.blogspot.com/2013/05/dear-richard-i-need-to-tell-you.html&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Dear Richard, I need to tell you something&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.newyorker.com/online/blogs/culture/2013/05/wagner-bicentennial-birthday-music-recordings.html&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;A Wagner birthday roast&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;None of this commentary actually addresses my mixed feelings about Wagner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;wagner-s-anti-semitism&#34;&gt;Wagner&amp;rsquo;s anti-Semitism?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much of the commentary touches upon Wagner&amp;rsquo;s anti-Semitism and Adolf Hitler&amp;rsquo;s use of Wagner in Germany for Nazi purposes. I will &lt;em&gt;not be discussing&lt;/em&gt; these (important) issues because others already do, and because I tend toward the view that people are imperfect and I would like to be able to assess their important and good work even if they could be judged as unpleasant or downright evil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;love-the-music-hate-the-man&#34;&gt;Love the music, hate the man?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I also do not agree with the sentiment of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.independent.co.uk/voices/comment/on-the-200th-anniversary-of-wagners-birth-lets-learn-to-love-the-music--yet-still-hate-the-man-8614155.html&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Let&amp;rsquo;s learn to love the music, yet still hate the man&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. I don&amp;rsquo;t think there is a total separation between Wagner&amp;rsquo;s music and everything else about him. In Wagner&amp;rsquo;s case, in particular, he specifically designed his music around a certain philosophy about the world, about &lt;em&gt;art&lt;/em&gt;. And that is what I really find interesting and unsettling, somewhat along the lines of Friedrich Nietzsche&amp;rsquo;s critique of his one-time friend, &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Case_of_Wagner&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Case of Wagner&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nietzsche_contra_Wagner&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Nietzsche contra Wagner&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;music-and-philosophy&#34;&gt;Music and philosophy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wagner&amp;rsquo;s philosophizing about the nature of and purpose of music embraced the notion of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gesamtkunstwerk&#34;&gt;Gesamtkunstwerk&lt;/a&gt;, the &amp;ldquo;total work of art&amp;rdquo;, that would unify all the arts, hence his development of his form of opera, the &amp;ldquo;music drama&amp;rdquo;, whose purpose was to unify music, poetry, theater in a grand and serious spectacle to inspire the audience. He proposed the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Music_of_the_Future&#34;&gt;Zukunftsmusik&lt;/a&gt;, or &amp;ldquo;music of the future&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;modernism&#34;&gt;Modernism?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Wagner&amp;rsquo;s day in the late 19th century, there was &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/War_of_the_Romantics&#34;&gt;fierce rivalry among the German Romantics&lt;/a&gt; on the direction of musical evolution. Roughly, there was the camp of Johannes Brahms (whose &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/05/07/happy-birthday-johannes-brahms/&#34;&gt;birthday I celebrated a few weeks ago&lt;/a&gt;, considered &amp;ldquo;conservative&amp;rdquo;, and the camp of Wagner, which considered itself &amp;ldquo;modern&amp;rdquo;. Aspects of this &amp;ldquo;war&amp;rdquo; seem quaint and exaggerated now, and Brahms has been &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.economist.com/node/367351&#34;&gt;re-evaluated&lt;/a&gt; in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/1996/09/29/arts/old-brahms-a-modernist-in-more-ways-than-one.html&#34;&gt;recent&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.americansymphony.org/concert_notes/the-other-voice-of-johannes-brahms&#34;&gt;decades&lt;/a&gt;, and the big tent of Western art music has historically learned from both camps&amp;rsquo; methods and sensibilities, but Wagner, at least, took very seriously his own self-importance and self-promotion as an artist/philosopher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An interesting question to me is, what is Wagner&amp;rsquo;s relationship to &lt;em&gt;modernism&lt;/em&gt;, both in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Modernism_%28music%29&#34;&gt;musical sense&lt;/a&gt; and in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Modernism&#34;&gt;more general sense&lt;/a&gt;, typically applied to the late 19th century and early 20th century trends in literature, art, architecture, and society that are still relevant today?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;tristan&#34;&gt;Tristan&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.guardian.co.uk/friday_review/story/0,,381181,00.html&#34;&gt;harmonic and other innovations&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tristan_und_Isolde&#34;&gt;Tristan und Isolde&lt;/a&gt; in 1865 (it is arguable that Franz Liszt was the real innovator first) can be considered the beginning of modernism in music (in the sense of dissolution of Western tonality). Check out this performance of the beginning of the prelude to act 1 along with a score annotated with harmonic analysis:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/Pwk3BKipjtQ&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s my favorite full performance of the prelude as well as the final sung Liebestod, by the great Wilhelm Furtwngler conducting and Kirsted Flagstad singing. It truly blew my mind when I first discovered and heard this music while in college.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/SQO7QIgNvA0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;who-claims-modernism&#34;&gt;Who claims modernism?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the modernist &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Second_Viennese_School&#34;&gt;Second Viennese School&lt;/a&gt; under Arnold Schnberg liked to claim Brahms as one of their own, and in even more revisionism recently, there have been attempts to situate &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.upress.umn.edu/book-division/books/modernism-after-wagner&#34;&gt;Wagner as the inspiration for modernism in the larger sense&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(A few of my notes about Schnberg &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/25/thank-you-glenn-gould/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Also, it is too large a topic for now, but I plan to write more later about modernism and postmodernism and post-postmodernism in music, in the context of today&amp;rsquo;s music and in my own experience of music, whether listening or performing.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;wagner-s-legacy&#34;&gt;Wagner&amp;rsquo;s legacy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe Wagner failed, that his philosophy was a dead end, and that his music was a dead end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This despite the fact that, of course, he changed the course of Western musical history, both by provoking the modernist backlash against his theatricalism and chromaticism, while paving the way for, say, Mahler and Bruckner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have enjoyed and continue to occasionally listen again to marvelous music by Wagner, but &lt;em&gt;not in the way he intended&lt;/em&gt;. I have never attended a performance of one of his operas. I have only seen (on TV or video) or listened to bits of his operas that are sung (rather than purely instrumental excerpts). Two decades ago, I did try to watch the mammoth &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Der_Ring_des_Nibelungen&#34;&gt;Ring cycle&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/1990/06/18/arts/review-television-taking-the-17-hour-plunge-with-wagner-s-ring-at-the-met.html&#34;&gt;broadcast on TV by the Metropolitan Opera&lt;/a&gt; over four long evenings, but my attention span allowed me to only drift in and out of consciousness periodically during that attempt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps most damning of all is that shortly after that TV experience, I rather enjoyed listening to Lorin Maazel&amp;rsquo;s album, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/music/dp/B000003CUJ&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Ring Without Words&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, basically showing that for me, Wagner totally failed as a philosopher, because I like his music best without the &amp;ldquo;poetry&amp;rdquo; (his lyrics, which he wrote himself, don&amp;rsquo;t make much sense to me) and without the on-stage drama.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even then, I cannot listen to his music much without feeling unclean. There is a sense in which I cannot separate his music from his philosophy and his wider artistic and cultural aims. Even if he had not been an anti-Semite, there should be controversy over him and his legacy. There is a sense in which I agree with some of the old-fashioned concerns about his music: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.guardian.co.uk/music/2013/may/22/wagner-bad-for-your-mental-health&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Wagner as mental health menace?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. In Nietzsche&amp;rsquo;s words, Wagner and his music are &lt;em&gt;decadent&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2014-07-13&#34;&gt;(Update of 2014-07-13)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/07/13/what-i-remember-lorin-maazel-for/&#34;&gt;RIP, Lorin Maazel&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;music-is-powerful&#34;&gt;Music is powerful&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it&amp;rsquo;s pretty delicious decadence. Last month a friend splurged on going to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://ringcycle.metoperafamily.org/&#34;&gt;Metropolitan Opera&amp;rsquo;s performance of the Ring&lt;/a&gt;, and I decided to indulge in listening to Siegfried&amp;rsquo;s funeral march in &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/G%C3%B6tterd%C3%A4mmerung&#34;&gt;Gtterdmmerung&lt;/a&gt;. As usual, the experience left me in tears. Wagner, master psychologist, master manipulator of emotions, master composer, weaving the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leitmotif&#34;&gt;leitmotifs&lt;/a&gt;, summing up the whole tragic story of the Ring:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/L8wHteSOwW4&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And for sheer &lt;em&gt;hypnotism&lt;/em&gt;, listen to Furtwngler again, with the prelude to act 1 of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lohengrin_%28opera%29&#34;&gt;Lohengrin&lt;/a&gt;. Close your eyes, turn out the lights, and listen. Beautiful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/I_m7PN5sn1U&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More hypnosis: prelude to act 1 of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parsifal&#34;&gt;Parsifal&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;ve chosen an old Furtwngler performance again:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/EZhSUX5Ix68&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;back-to-die-meistersinger&#34;&gt;Back to Die Meistersinger&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, to end where I started, with the prelude to act 1 of Die Meistersinger that I happened to enjoy on the radio, here is Furtwngler again, conducting a performance of it live. &lt;strong&gt;Warning: this is a video of a live performance in 1942 in Germany with swastikas in the background, so you may not wish to view this.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/3rM96_RS1Os&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, this video is totally creepy, but I thought it would be appropriate to close on this jarring note. Die Meistersinger was, after all, Wagner&amp;rsquo;s telling of a story to glorify old Germany, and was a favorite opera of the Nazis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(And the subject of Furtwngler, a conductor I have many mixed feelings about, will have to wait for another blog post as well.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I cannot help but admire and be affected by Wagner&amp;rsquo;s music, but at the same time feel that his entire philosophy and aim was bankrupt. I&amp;rsquo;ve touched on only a little bit of how I have come to feel this, since the larger issues go beyond Wagner, but I don&amp;rsquo;t yet have complete thoughts and rationales to offer at this time. As with the towering figure of Beethoven, his musical and cultural legacy is still controversial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;postscript&#34;&gt;Postscript&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided I wanted to end more positively. My favorite piece of Wagner&amp;rsquo;s is one that was actually always intended to be purely instrumental and is self-contained, not just an excerpt: the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Siegfried_Idyll&#34;&gt;Siegfried Idyll&lt;/a&gt;. Oh wait, again we all subvert his intention anyway, because he composed it for his wife Cosima&amp;rsquo;s birthday (what a beautiful present to wake up to in the morning) and only ever intended it to be performed privately!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furtwngler again:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/_jlzEFg-zkY&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2014-07-11&#34;&gt;(Update of 2014-07-11)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I just saw yet another article about &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.newrepublic.com/article/118331/forbidden-music-michael-haas-reviewed-james-loeffler&#34;&gt;Wagner and anti-Semitism&lt;/a&gt;. The topic never goes anyway, and I don&amp;rsquo;t think it should. That said, I don&amp;rsquo;t personally have anything to add to the discussion, but offer the link if you feel you need to engage further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2015-01-14&#34;&gt;(Update of 2015-01-14)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I saw yet another (and excellent) article &lt;a href=&#34;http://mosaicmagazine.com/essay/2015/01/wagner-and-the-jews/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Wagner and the Jews&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thanking the best of all possible worlds</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/11/22/thanking-the-best-of-all-possible-worlds/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Nov 2012 21:55:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/11/22/thanking-the-best-of-all-possible-worlds/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Happy Thanksgiving, everyone!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-Lc7Oc2PreKI/T3U0A6pSPBI/AAAAAAAABxY/iTXcrFFn1sQ/s1600/tumblr_kx61vvQHfG1qz82gvo1_500.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Oppenheimer quote&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Today, on a sunny Thanksgiving, I surprised myself by spontaneously deciding to thank this world, and go as far as to call it &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Best_of_all_possible_worlds&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;the best of all possible worlds&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;m still not entirely sure what I mean by that, but somehow, I &amp;ldquo;believe&amp;rdquo; it; more precisely, it&amp;rsquo;s an &lt;em&gt;attitude&lt;/em&gt; I now have that I have never really had in my life up till now. Even &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/23/every-day-is-thanksgiving/&#34;&gt;a year ago&lt;/a&gt;, I would have thought it silly to adopt such an attitude.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A friend of mine asked, &amp;ldquo;Dr. Pangloss?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, am I being a fool?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;being-dr-pangloss&#34;&gt;Being Dr. Pangloss?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Pangloss is a fictional character from &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Voltaire&#34;&gt;Voltaire&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s satirical novella &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Candide&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Candide&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; that was required reading in high school French. I remember reading that novella in high school, of course: it was a &lt;em&gt;profound&lt;/em&gt; influence on me at the time, instilling a certain cynicism in me that lasted years. Voltaire wrote this novella as a direct attempt to refute &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gottfried_Wilhelm_Leibniz&#34;&gt;Leibniz&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s philosophy of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Best_of_all_possible_worlds&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;best of all possible worlds&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;: Pangloss is a buffoonish character who spouts parodies of Leibniz&amp;rsquo;s reasoning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No question about it, Candide is a wickedly entertaining satire, and Voltaire is a towering figure from the French Enlightenment, one who exposed a lot of hypocrisy and was an advocate of many social reforms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;philosophy-vs-attitude&#34;&gt;Philosophy vs. attitude&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I have over the years come to believe that the Enlightenment emphasis on Reason is not by itself the panacea to the mysteries and problems of life. In particular, I perceive that often, this emphasis leads to arrogance, anger, and selective blindness. There doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem any logical &lt;em&gt;reason&lt;/em&gt; that &lt;em&gt;Reason&lt;/em&gt; should lead to this, but it really happens. It happened to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I have not by any means abandoned &lt;em&gt;reason&lt;/em&gt;, but I have long since abandoned &lt;em&gt;Reason&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, I&amp;rsquo;m going to confess that Leibniz&amp;rsquo;s philosophical work does not make a whole lot of sense to me. So my adopting an &lt;em&gt;attitude&lt;/em&gt; of &amp;ldquo;this is the best of all possible worlds&amp;rdquo; is in no way an endorsement of any belief in Leibniz&amp;rsquo;s philosophical/theological system. And I certainly have also observed that there are people who do accept Leibniz&amp;rsquo;s purported solution to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Problem_of_evil&#34;&gt;problem of evil&lt;/a&gt;, who seem to use it as a way to turn a blind eye to the injustices that still occur in our world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short, I am taking an &lt;em&gt;attitude&lt;/em&gt; that I find helps me function in a positive way in the world, without tying myself to a fully worked out philosophy about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;related-ideas&#34;&gt;Related ideas&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A related idea is &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amor_fati&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;amor fati&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (&amp;ldquo;love of fate&amp;rdquo;), popularized by Nietzsche but coming from &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stoicism&#34;&gt;Stoicism&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Steve Pavlina wrote today about &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.stevepavlina.com/blog/2012/11/this-is-heaven/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;heaven&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;application&#34;&gt;Application&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That I have adopted the &lt;em&gt;optimistic&lt;/em&gt; attitude toward life, after having a mostly &lt;em&gt;pessimistic&lt;/em&gt; one during most of my years, has practical applications. Being &lt;em&gt;grateful&lt;/em&gt; every single day for every positive thing that happens enables me to more easily overcome the negative. My attitude is a choice I have made, and nurtured through various techniques, as mentioned &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/23/every-day-is-thanksgiving/&#34;&gt;last Thanksgiving&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being optimistic does not mean ignoring the negative. It means maintaining the energy to do things, to set things right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have embrace this world as &lt;em&gt;my&lt;/em&gt; world. This is my choice, my attitude. May it be yours as well.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>