<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Liberty Mile on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/liberty-mile/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Liberty Mile on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/liberty-mile/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Getting up when reality punches you in the face: running the second Liberty Mile in Pittsburgh</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/08/09/getting-up-when-reality-punches-you-in-the-face-running-the-second-liberty-mile-in-pittsburgh/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Aug 2013 20:49:35 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/08/09/getting-up-when-reality-punches-you-in-the-face-running-the-second-liberty-mile-in-pittsburgh/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Last year, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/08/17/the-inaugural-liberty-mile-a-review-of-pittsburghs-first-road-mile-race/&#34;&gt;I reported on the excitement I had running in and watching&lt;/a&gt; the first &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.libertymile.org/&#34;&gt;GNC Live Well Liberty Mile&lt;/a&gt;. I was so excited about running it again that late this May, having mostly recovered from my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/05/06/2013-pittsburgh-marathon-my-135th-race-was-my-worst-i-finished/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Marathon disaster&lt;/a&gt;, I quickly pre-registered for the Liberty Mile for this year. I anticipated training to run well in this year&amp;rsquo;s Liberty Mile, given that I was not really trained last year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, this year I have been in very poor shape since the marathon, because of a whole series of health problems and disruptions in my life resulting from a skin rash I got during a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/05/12/my-rachel-carson-trail-hike-for-the-year/&#34;&gt;Rachel Carson Trail hike in May&lt;/a&gt;. The upshot is that I have been running (and exercising in general) very little in the past three months. As the Liberty Mile approached, I wished that I had not registered for it at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I faced a dilemma: what should I do about the race?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;deciding-to-run-it&#34;&gt;Deciding to run it&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The good thing about the mile is that it&amp;rsquo;s short enough that of course I can finish the thing. So I felt there was no excuse to just bail out and forfeit my pre-registration. I was going to run it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bad thing about the mile is that it is brutal to actually run &lt;em&gt;fast&lt;/em&gt;. I have always felt pukey after running a mile as &amp;ldquo;fast&amp;rdquo; as I can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, I decided to still try to run the Liberty Mile as fast as I could, knowing that I would probably suffer for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In recent weeks I&amp;rsquo;ve been trying to go out periodically for short, slow runs, something like two miles at a time, to gain at least have &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; kind of conditioning. Also, earlier this week I put in some &amp;ldquo;fast&amp;rdquo; repeats of about 300m out in Frick Park: the only &amp;ldquo;fast&amp;rdquo; running I&amp;rsquo;ve done since April!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this whole week I was feeling bad, stress exacerbated by home repair disruptions with the contractors coming over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;support-from-abby&#34;&gt;Support from Abby&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, I went to the race alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year, Abby offered to go downtown with me so she could watch the race and be with me. (In May when I was pre-registering for the race, she had just spent months barely mobile because of a broken foot and was simply not certain she would be able to even run a mile again by August.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really appreciated this because I felt rather vulnerable about this race. We planned to watch the first wave start, and then have me run my heat (again the &amp;ldquo;Unstoppable 40+&amp;rdquo; heat), then hang out afterwards and watch the elite heats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We drove downtown and parked and walked to the packet pickup area in Market Square. I was pleased that it wasn&amp;rsquo;t raining; it had rained earlier in the day, but that was all over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because we arrived later than other people, they had run out of Small T-shirts and so I got a Medium.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/liberty-mile-2013/abby.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby holding my T-shirt&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;changes-in-the-course&#34;&gt;Changes in the course&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I should note that the course was changed from last year. The change makes sense because it considerably simplifies the logistics. Last year, the course was a straight shot down Liberty Ave toward downtown. This year, the course was an almost-loop course, first going out on Penn Ave, then turning to head back in on Liberty Ave. The advantage is that the start and finish are close together, so it is much easier for people to plan to spectate or get back to their cars or whatever. I do like the concept of the straight downhill road course, but understand the logistical difficulties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My plan was to do my best to avoid going out too fast, and try to push hard in the final downhill portion of the race. Easier said than done, because last year I certainly wanted to avoid going out too fast, but did anyway!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;before-the-race&#34;&gt;Before the race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wore my Vibram FiveFingers Bikila LS shoes again.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/liberty-mile-2013/before-start.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin before race&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At the GNC booth, I saw they were giving out free samples of energy bars and other stuff. I was feeling hungry, and although I know that it is best not to race having just eaten, especially unfamiliar foods, I took a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.gnc.com/product/index.jsp?productId=4468895&#34;&gt;GNC Pro Performance Pro Crunch Lite&lt;/a&gt; energy bar, and ate a couple of bites before giving the remainder to Abby to put away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was probably a big mistake to have eaten from the energy bar, because it didn&amp;rsquo;t really agree with me. Oops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;start-and-finish-lines&#34;&gt;Start and finish lines&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We checked out the start and finish lines.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/liberty-mile-2013/start-line.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Start line&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/liberty-mile-2013/finish-line.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Finish line&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;first-heat-at-7-00-pm&#34;&gt;First heat (at 7:00 PM)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We watched as the first &amp;ldquo;fun run&amp;rdquo; heat went.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/liberty-mile-2013/first-heat-start.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-race-heat-at-7-20-pm&#34;&gt;My race (heat at 7:20 PM)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got to the start line and lined up &lt;em&gt;at the back&lt;/em&gt;, where I knew I belonged. I was not sure that I would not be last place in my heat!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/liberty-mile-2013/my-heat-start.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here I am, looking as tired as I in fact was, still taking medication for my skin problem that is not completely gone (usually showing up as spots on my neck or hands and arms):&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/liberty-mile-2013/franklin-before.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin before the race&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As the race began, I tried not to go too fast, but did. 1:34 for the first quarter mile, not good at all! Last year, I ran the mile in 6:39, and went out in 1:29 for the first quarter. This year, I was hoping to go under 7:00 at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I slowed down for the second quarter, then finally found a steady pace for the third quarter. During the final quarter, I saw the finish line and eventually saw the clock ticking up toward 7:00. I was &lt;em&gt;furious&lt;/em&gt; that I might not be able to finish a 7-minute mile. I sprinted all out and didn&amp;rsquo;t actually finish under 7:00 according to the clock (the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.areep.com/events/libertymile/&#34;&gt;official race results&lt;/a&gt; say I finished in 7:02), but my chip time was 6:56, so I actually did run the mile in under 7 minutes!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My splits:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1:34 (went too fast)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1:56 (uphill, deliberately slowed down)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1:46 (steady)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1:40 (final kick)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;more-photos-of-the-liberty-mile&#34;&gt;More photos of the Liberty Mile&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More photos of the entire event can be seen &lt;a href=&#34;http://petemadia.photoshelter.com/gallery/2013-GNC-Live-Well-Liberty-Mile/G0000gQc.MfyoOAE/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;after-my-race&#34;&gt;After my race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Afterwards, I felt really, really crappy:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/liberty-mile-2013/done-in-pain.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin done for a while but still in pain&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In fact, for a full half hour after the race, all I could do was walk and sit around with Abby trying to feel less crappy. &lt;strong&gt;I have never felt so bad for so long after any race of any distance.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;reflections&#34;&gt;Reflections&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mentally, also, I was still very &lt;em&gt;angry&lt;/em&gt; at myself: I came in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.areep.com/events/libertymile/results/13lm_uno.txt&#34;&gt;60th place out of 74&lt;/a&gt;, running a chip time of 6:56, a whopping &lt;em&gt;18 seconds&lt;/em&gt; slower than last year. That&amp;rsquo;s a huge decrease in fitness for a mile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My plan for this year, 2013, was supposed to be to get back into great health and fitness, &amp;ldquo;the shape I was in five years ago&amp;rdquo;. It&amp;rsquo;s why, for the new year, I got into &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/28/meditations-on-climbing-the-36-floors-of-the-pitt-cathedral-of-learning/&#34;&gt;climbing the Cathedral of Learning&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s why I got into running in the winter](/blog/2012/12/31/why-i-went-frick-park-trail-running-in-snowfall-for-the-first-time-in-a-decade/). It&amp;rsquo;s why I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/30/why-and-how-i-am-going-to-run-the-2013-pittsburgh-marathon/&#34;&gt;decided to run the Pittsburgh Marathon&lt;/a&gt;. I blew it my overtraining for the marathon and then suffering freak skin problems after a hike that ended up seeing doctors something like five times, and being put on medication that messed with me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a lot to be angry about. But after I recovered, I became calm and stopped being angry about being punched in the face by reality. I decided that it was motivation for me to turn my life around. I decided that I was going to get back into a regular exercise routine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In just the past three months, I have lost all of my fitness of the past several years. But I have a plan to get back on track, starting &lt;em&gt;tomorrow&lt;/em&gt;. I believe that for 2014, I can still get back into my 2008 shape. It&amp;rsquo;s a matter of making it a priority, over all the other things I have been doing in my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;going-home&#34;&gt;Going home&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After I recovered enough that I felt like eating and walking again, Abby and I went back to our car and we went home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only minutes after getting home did I realize that I had &lt;em&gt;totally forgotten&lt;/em&gt; to stick around to watch the elite runners&amp;rsquo; races!! That was far from my mind when I was feeling nauseous and reflecting on my poor fitness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The race was very well organized, and I&amp;rsquo;m thankful for the continuation of this new Pittsburgh tradition. Although I had a humbling experience in my heat, I totally want to be back for a third try at executing a good mile next year! And I am thankful that I actually ran it, because it gave me the resolve to regain my lost fitness.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The inaugural Liberty Mile: a review of Pittsburgh&#39;s first road mile race, a great community event</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/08/17/the-inaugural-liberty-mile-a-review-of-pittsburghs-first-road-mile-race/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Aug 2012 21:44:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/08/17/the-inaugural-liberty-mile-a-review-of-pittsburghs-first-road-mile-race/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/liberty-mile-2012.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin&amp;#39;s race number and Bikila LS shoes&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Tonight I was really excited to race in, and also watch, the inaugural &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.libertymile.org/&#34;&gt;GNC Live Well Liberty Mile&lt;/a&gt;, a road race that runs along Liberty Avenue in Pittsburgh, starting from the Strip District and ending downtown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s about time Pittsburgh had a road mile race! Pittsburgh already has the wonderful&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://rungreatrace.com/&#34;&gt;Great Race&lt;/a&gt;, which &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/25/blistered-but-blissful-in-the-burgh/&#34;&gt;I ran for my ninth time last year&lt;/a&gt; and will run for my tenth time this year (good think I pre-registered early, because today it &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburgh.cbslocal.com/2012/08/17/2012-great-race-officially-sold-out/&#34;&gt;already sold out!!&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pittsburghmarathon.com/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Marathon&lt;/a&gt;, which I&amp;rsquo;ve run once.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope this event is here to stay. Here&amp;rsquo;s my report on the event as both a runner and a spectator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-history-in-the-mile&#34;&gt;My history in the mile&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve run a mile race only twice before in my life, and that was on the track at Carnegie Mellon University. A decade ago, in June 2002, I ran in my first track mile, the Pittsylvania Mile on that track, and did it in 6:22. I could have run faster, but because of total inexperience, went out way too fast for the first quarter, doing it in 1:22, and paying the price in the other laps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following year, 2003, in probably my peak condition in my life, I improved, doing the Pittsylvania Mile in 6:10. I still went out too fast, in 1:26, had no sense of rhythm, slowed down a lot to try to compensate for going out too fast, then had too much energy at the end, which was wasted. Again, I had not trained for the mile distance at all, but happened to be in my peak condition anyway just because I was still conditioned from my intense training for the Pittsburgh Marathon that I had just done in May (my lifetime personal best in the 5K of 20:37 was achieved just two weeks after the Pittsburgh Marathon).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I never broke a 6-minute mile during my peak.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That was the last timed mile I ever ran, until tonight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;preparation&#34;&gt;Preparation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, I wasn&amp;rsquo;t prepared for the mile at all. Apart from not having run much because of a non-running injury to my left leg that happened a month ago (from which I have fully recovered), I have just come back from a week of unexpected travel and am still kind of recovering from that. And no speed work to speak of in the past month, other than a few random sprints (which I do for general physical conditioning when I don&amp;rsquo;t do much else).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had no idea what &amp;ldquo;mile pace&amp;rdquo; feels like. I just figured I would run a bit faster than 5K pace (which I always have a reasonable feel for).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hoped to finish somewhere near 6:30.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;dr-vonda-wright&#34;&gt;Dr. Vonda Wright&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://vondawright.com/images/stories/vonda-at-work.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Vonda Wright&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I bumped into &lt;a href=&#34;http://vondawright.com/&#34;&gt;Dr. Vonda Wright&lt;/a&gt; while heading toward the start line, and thanked her for her support of those of us who care about maintaining our health as we get older. I want to plug her great work in promoting lifetime fitness, especially for those over 40. She has written a book &lt;a href=&#34;http://vondawright.com/index.php?option=com_content&amp;amp;view=article&amp;amp;id=62&amp;amp;Itemid=83&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Fitness After 40&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; which is pretty good and has a lot of scientifically-backed tips on remaining strong and vital and even reversing what used to be considered &amp;ldquo;normal aging&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I heard about Dr. Wright from a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/01/20/cmu-fitness-challenge-keynote-lecture-by-vonda-wright-stay-strong-at-any-age/&#34;&gt;CMU &amp;ldquo;healthy campus week&amp;rdquo; talk she gave this January&lt;/a&gt;. Even though I had already known some of what she advocated, I was impressed that she summarized well the whole gamut of what we now know to be effective ways to increase strength and flexibility and avoid injury. Again, I recommend her books to anyone of any age who wants to be smart about diet and exercise and more than that, a whole philosophical approach to living in general.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-race-in-waves&#34;&gt;The race, in waves&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The race was held in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.libertymile.org/Race-Waves.asp&#34;&gt;waves separated by ten or twenty minutes&lt;/a&gt;. This is obviously necessary because of the variation in people&amp;rsquo;s speed. The slower, open waves were held first, and the elite racers were in the final waves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;early-waves&#34;&gt;Early waves&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I arrived to pick up my race number when the first wave was already in progress. There was a bit of confusion in the first two waves because a good number of people arrived late or were unclear about when to run, and therefore missed the first wave. Most of these seemed to be kids. By the way, it was great to see so many kids at the Liberty Mile. Running a 5K (3.1-mile) race can be daunting for a kid, but a single mile is surely a great introduction to many kids (and adults too!) to the joy of running. I think it is really great that the Liberty Mile is not just an elite race, but also a race anyone can participate in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;my-race-in-the-masters-wave&#34;&gt;My race, in the Masters wave&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Masters &amp;ldquo;Winning at 40+&amp;rdquo; wave was the first qualification-required wave.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ran in this serious, competitive wave, not one of the open waves, because I easily qualified to run in this wave, whose requirement was proof of ability to run an 8-minute mile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lining up, I saw a lot of really fit-looking people in this wave, many of whom were clearly well over 40. In any case, anyone who looked anywhere near my age (42) was obviously going to kick my butt all the way to the moon. There was no chance for an age-group prize for me today! No problem: as a non-elite racer, I don&amp;rsquo;t race for prizes, but just to do the best that I can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ended up running &lt;a href=&#34;http://runhigh.com/2012RESULTS/R081712AD.html&#34;&gt;6:38.8&lt;/a&gt;, good for 26th place out of 27 in my age group, ha! I was disappointed that I didn&amp;rsquo;t make 6:30 as I had originally hoped when I signed up a month ago, but that&amp;rsquo;s OK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the first quarter, I ran 1:29; oops, went out too fast yet again! &lt;strong&gt;I hereby pledge that before the next mile race I run, I will actually train and learn not to go out too fast.&lt;/strong&gt; There is no excuse for running three mile races going out too fast. I don&amp;rsquo;t go out too fast in 5K or longer distances, after all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the second and third quarters, 1:46 and 1:46 showed that I had gone out too fast. I did save something for the sprint finish, however, and did the final quarter in 1:38.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A serious and unexpected problem I had while running this race was that my mouth got very dry and I had trouble breathing as a result. It was pretty weird. I don&amp;rsquo;t exactly remember this in my mile races from a decade ago. I did hydrate considerably before the race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, of course, as I do in 5K races, I felt like puking during the final quarter, and my arms were getting tingly and losing sensation. It&amp;rsquo;s just what happens to me in the final push. I believe there is no way to avoid feeling like puking if I&amp;rsquo;m running as hard as I can, but I have a feeling that the problem with my arms has to do with my tightening up (rather than relaxing) and flailing around. I plan to try to fix that for my next races this month and next month; what is required, clearly, is disciplined speed work, which is something I have not done in years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;enjoying-being-a-spectator&#34;&gt;Enjoying being a spectator&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The really cool thing about a mile race held in waves is that you get to be a spectator for the remaining waves after you&amp;rsquo;re done. In a 5K race or longer, there aren&amp;rsquo;t any heats and you never get to be a spectator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was wowed watching the &amp;ldquo;Unstoppable&amp;rdquo; under-40 wave whose qualification time was running faster than 6:00. Watching good, fast running is a real pleasure to me, like watching skilled dancers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also a treat was getting to watch the female elite wave and male elite wave. These &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/27/why-i-do-not-watch-the-olympics-any-more/&#34;&gt;Olympic&lt;/a&gt;-caliber runners looked so elegant with their long, powerful strides.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-shoes&#34;&gt;My shoes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d been considering running a race soon wearing my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/26/walking-and-running-in-invisible-shoes-a-review/&#34;&gt;Invisible Shoes huaraches&lt;/a&gt;, but without testing them out with speed work, I&amp;rsquo;m not ready to go there yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I wore the shoes I&amp;rsquo;ve been &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/23/happiness-is-finishing-39th-of-43-men-in-a-race/&#34;&gt;road racing in for almost a full year now&lt;/a&gt;, the Vibram FiveFingers Bikila LS. They worked out just fine. I didn&amp;rsquo;t get blistered because it was cool and it was only a mile. Next month I&amp;rsquo;ll see whether I get blistered in the Great Race &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/25/blistered-but-blissful-in-the-burgh/&#34;&gt;the way I did last year&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;race-organization&#34;&gt;Race organization&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought the race was pretty well-organized, especially given that this was the first time such a race has been held in Pittsburgh. Thanks go to the sponsors, the timers, the announcers, the volunteers who handed out race numbers and stocked water and bagels at the finish line and handed out goodie bags and T-shirts, the police officers who closed the roads and lanes where necessary and directed traffic and kept Liberty Avenue clear, the spectators who cheered, the providers of the many port-a-johns near the start line, the &lt;a href=&#34;http://bringbackthemile.com/news/detail/Miller_and_Kampf_Win_GNC_Live_Well_Liberty_Mile&#34;&gt;elite runners who put on a display of amazing running&lt;/a&gt;. Everyone without question was helpful and friendly. The whole experience was just wonderful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The inaugural GNC Live Well Liberty Mile was a great event. I hope it is the beginning of a Pittsburgh tradition that, like the Great Race and the Pittsburgh Marathon, will continue for years and decades to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-08-09&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-08-09)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/08/09/getting-up-when-reality-punches-you-in-the-face-running-the-second-liberty-mile-in-pittsburgh/&#34;&gt;I ran the second Liberty Mile a year later.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>