<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Voting on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/voting/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Voting on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/voting/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Some good science-based reading for Election Day, whether or not you voted</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/04/some-good-science-based-reading-for-election-day/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2014 15:41:25 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/04/some-good-science-based-reading-for-election-day/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/11/01/how-i-avoid-demotivating-myself-away-from-voting/&#34;&gt;I voted&lt;/a&gt; today, on Election Day in the US.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/franklinmingchen/15527007380&#34; title=&#34;IMG_20141104_153326 by Franklin Chen, on Flickr&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7496/15527007380_abfb7f5691.jpg&#34; width=&#34;375&#34; height=&#34;500&#34; alt=&#34;IMG_20141104_153326&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, now is as good a time as any for some interesting articles about politics and voting. Here are some that came my way:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;motive-attribution-asymmetry&#34;&gt;Motive attribution asymmetry&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/oliver-burkeman-column/2014/nov/04/get-along-enemies-motive-attribution&#34;&gt;Oliver Burkeman&lt;/a&gt; discusses a study that shows that you argue that your side is motivated by &lt;em&gt;love&lt;/em&gt;, while the other side is motivated by &lt;em&gt;hate&lt;/em&gt;. But since the other side thinks the same, what is the &amp;ldquo;truth&amp;rdquo;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;One of the reasons it’s so hard to accept the notion that our enemies might be motivated by love, I suspect, is because that conclusion seems to suggest that our enemies’ cause must therefore have merit.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Actually, those two issues are completely unrelated.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I agree with this: it is quite possible (I&amp;rsquo;m not saying it&amp;rsquo;s always the case) for someone you disagree with to have the most loving intentions, but simply be &lt;em&gt;mistaken&lt;/em&gt; rather than &lt;em&gt;evil&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;dangers-of-accurate-statistical-prediction-by-data-journalism&#34;&gt;Dangers of accurate statistical prediction by data journalism&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A good article in the Berkeley Journal of Sociology about &lt;a href=&#34;http://berkeleyjournal.org/2014/11/what-should-the-fox-say/&#34;&gt;Nate Silver&amp;rsquo;s statistical journalism&lt;/a&gt; argues that data journalism should focus on understanding rather than prediction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;This extensive use of Big Data for election forecasting passively promotes our current sense of political fatalism.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;If our politicians can’t risk making public appearances or trying to appear human without navigating at least three levels of performative irony, then our political culture has entered a state of structural crisis.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;emotions-of-election-day-asymmetric-hedonic-response&#34;&gt;Emotions of Election Day: asymmetric hedonic response&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://harvardmagazine.com/2014/11/emotions-of-elections-study-todd-rogers&#34;&gt;Harvard Kennedy School research result&lt;/a&gt; on asymmetric hedonic response: after an election, losing makes you far sadder than winning makes you happy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I confess to having been really bummed out fairly often in the past two decades of voting. I&amp;rsquo;ve been trying to be more detached.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;in-praise-of-the-occasional-voter&#34;&gt;In praise of the occasional voter&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, some people make fun of people who do not vote (I never do this; there are often quite rational reasons to avoid voting). Here&amp;rsquo;s an interesting article arguing that the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2014/11/02/upshot/the-vital-role-of-the-occasional-voter.html&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;occasional voter&amp;rdquo; is actually quite valuable&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From an economics point of view, &amp;ldquo;voting is a classic example of a free-rider problem&amp;rdquo; because the possible gain for each individual is so tiny, statistically, that it may not make sense to go out of one&amp;rsquo;s way to vote.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, voting has an interesting cost to the voter: &amp;ldquo;The very act of voting for a given candidate or party ties us mentally to that candidate and inadvertently costs us some measure of our neutrality.&amp;rdquo; This is because we &lt;em&gt;rationalize&lt;/em&gt; what we do in order to resolve our &lt;em&gt;cognitive dissonance&lt;/em&gt; about the apparent pointlessness of voting. We try to fool ourselves into thinking we did something really important. &amp;ldquo;We don’t just choose what we like; we like more and more what we choose.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the &amp;ldquo;occasional voter&amp;rdquo; can be an outsider not subject to cognitive dissonance as much as the regular and party-registered voter, countering partisanship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, it could be argued that partisanship, and the resulting gridlock, is good. But is it? That&amp;rsquo;s another topic entirely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-strange-sameness-of-political-candidates-in-the-face-of-competition&#34;&gt;The strange sameness of political candidates in the face of competition&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Conversable Economist, Timothy Taylor, offered an explanation for &lt;a href=&#34;http://conversableeconomist.blogspot.com/2014/11/the-excessive-sameness-of-politics-and.html&#34;&gt;why politicians end up in the same squishy middle&lt;/a&gt;, based on &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Harold_Hotelling&#34;&gt;Hotelling&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s famous 1929 mathematical model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Mainstream politicians thus face a continual dynamic where they seek to reassure their more ardent partisans that they are on their side, while shading and tacking as needed to pick up voters in the middle.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, if you are interested in more mathematical modeling, check out Scott Page&amp;rsquo;s free MOOC on &amp;ldquo;model thinking&amp;rdquo;, which I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/06/16/review-of-coursera-course-model-thinking/&#34;&gt;reviewed here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;bloggers-reactions-to-election-day&#34;&gt;Bloggers&amp;rsquo; reactions to Election Day&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a blogger I follow, &lt;a href=&#34;http://ayjay.tumblr.com/post/101755797073/and-one-more-note-on-politics&#34;&gt;Alan Jacobs, on his options&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/the-fix/wp/2013/05/09/people-hate-congress-but-most-incumbents-get-re-elected-what-gives/&#34;&gt;People hate Congress, but 90% of incumbents get re-elected&lt;/a&gt;. &amp;ldquo;The message from voters to Congress? Throw the bums out. But not my bum.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope you enjoyed this taste of research results concerning psychology, sociology, and economics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not staying up to watch the returns from today&amp;rsquo;s election. I did what I did, and it&amp;rsquo;s over for me until next May.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Did you learn anything surprising in the links I shared here? Is there anything that will change how you think or behave when it comes to politics?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How I avoid demotivating myself away from voting</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/01/how-i-avoid-demotivating-myself-away-from-voting/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Nov 2014 22:11:10 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/01/how-i-avoid-demotivating-myself-away-from-voting/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s that time of year again: three days from today is Election Day. I&amp;rsquo;ve written a few posts about voting over the past couple of years here already, and I&amp;rsquo;ve clearly changed my attitude about it over time:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/08/i-dont-know-if-i-should-vote-but-i-did/&#34;&gt;November 2011&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;April 2012: I was too apathetic to vote.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/11/06/i-decided-to-resign-myself-to-continue-voting/&#34;&gt;November 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/05/21/voting-in-the-face-of-election-apathy/&#34;&gt;May 2013&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;November 2013: I voted but wrote nothing about it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/05/20/why-i-voted-yet-again/&#34;&gt;May 2014&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is my first post &lt;em&gt;before&lt;/em&gt; an Election Day rather than &lt;em&gt;after&lt;/em&gt; having voted. Why the change this time?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;reflections-on-my-past-behavior-and-attitudes&#34;&gt;Reflections on my past behavior and attitudes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have always been frustrated by politics and voting. That showed in my posts in the last three years. I always got very &lt;em&gt;emotional&lt;/em&gt; and torn about the whole process. I finally settled on a habit of trying to &lt;em&gt;minimize&lt;/em&gt; my involvement, not paying attention to any races or &amp;ldquo;debates&amp;rdquo; or any political coverage in the news until the night before Election Day, but I was still unhappy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-situation-now&#34;&gt;The situation now&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, it is still the case that I have not looked at any political coverage for Tuesday. In fact, I have no idea who&amp;rsquo;s running for what, with one major exception: Governor of Pennsylvania. That&amp;rsquo;s been in the news for a year now, and totally unavoidable if you live in PA at all, and especially if you bothered to vote in the primary in May, which I did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that I am accidentally less &lt;em&gt;angry&lt;/em&gt; now than I used to be, because unknown to me, Abby has intercepted all political flyers arriving in our mailbox or &lt;em&gt;on our doorknob&lt;/em&gt; (how dare they!) and recycled them, with one exception.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;negative-emotions-came-back&#34;&gt;Negative emotions came back&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I saw a flyer in a pile of mail. I tried not to see anything as I picked it up and recycled it, but it was impossible to see &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt;. I have to hand it to the designer: the name of the politician reached my eye somehow, even though I prided myself on not seeing a single word (at least consciously) of anything else on the flyer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A rush of disgust and anger came my way, as I reflected that actually, this is someone I already decided last May in the primary to vote for in the general election. As I&amp;rsquo;ve mentioned in previous posts, flyers that are shouting, negative, fear-mongering, and deceptive &lt;em&gt;piss me off&lt;/em&gt; and make me want to &lt;em&gt;puke down the throats&lt;/em&gt; of these politicians, &lt;em&gt;especially those I expect to vote for&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Note that in order to minimize bias, I have never heard this guy talk, and barely recall what he looks like, although I think I saw some head shot back in May. Also, I have no idea what he&amp;rsquo;s been doing or saying since May, or whether any truly major scandal has broken out, although I assume I would have heard by now if so. I will learn what I need to know on Monday night.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;taking-more-control&#34;&gt;Taking more control&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But now, after having &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/10/31/win-ugly-or-lose-pretty-do-you-agree/&#34;&gt;read that fascinating article yesterday about emotional manipulation&lt;/a&gt;, I have decided that these politicians are only doing the rational thing in their game, nothing personal. You might want to argue that this is a flaw in democracy, as many ancient and modern philosophers have, of course, but that would be another topic of discussion entirely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was also annoyed by the robocall on the answering machine at home today, from the same guy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;action-to-further-minimize-annoyance&#34;&gt;Action to further minimize annoyance&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We shut off the answering machine for our land line. We will not be answering any phone calls until after Election Day. Actually, we are not sure why we need any phones connected to our land line anyway, because in principle we could make sure all relevant accounts list our cell phones as our primary phone numbers (most already do but some old ones don&amp;rsquo;t yet). We only need the land line for DSL purposes. The land line has been mostly nothing but trouble, a target for robocalls of all kinds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, I wish there were a way to stop getting junk mail in general. Not just the election season junk mail, but all junk mail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There will be no Election Day blog post on Tuesday. I&amp;rsquo;ve said all I need to say for this Election Day.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why I voted yet again</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/05/20/why-i-voted-yet-again/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 May 2014 22:52:11 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/05/20/why-i-voted-yet-again/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I voted again, as I&amp;rsquo;ve been doing regularly for some years now.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/voter-receipt-primary-2014.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;2014 PA primary election voter receipt&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But why?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/05/21/voting-in-the-face-of-election-apathy/&#34;&gt;vented a bit about voting&lt;/a&gt; but did so anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year, I paid almost no attention to any media coverage before the election. This included deleting answer machine messages, and summarily recycling all campaign flyers sent to my home, with an attempt not to even see who sent them. I don&amp;rsquo;t know if it&amp;rsquo;s just my imagination, but these flyers have gotten louder and more annoying and inane. I made the mistake of actually seeing &lt;em&gt;one&lt;/em&gt; of these flyers (and therefore know who it was from). In all caps and colored, bold text (if I recall correctly), it said something like&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Mike knows us.

And we know Mike.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That pretty much sums up what political campaigns are. And we know that psychologically, this stuff works. Just slamming someone&amp;rsquo;s name into our brains, creating &amp;ldquo;familiarity&amp;rdquo;, influences votes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yeah, I voted for Mike anyway. After all, &amp;ldquo;I know him&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;governor&#34;&gt;Governor&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I knew very little about the main race, the primary election for Pennsylvania governor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The night before, I did a little bit of research, largely on whom to vote &lt;em&gt;against&lt;/em&gt;. One candidate apparently stood out for pretty harsh negative ads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the whole, such negative ads turn me off. Now, I understand that psychologically, some people are motivated by negative ads to go vote against the target. But it&amp;rsquo;s actually difficult to anticipate exactly what the tradeoff is, in terms of attracting support vs. fueling the opposition. Obviously, I would never make a decision based purely on campaign tactics, but in this case, I figured I would go with someone not particularly different on issues who did &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; engage in this kind of behavior.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;but-why-vote-at-all&#34;&gt;But why vote at all?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wish I could tell you that I feel I&amp;rsquo;m making a difference by voting. I&amp;rsquo;m not sure that&amp;rsquo;s true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wish I could tell you that I feel it is my &amp;ldquo;civic duty&amp;rdquo; to vote, because I have the privilege of having the right to do so as a citizen of the United States. I&amp;rsquo;m not sure I feel that is my duty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The truth is, I vote every election day now simply because I&amp;rsquo;ve developed a &lt;em&gt;habit&lt;/em&gt; of it, and a &lt;em&gt;system&lt;/em&gt; (avoiding media coverage that would piss me off, and doing a bit of homework the night before election day). So, it&amp;rsquo;s just what I do now. I no longer question whether I will get out there and press the big red button. I just do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Do you vote? In every election or just high-profile primary or general elections, such as presidential? Why do you vote or not vote?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Voting in the face of election apathy</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/05/21/voting-in-the-face-of-election-apathy/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 May 2013 19:17:44 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/05/21/voting-in-the-face-of-election-apathy/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/voter-receipt-primary-2013.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;My voter receipt, May 2013&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Those of you who follow my blog know that I have been conflicted about voting, but go and do it anyway, &lt;em&gt;most of the time&lt;/em&gt;, e.g., &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/08/i-dont-know-if-i-should-vote-but-i-did/&#34;&gt;in November 2011 for the municipal election&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/11/06/i-decided-to-resign-myself-to-continue-voting/&#34;&gt;in November 2012 for the general election&lt;/a&gt;, when I felt there were some politicians very important to &lt;em&gt;vote against&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;apathy-or-ignorance&#34;&gt;Apathy or ignorance?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In April 2012&amp;rsquo;s general primary, however, I was sufficiently apathetic that I didn&amp;rsquo;t bother voting, although Abby did. For that election, it seemed to me that the winners were all going to be obvious no matter what I did, and there were no close races where I really cared about who won. I feel that in the absence of an informed opinion, the only rational and moral thing to do is to stay out. It is &lt;em&gt;unfashionable&lt;/em&gt; in our society to admit &lt;a href=&#34;http://opinionator.blogs.nytimes.com/2013/04/29/the-power-of-i-dont-know/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;I don&amp;rsquo;t know&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, but if I truly don&amp;rsquo;t know, then I see no point in participating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Primary_election&#34;&gt;Primary elections&lt;/a&gt; are particularly problematic for me, because I simply oppose the concept and also resent being forced to register for one of the two major American political parties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;may-2013-municipal-primary-choosing-mayor&#34;&gt;May 2013 municipal primary: choosing mayor!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this year&amp;rsquo;s Democratic primary is &lt;em&gt;critical&lt;/em&gt;, because it will basically determine who becomes the next &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pittsburgh_mayoral_election,_2013&#34;&gt;mayor of Pittsburgh&lt;/a&gt;, given that a Democrat will win in the general election in November. And since &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Luke_Ravenstahl&#34;&gt;Luke Ravenstahl&lt;/a&gt; decided to step down, there is a possibility of &lt;em&gt;real change&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I was pretty excited to vote today to make a difference (I hope). This will be the first time I have voted for a &lt;a href=&#34;http://triblive.com/politics/politicalheadlines/4052165-74/percent-mayor-turnout&#34;&gt;mayoral candidate in a primary&lt;/a&gt; in my 15 years as a Pittsburgh resident. For once there may be a crack in the rusty Democratic political machine here?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.post-gazette.com/stories/local/neighborhoods-city/polls-open-for-primary-election-688496/&#34;&gt;Voter turnout today has been crazy low&lt;/a&gt;. There was no line whatsoever when I went to vote or when Abby went. I&amp;rsquo;ve never participated in an election, I think, with such low turnout.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Maybe this low turnout will end up being a good thing&lt;/em&gt;. If people choose not to vote because they don&amp;rsquo;t have informed opinions, then it means that I and the surprisingly large number of people I know who also voted for the same guy I did will &lt;em&gt;win&lt;/em&gt;! (That said, it&amp;rsquo;s sad if &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pittsburghmagazine.com/Best-of-the-Burgh-Blogs/Pitt-Girl/June-2013/Why-You-Must-Vote-in-Pittsburghs-Mayoral-Election/&#34;&gt;only 2 percent of us decide the mayor&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;media-coverage&#34;&gt;Media coverage&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I avoided &lt;em&gt;most&lt;/em&gt; media coverage of the election (hard to avoid everything completely, admittedly) until I had already voted. (Yes, that includes ignoring the basically meaningless &amp;ldquo;endorsements&amp;rdquo; of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.post-gazette.com/&#34;&gt;Post-Gazette&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://triblive.com/&#34;&gt;Tribune-Review&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I enjoyed reading &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pghcitypaper.com/Blogh/archives/2013/05/21/election-day-thoughts&#34;&gt;this little look at what&amp;rsquo;s been going on with the mayoral race&lt;/a&gt;. And tomorrow I am back to ignoring the news.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, I had to recycle probably 30 or so paper flyers during election season. What a waste. And summarily delete dozens of robocalls on the answering machine. Note to everyone who sent me junk or left junk messages on my answering machine: &lt;em&gt;I did not read a single thing you sent, or listen to a single word you spoke; your junk only made me angry and at least partly less likely to vote for you, if I caught your name and remembered it&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;Pathetic.&lt;/strong&gt; I realize this crap works on some people, but I&amp;rsquo;m afraid it doesn&amp;rsquo;t work on me: I&amp;rsquo;m not going to believe that your opponent eats children for breakfast, no matter what large fonts you use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a moment of relief from apathy and cynicism about politics, I eagerly voted today. I hope I&amp;rsquo;ll get to see whether I was justified.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I decided to resign myself to continue voting</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/11/06/i-decided-to-resign-myself-to-continue-voting/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Nov 2012 12:05:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/11/06/i-decided-to-resign-myself-to-continue-voting/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/voter-receipt-2012.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;My voter receipt 2012&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Last year I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/08/i-dont-know-if-i-should-vote-but-i-did/&#34;&gt;wondered aloud about the act of voting&lt;/a&gt;, being unsure about how to justify my annual participation in this ritual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This being a presidential election, avoiding getting sucked in is a perpetual chore, given that it is impossible for me to completely avoid people&amp;rsquo;s political pontifications on their blogs, Twitter, Facebook, Google+, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I even had to stay home from work in order to avoid &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/06/obama-is-speaking-outside-my-office-window-so-why-did-i-stay-home/&#34;&gt;politicians annoyingly disrupting the workplace&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My conclusion was that, for me, the only rational response (that didn&amp;rsquo;t result in my getting frustrated and angry, which seems the tone of most of the politics-related chatter I see on social media) is to spend as little time as possible on politics, spend the evening before an election to do some research, and then go out and vote for the &amp;ldquo;lesser evil&amp;rdquo; for each race (yes, it&amp;rsquo;s not just about President, and in fact, local races are the ones in which voting is most likely to make a difference).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So last night, I held my nose, read up on various PA state candidates, made my choices, and this morning I went and voted. And now I&amp;rsquo;m going to simply proceed with my day. I&amp;rsquo;m not going to follow any election news coverage whatsoever. Instead, I&amp;rsquo;m going to try to get stuff done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, and whoever wins in each of these races, please go and do your job for us the best you can. Get stuff done. Stop blabbering lies and promises.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Obama is speaking outside my office window, so why did I stay home?</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/07/06/obama-is-speaking-outside-my-office-window-so-why-did-i-stay-home/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jul 2012 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/07/06/obama-is-speaking-outside-my-office-window-so-why-did-i-stay-home/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Right now, President Obama is &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cmu.edu/news/stories/archives/2012/july/july3_obama.html&#34;&gt;speaking&lt;/a&gt; on the College of Fine Arts lawn at Carnegie Mellon University, right outside my office window. Apparently, &lt;a href=&#34;http://twitter.com/thetartan/status/221267182707949569&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;the line for President Obama&amp;rsquo;s visit to CMU goes from Purnell to Gesling Stadium&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. That&amp;rsquo;s some line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday at work I saw a lot of setup going on out on the lawn:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/obama-cmu-setup.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;CFA lawn being set up for Obama&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, today I stayed at home. Why did I stay at home when I could have picked up a free ticket yesterday for this event? (Below is a photo of someone else&amp;rsquo;s ticket since I did not get one.)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/obama-cmu-ticket.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Ticket for Obama event at CMU&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;it-s-not-about-obama&#34;&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s not about Obama&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, I want to make it clear that this is not about Obama. It is not about whether I like or hate him, or whether I will vote for or against him this fall. If it were Mitt Romney, I would not be attending.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;it-s-about-politics&#34;&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s about politics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t like politics, but &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/08/i-dont-know-if-i-should-vote-but-i-did/&#34;&gt;I do vote&lt;/a&gt;. In fact, just in the last couple of years, I even do what I have to do in order to vote in closed primaries. I find it extremely distasteful to have to register for some official &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.goodreads.com/quotes/show/401859&#34;&gt;party&lt;/a&gt; in order to vote in primaries, but I did it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At various points in my life, I have either been apathetic, cynical, or idealistic about politics. Right now, I would say I am simply realistic and take a rational approach, devoid of all emotion. I minimize following of political news or getting into heated arguments. I go out twice a year to vote.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nothing Obama is saying right now or not saying would likely affect my vote, so from a rational point of view, there is nothing to be gained from wasting valuable time (and suffering in the summer heat outside) just to hear him on his campaign tour. Furthermore, if he really is saying anything truly interesting, I&amp;rsquo;m sure I&amp;rsquo;ll get the executive summary from someone and if I really wanted to, I could get a transcript too, probably.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a world of too much pointless information, I don&amp;rsquo;t need political speeches to use up my brain cells.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;it-s-especially-about-presidents&#34;&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s especially about presidents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m particularly uninterested in following presidential politics, because the cult of the presidency has overwhelmed American politics. The president gets credit or blame for everything. People forget that the US was founded with three branches of government, and the executive is just one of those three. Congress and the Supreme Court are critical. In fact, just recently we saw how important the Supreme Court is, when the Roberts Supreme Court &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.forbes.com/sites/aroy/2012/07/01/the-supreme-courts-john-roberts-changed-his-obamacare-vote-in-may/&#34;&gt;surprisingly upheld Obamacare&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At a time when monarchy was still the norm, George Washington chose not to become a king. We&amp;rsquo;re not supposed to have kings in this country. Yet people really do long for king-like figures, whether as saviors or villains. This longing is &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.enduringword.com/commentaries/0908.htm&#34;&gt;part of human nature&lt;/a&gt;, unfortunately. I&amp;rsquo;m doing my part to choose to buck human nature and ignore presidents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d be more likely to attend a speech by a prospective candidate for Mayor of Pittsburgh than to attend speeches by any future presidents or presidential candidates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obama&amp;rsquo;s talking, and I stayed at home to get stuff done.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I don&#39;t know if I should vote but I did</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/11/08/i-dont-know-if-i-should-vote-but-i-did/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Nov 2011 09:09:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/11/08/i-dont-know-if-i-should-vote-but-i-did/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t like politics, and I don&amp;rsquo;t like voting. When I turned eighteen years old, I didn&amp;rsquo;t celebrate by getting registered to vote and participating in the presidential election the very same year. The first time I ever voted, I was twenty-two. In recent years, I have been voting almost every chance I have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/voter-receipt-2011.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin&amp;#39;s voter receipt for 2011&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-vote&#34;&gt;Why vote?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, I don&amp;rsquo;t know exactly why. I know all the arguments &lt;em&gt;for&lt;/em&gt; voting: it&amp;rsquo;s my civic duty, I can&amp;rsquo;t complain about what politicians do if I&amp;rsquo;m not involved in selecting them, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-not-vote&#34;&gt;Why not vote?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also know all the arguments &lt;em&gt;against&lt;/em&gt; voting: what difference do I make anyway (empirically, the vast proportion of the time, whenever I vote for someone, that person &lt;strong&gt;loses&lt;/strong&gt;), why should I vote for someone I find loathsome, why should I vote for someone who is going to do a lot of things I oppose, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-is-actually-at-stake&#34;&gt;What is actually at stake?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, it seems to me that what is at stake is often purely personal gratification. People like to feel good about themselves, by imagining that they are doing their civic duty or that they are &amp;ldquo;sending a message&amp;rdquo; by refusing to compromise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;lesser-evil&#34;&gt;Lesser evil&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is another perspective that I used to strongly dislike: voting as choosing a &amp;ldquo;lesser evil&amp;rdquo;. Once framing voting as an unpleasant task, with low expectations, it&amp;rsquo;s easier to hold your nose and do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, there are arguments against &amp;ldquo;lesser evilism&amp;rdquo;: because the American political system is completely broken, captured by lobbyists, and unfriendly to third parties, choosing a lesser evil narrows debate and does nothing to encourage politicians to adopt alternative points of view outside the narrow bipartisan consensus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The argument for lesser evilism is that maybe on some issues, the other side has views and intentions that are considerably worse, maybe even &lt;em&gt;crazy&lt;/em&gt;, and it&amp;rsquo;s worth doing everything possible to stop the other side. Hence, politicians love using negative ads in order to paint the other side as crazy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I try to avoid all exposure to robocalls and negative ads, because I tend to think that politicians who go out of their way to smear their opponents in filth are themselves the filthy ones I don&amp;rsquo;t want to vote for, and therefore if I see too many ads, I end up not wanting to vote for anyone at all!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;local-pittsburgh-referendum&#34;&gt;Local (Pittsburgh) referendum&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today&amp;rsquo;s election I was going to turn up for, independent of all I have said above, because of the Carnegie Library &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Referendum&#34;&gt;referendum&lt;/a&gt; on a 0.25 mill special tax on all taxable real estate in the City of Pittsburgh to be allocated and used only for the maintenance and operation of the Carnegie Library of Pittsburgh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are lot of people who don&amp;rsquo;t like referenda, because as a form of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Direct_democracy&#34;&gt;direct democracy&lt;/a&gt; it bypasses the overall framework of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Representative_democracy&#34;&gt;representative democracy&lt;/a&gt; in which we, the people, are supposed to elect politicians to decide matters for us, rather than act as a mob. The upsides and downsides of both forms of democracy are well-known (California&amp;rsquo;s political system, incorporating both the representative process as well as its infamous &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/California_ballot_proposition&#34;&gt;ballot propositions&lt;/a&gt;, is completely broken).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the case of the Carnegie Library referendum, I&amp;rsquo;ve heard a lot of very heated rhetoric on both sides of it. This time, at least, I appreciated the opportunity to have a say rather than depend on politicians to decide for me, because I feel strongly about the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/30/free-to-the-people-since-1895/&#34;&gt;importance of libraries&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2012-11-06&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-11-06)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following year, I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/11/06/i-decided-to-resign-myself-to-continue-voting/&#34;&gt;continued to vote&lt;/a&gt; and expect to continue, year after year.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>