<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Running on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/running/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Running on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/running/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>How I forgot to meditate after sixty days in a row of remembering and what that means</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/01/24/how-i-forgot-to-meditate-after-sixty-days-in-a-row-of-remembering-and-what-that-means/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2015 13:58:29 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/01/24/how-i-forgot-to-meditate-after-sixty-days-in-a-row-of-remembering-and-what-that-means/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I woke up this morning feeling very tired. I also suddenly realized that yesterday, I forgot to set aside time for the daily meditation practice (just ten minutes a day) that I had successfully done for &lt;em&gt;sixty days in a row&lt;/em&gt;, having deliberately started it &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/11/24/report-on-my-first-day-of-stoic-week-2014/&#34;&gt;shortly before Thanksgiving&lt;/a&gt;. I was pretty angry at myself. But I also thought about how it was possible that I slipped after sixty days, and what that means.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-s-my-meditation-schedule&#34;&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s my meditation schedule?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The optimal way to maintain any habit is to make it as rigid and automatic as possible. Several years ago, when I went months at a time without missing a single day, my system was to meditate first thing in the morning, before eating or exercising or anything else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I confess that I still don&amp;rsquo;t have that kind of rigid schedule yet. Much of the time, I do meditate first thing. Other times, I feel pressed for time and want to get some work done. Or I&amp;rsquo;m feeling very hungry and decide to eat breakfast first. But usually I do complete meditation in the morning. Occasionally I &amp;ldquo;forget&amp;rdquo; but then remember well before bedtime, and get it in before sleeping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-my-forgetting-yesterday-says-about-my-life&#34;&gt;What my forgetting yesterday says about my life&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, I was feeling tired when I woke, because of a week of accumulated fatigue from doing many things, including going out last night with Abby for the second week of blues dance class at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.tartanswing.com/&#34;&gt;Tartan Swing&lt;/a&gt; at CMU. Adding an extra evening out every week is requiring some changes in how much other stuff I can get done in evenings, and apparently I have not scaled back enough to make up for that additional commitment; it is always a struggle for me to &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/12/15/thoughts-on-giving-up-an-old-project-to-make-room-for-the-new/&#34;&gt;give up something to make room for something else&lt;/a&gt;, but especially on short notice, since we had not originally planned, in December, to start checking out Tartan Swing this January!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, yesterday was Friday, and I tend to feel I have many things to try to get done on Friday. I ate breakfast immediately, did work stuff, then since I was scheduled to go for a run, I did that. I&amp;rsquo;ve been ramping up on my run distances, and I ran my second longest distance so far this month: the length was the sum of the length of my Monday and Wednesday runs this week! So that took more energy than I am used to yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I came home from work, I was extremely tired and hungry, to the point that I decided I wanted to eat a whole lot of food and do something different, so Abby and I went out for dinner. I came home totally stuffed. In any case, going out was an unscheduled, spontaneous decision, and by the time we came home, none of the whole day had gone according to my usual pattern. And so I somehow forgot to get in meditation before going to bed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;lessons-learned&#34;&gt;Lessons learned&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first lesson is that just because I missed one day of meditation after sixty in a row, that doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean I&amp;rsquo;ve lost everything. I meditated today, and will continue my practice. It&amp;rsquo;s important to recover as quickly as possible, to avoid what has happened to me before, which is to feel ashamed, start identifying (after too many days in a row missed) as a &amp;ldquo;non-meditator&amp;rdquo;, and give up the practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other is that I&amp;rsquo;m definitely overbooked and need to make sure I get rest, and get back on schedule for what I can manage to do. A busy week is coming up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What do you do when you find out that you&amp;rsquo;ve missed a day of meditation, exercise, or some other daily practice? Do you feel bad about yourself? Do you make excuses? Do you examine what is really important? Do you set up a system to prevent having to rely on will power? What is your latest experience of slipping, and how did you deal with it?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Report on my final day of Stoic Week 2014: the view from above</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/30/report-on-my-final-day-of-stoic-week-2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2014 22:16:07 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/30/report-on-my-final-day-of-stoic-week-2014/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s the seventh and final day of Stoic Week 2014! I am very glad I participated in the daily readings and reflections. I&amp;rsquo;ve made so many positive changes in my life already. Now it&amp;rsquo;s time to stick to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;health&#34;&gt;Health&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been spending all of the Thanksgiving long holiday weekend catching up on sleep. I have a meditation habit now and today it was warm out and I went for a run and ended up doing five miles in Frick Park. This is the longest distance I&amp;rsquo;ve run in months!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;nature-providence-the-larger-whole&#34;&gt;Nature, providence, the larger whole&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is fitting that today&amp;rsquo;s theme is the Stoic view of humanity as being embedded in something bigger, call it &amp;ldquo;nature&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;providence&amp;rdquo;. Part of why I enjoy running in the trails of Frick Park is that in its own small way, the experience puts me in touch &lt;em&gt;directly&lt;/em&gt; with something bigger than us; I encounter dogs, chipmunks, trees, creeks, leaves, mud, and even deer (not today, but Abby and I saw one during our hike there yesterday).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I honestly feel more whole and alive when I see more of nature, and not in some self-conscious sentimental way. It&amp;rsquo;s more subtle than that. And there&amp;rsquo;s nothing sentimental about those steep hills that make me gasp for air when I climb them. But I sure appreciate the cleaner air in the park than on the main urban roads of Pittsburgh! And I remember where air comes from and how fragile its quality and composition is. The big picture matters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am grateful for the organizers of Stoic Week for putting it on again this year. Here is something I&amp;rsquo;ve decided to do, to keep its spirit alive indefinitely: I will continue to explore various interpretations of Stoicism (note that I don&amp;rsquo;t feel compelled to buy into any particular school or even call myself a Stoic at all), as well as other philosophy (for example, the Zen I had begun looking into years ago) on a daily basis, to keep my mind always focused on applying principles of practical living.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Did you hear about Stoic Week this year? If you did, why did you choose to participate in it, or more interestingly, choose not to?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Report on my first day of Stoic Week 2014</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/24/report-on-my-first-day-of-stoic-week-2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2014 22:30:51 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/24/report-on-my-first-day-of-stoic-week-2014/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Last year, I heard about the first Stoic Week, &lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.exeter.ac.uk/stoicismtoday/stoic-week-2013/&#34;&gt;Stoic Week 2013&lt;/a&gt;, but did not participate because I was distracted at the time and did not feel like focusing. This week, I decided it was time to sign up for &lt;a href=&#34;http://modernstoicism.com/course/view.php?id=5&#34;&gt;Stoic Week 2014&lt;/a&gt;, and I did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-my-interest-in-stoicism&#34;&gt;Why my interest in Stoicism?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve mentioned Stoicism only briefly in my blog: once in 2012 when &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/11/22/thanking-the-best-of-all-possible-worlds/&#34;&gt;thinking about Thanksgiving&lt;/a&gt; and once earlier this year after &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/01/17/hiroo-onoda-and-the-six-million-dollar-man/&#34;&gt;rewatching an old TV episode&lt;/a&gt;. As I mentioned, it was in 2011, upon reading a book on Stoicism, that I made some major changes in my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that a couple of weeks ago, I decided to make major changes in my life again, but not while thinking about Stoicism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over a year ago, my meditation practice fell apart, and I never really regained it. As a result, my thoughts and habits have become disordered, I have felt. For example, I stopped writing regularly for my blog. I spent too much time on Facebook and Twitter instead, being distracted, annoyed, and worse, behaving in ways that I later came to feel counterproductive. I did &amp;ldquo;quit&amp;rdquo; Facebook in July, and also &amp;ldquo;quit&amp;rdquo; Twitter some weeks ago (part of the big life changes I set in motion), but still, I have felt ungrounded. I decided Stoic Week 2014 would be a good opportunity for me to return to the contemplative life that Buddhism and Stoicism in their different ways aspire to and that I had forgotten.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-i-did-the-first-day-of-stoic-week-2014&#34;&gt;What I did the first day of Stoic Week 2014&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, as I started the first day of Stoic Week 2014, I began by meditating ten minutes, Zen style. &lt;em&gt;This was my first meditation session in weeks&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I read the assigned text for today in the Stoic Week handbook, on &amp;ldquo;What is in our power?&amp;rdquo; A basic principle of Stoicism is that we should know what is under our control and what is not, and summarily refuse to dwell on or resent what is not under our control, and focus on making good decisions about what is under our control. A very simple but powerful concept, especially in a world in which it is easy to get annoyed or angry about many things we hear about in the news or encounter in our daily lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My exercise habit has been very spotty for months now. Well, today I reflected that, what the hell, it is completely under my control whether I choose to exercise or not, so why am I wasting this precious freedom? Some people don&amp;rsquo;t have this freedom. Others, including prisoners in jail, have little freedom but make use of what they have, and &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/17/the-joys-of-convict-conditioning-bodyweight-exercising/&#34;&gt;they exercise&lt;/a&gt;! It happened to be warm outside today, so I really had no excuse. I went for a run in Frick Park. It was short, less than three miles long, but I went. &lt;em&gt;This was my first run in weeks&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was my turn to cook today at home, so I made a substantial beef casserole dish. Abby has (rightfully) complained in the past when I didn&amp;rsquo;t completely clean up after cooking. Well, today I thought to myself that it is completely within my control whether I choose to attend to the details of cleanup as much as I attend to the details of using our skillets and baking pans. So I cleaned up as well as I could.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have not been feeling very well physically for weeks now since an incident involving emergency dental work that somehow resulted in complications. I am still in recovery. OK, so it is not under my control that I am not in good health right now. But what is under my control? After lunch I took a nap, because I felt like I needed it. I have been skimping on naps, but this is stupid, because I know that sleep is the best restorative practice when ill. It is under my control whether I choose to set aside time to sleep as needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At work, a colleague just came back from his first trip in Asia. He gave me samples of some odd snacks: chips, cookies, and candy. In recent months, I would have opened them up and eaten them on the spot. Indeed, I have been having problems with eating too many snacks for no rational reason. Today, I decided that it is up to me whether I choose to give in to random cravings or temptations, and so I chose to put the snacks aside for later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After work, I went to a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/Pittsburgh-Code-Supply/events/210396972/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Code and Supply Build Night&lt;/a&gt;, where food was served. Apart from a Thanksgiving dinner (!), some kind of cake lurked around. I took one glance, and chose not to even look at it again until leaving (when it was already all eaten).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leaving Build Night, I found myself annoyed that it was taking forever for the pedestrian light to change, but caught myself and observed that, first of all, the cycle is as it is, beyond my control; and second, I had mistakenly assumed that someone had pressed the button, so it was my fault I had to wait so long. I pressed the button and eventually got to cross. Next, while driving home, I made the mistake of driving behind a bus, which kept stopping. I got annoyed, not by the bus, but by myself, for mistakenly driving on the wrong street rather than the other one that does not have this problem; I got annoyed that I was too lazy to make a U-turn on the street I was parked on in order to get to that other street. But I stopped myself when I realized that what was done was done, and I simply had to endure the rest of the drive home behind the bus because it was not going to save any more time if I detoured around it late in the game: the best I can do is to be more careful in the future when making choices while driving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I felt I improved my life today by keeping in mind the fundamental Stoic principle of observing what is not under my control and what is under my control. I look forward to continuing to adopt this outlook for the rest of the week, and beyond that.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thoughts on the construction of the new Frick Environmental Center</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/08/05/thoughts-on-the-construction-of-the-new-frick-environmental-center/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2014 21:12:30 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/08/05/thoughts-on-the-construction-of-the-new-frick-environmental-center/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Almost exactly twelve years ago, in 2002, tragedy struck in Frick Park in Pittsburgh. I was on a long evening run in Frick Park when I unwittingly came across what had happened earlier in the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;from-my-journal-august-4-2002&#34;&gt;From my journal, August 4, 2002&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;91 degrees, heat index 93. The Frick Park entrance was closed off for
some reason with tape, so that I could not access the water fountain I
had counted on using, so I ran up to Forbes instead and to Braddock to
get a fountain at that end of the park.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later in the evening, I found out what had happened:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Whoa!!!  The Frick Environmental Center was burned down in the
morning.  No wonder it was all closed off when I tried to run to the
water fountain.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was &lt;a href=&#34;http://old.post-gazette.com/neigh_city/20020805frickpark0805p1.asp&#34;&gt;reported the next day in the Post-Gazette&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;construction&#34;&gt;Construction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.post-gazette.com/local/city/2014/08/04/Frick-Environmental-Center-construction-begins/stories/201408040171&#34;&gt;Yesterday&lt;/a&gt;, construction of the new &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pittsburghparks.org/environmentalcenter&#34;&gt;Frick Environmental Center&lt;/a&gt; began, finally, after twelve years of uncertainty and controversy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On my evening run tonight (very cool, in the 60s, this summer, unlike the summer of twelve years ago!), I checked out the construction site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Road sign on Beechwood Blvd:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/franklinmingchen/14817138516&#34; title=&#34;Road sign for Frick Environmental Center by Franklin Chen, on Flickr&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3882/14817138516_f9529cdba9.jpg&#34; width=&#34;375&#34; height=&#34;500&#34; alt=&#34;Road sign for Frick Environmental Center&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Old burned building still there:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/franklinmingchen/14653568337&#34; title=&#34;Old Frick Environmental Center by Franklin Chen, on Flickr&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5581/14653568337_6f5ec39932.jpg&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; height=&#34;375&#34; alt=&#34;Old Frick Environmental Center&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some trail detour signs:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/franklinmingchen/14840109625&#34; title=&#34;Trails detoured for Frick Environmental Center construction by Franklin Chen, on Flickr&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3914/14840109625_f49a9061fb.jpg&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; height=&#34;375&#34; alt=&#34;Trails detoured for Frick Environmental Center construction&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;controversy&#34;&gt;Controversy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was controversy because of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pghcitypaper.com/pittsburgh/natural-selection-critics-question-choice-of-site-for-new-frick-environmental-center/Content?oid=1760832&#34;&gt;concerns&lt;/a&gt; about the impact of the major development planned on Frick Park, which has been prized by many (certainly by me!) as the &amp;ldquo;wildest&amp;rdquo; space in Pittsburgh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I understand the concerns, and realize there are some major tradeoffs in creating a new, fancy Environmental Center. It is &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburghparks.wordpress.com/2014/06/26/like-a-pheonix-rebuilding-a-new-frick-environmental-center/&#34;&gt;argued by the Pittsburgh Parks Conservancy&lt;/a&gt; that there are potentially tremendous benefits to having a modern community facility for education, especially for children. While I regret that some of the wildness of this part of Frick Park will be demolished, I hope that bringing interesting programs to children, especially urban children who might otherwise fail to ever appreciate nature, will be worth the development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will miss not accessing some trails of the park from this direction for a while, but having sadly seen the old burned building lying around abandoned for twelve years, I look forward to its being replaced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;questions&#34;&gt;Questions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you live in the neighborhood of Frick Park, how do you feel about the controversy over the new Frick Environmental Center? Do you believe the risks are uncertain or not worthwhile? What do you think will be the actual outcome and impact, to the environment as well as to the community, of the development and of the planned educational center?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you do not live in the neighborhood, how do you feel about these fancy developments in general? Have you seen them turn out badly somewhere else? Or turn out well?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thoughts on National Running Day 2014</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/06/04/thoughts-on-national-running-day-2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2014 19:19:21 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/06/04/thoughts-on-national-running-day-2014/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;This is my third year of celebrating &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.runningday.org/&#34;&gt;National Running Day&lt;/a&gt;. The first year, I did so by &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/06/06/i-celebrated-national-running-day-in-schenley-park-remembering-how-i-began-to-run-13-year-ago/&#34;&gt;running in Schenley Park&lt;/a&gt;; last year, I quietly did &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/06/05/celebrating-national-running-day-quietly-in-frick-park/&#34;&gt;my usual Frick Park run&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year, I ran in Frick Park again, a shorter run, because I took such a long break from running since last October, and only recently returned to regular running.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/frick-park-2014-06-04/frick.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;luna-venado-sandals&#34;&gt;Luna Venado Sandals&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since it was a shorter run of just 3 miles, I wore my thin &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lunasandals.com/products/luna-venado&#34;&gt;Luna Venado Sandals&lt;/a&gt; (only 7 mm thick) instead of the Luna Mono Sandals that I wore on last year&amp;rsquo;s run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/frick-park-2014-06-04/luna-venado-sandals-top.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Luna Venado Sandals&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/frick-park-2014-06-04/luna-venado-sandals-side.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Luna Venado Sandals&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;thoughts&#34;&gt;Thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m grateful that I have returned to running after many months off. It&amp;rsquo;s good for my body and most of all, my mind, actually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m grateful that I have no excuse to go out since I live so close to Frick Park.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m grateful that running is one of those things that (assuming your legs and feet are doing OK) you can do as slowly or as easily as you need or want to. I&amp;rsquo;m just ramping up slowly right now, and feel no anxiety about what level of fitness I&amp;rsquo;m at now. If I get tired, I can always walk, no shame. It&amp;rsquo;s all good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Do you run? Do you make it a ritual, as apparently I have, of taking time out periodically to reflect on what running means to you?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A note on running in warm weather</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/04/13/a-note-on-running-in-warm-weather/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Apr 2014 21:43:14 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/04/13/a-note-on-running-in-warm-weather/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I haven&amp;rsquo;t been running much at all in recent months; actually, I barely ran all winter, in contrast to last winter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since it&amp;rsquo;s warmer now, I no longer have an excuse. I went out for a short run in Frick Park late in the afternoon, when it was warm and sunny, probably around 80 degrees F.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a really tough time out there, going less than three miles before I turned around and started walking home. I know from prior experience that after not running much, I have to ramp up slowly, but in this case, the suddenly warm weather (after months of a seemingly endless winter) took a toll on me. So I&amp;rsquo;d like to remind anyone else coming out of &amp;ldquo;hibernation&amp;rdquo; not to feel discouraged if feeling unfit: just do a little bit of running at a time, &lt;em&gt;hydrate&lt;/em&gt; (I was grateful that the water fountains in the park are operational), and &lt;em&gt;be patient&lt;/em&gt;! If I didn&amp;rsquo;t know any better, I would be feeling quite discouraged after my excursion today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I treated myself to some cookies after my run. These are cookies I saved from an event at work last week, specifically for only after hiking or running. &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/01/16/a-system-for-quitting-eating-cookies/&#34;&gt;I would not eat&lt;/a&gt; these unremarkable cookies otherwise!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/frick-park-2014-04-13/cookie1.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Cookie 1&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/frick-park-2014-04-13/cookie2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Cookie 2&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/frick-park-2014-04-13/franklin.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Did glucosamine and MSM relieve my knee pain?</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/28/did-glucosamine-and-msm-relieve-my-knee-pain/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2013 22:39:20 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/28/did-glucosamine-and-msm-relieve-my-knee-pain/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.drug3k.com/img2/msm_16804_4_%28big%29_.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;MSM&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I just saw an article &lt;a href=&#34;http://well.blogs.nytimes.com/2013/10/28/ask-well-glucosamine-and-msm-for-joint-pain/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Glucosamine and MSM for Joint Pain?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; that brought up some old memories. The article examined whether these supplements are actually useful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-story&#34;&gt;My story&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started running and hiking over a decade ago, at age 29. Some of my blog posts here have discussed why and how I started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the first couple of years of such activity, I was plagued with a lot of knee and other pain (especially shin pain). I experimented with many things, including changing types of shoes and foot landing form. Meanwhile, someone told me about &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Methylsulfonylmethane&#34;&gt;MSM&lt;/a&gt; and swore by it for his joint pain, and shared some with me. He showed me packets of white powder he bought from bulk by mail order, and I periodically mixed some in with water to drink. I was never sure whether it was effective, but wanted to believe it was. But I still got knee pain periodically; I never knew whether I got it less bad than when I wasn&amp;rsquo;t taking MSM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-actual-solution-to-pain&#34;&gt;My actual solution to pain&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eventually, I did fix my knee pain, so I stopped taking MSM (and glucosamine, which I was taking also, as late as 2003).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My solution, found by sheer trial and error and desperation, was to migrate entirely to wearing only minimalist shoes: in particular, a zero-drop &lt;em&gt;heel&lt;/em&gt;. Some experiments with different shoes revealed to me a clear correlation between knee pain and the height of the heel of a shoe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was very difficult for me to accept this solution, as I had acquired a large collection of non-minimalist shoes: in fact, I had stocked up on some of the &amp;ldquo;less bad&amp;rdquo; shoes and had boxes of shoes in my basement that I had never opened!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the complete disappearance of my impact pain and injuries said it all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, a decade later, there is much more widespread knowledge of the differences in &lt;em&gt;impact&lt;/em&gt; forces depending on shoe style and foot strike. Obviously, there are many variables and individual differences in biomechanics, but here is a &lt;a href=&#34;http://barefootrunning.fas.harvard.edu/4BiomechanicsofFootStrike.html&#34;&gt;good overview of the sorts of things that happen during foot strike&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://barefootrunning.fas.harvard.edu/Fig1b.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Shoe heel strike&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I seem particularly susceptible to the forces on my knees when running in shoes with a built-up heel, so I have &lt;em&gt;finally&lt;/em&gt; decided to completely abandon them. Up till now, I had abandoned them except for &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/31/why-i-went-frick-park-trail-running-in-snowfall-for-the-first-time-in-a-decade/&#34;&gt;winter running when I did not have a good alternative&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am currently evaluating suitable minimalist running shoes for winter, before winter arrives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I learned a big lesson a decade ago when I tried to solve physical problems by throwing medication and supplements at them, and eventually found out that my problems had to do with misusing my body with shoes that disabled me from running in an optimally healthy way. Since then, I have never resorted to medication or fancy technology as the first step in solving problems.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My promise to prioritize my sleep</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/12/my-promise-to-prioritize-my-sleep/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Oct 2013 22:33:48 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/12/my-promise-to-prioritize-my-sleep/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Despite my knowledge (both firsthand and from reading research results) that sleep is important to healthy living, I have been failing to get my optimal sleep for a long time now. There are several reasons of this, but I am taking steps to address each one of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;too-many-activities&#34;&gt;Too many activities&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I began the process of catching up on sleep today by sleeping almost all day. Abby and I had yesterday decided to cancel our hiking plan for today because we both felt tired and decided it was a good time to just rest. We both have a bad habit of doing too many activities and not getting enough down time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I already mentioned some of the things I&amp;rsquo;m scaling down on: &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/10/04/final-rehearsal-for-my-first-ukulele-gig/&#34;&gt;musical activities&lt;/a&gt;. Today was the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.coolhanduke.com/&#34;&gt;Cool Hand Uke&lt;/a&gt; workshop and concert, both of which I had decided earlier to skip.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;night-time-distractions&#34;&gt;Night time distractions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not sleeping as early or deeply as I should, because of not turning down the lights and getting off the computer at night. I&amp;rsquo;m going to change that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In particular, social media at night are the worst. My decision today to &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/10/12/taking-a-break-from-twitter/&#34;&gt;take a break from Twitter, Facebook, and Google+&lt;/a&gt; will help a lot. Too much stimulation at night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;exercise&#34;&gt;Exercise&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a symbiotic relationship between sleep and exercise: the better the sleep, the more energy for stimulating exercise, and the more exercise, the more ready the body is to sleep in the evening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, after I slept almost all day, I found myself with energy to go for a run (I&amp;rsquo;ve barely been running in the past week). To my surprise, I effortlessly kept going and going, and ended up doing ten miles, no problem, in Frick Park and Summerset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was huge confirmation to me, that just catching up on sleep enabled me to enjoy a ten-mile run when I&amp;rsquo;ve barely been feeling like running at all in the past week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-2013-10-12/1.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-2013-10-12/2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-2013-10-12/3.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-2013-10-12/4.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-2013-10-12/5.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-2013-10-12/6.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m going to keep up good habits in order to improve my life. Sleep is the number one priority that I believe will benefit everything else.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Was that a ukulele I heard in Frick Park? No, a cavaquinho</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/06/was-that-a-ukulele-i-heard-in-frick-park-no-a-cavaquinho/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Oct 2013 14:19:09 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/06/was-that-a-ukulele-i-heard-in-frick-park-no-a-cavaquinho/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I had just run into Frick Park past the blue slide playground entrance when I thought I heard someone playing a ukulele! I looked around and saw a guy sitting on a park bench. I thought of approaching him, but decided not to interrupt my run, and kept going.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s what Frick Park looked today on a trail, with some fallen leaves. Bizarre that it&amp;rsquo;s still summer temperatures right now though.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/frick-park-2013-10-06.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Frick Park trail with fallen leaves&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When I came back around out of the trails, I saw the guy again and he was packing up to leave, so I approached him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out to be Ben, to whom &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/01/run-shadyside-5k-outrunning-mickey-mouse-and-lending-a-trumpet/&#34;&gt;I had lent a trumpet two years ago&lt;/a&gt; (since returned)! I asked him if the instrument in his case was a ukulele. He said no. I asked if it was a guitar. He said no. It was a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cavaquinho&#34;&gt;cavaquinho&lt;/a&gt;, the Portuguese ancestor of the Hawaiian ukulele! He pulled it out of the case and let me check it out. It&amp;rsquo;s tuned differently from the ukulele:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/cavaquinho.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Ben&amp;#39;s cavaquinho&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I had heard of this instrument, from reading something about the history of the ukulele (in particular, I had looked at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.coolhanduke.com/worldukehistory.html&#34;&gt;Cool Hand Uke&amp;rsquo;s booklet on ukulele history&lt;/a&gt; recently). Also, Handerson (who is from Brazil) had asked me if I knew where to buy a cavaquinho. Ben said he was looking for other cavaquinho players in Pittsburgh, so I sent him Handerson&amp;rsquo;s contact information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So no, I was not just hallucinating &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/10/05/performing-with-the-steel-city-ukuleles-at-the-wilkins-school-community-center-ecofest-2013-with-videos/&#34;&gt;post-ukulele-gig&lt;/a&gt; when I thought I heard a ukulele in Frick Park.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You never know what or who you might encounter in the park on a nice day.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>9 things you could be doing in Pittsburgh on Saturday, October 5</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/04/9-things-you-could-be-doing-in-pittsburgh-on-saturday-october-5/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2013 00:46:44 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/04/9-things-you-could-be-doing-in-pittsburgh-on-saturday-october-5/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m always frustrated at this time of year because there are so many events of interest to me in Pittsburgh that seem to happen on the first weekend of October. Since I cannot attend all of them, I figured I might as well attempt a public service and mention some of them so that if you are in the Pittsburgh area, maybe you can go and enjoy what I can&amp;rsquo;t attend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So here are 9 of the probably dozens of cool things you could be doing tomorrow, Saturday, October 5, 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;free-concert-allegheny-city-ragtime-orchestra&#34;&gt;Free concert: Allegheny City Ragtime Orchestra&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re interested in ragtime or Latin music, check out &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.shadysideacademy.org/page.cfm?p=12541&#34;&gt;this concert by the Allegheny City Ragtime Orchestra&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some articles in anticipation of it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.post-gazette.com/stories/ae/music/preview-ragtime-orchestra-connects-with-history-705929/&#34;&gt;Post-Gazette&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://triblive.com/aande/music/4763900-74/ragtime-music-concert&#34;&gt;Trib&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I wanted to go, but finally decided that we have too many other activities earlier in the day and need to just stay home and unwind in the evening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;free-conference-podcamp-pittsburgh-8&#34;&gt;Free conference: PodCamp Pittsburgh 8&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 8th annual &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.podcamppittsburgh.com/&#34;&gt;PodCamp Pittsburgh&lt;/a&gt; should be good. If you have any interest in using social media for personal or professional purposes, you should check it out. Interesting talks, opportunities to just socialized and learn new things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I attended in 2010, 2011, 2012, and will attend again for the fourth year. Unfortunately, I will only be able to attend the afternoon sessions. But I didn&amp;rsquo;t want to completely miss it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that PodCamp completely changed my life. For example, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/21/one-month-anniversary-of-my-blog/&#34;&gt;I started this blog in 2011 because of my second PodCamp&lt;/a&gt;, and I became serious about using social media in general, and that led to a total transformation of my life as I learned about local activities and made new friends. (Unfortunately, I didn&amp;rsquo;t get around to finishing my draft reports about my experience at last year&amp;rsquo;s PodCamp 7.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;pittsburgh-south-side-slopes-step-trek&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh South Side Slopes Step Trek&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The annual &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.southsideslopes.org/steptrek/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh South Side Slopes Step Trek&lt;/a&gt; is another event you can attend tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/08/my-god-its-full-of-stairs-pittsburgh-step-trek-2011/&#34;&gt;blog coverage two years ago&lt;/a&gt; as well as my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/09/25/why-you-should-go-out-to-the-pittsburgh-south-side-slopes-step-trek/&#34;&gt;recent update&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, Abby and I will be missing it this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;run-shadyside-5k&#34;&gt;Run Shadyside 5K&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you like to run in races, a fine race is the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.runshadyside.com/&#34;&gt;Run Shadyside 5K&lt;/a&gt;. Fast and flat, with a pancake breakfast and festivities afterwards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not running in it this year, just because I have too many other things to do already for the rest of the day, but here&amp;rsquo;s my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/01/run-shadyside-5k-outrunning-mickey-mouse-and-lending-a-trumpet/&#34;&gt;report from two years ago&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;free-5th-annual-wilkins-school-community-center-ecofest-in-regent-square&#34;&gt;Free: 5th annual Wilkins School Community Center Ecofest in Regent Square&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/ecofest-2013.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;5th annual Wilkins School Community Center Ecofest in Regent Square&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Interested in green living? Check out the &lt;a href=&#34;http://foresthills-regentsquare.patch.com/groups/around-town/p/ecofest-encourages-recycling-green-living&#34;&gt;5th annual Wilkins School Community Center Ecofest in Regent Square&lt;/a&gt;. Abby has regularly attended for the clothing swap. There will also be food, information, and entertainment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that this year, I will also be attending, to perform as a new member of the Steel City Ukuleles. &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/08/23/another-unexpected-life-change-one-month-of-learning-to-play-ukulele/&#34;&gt;I just started playing the ukulele a bit over two months ago&lt;/a&gt;, and have been working hard to help put on an entertaining show!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;ll be performing around 11:30 AM to 12:30 PM. If you come, say hello!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;cmu-donut-dash-2-mile-race&#34;&gt;CMU Donut Dash 2 mile race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, if you are into weird running events, there is the &lt;a href=&#34;http://cmudonutdash.org/&#34;&gt;Carnegie Mellon University Donut Dash&lt;/a&gt;, a 2 mile event serving as a fundraiser for the Children&amp;rsquo;s Hospital of Pittsburgh of UPMC. This is not an event I have ever done, and not one I intend to do, but what the heck, some of you might love this sort of thing!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;national-chess-day-gateway-open-tournament-at-the-pittsburgh-chess-club&#34;&gt;National Chess Day: Gateway Open tournament at the Pittsburgh Chess Club&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did you know that it&amp;rsquo;s time for &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nationalchessday.com/&#34;&gt;National Chess Day&lt;/a&gt;? There will be a tournament at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburghcc.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Chess Club&lt;/a&gt;, the 56th annual Gateway Open. Yes, chess in Pittsburgh has a long and illustrious history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;pittsburgh-perl-workshop&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Perl Workshop&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are a Perl programmer, the &lt;a href=&#34;http://pghpw.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Perl Workshop&lt;/a&gt; is back &lt;a href=&#34;http://pghpw.org/ppw2013/&#34;&gt;this year&lt;/a&gt;. Registration is already closed, so it&amp;rsquo;s not so helpful right now for me to mention it, but in case you didn&amp;rsquo;t know it existed, watch for it next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;ninth-thing&#34;&gt;Ninth thing?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, I guess I miscounted. But there are a whole lot more than nine things to do in Pittsburgh tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, if you are interested in some free stuff to do, there&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.radworkshere.org/interior.php?pageID=64&#34;&gt;RADical Days&lt;/a&gt; listing a whole bunch of stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s no shortage of stuff to do in this great city of Pittsburgh at any time or day of year. I think it&amp;rsquo;s unfortunate that many things I like to do happen to repeatedly fall on the first Saturday of the year, but I&amp;rsquo;m not complaining about an embarrassment of riches. Go out and take advantage of what I can&amp;rsquo;t.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Was it worth sprinting to a terrible fall to finish 25th in the CMU Pretty Good Race 5K?</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/09/06/was-it-worth-sprinting-to-a-terrible-fall-to-finish-25th-in-the-cmu-pretty-good-race-5k/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Sep 2013 22:01:27 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/09/06/was-it-worth-sprinting-to-a-terrible-fall-to-finish-25th-in-the-cmu-pretty-good-race-5k/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On a pleasant Friday late afternoon, not too hot or humid, I ran my 9th CMU Pretty Good Race 5K (and this was Abby&amp;rsquo;s 3rd).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two weeks ago, I did the Run Around The Square 5K in my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/08/24/reflections-on-my-slowest-run-around-the-square-5k-in-13-years/&#34;&gt;slowest time in 13 years&lt;/a&gt;. I was happy to be finishing a 5K race at all. I&amp;rsquo;ve improved some in fitness in the past two weeks, but not enough to make a big difference for today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like last year, I was going into this race not optimally fit. However, given that I just ran a 5K two weeks ago, I had a good idea of what I could do in another 5K, how hard I could push myself. Like I said last year, &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;It&amp;rsquo;s not about how fast I went, but how much I gave of what I had&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I never expected just how much I would give this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;before-the-race&#34;&gt;Before the race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I walked over from my office across Flagstaff Hill to Schenley Park.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pretty-good-race-2013/flagstaff-hill.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Flagstaff Hill&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For some reason, Abby decided to use our dinky Razor kick scooter to come in from home for the race. Unfortunately, she showed up before the race with a bloody hand and knee, having had a nasty fall while using the scooter on the way to Schenley Park. Oops. She&amp;rsquo;s been tired a lot lately (I previously mentioned her dangerous &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/08/24/reflections-on-my-slowest-run-around-the-square-5k-in-13-years/&#34;&gt;decline in fitness all year&lt;/a&gt;) and was regretting signing up to do the Pretty Good Race with me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She tried to be a good sport despite the accident coming in.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pretty-good-race-2013/abby-before.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby before race&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here I am in orange:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pretty-good-race-2013/franklin-before.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin before race&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;weather-conditions&#34;&gt;Weather conditions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Temperature and humidity were much, much better than last year. That promised a considerable time advantage relative to last year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-plan&#34;&gt;The plan&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As with last year, my plan was to make the most of the final downhill part of the course, as well as go for a sprint to pass as many people as I possibly could during the final brief but terrible uphill to the finish line. I was going to have to pace myself intelligently to have something left for the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-race&#34;&gt;The race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I paced myself, not going too fast in the first half of the race. I almost entirely ran my own slow race, as there was nobody else really near my steady pace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After turning around, I starting going hard downhill. I was worried that I didn&amp;rsquo;t see Abby at all during the race. At some point, I passed her walking back to the start. She must have dropped out very early on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was pushing really hard in the final part of the race. Near the uphill finish, I saw a guy slowing down, and he raised his arms as though celebrating finishing. This gesture instantly caused me to go into a sprint more furious than any other sprint finish in my entire life. I made up a huge distance and reached the finish chute just a step before he did. And as I did so, the dry gravel and my leaning too far forward caused me to slip and fall, really, really badly. But I had finished ahead of the guy. Mission accomplished.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;injuries&#34;&gt;Injuries&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I lay stunned and in terrible pain for a few seconds. I had to check whether I was seriously broken. It felt like I was not. I was rather injured, but miraculously, no broken bones. I had managed to break my fall not with my teeth or eyes or fingers, but with my left thigh, right knee, left forearm, left palm, and right palm. I was quite badly scraped and bruised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I heard people asking me, &amp;ldquo;Was it worth it?&amp;rdquo; I didn&amp;rsquo;t know how to answer that. I moved on, stumbling in pain as I tried to catch my breath. I had done what I do, give the race my all, and then some. I was gouged and bleeding, and my right knee had swollen up hugely almost instantly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This wasn&amp;rsquo;t the worst falling injury I&amp;rsquo;ve had in my life, but it&amp;rsquo;s probably my worst since a fall off a bike (also spinning off loose gravel) twenty years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pretty-good-race-2013/left-palm.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Left palm&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pretty-good-race-2013/left-thigh.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Left thigh&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pretty-good-race-2013/right-knee.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Right knee&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pretty-good-race-2013/left-arm.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Left arm&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby returned, and had to explain to the volunteers that she wasn&amp;rsquo;t just finishing, but had dropped out earlier. While I was trying to clean myself up some, she said that she had fallen early on during the race and decided that that was enough and she wasn&amp;rsquo;t going to finish the race. So this is her first Did Not Finish (DNF) in a race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;feeling-lucky&#34;&gt;Feeling lucky&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main thing I kept on feeling while we walked back to my office and then back to my car (very slowly; everything around my right knee was just messed up) and went home for both of us to clean up from our injuries: &lt;em&gt;luck&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It could have been much worse for both of us. My most severe damage was not even to my right knee area (even though walking was difficult) but really my left hand, whose heel of palm was basically scraped away and bruised and my wrist was messed up. But no broken fingers or teeth or wrists or ankles. Same with Abby: lucky us!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;was-it-worth-it&#34;&gt;Was it worth it?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I finished officially tied for 25th place with the guy I actually beat, both of us registering as finishing in 25:28 in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~kalp/PGR/2013.html&#34;&gt;official race results&lt;/a&gt;. Well, I ran 37 seconds faster than last year. That&amp;rsquo;s not nothing, although two years ago I ran 24:36.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I knew the time was not going to be great: I just ran 25:36 in Run Around The Square two weeks ago. The real point was that like last year, I gave it my all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But was it worth getting injured for sprinting for no glory whatsoever? It&amp;rsquo;s not like I was running for first place or something &amp;ldquo;important&amp;rdquo;. Or is that the wrong way to think about it? Why is it worth trying your best for first place but not for 25th place instead of 26th place? Let&amp;rsquo;s ignore the (unfortunate?) fact that in some circles, first place is associated with large monetary rewards, when pondering that question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A different question would be, &amp;ldquo;If you knew you would get this injured from this sprint, would you have done it anyway?&amp;rdquo; I guess the question is &amp;ldquo;no&amp;rdquo;. But how could I &lt;em&gt;know&lt;/em&gt;? There is always risk. There is risk crossing the street, or driving on the turnpike. I&amp;rsquo;ve never fallen during a sprint before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another different question: &amp;ldquo;How will this accident change how you run in the future?&amp;rdquo; I suppose my answer is, I&amp;rsquo;ll be more careful to keep my balance. But am I going to stop the sprinting at the end of a race? I don&amp;rsquo;t see how I can. &lt;em&gt;It is in those moments when I can barely breathe and the world is becoming a blur that I am living with most intensity and purity.&lt;/em&gt; These moments don&amp;rsquo;t come often, but when they are available for the taking, why would I not accept these gifts?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will keep sprinting. I will keep trying to beat whoever is beatable in front of me. That&amp;rsquo;s part of the whole point of racing. I admit to feeling a little odd to being so serious about it when others do it much more casually (and it&amp;rsquo;s their right to do so and they&amp;rsquo;re probably smarter and more balanced than me, I concede). But I don&amp;rsquo;t race often, so when I do, I try to make it matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So my response is: I will need to work on maintaining balance and running on tricky surfaces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, Abby and I decided we should make sure to have a first aid kit around in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-next-race&#34;&gt;The next race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My eleventh Great Race 10K is coming up. I want to do considerably better than I did last year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, I have a lot of healing to do. I am more of a wreck right now than the post-race photos indicate. Things are all swollen and messed up and probably will be for an entire week or two. It&amp;rsquo;s just amazing I haven&amp;rsquo;t broken bones or ligaments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I simultaneously had unfortunate falling accidents today. I was proud to have run as hard as I could given my fitness and will. I don&amp;rsquo;t regret sprinting for 25th place, even if it cost me this time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, we both need to heal.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reflections on my slowest Run Around the Square 5K in 13 years</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/08/24/reflections-on-my-slowest-run-around-the-square-5k-in-13-years/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Aug 2013 12:45:47 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/08/24/reflections-on-my-slowest-run-around-the-square-5k-in-13-years/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This year was the ninth time I ran in the annual &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.runaroundthesquare.com/&#34;&gt;Run Around The Square 5K race&lt;/a&gt;, and Abby&amp;rsquo;s third year in a row. The conditions were great: cool and dry, in contrast to the usual hot and humid conditions at this time of year. (Last year I reported on &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/08/25/my-eighth-time-doing-run-around-the-square-5k/&#34;&gt;my eighth running of the race&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both Abby and I ran this race rather slowly, but were happy and enjoyed the day. Here&amp;rsquo;s why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;both-of-us-coming-back-from-setbacks&#34;&gt;Both of us coming back from setbacks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing to note is that both Abby and I have been recovering from setbacks this year, as I reported two weeks ago after I ran the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/08/09/getting-up-when-reality-punches-you-in-the-face-running-the-second-liberty-mile-in-pittsburgh/&#34;&gt;second GNC Live Well Liberty Mile&lt;/a&gt; 18 seconds slower than last year. That race had me vowing to get back on track, and the very next day I did &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/08/10/emerging-from-my-three-months-of-illness-self-pitying-and-self-loathing/&#34;&gt;begin getting back on track&lt;/a&gt;. The road back to a regular exercise routine has not been easy in the past two weeks, but I have very gradually ramping up on running as well as minimal strength training every single day since then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, I ran the Run Around The Square 5K in 24:35.6 and was pretty to have recovered from several years of decline in fitness and self-care, by running my best time since 2006. For this year, I wrote, &amp;ldquo;I don&amp;rsquo;t know what goal to set for next year. I suppose I could set a goal of getting yet faster, breaking 24:15. That sounds reasonable to me. Going back down to 24:00 may even be possible. It&amp;rsquo;s too early right now to tell. But one thing is for sure: I have no intention of slowing down from this year to next.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, I did not set a firm enough goal. I have learned the hard way that if you don&amp;rsquo;t make a commitment (and then follow up with the discipline and sacrifices required to achieve it), then even in the absence of accidents, a maybe-goal is worthless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year, I went into the 5K race so untrained (two weeks of slowly ramping up before the race is not enough for any training benefits to kick in) that I basically knew that I was going to be super slow. I figured that since I lost 18 seconds in the mile, I would be happy if I lost only one minute in a 3K. So that was my expectation: finish around 25:36 this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;before-the-race&#34;&gt;Before the race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided that this was the race in which I debut my new orange running singlet, to replace my over-decade use of a blue singlet that Abby has gotten very annoyed with:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-around-the-square-2013/franklin-orange.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin wearing orange singlet&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Also, note that since I bought a SPIbelt earlier this year, I now always run races wearing a SPIbelt to carry my phone. This is particularly convenient when running a race where you have to park far from the start line and want access to your phone after a race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wore my Vibram FiveFingers KSO Trek shoes again. Since last year&amp;rsquo;s fiasco in which I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/30/running-my-10th-great-race-10k-obscene-but-in-a-good-way/&#34;&gt;injured my left foot from having the straps on my left foot too tight&lt;/a&gt;, I never again put the straps on too tight!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hanging out before the race start in Regent Square:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-around-the-square-2013/before.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Before start&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-around-the-square-2013/franklin-ready.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin ready&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Start line just a few minutes before race start:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-around-the-square-2013/start-line.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Start line&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-race&#34;&gt;The race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(&lt;a href=&#34;http://runhigh.com/2013RESULTS/R082413AA.html&#34;&gt;Race results.&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;different-race-logistics&#34;&gt;Different race logistics&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One very important change to the race, and one I greatly appreciated, was the staggered start. Faster runners were told to line up front and start up first. This is very helpful to control the congestion and confusion that happens in a large race when too many slower people start up front and have to be passed (including unfortunately young children that Abby and I have seen trampled on every year!). In particular, it is really tricky to be passing lots of people once in the trails of Frick Park.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;first-mile&#34;&gt;First mile&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of the ridiculous problems I created for myself by going too fast two weeks ago in the Liberty Mile, I vowed to go out at a reasonable pace in this 5K. I found this easy to do because of the staggered start, which meant that there were fewer people to have to accelerate past throwing off one&amp;rsquo;s own internal speedometer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The usual lot of young and old musicians were playing music along the course. What a great neighborhood tradition!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still get confused seeing the champagne stop near the end of the first mile at the entrance into the trails of Frick Park.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did the first mile in a leisurely 8:15 (compared to 7:18 last year).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;second-mile&#34;&gt;Second mile&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did the second mile in 10:17 (compared to 10:11 last year). I did not feel too bad. I was running a bit conservatively, because my training runs had been so slow and short and tough for me in the past two weeks. I wanted to be in position to run really well the final downhill in the third mile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;third-mile&#34;&gt;Third mile&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I let loose in the third mile. Because I had avoided going pukey in the second mile, I covered it in 7:06, actually a second faster than the 7:07 of last year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of the staggered start, there was not bad congestion during the third mile, and I found it safe to pass people at will.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;final-sprint&#34;&gt;Final sprint&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t have a gut-wrenching final sprint. I wasn&amp;rsquo;t even looking at the clock or my watch. This wasn&amp;rsquo;t one of those races in which I put it all out there on the course. Instead, this was a race where I was grateful to be running at all, and had no expectations other than to finish strong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I finished in 25:38, just a bit longer than a minute over last year&amp;rsquo;s 24:35.6. My &lt;em&gt;slowest&lt;/em&gt; Run Around The Square 5K time &lt;em&gt;in 13 years&lt;/em&gt;. But it was a clean finish, and I was so excited to simply be back and running faster than 26 minutes, at least.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;after-the-race&#34;&gt;After the race&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although I was not pukey, I was certainly breathing hard when I finished.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-around-the-square-2013/franklin-after.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin after the race&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I went off to drink water and start eating some food.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-around-the-square-2013/view.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;View&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;improvement&#34;&gt;Improvement&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I went back to the finish line to wait for Abby to finish. I saw Todd and his wife Gabrielle hanging around. Gabrielle said she took my &amp;ldquo;advice&amp;rdquo; (from last year) to go all out to the point of feeling pukey. I admitted that this time around, I didn&amp;rsquo;t follow my own advice. Gabrielle finished over 5 minutes faster this year than last year!! Todd finished over 8 minutes faster!! It&amp;rsquo;s great to see people in their late 40s improve their fitness so much in a single year. I saw the couple running together a couple of times in Frick Park this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;decline&#34;&gt;Decline&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby finished. She was out of breath and pukey, but I was proud of her for finishing. Because of the tremendous decline in health and fitness she has experienced this year, I was not sure she would actually finish the race.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-around-the-square-2013/abby-finish.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby finishing&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;more-food-and-refreshments&#34;&gt;More food and refreshments&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We lined up to sample more food and recovered. It was a beautiful day to be outside.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-around-the-square-2013/abby-recovered.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-around-the-square-2013/franklin-recovered.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The hot dogs and beer line was particularly long, but we finally reached the tables.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-around-the-square-2013/hot-dogs-beer.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Hot dogs and beer&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;walking-out-of-frick-park-back-to-the-car&#34;&gt;Walking out of Frick Park back to the car&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I couldn&amp;rsquo;t help taking a photo of the sign for beer and champagne that was still up on the trail entrance as we passed by:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-around-the-square-2013/beer-champagne.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Dunning&amp;#39;s beer and champagne stop&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;concern-about-abby&#34;&gt;Concern about Abby&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although I was happy that Abby managed to finish the 5K race, I was very concerned about her overall health and fitness, which have continued to be poor this year since she broke her foot in February. Here are her Run Around The Square 5K times since she started doing it with me:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2011: 37:15&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2012: 36:04&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2013: 39:54&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She was almost 4 minutes slower than last year. She&amp;rsquo;s lost &lt;em&gt;several years of fitness&lt;/em&gt; this year, and came in 105th of 116 in her age group. Again, we are grateful she is walking and running at all, but this has been a very bad year for her, and this impacts not only her own life, but ours more generally. We need to work on getting her back on track.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;goal-for-next-year&#34;&gt;Goal for next year?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right now, my real goal is to simply continue my exercise program and not break it again, and that includes the winter slump I usually enter. Last year, I had a slump in the final months of the year, and then woke up and &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/28/meditations-on-climbing-the-36-floors-of-the-pitt-cathedral-of-learning/&#34;&gt;started exercising again around New Year&lt;/a&gt;, and even signed up for the Pittsburgh Marathon as a way to force myself to stay active in the winter. I believe that if I simply avoid self-caused setbacks, I should be able to return myself to a decent level of fitness. I am &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; going to sign up for the Pittsburgh Marathon again. Almost certainly, however, I will sign up for the Pittsburgh Half Marathon! Last winter, I rather enjoyed &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/30/report-on-just-a-short-run-my-first-half-marathon-in-nine-years/&#34;&gt;training for and running the Just A Short Run half marathon&lt;/a&gt;. I reached good fitness through that, but squandered my fitness through overtraining and injury leading up to the marathon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;races-this-year&#34;&gt;Races this year&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the shorter term, I have two races to run in the coming month: the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/07/running-my-8th-pretty-good-race-5k-dealing-with-disappointment/&#34;&gt;CMU Pretty Good Race 5K&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/30/running-my-10th-great-race-10k-obscene-but-in-a-good-way/&#34;&gt;Great Race 10K&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, I did very poorly in the Pretty Good Race 5K because I was injured and exhausted, running 26:05. This year, I expect to do better than that. I&amp;rsquo;m not going to do the 24:36 of 2011, but given that I easily beat 26 minutes today, I will beat 26 minutes two weeks from now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Great Race 10K last year, I was still in a state of exhaustion and undertraining, so I didn&amp;rsquo;t even pay any attention to time goals, and finished slowly in 48:23. I see no reason why, if I continue improving my fitness in the next month (in contrast to last year&amp;rsquo;s dreadful September), I should not be able to run under 48:00.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;update-of-2013-09-06&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-09-06)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/09/06/was-it-worth-sprinting-to-a-terrible-fall-to-finish-25th-in-the-cmu-pretty-good-race-5k/&#34;&gt;my report on running the Pretty Good Race 5K this year&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Run Around The Square continued to thrive and improve, and I&amp;rsquo;m grateful for both the registration cap (to maintain the quality of the event) as well as the staggered start. And all the sponsors feeding us afterwards!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I were happy to have finished the race, even if we are both less fit now than we have been in years. But I think this is a wake up call for us to get back in shape. For example, I miss the long hikes we used to do last year when we had the stamina to actually do and enjoy them. The example Todd and Gabrielle set as they massively improved their fitness in the past year is inspiring. Abby and I should be able to do this too, if we make it a priority.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why I was so happy to run 5 miles in 63 minutes today when I was doing it in 50 earlier this year</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/08/13/why-i-was-so-happy-to-run-5-miles-in-63-minutes-today-when-i-was-doing-it-in-50-earlier-this-year/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Aug 2013 21:18:29 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/08/13/why-i-was-so-happy-to-run-5-miles-in-63-minutes-today-when-i-was-doing-it-in-50-earlier-this-year/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I went for a run in Frick Park, my usual 5-mile route, which I haven&amp;rsquo;t done in a while. It took me 63 minutes. Earlier this year I was doing it in 50. My fitness is pretty low right now, as &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/08/10/emerging-from-my-three-months-of-illness-self-pitying-and-self-loathing/&#34;&gt;I explained three days ago&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I&amp;rsquo;m happy to be on the upswing. I&amp;rsquo;m getting out there, not pushing too hard, but challenging myself. I have faith that I will get back out of my slump. I have done this before. Other people have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you also have this experience of being happy to do something worse than you used to do it, because you&amp;rsquo;re doing it at all rather than doing nothing?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Emerging from my three months of illness, self-pitying, and self-loathing</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/08/10/emerging-from-my-three-months-of-illness-self-pitying-and-self-loathing/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Aug 2013 08:39:23 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/08/10/emerging-from-my-three-months-of-illness-self-pitying-and-self-loathing/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, I reported on my feelings after &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/08/09/getting-up-when-reality-punches-you-in-the-face-running-the-second-liberty-mile-in-pittsburgh/&#34;&gt;having a very painful and embarrassing performance in the Liberty Mile road race&lt;/a&gt;. I resolved to slowly return myself to health and fitness, starting &lt;em&gt;immediately&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, Leo Babauta wrote a great blog post that really spoke to me, &lt;a href=&#34;http://zenhabits.net/fraud/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Fear of Being Found a Fraud&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. Basically, he writes advice, but he&amp;rsquo;s not perfect, and doesn&amp;rsquo;t always successfully do what he preaches. I periodically have feelings like that, since I write about stuff too and also post &amp;ldquo;advice&amp;rdquo; links on Twitter, Facebook, and Google+. What would people think if they knew I have been failing myself in the past three months?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, I have to be honest. There&amp;rsquo;s no point lying. I sometimes &lt;em&gt;know&lt;/em&gt; what&amp;rsquo;s best and what has worked for me, but don&amp;rsquo;t take my own advice. This in itself is not the big problem. The real problem is the second-order problem, which is that of believing that I&amp;rsquo;m not only imperfect (we all are), but sometimes ending also deciding to give up on myself. That&amp;rsquo;s the worst thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, after health conditions disrupted my &amp;ldquo;normal&amp;rdquo; routines, I ended up not getting back on track when in fact I should and could have, through a gradual process. In a way, I was too proud to &lt;em&gt;adapt to reality&lt;/em&gt;. I was willing to operate under a different, better reality, but given the worse one, I chickened out, and entered a downward spiral of bad habits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;meditation-habit-destroyed&#34;&gt;Meditation habit, destroyed&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/02/01/a-report-on-one-month-of-daily-meditation/&#34;&gt;restarted a daily meditation practice for the new year&lt;/a&gt;, and entered into a 100-day meditation challenge. I encountered setbacks in my first month, but kept bouncing back. I even &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/01/dealing-with-setbacks-during-my-second-month-of-meditation/&#34;&gt;continued into a second month&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then things got worse, and as you can see in the archives to my blog, I &lt;em&gt;never wrote a report for the third month&lt;/em&gt;. According to my &lt;a href=&#34;http://insighttimer.com/&#34;&gt;Insight Timer&lt;/a&gt; journal, I actually did meditate in March almost every day, so I could have written a blog post on that, but I didn&amp;rsquo;t. &lt;em&gt;That was a mistake&lt;/em&gt;. I have found that public updates on progress keep me more accountable to myself; this is why I have written so much about my personal musical activities: not only to share my journey with those who are interested (because they are friends or because they are themselves on their own journeys), but also to keep myself honest about where I&amp;rsquo;ve been, what I still need to do, where I intend to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In April, my meditation practice started to fall apart. I missed April 10 and 11, then 13, 14, 15, then 18, 19, 20, 20, 23, and the rest of the month. In May I was erratic, till after May 13, &lt;em&gt;I completely stopped identifying myself as a &amp;ldquo;meditator&amp;rdquo; and quit&lt;/em&gt;. That&amp;rsquo;s right: I felt so ashamed of myself that I did not meditate between May 14 and August 9 this year. Big mistake, this pointless shame, especially given that I know, empirically, that &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/30/when-i-dont-have-time-to-sit-and-breathe-something-is-wrong-with-my-life/&#34;&gt;when I don&amp;rsquo;t &amp;ldquo;have time&amp;rdquo; to meditate, something is wrong with my life&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;exercise&#34;&gt;Exercise&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, my exercise schedule completely fell apart. &amp;ldquo;Normally&amp;rdquo;, I run every other day and do strength training the other days. None of this has to be a super-long session. Just enough to keep me mentally and physically alert. My strength training has generally been just a simple half-hour &amp;ldquo;core performance&amp;rdquo; type of workout at home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, I lost the habit, partially because marathon training caused me to cut back on strength training and because after the marathon, I took a break from running. The big lesson I learned here is that marathoning is very disruptive to my ordinary life, and I do not plan to ever do a marathon again in my life. But apart from that, I had non-marathon disruptions also, such as the skin rash after a hike that I&amp;rsquo;ve been dealing with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-i-did-today&#34;&gt;What I did today&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Today is the first day of the rest of my life.&lt;/strong&gt; Clean slate, forget the past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I meditated this morning. And I will continue to make this a high priority and do it daily. I must make sure that if I slip, I simply get back on track, rather than feel shame or whatever. It must simply be a habit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I ran yesterday, today was a non-running day. I decided that one way to prevent myself from completely slipping is to have a backup &amp;ldquo;very short&amp;rdquo; workout in case any kind of laziness or disruption causes me to think about just canceling a workout rather than do a longer one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So today was my first experiment with a &lt;a href=&#34;http://medium.com/editors-picks/e4975b151181&#34;&gt;7-minute workout&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s intense, but fast to get over with. I highly recommend checking it out!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are more links to this type of workout:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://journals.lww.com/acsm-healthfitness/Fulltext/2013/05000/HIGH_INTENSITY_CIRCUIT_TRAINING_USING_BODY_WEIGHT_.5.aspx&#34;&gt;Journal paper&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://7minworkoutapp.com/&#34;&gt;Online app&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifehack.org/articles/lifestyle/master-the-7-minute-workout-with-this-video.html&#34;&gt;Lifehack article&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if you&amp;rsquo;re lazy, surely you have 7 minutes a day to squeeze in this little circuit. I did!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-future&#34;&gt;The future&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back to meditating every day, just 10 minutes a day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I&amp;rsquo;m going to take it easy to ramp back up to fitness. I know it&amp;rsquo;s going to take &lt;em&gt;months&lt;/em&gt; to get back to where I was earlier in the year. &lt;em&gt;Patience is a virtue&lt;/em&gt;. I will start small. A little bit of slow running every other day, and the 7-minute workout every other day, to get started, before extending further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was time to stop my descent into endless self-pitying and self-loathing over all the misfortunes that have come my way in the past months. I&amp;rsquo;m taking my life back.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Getting up when reality punches you in the face: running the second Liberty Mile in Pittsburgh</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/08/09/getting-up-when-reality-punches-you-in-the-face-running-the-second-liberty-mile-in-pittsburgh/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Aug 2013 20:49:35 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/08/09/getting-up-when-reality-punches-you-in-the-face-running-the-second-liberty-mile-in-pittsburgh/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Last year, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/08/17/the-inaugural-liberty-mile-a-review-of-pittsburghs-first-road-mile-race/&#34;&gt;I reported on the excitement I had running in and watching&lt;/a&gt; the first &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.libertymile.org/&#34;&gt;GNC Live Well Liberty Mile&lt;/a&gt;. I was so excited about running it again that late this May, having mostly recovered from my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/05/06/2013-pittsburgh-marathon-my-135th-race-was-my-worst-i-finished/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Marathon disaster&lt;/a&gt;, I quickly pre-registered for the Liberty Mile for this year. I anticipated training to run well in this year&amp;rsquo;s Liberty Mile, given that I was not really trained last year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, this year I have been in very poor shape since the marathon, because of a whole series of health problems and disruptions in my life resulting from a skin rash I got during a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/05/12/my-rachel-carson-trail-hike-for-the-year/&#34;&gt;Rachel Carson Trail hike in May&lt;/a&gt;. The upshot is that I have been running (and exercising in general) very little in the past three months. As the Liberty Mile approached, I wished that I had not registered for it at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I faced a dilemma: what should I do about the race?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;deciding-to-run-it&#34;&gt;Deciding to run it&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The good thing about the mile is that it&amp;rsquo;s short enough that of course I can finish the thing. So I felt there was no excuse to just bail out and forfeit my pre-registration. I was going to run it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bad thing about the mile is that it is brutal to actually run &lt;em&gt;fast&lt;/em&gt;. I have always felt pukey after running a mile as &amp;ldquo;fast&amp;rdquo; as I can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, I decided to still try to run the Liberty Mile as fast as I could, knowing that I would probably suffer for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In recent weeks I&amp;rsquo;ve been trying to go out periodically for short, slow runs, something like two miles at a time, to gain at least have &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; kind of conditioning. Also, earlier this week I put in some &amp;ldquo;fast&amp;rdquo; repeats of about 300m out in Frick Park: the only &amp;ldquo;fast&amp;rdquo; running I&amp;rsquo;ve done since April!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this whole week I was feeling bad, stress exacerbated by home repair disruptions with the contractors coming over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;support-from-abby&#34;&gt;Support from Abby&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, I went to the race alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year, Abby offered to go downtown with me so she could watch the race and be with me. (In May when I was pre-registering for the race, she had just spent months barely mobile because of a broken foot and was simply not certain she would be able to even run a mile again by August.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really appreciated this because I felt rather vulnerable about this race. We planned to watch the first wave start, and then have me run my heat (again the &amp;ldquo;Unstoppable 40+&amp;rdquo; heat), then hang out afterwards and watch the elite heats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We drove downtown and parked and walked to the packet pickup area in Market Square. I was pleased that it wasn&amp;rsquo;t raining; it had rained earlier in the day, but that was all over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because we arrived later than other people, they had run out of Small T-shirts and so I got a Medium.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/liberty-mile-2013/abby.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby holding my T-shirt&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;changes-in-the-course&#34;&gt;Changes in the course&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I should note that the course was changed from last year. The change makes sense because it considerably simplifies the logistics. Last year, the course was a straight shot down Liberty Ave toward downtown. This year, the course was an almost-loop course, first going out on Penn Ave, then turning to head back in on Liberty Ave. The advantage is that the start and finish are close together, so it is much easier for people to plan to spectate or get back to their cars or whatever. I do like the concept of the straight downhill road course, but understand the logistical difficulties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My plan was to do my best to avoid going out too fast, and try to push hard in the final downhill portion of the race. Easier said than done, because last year I certainly wanted to avoid going out too fast, but did anyway!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;before-the-race&#34;&gt;Before the race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wore my Vibram FiveFingers Bikila LS shoes again.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/liberty-mile-2013/before-start.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin before race&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At the GNC booth, I saw they were giving out free samples of energy bars and other stuff. I was feeling hungry, and although I know that it is best not to race having just eaten, especially unfamiliar foods, I took a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.gnc.com/product/index.jsp?productId=4468895&#34;&gt;GNC Pro Performance Pro Crunch Lite&lt;/a&gt; energy bar, and ate a couple of bites before giving the remainder to Abby to put away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was probably a big mistake to have eaten from the energy bar, because it didn&amp;rsquo;t really agree with me. Oops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;start-and-finish-lines&#34;&gt;Start and finish lines&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We checked out the start and finish lines.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/liberty-mile-2013/start-line.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Start line&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/liberty-mile-2013/finish-line.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Finish line&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;first-heat-at-7-00-pm&#34;&gt;First heat (at 7:00 PM)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We watched as the first &amp;ldquo;fun run&amp;rdquo; heat went.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/liberty-mile-2013/first-heat-start.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-race-heat-at-7-20-pm&#34;&gt;My race (heat at 7:20 PM)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got to the start line and lined up &lt;em&gt;at the back&lt;/em&gt;, where I knew I belonged. I was not sure that I would not be last place in my heat!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/liberty-mile-2013/my-heat-start.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here I am, looking as tired as I in fact was, still taking medication for my skin problem that is not completely gone (usually showing up as spots on my neck or hands and arms):&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/liberty-mile-2013/franklin-before.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin before the race&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As the race began, I tried not to go too fast, but did. 1:34 for the first quarter mile, not good at all! Last year, I ran the mile in 6:39, and went out in 1:29 for the first quarter. This year, I was hoping to go under 7:00 at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I slowed down for the second quarter, then finally found a steady pace for the third quarter. During the final quarter, I saw the finish line and eventually saw the clock ticking up toward 7:00. I was &lt;em&gt;furious&lt;/em&gt; that I might not be able to finish a 7-minute mile. I sprinted all out and didn&amp;rsquo;t actually finish under 7:00 according to the clock (the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.areep.com/events/libertymile/&#34;&gt;official race results&lt;/a&gt; say I finished in 7:02), but my chip time was 6:56, so I actually did run the mile in under 7 minutes!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My splits:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1:34 (went too fast)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1:56 (uphill, deliberately slowed down)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1:46 (steady)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1:40 (final kick)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;more-photos-of-the-liberty-mile&#34;&gt;More photos of the Liberty Mile&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More photos of the entire event can be seen &lt;a href=&#34;http://petemadia.photoshelter.com/gallery/2013-GNC-Live-Well-Liberty-Mile/G0000gQc.MfyoOAE/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;after-my-race&#34;&gt;After my race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Afterwards, I felt really, really crappy:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/liberty-mile-2013/done-in-pain.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin done for a while but still in pain&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In fact, for a full half hour after the race, all I could do was walk and sit around with Abby trying to feel less crappy. &lt;strong&gt;I have never felt so bad for so long after any race of any distance.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;reflections&#34;&gt;Reflections&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mentally, also, I was still very &lt;em&gt;angry&lt;/em&gt; at myself: I came in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.areep.com/events/libertymile/results/13lm_uno.txt&#34;&gt;60th place out of 74&lt;/a&gt;, running a chip time of 6:56, a whopping &lt;em&gt;18 seconds&lt;/em&gt; slower than last year. That&amp;rsquo;s a huge decrease in fitness for a mile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My plan for this year, 2013, was supposed to be to get back into great health and fitness, &amp;ldquo;the shape I was in five years ago&amp;rdquo;. It&amp;rsquo;s why, for the new year, I got into &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/28/meditations-on-climbing-the-36-floors-of-the-pitt-cathedral-of-learning/&#34;&gt;climbing the Cathedral of Learning&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s why I got into running in the winter](/blog/2012/12/31/why-i-went-frick-park-trail-running-in-snowfall-for-the-first-time-in-a-decade/). It&amp;rsquo;s why I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/30/why-and-how-i-am-going-to-run-the-2013-pittsburgh-marathon/&#34;&gt;decided to run the Pittsburgh Marathon&lt;/a&gt;. I blew it my overtraining for the marathon and then suffering freak skin problems after a hike that ended up seeing doctors something like five times, and being put on medication that messed with me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a lot to be angry about. But after I recovered, I became calm and stopped being angry about being punched in the face by reality. I decided that it was motivation for me to turn my life around. I decided that I was going to get back into a regular exercise routine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In just the past three months, I have lost all of my fitness of the past several years. But I have a plan to get back on track, starting &lt;em&gt;tomorrow&lt;/em&gt;. I believe that for 2014, I can still get back into my 2008 shape. It&amp;rsquo;s a matter of making it a priority, over all the other things I have been doing in my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;going-home&#34;&gt;Going home&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After I recovered enough that I felt like eating and walking again, Abby and I went back to our car and we went home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only minutes after getting home did I realize that I had &lt;em&gt;totally forgotten&lt;/em&gt; to stick around to watch the elite runners&amp;rsquo; races!! That was far from my mind when I was feeling nauseous and reflecting on my poor fitness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The race was very well organized, and I&amp;rsquo;m thankful for the continuation of this new Pittsburgh tradition. Although I had a humbling experience in my heat, I totally want to be back for a third try at executing a good mile next year! And I am thankful that I actually ran it, because it gave me the resolve to regain my lost fitness.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>