<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Kale on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/kale/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Kale on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/kale/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Why we decided to compile our own family cookbook</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/12/07/why-we-decided-to-compile-our-own-family-cookbook/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Dec 2014 19:46:48 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/12/07/why-we-decided-to-compile-our-own-family-cookbook/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Cooking has been a significant part of my life since 1999 when, shortly before reaching age 30, my bachelor self decided to completely change his unhealthy diet and lifestyle, and that meant &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/03/21/time-to-taste-the-world-thoughts-on-expanding-my-food-tastes-as-an-adult/&#34;&gt;finally getting down and dirty with seriously cooking for myself&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After getting married to Abby ten years later, cooking responsibilities have rotated between us based on the situation; there have been long stretches of time during which I did all the cooking every day, and there have been long periods during which she did all the cooking. Currently, we roughly split the cooking between us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-compile-our-own-cookbook&#34;&gt;Why compile our own cookbook?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve occasionally posted on this blog a recipe and/or photos of some food I&amp;rsquo;ve cooked, but for the most part, cooking is just a mundane everyday activity that I don&amp;rsquo;t keep track of, since the task of cooking is primarily utilitarian for us, not innovative or artistic. We simply need to eat every day, and prefer not to eat out often, for various reasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently I decided that we should start compiling our own family cookbook, noting details of what we prepare and how, in order to better replicate good results and improve on bad results, and make planning and impromptu cooking more efficient. Without our own cookbook, we have to rely on our faulty memories, and things sometimes don&amp;rsquo;t come out right (especially where the oven is concerned).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below is an example of the kind of cooking we do. This is not a cooking blog, so I don&amp;rsquo;t expect to write much or often about our cooking, but I just felt like it tonight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-i-prepared-tonight&#34;&gt;What I prepared tonight&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;raw-veggie-sticks&#34;&gt;Raw veggie sticks&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/franklinmingchen/15945039966&#34; title=&#34;IMG_20141207_174932 by Franklin Chen, on Flickr&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7535/15945039966_f2273fbf1d.jpg&#34; width=&#34;375&#34; height=&#34;500&#34; alt=&#34;IMG_20141207_174932&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We like to regularly cut up raw veggie sticks to eat as daytime snacks at work, or sometimes also as crunchy variety during regular meals as part of salads. I chopped up some carrots and celery for this purpose tonight. We often use other ingredients also, but tonight I just stuck to the basics. A list of some random options we&amp;rsquo;ve used (depending on season, availability in our &lt;a href=&#34;http://kretschmannfarm.com/&#34;&gt;Kretschmann Farm&lt;/a&gt; box subscription, and whim while out grocery shopping):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;carrots&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;celery&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;cucumbers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;peppers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;radishes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;parsnips&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;beets&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;turnips&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trick is simply to slice stuff lengthwise into reasonable widths, then chop them across to create reasonable lengths. No need to be exact. Also, &lt;a href=&#34;http://groovygreenlivin.com/5-vegetables-that-you-don%E2%80%99t-need-to-peel/&#34;&gt;we don&amp;rsquo;t bother to peel carrots&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;kale-boiled&#34;&gt;Kale, boiled&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/franklinmingchen/15970795205&#34; title=&#34;IMG_20141207_174941 by Franklin Chen, on Flickr&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7560/15970795205_3e6492769a.jpg&#34; width=&#34;375&#34; height=&#34;500&#34; alt=&#34;IMG_20141207_174941&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We like kale. There are actually many different varieties with different colors and textures. Here&amp;rsquo;s some ordinary kale. I find it easiest to just boil it while preparing other foods. I test it periodically to make sure it is no longer tough to eat but still has some bite also and is not soggy. We boil the kale either in water or in our own homemade chicken broth that we make with the bones and other parts of whole chickens after eating the muscle meat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;turnips-sauteed&#34;&gt;Turnips, sauteed&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/franklinmingchen/15970797965&#34; title=&#34;IMG_20141207_174949 by Franklin Chen, on Flickr&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8671/15970797965_64a385e5dd.jpg&#34; width=&#34;375&#34; height=&#34;500&#34; alt=&#34;IMG_20141207_174949&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OK, this is an example of something of an experiment that is going into the family cookbook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have cooked turnips in many ways (including, of course, as raw veggie sticks). Possibly the most common way we cook them is in the oven along with beets, potatoes, or the like, either as chunks or in &amp;ldquo;home fries&amp;rdquo; shapes. I&amp;rsquo;ve also prepared them as part of beef casserole dishes in the oven. Or as chicken stir fry with turnips. The possibilities are endless. You just have to be aware of how long they take to cook, and how thinly to slice for the purpose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tonight, I decided to slice the turnips very thin, for the purpose of creating a nice topping for the main dish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;extra virgin olive oil&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;turnips, sliced very thin&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;some onion bits&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;fresh rosemary&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;salt and pepper&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;garlic, generous amount&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My habit these days when cooking in the skillet is to delay the introduction of the garlic, in order to give the result more kick.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;baked-salmon&#34;&gt;Baked salmon&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/franklinmingchen/15968891841&#34; title=&#34;IMG_20141207_180014 by Franklin Chen, on Flickr&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7570/15968891841_7e3aa84a19.jpg&#34; width=&#34;375&#34; height=&#34;500&#34; alt=&#34;IMG_20141207_180014&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, some fish (salmon). I have to confess that I&amp;rsquo;m not yet very happy about the results when I cook fish. Abby does a better job than me overall, so I usually let her cook fish. Still, both of us find it tricky to get fish just so: what&amp;rsquo;s the perfect balance between undercooked and overcooked?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I slightly overcooked the salmon tonight, for a couple of reasons: I forgot to get it out of the fridge earlier in the day to warm it up more before preparation, and I baked a bit too long as an attempt to make up for that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using the oven is always tricky for me. Higher temperature means cooking faster, but also means drying things out. For this dish, I decided on a temperature of 400 F for 30 minutes. Next time, if I have the salmon fully defrosted, I believe 20 should do the trick.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;extra virgin olive oil&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;lemon slices&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;salmon fillets, skin side down on top of the lemon slices&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;salt and pepper&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;fresh rosemary&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;garlic, generous amount&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;some onion bits&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result came out a bit dry, but other than that tasted great to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re wondering &amp;ldquo;why rosemary in particular&amp;rdquo;, the answer is &amp;ldquo;our farm box from last week gave us a bunch and we need to use it&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cooking is a necessity but can be a pleasure or a frustration as well. There are times when I feel &amp;ldquo;lazy&amp;rdquo; and don&amp;rsquo;t want to cook and feel it&amp;rsquo;s a chore, but there are times when I feel slightly creative or experimental and want to make something I will find enjoyable to eat (and hopefully Abby will find enjoyable to eat also). Hopefully collecting our efforts into a cookbook will make it easier to whip up more variety when we are feeling &amp;ldquo;lazy&amp;rdquo; and don&amp;rsquo;t want to think too much.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>&#34;Time to Taste the World&#34;: thoughts on expanding my food tastes as an adult</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/03/21/time-to-taste-the-world-thoughts-on-expanding-my-food-tastes-as-an-adult/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Mar 2014 21:37:07 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/03/21/time-to-taste-the-world-thoughts-on-expanding-my-food-tastes-as-an-adult/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This evening, right after work, I attended an event called &amp;ldquo;Time to Taste the World&amp;rdquo;, organized by Carnegie Mellon University&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cmu.edu/dietrich/modlang/student-organizations/mlsac.html&#34;&gt;Modern Languages Student Advisory Council&lt;/a&gt; for the Department of Modern Languages. It was an informal event featuring some food selections followed by a German film that I opted not to watch, since I needed to go home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were three tables of food, one for &amp;ldquo;Asian&amp;rdquo;, another for &amp;ldquo;Mediterranean&amp;rdquo;, and another for &amp;ldquo;European&amp;rdquo;. Obviously, only a very tiny fraction of the world was actually represented in this event, and the selections were mostly not very exciting, but it was interesting and even jarring going from one table to another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/time-to-taste-the-world-2014/mediterranean.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Mediterranean&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/time-to-taste-the-world-2014/asian.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Asian&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/time-to-taste-the-world-2014/european.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;European&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that standard CMU catering cookies were also provided.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did try a bit of everything, including stuff I less frequently encounter. Unexpectedly, the experience of hopping from one table to another, and sampling every single item, led me to reflect on how unfamiliar some of these items were to me until later in life, and how my taste in food has expanded considerably in my &lt;em&gt;30s and 40s&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;linking-my-history-of-eating-to-time-to-taste-the-world&#34;&gt;Linking my history of eating to &amp;ldquo;Time to Taste the World&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Most of what I like to eat now is what I never ate or knew existed before I was 30 years old&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This probably goes against &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.theguardian.com/lifeandstyle/wordofmouth/2013/jan/29/changing-tastes-food-and-aging&#34;&gt;most people&amp;rsquo;s eating histories&lt;/a&gt;, but heck, I&amp;rsquo;m a late bloomer, because for various reasons, I had very limited life experiences until my 30s and even more so, my 40s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For fun, I decided to think back about when it was that I first ate or even encountered, each of the items I sampled in &amp;ldquo;Time to Taste the World&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;mediterranean-table&#34;&gt;Mediterranean table&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pita bread: OK, I suppose I probably encountered this first in college, when the dorm cafeteria provided it and I used it to eat with tuna fish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grape leaves stuffed with rice: first time encountered and eaten was as a grad student at CMU in 1997, age 27, from Sree&amp;rsquo;s food truck, actually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hummus: also discovered in Pittsburgh upon arrival in 1997.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Baba ghanoush: also discovered in Pittsburgh upon arrival in 1997.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, I still love grape leaves and hummus. Baba ghanoush I still find a bit harsh and biting, but happily eat it in small quantities at a time. By the way, I should note that I discovered olive oil in 1997 also. At first its strong taste and appearance were confusing to me, but I got used to them, and have been using olive oil since as part of my everyday cooking, in fact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;asian-table&#34;&gt;Asian table&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OK, my parents were immigrants from Taiwan, so these foods have never been unfamiliar to me!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spring rolls: my mother makes them sometimes, and of course much better than the commercial frozen ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chicken wings: some of my favorite childhood food memories involve my mother&amp;rsquo;s chicken wings with soy sauce and ginger. Still my favorite flavor of wings!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Noodle dishes: again, my mother makes this stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.npr.org/2011/08/08/139033757/babys-palate-and-food-memories-shaped-before-birth&#34;&gt;our initial food tastes are actually formed in the womb&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;european-table&#34;&gt;European table&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OK, this is the stuff that I&amp;rsquo;m least familiar with, find overall least appealing, and still encounter surprises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was some &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gorgonzola&#34;&gt;gorgonzola&lt;/a&gt; cheese appetizer thing that I&amp;rsquo;ve had before, and I had some here, but it&amp;rsquo;s not really my thing. I don&amp;rsquo;t think I ever ate something like this until my 30s. The taste and texture is interesting. Not my favorite thing to eat, but I could have a little bit now and then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was also &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prosciutto&#34;&gt;prosciutto&lt;/a&gt; wrapped around some cheesy stuff, something I think I never tried until my 40s. Again, it still tastes weird to me, but I can eat it if I have to. It&amp;rsquo;s not revolting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main thing is that I have historically &lt;em&gt;fundamentally&lt;/em&gt; disliked all dairy. I emerged into the world seemingly hating milk: I don&amp;rsquo;t like the taste, I don&amp;rsquo;t like the smell. I was forced to drink milk as a toddler and basically accepted that I was supposed to drink it, and that it was the only thing to go with cereal, so I tolerated it all the way till I went to college. Then in freshman year in college, I came down with severe puzzling health problems, and finally found out by accident (upon missing breakfast for a couple of days) that cutting out my usual breakfast cereal with milk completely solved my problems: I was simply &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lactose_intolerance&#34;&gt;lactose intolerant&lt;/a&gt;. I cut down significantly on dairy consumption (which for me was only milk for cereal, and cheese on pizza).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point in my late 30s, I found that my lactose intolerance had let up, and with care I could eat some forms of dairy without having problems. Cheese on pizza is OK, if it&amp;rsquo;s not &amp;ldquo;extra thick&amp;rdquo;. Cheese in a serving of lasagna is typically not OK, in the quantities provided. Also, in my late 30s I began developing a taste for hard cheeses, which smell less bad to me, and happen to also have far less lactose, and so I do enjoy eating some hard cheeses occasionally: my favorite is &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gruy%C3%A8re_cheese&#34;&gt;Gruyère&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is some food awkwardness at home, because I&amp;rsquo;m married to Abby, who comes from the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nature.com/news/archaeology-the-milk-revolution-1.13471&#34;&gt;dairy-loving peoples&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;m perpetually having to tolerate the odor of dairy of all kinds at home. This is &lt;em&gt;quite difficult&lt;/em&gt; for me, but such is life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;notes-on-more-recent-food-adventures&#34;&gt;Notes on more recent food adventures&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I explored a tremendous amount of new food when I went vegetarian (for several months) at age 29, and got serious for the first time in my life, about cooking for myself. All kinds of bean, lentils, unfamiliar nuts, spices, herbs, vegetables such as kale, etc. Although I didn&amp;rsquo;t stay vegetarian long, that phase of my life resulted in the biggest explosion in my food taste diversity ever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I didn&amp;rsquo;t even touch beets until my mid-30s, when I was &amp;ldquo;forced&amp;rdquo; to because they came in my &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.kretschmannfarm.com/&#34;&gt;farm subscription box&lt;/a&gt;. A whole bunch of other unfamiliar vegetables have come my way through my annual subscription since I began it. The latest was celeriac, which I had never even heard of until it started showing up in our farm box last year. I figured out stuff to do with it, and I like it! It&amp;rsquo;s fantastic continuing to discover new stuff to cook and eat. Life is not boring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m even learning to eat &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brussels_sprout&#34;&gt;Brussels sprouts&lt;/a&gt;. My initial experiences in my 30s made me want to vomit, but there are ways to cook these to make them much more palatable, and in the past couple of years, I have enough tolerable experiences that I can see myself trying them more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;cookies&#34;&gt;Cookies&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did eat some cookies at the event, but only three, in accordance with &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/03/16/pittsburgh-recorder-society-something-new-recently-recording-our-practice-sessions/&#34;&gt;my recent findings about how many I should eat at a time&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/time-to-taste-the-world-2014/cookie1.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Cookie 1&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/time-to-taste-the-world-2014/cookie2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Cookie 2&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/time-to-taste-the-world-2014/cookie3.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Cookie 3&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s never too late to try new foods. You might be surprised and enjoy something new. And if you don&amp;rsquo;t like it, you don&amp;rsquo;t have to keep eating it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m very grateful to have had the opportunity to try new foods now and then, and add to my enjoyment of life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many thanks to the Modern Languages Department at CMU for sponsoring this little event! I hope many of the students attending it got some exposure to new foods that they will remember for the rest of their lives.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>