<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/wolfgang-amadeus-mozart/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/wolfgang-amadeus-mozart/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Chamber music concert at CMU featured Bach&#39;s Goldberg Variations arranged for string trio</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/11/19/chamber-music-concert-at-cmu-featured-bachs-goldberg-variations-arranged-for-string-trio/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Nov 2013 23:04:37 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/11/19/chamber-music-concert-at-cmu-featured-bachs-goldberg-variations-arranged-for-string-trio/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.cmu.edu/news/stories/archives/2013/november/images/chamber-recital_400x340.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;David Harding, Noah Bendix-Balgley, Lorna McGhee, Amit Peled&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I attended a special &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cmu.edu/news/stories/archives/2013/november/nov8_chambermusic.html&#34;&gt;chamber music concert at CMU&lt;/a&gt; that featured some truly excellent musicians.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-musicians&#34;&gt;The musicians&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was particularly interested in seeing &lt;a href=&#34;http://trioverlaine.com/bios/lorna-mcghee/&#34;&gt;Lorna McGhee&lt;/a&gt;, the current principal flute of the Pittsburgh Symphony Orchestra, and violinist &lt;a href=&#34;http://noahbendixbalgley.com/&#34;&gt;Noah Bendix-Balgley&lt;/a&gt;, the concertmaster, both of whom are relatively recent additions to the orchestra. The other two musicians, also fantastic, were violist and CMU professor &lt;a href=&#34;http://trioverlaine.com/bios/david-harding/&#34;&gt;David Harding&lt;/a&gt; and cellist &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amitpeled.com/&#34;&gt;Amit Peled&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;mozart-s-flute-quartet-no-1-in-d-major&#34;&gt;Mozart&amp;rsquo;s flute quartet no. 1 in D major&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lorna McGhee played in the first part of the program, which was Mozart&amp;rsquo;s first flute quartet. I was very curious how she would approach the work, because I&amp;rsquo;m very picky nowadays about the performance of music from the 18th century or earlier, which I far prefer to be both on period instruments and in period style. The typical &amp;ldquo;modern&amp;rdquo; performance I can no longer enjoy, because of stylistic anachronisms that in my mind invalidate the beauty and freshness of early music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed the quartet&amp;rsquo;s performance of the Mozart. The playing was crisp, lively, and transparent. There was little to quibble with in Lorna McGhee&amp;rsquo;s performance: she played with verve, sensitivity, and clarity. In some phrases she held a legato longer than I would like, but overall I quite liked the performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;bach-s-goldberg-variations-arranged-for-string-trio-by-dmitry-sitkovetsky&#34;&gt;Bach&amp;rsquo;s Goldberg Variations arranged for string trio by Dmitry Sitkovetsky&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bulk of the program was devoted to a performance by the string trio of the entire Goldberg Variations by Bach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past quarter century, I&amp;rsquo;ve listened to countless performances of the Goldberg Variations on all kinds of keyboard instrument, including harpsichord, fortepiano, and modern piano, but until tonight, I hadn&amp;rsquo;t bothered listening to Sitkovetsky&amp;rsquo;s arrangement for string trio that came out several years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought it worked out pretty well tonight, with the three string players working really hard to create dynamism and contrast along with unity in this monumental work. I couldn&amp;rsquo;t help but think that it&amp;rsquo;s actually harder to pull off as a trio than as a solo keyboard piece. What was particularly interesting was visually seeing and hearing (in the different tonal qualities) all the different voices in the music. They are there in the original version, of course, but experiencing the spatial separation just made me even more amazed by Bach&amp;rsquo;s creation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I appreciate the time the four musicians took to perform in this chamber music recital free to the public, and thank you, CMU, for bringing them in for these invigorating performances of Mozart and Bach!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>RIP Charles Rosen, pianist and scholar</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/12/10/rip-charles-rosen/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Dec 2012 22:07:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/12/10/rip-charles-rosen/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://yalepress.yale.edu/yupbooks/images/full13/9780300126402.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Charles Rosen, cover of &amp;#34;Music and Sentiment&amp;#34;&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
This book was written from the conviction that understanding music does not come from memorizing an esoteric code. ([Charles Rosen, *Music and Sentiment*, 2010](http://yalepress.yale.edu/yupbooks/book.asp?isbn=9780300126402).)
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, I heard that the noted pianist and musical scholar &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles_Rosen&#34;&gt;Charles Rosen&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.npr.org/blogs/deceptivecadence/2012/12/10/166876593/remembering-charles-rosen-a-prodigious-pianist-and-polymath&#34;&gt;died at 85 yesterday&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://s.wsj.net/public/resources/images/OB-VQ187_rosen6_EV_20121210175859.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Charles Rosen&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I type these words while his book of this year (2012), &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.hup.harvard.edu/catalog.php?isbn=9780674047525&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Freedom and the Arts&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; is visible on my book shelf next to my computer: I had taken it out of the library a while back. I own copies of several of his previous books, starting with his famous [&amp;ldquo;The Classical Style&amp;rdquo;] which was my introduction to his thinking about music. I also own a number of his piano recordings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Put simply, &lt;strong&gt;Charles Rosen changed the entire course of my life&lt;/strong&gt;. Without him, my life would have been completely different, and I would have been a completely different person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t actually remember exactly how I came across Rosen&amp;rsquo;s writings. Here is what I remember about the context.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;freshman-year-in-college&#34;&gt;Freshman year in college&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve mentioned before that I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/09/taking-up-flute-again-after-decades/&#34;&gt;entered freshman year in college having very little musical background&lt;/a&gt;, either as a listener or as a performer, but in order to fulfill a core requirement, in my first semester took an &amp;ldquo;easy&amp;rdquo; music appreciation course called &amp;ldquo;Piano Music of the 19th Century&amp;rdquo;. I also made a new friend in my dorm during freshman week, who happened to be a big fan of Mozart and lent me some of his recordings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, freshman year in college was the year when I fell in love with music all over again, having mostly ignored it after my middle school disasters in music class and band class. Because I made some new friends (from my math and science classes) who were heavily into classical music, I ended up listening to their collections and getting into it myself. Since one of them was a fan of Mozart and the other of Beethoven, it was natural that I became very familiar with music of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Classical_period_(music)&#34;&gt;Classical period&lt;/a&gt;, focused on the late 18th century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;accidental-discovery-of-rosen&#34;&gt;Accidental discovery of Rosen&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point before sophomore year, I must have seen Rosen&amp;rsquo;s book &amp;ldquo;The Classical Style&amp;rdquo; in a local book store and browsed it and found it sufficiently engaging and approachable to buy it. I liked that he combined both readable text as well as excerpts from scores and actual music theoretic analysis. In order to understand better the analysis, of course, I had to learn some music theory, and I eventually ended up taking a two-semester &amp;ldquo;non-majors&amp;rdquo; course on music theory. But the book was readable even without much theoretical knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;making-me-think&#34;&gt;Making me think&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What Rosen&amp;rsquo;s book did for me was that it made me &lt;em&gt;think&lt;/em&gt; about music, and also about a lot more than music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d had a year in college of listening to a lot of music for enjoyment, but felt I wanted to &lt;em&gt;understand&lt;/em&gt; more of what I &lt;em&gt;felt&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;experienced&lt;/em&gt; intuitively. Rosen explained things about how the Classical era&amp;rsquo;s music was very different from the Baroque that preceded it and also very different from the Romantic era&amp;rsquo;s that followed it. He talked about musical forms and structures, the emergent harmonic language, as well as contemporary changes in society, in philosophy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I came away from the book with a much better understanding of various ongoing debates about composer &amp;ldquo;intent&amp;rdquo;, about whether some music is &amp;ldquo;better&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;more advanced&amp;rdquo; than others, about whether old music should be played on modern instruments, about culture in general. I didn&amp;rsquo;t necessarily adopt Rosen&amp;rsquo;s opinions about things, but enjoyed that he provided reasons for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;other-books&#34;&gt;Other books&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the years, I picked up several new books by Rosen as they appeared. Here are examples of what I learned from two of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;frontiers-of-meaning&#34;&gt;Frontiers of Meaning&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 1994 slim volume &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Frontiers-Meaning-Charles-Rosen/dp/187108265X&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Frontiers of Meaning&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; was interesting because Rosen argued that music has &amp;ldquo;meaning&amp;rdquo; and offered his own personal story about changes in his musical taste and understanding. The big message was that if we don&amp;rsquo;t understand a piece of music, we would do well &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; to immediately dismiss it as junk or noise, but try to understand it on its own terms, and maybe even end up actually enjoying it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rosen notes that although he found the string quartets of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/B%C3%A9la_Bart%C3%B3k&#34;&gt;Béla Bartók&lt;/a&gt; harsh and incomprehensible at first, he came to like one of them a lot. He still never ended up liking a different one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, the takeaway message from the book was that if we want to enjoy life, and enjoy as much music as we can, we should open ourselves up to new possibilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;arnold-schönberg&#34;&gt;Arnold Schönberg&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another memorable book was a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Arnold-Schoenberg-Charles-Rosen/dp/0226726436&#34;&gt;1996 book on Arnold Schönberg&lt;/a&gt; that was really fascinating in its discussion of this controversial composer and theoretician. Rosen portrayed Schönberg as a unifier of the past as well as creator of the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I&amp;rsquo;ve &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/25/thank-you-glenn-gould/&#34;&gt;mentioned before&lt;/a&gt;, I still do not enjoy much of Schönberg&amp;rsquo;s music, but thanks to Rosen, I understand where he was coming from, and I think that is important. I also better understand why I like the music of his I like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;recordings&#34;&gt;Recordings&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the years, I went out of my way to obtain some rare recordings of Charles Rosen himself playing piano, such as the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Late-Piano-Sonatas-Charles-Rosen/dp/B00000291P&#34;&gt;late Beethoven piano sonatas&lt;/a&gt;, to test how his interpretations matched what I imagined they would be, from his discussions in his books. I was surprised by some interpretive decisions, and not all of them &amp;ldquo;worked&amp;rdquo; for me, but I felt a sense of satisfaction that here was a guy who not only thought about and wrote about music, but performed it also.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;some-obituaries&#34;&gt;Some obituaries&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2012/12/11/arts/music/charles-rosen-pianist-polymath-and-author-dies-at-85.html&#34;&gt;New York Times&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.guardian.co.uk/music/2012/dec/10/charles-rosen&#34;&gt;Guardian&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.wsj.com/speakeasy/2012/12/10/master-of-piano-and-prose/&#34;&gt;Wall Street Journal&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.artsjournal.com/slippeddisc/2012/12/death-of-a-great-musical-mind.html&#34;&gt;Norman Lebrecht&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;breadth&lt;/em&gt; of Charles Rosen&amp;rsquo;s interests and knowledge was one of the most appealing features of his work: he talked about music theory, piano performance, art, philosophy. I&amp;rsquo;ll miss his presence as an analyst and cultural commentator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-03-11&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-03-11)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An entertaining &lt;a href=&#34;http://standpointmag.co.uk/music-march-13-a-fusion-of-piano-and-cerebellum-norman-lebrecht-charles-rosen&#34;&gt;article by Norman Lebrecht&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-05-22&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-05-22)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In light of future discussions of the influence of Charles Rosen on my thought, I felt I should mention that what he introduced me to was a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Modernism_%28music%29&#34;&gt;modernist&lt;/a&gt; sensibility that, while unapologetic, was also honest and not rigid or doctrinaire. I respected that, given my ambivalence about the modernist philosophy and attitude, an ambivalence I still have two decades after first reading him (I do not consider myself a modernist). As mentioned, this modernist sensibility is at odds with aspects of Romanticism, which had been my default sensibility until I started immersing myself in the music of the Classical era.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Celebrating the birthday of John Coltrane, the Beethoven of jazz</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/09/23/celebrating-the-birthday-of-john-coltrane/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Sep 2012 00:44:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/09/23/celebrating-the-birthday-of-john-coltrane/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://userserve-ak.last.fm/serve/252/50664911.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;John Coltrane&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So today is the birthday of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Coltrane&#34;&gt;John Coltrane&lt;/a&gt; (1926-1967), a towering figure in the history of jazz like no other. Several years ago, in a moment of inspiration, I quipped to a friend that while it was clear to me that &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charlie_Parker&#34;&gt;Charlie Parker&lt;/a&gt; the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mozart&#34;&gt;Mozart&lt;/a&gt; of jazz, it was even more clear that Coltrane was the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beethoven&#34;&gt;Beethoven&lt;/a&gt; of jazz.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What did I mean by that remark? I meant it on philosophical, historical, and musical levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;mozart-to-beethoven-parker-to-coltrane&#34;&gt;Mozart to Beethoven; Parker to Coltrane&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mozart refined the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Classical_period_(music)&#34;&gt;Classical style&lt;/a&gt; inherited from Haydn and became a most admired practitioner of it; Mozart was accused (perhaps only fictionally) of writing &amp;ldquo;too many notes&amp;rdquo; in his music.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Beethoven started off in the Classical tradition and then went beyond that in his &amp;ldquo;middle&amp;rdquo; period, and then even further beyond that in his &amp;ldquo;late&amp;rdquo; period, to the point where he became completely unique and an existential challenge (to emulate or reject) to all future composers of Western art music.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Charlie Parker refined &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bebop&#34;&gt;bebop&lt;/a&gt; in jazz, which, among other things, involved packing in quite a lot of notes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Coltrane started off in the bebop tradition and then went beyond that along with Miles Davis and others, and then even further beyond that, to the point of challenging notions of what jazz even was or should be.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as I find Beethoven in his late period to be among the most sublime, yet most bizarre music of the entire history of Western art music, and was a hard act to follow, so too Coltrane. Just as many composers after Beethoven judged that he ruined Western art music permanently, so did many jazz musicians react in the same way toward Coltrane.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-coltrane-sampler&#34;&gt;A Coltrane sampler&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a lot of good music by Coltrane I could discuss for pages and pages. Look up popular examples such as &amp;ldquo;My Favorite Things&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;A Love Supreme&amp;rdquo;, for example. But for today, I celebrated not with those favorites (which I do love), but a different set:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;giant-steps-1960&#34;&gt;Giant Steps (1960)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Giant Steps&amp;rdquo; features some of the most amazing yet fluid improvisation I have ever encountered, and I love this video someone created to show transcribed notes. This is a classic that I never tire of listening to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/2kotK9FNEYU&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;vigil-1965&#34;&gt;Vigil (1965)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Vigil&amp;rdquo; is intense and even almost chaotic. It makes strange sense to me, a flow, an expression. I love it, although I don&amp;rsquo;t watch it very often; I have to be in the right mood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/5UHZaqG87N0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;ascension-1965&#34;&gt;Ascension (1965)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OK, &amp;ldquo;Ascension&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;makes no sense to me&lt;/em&gt;, and is not something I enjoy trying to listen to. You be the judge, but he lost me here. I&amp;rsquo;m just speaking the truth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/tgrQhBTDfhk&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-beethoven-sampler&#34;&gt;A Beethoven sampler&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For kicks, even though I&amp;rsquo;m not celebrating Beethoven today, here are examples of my favorite late Beethoven.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;diabelli-variations-http-en-wikipedia-org-wiki-diabelli-variations-1819&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Diabelli_Variations&#34;&gt;Diabelli Variations&lt;/a&gt; (1819)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Truly amazing set of theme and variations for the piano, taking the listener to alternate realities before returning back to earth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/wctoxElV8Os&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;große-fuge-http-en-wikipedia-org-wiki-gro-c3-9fe-fuge-1825&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gro%C3%9Fe_Fuge&#34;&gt;Große Fuge&lt;/a&gt; (1825)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nobody at this point in history was writing stuff like this. Beethoven just went wild and created this dissonant, difficult, and emotionally cathartic movement. Amazing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/XEZXjW_s0Qs&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>