<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Tango on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/tango/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Tango on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/tango/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Accidentally discovering and performing some music by Brazilian composer Ernesto Nazareth: Coração que Sente</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/12/29/accidentally-discovering-and-performing-some-music-by-brazilian-composer-ernesto-nazareth-cora%C3%A7%C3%A3o-que-sente/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Dec 2015 23:05:10 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/12/29/accidentally-discovering-and-performing-some-music-by-brazilian-composer-ernesto-nazareth-cora%C3%A7%C3%A3o-que-sente/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In November, I fell in love with some music I accidentally discovered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What happened was that I was looking for some music for &lt;em&gt;flute&lt;/em&gt; and
&lt;em&gt;guitar&lt;/em&gt; to play, with me on flute and one of my friends on guitar, and
I did a simple search in the
&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/30/free-to-the-people-since-1895/&#34;&gt;local library&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://librarycatalog.einetwork.net/&#34;&gt;online catalog&lt;/a&gt;, and at the top
sorted by date was
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.halleonard.com/product/viewproduct.action?itemid=49044167&amp;amp;&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Brazilian folk tunes for flute and guitar&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;,
which came with a CD of sample performance tracks,
so I picked it up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What followed was a series of explorations that resulted in unexpected
changes in my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;exploring-the-brazilian-music-in-the-score-book&#34;&gt;Exploring the Brazilian music in the score book&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I listened to some tracks on the CD of this book of arrangements and
found the music (Brazilian polkas, tangos, waltzes) really
enchanting. Most of the music was by a composer
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ernesto_Nazareth&#34;&gt;Ernesto Nazareth&lt;/a&gt;,
who lived 1863-1934. I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t call this music &amp;ldquo;folk tunes&amp;rdquo;: it&amp;rsquo;s
a sophisticated combination of popular and classical styles using
catchy dance rhythms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m a real sucker for waltzes, so at first I thought I would pick one
of the beautiful waltzes to choose to suggest to play with a partner
on guitar. It came down to &amp;ldquo;Confidências&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;Coração que Sente&amp;rdquo;
(English translation: &amp;ldquo;Heart that Feels&amp;rdquo;). The
latter was much easier and shorter, as I learned while sight reading
through it with the CD track, so I thought I was done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;finding-astounding-performances-of-coração-que-sente-on-youtube&#34;&gt;Finding astounding performances of &amp;ldquo;Coração que Sente&amp;rdquo; on YouTube&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking for performances of the piece on YouTube to get an idea of
how people play it, I immediately entered a strange new world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, I learned that the original music was for
&lt;em&gt;piano&lt;/em&gt;. OK. Then, while listening to and/or watching a dozen or so
videos of performances of this piece (OK, I was obsessed), I found a
huge variety of interpretations, and some of them spoke to me more
than others. Some I found light and boring. The ones that interested
me were the ones that were extremely intense and probing. You might
think this music was just fluff, but I found a dark undercurrent
behind it that spoke to me, in that its different sections (the piece
is roughly in rondo form) present clear emotional contrasts, with
longing, melancholy, and manic excitement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;arthur-moreira-lima&#34;&gt;Arthur Moreira Lima&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A very intense performance I found was by a pianist named
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arthur_Moreira_Lima&#34;&gt;Arthur Moreira Lima&lt;/a&gt;
in 1975, used after the fact as soundtrack on YouTube for a silent
film using footage from 1929. What an odd pairing!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lima goes all out in Romantic expressiveness, with extensive rubato
and dynamic and rhythmic flexibility. It was completely different from
the relatively straight, danceable version on the flute/guitar CD
demo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have to listen to his performance (ignore the film or watch it, as
you wish):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Mmjt8RrfXtA&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;joão-carlos-assis-brasil&#34;&gt;João Carlos Assis Brasil&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even more extreme than Lima was this weird guy João Carlos Assis
Brasil, who is apparently so unknown in the English-speaking world
that Wikipedia doesn&amp;rsquo;t have an entry on him, although I found this
random
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bach-cantatas.com/Bio/Assis-Brasil-Joao-Carlos.htm&#34;&gt;pieced-together bio&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His live performance here from 2013 is the single most extreme, yet
deepest, interpretation of this waltz I found (he adds his own
ornamentation). I was deeply moved by it. (Warning, bad sound
quality.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/iG_o94sU1tE&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;other-good-performances&#34;&gt;Other good performances&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://pt.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fernanda_Chaves_Canaud&#34;&gt;Fernanda Canaud&lt;/a&gt;,
with a very expressive performance (including her own extensive
embellishments), uses drastic changes in articulation and tempo for
contrast. I particularly liked how naturally she seemed to express her
personality through the piece:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/-DfOYvNCaqk&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://pt.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maria_Teresa_Madeira&#34;&gt;Maria Theresa Madeira&lt;/a&gt;
captures well the moods of the different sections of the piece; I
really like the rhythmic alertness and drive throughout:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/eeztzLsF6Cc&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some random YouTube guy named Ilton, playing a really crappy upright
piano, but with amazing rhythmic expression that I totally love (if he
played this on a good piano, I would consider his interpretation one
of my favorites, period):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/b-gYk_YUoIM&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://lucianoalves.com.br/&#34;&gt;Luciano Alves&lt;/a&gt;, 2013, in an elegant
performance:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/y8LchR8Mi5Y&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://pt.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marcelo_Bratke&#34;&gt;Marcelo Bratke&lt;/a&gt; in a
relaxed, easygoing, dream interpretation with a lilt (but after all
the intense interpretations, I find this tame, I confess):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Pn5vYhfQYHs&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-performance-that-made-me-decide-to-learn-and-play-the-piece&#34;&gt;The performance that made me decide to learn and play the piece&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I spent a lot of time listening to and watching performances of the
piece, but one performance was the one that made me decide to go learn
and play the piece! It was this one by some random guy Marcelo Chiarella:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/QaQL9VlJy8s&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why? Because I could &lt;em&gt;relate to&lt;/em&gt; his playing:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;He wasn&amp;rsquo;t some famous pro pianist, as far as I could tell.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The sound quality was good and the recording was as though I were
standing right there, made me feel like I was in his home, and
nobody else there.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I could see his hands up close.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I liked various things he did with expression (especially when he
&lt;em&gt;wasn&amp;rsquo;t&lt;/em&gt; pedaling).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I knew that I could be much more expressive and personal
(remember, the title in English translation is &amp;ldquo;Heart that feels&amp;rdquo;)
while playing this piece &lt;em&gt;solo&lt;/em&gt;, on piano, than in a flute/guitar
duet. So I decided to go for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;finding-an-official-free-score&#34;&gt;Finding an official free score&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had to find a score. Luckily, it turned out that there was some
big
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ernestonazareth150anos.com.br/&#34;&gt;150-year anniversary celebration for Ernesto Nazareth&lt;/a&gt;
in 2013, and I found an official &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ernestonazareth150anos.com.br/files/uploads/work_elements/work_43/coracao_que_sente_piano.pdf&#34;&gt;free PDF score&lt;/a&gt; on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ernestonazareth150anos.com.br/works/view/43&#34;&gt;page for the piece&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That page also had a story about the title of the piece and why it was
composed. It was in Portuguese, so I tried with the help of Google
Translate to translate it (I only studied Portuguese for several weeks
many years ago), and pieced together (I hope I didn&amp;rsquo;t get this too
wrong) that Nazareth dedicated it to a student of his, Gabriella
Crauz, who had showed great emotion as Nazareth described the last
days of a dying nephew, as though she had been there herself
experiencing what he experienced as he saw the sights in the city one
last time. (If you know Portuguese, please correct me if I got the
story wrong.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This story only added to the sense I already had that this seemingly
simple piece hid a depth of emotion that some performers already
revealed for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-performance-of-coração-que-sente&#34;&gt;My performance of &amp;ldquo;Coração que Sente&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I started working on the piece, I had to decide where and when to
perform it. It turned out that I learned that friends who mean a lot
to me decided to move. This was really tough news to me, and they have
always invited me and Abby to their December holiday party, where I
play music, so I decided that I was going to perform the piece at
their (now farewell) party and openly dedicate my performance to them,
because they are human beings of deep feeling, hence &amp;ldquo;Heart that
feels&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I performed the piece at the party the day after Christmas. In my
nervousness, I completely lost my train of thought a couple of times
and botched things up inexplicably (I had gone through the piece with
no errors so many times at home), but I made it through, and my
gesture was appreciated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I then decided to quickly record myself at home soon after (and still
botched some things up), so here I am. This is for Henry and Gina:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34;
src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/VBOS9btMUPI&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;
allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;other-music-by-ernesto-nazareth&#34;&gt;Other music by Ernesto Nazareth&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spent all this time talking about just one piece by Nazareth, but he
wrote much more, and more substantial pieces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I totally love Fernanda Canaud&amp;rsquo;s performance of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ernestonazareth150anos.com.br/works/view/133&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Batuque&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, &amp;ldquo;Coração
que Sente&amp;rdquo;, and
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ernestonazareth150anos.com.br/works/view/136&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Odeon&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;
(the performance of &amp;ldquo;Coração que Sente&amp;rdquo; is very different from the one
I posted above: more inward, refined, beautiful rather than super-dramatic):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/U6WaAgRWqaw&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is Nazareth playing his own pieces in recordings from 1912-1930:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/eZS3bDNJEUY&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a one-hour special documentary video &amp;ldquo;Nazareth Revisitado&amp;rdquo;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/TJAT3pJJR6M&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-note-on-the-english-language-oriented-web&#34;&gt;A note on the English-language-oriented Web&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found a whole world of music and musicians that barely register in
the English-language-oriented part of the Web. Most of what I found
when trying to look up Nazareth or various Brazilian pianists was in
Portuguese. So it&amp;rsquo;s been really humbling to remember that many in the
English-speaking world might not even know about all these Brazilian
composers and musicians who are not big enough stars to warrant
international fame.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am grateful for accidentally discovering an entire world of
Brazilian music and performers of it through my search in the local
library catalog for music to play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am grateful for friends who inspire me by their examples as human
beings of genuine and great feeling.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Discovering the Eolina, a beautiful musical instrument</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/02/18/discovering-the-eolina-a-beautiful-musical-instrument/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2015 20:56:18 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/02/18/discovering-the-eolina-a-beautiful-musical-instrument/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I just discovered a musical instrument that was new to me, the
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.melodicaworld.com/post_reviews/ballone-burini-eolina-45/&#34;&gt;Eolina&lt;/a&gt;,
which has a surprisingly beautiful sound, given that it is a form of
melodica, which although a perfectly fine instrument I enjoy playing,
does not have the loveliest, most refined sound.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I encountered the Eolina through my following the
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/user/GerardvanR&#34;&gt;YouTube channel&lt;/a&gt; of Gerard
van Reenen, who is just some random musician I found on YouTube at some
point in the past couple of years through some music search that I
have now completely forgotten.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His specialty is playing duets with himself, by playing a wind
instrument with one hand while accompanying himself on a
keyboard instrument. Remarkably, he often makes this work quite well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what exactly is an Eolina, and what does it sound like?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;example-a-handel-sonata-performed-on-eolina-and-organ&#34;&gt;Example: a Handel sonata performed on Eolina and organ&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out Gerard van Reenen&amp;rsquo;s self-duet on Eolina and organ of George
Frideric Handel&amp;rsquo;s sonata in B-flat major, HWV 377. I really like this
performance, showcasing his musicality on both instruments, and the
expressiveness of the Eolina, which is an upscale melodica made of
wood rather than plastic and therefore has more subtlety and
smoothness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/zNvV5WXRP1Q&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;another-example&#34;&gt;Another example&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was so curious about the Eolina that I tried to find other uses of
it on YouTube.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some musicians performing Piazzolla&amp;rsquo;s tango &amp;ldquo;Oblivion&amp;rdquo;, with
one of them playing an Eolina:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34;
src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/U0h39B6blVE&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;
allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Over two years ago,
&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/02/oblivion-obsession-time-to-start-playing-melodica/&#34;&gt;I had attempted to play &amp;ldquo;Oblivion&amp;rdquo; on my cheap melodica&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;d
love to have access to an Eolina sometime!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I always enjoy discovering a new musical instrument, and the Eolina
counts as one, even if it is just a wooden melodica.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Had you heard of or heard an Eolina before you read this blog post?
  What do you think of the sound? What do you think of melodicas in
  general? They are not so commonly used except as teaching
  instruments for children, so does that affect your perception?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Finally playing Piazzolla&#39;s &#34;Oblivion&#34; on flute</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/09/13/finally-playing-piazzollas-oblivion-on-flute/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2013 23:49:09 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/09/13/finally-playing-piazzollas-oblivion-on-flute/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Almost a year ago, I almost played Piazzolla&amp;rsquo;s tango &amp;ldquo;Oblivion&amp;rdquo; on flute with piano accompaniment by Henry &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/02/oblivion-obsession-time-to-start-playing-melodica/&#34;&gt;at a party&lt;/a&gt; but I ended up playing melodica instead of flute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having the opportunity to play with Henry again, this time I played it on flute, finally! I had found an oboe and piano arrangement which we used, sight reading it. I think the arranger filled in his own ornamentation into the melodic line. I only used that as a guide. Personally, when I play &amp;ldquo;Oblivion&amp;rdquo;, I improvise my own embellishments on the spot, depending on my mood. I play it very freely: it cries out for self-expression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2014-10-23-some-other-performances-of-oblivion&#34;&gt;(Update of 2014-10-23) Some other performances of &amp;ldquo;Oblivion&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/02/oblivion-obsession-time-to-start-playing-melodica/&#34;&gt;blog post of 2012&lt;/a&gt;, I embedded a lot of my favorite performances I found on YouTube of &amp;ldquo;Oblivion&amp;rdquo;. Here are some more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;flute-cello-piano-trio-mathilde-caldérini-zoé-karlikow-aurèle-marthan&#34;&gt;Flute/cello/piano trio (Mathilde Caldérini, Zoé Karlikow, Aurèle Marthan)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Very beautiful performance, great unity and balance and expression from all three musicians.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/DDCB1GqwL0I&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;7-flute-choir&#34;&gt;7 flute choir&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An unusual 7-flute arrangement, with all parts played by the same person, Manja Thessin! A bonus is that the video is a beautiful demonstration of tango dancing by David and Kim Benitez of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.tangomovement.com/&#34;&gt;Tango Movement&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/qvzgzpft8Xg&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;j-oublie-voice-elena-lydia-stamellou&#34;&gt;J&amp;rsquo;oublie (voice), Elena-Lydia Stamellou&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lovely, pure voice with piano accompaniment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/vfP4UF_1cUY&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;piano-improvisational-gila-goldstein&#34;&gt;Piano, improvisational, Gila Goldstein&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A gorgeous, floating performance, very free, with lovely touches in filling in inner voices and adding drama effectively through contrast, detail, and improvisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/J5meF7u3HpY&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;guitar-duo-katrin-klingeberg-and-sebastián-montes&#34;&gt;Guitar duo, Katrin Klingeberg and Sebastián Montes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What a partnership! A passionate performance with contrasting moods, immense focus, really captures the spirit of the piece.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/gONVtoQaovQ&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;guitar-solo-ryuji-kunimatsu&#34;&gt;Guitar solo, Ryuji Kunimatsu&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wow, one guy on guitar, all by himself, in his own arrangement, beautifully expressive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/2WZBOawjNiQ&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;melodica-and-piano-one-musician-simultaneously-haim-shapira&#34;&gt;Melodica and piano, one musician simultaneously! Haim Shapira&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A novelty item, definitely. There are compromises from trying to arrange to play both melodica and piano at the same time, but this is a fascinating free arrangement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/-R_jdtCACQw&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;piano-solo-arrangement-viktoriya-yermolyeva&#34;&gt;Piano solo arrangement, Viktoriya Yermolyeva&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A very passionate performance on piano by the arranger herself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/w1azi_oJGxY&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;digital-piano-solo-roland-fp4&#34;&gt;Digital piano solo (Roland FP4),&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Really quite good, based on Yermolyeva&amp;rsquo;s arrangement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/_Av7LcGRcd8&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Singing and playing tango and jazz at an unexpected music party</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/04/12/singing-and-playing-tango-and-jazz-at-an-unexpected-music-party/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Apr 2013 23:20:59 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/04/12/singing-and-playing-tango-and-jazz-at-an-unexpected-music-party/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/bob-party-2013-04-12/henry-franklin.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Henry and Franklin performing El Choclo&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I suddenly got email from Henry on a Friday afternoon while I was at work. He invited me to join him at some guy&amp;rsquo;s party in the evening to play some tangos, since the party was going to have an &amp;ldquo;Argentina&amp;rdquo; theme. My first thought was that Abby was not going to be able to go, and I myself had made plans to rest up before my very important training run Saturday morning for the Pittsburgh Marathon, but the opportunity to meet some new musicians and other people, and express my love for passionate tango music, made me decide, after consulting with Abby, to attend the party.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The good news was that I had done some tango music earlier, so there was some reuse possible. Last year, I had finally worked up the courage to do some singing, and rather enjoyed singing classic traditional tango in particular, such as &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/11/17/a-childhood-dream-come-true-i-am-now-finally-singing-for-real/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Por una Cabeza&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. And this year, I had finally given a shot at playing &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/26/music-i-just-played-for-the-first-time-recorder-sonata-tangos/&#34;&gt;tango on flute&lt;/a&gt;, playing both &amp;ldquo;El Choclo&amp;rdquo; as well as &amp;ldquo;Por una Cabeza&amp;rdquo; (as a flute-violin duet).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bad news was that someone else was already going to play &amp;ldquo;Por una Cabeza&amp;rdquo; on violin, so that left me with only one other tango I had played with Henry before, &lt;a href=&#34;http://joanveronica.hubpages.com/hub/The-Tango-La-Cumparsita-El-Choclo-and-Mi-Buenos-Aires-Querido&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;El Choclo&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, whose contrasts of staccato/legato and minor/major, with a lot of room for rubato and ornamental bravado quite appeal to me.. I wanted a tango to sing, and by sheer coincidence, I knew exactly which tango I always wanted to sing, but had only half-sung it to myself in private: this was &lt;a href=&#34;http://joanveronica.hubpages.com/hub/Outstanding-Tango-selection-Mi-Buenos-Aires-Querido-Uno-and-Caminito&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Uno&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, by &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mariano_Mores&#34;&gt;Mariano Mores&lt;/a&gt; from 1943.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;uno&#34;&gt;Uno&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By coincidence, only a couple of days ago, the Spanish actress/singer &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sara_Montiel&#34;&gt;Sara Montiel&lt;/a&gt; died, and in her memory I rewatched and &lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/100967806642012078047/posts/6xV5iasmXxj&#34;&gt;reposted&lt;/a&gt; a video clip of her singing &amp;ldquo;Uno&amp;rdquo; in a film:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/5Z7rHztinaM&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe that I first came across &amp;ldquo;Uno&amp;rdquo; by accident when some years ago I found Montiel&amp;rsquo;s performance while searching for other tangos. In any case, it was love at first hearing, and made it to my list of tangos I wanted to sing some day. I&amp;rsquo;d put off this project for some good reasons, but today I decided I wanted to give it a shot!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I hastily found a score, printed out the lyrics, and after eating dinner at home after work, and just an hour or so before the party, I worked on being able to sing the Spanish lyrics without completely stumbling over myself. Most songs in Spanish I can sing with no problem, but &amp;ldquo;Uno&amp;rdquo; features a huge number of words in the lyrics, which means there are considerable challenges:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;pronouncing Spanish at basically spoken speed (I&amp;rsquo;m not that fluent yet)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;breaking up the words into logical and emotional groupings at speed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;singing Spanish in the face of many, many instances of word pairs with vowels in between&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I knew I wasn&amp;rsquo;t going to get everything perfect in time in less than half an hour of determining where to break things up and where to link things, and actually doing this fluently, so I was nervous, but I&amp;rsquo;ve learned that when it comes to music, perfect technique is not the most important thing; I felt I could reasonably well convey the emotional content of this song despite imperfections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-party&#34;&gt;The party&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a great party, with food, music, and conversation, and I was excited to meet a whole bunch of new people of all ages. I hope the next time Bob and his wife host another music party, Abby will be able to attend too!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before the musical part of the party began, Henry and I spent about five minutes in the basement, with him on the upright piano down there, and me singing, trying to read through &amp;ldquo;Uno&amp;rdquo; together so that it would be at least halfway presentable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We performed &amp;ldquo;El Choclo&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Uno&amp;rdquo; near the end of the program (since we were last minute additions that didn&amp;rsquo;t make it onto the printed program). I was physically shaking while doing both of them, because I was in front of a completely new crowd of people and just wasn&amp;rsquo;t as prepared as I would have preferred. But it was a friendly crowd, and the audience seemed to enjoy our music-making. I was happy to have contributed something to the &amp;ldquo;Argentina&amp;rdquo; theme with some authentic Golden Age tango music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What was really enjoyable about this music party was that so many of the guests participated in performing something: young and old, amateur and professional. This welcoming atmosphere was wonderful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;jazz-improvisation&#34;&gt;Jazz, improvisation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the official music program ended, some people continued to jam. This guy I met, Keith, was particularly interesting to me, as he is a wind player, and played both soprano saxophone and flute on the program, and then after the program, was doing jazz standards on alto saxophone. I was so inspired by this that I decided I wanted to do some jazz also. I bring a little binder of music nowadays when I go to musical parties, just in case, and happened to have on me &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jazzstandards.com/compositions-0/sweetlorraine.htm&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Sweet Lorraine&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, which I had never played before other than to myself with a CD track. So I got Henry to the piano so that we could just go for it and improvise to the chord changes. We totally got into it and I really enjoyed the jamming. I really enjoy nothing more than improvisation, and appreciate that Henry is game for doing this with me, as when we were doing it with Latin jazz (bolero and cha cha) &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/17/finally-doing-some-latin-music-jamming-on-flute/&#34;&gt;last month&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had tremendous fun attending Bob&amp;rsquo;s party, seeing so many people sing or play an instrument, all of us sharing our love of music together. I was very inspired by everyone who contributed something of their unique soul there, and I feel like this is what life is all about.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Music I just played for the first time: recorder sonata, tangos</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/01/26/music-i-just-played-for-the-first-time-recorder-sonata-tangos/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Jan 2013 23:03:10 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/01/26/music-i-just-played-for-the-first-time-recorder-sonata-tangos/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Abby and I went to Henry&amp;rsquo;s birthday party, marking an important anniversary: we attended his birthday party for the first time a year ago, and that began &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/01/27/a-new-friends-very-musical-birthday-party-changed-my-life/&#34;&gt;one of the most important developments in my entire life, my decision to make music playing an integral part of my life&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of music happened, as usual, and this time, unlike a year ago, I played. What a year it&amp;rsquo;s been!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;handel-s-recorder-sonata-in-g-minor&#34;&gt;Handel&amp;rsquo;s recorder sonata in G minor&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided to finally give a shot at playing, for the first time outside of home, &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Recorder_sonata_in_G_minor_%28HWV_360%29&#34;&gt;Handel&amp;rsquo;s recorder sonata in G minor, op. 1 no. 2&lt;/a&gt;, me being on alto recorder and Henry on piano.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This piece is extremely special to me, because I discovered it by accident as one of the first &amp;ldquo;real&amp;rdquo; recorder pieces that I started working on when I was just a beginner at recorder. A method book I was using at the time, one and half years ago, in May 2011, by Mario Duschenes, had a section with the title &amp;ldquo;How to practise a difficult piece&amp;rdquo;, and the example and suggestions on practice was the Andante from this recorder sonata by Handel. I hunted down the complete score of the recorder sonata and started to learn the whole thing. I did this intermittently over the course of a year or so while doing other things, but always had the intention of at some point polishing it up for actual performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main holdup eventually was that I wanted to be able to really express myself well, and incorporate my own ornamentations. To this end, I made some study of Baroque ornamentation and checked out a book I found in the library, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.oup.com/us/catalog/general/subject/Music/PerformanceStudiesAppliedMusic/WindsBrass/?view=usa&amp;amp;ci=9780198790013&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Playing Recorder Sonatas&amp;rdquo;, by Anthony Rowland-Jones&lt;/a&gt;. I have found this book quite useful as a guide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I had fun reading through this with Henry. Eventually I want to play it for real, as performance, in a setting with harpsichord continuo, rather than with piano.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-02-23&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-02-23)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ended up performing the recorder sonata with bass recorder accompaniment at the Pittsburgh Recorder Society&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/02/23/celebrating-two-years-of-playing-recorder/&#34;&gt;Midwinter Musical Feast&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;bach-s-flute-sonata-in-e-minor-bwv-1034&#34;&gt;Bach&amp;rsquo;s flute sonata in E minor, BWV 1034&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I played music by Johann Sebastian Bach on flute for the first time outside the home. I&amp;rsquo;ve held back because I feel like I&amp;rsquo;m still not doing the music justice, but decided I can&amp;rsquo;t hide forever my love of Bach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On modern flute with Henry on piano, I played the first movement of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sonata_in_E_minor_for_flute_or_recorder_and_basso_continuo&#34;&gt;Bach&amp;rsquo;s flute sonata in E minor&lt;/a&gt;. I would have considered playing it on Baroque flute, but the piano as well as the the party environment &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/21/my-first-time-singing-bossa-nova-also-a-temporary-farewell-to-baroque-flute/&#34;&gt;is not friendly for Baroque flute&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-03-21&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-03-21)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Bach&amp;rsquo;s birthday in 2013, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/21/my-second-year-of-celebrating-johann-sebastian-bachs-birthday/&#34;&gt;I reflected on&lt;/a&gt; how the very same recorder method book by Duschenes I mentioned above was the impetus for my getting into Bach flute sonatas!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;tangos&#34;&gt;Tangos&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I played tango on flute for the first time ever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/11/17/a-childhood-dream-come-true-i-am-now-finally-singing-for-real/&#34;&gt;sing tango for the first time recently&lt;/a&gt;, and also played &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/22/playing-tango-on-melodica-and-singing-christmas-carols/&#34;&gt;tango on melodica for the first time&lt;/a&gt;, but had not yet dared to play on flute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, I did, and not only that, one of them ended up becoming a flute-violin duet, in which Barbara (whom I met exactly a year ago at the last birthday party) played violin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story is that several months ago, in October, I got hold of a book of tangos for violin duet. I judged that with some modifications I could play the first part on flute, if only I could simultaneously find someone on violin (and someone on piano). The opportunity did not spontaneously arise until today!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, I played &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/El_Choclo&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;El Choclo&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; with just Henry on piano.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then Barbara joined in on violin and we played &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Por_una_Cabeza&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Por una Cabeza&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; with Henry. This was one of the most satisfying experiences of my life. It&amp;rsquo;s one thing playing duets with Henry, but it&amp;rsquo;s another having three to really fill in the harmonies and textures and two melodic voices playing off each other. Wow. I need to do this more often. And I have to confess, I never tire of this particular classic tango, because it&amp;rsquo;s so dramatic and expressive, and has that suddenly shift from major to the lyrical chorus in minor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;more-bach-double-violin-concerto&#34;&gt;More Bach: double violin concerto&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Barbara was so excited that she goaded me into trying to sight read &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Concerto_for_Two_Violins_%28Bach%29&#34;&gt;Bach&amp;rsquo;s double violin concerto&lt;/a&gt; on the spot together with Henry. I knew I was probably going to cause a minor disaster, but heck, it&amp;rsquo;s a party, we&amp;rsquo;re just having fun. And indeed, I got confused or lost many times, because first of all, I&amp;rsquo;m not so great on flute right now at all, and second, this music was for violin and some stuff was not very suitable for flute and also needed me to go up an octave all of a sudden because the violin has a bigger range. So, it was a struggle for me, but I enjoyed some nice moments in the less frantic slow movement, where the two melodic voices really combine beautifully.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, it was all in fun, Bach forgive me!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As at all of Henry&amp;rsquo;s parties, I strive to go to them prepared to do something better and new and interesting musically, for our enjoyment as well as that of the other guests. I had a great time again. I am so grateful for the past year of getting to know Henry and his sharing the gift of music with me!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Playing tango on melodica and singing Christmas carols</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/12/22/playing-tango-on-melodica-and-singing-christmas-carols/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Dec 2012 23:57:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/12/22/playing-tango-on-melodica-and-singing-christmas-carols/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I went to a Christmas party at Gina&amp;rsquo;s, and of course there had to be a lot of music-making. Probably ten of us at some point or another were playing music. There was singing, flutes, accordions, piano, mandolin, etc., on all kinds of music, for hours and hours, even in separate rooms simultaneously. I did a lot of sitting and listening to others and also some participation of my own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, personally, my favorite moments that I was involved in were the following.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;piazzolla-s-oblivion-on-melodica-and-piano&#34;&gt;Piazzolla&amp;rsquo;s Oblivion on melodica and piano&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Henry and I did Piazzolla&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Oblivion&amp;rdquo;, with me on melodica, and him accompanying on piano. I&amp;rsquo;ve &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/02/oblivion-obsession-time-to-start-playing-melodica/&#34;&gt;recently mentioned wanting to do this&lt;/a&gt;, so I was happy to have this opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My cheap secondhand student melodica has poor intonation on the lower notes, unfortunately, as &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/14/pittsburgh-contras-and-squares-holiday-ball-2012/&#34;&gt;I observed recently when playing it in the Pittsburgh Contras and Squares Holiday Ball&lt;/a&gt;. So the results were not ideal. I&amp;rsquo;ve decided that if I want to continue playing the melodica seriously, I need a better instrument.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve decided that next time I play &amp;ldquo;Oblivion&amp;rdquo; again, it will be on flute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;niccolò-dôthel-s-first-flute-and-cello-sonata-first-movement-http-imslp-org-wiki-6-sonatas-for-flute-and-cello-op-2-28d-c3-b4thel-niccol-c3-b2-29&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://imslp.org/wiki/6_Sonatas_for_Flute_and_Cello,_Op.2_%28D%C3%B4thel,_Niccol%C3%B2%29&#34;&gt;Niccolò Dôthel&amp;rsquo;s first flute and cello sonata, first movement&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For variety, I threw in some Baroque music to play with Henry on piano for continuo. We did the first movement of Dôthel&amp;rsquo;s first flute and cello sonata. I had first heard this by accident, while following a discussion &lt;a href=&#34;http://launch.groups.yahoo.com/group/earlyflute/message/12041&#34;&gt;three months ago&lt;/a&gt; on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://launch.groups.yahoo.com/group/earlyflute/&#34;&gt;Yahoo &amp;ldquo;early flute&amp;rdquo; group&lt;/a&gt;, in which one of the posters, Javier Gelati, put up a link to a YouTube video of himself playing it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/HmMoNwm-Hx8&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found this piece so delightful and suitable for the Baroque flute that I decided I wanted to play it, and worked on it, and so I finally got the chance to play it with someone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-02-23&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-02-23)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ended up playing this piece again, but in a quiet recital environment, with viola da gamba continuo, at the Pittsburgh Recorder Society&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/02/23/celebrating-two-years-of-playing-recorder/&#34;&gt;Midwinter Musical Feast&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;have-yourself-a-merry-little-christmas&#34;&gt;Have Yourself a Merry Little Christmas&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of my favorite Christmas songs is &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Have_Yourself_a_Merry_Little_Christmas&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Have Yourself a Merry Little Christmas&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. It can still bring tears to my eyes. It brings back a lot of winter memories of being alone for one reason or another, while out and about and hearing it playing in stores and subway stations. Those days are over, but still, the song is really quite moving. Especially, I prefer the original lyrics, &amp;ldquo;Until then we&amp;rsquo;ll have to muddle through somehow&amp;rdquo;, to the alternate lyrics Frank Sinatra popularized, &amp;ldquo;Hang a shining star upon the highest bough&amp;rdquo;. The original melancholy lyrics underline the message of a hope for the future that is not yet reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So for the first time, I sang this song for others to hear, with Henry on piano.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, the classic performance (with the original lyrics) is the beautiful one by Judy Garland:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/5g4lY8Y3eoo&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;christmas-carols-with-other-people&#34;&gt;Christmas carols with other people&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I had the opportunity to sing a lot of Christmas carols with a number of other guests, some of whom were music students with astounding voices. Since they were female, I tried to blend in along with the pianist to fill in some harmony. I have basically no real experience in doing this, but it was fun, and I really enjoyed singing with other people.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Oblivion obsession: time to start playing melodica!</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/12/02/oblivion-obsession-time-to-start-playing-melodica/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Dec 2012 21:32:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/12/02/oblivion-obsession-time-to-start-playing-melodica/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have been obsessed for some time with Piazzolla&amp;rsquo;s beautiful tango piece &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.astor-piazzolla.org/astor-piazzolla-oblivion/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Oblivion&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. I was planning to perform it some time on flute, but today, by accident, I decided that I want to play it on my &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.grothmusic.com/p-4654-hohner-s32-student-32-key-melodica.aspx&#34;&gt;melodica&lt;/a&gt; instead!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/hohner-student-32-melodica.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Hohner Student 32 Melodica&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-melodica-came-into-the-picture&#34;&gt;How melodica came into the picture&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This afternoon was the first rehearsal of the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/11/24/preparing-to-play-irish-flute-in-the-holiday-ball/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Holiday Ball Orchestra&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. (Today was also round 4 of the Pittsburgh Chess League team matches, but as I did once before for round 1, I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/16/excited-by-the-new-season-of-the-pittsburgh-recorder-society/&#34;&gt;prioritized music over chess&lt;/a&gt; and told the team I could not play.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the rehearsal, I played both flute and Irish flute, depending on the key. Afterward, while socializing, I happened to ask about the ukuleles that some people had. I mentioned that I still hadn&amp;rsquo;t gotten around to learning ukulele, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/11/learning-another-instrument-the-tin-whistle/&#34;&gt;despite having intended to&lt;/a&gt; and bought a soprano a long while back. I just found it very hard to get started with my first string instrument, and other things came up. I joked about the other instruments I have that I don&amp;rsquo;t play, including my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/01/run-shadyside-5k-outrunning-mickey-mouse-and-lending-a-trumpet/&#34;&gt;melodica&lt;/a&gt;. Lynette said in all seriousness that I was welcome to play it at the Holiday Ball.
So after I got home, I pulled out the melodica.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-is-the-melodica-good-for&#34;&gt;What is the melodica good for?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that I don&amp;rsquo;t think the melodica works well at all for the Holiday Ball music, actually. The instrument is not best at fast runs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;But&lt;/strong&gt;, since I had the instrument out: I decided to try playing it &lt;em&gt;in place of flute&lt;/em&gt; for some music I&amp;rsquo;ve been working on, such as tango and bossa nova. And I discovered that &lt;em&gt;melodica works great&lt;/em&gt; for these kinds of music! Then one thing led to another, and I was searching for covers of various songs on melodica on YouTube, and found quite a lot of cool performances by people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So now I&amp;rsquo;m completely serious about preparing to use my melodica in actual musical performances. Frankly, a lot of music I&amp;rsquo;ve been playing on flute sounds better with a darker, reeded instrument such as the melodica. For example, I&amp;rsquo;ve been playing jazzy bossa nova that I think really works best with a saxophone, but I don&amp;rsquo;t (yet!) play saxophone. The melodica works well as a substitute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In tango, of course, a bandoneón is the traditional instrument, and accordions are commonly used instead. Here, again, the melodica is great, for the melody line anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, other music that involves accordions or harmonicas work great with melodica as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;piazzolla-s-oblivion&#34;&gt;Piazzolla&amp;rsquo;s Oblivion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I am confessedly obsessed with &amp;ldquo;Oblivion&amp;rdquo;, here are some performances I found moving or otherwise useful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;flute-guitar&#34;&gt;Flute/guitar&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s Cavatina Duo on flute and guitar:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/sZD7aGqmO6w&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;melodica-with-chamber-group&#34;&gt;Melodica with chamber group&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is someone playing melodica:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/fG0TcCFUrBQ&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;melodica-and-piano-discovered-2013-08-22&#34;&gt;Melodica and piano (discovered 2013-08-22)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Japanese duo:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/AAP4GB8T8DI&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;accordion&#34;&gt;Accordion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s my friend Henry playing his solo arrangement for accordion:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/FrOHDEMOhkc&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;bandoneón-and-piano&#34;&gt;Bandoneón and piano&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Julian Rowlands and Ivo de Greef:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/sj-JUBIGKnE&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;violin-and-orchestra&#34;&gt;Violin and orchestra&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vesko Eschkenazy:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/kP6Vgm4k4xc&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;voice&#34;&gt;Voice&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wow. Wow. Milva singing French lyrics, Piazzolla himself on bandoneón!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/lzC1kKZGxBg&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;recorder-quartet-discovered-2013-08-22&#34;&gt;Recorder quartet (discovered 2013-08-22)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Japanese recorder quartet, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.geocities.jp/sekishirecorderquartet/english.htm&#34;&gt;Sekishi Recorder Quartet&lt;/a&gt;. Very nice!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/3PmaOyZNWo8&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;tango-dancers&#34;&gt;Tango dancers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, here are Daniela Pucci and Luis Bianchi dancing to the piece:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/RdU3eORpNhY&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, here is Daniela Pucci explaining why she gave up her MIT academic faculty career for tango:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/7BbAt1gnkBE&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are a tango fan, make sure to read Daniel Pucci&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.thedelicatestrength.com/?p=1522&#34;&gt;great article on tango dance connection&lt;/a&gt;. It is consonant with my own dance philosophy as well as music philosophy!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By accident, I have rediscovered the melodica, and now intend to work on it as a serious melodic instrument!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2014-10-23&#34;&gt;(Update of 2014-10-23)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/09/13/finally-playing-piazzollas-oblivion-on-flute/&#34;&gt;I put up more videos&lt;/a&gt; I found of &amp;ldquo;Oblivion&amp;rdquo; while thinking back to 2013 when I did play it on flute after all.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A childhood dream come true: I am now finally singing for real!</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/11/17/a-childhood-dream-come-true-i-am-now-finally-singing-for-real/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 Nov 2012 23:25:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/11/17/a-childhood-dream-come-true-i-am-now-finally-singing-for-real/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Abby and I went to a pre-Thanksgiving party hosted by Henry and yet again, &lt;strong&gt;I changed my life&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the last party at Henry&amp;rsquo;s, two months ago, I had begun singing there for the first time, and afterwards &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/21/my-first-time-singing-bossa-nova-also-a-temporary-farewell-to-baroque-flute/&#34;&gt;vowed that I would take up singing for real&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d followed up very slowly, taking a month before &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/10/27/singing-an-irish-ballad-as-an-asian-pirate-at-a-halloween-belly-dance-hafla/&#34;&gt;actually singing in public&lt;/a&gt;, and then the day after that, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/10/28/singing-and-playing-bossa-nova-favorite-chega-de-saudade-at-dunkin-donuts-for-j-jam/&#34;&gt;continuing to sing in public at J-Jam&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was the last event, J-Jam, that got me to decide to really prepare some songs to sing for the next J-Jam. What happened was that I had started off by trying to find some suitable flute/guitar music to work on with Cantor Ben Rosner for J-Jam, but I noticed that I was picking some material that was actually originally sung and then transcribed for flute. After being &lt;em&gt;unsatisfied&lt;/em&gt; with playing these songs on flute, because I couldn&amp;rsquo;t get quite the expression I wanted, I bit the bullet: I decided that &lt;em&gt;the voice is the original and best instrument we have&lt;/em&gt;, and that I should use the &lt;em&gt;best&lt;/em&gt; instrument to achieve what I wanted to do, which was to maximize expressiveness in lyrical music. So I started looking for transpositions of songs to a suitable range for me in order for me to sing them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then when Henry&amp;rsquo;s party invitation came up, I jumped at the opportunity to try out some of the music I was preparing for J-Jam, to perform with Henry on piano.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What did I do?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;one-year-anniversary-of-my-deciding-to-sing&#34;&gt;One year anniversary of my deciding to sing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By coincidence, it&amp;rsquo;s almost exactly one year since &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/18/i-want-to-sing/&#34;&gt;I decided here on this blog that I was going to get into singing&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;music-plan&#34;&gt;Music plan&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I picked out four pieces to give Henry advance warning on, so that I could give him the piano parts for him to take a look at before the party. During the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/11/13/round-1-of-pittsburgh-chess-club-tournament-revenge-of-the-knight/&#34;&gt;first round of the chess tournament we were both playing in&lt;/a&gt;, I gave him a big collection of music, not only for the upcoming party but for possible future projects also.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The selections I chose to work on for the party:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gabriel Fauré: Sicilienne (flute and piano)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gabriel Fauré: Après un rêve (voice and piano)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Robert Schumann: Widmung (voice and piano)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Carlos Gardel: Por una cabeza (voice and piano)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;at-the-party&#34;&gt;At the party&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;food&#34;&gt;Food&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Barbara rather than Anna took charge of providing the main food this time, while the rest of us pitched in with our contributions. There were over twenty people at this party, I believe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I made my own very small contributions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;cabbage-with-leeks-and-potatoes&#34;&gt;Cabbage with leeks and potatoes&lt;/h4&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pre-thanksgiving-2012/cabbage.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Cabbage with leeks and potatoes&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Cabbage with leeks and potatoes, with olive oil and butter and seasoning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Make sure to &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Caramelization&#34;&gt;caramelize&lt;/a&gt; in the skillet.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;turnips-and-carrots&#34;&gt;Turnips and carrots&lt;/h4&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pre-thanksgiving-2012/turnips.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Roasted turnips and carrots&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Roasted turnips and carrots, with olive oil and seasoning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;music&#34;&gt;Music&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I unexpected ended up providing a lot of the music this evening. There were fewer people involved in playing music than in some of the other parties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This time, I brought just my (modern) flute and my voice. I left my recorders and Baroque flute and Irish flute and tin whistle at home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started off with singing the tango &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Por_una_Cabeza&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Por una cabeza&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; (made famous in &amp;ldquo;Scent of a Woman&amp;rdquo;), very hesitatingly:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pre-thanksgiving-2012/franklin-por-una-cabeza.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin&amp;#39;s first try at Por una Cabeza&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I was so nervous that my legs were shaking and my arms trembling as I began; it was exactly as what happened &lt;em&gt;eight months ago&lt;/em&gt; at the first of Henry&amp;rsquo;s parties at which &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/17/st-patricks-day-party-playing-tin-whistle-and-flute/&#34;&gt;I played an instrument&lt;/a&gt;. The difference was that although that one time, I knew I was playing the flute &lt;em&gt;badly&lt;/em&gt;, this time, I was confident that I was singing OK: not great yet, but not badly. I&amp;rsquo;d worked two weeks on singing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;memory&#34;&gt;Memory&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing I have observed again and again during my past year of music is that it really is ideal to have stuff memorized. I have not put enough work into that, since with my limited time, I tend to use it on working on technique and on learning material, rather than on memorizing what I can play off a score or sing off a printed set of lyrics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I did make a special effort to memorize at least two of the songs I had prepared: the Fauré and the Schumann. I did manage to more or less memorize them in time, since the French and German vocabulary of these love songs were fairly straightforward (I studied French and German in high school and college). The tango in Spanish, &amp;ldquo;Por una cabeza&amp;rdquo;, I did not have hope of memorizing any time soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I brought along printouts to help me so I could glance at them at least now and then. Obviously, I aim to become independent of these aids so that I can sing unencumbered by looking at a printout, and connect directly with the audience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;what-it-s-like-to-sing&#34;&gt;What it&amp;rsquo;s like to sing&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The feeling of singing is like nothing else. It&amp;rsquo;s so &lt;em&gt;physical&lt;/em&gt; in a primal way, compared to playing flute or recorder. I completely lose myself in emotion, when I can squeeze as much expression out of the voice as I can. It&amp;rsquo;s an amazing sensation. It&amp;rsquo;s a communication that is very direct.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe if I played a violin I would feel something like that, because of the expressive qualities of the violin. On flute, I cannot do everything that I can do with my voice. I try, but it is not the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;flute&#34;&gt;Flute&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My focus on singing overshadowed the fact that I was actually making something of a debut on modern flute here. I had played modern flute in anyone&amp;rsquo;s presence outside the home only a handful of times before:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/17/st-patricks-day-party-playing-tin-whistle-and-flute/&#34;&gt;for St. Patrick&amp;rsquo;s Day&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/04/27/baroque-jam-session-at-cmu/&#34;&gt;Baroque jam session in March&lt;/a&gt;, playing a Baroque piece&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/28/my-first-appearance-on-a-music-recital-program/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Recorder society potluck/recital&lt;/a&gt;, playing a pre-Classical piece&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/10/28/singing-and-playing-bossa-nova-favorite-chega-de-saudade-at-dunkin-donuts-for-j-jam/&#34;&gt;J-Jam&lt;/a&gt;, where I did a bit of bossa nova improvisation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s not only because I was focusing on other instruments all year. It&amp;rsquo;s also because I&amp;rsquo;ve found it very challenging to make the kinds of sounds on the modern flute I want to hear. On each of those four occasions in which I played the modern flute, I felt that I needed to improve a lot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have improved a lot, actually, but I&amp;rsquo;m still far from satisfied; I&amp;rsquo;ve only now gotten to the point at which I feel I am not an embarrassment. Developing a truly beautiful, flexible tone seems a years-long task, and I keep working at it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I have finally jumped into the late 19th century, out of the 18th, to play Romantic music on the instrument that is suited for it, the modern flute:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pre-thanksgiving-2012/franklin-flute.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin playing Fauré, Sicilienne&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h4 id=&#34;unexpected-singing&#34;&gt;Unexpected singing&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Henry so enjoyed going through songs with me that he had me repeat &amp;ldquo;Por una cabeza&amp;rdquo; later in the party. I did, and I felt &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; more relaxed than when I did it the first time. I thought I did much better this time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I thought, hey, I had given him a whole folder of stuff, so we should just sight read some of it. I ended up singing Schubert&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Nacht und Traüme&amp;rdquo; as well as &amp;ldquo;An die Musik&amp;rdquo;, which I had intended for a later occasion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, finally, before Abby and I had to leave, I decided that I wanted to sing a song especially for Abby, and pulled out Alvaro Carrillo&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Sabor a mî&amp;rdquo;, which I know by heart (I will explain in a later blog post the significance of this song for me), and sang it to her, with Henry providing great accompaniment on first sight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;dancing&#34;&gt;Dancing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dancing with Abby at these parties is always a special pleasure for us&amp;hellip; Vasili on accordion.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pre-thanksgiving-2012/abby-franklin-dance.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby and Franklin dancing waltz&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-did-so-few-other-people-sing&#34;&gt;Why did so few other people sing?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the guests had been introduced to me as singers, yet &lt;em&gt;none&lt;/em&gt; of them sang at the party! This was puzzling to me. There could be many reasons, but I won&amp;rsquo;t speculate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for those who expressed enjoyment of singing to themselves, but identified themselves as non-singers (as I did), that&amp;rsquo;s very easy to understand, because I was there myself. I&amp;rsquo;ve simply chosen to overcome my fear and anxiety, work on improvement, and then put myself out there, warts and all. I do this because I saw the younger people under 20 do this, and I decided that if being &amp;ldquo;old&amp;rdquo; means being afraid, I&amp;rsquo;d rather do what the younger people do, and just get out there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-next&#34;&gt;What next?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m going to do serious study of singing. Henry mentioned a book &amp;ldquo;Singing for Dummies&amp;rdquo; that I&amp;rsquo;ll check out. I would like to work through it systematically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way: I noticed that my flute and recorder playing have improved in several dimensions since I started working on singing. My breath awareness is better, my control over my breath stream, and even more than that, I&amp;rsquo;m really trying to treat my instruments as parts of my body, to get that integrated feel I have when just singing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m singing now. &lt;strong&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s no going back.&lt;/strong&gt; It&amp;rsquo;s like when I originally started dancing, after decades as a non-dancer, or started running, or started cooking, or started public speaking. There&amp;rsquo;s just no going back, after the first big step.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Classical Revolution: Pittsburgh&#39;s AquiTango delivers passionate traditional tango</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/11/14/classical-revolution-pittsburghs-aquitango-delivers-passionate-traditional-tango/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Nov 2012 20:48:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/11/14/classical-revolution-pittsburghs-aquitango-delivers-passionate-traditional-tango/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;So I got word of a relatively new movement called &lt;a href=&#34;http://classicalrevolution.org/&#34;&gt;Classical Revolution&lt;/a&gt; that is spreading &lt;a href=&#34;http://classicalrevolution.org/chapters/&#34;&gt;around the world&lt;/a&gt;, and has reached Pittsburgh, which has its &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.classicalrevolutionpgh.org/&#34;&gt;own chapter&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/classicalrevolutionpgh&#34;&gt;Facebook page&lt;/a&gt;). The point of Classical Revolution is to &lt;a href=&#34;http://classicalrevolution.org/about/&#34;&gt;perform chamber music in non-traditional settings&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;tango&#34;&gt;Tango&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I saw that the local Pittsburgh tango group &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.aquitango.com/&#34;&gt;AquiTango&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/AquiTango&#34;&gt;Facebook page&lt;/a&gt;) was &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/events/380553315352985/&#34;&gt;going to perform&lt;/a&gt; at &lt;a href=&#34;http://barmarcopgh.com/&#34;&gt;Bar Marco&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AquiTango was to perform traditional &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Argentine_tango&#34;&gt;Argentine tango&lt;/a&gt; music. I had actually encountered, a decade ago, an earlier incarnation (with some member changes since then) of the group, when I was taking Argentine tango classes and dancing; it was formerly Tangueros de Ley. I remember when Julieta Ugartemendia was in the group, playing clarinet and singing, and she also danced! In any case, the group has been revived after she left, as a quartet.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://lh5.ggpht.com/hopUhptskdqtJ-rQfGKZ2awY2KUwuQS9waErFnvkkmdrot9eRTguZRgn--7a8JHRNfGuU2R73hzDssjWGfO5=s615&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;AquiTango&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I decided to attend, not only to check out what the experience of &amp;ldquo;Classical Revolution&amp;rdquo; in such a venue is like, but also for my own special reason: to be inspired by some good tango performances, because I am actually planning to soon play tango on flute and also sing it for the first time!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So here&amp;rsquo;s my review of the concert.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2012-11-17&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-11-17)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/11/17/a-childhood-dream-come-true-i-am-now-finally-singing-for-real/&#34;&gt;Three days later, I did in fact perform tango, at a party!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-venue&#34;&gt;The venue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second floor of Bar Marco is a nice place for chamber music. Not too big, not too small. The musicians play near the windows, while the audience is seated in folding chairs. Wine was available for those who wanted it (I chose not to have any).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-concert&#34;&gt;The concert&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;dancers&#34;&gt;Dancers?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although I am no longer part of the local tango dance community, I could tell as people arrived that some of them knew each other and were dancers. During the concert, it was easy to tell who were the dancers, because they couldn&amp;rsquo;t keep still and fidgeted in their seats or tapped out rhythms. (OK, I kind of did that too.) I was a little surprised that nobody just got up and danced. Maybe there weren&amp;rsquo;t quite enough dancers, or maybe they thought it was a more formal kind of event at which dancing would not have been appropriate. It was definitely a &amp;ldquo;chamber music recital&amp;rdquo; kind of atmosphere rather than a dance atmosphere. That was fine, but I did miss seeing a little bit of dancing. (Or maybe people were dancing at the back whom I didn&amp;rsquo;t see; I was sitting near the front to better see and hear the musicians.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;musicians-and-music&#34;&gt;Musicians and music&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The quartet (keyboard, violin, bass, accordion/voice) seemed to be having fun playing in this environment. The vibe was fairly informal, with a lot of smiling and banter. They played a lot of classic tangos, waltzes, and milongas, including some I had practiced myself at home, such as &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Por_una_Cabeza&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Por una Cabeza&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed how Ernesto Contenti, who is originally from Argentina actually, talked about his history and the songs he sang (he both sang and played the accordion). He said that when he was growing up, tango was just old-people stuff, and it barely even registered in his youthful existence. It was only after he had left the country and then encountered the passion for tango elsewhere that he really discovered the music of his homeland! When he sang the classic &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mi_Buenos_Aires_querido_(song)&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Mi Buenos Aires querido&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, it seemed to ring out in a deeply personal way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The violinist, Maureen Conlon-Gutierrez, is originally from Mexico, and her classical training showed in the brilliance and polish of her play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bassist, Jose Puentes, providing the foundation for the quartet, is from Venezuela.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pianist, Tom Roberts, joked about his non-Latin heritage, being a local. They have a nickname for him, &amp;ldquo;El Cacho&amp;rdquo;. His keyboard playing was particularly lively and adventurous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AquiTango at some point played some non-traditional pieces also. I enjoyed the added variety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;after-the-concert&#34;&gt;After the concert&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had to leave immediately after the concert, because of many things to do this busy week. It would have been nice to stay and chat with the musicians and other audience members; I saw a lot of people going up to the musicians to chat. One thing great about this informal &amp;ldquo;Classical Revolution&amp;rdquo; format is that there is not as much &amp;ldquo;distance&amp;rdquo; between the performers and audience as in a traditional venue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I left feeling excited about my plans to perform tango music soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;some-videos-online&#34;&gt;Some videos online&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a recent sample of AquiTango in action, performing the tango classic &amp;ldquo;La Cumparsita&amp;rdquo;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/zHaasDMVYYo&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is an older sample of AquiTango, playing on the street in Squirrel Hill:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/6u6RO8c5b8I&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re in the Pittsburgh area and looking for some live traditional tango music performed with precision and fire, check out the AquiTango quartet!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-02-28&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-02-28)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went to Bar Marco again for &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/02/28/another-exciting-concert-at-bar-marco-chris-norman-and-the-chatham-baroque-playing-a-tasty-assortment-of-dynamic-music/&#34;&gt;another enjoyable music performance&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Playing French music for the first time, and dancing blues for the first time</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/05/14/playing-french-music-for-first-time-and-dancing-blues-for-first-time/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 May 2012 23:44:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/05/14/playing-french-music-for-first-time-and-dancing-blues-for-first-time/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Although I have stopped writing about it, Abby and I have continued to do &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/02/20/enjoying-more-french-dancing-in-pittsburgh/&#34;&gt;French dancing here in Pittsburgh&lt;/a&gt;. Tonight, for the first time, we finally attended the regular Monday night French and blues dance hosted by Lisa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was quite an intense evening for me, both playing French music &lt;em&gt;for the first time&lt;/em&gt; and dancing blues &lt;em&gt;for the first time&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;french-and-blues-social-dance&#34;&gt;French and blues social dance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;French &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; blues night?! What&amp;rsquo;s the connection?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, the story is simply that Lisa and Gregory (and some other dancers) enjoy both French music/dance and blues music/dance, so both types of music and dance are combined into one evening of dancing. Of course, there are people who show up who are only interested in the French or only interested in the blues. The iTunes playlists have a mix of both.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-i-wanted-to-go&#34;&gt;Why I wanted to go&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d never done blues dancing before, and was curious to see it, and maybe learn some and try it with Abby, who is also completely unfamiliar with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also: since Gregory is going back back to Europe soon, I wanted to have an opportunity to see him again before he left, and finally play French music with him. I&amp;rsquo;d never played French music before. When I told him I wanted to come and play with him for the first time, he helpfully sent me a link to his compilation of French tunes, &lt;a href=&#34;http://drawthedots.com/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Campanule&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. I feverishly tried to learn some of them before showing up. That was tricky because I wanted to play the music on my Baroque flute, an instrument that I&amp;rsquo;m &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/04/21/my-first-time-in-a-public-music-jam-intense-fun-with-chris-norman-and-david-greenberg/&#34;&gt;still quite a beginner at&lt;/a&gt;. But I didn&amp;rsquo;t want to use the modern flute for this music; it doesn&amp;rsquo;t produce the kind of sound I like for traditional music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;playing-music-with-gregory&#34;&gt;Playing music with Gregory&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gregory and I spent maybe ten minutes playing some of his compiled music sort of together. This was very hard for me for a number of reasons:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m still pretty bad at Baroque flute, having trouble with fingerings and intonation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t know the tunes very well, and was trying to find them in my printouts of his scores.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;He doesn&amp;rsquo;t even look at the scores, but just plays from memory.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;He doesn&amp;rsquo;t play exactly what was in the scores anyway, but improvises at will.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We were not coordinated, because he repeated sections or measures at will, and we didn&amp;rsquo;t really take turns or something.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t know how to come up with a secondary line or accompaniment on the fly to blend in with Gregory.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As dancers started arriving and Gregory kept on playing, I stopped my feeble attempts at contributing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a way, my attempt to get into playing French music tonight was a &lt;em&gt;failure&lt;/em&gt;, but on the other hand, I actually learned a lot from observing Gregory, and knew what I had to do to be able to function as an actual musician for dancing. I had to memorize tunes, learn them by ear, get myself off the tyranny of printed scores, watch dancers, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;dancing-blues&#34;&gt;Dancing blues&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point, the French dance part of the evening started to end, as the demand for blues rose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There wasn&amp;rsquo;t going to be any blues dance instruction, so Abby and I had a choice. We could just watch, or we could leave. We did do some watching, but I decided I wanted to dance, and so I just started making stuff up. I got the impression that people were basically just leading and following through improvisation similar to what I&amp;rsquo;ve experienced before when I did some Argentine tango (and a bit of Lindy hop and West Coast swing). I rather enjoy that kind of improvisational dancing, but have had little opportunity to participate in it because Abby is not used to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We did do a bit of blues dancing tonight, but it&amp;rsquo;s not clear to me whether we will continue. I&amp;rsquo;m very interested in exploring blues dance further, but Abby seems less interested. People are interested in different activities; that&amp;rsquo;s just a fact of life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This evening highlighted the contrast between my lack of ability to function as a practical musician for dancers and my comfort with improvisation as a dancer. I plan to work toward merging these two worlds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel sad that Gregory is leaving us, because I wanted to start working with him on French music, but his example has inspired me to want to continue playing French music after he is gone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2012-07-02&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-07-02)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And less than two months later, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/02/my-first-french-music-jam-anxious-but-excited/&#34;&gt;I joined Lisa and others in playing French music together, inspired by Gregory&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Flute: loving it again, remembering why I dance, and how I met my wife!</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/03/10/flute-loving-it-again/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Mar 2012 21:28:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/03/10/flute-loving-it-again/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, after four days of &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/07/flute-taking-a-break-while-clarifying-my-goals&#34;&gt;not even touching my (modern) flute&lt;/a&gt; and having spent the time having fun with my Baroque flute instead, I felt the urge to return to the modern flute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still have not regained the inclination to continue working on the orchestra music I still have to improve a lot on in the coming week, but I rediscovered the joy of simply playing my instrument.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;sound-intonation&#34;&gt;Sound, intonation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The perpetual challenges of getting clean sounds and accurate pitches on the Baroque flute in the past four days have given me an increased appreciation for the modern flute. I picked it up and spent time just trying to make beautiful sounds. Freed from the stress of orchestra practice, I felt much more relaxed on the instrument than I have for a while now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To my surprise (but not really), I have improved considerably on the flute after not playing it for four days. I really needed a break, a consolidation of lessons learned. My production of tones is much improved, and high notes are squeaking less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;music-for-dance&#34;&gt;Music for dance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing I&amp;rsquo;ve truly come to realize is that I particularly enjoy playing rhythmic music suitable for dancing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, every time I attend a dance, and there is live music, I experience a strange internal conflict: I do like to dance, but sometimes, I&amp;rsquo;d rather be on the other side of the dance floor, being the musical performer! The &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; time I&amp;rsquo;ve been on the other side has been at last year&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburghcontra.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Contras and Squares&lt;/a&gt; Holiday Ball.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most recent instance of my wishing I could sometimes stop dancing and just join the musicians has been at the local &lt;a href=&#34;http://coalcountry.org/frenchdance.html&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh French dance workshop and social&lt;/a&gt;, where we&amp;rsquo;ve had live piano, fiddle, and of course, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~gdyke/&#34;&gt;Gregory&lt;/a&gt; on his Irish flute. I wonder whether at some point I might be qualified to play for the event, using either my modern flute or Baroque flute. (By the way, it was held again today, but unfortunately, Abby and I chose not to go because we had too many things to do this weekend.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;remembering-dancing&#34;&gt;Remembering dancing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday I spent time playing along to a score/CD set I&amp;rsquo;ve mentioned before, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/World-Music-Cuba-Flute-play-along/dp/3702465804&#34;&gt;World Music Cuba&lt;/a&gt;. While playing the bolero, cha cha, and mambo pieces in particular, I felt I was returning &amp;ldquo;home&amp;rdquo; in many ways. This was among the first music I heard and saw people dancing to when I was curious and visited the &lt;a href=&#34;http://cmubdc.org/&#34;&gt;CMU Ballroom Dance Club&lt;/a&gt; in 2000, and fell in love with, and learned to dance to. I also played along to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Play-along-Argentina-Flute-World-Music/dp/3702465871&#34;&gt;World Music Argentina&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;some-photos-of-my-ballroom-dance-days&#34;&gt;Some photos of my ballroom dance days&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some photos of me dancing in 2002 with my last dance partner, Amy, before I quit competitive ballroom dancing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here we are at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dcdancesportinferno.com/&#34;&gt;DC DanceSport Inferno&lt;/a&gt; in 2002 doing a hockey stick in international rumba:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/ballroom/dcdi-2002-hockey-stick.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Amy and Franklin at DCDI 2002 in rumba&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And here were are at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://comp.cornelldancesport.org/&#34;&gt;Cornell DanceSport Classic&lt;/a&gt; in 2002 in cha cha, rumba, and tango:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/ballroom/cornell-2002-new-yorker.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Amy and Franklin at Cornell 2002 in cha cha&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/ballroom/cornell-2002-hockey-stick.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Amy and Franklin at Cornell 2002 in rumba&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/ballroom/cornell-2002-tango-promenade.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Amy and Franklin at Cornell 2002 in tango&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;dancing-with-abby&#34;&gt;Dancing with Abby&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But never mind the ballroom dance days. It was through salsa dancing that I met my wife!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;how-i-met-abby&#34;&gt;How I met Abby&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was through dancing that I met Abby in the first place. After quitting dancing in 2003, I never danced again until late 2006, when my friend Jon told me he had recently started salsa dancing (because of a girlfriend who got him into it) and invited me to join him at a free outdoors dance, and I went. Then as I re-entered the Pittsburgh salsa dance scene, I kept running into Abby.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;some-photos-of-us-dancing-salsa&#34;&gt;Some photos of us dancing salsa&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are not many photos of Abby dancing with me, because when I&amp;rsquo;m dancing, I&amp;rsquo;m not holding my camera, but here are some photos a friend took at a big salsa dance weekend at the Palisades in McKeesport in April 2008, a year after we started dating in 2007.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/palisades-2008/abby-franklin.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby and Franklin dancing salsa at Palisades&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/palisades-2008/abby-franklin-hair.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby and Franklin dancing salsa at Palisades, hair flying&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;expression-and-improvisation-in-dance-and-in-music&#34;&gt;Expression and improvisation in dance and in music&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;dance&#34;&gt;Dance&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One reason I gave up ballroom dancing was that I felt there was an overemphasis on &amp;ldquo;syllabus steps&amp;rdquo; (I realize this is an oversimplification of the ballroom dance culture; all very good ballroom dancers go beyond the syllabus mindset). After quitting ballroom dancing, I explored Argentine tango, which is all about improvisation, but I left it because (at the time) it seemed that most of the women in the local scene were very tall, which made dancing awkward for me. I got into salsa because freed from the closed embrace, there was clearly a lot of room for personal improvisation. Ironically, I first got into making stuff up as a result of my imperfect memory: I could never memorize long choreography of step patterns, whether I was doing ballroom dancing or anything else. So I would always make a &amp;ldquo;mistake&amp;rdquo;, then I would make something out of the mistake. I learned that as long as you get back in time with the music, and keep the lead and follow communication strong, there is no such thing really as a mistake. You just keep going, with whatever is happening at the present moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I now have a long-term goal of developing my technique and releasing my inhibitions so that I can improvise musically at will. Yesterday, I played with improvising when playing bolero, cha cha, and tango. It was a lot of fun and profoundly satisfying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;music&#34;&gt;Music&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I actually credit my study of the recorder and the Baroque flute for reawakening me to my dream of free expression and improvisation. Baroque music leaves room for a lot of interpretation of trills and ornamentation and articulation (subject, of course, to &amp;ldquo;good taste&amp;rdquo;). I want to go beyond that, but it has been a great starting point. For some reason, too much exposure to later music (such as Beethoven) had turned me into a score-reader, since such later music has so much already marked up for the performer to simply &lt;em&gt;obey&lt;/em&gt;. The sparse annotations in Renaissance and Baroque music give one much more freedom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am enjoying playing the flute again, now that I know what I really want to do with it. And I would like to merge my dance and music lives, just as Abby has always played the Balkan music she also dances to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2012-03-12&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-03-12)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ended up &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/12/quitting-the-cmu-all-university-orchestra-one-of-the-hardest-decisions-in-my-life/&#34;&gt;quitting the CMU AUO&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2013-01-26&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-01-26)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost a year later, I finally played tangos on flute &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/26/music-i-just-played-for-the-first-time-recorder-sonata-tangos/&#34;&gt;at a party&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2013-03-17&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-03-17)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost exactly a year later, I ended up playing selections from the World Music Cuba book &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/17/finally-doing-some-latin-music-jamming-on-flute/&#34;&gt;at a party&lt;/a&gt;, and improvising freely with two other guys!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On duets with dead musicians</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/11/15/on-duets-with-dead-musicians/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Nov 2011 22:05:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/11/15/on-duets-with-dead-musicians/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I came across a story about technology-created video and audio recordings of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.npr.org/blogs/deceptivecadence/2011/11/10/142209842/when-is-a-duet-actually-a-duet&#34;&gt;current musicians &amp;ldquo;performing&amp;rdquo; with legends no longer alive&lt;/a&gt;. There were vehement comments on the story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amusingly, the story had ended with the observation that &amp;ldquo;Perhaps there&amp;rsquo;s a greater sensitivity to such projects in the classical world, which is so often occupied with &amp;ndash; and maybe even paralyzed by &amp;ndash; very strongly held notions of received tradition and respect.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without vehemence, here are some of my thoughts on these &amp;ldquo;re-performances&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;curiosity&#34;&gt;Curiosity&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first reaction was curiosity, rather than immediate hostility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are some people who get pre-emptively angry about something just on the basis of some ideology without even trying something out. These people do things like write negative reviews of books they never read, or complain about proposed legislation that they have never read and whose consequences they have not calculated. Life is short, but I try not to make those kinds of errors. I prefer to claim ignorance or non-opinion rather than have an opinion about everything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;gheorghiu-and-callas&#34;&gt;Gheorghiu and Callas&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I clicked on the video clip of soprano Angela Gheorghiu singing the Habanera from Carmen &amp;ldquo;with&amp;rdquo; Maria Callas.  I&amp;rsquo;m not a real opera fan (have never been to a live opera performance), but in the past have listened to and watched a lot of Maria Callas singing famous arias. Her raw emotional intensity was unparalleled, but her voice (such as it was in her later years in recordings) had rather imperfect aspects; but overall, I would consider myself a fan of Callas. It is hard not to cry when watching and listening to her sing, say, &lt;a href=&#34;http://operalady.blogspot.com/2011/01/maria-callas-as-tosca-vissi-darte.html&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Vissi d&amp;rsquo;arte&amp;rdquo; from Tosca&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Aside: I actually took an Italian class because I wanted to sing along to and better understand Italian opera arias, just as I took German for Mozart and Schubert, and took Spanish for rumba, salsa, and tango!  Want to get me to learn a language?  Find me some beautiful music in that language for me to sing.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gheorghiu I confess never having been a big fan of. I tried to discount this fact while evaluating her video.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fundamentally, I disliked the video because it does not make sense. In its original context, the famous Habanera is sung by Carmen while taunting Don Jose to charm him. A chorus does come in during this aria, but clearly, it is a one-on-one message. It makes no sense being spread out over two Carmens. Also, there is no semblance of actual interaction in this &amp;ldquo;re-performance&amp;rdquo;. Video makes this painfully obvious. It&amp;rsquo;s not as if Callas is alive and reacting to what Gheorghiu does and matching her.  Also, as one of the commenters noted, Gheorghiu is not matching Callas, but putting her in a &amp;ldquo;subordinate position&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an audio-only version, one would not notice how asymmetric the &amp;ldquo;duet&amp;rdquo; was. It would also be uninteresting and confusing, because the two voices are both high and without contrasting lines. It becomes clear that the whole gimmick of the video is the visual of Gheorghiu on stage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;joshua-bell-and-sergei-rachmaninoff&#34;&gt;Joshua Bell and Sergei Rachmaninoff&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I clicked on the video of Joshua Bell on violin playing &amp;ldquo;with&amp;rdquo; Sergei Rachmaninoff on piano (actually, some kind of piano rigged so that its keys are pressed as though a ghost were playing).  This was actually kind of interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, I have to discount the fact that I have always been a big fan of Joshua Bell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can definitely do without the ghostly piano action. I have no interest whatsoever in ever attending a concert where I see a piano being &amp;ldquo;played&amp;rdquo; mechanically, even if reproduced from an actual recording by Rachmaninoff himself. I say this even though I had no problem listening to piano rolls from Rachmaninoff or Mahler or others; they were just another form of audio recording. &lt;strong&gt;There is a difference between the musical experience I am willing to accept when just listening to audio at home and what I am willing to accept when being physically at a concert or watching a video.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suppose I were just hearing Bell playing &amp;ldquo;with&amp;rdquo; Rachmaninoff, not seeing the video. I tried that. It was pretty good. Note that this music really is inherently a duet for piano and violin. So Bell simply filled in where &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.zenph.com/the-music/artists/rachmaninoff-plays-rachmaninoff/joshua-bell-at-home-with-friends&#34;&gt;Fritz Kreisler had originally played with Rachmaninoff&lt;/a&gt;. And I think he played very much with an awareness of the piano part and blending musically with it. The only difference from a real duet is that there was no pianist reacting in turn to Bell&amp;rsquo;s playing. Ideally in a duet you&amp;rsquo;d have a give and take, while here there is a fixed accompaniment to the violin. I give credit to Bell for being &amp;ldquo;respectful&amp;rdquo; and making the most of this constraint.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;extra-musical-considerations&#34;&gt;Extra-musical considerations&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s where extra-musical factors can affect our evaluation. I suppose I think that the live audience at Bell&amp;rsquo;s concert missed out, because some living pianist could have been there playing with Bell and being appreciated, rather than the ghost of Rachmaninoff. The dead have already done their music-making; let the living have their say.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, we cannot pretend that anything outside of being present at a live performance is &amp;ldquo;pure&amp;rdquo;. In particular, we know that audio recordings since the dawn of time have involved takes, edits, filtering, overdubbing. An audio recording is its own artifact, whether its the backwards sitars and other effects famously used by the Beatles, or Glenn Gould duplicating segments for repeats and manipulating the sound he wanted to hear back from the recording. We cannot be naive about these things. We accept that films are fiction, and that photos are retouched.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If one really believes in pure, unmediated musical experience, there is only one option: get off the iPod or iTunes or whatever other devices or software, leave the living room, and check out the local music ensembles. Even better, join or form one and participate as a performer! I think it is regrettable that technology has turned music into an abstract commodity rather than a living, participatory activity for everyone. Our society has deemed it necessary for everyone to develop basic competence in reading, writing, and arithmetic; we do not require everyone to be an expert at any of these. Why do we not also expect basic musical competence?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Duets with dead musicians do not really appeal to me, but there are degrees of unpleasantness or weirdness. And the artifice is not all that different from other technological manipulations we already take for granted or choose to ignore.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>