<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Economics on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/economics/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Economics on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/economics/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>What happens when you donate your used clothing?</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/05/22/what-happens-when-you-donate-your-used-clothing/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 May 2015 22:39:14 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/05/22/what-happens-when-you-donate-your-used-clothing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I hate throwing stuff away, and that includes clothing I have that I
no longer wear. Abby participates in clothing exchanges with &lt;em&gt;local&lt;/em&gt;
women in order to avoid wastage, and she takes my clothing also, to
give away somewhere when possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was interested to read an
&lt;a href=&#34;http://conversableeconomist.blogspot.com/2015/05/quandaries-of-global-trade-in.html&#34;&gt;economics blog post&lt;/a&gt;
about possible unintended consequences, however, of clothing donations
that go to low-income countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apparently, what happens is that this flow of used clothing thanks to
&lt;em&gt;globalization&lt;/em&gt; competes with &lt;em&gt;local&lt;/em&gt; textile and clothing
industries. The used clothing ends up being resold rather than
donated. Interesting, huh?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>World Toilet Day is not just another crappy holiday</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/19/world-toilet-day-is-not-just-another-crappy-holiday/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2014 23:41:34 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/19/world-toilet-day-is-not-just-another-crappy-holiday/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;From an excellent blog I follow, Timothy Taylor&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://conversableeconomist.blogspot.com/&#34;&gt;Conversable Economist&lt;/a&gt;, I read his &lt;a href=&#34;http://conversableeconomist.blogspot.com/2014/11/world-toilet-day.html&#34;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; about &lt;a href=&#34;http://worldtoilet.org/&#34;&gt;World Toilet Day&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, every day is some kind of observed day somewhere in the world promoted by someone, but World Toilet Day is not just another crappy commercial holiday. It&amp;rsquo;s about a serious problem, which is that 15 percent of the world population still lives without proper sanitation. Open sanitation, especially in densely populated areas, is a cause of much serious illness (especially to children, who are especially vulnerable). So I&amp;rsquo;m happy about the invention of World Toilet Day in 2001 by the World Toilet Organization global non-profit. It&amp;rsquo;s curious that I hadn&amp;rsquo;t heard about it for thirteen years, but I&amp;rsquo;m grateful Timothy Taylor pointed it out in his blog. Because this is a serious issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I, for one, am grateful to live in the industrialized US where toilets abound everywhere, and even in parks such as my local Frick Park in Pittsburgh, there are port-a-potties in various locations within the park. I used to make fun of my immigrant parents for being strangely fixated on and happy about functioning and clean toilets, but the reality is that their generation and their parents&amp;rsquo; generation in rural Taiwan did not necessarily have this luxury. In fact, even today, apparently, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ketagalanmedia.com/2014/09/03/dreaming-odor-free-bathroom-taiwan/&#34;&gt;the sewage system is not great in Taiwan&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Some good science-based reading for Election Day, whether or not you voted</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/04/some-good-science-based-reading-for-election-day/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2014 15:41:25 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/04/some-good-science-based-reading-for-election-day/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/11/01/how-i-avoid-demotivating-myself-away-from-voting/&#34;&gt;I voted&lt;/a&gt; today, on Election Day in the US.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/franklinmingchen/15527007380&#34; title=&#34;IMG_20141104_153326 by Franklin Chen, on Flickr&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7496/15527007380_abfb7f5691.jpg&#34; width=&#34;375&#34; height=&#34;500&#34; alt=&#34;IMG_20141104_153326&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, now is as good a time as any for some interesting articles about politics and voting. Here are some that came my way:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;motive-attribution-asymmetry&#34;&gt;Motive attribution asymmetry&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/oliver-burkeman-column/2014/nov/04/get-along-enemies-motive-attribution&#34;&gt;Oliver Burkeman&lt;/a&gt; discusses a study that shows that you argue that your side is motivated by &lt;em&gt;love&lt;/em&gt;, while the other side is motivated by &lt;em&gt;hate&lt;/em&gt;. But since the other side thinks the same, what is the &amp;ldquo;truth&amp;rdquo;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;One of the reasons it’s so hard to accept the notion that our enemies might be motivated by love, I suspect, is because that conclusion seems to suggest that our enemies’ cause must therefore have merit.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Actually, those two issues are completely unrelated.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I agree with this: it is quite possible (I&amp;rsquo;m not saying it&amp;rsquo;s always the case) for someone you disagree with to have the most loving intentions, but simply be &lt;em&gt;mistaken&lt;/em&gt; rather than &lt;em&gt;evil&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;dangers-of-accurate-statistical-prediction-by-data-journalism&#34;&gt;Dangers of accurate statistical prediction by data journalism&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A good article in the Berkeley Journal of Sociology about &lt;a href=&#34;http://berkeleyjournal.org/2014/11/what-should-the-fox-say/&#34;&gt;Nate Silver&amp;rsquo;s statistical journalism&lt;/a&gt; argues that data journalism should focus on understanding rather than prediction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;This extensive use of Big Data for election forecasting passively promotes our current sense of political fatalism.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;If our politicians can’t risk making public appearances or trying to appear human without navigating at least three levels of performative irony, then our political culture has entered a state of structural crisis.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;emotions-of-election-day-asymmetric-hedonic-response&#34;&gt;Emotions of Election Day: asymmetric hedonic response&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://harvardmagazine.com/2014/11/emotions-of-elections-study-todd-rogers&#34;&gt;Harvard Kennedy School research result&lt;/a&gt; on asymmetric hedonic response: after an election, losing makes you far sadder than winning makes you happy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I confess to having been really bummed out fairly often in the past two decades of voting. I&amp;rsquo;ve been trying to be more detached.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;in-praise-of-the-occasional-voter&#34;&gt;In praise of the occasional voter&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, some people make fun of people who do not vote (I never do this; there are often quite rational reasons to avoid voting). Here&amp;rsquo;s an interesting article arguing that the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2014/11/02/upshot/the-vital-role-of-the-occasional-voter.html&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;occasional voter&amp;rdquo; is actually quite valuable&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From an economics point of view, &amp;ldquo;voting is a classic example of a free-rider problem&amp;rdquo; because the possible gain for each individual is so tiny, statistically, that it may not make sense to go out of one&amp;rsquo;s way to vote.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, voting has an interesting cost to the voter: &amp;ldquo;The very act of voting for a given candidate or party ties us mentally to that candidate and inadvertently costs us some measure of our neutrality.&amp;rdquo; This is because we &lt;em&gt;rationalize&lt;/em&gt; what we do in order to resolve our &lt;em&gt;cognitive dissonance&lt;/em&gt; about the apparent pointlessness of voting. We try to fool ourselves into thinking we did something really important. &amp;ldquo;We don’t just choose what we like; we like more and more what we choose.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the &amp;ldquo;occasional voter&amp;rdquo; can be an outsider not subject to cognitive dissonance as much as the regular and party-registered voter, countering partisanship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, it could be argued that partisanship, and the resulting gridlock, is good. But is it? That&amp;rsquo;s another topic entirely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-strange-sameness-of-political-candidates-in-the-face-of-competition&#34;&gt;The strange sameness of political candidates in the face of competition&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Conversable Economist, Timothy Taylor, offered an explanation for &lt;a href=&#34;http://conversableeconomist.blogspot.com/2014/11/the-excessive-sameness-of-politics-and.html&#34;&gt;why politicians end up in the same squishy middle&lt;/a&gt;, based on &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Harold_Hotelling&#34;&gt;Hotelling&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s famous 1929 mathematical model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Mainstream politicians thus face a continual dynamic where they seek to reassure their more ardent partisans that they are on their side, while shading and tacking as needed to pick up voters in the middle.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, if you are interested in more mathematical modeling, check out Scott Page&amp;rsquo;s free MOOC on &amp;ldquo;model thinking&amp;rdquo;, which I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/06/16/review-of-coursera-course-model-thinking/&#34;&gt;reviewed here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;bloggers-reactions-to-election-day&#34;&gt;Bloggers&amp;rsquo; reactions to Election Day&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a blogger I follow, &lt;a href=&#34;http://ayjay.tumblr.com/post/101755797073/and-one-more-note-on-politics&#34;&gt;Alan Jacobs, on his options&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/the-fix/wp/2013/05/09/people-hate-congress-but-most-incumbents-get-re-elected-what-gives/&#34;&gt;People hate Congress, but 90% of incumbents get re-elected&lt;/a&gt;. &amp;ldquo;The message from voters to Congress? Throw the bums out. But not my bum.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope you enjoyed this taste of research results concerning psychology, sociology, and economics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not staying up to watch the returns from today&amp;rsquo;s election. I did what I did, and it&amp;rsquo;s over for me until next May.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Did you learn anything surprising in the links I shared here? Is there anything that will change how you think or behave when it comes to politics?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why it&#39;s so funny that Fama and Shiller just simultaneously shared the Nobel in economics</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/15/why-its-so-funny-that-fama-and-shiller-just-simultaneously-shared-the-nobel-in-economics/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2013 22:32:14 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/15/why-its-so-funny-that-fama-and-shiller-just-simultaneously-shared-the-nobel-in-economics/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;It was terribly amusing to me when I heard that &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nobelprize.org/nobel_prizes/economic-sciences/laureates/2013/&#34;&gt;Eugene Fama, Lars Peter Hansen, and Robert Shiller shared the Nobel in economics for 2013&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not an economist, so I don&amp;rsquo;t know all the details of the work of these guys. In fact, I had not heard of Lars Peter Hansen before, so I have nothing to say about him. But Eugene Fama and Robert Shiller are practically household words if you pay any attention to financial markets and investment, and the story of the housing bubble. What is really funny is that Fama and Shiller have such different opinions about fundamental matters in economics, but are sharing the Nobel! I think it&amp;rsquo;s cool that the media are covering this amusing situation, because maybe the wider public will get an idea of what kinds of ongoing debates there are in economics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And here&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://conversableeconomist.blogspot.com/2013/10/the-2013-nobel-prize-to-fama-hanson-and.html&#34;&gt;one of the economics blogs I follow that has a discussion of what these economists did&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;eugene-fama&#34;&gt;Eugene Fama&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I first learned about Eugene Fama through books on personal investing that promoted his &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Efficient-market_hypothesis&#34;&gt;efficient market hypothesis&lt;/a&gt; and therefore the use of indexed mutual funds and ETFs. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dfaus.com/&#34;&gt;Dimensional Fund Advisors&lt;/a&gt;, making use of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dimensional.com/famafrench/&#34;&gt;work of Eugene Fama and Kenneth French&lt;/a&gt;, has in particular promoted sophisticated portfolio management based on modifying plain indexing (such as Vanguard&amp;rsquo;s mutual funds) with small cap and value stock overweighting. William Bernstein was famously enthusiastic about DFA and even suggested ways for &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.efficientfrontier.com/ef/702/3FM-10.htm&#34;&gt;individual investors to do their own simulation of their three-factor approach&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More on &lt;a href=&#34;http://indexinvestor.com/Members/2004/November/nov045.php3&#34;&gt;DFA versus Vanguard&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fama&amp;rsquo;s fellow &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chicago_school_of_economics&#34;&gt;Chicago school&lt;/a&gt; economist wrote up some &lt;a href=&#34;http://faculty.chicagobooth.edu/john.cochrane/research/papers/Fama_nobel.pdf&#34;&gt;very opinionated and enthusiastic praise and summary of Fama&amp;rsquo;s work&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, Fama remains one of the biggest die-hard defenders of the efficient market hypothesis, to this day. His impact on the world of investing cannot be overstated. If you invest in passively managed indexed funds, rather than chasing &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alpha_%28investment%29&#34;&gt;alpha&lt;/a&gt;, you&amp;rsquo;re implicitly relying on and believing in the work that he and others have done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;robert-shiller&#34;&gt;Robert Shiller&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Robert Shiller comes from a completely different economic philosophy and even public existence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In stark contrast to Fama and the Chicago school of neoclassical economics based on rational expectations, Shiller is a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Behavioral_economics&#34;&gt;behavioral economist&lt;/a&gt;, which believes in irrationality and market inefficiency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He has written a lot of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.econ.yale.edu/~shiller/books.htm&#34;&gt;popular books&lt;/a&gt; and often goes around giving talks. He is most famous for warning about the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Economic_bubble&#34;&gt;market bubbles&lt;/a&gt; of the past decade and more, including the last housing bubble.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking of bubbles, check out what &lt;a href=&#34;http://delong.typepad.com/sdj/2013/10/eugene-fama-on-the-housing-bubble.html&#34;&gt;Fama said about the housing bubble and bubbles in general&lt;/a&gt;. He&amp;rsquo;s practically denying that bubbles exist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it&amp;rsquo;s awesome to have two very outspoken economists with radically different approaches to economics shared the Nobel this year. It may help the public understand better the nature of the field of economics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-12-10&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-12-10)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two months later, Fama and Shiller are still an item. Check out &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.theguardian.com/business/2013/dec/10/nobel-prize-economists-robert-shiller-eugene-fama&#34;&gt;this interview&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why soda bans don&#39;t work</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/11/07/why-soda-bans-dont-work/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Nov 2011 19:13:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/11/07/why-soda-bans-dont-work/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I just saw an article, &lt;a href=&#34;http://well.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/11/07/soda-bans-in-schools-have-limited-benefit/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Soda Bans in Schools Have Limited Impact&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. It boggles my mind that anyone would advocate soda bans in school as a policy in isolation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are my thoughts on the economics and politics, and health and cultural aspects of the issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;economics-101&#34;&gt;Economics 101&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The article describes the empirical results from soda bans:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Students were drinking other sugary beverages instead&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Students were bringing in their own sugary beverages&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;economics&lt;/em&gt; of the situation are obvious:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are plenty of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Substitute_good&#34;&gt;substitute goods&lt;/a&gt; for soda that satisfy students&amp;rsquo; demand for sugary beverages.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Since the school is not a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Monopoly&#34;&gt;monopoly&lt;/a&gt;, and there are plenty of other &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Supply_(economics)&#34;&gt;suppliers&lt;/a&gt; of soda and other sugary beverages outside of school, all that happens is that students buy from another supplier.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basic economic theory has a way to reduce consumption of sugary beverages, of course: a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pigovian_tax&#34;&gt;Pigovian tax&lt;/a&gt; such as the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sin_tax&#34;&gt;sin tax&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cigarette_taxes_in_the_United_States&#34;&gt;cigarettes&lt;/a&gt;. A tax on the entire category of sugary beverages would do the trick. There is reason to believe the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Price_elasticity_of_demand&#34;&gt;price elasticity&lt;/a&gt; is sufficient that such a tax would considerably reduce consumption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;politics-101&#34;&gt;Politics 101&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And such a wide-ranging tax is completely impossible, politically. Even an overall &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Soda_tax&#34;&gt;soda tax&lt;/a&gt; is, I believe, politically impossible. Worse, it would not solve the problem, because as we know from the school example, there are other sugary beverages that pose the very same health problems but are not labeled as &amp;ldquo;soda&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;bigger-picture-of-economics&#34;&gt;Bigger picture of economics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Worse, the &lt;em&gt;problem&lt;/em&gt; as narrowly defined, that of decreasing consumption of sugary beverages, is only the tip of the iceberg when it comes to the bigger picture of public health. People will eat cookies and any number of other less perfect substitutes for sugary beverages anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;beyond-economics-to-health&#34;&gt;Beyond economics to health&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the purported motivation for reducing sugary beverages has been to reduce obesity. Obesity happens for all kinds of reasons. Worse, I don&amp;rsquo;t even like the focus on &lt;em&gt;weight&lt;/em&gt;. Poor health has to do with a lot more than weight. Most people, when thinking about their weight, and try to lose it, don&amp;rsquo;t even apply healthy strategies to lose weight, or even to do so permanently rather than temporarily. I don&amp;rsquo;t believe stopgap politically controversial initiatives can do much to address the real problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;culture-and-a-personal-note&#34;&gt;Culture and a personal note&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am bombarded daily with access to sugary beverages. Every time I go to a lunch seminar or party or reception, cans and bottles of soda, sports beverages, juices, and sweetened teas are provided. Clearly American culture is simply not ready to give up on these beverages. I get the impression that I am in the minority in choosing not to drink them. I have had maybe &lt;em&gt;four or five&lt;/em&gt; cans or bottles of such beverages in the past ten years. I get the impression that a lot of people I see around have had approximately &lt;em&gt;ten thousand&lt;/em&gt; cans or bottles in the past ten years. I don&amp;rsquo;t lecture people on why they should abstain, because it is useless even when directed toward, say, my own parents. I don&amp;rsquo;t know what it will take for the culture to change, or what I can do to help. Right now, I just silently abstain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you have any suggestions of what I could really do to help spread the word that life really might be more enjoyable without consuming sugary beverages all the time?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>When is something overpriced? 36 examples</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/10/28/when-is-something-overpriced/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Oct 2011 20:44:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/10/28/when-is-something-overpriced/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Very often I hear people complaining that &amp;ldquo;X is overpriced&amp;rdquo;. I always listen carefully to try to figure out what they mean, because I&amp;rsquo;ve learned that the word &amp;ldquo;overpriced&amp;rdquo; can mean many things. I find that I learn a lot about people from how they use that word.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are 36 things people might mean when they say something is &amp;ldquo;overpriced&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;gas-for-my-car-is-overpriced&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Gas for my car is overpriced&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The evil oil companies are colluding and price-fixing and don&amp;rsquo;t deserve to keep all their huge profits.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I am paying much more now for than I used to. Anything higher than I am used to is overpriced.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cheap driving is an American entitlement, and we need to do something in the Middle East.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The un-American liberals won&amp;rsquo;t let us drill, baby, drill!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;college-is-overpriced&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;College is overpriced&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My parents had to work extra jobs to pay for my education.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t get the kind of job I thought I was guaranteed when taking out student loans.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Those lazy liberal professors are getting paid way too much for doing nothing useful for society.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I hate the whole stupid college sports system in America.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The ease of getting federal student loans drives up college enrollment demand and therefore drives up college tuition as well.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Those evil conservatives have turned education into a cold for-profit business enterprise.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;symphony-tickets-are-overpriced&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Symphony tickets are overpriced&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t like classical music and would rather be going to a musical.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d rather just download music at home.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The tickets are not overpriced, but the parking should be easy and free.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;People who go to the symphony are privileged and wealthy and think they are better than me.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;textbooks-are-overpriced&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Textbooks are overpriced&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I could pay less for textbooks if the publishers didn&amp;rsquo;t keep on churning out new editions every year and the professor made us get the new editions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The textbook industry is a parasite, and the authors are not getting their fair sure of the profits.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Information should be free.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d rather buy e-books for less than pay for dead tree books.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;macintosh-computers-are-overpriced&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Macintosh computers are overpriced&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I hate Steve Jobs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I hate those artsy liberals who love Macintosh computers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Computers manufactured from comparable materials should have similar costs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When I pay more, I should have more applications to choose from, not fewer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Apple takes away my freedom to tinker and charges me for taking away my freedom?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;fresh-vegetables-are-overpriced&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Fresh vegetables are overpriced&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why would I buy vegetables when I can buy a tasty Big Mac for less?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All food should be cheap.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t like to eat vegetables.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The government artificially makes a lot of unhealthy, processed food cheaper than fresh vegetables because of lobbyists who get their subsidies to the industry.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;homes-are-overpriced&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Homes are overpriced&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I can&amp;rsquo;t buy the home that I deserve.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I won&amp;rsquo;t settle for a smaller home.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I only want to live in a &amp;ldquo;good&amp;rdquo; neighborhood.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Speculators and lax lending policies have created a housing bubble.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;End the Fed!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;that-big-tv-is-overpriced&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;That big TV is overpriced&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m jealous that you have a TV I can&amp;rsquo;t buy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TV is stupid.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you just wait a while, you can pay less for the same TV in a couple of months.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The price of the TV does not scale linearly with the size.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>