<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Great Race on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/great-race/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Great Race on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/great-race/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Getting up when reality punches you in the face: running the second Liberty Mile in Pittsburgh</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/08/09/getting-up-when-reality-punches-you-in-the-face-running-the-second-liberty-mile-in-pittsburgh/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Aug 2013 20:49:35 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/08/09/getting-up-when-reality-punches-you-in-the-face-running-the-second-liberty-mile-in-pittsburgh/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Last year, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/08/17/the-inaugural-liberty-mile-a-review-of-pittsburghs-first-road-mile-race/&#34;&gt;I reported on the excitement I had running in and watching&lt;/a&gt; the first &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.libertymile.org/&#34;&gt;GNC Live Well Liberty Mile&lt;/a&gt;. I was so excited about running it again that late this May, having mostly recovered from my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/05/06/2013-pittsburgh-marathon-my-135th-race-was-my-worst-i-finished/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Marathon disaster&lt;/a&gt;, I quickly pre-registered for the Liberty Mile for this year. I anticipated training to run well in this year&amp;rsquo;s Liberty Mile, given that I was not really trained last year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, this year I have been in very poor shape since the marathon, because of a whole series of health problems and disruptions in my life resulting from a skin rash I got during a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/05/12/my-rachel-carson-trail-hike-for-the-year/&#34;&gt;Rachel Carson Trail hike in May&lt;/a&gt;. The upshot is that I have been running (and exercising in general) very little in the past three months. As the Liberty Mile approached, I wished that I had not registered for it at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I faced a dilemma: what should I do about the race?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;deciding-to-run-it&#34;&gt;Deciding to run it&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The good thing about the mile is that it&amp;rsquo;s short enough that of course I can finish the thing. So I felt there was no excuse to just bail out and forfeit my pre-registration. I was going to run it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bad thing about the mile is that it is brutal to actually run &lt;em&gt;fast&lt;/em&gt;. I have always felt pukey after running a mile as &amp;ldquo;fast&amp;rdquo; as I can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, I decided to still try to run the Liberty Mile as fast as I could, knowing that I would probably suffer for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In recent weeks I&amp;rsquo;ve been trying to go out periodically for short, slow runs, something like two miles at a time, to gain at least have &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; kind of conditioning. Also, earlier this week I put in some &amp;ldquo;fast&amp;rdquo; repeats of about 300m out in Frick Park: the only &amp;ldquo;fast&amp;rdquo; running I&amp;rsquo;ve done since April!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this whole week I was feeling bad, stress exacerbated by home repair disruptions with the contractors coming over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;support-from-abby&#34;&gt;Support from Abby&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, I went to the race alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year, Abby offered to go downtown with me so she could watch the race and be with me. (In May when I was pre-registering for the race, she had just spent months barely mobile because of a broken foot and was simply not certain she would be able to even run a mile again by August.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really appreciated this because I felt rather vulnerable about this race. We planned to watch the first wave start, and then have me run my heat (again the &amp;ldquo;Unstoppable 40+&amp;rdquo; heat), then hang out afterwards and watch the elite heats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We drove downtown and parked and walked to the packet pickup area in Market Square. I was pleased that it wasn&amp;rsquo;t raining; it had rained earlier in the day, but that was all over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because we arrived later than other people, they had run out of Small T-shirts and so I got a Medium.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/liberty-mile-2013/abby.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby holding my T-shirt&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;changes-in-the-course&#34;&gt;Changes in the course&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I should note that the course was changed from last year. The change makes sense because it considerably simplifies the logistics. Last year, the course was a straight shot down Liberty Ave toward downtown. This year, the course was an almost-loop course, first going out on Penn Ave, then turning to head back in on Liberty Ave. The advantage is that the start and finish are close together, so it is much easier for people to plan to spectate or get back to their cars or whatever. I do like the concept of the straight downhill road course, but understand the logistical difficulties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My plan was to do my best to avoid going out too fast, and try to push hard in the final downhill portion of the race. Easier said than done, because last year I certainly wanted to avoid going out too fast, but did anyway!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;before-the-race&#34;&gt;Before the race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wore my Vibram FiveFingers Bikila LS shoes again.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/liberty-mile-2013/before-start.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin before race&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At the GNC booth, I saw they were giving out free samples of energy bars and other stuff. I was feeling hungry, and although I know that it is best not to race having just eaten, especially unfamiliar foods, I took a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.gnc.com/product/index.jsp?productId=4468895&#34;&gt;GNC Pro Performance Pro Crunch Lite&lt;/a&gt; energy bar, and ate a couple of bites before giving the remainder to Abby to put away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was probably a big mistake to have eaten from the energy bar, because it didn&amp;rsquo;t really agree with me. Oops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;start-and-finish-lines&#34;&gt;Start and finish lines&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We checked out the start and finish lines.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/liberty-mile-2013/start-line.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Start line&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/liberty-mile-2013/finish-line.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Finish line&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;first-heat-at-7-00-pm&#34;&gt;First heat (at 7:00 PM)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We watched as the first &amp;ldquo;fun run&amp;rdquo; heat went.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/liberty-mile-2013/first-heat-start.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-race-heat-at-7-20-pm&#34;&gt;My race (heat at 7:20 PM)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got to the start line and lined up &lt;em&gt;at the back&lt;/em&gt;, where I knew I belonged. I was not sure that I would not be last place in my heat!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/liberty-mile-2013/my-heat-start.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here I am, looking as tired as I in fact was, still taking medication for my skin problem that is not completely gone (usually showing up as spots on my neck or hands and arms):&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/liberty-mile-2013/franklin-before.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin before the race&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As the race began, I tried not to go too fast, but did. 1:34 for the first quarter mile, not good at all! Last year, I ran the mile in 6:39, and went out in 1:29 for the first quarter. This year, I was hoping to go under 7:00 at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I slowed down for the second quarter, then finally found a steady pace for the third quarter. During the final quarter, I saw the finish line and eventually saw the clock ticking up toward 7:00. I was &lt;em&gt;furious&lt;/em&gt; that I might not be able to finish a 7-minute mile. I sprinted all out and didn&amp;rsquo;t actually finish under 7:00 according to the clock (the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.areep.com/events/libertymile/&#34;&gt;official race results&lt;/a&gt; say I finished in 7:02), but my chip time was 6:56, so I actually did run the mile in under 7 minutes!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My splits:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1:34 (went too fast)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1:56 (uphill, deliberately slowed down)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1:46 (steady)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1:40 (final kick)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;more-photos-of-the-liberty-mile&#34;&gt;More photos of the Liberty Mile&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More photos of the entire event can be seen &lt;a href=&#34;http://petemadia.photoshelter.com/gallery/2013-GNC-Live-Well-Liberty-Mile/G0000gQc.MfyoOAE/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;after-my-race&#34;&gt;After my race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Afterwards, I felt really, really crappy:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/liberty-mile-2013/done-in-pain.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin done for a while but still in pain&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In fact, for a full half hour after the race, all I could do was walk and sit around with Abby trying to feel less crappy. &lt;strong&gt;I have never felt so bad for so long after any race of any distance.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;reflections&#34;&gt;Reflections&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mentally, also, I was still very &lt;em&gt;angry&lt;/em&gt; at myself: I came in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.areep.com/events/libertymile/results/13lm_uno.txt&#34;&gt;60th place out of 74&lt;/a&gt;, running a chip time of 6:56, a whopping &lt;em&gt;18 seconds&lt;/em&gt; slower than last year. That&amp;rsquo;s a huge decrease in fitness for a mile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My plan for this year, 2013, was supposed to be to get back into great health and fitness, &amp;ldquo;the shape I was in five years ago&amp;rdquo;. It&amp;rsquo;s why, for the new year, I got into &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/28/meditations-on-climbing-the-36-floors-of-the-pitt-cathedral-of-learning/&#34;&gt;climbing the Cathedral of Learning&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s why I got into running in the winter](/blog/2012/12/31/why-i-went-frick-park-trail-running-in-snowfall-for-the-first-time-in-a-decade/). It&amp;rsquo;s why I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/30/why-and-how-i-am-going-to-run-the-2013-pittsburgh-marathon/&#34;&gt;decided to run the Pittsburgh Marathon&lt;/a&gt;. I blew it my overtraining for the marathon and then suffering freak skin problems after a hike that ended up seeing doctors something like five times, and being put on medication that messed with me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a lot to be angry about. But after I recovered, I became calm and stopped being angry about being punched in the face by reality. I decided that it was motivation for me to turn my life around. I decided that I was going to get back into a regular exercise routine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In just the past three months, I have lost all of my fitness of the past several years. But I have a plan to get back on track, starting &lt;em&gt;tomorrow&lt;/em&gt;. I believe that for 2014, I can still get back into my 2008 shape. It&amp;rsquo;s a matter of making it a priority, over all the other things I have been doing in my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;going-home&#34;&gt;Going home&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After I recovered enough that I felt like eating and walking again, Abby and I went back to our car and we went home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only minutes after getting home did I realize that I had &lt;em&gt;totally forgotten&lt;/em&gt; to stick around to watch the elite runners&amp;rsquo; races!! That was far from my mind when I was feeling nauseous and reflecting on my poor fitness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The race was very well organized, and I&amp;rsquo;m thankful for the continuation of this new Pittsburgh tradition. Although I had a humbling experience in my heat, I totally want to be back for a third try at executing a good mile next year! And I am thankful that I actually ran it, because it gave me the resolve to regain my lost fitness.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Running my 10th Great Race 10K: &#34;obscene but in a good way&#34;</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/09/30/running-my-10th-great-race-10k-obscene-but-in-a-good-way/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Sep 2012 19:08:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/09/30/running-my-10th-great-race-10k-obscene-but-in-a-good-way/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/great-race-2012/great-race-expo.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Great Race quilt&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Today I ran in Pittsburgh&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://rungreatrace.com/&#34;&gt;Great Race 10K&lt;/a&gt; for the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/25/blistered-but-blissful-in-the-burgh/&#34;&gt;tenth time in my life&lt;/a&gt;. For various reasons, I performed a number of experiments for this tenth running of the race, doing things I&amp;rsquo;ve never done before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the race, I heard someone say, as I passed him:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
...obscene... but in a good way!
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It made my day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll explain what might have triggered this reaction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;preparation-and-uncertainty&#34;&gt;Preparation and uncertainty&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/07/running-my-8th-pretty-good-race-5k-dealing-with-disappointment/&#34;&gt;Pretty Good Race 5K&lt;/a&gt;, I was so tired out from my effort that I totally lost the desire to run. Plus my left foot was hurting more again. I ended up not running a single step for two weeks. This meant, of course, that there was no way I was going to go after the goal of beating last year&amp;rsquo;s time in the Great Race 10K.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, there was the question of whether I should even run the Great Race at all this year! Until almost the last minute, Abby and I agreed that if I did not feel up for running it at all, I would just sell my registration. Part of me felt bad about the possibility of breaking &amp;ldquo;tradition&amp;rdquo; and not running the race; I have stubbornly run it while horribly sick in some years! At the same time, it&amp;rsquo;s not really the end of the world if I miss a race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;change-of-purpose-and-plan-enter-the-invisible-shoes&#34;&gt;Change of purpose and plan: enter the Invisible Shoes!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eventually, after my two-week absence from running, my left foot injury resolved itself, and I started running again. The plan was to start road running (since I prefer to trail running) in preparation for the Great Race. The problem is that I actually don&amp;rsquo;t like wearing my road running Vibram FiveFingers shoes, my Bikila LS shoes. In fact, since my taste in footwear has become more and more minimalist over time, the Bikila LS shoes seem like a step totally in the wrong direction. I got them last year really only for the purpose of road racing, since the KSO blisters me and the KSO Trek is for the trails.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just to start running again, I began going out for 2-3 mile casual runs in my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/26/walking-and-running-in-invisible-shoes-a-review/&#34;&gt;Invisible Shoes&lt;/a&gt; that I&amp;rsquo;d been wearing all summer for walking, and sometimes for running. I enjoyed my short runs in these huaraches.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/great-race-2012/invisible-shoes-rolled.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Invisible Shoes rolled up&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Given that I was just getting back into running after such a long break, I never ran more than 3 miles during any of my runs leading up to the Great Race. And I never wore anything other than the Invisible Shoes. So that led me to the idea that since I wasn&amp;rsquo;t going to be able to achieve a goal of running super fast this year, I could set a &lt;em&gt;different goal&lt;/em&gt; for myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My new goal: &lt;em&gt;run the Great Race 10K in 4mm huaraches&lt;/em&gt;. More specifically, I wanted to see how my joints and muscles would hold up, as well as my feet and skin. Also, I&amp;rsquo;d never run fast in huaraches before, so this would also be an experiment in running fast in them. I had every intention of running pretty fast: I simply expected that I would not be able to run as fast as if I were running more protected shoes, because of many factors such as flopping soles and more pounding, resulting in my going more conservatively than if I had already experimented and knew what the limits were.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, originally I had planned to run a 5K race sometime in the huaraches; I had never planned to suddenly run a 10K in them without running a 5K first!! Also, I was going to run this 10K without having run more than 3 miles at a time in an entire month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;last-minute-panic-and-recovery&#34;&gt;Last minute panic and recovery&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Friday, I was coming down with a sore throat, and my boss said he and his son were both sick (they were both signed up for the Great Race this year). Now I was totally uncertain about whether I was going to run on Sunday. I tried to get healthy, and on Saturday, was feeling more stable, although a sore throat kept lingering, and picked up my race packet. Luckily, I was feeling great this morning, with no sign of a sore throat, so apparently my &amp;ldquo;placebos&amp;rdquo; worked (sleep, healthy food, various supplements). I canceled all my Saturday plans (such as going to a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/28/another-french-music-jam-also-announcing-cats-dance/&#34;&gt;French dance workshop&lt;/a&gt;) in order to rest up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other concern was the weather forecast. All week it seemed like it was going to rain sometime this morning. I&amp;rsquo;ve run in rain before, raced in rain before. I can do it. But the last time I ran in Invisible Shoes in the rain, I got into trouble. So now what? I simply decided I was going to deal with rain if it happened. Yet another variable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-race&#34;&gt;The race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;to-eat-or-not-to-eat&#34;&gt;To eat or not to eat?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One experiment I did today that I deem a big success: &lt;em&gt;I ate almost nothing before the race&lt;/em&gt;. I ate a bunch of almonds when I was leaving the house, but that was it. In the past, I always ate something more substantial before a race. Rationally, it does not make sense, but for some reason, I always felt that I should eat a mini-meal. This was completely irrational, a weird clinging behavior I engaged in: after all, when I casually go running in the morning, I do it before breakfast! So why should race day be any different? We human beings have enough fuel stored in our bodies. It&amp;rsquo;s true that when I go for a run of over, say, 8 miles, I get hungry, and like to either have a snack on me to eat, or have eaten right before going on the run, but when it comes to 5K and 10K races, clearly there is no need for me to eat before the race. Experience has shown that it only makes me feel sluggish. So from now on, &lt;em&gt;no more mini-meals before a race of 10K or shorter&lt;/em&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;shoes&#34;&gt;Shoes&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/great-race-2012/franklin-before.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin wearing Invisible Shoes and race number 1853&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/great-race-2012/feet-before.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin wearing Invisible Shoes&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As usual, I jogged a mile from home to the start line as my warmup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;beginning&#34;&gt;Beginning&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The temperature was in the low 50s F: ideal racing temperature, not too cold. Under 50, I would have worn a long-sleeve T-shirt instead of a short-sleeve one. As it was, since I anticipated rain, I did not wear my usual singlet but instead a standard short-sleeve T-shirt. It was not yet raining, thankfully!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some guy stepped on my right toes with his shoes as he wandered through the crowd. I was upset by this and hoped that my toes were OK. They were sore for a few minutes but then I forgot about them and was OK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within the first few minutes, I saw Don Slusser ahead of me; last year I had tracked him and then passed him at the end of the race. This year, he was obviously going much slower, thanks to his shot knees, so I passed him early on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I saw my boss standing on his street corner watching the race. I asked why he wasn&amp;rsquo;t running and he said he was too sick. It&amp;rsquo;s too bad he had to miss the race yet again, after missing it last year because of another commitment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My huaraches seemed to be working pretty well as I ran faster than I had ever run in them. I rather enjoyed being able to feel the ground, as though I were fully barefoot. At 4mm, running with these is pretty close to being barefoot, much closer than wearing Vibram FiveFingers shoes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wasn&amp;rsquo;t paying much attention to any glances or stares at my feet, or remarks people may have been making, although a few runners did directly ask me about my &amp;ldquo;flip flops&amp;rdquo;, with an attitude ranging from incredulity to amusement to admiration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;middle&#34;&gt;Middle&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Near halfway through the race, it started raining fairly steadily. I had to periodically wipe the water away from my eyes. Well, it was in the forecast. One thing I can say is that I was never in danger of overheating in this race! There have been instances of the Great Race in warm conditions under a sun, when even in a singlet I got very warm and had to dump water over my head: ha, today I got free water on my head constantly!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I started the race further back than I usually do, there were very few people running at exactly my pace. I was always either passing or being passed by people. This is one thing annoying about big races where people can cross the start mat at very different times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, at one point, a guy came to be in front of me who was running approximately my pace, so that I was almost a constant distance from him. On downhills I would tend to overtake him, but then he would come back. We would be mostly together for approximately the last two miles. At one point when I slowly passed him, I think I heard him say, &amp;ldquo;That&amp;rsquo;s obscene&amp;hellip; but in a good way!&amp;rdquo; I believe that comment was directed at me and my footwear, and I kind of took it as a compliment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;end&#34;&gt;End&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The water puddles were starting to get to me, as I had earlier feared. I did not feel confident about running any faster than I already was, given the road conditions and the way my huaraches were slipping around. And my toes were getting sore from the pounding. Normally, in the end of a race, I turn it on and try to use up the remaining energy I have, but today, I just did not feel confident in my footing. I continued going reasonably fast, but did not put in any finishing sprint at all. Even if I had wanted to, it would have been difficult, because of so many slower people in front of me. This is a direct consequence of my lining up at the start line far further back than I usually do: what happens is that slower people who started further up are in the way for the entirety of the race!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I did turn it on just enough to pass that guy I had been more or less with for two miles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;result&#34;&gt;Result&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My chip time was 48:23, not too bad given my footwear experimentation and lack of conditioning and failure to go all out in the final mile; last year&amp;rsquo;s time was 47:46. Next year, I would like to go under 47:00. I should be able to do that if I maintain a regular running regimen. 2006 was the last year that I went under 47:00.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;after-the-race&#34;&gt;After the race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got some water, was given two Smiley Cookies, and ate a bagel and a banana also. I hopped on the shuttle bus back to the start line (the ride took 30 minutes), then walked 25 minute (1.5 miles) back home in the cold. In the future, I don&amp;rsquo;t want to do this walk. I should park my car near the start line the night before, so that I can hop off the bus and drive home. It&amp;rsquo;s no fun to be walking so long in the cold when you&amp;rsquo;re tired and you&amp;rsquo;re not sure what the condition of your feet are, except that they hurt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are my feet after I got home:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/great-race-2012/feet-after.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin&amp;#39;s bare feet after race, at home&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It turns out that I got only one blister, and it was exactly where I got a blister last time I ran in the rain in the huaraches: between my first two toes. There was some roughing up of the callouses on the balls of my feet (from wearing the huaraches all summer), but otherwise, my feet were OK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After some more hours of recovery, I was feeling fine. No joint pain whatsoever, no muscle soreness whatsoever, none of that stuff. Even last year I had some stiffness when I got off the shuttle bus. My conclusion is that truly minimalist footwear trains me to land in such a way as to minimize problems to my body. No shin splints, no ankle soreness, no knee pain, no hip pain, no shot quads, no cramping calves, nothing. Just a blister, and toes and forefoot that were sore for a while but right now no longer are. It&amp;rsquo;s amazing what &lt;em&gt;no cushioning for the feet at all&lt;/em&gt; did to prevent the problems I used to face when running. I am so completely sold that I will look into running more races in huaraches, and in optimizing my lacing in order to prevent the flopping limitation and that one blister spot. I am consider going up to the 6mm sole from the 4mm sole, with the idea that 6mm would be more solid for racing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another thought: assuming a race with no rain or extreme cold or hot surfaces, I should run a race &lt;em&gt;barefoot&lt;/em&gt; sometime next year. I&amp;rsquo;ll think about this. I know people who have done this. Why not? Barefoot, one does not have to worry about blisters caused from laces, or sole flopping, or water slipping. One may have other worries instead, but knowing a course ahead of time can help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;photos&#34;&gt;Photos&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Official photos of me in action, including beating the guy I mentioned, are &lt;a href=&#34;http://orders.islandphoto.com/RACE/Proofs.aspx#26561404-00002-0026&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, but since they are copyrighted, I have not inserted them directly into my report here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The inaugural Liberty Mile: a review of Pittsburgh&#39;s first road mile race, a great community event</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/08/17/the-inaugural-liberty-mile-a-review-of-pittsburghs-first-road-mile-race/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Aug 2012 21:44:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/08/17/the-inaugural-liberty-mile-a-review-of-pittsburghs-first-road-mile-race/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/liberty-mile-2012.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin&amp;#39;s race number and Bikila LS shoes&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Tonight I was really excited to race in, and also watch, the inaugural &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.libertymile.org/&#34;&gt;GNC Live Well Liberty Mile&lt;/a&gt;, a road race that runs along Liberty Avenue in Pittsburgh, starting from the Strip District and ending downtown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s about time Pittsburgh had a road mile race! Pittsburgh already has the wonderful&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://rungreatrace.com/&#34;&gt;Great Race&lt;/a&gt;, which &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/25/blistered-but-blissful-in-the-burgh/&#34;&gt;I ran for my ninth time last year&lt;/a&gt; and will run for my tenth time this year (good think I pre-registered early, because today it &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburgh.cbslocal.com/2012/08/17/2012-great-race-officially-sold-out/&#34;&gt;already sold out!!&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pittsburghmarathon.com/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Marathon&lt;/a&gt;, which I&amp;rsquo;ve run once.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope this event is here to stay. Here&amp;rsquo;s my report on the event as both a runner and a spectator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-history-in-the-mile&#34;&gt;My history in the mile&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve run a mile race only twice before in my life, and that was on the track at Carnegie Mellon University. A decade ago, in June 2002, I ran in my first track mile, the Pittsylvania Mile on that track, and did it in 6:22. I could have run faster, but because of total inexperience, went out way too fast for the first quarter, doing it in 1:22, and paying the price in the other laps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following year, 2003, in probably my peak condition in my life, I improved, doing the Pittsylvania Mile in 6:10. I still went out too fast, in 1:26, had no sense of rhythm, slowed down a lot to try to compensate for going out too fast, then had too much energy at the end, which was wasted. Again, I had not trained for the mile distance at all, but happened to be in my peak condition anyway just because I was still conditioned from my intense training for the Pittsburgh Marathon that I had just done in May (my lifetime personal best in the 5K of 20:37 was achieved just two weeks after the Pittsburgh Marathon).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I never broke a 6-minute mile during my peak.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That was the last timed mile I ever ran, until tonight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;preparation&#34;&gt;Preparation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, I wasn&amp;rsquo;t prepared for the mile at all. Apart from not having run much because of a non-running injury to my left leg that happened a month ago (from which I have fully recovered), I have just come back from a week of unexpected travel and am still kind of recovering from that. And no speed work to speak of in the past month, other than a few random sprints (which I do for general physical conditioning when I don&amp;rsquo;t do much else).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had no idea what &amp;ldquo;mile pace&amp;rdquo; feels like. I just figured I would run a bit faster than 5K pace (which I always have a reasonable feel for).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hoped to finish somewhere near 6:30.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;dr-vonda-wright&#34;&gt;Dr. Vonda Wright&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://vondawright.com/images/stories/vonda-at-work.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Vonda Wright&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I bumped into &lt;a href=&#34;http://vondawright.com/&#34;&gt;Dr. Vonda Wright&lt;/a&gt; while heading toward the start line, and thanked her for her support of those of us who care about maintaining our health as we get older. I want to plug her great work in promoting lifetime fitness, especially for those over 40. She has written a book &lt;a href=&#34;http://vondawright.com/index.php?option=com_content&amp;amp;view=article&amp;amp;id=62&amp;amp;Itemid=83&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Fitness After 40&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; which is pretty good and has a lot of scientifically-backed tips on remaining strong and vital and even reversing what used to be considered &amp;ldquo;normal aging&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I heard about Dr. Wright from a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/01/20/cmu-fitness-challenge-keynote-lecture-by-vonda-wright-stay-strong-at-any-age/&#34;&gt;CMU &amp;ldquo;healthy campus week&amp;rdquo; talk she gave this January&lt;/a&gt;. Even though I had already known some of what she advocated, I was impressed that she summarized well the whole gamut of what we now know to be effective ways to increase strength and flexibility and avoid injury. Again, I recommend her books to anyone of any age who wants to be smart about diet and exercise and more than that, a whole philosophical approach to living in general.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-race-in-waves&#34;&gt;The race, in waves&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The race was held in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.libertymile.org/Race-Waves.asp&#34;&gt;waves separated by ten or twenty minutes&lt;/a&gt;. This is obviously necessary because of the variation in people&amp;rsquo;s speed. The slower, open waves were held first, and the elite racers were in the final waves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;early-waves&#34;&gt;Early waves&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I arrived to pick up my race number when the first wave was already in progress. There was a bit of confusion in the first two waves because a good number of people arrived late or were unclear about when to run, and therefore missed the first wave. Most of these seemed to be kids. By the way, it was great to see so many kids at the Liberty Mile. Running a 5K (3.1-mile) race can be daunting for a kid, but a single mile is surely a great introduction to many kids (and adults too!) to the joy of running. I think it is really great that the Liberty Mile is not just an elite race, but also a race anyone can participate in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;my-race-in-the-masters-wave&#34;&gt;My race, in the Masters wave&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Masters &amp;ldquo;Winning at 40+&amp;rdquo; wave was the first qualification-required wave.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ran in this serious, competitive wave, not one of the open waves, because I easily qualified to run in this wave, whose requirement was proof of ability to run an 8-minute mile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lining up, I saw a lot of really fit-looking people in this wave, many of whom were clearly well over 40. In any case, anyone who looked anywhere near my age (42) was obviously going to kick my butt all the way to the moon. There was no chance for an age-group prize for me today! No problem: as a non-elite racer, I don&amp;rsquo;t race for prizes, but just to do the best that I can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ended up running &lt;a href=&#34;http://runhigh.com/2012RESULTS/R081712AD.html&#34;&gt;6:38.8&lt;/a&gt;, good for 26th place out of 27 in my age group, ha! I was disappointed that I didn&amp;rsquo;t make 6:30 as I had originally hoped when I signed up a month ago, but that&amp;rsquo;s OK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the first quarter, I ran 1:29; oops, went out too fast yet again! &lt;strong&gt;I hereby pledge that before the next mile race I run, I will actually train and learn not to go out too fast.&lt;/strong&gt; There is no excuse for running three mile races going out too fast. I don&amp;rsquo;t go out too fast in 5K or longer distances, after all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the second and third quarters, 1:46 and 1:46 showed that I had gone out too fast. I did save something for the sprint finish, however, and did the final quarter in 1:38.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A serious and unexpected problem I had while running this race was that my mouth got very dry and I had trouble breathing as a result. It was pretty weird. I don&amp;rsquo;t exactly remember this in my mile races from a decade ago. I did hydrate considerably before the race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, of course, as I do in 5K races, I felt like puking during the final quarter, and my arms were getting tingly and losing sensation. It&amp;rsquo;s just what happens to me in the final push. I believe there is no way to avoid feeling like puking if I&amp;rsquo;m running as hard as I can, but I have a feeling that the problem with my arms has to do with my tightening up (rather than relaxing) and flailing around. I plan to try to fix that for my next races this month and next month; what is required, clearly, is disciplined speed work, which is something I have not done in years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;enjoying-being-a-spectator&#34;&gt;Enjoying being a spectator&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The really cool thing about a mile race held in waves is that you get to be a spectator for the remaining waves after you&amp;rsquo;re done. In a 5K race or longer, there aren&amp;rsquo;t any heats and you never get to be a spectator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was wowed watching the &amp;ldquo;Unstoppable&amp;rdquo; under-40 wave whose qualification time was running faster than 6:00. Watching good, fast running is a real pleasure to me, like watching skilled dancers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also a treat was getting to watch the female elite wave and male elite wave. These &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/27/why-i-do-not-watch-the-olympics-any-more/&#34;&gt;Olympic&lt;/a&gt;-caliber runners looked so elegant with their long, powerful strides.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-shoes&#34;&gt;My shoes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d been considering running a race soon wearing my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/26/walking-and-running-in-invisible-shoes-a-review/&#34;&gt;Invisible Shoes huaraches&lt;/a&gt;, but without testing them out with speed work, I&amp;rsquo;m not ready to go there yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I wore the shoes I&amp;rsquo;ve been &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/23/happiness-is-finishing-39th-of-43-men-in-a-race/&#34;&gt;road racing in for almost a full year now&lt;/a&gt;, the Vibram FiveFingers Bikila LS. They worked out just fine. I didn&amp;rsquo;t get blistered because it was cool and it was only a mile. Next month I&amp;rsquo;ll see whether I get blistered in the Great Race &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/25/blistered-but-blissful-in-the-burgh/&#34;&gt;the way I did last year&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;race-organization&#34;&gt;Race organization&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought the race was pretty well-organized, especially given that this was the first time such a race has been held in Pittsburgh. Thanks go to the sponsors, the timers, the announcers, the volunteers who handed out race numbers and stocked water and bagels at the finish line and handed out goodie bags and T-shirts, the police officers who closed the roads and lanes where necessary and directed traffic and kept Liberty Avenue clear, the spectators who cheered, the providers of the many port-a-johns near the start line, the &lt;a href=&#34;http://bringbackthemile.com/news/detail/Miller_and_Kampf_Win_GNC_Live_Well_Liberty_Mile&#34;&gt;elite runners who put on a display of amazing running&lt;/a&gt;. Everyone without question was helpful and friendly. The whole experience was just wonderful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The inaugural GNC Live Well Liberty Mile was a great event. I hope it is the beginning of a Pittsburgh tradition that, like the Great Race and the Pittsburgh Marathon, will continue for years and decades to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-08-09&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-08-09)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/08/09/getting-up-when-reality-punches-you-in-the-face-running-the-second-liberty-mile-in-pittsburgh/&#34;&gt;I ran the second Liberty Mile a year later.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Running My Ninth Pittsburgh Great Race 10K: Blistered but Blissful in the &#39;Burgh</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/09/25/blistered-but-blissful-in-the-burgh/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Sep 2011 15:28:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/09/25/blistered-but-blissful-in-the-burgh/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m temporarily using a walking stick right now, because of bad blisters I got on my right foot this morning. But I am very happy today, and it was a &lt;a href=&#34;http://rungreatrace.com/&#34;&gt;Great&lt;/a&gt; day in the &amp;lsquo;Burgh.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/franklin-finishing-great-race-10k-2011.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin finishing Great Race 10K (photo by Abby)&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/great-race-2011-official/0020.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin giving it all he has&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/great-race-2011-official/0093.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin crossing finish line&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/great-race-2011-official/0094.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin over finish line&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/great-race-2011-official/0072.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin stopping his watch&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have now run the Pittsburgh &lt;a href=&#34;http://rungreatrace.com/&#34;&gt;Great Race&lt;/a&gt; 10K nine times now, beginning in 2000: I have only missed 2003 (the year it was canceled), 2009, and 2010. I have run it in all kinds of conditions (both in terms of weather and my physical state). There is no other race I have run for so many years, so it is always special to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But beyond that, today&amp;rsquo;s race was special because Abby participated in it, for the first time. She did not run the 10K, but did run the 5K (and took the photo of me above nearing the finish line). She just started running in races with me this year, and I am very proud of her for getting into running! Having once been a non-runner, it gives me great pleasure to encourage others to take up this wonderful form of exercise.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/abby-before-great-race-5k-2011.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby in Oakland before Great Race 5K start&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Of course, right after catching my breath and finding Abby, my first instinct was to ask her, &amp;ldquo;Where are the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.eatnpark.com/smiley.asp&#34;&gt;Smiley Cookies&lt;/a&gt;?&amp;rdquo; I limped over to pick one up, even as sweat was still dripping down my face, and eagerly gobbled it!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/franklin-great-race-2011-smiley-cookie.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin with Smiley Cookie after race&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;tradition&#34;&gt;Tradition&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Great Race is a wonderful Pittsburgh tradition. It is not only thrilling to be on the Boulevard of the Allies heading downtown getting a fine view of our city (although the uphill during mile 5 of the race is admittedly tough), but the sight of so many people participating in this event is heartwarming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/great-race-2011-crowd.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/great-race-2011-crowd-2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-great-race-stats&#34;&gt;My Great Race stats&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was also very happy about my finish time. I had a plan to break 48:00 this year, and I succeeded handily (all times mentioned are &amp;ldquo;chip times&amp;rdquo;, not &amp;ldquo;gun times&amp;rdquo;). My time was, of course, not one of my fastest times in this race (my fastest time was 42:49 nine years ago), but it was faster than my time in 2008. The last three years of my life have been very tough for me physically, so I have enjoyed starting to get back into shape this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s my record in the Great Race 10K over the years:
&lt;table style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 15px&#34;&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;th style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px; font-size: 1.1em&#34;&gt;Year&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;th style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px; font-size: 1.1em&#34;&gt;Chip time&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;th style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px; font-size: 1.1em&#34;&gt;Comment&lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;2000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;53:53&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;First time ever ran more than 3 miles continuously at all!&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;2001&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;45:02&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;Lost weight, trained seriously.&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;2002&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;42:49&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;Trained really hard.&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;2003&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;(not held)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;2004&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;45:36&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;Very sick, but was preregistered, and didn&amp;rsquo;t want to break tradition.&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;2005&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;46:49&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;Was too busy to train.&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;2006&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;46:55&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;Again untrained. Slower and slower.&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;2007&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;47:11&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;Not trained at all; extreme pain halfway, but kept going.&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;2008&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;49:12&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;Not trained at all, left shin hurting, unmotivated.&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;2009&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;(did not run)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;Too untrained to even think of running.&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;2010&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;(did not run)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;Too untrained to even think of running.&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;2011&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;47:46&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;Lightly trained, but put in a genuine effort on race day.&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;details-of-the-race&#34;&gt;Details of the race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My splits (for each mile, then the final 0.22 mile) are below. I tried to run an even effort (till the final mile, when I simply tried to keep going hard despite the pain), accounting for the changes in elevation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;7:40.73&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;7:07.52&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;8:09.14&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;7:23.90&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;8:24.08&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;7:29.08&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1:31.03&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One trick I try to use in a race is to pick someone ahead of me who is running just a bit faster than what I feel I can hold, and see if I can slowly catch up (and maybe overtake eventually). In the Great Race, this is hard to do because there are so many runners, and people starting at different times, so there is always a lot of passing and slowing down going on, unlike in smaller races where things get spread out and you know people are basically running at the pace they can hold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have to work harder in these big races to maintain my own sense of pace. I do this by &amp;ldquo;feel&amp;rdquo;: having run in races from a mile up to the marathon, I know what a sustainable pace feels like. 5K pace gives me a burning, pukey sensation, for example, while half-marathon pace is not at all pukey. 10K pace is in between: uncomfortable but tolerable, till the final mile when I just do whatever I can without completely falling apart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;don-slusser&#34;&gt;Don Slusser&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it was after around two miles that I noticed ahead of me &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.newsandsentinel.com/page/content.detail/id/538234.html&#34;&gt;Don Slusser&lt;/a&gt;, a local legend in the running scene. OK, he is not at all what he used to be, and has had a lot of knee surgeries, but still, I felt it was an honor to be see him out there still running.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As long as Don was still ahead of me, he was going to be my target. He pulled away from me slightly over the next three miles, but was always in my sight. So in the final mile, I finally blasted past him. Then somehow he passed me at one point downtown, and that pushed me to pick up the pace again and finish ahead of him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After he finished, I went up to him and shook his hand. He probably has no idea who I am or why I respect him or how he helped provide focus for me in my own attempt to run as well as I could today, but what can I say, it was a spontaneous gesture on my part. I salute you, Don: you and your wife Tammy have done much for the Pittsburgh running community and I am grateful for that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-note-on-shoes&#34;&gt;A note on shoes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the second race in which I&amp;rsquo;ve run in my &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.vibramfivefingers.com/products/Five-Fingers-BikilaLS-Mens.htm&#34;&gt;Bikila LS&lt;/a&gt; shoes (the first race was &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/23/happiness-is-finishing-39th-of-43-men-in-a-race/&#34;&gt;three days ago&lt;/a&gt;). Unfortunately, these shoes tend to give me blisters if I run over three miles and fast. I&amp;rsquo;ve run a slow eight miles before without blisters, but going fast, and in warm weather, my feet sweat and chafing happens. These shoes are nice but have a ventilation problem. I have never had any problems with my &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.vibramfivefingers.com/products/Five-Fingers-KSO-Trek-Mens.htm&#34;&gt;KSO Trek&lt;/a&gt; shoes that I use for trail running and hiking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see in the photo above that Abby wore her &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.vibramfivefingers.com/products/five-fingers-komodo-sport-ls-mens.htm&#34;&gt;KomodoSport LS&lt;/a&gt; shoes in the race. Wearing &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.vibramfivefingers.com/&#34;&gt;Vibram FiveFingers&lt;/a&gt; shoes for walking, hiking, and running has really improved our lives. (More on that in a later blog post.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;photo-update-on-september-28-2011&#34;&gt;Photo update on September 28, 2011&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some official photos from Island Photography have appeared online. I have to confess that my original plan was to try to spot the cameras and try to look good for any photos of me that might be taken. Unfortunately, I was in such pain in the final mile of the race that I had tunnel vision and could not really perceive anything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve added some of these photos to the beginning of this blog post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2012-09-30&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-09-30)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following year, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/30/running-my-10th-great-race-10k-obscene-but-in-a-good-way/&#34;&gt;I ran in the Great Race again&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Happiness Is: Finishing 39th of 43 Men in a Race!</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/09/23/happiness-is-finishing-39th-of-43-men-in-a-race/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Sep 2011 19:31:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/09/23/happiness-is-finishing-39th-of-43-men-in-a-race/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, on a late, muggy afternoon, I ran in a race, and finished 39th of 43 men in the race. I ran as hard as I could, just as I do in every race: my goal is always to run fast and beat as many competitors as I can. I don&amp;rsquo;t run in a race for &amp;ldquo;fun&amp;rdquo; (in the conventional sense of the word): I race to know pain and to stretch my limits. (I save my &amp;ldquo;fun&amp;rdquo; running for when I&amp;rsquo;m not racing.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So why was I pretty happy, despite getting my butt totally kicked?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For amusement, here is an excerpt of the men&amp;rsquo;s individual results of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cmu.edu/athletics/recreation/intramurals/activities.html&#34;&gt;CMU intramural&lt;/a&gt; XC race yesterday (billed as 2 miles but the course was clearly shorter than that): &lt;ol start=&#34;38&#34;&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;13:17.3&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;13:27.7 (me)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;14:33.7&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;14:33.71&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;14:33.72&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;14:59.9&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, I was happy for a number of reasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For one thing, this is the first &amp;ldquo;cross-country&amp;rdquo; race I have done, so I was just plain excited to do something different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, my expectations were low. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ted.com/talks/barry_schwartz_on_the_paradox_of_choice.html&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Low expectations are the secret to happiness.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; I entered the race knowing there was a definite possibility that I would finish last. I knew many of the runners would be undergrads less than half my age, and a self-selected group too, a group that does not include the (sadly numerous) students I see around every day who take the bus down one or two blocks or take the elevator up one floor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I was one of those students once&lt;/em&gt;. I was not a runner as a child, or in high school, or in college, or even in graduate school. I was sickly as a child, and also I was raised to pay no attention to physical fitness and even to look down on those who were fit (I know, &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sour_grapes&#34;&gt;sour grapes&lt;/a&gt;). I started running only after I left graduate school and embarked on several radical life changes (including losing 30 pounds, altering my diet, and taking up competitive ballroom dancing). So in a way, taking advantage of the opportunity (as CMU staff) to take part in the CMU intramural cross-country race was a way to fill in a gap in my collection of novel and exciting lifetime experiences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can bet I&amp;rsquo;ll be running this race again next year, and with every intention of placing higher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2012-09-27&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-09-27)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/27/why-i-missed-the-cmu-intramural-xc-race-this-year/&#34;&gt;I ended up not running this race in 2012&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-note-on-shoes&#34;&gt;A note on shoes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ran yesterday&amp;rsquo;s race in my &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.vibramfivefingers.com/products/Five-Fingers-BikilaLS-Mens.htm&#34;&gt;Vibram FiveFingers Bikila LS shoes&lt;/a&gt;, the first time I&amp;rsquo;d worn this pair of shoes in a race. I will run the Great Race in these shoes also. (More later on this blog about &amp;ldquo;minimalist shoes&amp;rdquo; and how they saved my life.)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/my-bikila-ls.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin&amp;#39;s Vibram FiveFingers Bikila LS shoes&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;preview-for-sunday&#34;&gt;Preview for Sunday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Sunday I will be running the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rungreatrace.com/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Great Race 10K&lt;/a&gt;. This will be the ninth time I have run the race. Stay tuned for a race report on Sunday!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below is a photo of my running it for the first time, in 2000, as the second race I had ever done (and I had never run more than three miles continuously in my life at that time). It was quite an ordeal. The following year I ran the race better prepared, 8:51 faster.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/great-race-2000.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin nearing the finish of the Great Race in 2000&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2011-09-25&#34;&gt;(Update of 2011-09-25)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/25/blistered-but-blissful-in-the-burgh/&#34;&gt;Great Race 2011 report&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>