<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Irish Music on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/irish-music/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Irish Music on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/irish-music/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Dan Possumato and friends playing Irish, Scottish, French music</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/11/25/dan-possumato-and-friends-playing-irish-scottish-french-music/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Nov 2012 21:42:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/11/25/dan-possumato-and-friends-playing-irish-scottish-french-music/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/dan-possumato/flyer.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;World Kaleidoscope Flyer&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Abby and I checked out a musical performance at the Carnegie Library of Pittsburgh, main branch. They have a regular Sunday afternoon &amp;ldquo;World Kaleidoscope&amp;rdquo; series featuring world sounds from local musicians: two months ago I reported on some delightful &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/23/living-appalachian-music-of-southwestern-pennsylvania/&#34;&gt;local Appalachian music&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.carnegielibrary.org/events/details.cfm?event_id=69116&#34;&gt;Today&amp;rsquo;s performance&lt;/a&gt; was by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.danpossumato.com&#34;&gt;Dan Possumato&lt;/a&gt; and friends, featuring mostly Irish music, with Dan on button accordion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had a good time. Among the selections:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scottish music&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Irish jigs and reels&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Irish waltz &amp;ldquo;Planxty Irwin&amp;rdquo; that Abby and I danced to&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a French &lt;a href=&#34;http://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hanter-dro&#34;&gt;hanter dro&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/dan-possumato/back.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;View from back&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/dan-possumato/right.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;View from right&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/dan-possumato/dan-possumato.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Dan Possumato&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A delayed St. Patrick&#39;s Day party: playing tin whistle and alto recorder</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/03/30/a-delayed-st-patricks-day-party-playing-tin-whistle-and-alto-recorder/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Mar 2012 22:58:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/03/30/a-delayed-st-patricks-day-party-playing-tin-whistle-and-alto-recorder/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Since so many people couldn&amp;rsquo;t make it to &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/17/st-patricks-day-party-playing-tin-whistle-and-flute/&#34;&gt;Henry&amp;rsquo;s St. Patrick&amp;rsquo;s Day party&lt;/a&gt;, Henry threw another party two weeks later, a second St. Patrick&amp;rsquo;s Day party! Abby and I attended this one too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was another huge milestone for me, musically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;chess&#34;&gt;Chess&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Henry has been playing chess very well lately in tournaments. In fact, last weekend in the big-money &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.chesstour.com/pit12.htm&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Open&lt;/a&gt;, he actually &lt;a href=&#34;http://chesstournamentservices.com/cca/tag/pittsburgh-open-2012-standings/&#34;&gt;tied for first in his section, winning $630&lt;/a&gt;, with a record of four wins and one draw, his best tournament in his life!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He sent me his games from the Pittsburgh Open, which I carefully analyzed and sent back to him with my annotations, just before the party. This was the first time I&amp;rsquo;ve analyzed games in well over a year. Doing it again sent the thrill of chess back into me. I thought I was done with chess, but now I&amp;rsquo;m vicariously living tournament chess through Henry. And I very much enjoying analyzing chess games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;music-preparation&#34;&gt;Music preparation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have learned by now that &amp;ldquo;preparation&amp;rdquo; when it comes to jamming does not amount to figuring out a few pieces. It means bringing a bunch of stuff and then figuring out what people want to hear or play with you, and then basically sight reading on the fly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So an important part of my music practice nowadays is &lt;em&gt;sight reading&lt;/em&gt;. I keep a big pile of music that I use simply to sight read.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because I felt still unready to play flute at a standard I found sufficiently acceptable to believe that people could take real pleasure in my playing, I decided not to bring my flute this time. I brought my tin whistle and recorders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;tin-whistle&#34;&gt;Tin whistle&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For tin whistle, I brought some big compilations of Irish music from the Carnegie Library, both fast and slow. I especially like slow Irish airs, not only because they&amp;rsquo;re slower and therefore &amp;ldquo;easier&amp;rdquo; to play, but because they are actually &amp;ldquo;hard&amp;rdquo; to play, in that you really have to pour yourself into expression and emotion; it&amp;rsquo;s actually easier to play fast music because you can cover up by just playing a lot of notes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;alto-recorder&#34;&gt;Alto recorder&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also brought a collection of Telemann minuets arranged for alto recorder and keyboard that I got out of the library as well. I have recently been getting a lot &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/21/flute-update-celebrating-bachs-birthday/&#34;&gt;into Baroque music&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;at-the-party&#34;&gt;At the party&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;chess-1&#34;&gt;Chess&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that David, a guy Henry knew from the Pittsburgh Chess Club tournaments, came to the party, so we spent a bit of time going over some recent games of theirs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;music-jamming&#34;&gt;Music jamming&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I felt much more comfortable than at the last party, since I was getting to know everyone, and I had not been &amp;ldquo;punished&amp;rdquo; in any way for my fumbling performances, but actually encouraged to keep playing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did soloing on tin whistle with slow Irish airs, and also did impromptu fast jigs and reels with Henry and Vassily.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what I enjoyed most was going through minuets with Henry at the piano while I played alto recorder. This being Baroque music, there was ample space for ornamentation on both parts. I have been working on the art of Baroque ornamentation, and was excited to let myself free during the repeats of the minuets we read through. At one point, Henry complimented me on my ornamentation, and I silently beamed. It&amp;rsquo;s a continual process, learning the art of ornamentation, because although there are some rules and guidelines, a lot is, as they say, a matter of having &amp;ldquo;good taste&amp;rdquo;. You want to do something interesting, but not too much, and not too distorting of the original. It&amp;rsquo;s tricky finding the right personal balance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby brought her various tamburas and mandolin to play and show Vassily.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a great time again at another of Henry&amp;rsquo;s parties. Great food, great company, fun playing music and talking chess.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>St. Patrick&#39;s Day party: playing tin whistle and flute</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/03/17/st-patricks-day-party-playing-tin-whistle-and-flute/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 Mar 2012 22:41:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/03/17/st-patricks-day-party-playing-tin-whistle-and-flute/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/st-patricks-2012/henry-franklin.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Henry and Franklin&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/st-patricks-2012/henry-franklin-abby.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Henry and Franklin and Abby&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Abby and I went to &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/01/27/a-new-friends-very-musical-birthday-party-changed-my-life/&#34;&gt;Henry&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/a&gt; place for a St. Patrick&amp;rsquo;s Day party, for which &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/12/quitting-the-cmu-all-university-orchestra-one-of-the-hardest-decisions-in-my-life/&#34;&gt;I had promised to play some music&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Today was one of the happiest days in my entire life!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;music-preparation&#34;&gt;Music preparation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All week, of course, I&amp;rsquo;ve been practicing &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/12/quitting-the-cmu-all-university-orchestra-one-of-the-hardest-decisions-in-my-life/&#34;&gt;tin whistle&lt;/a&gt;, and also some flute as well, in preparation for this party.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, I bought a brand new tin whistle just yesterday at the local music store down the street from home, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.acousticmusicworks.com/&#34;&gt;Acoustic Music Works&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/clarke-sweetone.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;My new Clarke Sweetone tin whistle&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It was a cheap &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.clarketinwhistle.com/&#34;&gt;Clarke&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.clarketinwhistle.com/products/sweetone-tin-whistle.aspx&#34;&gt;Sweetone&lt;/a&gt;. I got this to replace the Feadóg tin whistle that &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/11/learning-another-instrument-the-tin-whistle/&#34;&gt;I used initially to learn&lt;/a&gt; but was badly out of tune.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had picked up from the library a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lemccullough.com/Music-WhistleDVD.html&#34;&gt;nice little tutorial&lt;/a&gt; on tin whistle and learned a few tunes and some basics of ornamentation:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.lemccullough.com/Music-WhistleDVD_files/DVD%20cover-front-sm-filtered.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Learn to Play Irish Tinwhistle&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Completely unlike the classical orchestra world, here, the tunes are very easy, but all the interest is in the personal solo expression and ornamentation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;at-the-party&#34;&gt;At the party&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were, of course, fewer guests than at Henry&amp;rsquo;s birthday party. That was good, because it meant it was easier to get to know some people better (whom we had met at the earlier party) and also some new people we hadn&amp;rsquo;t met before. Actually, since Abby and I arrived very early, we got to know Henry better and vice versa before other guests arrived.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/st-patricks-2012/abby-franklin-st-patricks.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby and Franklin in green&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;chess&#34;&gt;Chess&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s always chess at Henry&amp;rsquo;s parties, because the kids like to play, and some adults too. I didn&amp;rsquo;t play this time; last time I did, but it was very time-consuming (Abby had to drag me away so we could go home), and I wasn&amp;rsquo;t playing any music then!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/st-patricks-2012/chess.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Boys playing chess&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;music-jamming&#34;&gt;Music jamming&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, there was jamming, before and after dinner. One of the young guys, Vassily, was eager to play accordion, and played waltzes and stuff from memory, and he had also brought a tin whistle and book, having heard I was coming with a tin whistle. (But he didn&amp;rsquo;t actually end up playing his!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that Vassily is interested in a wide variety of music, including Balkan, so Abby got all excited about meeting someone new who into the music she likes. Abby brought her tambourine and joined in a bunch of the jamming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;dancing&#34;&gt;Dancing&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any time I hear someone on accordion playing a waltz or polka, I just have to dance with Abby!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/st-patricks-2012/abby-franklin.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby and Franklin dancing&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h4 id=&#34;tin-whistle&#34;&gt;Tin whistle&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d only had a couple of days to work on tin whistle playing, so I&amp;rsquo;d only prepared to play a couple of tunes. But after I quickly ran out, people wanted more. And Henry wanted to accompany me with accordion or piano. I figured, what the heck, I&amp;rsquo;ll sight read some of the stuff I hadn&amp;rsquo;t even looked at in the tutor book. So I did, Henry figured out chords quickly, I stumbled around with lots of &amp;ldquo;wrong notes&amp;rdquo;, and it was all nevertheless OK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, not all of my notes were actually &amp;ldquo;wrong&amp;rdquo;: they just weren&amp;rsquo;t what was printed, but as long as stuff goes with the harmonies, there is no real sense in which the notes are wrong! That&amp;rsquo;s what&amp;rsquo;s so liberating about playing Irish music. I&amp;rsquo;m not following some orchestra score where every dynamic, every flurry of fast notes is carefully notated and is supposed to be followed exactly. And nevertheless, this freedom does not mean pure chaos. You still have to be aware of the stylistic conventions, of the implied shapes of phrases that you want to maintain or transform in some consistent way, etc. I really feel that playing this kind of music makes one much more connected with the role of &amp;ldquo;composer&amp;rdquo;, being very actively engaged and making short-term and long-term decisions about where to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vassily and I did some random jamming where he tried to accompany me as I read through some Irish music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;flute&#34;&gt;Flute&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also played flute for the first time in my life for people outside the context of school band and the CMU All-University orchestra I had just quit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I chose to play an arrangement of &amp;ldquo;Londonderry Air&amp;rdquo; for flute and piano, from &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/20/much-progress-playing-flute/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;I Used to Play Flute&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; so Henry accompanied me. I was standing as I played. I was so &lt;em&gt;nervous&lt;/em&gt; that my leg shook like crazy and I thought I was going to fall. I should have played sitting down. It was a huge deal for me, working up the courage to try to play flute while feeling like I was still a rank beginner (I still have terrible breath support and tone). I knew I didn&amp;rsquo;t play well, but I&amp;rsquo;d gone out there and done my best. I was proud of myself for that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed continuing to get to know Henry and his other guests better, and feeling more and more comfortable about playing music with them and for them. I felt like I was really coming out of my shell, both socially and musically. This is only the beginning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2012-03-30&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-03-30)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out my report on &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/30/a-delayed-st-patricks-day-party-playing-tin-whistle-and-alto-recorder/&#34;&gt;the next Henry party Abby and I attended&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quitting the CMU All-University Orchestra: one of the hardest decisions in my life</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/03/12/quitting-the-cmu-all-university-orchestra-one-of-the-hardest-decisions-in-my-life/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Mar 2012 22:45:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/03/12/quitting-the-cmu-all-university-orchestra-one-of-the-hardest-decisions-in-my-life/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s the Monday after what would have been the regular Sunday evening CMU All-University Orchestra rehearsal, except that there was no rehearsal because of Spring Break.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surprise (or not)!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have decided to immediately &lt;em&gt;quit&lt;/em&gt; the CMU AUO that I had &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/02/01/joining-an-orchestra-learning-in-the-face-of-terror/&#34;&gt;just joined less than two months ago&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have already told everyone that I&amp;rsquo;m quitting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t like quitting. I don&amp;rsquo;t like being a quitter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what&amp;rsquo;s the story? And what next?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;orchestra-morale-problems&#34;&gt;Orchestra morale problems&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Five days ago, I reported on &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/07/flute-taking-a-break-while-clarifying-my-goals/&#34;&gt;problems in the orchestra&lt;/a&gt; and deciding that I would probably quit the orchestra after the spring term is over. The memories of that have lingered in my mind. And my relief yesterday at not having rehearsal was a real message to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2012-03-21&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-03-21)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maria just sent the mailing list (which I&amp;rsquo;m still on despite having quit the orchestra) an email saying, &amp;ldquo;It seems that over spring break we may have lost much of what we did in the first portion of the semester.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No kidding. As I had observed earlier, people clearly just weren&amp;rsquo;t taking practice seriously. They probably didn&amp;rsquo;t touch their instruments when they went on spring break. I&amp;rsquo;m so glad I quit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;personal-musical-goals&#34;&gt;Personal musical goals&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past couple of days while off the hook on orchestral practice, I had an opportunity to think about &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/10/flute-loving-it-again/&#34;&gt;what I actually love about music, and what role I want it to play in my life&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;a-chance-opportunity&#34;&gt;A chance opportunity&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that Abby and I have just been invited to a St. Patrick&amp;rsquo;s Day party by Henry, whose &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/01/27/a-new-friends-very-musical-birthday-party-changed-my-life/&#34;&gt;birthday party less than two months ago&lt;/a&gt; had so moved me musically (and right after I had joined the AUO). I was so eager to attend that I asked Henry whether I should bring a tin whistle and play some Irish music, and he said, sure! I had promised myself after his birthday party that if we were ever invited to a party by him, I would play music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;brute-reality&#34;&gt;Brute reality&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, I can no longer deny the reality: being in an orchestra is &lt;em&gt;completely contrary&lt;/em&gt; to the kind of musical life I actually enjoy and want. I need to play music of my choice, I want to improvise, I want to play in small groups. The task of mastering some difficult flute parts in a big orchestral work and being a tiny part of a performance, &lt;em&gt;does not appeal to me at all&lt;/em&gt;, even if I could do it well (which I currently cannot at all).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a concrete example: I could spend my time this week slogging away at AUO music practice, or I could be learning some tunes on tin whistle so that I can play them on Saturday at Henry&amp;rsquo;s party and have a blast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s no comparison, whether in the short term or in the long term.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But emotionally, it&amp;rsquo;s just tough to quit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-did-i-really-ever-hope-to-get-out-of-orchestra&#34;&gt;What did I really ever hope to get out of orchestra?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think part of me hoped that somehow, being in an orchestra was a standard rite of passage that a &amp;ldquo;serious&amp;rdquo; musician should do. When I was a kid, I was kind of envious that classmates joined the school orchestra, while I remained out of music entirely. My younger sister played violin in various orchestras in middle school and in high school and college.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But now it occurs to me that not much of what I could get out of orchestra would help me with my real musical goals anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-art-of-quitting&#34;&gt;The art of quitting&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a policy of never just &lt;em&gt;quitting&lt;/em&gt; something, but &lt;em&gt;replacing&lt;/em&gt; the void instead. &lt;em&gt;Quitting&lt;/em&gt; is negative. &lt;em&gt;Replacing&lt;/em&gt; is positive. In my case, quitting orchestra frees up a considerable amount of time to work toward my real musical goals. Instead of fruitlessly working on difficult flute parts that are currently beyond my capabilities, and beyond my interests, I can focus on gradually improving at the music I do want to play, and building the technique necessary, without arbitrary deadlines like some big concert.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;resources&#34;&gt;Resources&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the United States, we are constantly bombarded with messages in the media and general culture not to be a &amp;ldquo;quitter&amp;rdquo;. And I got that a lot from my parents (who came from Taiwan) when I was a kid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My current point of view: &lt;em&gt;not learning to be an effective quitter was the single worst mistake of my first decades in life&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some articles that really resonated with me about the benefits of quitting correctly:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.projecthappilyeverafter.com/2009/03/sometimes-its-better-to-be-a-quitter/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Sometimes it&amp;rsquo;s better to be a quitter&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cormackcarr.com/2009/12/05/how-to-be-a-quitter/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;How to be a quitter&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s never easy for me to quit something. Part of me always feels like I failed, wasn&amp;rsquo;t good enough, wasn&amp;rsquo;t courageous enough, or something like that. Maybe sometimes that is actually true. But other times, it clearly is not. All signs point to quitting orchestra as the best thing I can do now for my flute playing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-is-your-own-relationship-to-quitting&#34;&gt;What is your own relationship to quitting?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is your gut reaction when hearing about someone quitting (like me just now), or when considering quitting something yourself? Is your &lt;em&gt;gut reaction&lt;/em&gt; one of disdain and shame, or of liberation? Is this a result of your upbringing, or the nature of your relationships with peers? Is it a deliberate rational philosophical position? Or is primarily emotional, based on either moral sentiment or ego?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When was the last time you quit and felt &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt; about it? When was the last time you quit and felt &lt;em&gt;bad&lt;/em&gt; about it? When was the last time you quit and &lt;em&gt;at the time&lt;/em&gt; felt one way, but later felt you had made the wrong decision?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>