<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Learning on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/learning/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Learning on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/learning/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Why I stopped saying something is easy or something is hard</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/12/23/why-i-stopped-saying-something-is-easy-or-something-is-hard/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2014 22:19:38 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/12/23/why-i-stopped-saying-something-is-easy-or-something-is-hard/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently, I decided to monitor how I talk about learning some subject or topic, because of observing both of myself and other people what our reactions can be if I say that something is &amp;ldquo;easy&amp;rdquo; or something is &amp;ldquo;hard&amp;rdquo;. I&amp;rsquo;ve come to the conclusion that there are serious drawbacks to saying that something is &amp;ldquo;easy&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;hard&amp;rdquo;, and an entirely different vocabulary should be used in helping a learner. I haven&amp;rsquo;t figured out exactly what that vocabulary is, but I&amp;rsquo;ve seen too many times some really disastrous results from overusing labels such as &amp;ldquo;easy&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;hard&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-s-easy-anyway&#34;&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;easy&amp;rdquo; anyway?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I never learned to drive stick shift in my youth. Therefore, when in recent years Abby tried to teach me to, I had a lot of trouble. She became impatient with me and started using phrases like &amp;ldquo;but it&amp;rsquo;s easy, you just do this&amp;rdquo;. These phrases were delivered in a way that sounded frustrated, and meanwhile, I &lt;em&gt;knew&lt;/em&gt; it wasn&amp;rsquo;t &amp;ldquo;easy&amp;rdquo;, else I would be getting it. I finally gave up, giving the excuse that it wasn&amp;rsquo;t worth the trouble to go through hell to get this skill working, since my own car is an automatic anyway and I would have very little opportunity or reason to drive stick shift. But the real point is that learning became very stressful for me as I had to fight not only my multitasking physical clumsiness, but also this idea that I wasn&amp;rsquo;t able to do something &amp;ldquo;easy&amp;rdquo;. Part of me knew that &lt;em&gt;rationally&lt;/em&gt;, I shouldn&amp;rsquo;t care about labels, but part of me also kept on saying silently, &amp;ldquo;You have no idea how hard this is for me. This is how you started learning to drive. You have no idea what I&amp;rsquo;m going through.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remember many other situations through my life where I was struggling with something supposedly &amp;ldquo;easy&amp;rdquo; and became very discouraged. In my youth, I may not have had quite as much metacognition to recognize that I shouldn&amp;rsquo;t necessarily give up (and I didn&amp;rsquo;t always give up), so it was particularly damaging when made fun of for not immediately grasping something &amp;ldquo;easy&amp;rdquo;, whether hitting a ball with a bat or racket, speaking English fluently, or using perfect grammar in my writing. In some cases, where I persevered, I not only &amp;ldquo;caught up&amp;rdquo; (there&amp;rsquo;s always some sense of &amp;ldquo;comparison&amp;rdquo; when someone uses the word &amp;ldquo;easy&amp;rdquo;), but excelled. In other cases, I just gave up, for decades (basically, anything athletic, I gave up before I finished elementary school), the shame was so great at being crappy at something &amp;ldquo;easy&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was even a perverse overreaction that sometimes kicked in. If I couldn&amp;rsquo;t do something &amp;ldquo;easy&amp;rdquo; (like draw in art class), I did the &amp;ldquo;sour grapes&amp;rdquo; thing and declared the subject stupid and not worth my time. I turned around and used &amp;ldquo;easy&amp;rdquo; as an excuse to make fun of those who could do it. And that leads to the dual problem of saying something is &amp;ldquo;hard&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-s-hard&#34;&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;hard&amp;rdquo;?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A harmful effect of the &amp;ldquo;easy&amp;rdquo;/&amp;ldquo;hard&amp;rdquo; classification is that it encourages us to play stupid status games in which nobody wins and everyone is hurt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s an example: it turned out that growing up, I found math &amp;ldquo;easy&amp;rdquo;. As a result, math became a convenient way for me to stay lazy about my perseverance and will to improve. I considered math, which was considered by many to be &amp;ldquo;hard&amp;rdquo;, as a way for me to impress and get approval (from those who thought math was &amp;ldquo;hard&amp;rdquo;). So I didn&amp;rsquo;t work very hard at math. Meanwhile, I just &amp;ldquo;gave up&amp;rdquo; on art and gym classes. I didn&amp;rsquo;t even try. All this because I got the idea that I was only punished for failing at stuff that was &amp;ldquo;easy&amp;rdquo; but rewarded for doing well at what was &amp;ldquo;hard&amp;rdquo;. I gravitated toward all kinds of &amp;ldquo;hard&amp;rdquo; academic subjects, for the sole purpose of boosting my self-esteem. This was a big mistake in the long run. Note that these subjects were not necessarily the ones that I was passionate about, or even truly talented at. They were they ones that somehow presented themselves as the &amp;ldquo;biggest prizes&amp;rdquo; and so I either secretly underworked at something I found easy or I put an inordinate amount of work into something &amp;ldquo;hard&amp;rdquo; for the wrong reasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, I saw my peers give up on all kinds of pursuits when by middle school it became apparent that some subjects were getting &amp;ldquo;harder&amp;rdquo; than others for them. This was sad. Often there was no rhyme or reason to what seemed &amp;ldquo;hard&amp;rdquo; or not: bad luck with a single terrible teacher in some random subject, for example, had massive impacts on the life paths of many of us. Whether it was a music class or one particular favored sport or game, I saw discouragement and disillusionment everywhere among everyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So marking something as &amp;ldquo;hard&amp;rdquo; not only discourages some people, but encourages others to play the game of racking up points solely by focusing on excelling at the &amp;ldquo;hard&amp;rdquo; for the sake of competition. This is such a waste.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;solution&#34;&gt;Solution?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Years of experience in learning many things I once thought were too hard for me have convinced me that every learner is different, and needs different motivations, contexts, kinds of help in order to achieve personal goals. In particular, not everyone is &amp;ldquo;ready&amp;rdquo; at any given time for something yet. And learning may come in unexpected spurts, sometimes sudden insight that comes after having been given enough encouragement to persist for a while even while struggling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not saying that learners cannot be irresponsible and lazy (I certainly sometimes am), but teachers should be aware that calling things &amp;ldquo;easy&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;hard&amp;rdquo; as a way to shame or encourage may well completely backfire, and there have to be better ways to concretely help learners make incremental progress at their own pace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Think about your own learning and teaching experiences. Do you remember particularly negative or positive ones? How many involved some kind of &amp;ldquo;easy&amp;rdquo;/&amp;ldquo;hard&amp;rdquo; talk that caused demotivation? Or are you one who thrives on such labels, using them as a challenge?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thoughts on giving up an old project to make room for the new</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/12/15/thoughts-on-giving-up-an-old-project-to-make-room-for-the-new/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2014 20:10:34 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/12/15/thoughts-on-giving-up-an-old-project-to-make-room-for-the-new/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Today I made a difficult decision to give up doing something that I have enjoyed for well &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/09/12/my-first-post-on-the-chess-improver-the-value-of-thematic-complete-games-against-a-weaker-opponent/&#34;&gt;over a year now&lt;/a&gt;: writing a &lt;a href=&#34;http://chessimprover.com/category/franklin-chen/&#34;&gt;weekly chess column&lt;/a&gt; at &lt;a href=&#34;http://chessimprover.com/&#34;&gt;The Chess Improver&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;writing&#34;&gt;Writing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s been a major commitment coming up with something to write about every week for such a long time. There have been times when I was overflowing with ideas; there have been times when I struggled to come up with something to write about that I could stand behind. Sometimes I have published something I felt was particularly good; sometimes I felt uninspired; sometimes I just dashed something out of uneven quality. But through it all, I learned a lot from my attempt to convey &lt;em&gt;something specific and concrete&lt;/em&gt; that I hoped readers would enjoy and ideally even use to their practical advantage in their own chess play. The best way to verify whether you actually understand something is to write about it! I definitely had to do homework in many cases in order to make sure I really understood what I was talking about, in order to be as accurate and correct as I could.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I even kept on writing about chess during very dry spells in my writing in general, when I wasn&amp;rsquo;t writing anything for my other two blogs, this personal blog and my &lt;a href=&#34;http://ConscientiousProgrammer.com/&#34;&gt;programming blog&lt;/a&gt;. I admit to being rather embarrassed that during these dry spells, I kept on posting links to my chess blog from this blog. I will never again waste readers&amp;rsquo; time by posting links from one blog to another except when relevant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-law-of-conservation-of-time-and-energy&#34;&gt;The law of conservation of time and energy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our lives, we can&amp;rsquo;t do it all. For 2015, recent circumstances have led me to commit to a bunch of personal projects that have nothing to do with chess, so I knew, as 2014 comes to a close, that I would have to give up something &lt;em&gt;old&lt;/em&gt; in order to free up time and energy for the &lt;em&gt;new&lt;/em&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;m going to writing up a retrospective on 2014 before 2015 comes, in order to plan out how to go about 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;it-s-not-really-giving-up&#34;&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s not really giving up&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I lied in my title. I&amp;rsquo;m not really &amp;ldquo;giving up&amp;rdquo; chess writing; I&amp;rsquo;m just putting it aside. If a time comes when I feel it is worthwhile to do it again, I may well return. However, for now, I&amp;rsquo;m shutting it down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All things come to an end, or at least, an adjournment. I look forward to tackling new challenges as I free myself from the responsibility of writing a weekly chess column.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How do you rearrange your life when you decide to start new demanding projects? Do you try to squeeze them in and cut out &amp;ldquo;non-essentials&amp;rdquo; or optimize your efficiency? Or do you decide that you have to cut out significant old projects? Or do you feel that you are already stretched to the limit with essentials (such as young children) and cannot possibly take on anything new?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My first post on The Chess Improver: The Value of Thematic Complete Games Against a Weaker Opponent</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/09/12/my-first-post-on-the-chess-improver-the-value-of-thematic-complete-games-against-a-weaker-opponent/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Sep 2013 05:04:25 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/09/12/my-first-post-on-the-chess-improver-the-value-of-thematic-complete-games-against-a-weaker-opponent/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Today is my debut as a contributor to the blog &lt;a href=&#34;http://chessimprover.com/&#34;&gt;The Chess Improver&lt;/a&gt;, thanks to the invitation of GM Nigel Davies to join in the sharing of ideas and observations about improving at chess (and even more generally, other endeavors as well). I will be regularly writing about chess there instead of here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that although the blog does not support comments, Nigel Davies hosts lively discussions about each blog post on Facebook through &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/nigel.davies1&#34;&gt;his account&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;both-participant-and-observer&#34;&gt;Both participant and observer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since it turns out that I have just finished two of the six rounds in the current Pittsburgh Chess Club Tuesday night tournament, the 15th Fred Sorensen Memorial, I began my debut by using my first round game as material for a post to beginn a discussion about &lt;a href=&#34;http://chessimprover.com/the-value-of-thematic-complete-games-against-a-weaker-opponent/&#34;&gt;learning from imperfectly played games that, however, illustrate chess themes well&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/15th-fred-sorensen-memorial/round-1.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Round 1&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/15th-fred-sorensen-memorial/round-1-in-progress.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Round 1 in progress&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I will have a post up next week about my second round game of this week, which was quite interesting. I will not always be writing about my own games on the blog, of course. They just happen to be, right now, a timely source of relevant material, since I am in the middle of a tournament.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;previous-chess-writings&#34;&gt;Previous chess writings&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I have not played tournament chess since &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/02/20/pittsburgh-chess-club-championship-2013-round-6-winning-as-black-like-a-madman/&#34;&gt;winning the 2013 Pittsburgh Chess Club Championship in February&lt;/a&gt;, if you have discovered this blog only recently, you may be interested in exploring my previous &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/chess/&#34;&gt;chess writings&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I changed how I live after reading Joshua Foer&#39;s &#34;Moonwalking with Einstein&#34;</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/12/24/i-changed-how-i-live-after-reading-joshua-foers-moonwalking-with-einstein/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Dec 2012 20:20:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/12/24/i-changed-how-i-live-after-reading-joshua-foers-moonwalking-with-einstein/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.strangehistory.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/02/memory.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Memory&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Recently I heard about the journalist &lt;a href=&#34;http://joshuafoer.com/&#34;&gt;Joshua Foer&lt;/a&gt; who embarked on a remarkable journey in which he ended up covering a story about memory and then actually training his own and in the process becoming the United States Memory champion. I watched his hilarious and inspiring &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ted.com/talks/joshua_foer_feats_of_memory_anyone_can_do.html&#34;&gt;TED talk&lt;/a&gt; and ended up reading his book &lt;a href=&#34;http://joshuafoer.com/moonwalking-with-einstein/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Moonwalking with Einstein: The Art and Science of Remembering Everything&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After reading this book, I made a firm decision to &lt;em&gt;immediately change my life&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A confession: I have all my life, since childhood, struggled with what I considered a bad memory (compared to &amp;ldquo;normal&amp;rdquo;, as in my peers).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;examples-of-my-concern-about-my-memory&#34;&gt;Examples of my concern about my memory&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I took a quick look at my blog posts in the past year, to see where I might have bemoaned my bad memory, and here are a few examples:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I complained about not remembering &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/18/i-want-to-sing/&#34;&gt;song lyrics&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I noted that not remembering &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/10/flute-loving-it-again/&#34;&gt;dance steps and choreography&lt;/a&gt; forced me to fall back on improvisation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I mentioned &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/14/for-real-geeks-today-is-not-pi-day-but-half-tau-day/&#34;&gt;memorizing fifty digits of pi&lt;/a&gt;, but did not say how grueling a task it was and how ashamed I was that I retained very little and never wanted to do it again.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I noted how I was &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/04/21/my-first-time-in-a-public-music-jam-intense-fun-with-chris-norman-and-david-greenberg/&#34;&gt;forced into improvisation in music because of memory problems&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I told a story of &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/06/08/heinz-hall-memories-at-the-pittsburgh-symphony-being-shocked-out-of-my-mind-upon-experiencing-prokofievs-second-piano-concerto-for-the-first-time/&#34;&gt;misremembering an event in the past and then reconstructing what really happened&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;major-life-decisions-i-made-based-on-my-belief-i-had-a-bad-memory&#34;&gt;Major life decisions I made based on my belief I had a bad memory&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some things that I&amp;rsquo;ve told almost nobody in my life before, but now feel I should speak out about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;school&#34;&gt;School&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I shaped my entire experience in school around trying to avoid having to rely on my memory. History and other subjects terrified me. I was so conscious about my problems that in middle school, during one of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rif.org/&#34;&gt;Reading is Fundamental&lt;/a&gt; free book distributions, I greedily picked up &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.harrylorayne.com/&#34;&gt;Harry Lorayne&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;How to Develop a Super Power Memory&amp;rdquo;. Unfortunately, after looking at it, I was discouraged by its odd ideas and just didn&amp;rsquo;t really give any of them a try at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Biology terrified me, to the point that in my first year of high school, &lt;em&gt;I chose not to take any science course at all&lt;/em&gt; because biology would have been the first course for me to take. Later, I did take biology, delayed from most of my college-bound peers, in the tenth grade, and survived it (but have almost no memory of what I &amp;ldquo;learned&amp;rdquo;). In my senior year of high school, I took Advanced Placement biology, which was a total nightmare of memorization, solely for the purpose of not ever having to take biology again when going to college (and in fact, I did get credit for it and therefore succeeded in my goal). Note: since childhood, I was actually very fascinated by biology, so it was with sadness that I decided I had to avoid further study in biology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to avoidance, my fear of memorization also pushed me into certain directions based primarily on the lack of need for memorization: by the end of high school, I had discovered that math and physics were great for me because they did not require much memorization. Everything was based primarily on basic principles that, if you learned, you could build on top of using logical reasoning rather than memorization. Logic was the connective that kept things together in my mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;language-learning&#34;&gt;Language learning&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Learning foreign languages has always been fascinating to me, ever since as a side effect of studying for spelling bees in elementary school and middle school, I found a trick to help deal with my memory problems: looking up the etymologies of words in the dictionary enabled me to see enough logical and historical connections between words to be able to spell pretty well. But when it came to remembering and using the meanings of words as I learned French, for example, I was lost. I loved learning grammar because it was about figuring out the logical patterns, but hated learning vocabulary. Unfortunately, without a sufficient working vocabulary, my facility in languages was limited in oral communication, and even reading texts was painful, requiring constant dictionary lookup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So even though I&amp;rsquo;ve actually taken entire courses in French, German, Italian, and Spanish, and taught myself Latin, I&amp;rsquo;ve always felt that I somehow wasted my time, because I mostly remember grammar and pronunciation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-new-motivation&#34;&gt;My new motivation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was excited to watch Joshua Foer&amp;rsquo;s talk and read his book, because if an average guy can become the national memory champion through proven techniques, then a below-average guy like me should be able to get to average and even beyond. Given that I believe that I am capable of improving at many things I&amp;rsquo;m not so good at, why have I spent so much of my life not believing that about my memory? I created this self-limiting myth that I now intend to shatter. 2013 will be the year when I make massive improvements to my memory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-book&#34;&gt;The book&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I loved Joshua Foer&amp;rsquo;s book. He is not only a very good storyteller, taking the reader deep into the strange world of memory championships, but he also explains the time-honored techniques that every memory champion uses and that he used, and describes the scientific research on memory. There is no trickery involved, just changing your attitude and putting in the work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book is not just a good story and a how-to manual, though. It is really a &lt;em&gt;philosophical&lt;/em&gt; exploration of what it means to be human, and what we have lost since the ancient times when memory was not only useful but critical, because we didn&amp;rsquo;t have the technological aids that we have now. It made me think about how I should balance time-saving technology and old-fashioned ways of dealing with life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-principle-behind-memory-techniques&#34;&gt;The principle behind memory techniques&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main idea behind remembering well is that we have to encode memories in such a way that they are truly concrete and vivid, because that&amp;rsquo;s what we humans remember.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &amp;ldquo;memory palace&amp;rdquo; is a well-known technique (that I remembered from Harry Lorayne&amp;rsquo;s book in my childhood, but never implemented). It involves creating a space in your mind that you already know, and then put things you want to remember into that space by associating them with images located in specific places in the space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foer discussed one of the open secrets of how to come up with vivid images to remember: &amp;ldquo;When forming images, it helps to have a dirty mind&amp;rdquo;. He quotes ancient handbooks on memory that advise using images of beautiful women, or images of &amp;ldquo;singular ugliness&amp;rdquo;, modified through disfigurement or comic effects. This can get awkward. When he was training to memorize a deck of cards, he writes, &amp;ldquo;it invariably meant inserting family members into scenes so raunchy I feared I was upgrading my memory at the expense of tormenting my subconscious. The indecent acts my own grandmother has had to commit in the service of my remembering the eight of hearts are truly unspeakable (if not, as I might have previously guessed, unimaginable)&amp;rdquo;. Also, his coach Ed said, &amp;ldquo;I eventually had to excise my mother from my deck&amp;hellip; I recommend you do the same&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-plans-for-memory-improvement&#34;&gt;My plans for memory improvement&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m starting small with my memory improvement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;languages&#34;&gt;Languages&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a &amp;ldquo;test&amp;rdquo;, I&amp;rsquo;ve gotten back into language learning/review, using &lt;a href=&#34;http://duolingo.com/&#34;&gt;Duolingo&lt;/a&gt; (about which I&amp;rsquo;ll write much more later), focusing on Spanish, which I took three semesters of a decade ago, but have been embarrassed to feel incompetent in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past, I had no reliable way to remember new words as I learn them. Now, I paused for 5-10 seconds, maybe even longer if I need to (I expect to become more quick and fluid with experience), to create a suitable image.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You don&amp;rsquo;t really want to know what kinds of images I create for my memory. I think one of the problems I always had with my memory was being ashamed of &amp;ldquo;inappropriate&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;illogical&amp;rdquo; imagery. I always wanted to remember through logical association. Now, I have given myself permission to be as raunchy, disgusting, sarcastic, or bizarre as I need, and just accept that. So in some sense, embracing memory improvement, for me, involves self-acceptance. I created shocking images to remember the Spanish words for &amp;ldquo;cranberry&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;box&amp;rdquo;, for example, but they do the job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve already seen huge improvements in my learning of new words, which I do every day. I wish I had used this technique years, decades ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My goal: getting the vocabulary down will be a big part of becoming actually functional in Spanish. I would like to achieve near-native conversational Spanish ability in a year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;numbers&#34;&gt;Numbers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have always been bad at remembering numbers. I intend to set up a practice for using the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mnemonic_major_system&#34;&gt;Major System&lt;/a&gt; in order to get into remembering numbers better. It&amp;rsquo;s embarrassing and potentially actually dangerous when I don&amp;rsquo;t have my phone or computer on me and I am supposed to remember a phone number, for example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My goal: remember all numbers that should be important in my life. (Sorry, pi, you are not important.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;others&#34;&gt;Others&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I think about it, there is so much that I could gain from remembering all kinds of things better. I will explore my ideas later, after first mastering the fundamentals and gaining confidence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a real sense, we are what we remember. If we don&amp;rsquo;t remember, then what was the point? Joshua Foer&amp;rsquo;s experience and his book have inspired me to move forward in recapturing one of the ancient skills and delights, that of remembering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How do you feel about your memory? Is it something you care about improving? Or is our technological outsourcing of our memory perfectly fine?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CreativeMornings/Pittsburgh, the first session: Nina Barbuto on &#34;Making Learning a Party&#34;</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/12/14/creativemornings-pittsburgh-the-first-session-nina-barbuto/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Dec 2012 23:40:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/12/14/creativemornings-pittsburgh-the-first-session-nina-barbuto/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This morning, out of curiosity, Abby and I &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.eventbrite.com/e/creativemorningspittsburgh-with-nina-barbuto-tickets-4458258772&#34;&gt;attended&lt;/a&gt; the inaugural &lt;a href=&#34;http://creativemornings.com/&#34;&gt;CreativeMornings&lt;/a&gt; talk of the new &lt;a href=&#34;http://creativemornings.com/cities/pgh&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh branch&lt;/a&gt;. Many thanks to Kate Stoltzfus for bringing this concept to Pittsburgh!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nina Barbuto spoke on &lt;a href=&#34;http://creativemornings.com/talks/nina-barbuto/1&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Making Learning a Party&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/creativemorningspittsburgh/8286843706&#34; title=&#34;Creative Mornings - Pittsburgh - Dec 14th 2012-13 by CreativeMornings Pittsburgh, on Flickr&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8204/8286843706_8d9b777c20.jpg&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; height=&#34;334&#34; alt=&#34;Creative Mornings - Pittsburgh - Dec 14th 2012-13&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nina Barbuto is someone I&amp;rsquo;ve encountered in the past, at &lt;a href=&#34;http://assemblepgh.org/&#34;&gt;Assemble&lt;/a&gt;, a Pittsburgh &amp;ldquo;community space for arts and technology&amp;rdquo;; I was there for a Pittsburgh Geek Out Day meeting a year ago (August 10, 2011). She is very active in Pittsburgh in promoting hands-on learning opportunities, especially for children.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She discussed how she likes to learn, and contrasted that with her experiences in school (she is an architect). One theme that came up was the idea that there are better ways to learn than the &amp;ldquo;factory model&amp;rdquo; of the 19th century. Another was that &lt;em&gt;art&lt;/em&gt; is important and should be part of &amp;ldquo;21st century&amp;rdquo; education, expanding &amp;ldquo;STEM&amp;rdquo; to &amp;ldquo;STEAM&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/creativemorningspittsburgh/8285786597&#34; title=&#34;Creative Mornings - Pittsburgh - Dec 14th 2012-31 by CreativeMornings Pittsburgh, on Flickr&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8065/8285786597_2d79bb47ca.jpg&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; height=&#34;334&#34; alt=&#34;Creative Mornings - Pittsburgh - Dec 14th 2012-31&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found her advocacy and description of her various local projects inspiring, and I myself think there are better environments for learning than standard schooling (I hated much of school myself), but I think the &amp;ldquo;party&amp;rdquo; theme of learning being &amp;ldquo;fun&amp;rdquo; may be too loose for serious learning. She mentioned how some of the classes offered to disadvantaged kids involved some coming and going, but without sustained participation. I think the problem of promoting learning, especially deep learning, is a difficult one. Getting someone in the door to do something at all, in the name of fun, may be useful, but I worry about how to build on that to encourage deep learning, which doesn&amp;rsquo;t have to be dreary, but may not always be fun, and certainly always involves repeatedly facing challenges, with intensive mentoring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, it was good to hear about what she has been doing and what her vision is, and the large audience seems to indicate that there are a lot of people in town who care enough to think about these issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;video-of-the-talk&#34;&gt;Video of the talk&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/EZY5YdP4csQ&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s great that Pittsburgh now has a CreativeMornings, and Nina Barbuto kicked off the premiere of this lecture series with a thoughtful presentation. I look forward to other presentations in the future. Many thanks to the sponsors, including the location host, the Andy Warhol Museum (which I entered for the first time ever, actually).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Round 5 of Pittsburgh Chess Club Tournament: On Benoni &#34;Emasculation&#34; and Learning</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/10/02/round-4-of-pittsburgh-chess-club-tournament-on-benoni-emasculation-and-learning/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Oct 2012 21:35:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/10/02/round-4-of-pittsburgh-chess-club-tournament-on-benoni-emasculation-and-learning/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/mirra-chen-2012-10-02_files/diag3FECB4B6781E764C.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;White in reverse Benoni being crushed&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Tonight was the fifth (and penultimate) round of the current six-round Tuesday night tournament at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburghcc.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Chess Club&lt;/a&gt;, the 14th Fred Sorensen Memorial. I last reported on the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/19/round-3-of-pittsburgh-chess-club-tournament-another-approach-against-the-sicilian-squeezing-with-the-bind/&#34;&gt;third round&lt;/a&gt;, rather than the fourth round, because as I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/08/29/returning-to-chess/&#34;&gt;mentioned in August upon signing up for the tournament&lt;/a&gt;, I took a bye for the fourth round because of a schedule conflict with a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pghtech.org/networks/PittJug/events.aspx&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Java User Group&lt;/a&gt; meeting that I wanted to attend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thankfully, I came back for the fifth round finding that I was still tied for first, despite taking a half point bye in the fourth round, because nobody else had a perfect score after four rounds either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The game tonight ended up one-sided; right after he resigned, he called it an &amp;ldquo;emasculation&amp;rdquo; (I won fairly quickly, in less than two hours). However:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the unfolding of the game provides what I think is a nice illustration of how to win thematically against a Benoni opening structure&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;my opponent and I had a good discussion, after the game, about learning and improvement&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-complete-annotated-game&#34;&gt;The complete annotated game&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At your convenience, you can &lt;a href=&#34;../../chess/mirra-chen-2012-10-02.htm&#34;&gt;enjoy playing over the game with my annotations, including diagrams.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-paradox-of-choice-how-to-play-against-the-english-opening-as-black&#34;&gt;The paradox of choice: how to play against the English Opening as Black?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I learned some days before tonight&amp;rsquo;s game that my opponent and I were going to be paired. Based on my memory, and my database of games, I expected my opponent to play the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/English_Opening&#34;&gt;English Opening&lt;/a&gt;. In our last game, in 2010, he had played the English. I planned to avoid the variation that I had played then, because of course he would be prepared for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;reverse-sicilian&#34;&gt;Reverse Sicilian?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a confession to make: in the past, I hated facing the English Opening as Black. It&amp;rsquo;s the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Paradox_of_Choice:_Why_More_Is_Less&#34;&gt;paradox of choice&lt;/a&gt;: there are so many different ways to play against it. It is not a forcing, direct opening the way &lt;code&gt;1 e4&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;1 d4&lt;/code&gt; are. In its purest form, in fact, it is a psychological trick, an attempt to play a &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/sicilian-defense/&#34;&gt;Sicilian Defense&lt;/a&gt; in reverse, but with an extra move, if Black takes up the challenge of playing &lt;code&gt;1... e5&lt;/code&gt;. That extra move makes a huge difference, both objectively and psychologically, in the kinds of positions and evaluations that can arise, as noted English Opening theoretician &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Mastering-Chess-Openings-John-Watson/dp/1904600980&#34;&gt;John Watson&lt;/a&gt; has brilliantly explained. Roughly, it&amp;rsquo;s like playing the Sicilian Defense but getting an extra punch in before the fight starts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my 2010 game against my opponent, I in fact took up the challenge as Black and went into an aggressive reversed Sicilian variation, one tempo down: I played the Rubinstein Variation, which is exactly the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/19/round-3-of-pittsburgh-chess-club-tournament-another-approach-against-the-sicilian-squeezing-with-the-bind/&#34;&gt;Maróczy Bind&lt;/a&gt; in reverse. This is very risky, and although I won that game, I have also lost playing it. I do not play that kind of reversed Sicilian any more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;alternatives&#34;&gt;Alternatives&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many, many alternatives to playing for a reverse Sicilian as Black. Tonight I chose to aim to fight for the &lt;code&gt;d5&lt;/code&gt; square, to play to occupy the center and Queen side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;overview-of-my-game&#34;&gt;Overview of my game&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-opening&#34;&gt;The opening&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As expected, my opponent played &lt;code&gt;1 c4&lt;/code&gt;, the English Opening. After some more moves, it turned out that my opponent allowed me to play a reversed &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Benoni_Defense&#34;&gt;Benoni&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, there are dangers in playing reversed openings, in which Black takes the aggressive role White ordinarily takes but with a tempo down, but in this case, because of a positional subtlety, I was allowed to play a good version of the reversed Benoni as Black:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/mirra-chen-2012-10-02_files/diag3FECB4B2327E393B.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;A good reversed Benoni for Black&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The problem for White is that he used his extra moves to play &lt;code&gt;b3&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;Bb2&lt;/code&gt;, but now the Bishop is blocked up and is misplaced. This is an example of what proponents of the Black pieces such as John Watson and &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andr%C3%A1s_Adorj%C3%A1n&#34;&gt;András Adorján&lt;/a&gt; have observed about the subtleties of having extra moves: sometimes they are committal and do not help the side which has them!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;concepts-of-the-benoni&#34;&gt;Concepts of the Benoni&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those who are not very familiar with the Benoni as a chess opening, here is an overview of the goals of the two sides, which I&amp;rsquo;ll call the &lt;em&gt;attacker&lt;/em&gt; and the &lt;em&gt;counter-attacker&lt;/em&gt; (in the regular Benoni, these are White and Black, respectively, and in the reversed Benoni, these are Black and White, respectively).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that I don&amp;rsquo;t mention a role &lt;em&gt;defender&lt;/em&gt; here, because this opening is so sharp and aggressive for both sides that really, both sides are simultaneously attacking and defending for their lives. This opening is not for the faint-hearted for either side! It is a &amp;ldquo;kill or be killed&amp;rdquo; type of opening. I have played the Benoni on both sides, and both killed and been killed. (Most recently, I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/05/31/some-pretty-attacking-chess-at-a-party-last-weekend/&#34;&gt;played the counter-attacking role against a boy in a casual game&lt;/a&gt; and broke through quickly.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;attacker&lt;/em&gt; has more space, has a center pawn wedge thrust into the innards of the counter-attacker&amp;rsquo;s position, and aims to squeeze the counter-attacker to death, preventing Queen side counterplay, while preparing to blast through at the tip of the pawn wedge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;counter-attacker&lt;/em&gt; has less space, and hopes to launch a flank attack on the back end of the attacker&amp;rsquo;s pawn wedge and destroy the attacker&amp;rsquo;s center, coming around the attacker&amp;rsquo;s weakened Queen side to swarm in that way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-middle&#34;&gt;The middle&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The game tonight had the counter-attacker never getting Queen side counterplay off the ground, while the attacker (Black) broke through without resistance in the center: note that Black has played &lt;code&gt;e4&lt;/code&gt; successfully and White&amp;rsquo;s thematic &lt;code&gt;b4&lt;/code&gt; is nowhere near possible.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/mirra-chen-2012-10-02_files/diag3FECB4B5607FAC81.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;e pawn advance against the Benoni&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-end&#34;&gt;The end&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was no real end game to speak of, since by the time Queens came off the board, the game was lost for White.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/mirra-chen-2012-10-02_files/diag3FECB4B9B8C41929.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Queens are off, but game is over&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;discussion-with-my-opponent&#34;&gt;Discussion with my opponent&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the game, my opponent and I discussed the errors that he made during the game: I considered that allowing the reverse Benoni after &lt;code&gt;b3&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;Bb2&lt;/code&gt; was an error, and then after that, failing to prevent e4 with Nd2 was an error.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;study&#34;&gt;Study&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He noted that he had prepared for our game by studying our game in 2010 and had improved his understanding of the opening variation we had played then, but I told him that I, too, had looked at the game, and never planned to walk into his preparation. He said that he had every confidence that if I had played the same opening variation, I would have done my homework also, to improve what I did last time. He said he respected that even against a weaker player such as himself, he trusted that I would not play an opening I considered inferior or unsound &lt;em&gt;just because I could get away it&lt;/em&gt;. I really appreciated this comment and statement of trust, because in fact this is my current serious attitude. In a blitz game, I might play around, but in a serious tournament game, I will no longer play &amp;ldquo;junk&amp;rdquo;. &lt;em&gt;This was not always the case&lt;/em&gt;. In fact, in one of our earliest games, years ago, I had played junk against him and won, but not felt happy about doing that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;learning&#34;&gt;Learning&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I congratulated him for doing his homework, and having improved so much in the past couple of years, and he said he learns from his mistakes. Bravo! I have no doubt that he will study the opening we played today and be ready in the future not just for me, but anyone who plays how I did today. Some people make the mistake, during these Tuesday night tournaments in which we face the same people repeatedly, of preparing one-shot ideas against specific opponents, but what we really want to do (and what he does and what I do) is use these rematches as excuses to improve our &lt;em&gt;general&lt;/em&gt; knowledge and skill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My opponent said, before we parted tonight, &amp;ldquo;I don&amp;rsquo;t learn from my wins. I learn from my losses.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would amend that remark, however. I try to learn from my wins as well. Just because I won this game doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean I haven&amp;rsquo;t gone and analyzed &lt;em&gt;where I could have won even faster&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;possible good moves he could have made that I overlooked&lt;/em&gt;. Every game that I play, whether I win or lose, I want to learn something from. I have won games in which I played horribly and didn&amp;rsquo;t see anything and only won because my opponent saw less. I&amp;rsquo;m not satisfied with just &lt;em&gt;seeing more than someone else&lt;/em&gt;; I actually want &lt;em&gt;to see the naked truth&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-next&#34;&gt;What next?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next Tuesday is the last round of the six-round tournament. I am now the undisputed leader for first, meaning that if I draw next week, I am guaranteed at least a tie for first prize; if I win, I get clear first prize.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;None of that really matters to me&lt;/em&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;m in this to play as well as I can, enjoy the art, enjoy the sport, and to write up everything I learn along the way, whether I win, draw, or lose. I am, of course, grateful that I have been winning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2012-10-07&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-10-07)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oops, it turns out that I was wrong in figuring that I was the undisputed leader for first going into the final round: in fact, someone took a bye in the fifth round after a perfect score in the first four rounds, so he and I are tied for first going into the final round, and in fact, we are playing each other on Tuesday. So if I draw, that only guarantees that we split first prize. I need to win in order to get clear first prize.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am, of course, playing for a win. For better or for worse, &lt;strong&gt;I have never played for a draw in my life, against anyone, even a Grandmaster.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tonight I got a chance to play an opening, reverse Benoni, that I haven&amp;rsquo;t played for some time in a tournament, and I won the game through clear, thematic moves. In addition, we had a pleasant discussion after the game, and I look forward to seeing him play better in this opening in the future, and I too will refine my play in it.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why I am grateful that my father never let me win a chess game against him</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/06/03/why-i-am-grateful-that-my-father-never-let-me-win-a-chess-game-against-him/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Jun 2012 20:59:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/06/03/why-i-am-grateful-that-my-father-never-let-me-win-a-chess-game-against-him/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been writing a lot recent about life lessons learned from playing chess as a kid. Here are some life lessons I learned as a result of the fact that &lt;strong&gt;my father never let me win a chess game against him&lt;/strong&gt;. Based on what I have seen adults doing with children, I somewhat suspect this is unusual. I get the impression that parents like to let their children &amp;ldquo;win&amp;rdquo; at something, presumably for the purpose of giving them a &amp;ldquo;self-esteem&amp;rdquo; boost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it&amp;rsquo;s important to demonstrate compassion and judgment in encouraging children in their pursuits, but based on my own experience, I am not sure it is necessary to let a kid &amp;ldquo;win&amp;rdquo; when the win is nowhere near deserved objectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My father &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; let me win a chess game against him. I played many games with him starting from around age 3, and I did not win a single chess game against him until age eleven, on my own merits alone, when I had overtaken him in my strength. I don&amp;rsquo;t know what his rationale was, but I do know what his behavior taught me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-life-lessons&#34;&gt;The life lessons&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reason and logic have a force of their own, that lies beyond nepotism and other external factors, and must be respected and cultivated.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sometimes one deserves to lose, based on reality, and a child should learn to be a loser and not let losing be correlated with self-esteem or love.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Children at some point can detect lying, and my father showed me respect by not pretending to lose.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Children also appreciate compassion, and I knew my father was not always playing at full strength (he magically got better as I got better), but also knew that by not playing at full strength he made the game challenging yet fun for me, rather than demoralizing and impossible to learn level-appropriate lessons from.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When I actually finally won, it was a big deal, not something that just randomly happened for no reason; I knew that I had reached a true milestone in my life, in which I had through hard work actually surpassed my father at something.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;postscript&#34;&gt;Postscript&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, it turned out that when I won my first game with my father, that was the last game we ever played again for two decades. We never talked about why we stopped playing. After that game, simultaneously neither of us asked again to play the other. There was some kind of unspoken awkwardness. I was heading toward puberty and had begun acting up and resisting authority by that time, and he had been discouraged in his own quest for chess improvement, so he basically quit playing chess after I beat him for the first time. It was an awkward time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We played our first game in decades only when I was into my thirties and I was visiting one Christmas and invited him to play. We played, and I showed no mercy, and I won, but it was an honest game. Like old days. We still play now and then when visiting each other. He knows my level, I know his level, and we know I am basically always going to win, but what can we do other than play some honest games and enjoy the artistry we create together, no matter who wins?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Outside of official competitions, winning is not the only thing. It wasn&amp;rsquo;t when I was a child, and it isn&amp;rsquo;t now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;photo-of-me-playing-chess-with-my-father-in-summer-2010&#34;&gt;Photo of me playing chess with my father in summer 2010&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found a photo of my father and me playing a game of chess at my parents&amp;rsquo; home when Abby and I were visiting in summer 2010. (My actual first chess game with my father in two decades was when I was visiting over Christmas 2004.)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/chess-nelson-franklin-2010.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Nelson versus Franklin in chess in summer 2010&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2013-02-27&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-02-27)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The renowned chess instructor Bruce Pandolfini gave a nuanced, thoughtful answer to a parent&amp;rsquo;s question about whether to let a child win. (&lt;strong&gt;Update of 2013-12-22&lt;/strong&gt;: Unfortunately, the link I originally provided to his article no longer works, as Chess Cafe has begun removing archives of its content).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still think that how my father operated worked out well for me. I learned to value getting better, rather than winning. I trusted that getting better would eventually lead to winning, and it did. Even as an adult who has limited time and ambition, I still value getting better over winning. And &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/02/20/pittsburgh-chess-club-championship-2013-round-6-winning-as-black-like-a-madman/&#34;&gt;I just won the 2013 Pittsburgh Chess Club Championship&lt;/a&gt;. I am in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pscfchess.org/ratings/regtoppa.htm&#34;&gt;top 40 of the active rated chess players in Pennsylvania&lt;/a&gt;. I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be here if my father had not instilled in me a love of excellence and an honest self-evaluation. I don&amp;rsquo;t even feel good when I win. I only feel good when I judge that I &lt;em&gt;deserved&lt;/em&gt; to win.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2013-12-22&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-12-22)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hugh Patterson at The Chess Improver posted a great article &lt;a href=&#34;http://chessimprover.com/some-thoughts-for-parents/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Some Thoughts for Parents&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, although I am not a parent yet, I am teaching chess now, so I&amp;rsquo;m personally facing practical decision-making in how I try to simultaneously install love for chess, sheer fun, and a healthy drive for excellence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2015-12-21&#34;&gt;(Update of 2015-12-21)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two years later, I made a focused push, temporarily putting many
things aside in my life, in the fall of 2015 to &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2016/01/22/on-finally-achieving-the-us-national-master-chess-title-at-age-45-part-1&#34;&gt;achieve my US Chess
National Master&lt;/a&gt; title, and finally made it, a dream come true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it wasn&amp;rsquo;t winning that matters to me in this achievement: it is
that I have actually been playing pretty well and feel I finally
deserved the title. When I was not playing well, I did not feel I
deserved.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>They published my brilliant chess game, hinting it was not so original, but was it?</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/06/02/they-published-my-brilliant-chess-game/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Jun 2012 12:19:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/06/02/they-published-my-brilliant-chess-game/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The past couple of days, I have been writing about what I learned through playing chess as a kid. I continue today by discussion a game I played right before retiring from chess at age fifteen. This game came to my mind when I was writing about the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/05/30/life-lessons-i-learned-from-a-lunch-recess-chess-game-at-age-seven/&#34;&gt;chess computer game I played at age seven&lt;/a&gt;, because I played against the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sicilian_Defence,_Accelerated_Dragon&#34;&gt;Accelerated Dragon of the Sicilian Defense&lt;/a&gt; in that game, and in my retirement tournament I also played a game against that opening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My final tournament before I started the 11th grade and became fully absorbed in academic study was kind of special because I played reasonably well, achieving an Expert rating just as I retired, jumping from a rating of 1934 to over 2000, and because it was one of those tournaments held in East Lansing, which meant visiting and staying with my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/16/remembering-my-uncle-steve/&#34;&gt;aunt and uncle and cousins&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The game I played in the Michigan Open was the second to last chess game I played in a serious tournament before returning to chess over twenty years later. It ended up being published in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.michess.org/interim/magazine/1980s/MC8510.pdf&#34;&gt;following Michigan Chess magazine issue&lt;/a&gt;, warranting a short note that it was reminiscent of a &amp;ldquo;famous Fischer-Reshevsky debacle&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;pride-or-shame-creative-or-original&#34;&gt;Pride or shame? Creative or original?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was playing my game, I was feeling pretty proud of my winning combination, even though I knew it was not completely original; I in fact had been inspired by a theme in the Fischer-Reshevsky game that I had remembered when first encountering it in a book with my father back when I was eight years old. When I read the Michigan Chess magazine column and saw that, of course, the editor saw the resemblance, I felt deflated. As a result, I never showed my father the mention of my game in the magazine, nor did I show the game to him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But today, I am going to display this game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-game&#34;&gt;My game&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my game, I embarked on a double sacrifice combination that, if one had never seen the theme before, looks spectacular. If one had seen the theme before, it might look boring. But actually, it required accurate calculation to make the concrete variation of the theme actually work: playing simply by analogy is disastrous in chess because any small difference in a position can radically change its evaluation. So although I cannot take credit for spotting the theme, I think I can take credit for making sure that it actually applies in context.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is the critical position of my game, with White to play and win:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/accelerated-dragon-trap_files/diag3FDFE53F3ECA481F.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Chen-Winfield, Michigan Open 1985&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here is the critical position of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.chessgames.com/perl/chessgame?gid=1008376&#34;&gt;Fischer-Reshevsky, US Championship 1958&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/accelerated-dragon-trap_files/diag3FDFE554B3C66396.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Fischer-Reshevsky, US Championship 1958&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you have not seen either game before, do you see the similarities? Can you spot the forced wins?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-full-annotations&#34;&gt;The full annotations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out my annotations of both &lt;a href=&#34;../../chess/accelerated-dragon-trap.htm&#34;&gt;my game and Bobby Fischer&amp;rsquo;s game&lt;/a&gt;. My annotations go further into what I was thinking during the game. (The game page pops up defaulting to showing my game; use the upper-right corner selection menu to switch view to Fischer&amp;rsquo;s game.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-discussion-of-the-theme-and-variations&#34;&gt;A discussion of the theme and variations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So if you have looked through the games now, you can see that the basic theme is of trying to trap Black&amp;rsquo;s Queen and win it, and in order to avoid losing the Queen immediately, Black has to move the King out and risk being checkmated. And the key moves for White are to play Bxf7+ to remove the f Pawn that defends e6, and then Ne6 attacking the Queen. What is critical is evaluating whether Black can just take the Knight on e6 with the King and survive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are some real differences in how the theme plays out in my game and Fischer&amp;rsquo;s game:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In Fischer&amp;rsquo;s game, the Queen really is trapped; and taking the Knight on e6 with the King leads to a quick forced checkmate&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In my game, the Queen is not actually trapped, because the Queen can always go to e8, but in that case, I win the rook on c7 instead; finally, in my game, Black can in fact take the Knight on e6 with the King, and this does not lead to a forced checkmate, because Black has Bxc3+ freeing up the g7 square for the King to possibly escape to.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In retrospect, I should not have been too ashamed by the resemblance to Fischer&amp;rsquo;s game, because there were real differences that lead to completely different calculations and variations in winning the game. I did have to use my own mind. The calculations are not so hard for a strong player, but I was not even at an Expert rating yet at the time, so my game was pretty good for a Class A rated player.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-i-have-learned&#34;&gt;What I have learned&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some useful lessons I have learned upon revisiting this game:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Having a deep background in already existing knowledge (such as already played games) helps one spot a theme and apply it in a new situation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is no shame in stealing and using someone&amp;rsquo;s good idea.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Even when stealing an idea, it requires one&amp;rsquo;s own ingenuity to make sure it works in a new context.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do not let your own honest judgment of your work be swayed too much by what is said about it in a publication.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I could have been more proud of myself in front of my parents when I was a kid and shared my excitement at my personal accomplishments.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Flute practice: dealing with burnout and injury</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/02/27/flute-practice-dealing-with-burnout-and-injury/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Feb 2012 11:27:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/02/27/flute-practice-dealing-with-burnout-and-injury/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/left-hand.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin&amp;#39;s left hand&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, I attended yet another &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/02/22/flute-progress-still-hanging-in-there/&#34;&gt;rehearsal&lt;/a&gt; of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.andrew.cmu.edu/user/auo/&#34;&gt;Carnegie Mellon All-University Orchestra&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did this while feeling burned out and injured.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;burnout-and-injury&#34;&gt;Burnout and injury&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past couple of days, I have experienced decreased desire to practice flute, although by changing up my material, I did manage to get some decent sessions in. Still, I could tell that I was beginning to risk burnout.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to mental fatigue, my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/02/14/flute-progress-report-day-of-reckoning-approaches/&#34;&gt;left forefinger soreness&lt;/a&gt; got worse in the past couple of days, such that yesterday, I didn&amp;rsquo;t practice before rehearsal. I started experiencing &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jennifercluff.com/lineup.htm#indentation&#34;&gt;tingling and numbness&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://theskooloflife.com/wordpress/sometimes-its-best-to-call-it-a-day/&#34;&gt;Sometimes it&amp;rsquo;s best to call it a day.&lt;/a&gt; So I decided yesterday that today, I would take a day completely off from practicing my flute, the first break I have given myself since January 19.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;injury&#34;&gt;Injury&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clearly I need a real strategy to take care of the side of my left finger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is pretty easy to get injured playing music. There are many unnatural positions and movements to work with to make as relaxed as possible. My favorite book for musicians, &lt;a href=&#34;http://musiciansway.com/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Musician&amp;rsquo;s Way&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; has two entire chapters on injury prevention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next time I pick up my flute, I will focus on what I might be doing that causes particular stress on my left finger, and try to adjust. Earlier in my practice, I had problems with my right pinkie finger and solved them, so I have hope of treating my left finger better also. I have read about balance points, using the chin, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-instrument&#34;&gt;My instrument&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One problem that I definitely have is that the instrument I have is not optimal for me, and I know it. My main fundamental problem (and this has been a problem for me with piano, guitar, ukulele) is that I have a small hand and short fingers. There are solutions to this problem for the flute. One very common option that would immediately solve some of my problems is the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flutesonline.com/in_offg.htm&#34;&gt;offset G&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.flutesonline.com/shopping/in_offg.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Offset G flute&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve always thought that I would like to get an offset G flute when I &amp;ldquo;upgrade&amp;rdquo; from my intermediate student flute. &lt;strong&gt;Now I&amp;rsquo;m thinking I should do this sooner rather than later.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;no-excuse&#34;&gt;No excuse&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another book on music practice that I enjoy, Madeline Bruser&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://artofpracticing.com/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Art of Practicing&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, has an anecdote (page 107) about a flutist, Janet Weiss, who found that the traditional flute did not fit her hand, and became a pioneer in redesigning it. Weiss was quoted as saying, &amp;ldquo;The instrument we&amp;rsquo;re playing is incorrect for many people&amp;hellip; it&amp;rsquo;s like trying to dance in a pair of shoes that don&amp;rsquo;t fit.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed! If we love music enough, we should take the initiative to make sure that we are not hampered by our instruments. Just as, I love running and hiking, and struggled with bad footwear for years, decades, until I solved most of my problems, by moving toward &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/fivefingers/&#34;&gt;Vibram FiveFingers&lt;/a&gt; shoes that do not cramp my very wide feet and do not introduce cushioning that causes me to mess up my knees and shins and ankles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have to do what we have to do. We can&amp;rsquo;t just complain that other people are lucky and mass-produced clothing and tools work for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-orchestra-rehearsal-last-night&#34;&gt;The orchestra rehearsal last night&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was still struggling at rehearsal last night. I still cannot play all of the music at full speed. If it were entirely up to me, I would improve at my own pace, rather than feel forced to tackle material that is currently more beyond me than I&amp;rsquo;d like. But in real life, we often have to cut corners. The question is, which corners?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One option is to just bumble through everything in an equally mediocre way. I don&amp;rsquo;t see how that would help the orchestra&amp;rsquo;s concert performance or my own long-term development. So I have chosen to refine what is easiest, and get that working fully, while &amp;ldquo;giving up&amp;rdquo;, at least temporarily, on what is most out of reach. I&amp;rsquo;ve been closing the gap, and believe that I can close it within another three weeks. That would mean I will feel fully ready probably two weeks before the actual concert.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone else is also still improving. We don&amp;rsquo;t sound very good right now, even at slowish speeds. But we are sounding better every week! That&amp;rsquo;s what matters. It&amp;rsquo;s exciting to feel us coming together more and more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m dealing with a temporary setback in motivation and physical condition right now, but hope to bounce back tomorrow. &lt;strong&gt;The show must go on.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2012-03-12&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-03-12)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ended up &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/12/quitting-the-cmu-all-university-orchestra-one-of-the-hardest-decisions-in-my-life/&#34;&gt;quitting the CMU AUO&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>When can you call yourself an expert at something?</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/02/24/when-can-you-call-yourself-an-expert-at-something/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Feb 2012 20:47:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/02/24/when-can-you-call-yourself-an-expert-at-something/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently I encountered on a blog that I follow, &lt;a href=&#34;http://expertenough.com&#34;&gt;Expert Enough&lt;/a&gt;, the question, &lt;a href=&#34;http://expertenough.com/1594/call-yourself-an-expert&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;When Can You Call Yourself An Expert?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; There have been some interesting comments on the blog. Here is my own thinking on the subject.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The short answer: &lt;strong&gt;I try not to call myself an expert at anything&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A short elaboration of the short answer: &lt;strong&gt;I try to approach everything as a beginner&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-arrogance-of-expertise&#34;&gt;The arrogance of &amp;ldquo;expertise&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was younger (and that even includes myself from a year or two ago), I sometimes liked to think of myself as an &amp;ldquo;expert&amp;rdquo; at something or other. Sometimes I just held this thought in my mind privately. Sometimes I would say things that reflected my arrogance. I regret all that now. It did not serve any useful purpose for me to either &lt;em&gt;believe&lt;/em&gt; that I was an &amp;ldquo;expert&amp;rdquo; or to try to display or boast of my expertise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know I sometimes still slip into this mindset, but the difference now is that I actually actively believe that this mindset is harmful and not helpful (so if you catch me displaying this mindset, please gently admonish me). Real &amp;ldquo;expertise&amp;rdquo; is not an attitude or a property of a human being, some kind of moral virtue. It is something that someone else believes, as a result of some kind of skillful or helpful action, whether in something created or advice given with an open heart, and received with recognition and gratitude.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I try to get better at stuff, but without aiming for some label of &amp;ldquo;expertise&amp;rdquo;. I just want to get better. Adding the ego into the picture only wastes energy that could be spent on getting better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;beginner-s-mind&#34;&gt;Beginner&amp;rsquo;s mind&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a related note: privately, even during my arrogant moments, I have always cultivated &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shoshin&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;beginner&amp;rsquo;s mind&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. There&amp;rsquo;s always something deeper to appreciate or integrate from the basics of one&amp;rsquo;s activities. Amusingly, in the past I used to return to the basics out of fear of having missed something, having not really mastered something. But then I realized that one never &amp;ldquo;masters&amp;rdquo; anything that is worthwhile. All worthwhile pursuits are endless, never to be &amp;ldquo;mastered&amp;rdquo; as such. I lost my fear and simply enjoyed exploring things anew.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, when I learn a new &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/dancing/&#34;&gt;dance&lt;/a&gt;, I don&amp;rsquo;t go around thinking, &amp;ldquo;Oh, I&amp;rsquo;ve done other dancing, so this is going to be easy.&amp;rdquo; The fact is, if you&amp;rsquo;ve done enough different styles of dance, you realize that they are all different, and no, everything is not just some kind of variant of a unified superior dance technique. Furthermore, even in a particular dance that seems &amp;ldquo;simple&amp;rdquo;, there are &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.newyorklifecoaching.com/2011/08/10/once-a-beginner-always-a-beginner-why-its-okay-to-be-a-novice&#34;&gt;endless subtleties&lt;/a&gt;. Take the waltz, where the basic turning step seems simple enough. You could do the waltz a couple of times and think to yourself, &amp;ldquo;OK, I know this step, so I want to learn some more steps&amp;rdquo;. But no, that one step is enough to last a lifetime of practice. The amount of swing, the preparation by the upper body, the lilt, the timing of the 1-2-3 (not as a metronome), the exact acceleration of a turning step, all these things are a matter of lifetime refinement and experimentation and delight. I never think, &amp;ldquo;Oh, waltz has only one or two steps, so I&amp;rsquo;ve learned it, and it&amp;rsquo;s a boring dance, and now I want to learn some other dance with five new steps I&amp;rsquo;ve never seen before&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or when I play the &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/flute/&#34;&gt;flute&lt;/a&gt; (which I very much want to say I&amp;rsquo;m still pretty &amp;ldquo;bad&amp;rdquo; at, but the corollary of not claiming expertise is that I&amp;rsquo;m also not supposed to denigrate myself either; false humility is just a passive-aggressive form of arrogance), I&amp;rsquo;m still learning how to play a long tone well. And I know I&amp;rsquo;m going to be doing this the rest of my life. There&amp;rsquo;s never going to be a time when I feel that I have &amp;ldquo;mastered&amp;rdquo; playing the most beautiful single long note, and then never have to go back to practicing that again. This isn&amp;rsquo;t &amp;ldquo;perfectionism&amp;rdquo;, just the beautiful reality that if we appreciate everything in life, we always have more to learn, more to explore, and will never be bored.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or as I continue improving my &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/programming/&#34;&gt;computer programming&lt;/a&gt; skills, I keep in mind how incredibly complex and difficult the task of programming actually is, and how great it is that there are all these &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/16/pittsburgh-software-developer-communities/&#34;&gt;local groups&lt;/a&gt; that I attend, with all of us knowing that we have much to learn about our craft.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am grateful to have the opportunities to always find things to learn, to correct my mistakes and misunderstandings, and to learn from others (the Web has been an amazing source and amplifier of all these opportunities).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every day I wake up, I&amp;rsquo;m a beginner, and I love that. I&amp;rsquo;m a beginner at running, at writing, at eating, at dancing, at programming, at sitting, at loving, at hearing. It&amp;rsquo;s an amazing world, an amazing life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Help me stay a beginner!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Flute progress after one month in orchestra: still hanging in there</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/02/22/flute-progress-still-hanging-in-there/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Feb 2012 20:19:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/02/22/flute-progress-still-hanging-in-there/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It was exactly one month ago, January 22, when &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/02/01/joining-an-orchestra-learning-in-the-face-of-terror/&#34;&gt;I joined&lt;/a&gt; the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.andrew.cmu.edu/user/auo/&#34;&gt;Carnegie Mellon All-University Orchestra&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another week has gone by, and what I thought might be a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/02/14/flute-progress-report-day-of-reckoning-approaches/&#34;&gt;day of reckoning&lt;/a&gt; has come and gone, and I am still playing the flute in the CMU AUO and have not dropped out!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a sample of the hardest music from Bernstein&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Symphonic Dances from West Side Story&amp;rdquo; that I&amp;rsquo;m still struggling to play correctly, cleanly, and in tempo:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/flute-music/west-side-story-fugue.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;West Side Story: Fugue&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/flute-music/west-side-story-rumble.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;West Side Story: Rumble&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It is not very visible from my photos, but I have a huge number of pencil markings on my copy of the score.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story as of now:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;practice-in-the-past-week&#34;&gt;Practice in the past week&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;getting-down-the-basics&#34;&gt;Getting down the basics&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last Wednesday, I continued with focusing purely on improving technique with the Rubank method book. I did not even look at the Gershwin or Bernstein music for orchestra. I simply recognize that I have to focus on making fundamental progress in technique and trust that this will enable me to actually play the hard music at hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have not written much about this strategy, but I feel that it is effective and that many &lt;em&gt;amateurs&lt;/em&gt; do not practice or pursue their various life activities with this discipline, and therefore fall short of reaching their potential. And then typically, we amateurs make excuses, blaming lack of talent or lack of time for our slow progress or quick plateau at a mediocre level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is something in the general culture that encourages immediate gratification at the expense of true &lt;em&gt;craft&lt;/em&gt;. Yes, it is true that we cannot give our all toward our hobbies, the way we might for what we consider our jobs, but at the same time, if you add up the number of hours we spend at our hobbies, they actually do add up, and we might as well have made them count efficiently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me to attack the hard passages of music prematurely without building up technique would be analogous to the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;never running before but aiming to run a marathon in four months, and jumping straight into trying to run 15 miles&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;being a non-programmer and wanting to create a cool Web site in a month, but trying to read a book like &amp;ldquo;Learn Web Programming in 7 Days&amp;rdquo; and not really mastering concepts such as variables and functions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;never having cooked but deciding to make a really fancy and subtle French dish without mastering the basics of knife usage or the properties of butter&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People like shortcuts. But they usually do not succeed, and even if they do, don&amp;rsquo;t provide a sustainable path of growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My real goal isn&amp;rsquo;t just to survive playing in an orchestra concert. That&amp;rsquo;s actually just an incentive for my real goal, which is to improve my overall technique, so that I can continue to play music in any genre, any ensemble, as I wish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;an-off-day&#34;&gt;An off day&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, the next day, Thursday, I was feeling tired and unmotivated for practice. This happens sometimes. In fact, typically it happens once a week. I&amp;rsquo;m human. I can&amp;rsquo;t magically improve a huge amount every single day. Sometimes I&amp;rsquo;m tired. Sometimes I backslide, and notes come out jumbled, slow, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This, too, is a part of life. I&amp;rsquo;ve found the hard way that it&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; best to just push through and waste time and emotional energy. &lt;em&gt;Overtraining&lt;/em&gt; doesn&amp;rsquo;t help. Sometimes it is best to just take a break. I generally prefer to take an &lt;em&gt;active&lt;/em&gt; break.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, on Thursday I decided to put away the technique practice, which was not going well, and instead have fun sight-reading a bunch of music I had gotten out of the library earlier. I played around sight-reading &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Play-Puccini-Arias-Transcribed-Flute/dp/0634046209/&#34;&gt;transcribed opera arias from Puccini&lt;/a&gt; (I secretly love singing them in Italian even though I&amp;rsquo;m not a soprano or female!), &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Debussy-Album-Flute-Piano/dp/9043129712/&#34;&gt;transcriptions from Debussy&amp;rsquo;s piano music&lt;/a&gt; (I want to play the original piano pieces some day), and a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/World-Music-Cuba-Flute-play-along/dp/3702465804&#34;&gt;World Music Cuba&lt;/a&gt; album. It was a lot of fun playing real, lyrical music. I especially liked playing the Cuban music, since I always dreamed about doing that back when I was dancing salsa, rumba, cha cha, and bolero (I also have a goal of seriously singing this genre of music).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: eventually I would like to actually practice some of these music arrangements seriously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;update-of-2012-11-17&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-11-17)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nine months after this blog post, I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/11/17/a-childhood-dream-come-true-i-am-now-finally-singing-for-real/&#34;&gt;sang bolero for the first time in my life, to Abby&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;update-of-2013-03-17&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-03-17)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over a year later, I ended up playing selections from the World Music Cuba book &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/17/finally-doing-some-latin-music-jamming-on-flute/&#34;&gt;at a party&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;continued-practice&#34;&gt;Continued practice&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Friday and Saturday I was back doing technique, and Saturday I finally hit the CMU AUO music again. I noticed that I was playing the high notes on the flute better. Also, of course, I improved my speed and facility at many scales, but I won&amp;rsquo;t bore with listing metronome numbers to indicate my progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;sunday-s-orchestra-rehearsal&#34;&gt;Sunday&amp;rsquo;s orchestra rehearsal&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;sectional-for-woodwinds&#34;&gt;Sectional for woodwinds&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I arrived at 6:30 PM on Sunday for the woodwind sectional, but only one other person was there! People were running late, apparently. I was concerned when only three flutes (plus piccolo) showed up: did we lose another flute? (Later in the full rehearsal, two others joined us.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that in the woodwind sectional, collectively we were still struggling, and therefore I was not as out of place as I had feared I might be. It was a very useful rehearsal, in which many different instruments&amp;rsquo; parts started falling in place. It was at this point that I realized that I was having trouble not only because of my own problems but also because other peoples&amp;rsquo; problems were affecting me. I was having trouble coming in at the right time in many places not only because I was counting badly (although I&amp;rsquo;ve been working steadily at improving my counting) but also because so many other lines were not coming in at the right place either, so I could not rely on listening to others as a way of finding my place. Anyway, we made huge progress in some very difficult music. I actually believe, for the first time, that we might be able to get this stuff working for the concert.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;full-rehearsal&#34;&gt;Full rehearsal&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maria kept on being disappointed in the full rehearsal, asking if we had actually listened to the music, because we were still having so much trouble. (Actually, I have the music and listen to the whole thing at least once every other day.) Perhaps it was a blessing in disguise that so many of us were still unprepared, because it enabled me to not be completely left behind, as we kept the tempos still on the slow side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even so, there were sections in which I simply was unable to keep up. I feel that I really need to master most of them by next rehearsal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;this-week-s-practice&#34;&gt;This week&amp;rsquo;s practice&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My practice this week so far since the rehearsal has been good. I&amp;rsquo;m still focusing on building technique.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Monday, I made significant improvements in my high notes with scales. I worked some with the Bernstein.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Tuesday, I continued Rubank, and went back to some real basics, playing long tones, working on control of dynamics, and relaxation. I did not touch orchestra music at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, I did an abbreviated Rubank practice, then launched into much work on the Bernstein, to make things faster. As I do once or twice a week, I included a &amp;ldquo;test&amp;rdquo; for myself in which I played through all the problematic sections of the piece along with an actual recording. I&amp;rsquo;m doing much, much better now. There is still hope that I might be able to play most of the piece at full speed by Sunday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-look-back-to-three-months-ago&#34;&gt;A look back to three months ago&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is amusing to look back to what I was still having trouble playing, as a flute beginner, three months ago. I was just starting to work through a collection of &amp;ldquo;easy flute classics&amp;rdquo;:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/flute-music/moyse-easy-classics.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Moyse Collection of Easy Flute Classics&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Compare these simple, slow scores with the Bernstein excerpts in the photos at the beginning of this blog post!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;recorder&#34;&gt;Recorder&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Needless to say, I&amp;rsquo;ve completely put away my recorders. I did go to the monthly meeting of the Pittsburgh chapter of the American Recorder Society on Sunday to play, but that is all I will do with recorder until after the April orchestra concert. I would like to get serious about recorder again for late spring and summer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, I felt I was automatically slightly better at playing recorder even without touching it for a month. It&amp;rsquo;s the cross-training effect. Music is music, whichever instrument you&amp;rsquo;re playing: breath control, tone awareness, flexibility of fingers, etc. Even if I did sometimes forget my fingerings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m still enjoying improving at flute and slowly getting closer to being able to play the second flute part of the Bernstein in its entirety. I get less and less panicky about being in the orchestra as I &amp;ldquo;catch up&amp;rdquo; according to plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2012-03-12&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-03-12)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ended up &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/12/quitting-the-cmu-all-university-orchestra-one-of-the-hardest-decisions-in-my-life/&#34;&gt;quitting the CMU AUO&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pittsburgh Java User Group: Get Going with Git on Java Projects</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/02/21/pittsburgh-java-users-group-get-going-with-git-on-java-projects/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Feb 2012 20:34:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/02/21/pittsburgh-java-users-group-get-going-with-git-on-java-projects/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Tonight the &lt;a href=&#34;http://java.net/projects/pittjug/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Java User Group&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/pittjug/&#34;&gt;PittJUG&lt;/a&gt;) had another meeting at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pghtech.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Technology Council&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;http://twitter.com/matthewmccull&#34;&gt;Matthew McCullough&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href=&#34;http://github.com/&#34;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt; gave a talk &amp;ldquo;Get Going with &lt;a href=&#34;http://git-scm.com/&#34;&gt;Git&lt;/a&gt; on Java Projects&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I arrived early and couldn&amp;rsquo;t help admiring the view outside before entering the building as there was still daylight. Here are the Birmingham Bridge and the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Monongahela_River&#34;&gt;Monongahela River&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittjug-2012-02-21/birmingham-bridge.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;View of Birmingham Bridge from Pittsburgh Technology Council&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittjug-2012-02-21/monongahela.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;View across Monongahela River from Pittsburgh Technology Council&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a good time tonight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;social-time&#34;&gt;Social time&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PittJUG meetings are advertised as starting at 5:30 PM, although the talk starts at 6:00. These days I always try to get there by 5:30 in order to get a good seat, settle in, and eat pizza and socialize, and that&amp;rsquo;s what I did today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-talk&#34;&gt;The talk&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittjug-2012-02-21/matthew-mccullough-git.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Matthew McCullough of GitHub speaking on Git at PittJUG&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Matthew McCullough gave an energetic and clear presentation on some fundamentals of Git. There were good questions from the audience throughout, and he answered them well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The title of the talk was, I suppose, inaccurate, because there was not much that was Java-specific. It was more of a general introduction to Git. He is going to be doing &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pghtech.org/networks/PittJug/events.aspx&#34;&gt;GitHub&amp;rsquo;s Git Foundations Workshop tomorrow&lt;/a&gt;, covering much more of Git and details of Java environments. I am not attending this workshop, but based on his introductory presentation today, I&amp;rsquo;m sure it will be great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not sure how to summarize his talk, since I came to it already having spent quite a bit of time learning and understanding Git from various sources, including working through many &lt;a href=&#34;http://gitimmersion.com/&#34;&gt;tutorials&lt;/a&gt;, reading excellent &lt;a href=&#34;http://progit.org/&#34;&gt;Web references&lt;/a&gt; and other books, and actually using it on a daily basis for some time now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;my-learning-style&#34;&gt;My learning style&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am definitely not yet an &amp;ldquo;expert&amp;rdquo; at Git (I have done some interactive rebasing, but nothing more complicated than that), so I felt it would be very useful to get an integrated personal view of what is important about Git and why, and Matthew was great at telling a story with his own words and emphases and personal anecdotes, such as moving &lt;a href=&#34;http://groovy.codehaus.org/&#34;&gt;Groovy&lt;/a&gt; over from &lt;a href=&#34;http://subversion.apache.org/&#34;&gt;Subversion&lt;/a&gt; to Git. I did end up taking quite a few notes even though I already &amp;ldquo;knew&amp;rdquo; most of what he talked about, because I liked various tips or analogies that he made. I find it highly valuable to get different narratives whenever deepening my understanding of something; in school and outside of school, I have always read multiple books in parallel, finding myself some book other than the &amp;ldquo;official&amp;rdquo; one, in order to broaden my perspective and as a robustness/redundancy measure, in case (as always happens), one source is flawed or confusing in some section.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed this PittJUG meeting and am motivated to continue to improve my understanding and use of Git. Actually, at work I am about to transition a legacy Subversion repository to Git. I expect we will get a lot of benefits from this transition, and I will report on the results after I effect the transition and observe how everyone operates under the new system.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Flute progress report: day of reckoning approaches</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/02/14/flute-progress-report-day-of-reckoning-approaches/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Feb 2012 20:47:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/02/14/flute-progress-report-day-of-reckoning-approaches/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/02/01/joining-an-orchestra-learning-in-the-face-of-terror/&#34;&gt;Two weeks ago, I wrote&lt;/a&gt; about joining the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.andrew.cmu.edu/user/auo/&#34;&gt;Carnegie Mellon All-University Orchestra&lt;/a&gt;, the first orchestra I have ever been in. I wrote of my terror as I realized that as a total beginner at flute, I was basically unable to play &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; of the music handed out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided to work very hard at improving my flute skills to see whether I could get good enough in time to make it to the April 15 concert in respectable shape. &lt;strong&gt;I believe this is the most ambitious goal I have ever set for myself in my entire life.&lt;/strong&gt; Not because it is the &lt;em&gt;hardest&lt;/em&gt; goal to achieve, but because of the &lt;em&gt;time&lt;/em&gt; pressure involved. If I were given eight months, I would say, yes, I can do it; it took me eight months to start playing the recorder and then be sufficiently skilled (at merely an intermediate level) to play easy music in a concert. But &lt;em&gt;two&lt;/em&gt; months is another story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, the day of reckoning is not April 15. I feel it is next Sunday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-day-of-reckoning&#34;&gt;A day of reckoning&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More precisely, next Sunday is the first day on which I might be in a lot of trouble if I can&amp;rsquo;t reach a certain level. The woodwind section will have a sectional before the main rehearsal to iron out our special problems. All of us flutes will be pretty naked at the sectional. I know where I&amp;rsquo;m still falling short.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;good-news&#34;&gt;Good news&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The good news is that I have made &lt;em&gt;huge&lt;/em&gt; progress in the past two weeks. Whereas two weeks ago I classified myself as a &amp;ldquo;beginner&amp;rdquo;, now I would classify myself as an &amp;ldquo;advanced beginner&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There have been exciting days during which I made a lot of progress and bad days during which I felt that I made little progress or backslid, but I kept the faith and kept going. I&amp;rsquo;ve put aside various other personal projects in order to work as much on flute as possible: some days I have practiced two hours instead of one, and sometimes even three or four hours (on weekends). My left forefinger is permanently sore!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also good news is that we were down to four flutes and one piccolo as of two weeks ago, but this week were have not lost more flutes! I expect the rest of us are in it for the long haul: two of us on first flute, two of us on second flute, and one of us on piccolo. I&amp;rsquo;m not sure if I should, but I would feel very uncertain if I were the only second flute remaining now. It&amp;rsquo;s nice to know someone else may be sharing my pain, and maybe we can help each other in the sectionals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;practice-details&#34;&gt;Practice details&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bulk of my practice has been continuing to get down basic technique by working through the Rubank intermediate method. I keep on filling in gaps, adding new exercises while continuing to improve on exercises I have begun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;high-notes&#34;&gt;High notes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the music that we are playing for the concert, it has been of very high priority that I manage to play the very high notes (of the third register) effectively. This has been quite, quite difficult. It takes time to learn to form the embouchure and use it; what has been helpful has been looking at Web resources and reminding myself to &lt;em&gt;relax&lt;/em&gt;. Undirected powering through, like powering through in any other activity, from running to rowing to programming, doesn&amp;rsquo;t work. I still have difficulty producing the kinds of notes in the third register I would like (our director Maria has repeatedly told us flutes collectively to work on our intonation, and you bet that in Sunday&amp;rsquo;s sectional I will be doing what I can to get it where it needs to be), but at least I now know the fingerings for A-flat, A, B-flat, and B, and am still hard at work practicing scales and arpeggios way up there. It is only this week, actually, that I managed to be able to get B-flat and B out of my instrument at all. A-flat remains weird, but A is clean. Also, F, F-sharp, and G were shaky for me at last report, but I&amp;rsquo;m more or less getting them now. E does not speak so well, unfortunately; I think this is partially an inherent flute matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;dynamics&#34;&gt;Dynamics&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maria also repeatedly reminded the whole orchestra that we were not very good with dynamics, and generally played at some kind of nondescript mezzo-forte. We need to be able to play pianissimo and crescendo to fortissimo, etc., for expression and effect as indicated in the score.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve improved on dynamics, but it is still very hard for me to play high notes softly, for example. I know the theory, but making my mouth and breath do this is taking time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;rhythm&#34;&gt;Rhythm&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maria works with the entire group large on rhythm. The music we have to play is jazzy and swings and has all kinds of syncopations, accents that have to be felt and interpreted. It is indeed more effective to listen and copy these rhythms rather than try to play the notations in the score. She tells us not to play so square, ha!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Needless to say, I still have anxiety about coming in at the wrong times, and blasting a note where there is supposed to be a rest. So you bet I am working on getting the tricky rhythms down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;speed&#34;&gt;Speed&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maria has been ramping up the speeds in the rehearsals. Unfortunately, last Sunday an important section of the Bernstein was run through at a speed exceeding what I could handle at the time. So I have been working on that. I feel I am always playing catch-up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For development of speed, there is no substitute for just plain foundational technique work with the metronome. The metronome does not lie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;progress-on-old-exercises&#34;&gt;Progress on old exercises&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some examples of progress:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last week I gave a record of speed progress on an exercise:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 24: 100&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 25: 106&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 26: 109&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 27: 130&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 28: 131&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 29: 133&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 31: 141&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Add to that the following improvements, which get me to roughly where I feel I need to be:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 2: 143&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 6: 145&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 7: 146&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 8: 147&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 11: 148&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 14: 149&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the Pareto rule, I will not seek further improvement on this exercise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 25: 95&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 26: 96&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 27: 102&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 28: 106&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 29: 107&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 1: 115&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve improved on this one to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 2: 118&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 3: 119&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 6: 120&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 7: 122&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 8: 123&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 10: 124&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve topped out there too for now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s an interesting exercise from last time that I had found rather difficult:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 25: 100&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 26: 102&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 27: 105&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 29: 106&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 30: 107&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 31: 108&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have made radical improvements as a result of noticing the need for relaxation and for adjusting my holding of the instrument and the alignment of my right wrist (and many other things I still keep on refining):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 2: 110&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 3: 114&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 6: 120&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 7: 136&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 8: 138&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 11: 139&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 14: 140&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will stop trying to improve on this also.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a difficult arpeggio study at which I have made a big leap:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 27: 70&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 31: 71&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 1: 72&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 2: 73&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 3: 74&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 6: 78&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 7: 94&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 10: 95&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that in a single day, something clicked and I was able to go much faster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s an exercise that is wicked and works the right ring finger and other stuff:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 31: 86&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 1: 87&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 2: 110&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 3: 112&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 6: 114&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 7: 116&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 8: 118&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 10: 122&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 11: 123&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 12: 124&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 14: 126&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;new-exercises&#34;&gt;New exercises&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously, I have also attacked brand new exercises since my last post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s one on thirds:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 7: 110&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 11: 130&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 12: 132&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 14: 136&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another on thirds:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 8: 92&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 10: 120&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 11: 130&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 12: 132&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 14: 136&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rapid improvement on these new exercises comes because, as I have admitted, I have been a total beginner with almost no technique at all, never having practiced scales or arpeggios in any key, so when I&amp;rsquo;m learning a new key, I start off all confused but then make progress quickly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the Bernstein and Gershwin music have all kinds of keys, changes of key, accidentals, the works, so there is no escaping mastering everything. I&amp;rsquo;m working particularly on A major and A-flat major now, with their four sharps and four flats, respectively. The scariest, fastest section of the Bernstein actually has a key signature with six sharps (although I have to wonder why, because the music is full of accidentals and almost atonal).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;motivation&#34;&gt;Motivation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are times when I do not feel motivated to practice the concert music at all. I have a confession to make: playing flute in an orchestra is not my favorite musical activity by a long shot. It&amp;rsquo;s something I&amp;rsquo;m doing because it is novel to me and because I hope to enjoy being a part of a group effort in which we somehow manage to sound on April 15 a lot better than we sound now. Also, having a goal, and having the threat of social shame, has proved sometimes to be an effective motivator for me to achieve my &amp;ldquo;real&amp;rdquo; goals as a side effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I really like doing, and aim to do more of, is playing music in very small groups. I like playing recorder with one or two or three or four others. So sometimes when I&amp;rsquo;m practicing I feel frustrated that I&amp;rsquo;m working on a second flute part of a large orchestral piece, rather than on a duet or something like that. Amusingly, the fact that there are only two of us second flutes left helps me feel like I am &amp;ldquo;making a difference&amp;rdquo;, however.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m still hanging in there with my crazy attempt to just jump into a new level of flute playing, with a hard deadline. It would be less stressful if I were just trying to improve at my own pace, but I have to admit that from November through December, when I was working on the flute, the fact that I did not have a concrete level of mastery as a goal definitely made my practice less effective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2012-03-12&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-03-12)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ended up &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/12/quitting-the-cmu-all-university-orchestra-one-of-the-hardest-decisions-in-my-life/&#34;&gt;quitting the CMU AUO&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Joining an orchestra: learning in the face of terror</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/02/01/joining-an-orchestra-learning-in-the-face-of-terror/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2012 19:29:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/02/01/joining-an-orchestra-learning-in-the-face-of-terror/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have not written about my &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/flute/&#34;&gt;flute activities&lt;/a&gt; since &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/01/08/finding-and-using-my-childhood-flute-books/&#34;&gt;a month ago&lt;/a&gt;, but that&amp;rsquo;s not for lack of action: in fact, I&amp;rsquo;ve been spending a lot of time on the flute, at the expense of other personal projects, including writing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two months ago, I mentioned that I was &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/01/im-going-to-perform-music-much-sooner-than-i-expected-monday/&#34;&gt;considering joining&lt;/a&gt; the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.andrew.cmu.edu/user/auo/&#34;&gt;Carnegie Mellon All-University Orchestra&lt;/a&gt;, which I claimed was &amp;ldquo;not very good&amp;rdquo; and that &amp;ldquo;I don&amp;rsquo;t have to be super good to be a part of it.&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;I take back those comments&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I joined the CMU AUO two Sundays ago, attending the first rehearsal then, and &lt;strong&gt;it was one of the most frightening experiences in my entire life&lt;/strong&gt;. I almost left before even entering the rehearsal room. But I went in, stayed for the two and a half hours, and last Sunday, I went to the second rehearsal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me put it this way: at the first rehearsal, there were about ten flutes and one piccolo in the flute section. At the second rehearsal, we are down to four flutes and one piccolo. I hope that we don&amp;rsquo;t lose any more flutes at the next rehearsal. OK, maybe some students happened to be busy and will be returning. Or maybe some of them had the same reaction that I had: &lt;em&gt;absolute terror&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me explain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-music-we-are-to-play-for-the-april-15-concert&#34;&gt;The music we are to play for the April 15 concert&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the door of the rehearsal room, we got to pick up the music for the concert scheduled for April 15. There are four works, but one is for brass and percussion only, and the other for strings only, so there are only two I would play in on flute:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;George Gershwin, &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rhapsody_in_Blue&#34;&gt;Rhapsody in Blue&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Leonard Bernstein, &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/West_Side_Story#Symphonic_Dances_from_West_Side_Story&#34;&gt;Symphonic Dances from West Side Story&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On inspection at the door, I immediately realized that I could not play &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; of this music. Both the Gershwin and Bernstein were totally out of my current abilities. Worse, the Bernstein piece looked particularly insanely hard to me, even though I picked up the &amp;ldquo;flute 2&amp;rdquo; part, not the &amp;ldquo;flute 1&amp;rdquo; part. There were a lot syncopations, accents, extreme dynamics, very high notes (some of which I had not yet even learned the fingerings for yet), and the music was very fast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was filled with terror. I almost left without entering the room and signing in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-i-stayed&#34;&gt;Why I stayed&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went in anyway. I decided that I needed to see what this orchestra was about, since I have never been in an orchestra in my life (I stopped my feeble playing of the flute at age 13 and never played again after that).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a &amp;ldquo;fail fast&amp;rdquo; plan: if I really felt I couldn&amp;rsquo;t make a decent contribution in this orchestra, I would walk out as soon as I felt I was a hopeless burden to the team. &lt;em&gt;Forget ego&lt;/em&gt;: what I do or do not do must be based entirely on objective considerations. I wasn&amp;rsquo;t going to walk away already just because I believed (and still believe!) that I must be the worst musician in the entire orchestra, nor would I be afraid to walk away in the future if I found that I was harming the team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-first-rehearsal&#34;&gt;The first rehearsal&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ended up surviving the first rehearsal, in that we did a sight-reading session in which although I could barely play any of the music, I sat there trying to learn and did what I could, playing a few notes here and there when I could, and sitting out when there was just no way I could get anything right at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, I sat next to a guy who was playing piccolo, and he seemed to nail everything, although I had asked him earlier how long he&amp;rsquo;d been playing flute and he said twelve years. Note: I have been playing flute seriously for only three months, and on the membership form for the orchestra, it asked for a self-rating of experience level, ranging from Beginner to Advanced Beginner to Intermediate to Advanced, and with all honesty I checked off &lt;strong&gt;Beginner&lt;/strong&gt; (not even Advanced Beginner).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, it gave me some hope when I realized that everyone was having a hard time with the music. I&amp;rsquo;m sure nobody was having as hard a time as me, but we were struggling while sight reading at a very slow tempo. It also gave me hope that the director, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sellner.org/maria/Home.html&#34;&gt;Maria Sensi Sellner&lt;/a&gt;, happened to mention that we were tackling probably the hardest work the orchestra had attempted in its history, because she is leaving after this season and wanted to do something ambitious. OK, so it wasn&amp;rsquo;t just me thinking this music was hard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, she seemed to me very effective in helping us get started with the music. She worked out the tricky rhythms with us, and the music began to make more sense to me during the rehearsal. She told us that we should listen to recordings and check out the West Side Story musical so that we would understand the music in the context of the action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I left the rehearsal still shell-shocked, but I reasoned to myself that it would be stupid to quit this early on, before having had a chance to study the score more, continue to improve my technique, etc. I had grave doubts that I would return for the second rehearsal, but I had &lt;em&gt;one week&lt;/em&gt; to decide whether I should even come back. (Note that the orchestra has an attendance policy, so that anyone missing too many rehearsals may not play in the concert.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-sample-auo-performance&#34;&gt;A sample AUO performance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For fun, here is the CMU AUO performing last fall Bernstein&amp;rsquo;s Overture to Candide. They weren&amp;rsquo;t bad. That gives me hope, because we sounded pretty bad sight reading the Symphonic Dances from West Side Story, so I actually have faith that Sellner can get us into reasonable shape in two months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/ZelG_nJ-QvE&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-practice-strategy-for-a-week-after-the-first-rehearsal&#34;&gt;My practice strategy for a week after the first rehearsal&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All January I had been working really hard for three weeks on flute practice, in anticipation of the first CMU AUO rehearsal that occurred on January 22. I was making a &lt;em&gt;huge&lt;/em&gt; amount of progress working through &amp;ldquo;easy&amp;rdquo; stuff. Flute is much, much harder to play than &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/recorder/&#34;&gt;recorder&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the first rehearsal, I decided that there was no way I could ever play the Gershwin or Bernstein without focusing really hard on pure technique. So the bulk of my practice was beginning to systematically work through the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Rubank-Intermediate-Method-Piccolo-Educational/dp/1423444221&#34;&gt;Rubank Intermediate Method: Flute or Piccolo&lt;/a&gt; that I mentioned &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/01/08/finding-and-using-my-childhood-flute-books/&#34;&gt;finding in early January&lt;/a&gt; and never having used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spent a little bit of time trying to play excerpts from the Gershwin and Bernstein at a very slow tempo, but frankly, these attempts were very frustrating because I was still having problems just playing the high notes at all, for example. &lt;strong&gt;I had to learn the fingerings for some notes I had never played in my life.&lt;/strong&gt; I also had to improve my embouchure in order to produce those notes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(By the way, I have almost completely stopped playing recorder for a month. I am still attending the monthly meetings of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.andrew.cmu.edu/user/lukas/pcars/Welcome.html&#34;&gt;local recorder group&lt;/a&gt;, and practicing a little before attending, but I cannot devote any more time to improving on recorder while trying to get successfully to the April 15 CMU AUO concert.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-second-rehearsal&#34;&gt;The second rehearsal&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the second rehearsal approached, I wondered what we were supposed to be preparing for it. I sent email to the guy I had contacted last year about joining the orchestra, asking him if I had been put on the announcement mailing list yet, and he apologized, saying that he hadn&amp;rsquo;t, and he put me on. So it was only hours before the second rehearsal that I learned we were supposed to have been for days watching some YouTube videos and working on the two very hardest sections of the Bernstein!!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I almost didn&amp;rsquo;t go to the second rehearsal, as a result. I had not even looked at the hardest sections of the Bernstein yet: during the entire week, I had worked on the sections just up till those hardest sections!! I spent half an hour before the Sunday evening rehearsal trying to do a little work on the hardest sections, but failing pretty miserably. Oh well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went to the second rehearsal anyway. I half expected that I would be asked to leave after being found out to be completely incompetent (as well as not doing my homework).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that many of us had not done our homework, or had done it but were still having a lot of problems. The director was patient and slowed things down a lot and again focused on our getting the rhythms and syncopation right, and all the instruments just staying together at all. Because we were so unprepared, we ran out of time to work on the Gershwin, which she had originally planned to cover as well as the Bernstein.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, we lost most of our flutists!! In fact, with only four flutes and a piccolo left, during a flute-dominated passage of the Bernstein, we found out that only one of us was playing &amp;ldquo;flute 1&amp;rdquo;. The director asked for someone else to join her, and so I guess now we have two on &amp;ldquo;flute 1&amp;rdquo;, and me and the other person on &amp;ldquo;flute 2&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-practice-strategy-for-this-week-after-the-second-rehearsal&#34;&gt;My practice strategy for this week after the second rehearsal&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we were having a rehearsal again next Sunday, I would be seriously worried and contemplate probably having to drop out of the orchestra then. Luckily, we are skipping Super Bowl Sunday. &lt;strong&gt;This gives me two weeks, rather than one, to improve drastically.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The director had said it was up to us individually and in the upcoming sections to get our act together on the Bernstein sections in question. So I have at least one concrete goal for the next rehearsal: being prepared to play reasonably accurately the difficult Bernstein sections, and at tempo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For three days now so far this week, I have continued with working through the Rubank intermediate method. I have made so much progress that I think that in another couple of days I may consider myself an Advanced Beginner at flute rather than just a Beginner, ha!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;deliberate-practice&#34;&gt;Deliberate practice&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am putting in the focused, &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Practice_%28learning_method%29#Deliberate_practice&#34;&gt;deliberate practice&lt;/a&gt; to improve as rapidly and efficiently as I can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, I have to put in a plug for Gerald Klickstein, author of the wonderful book &lt;a href=&#34;http://musiciansway.com/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Musician&amp;rsquo;s Way&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, and his &lt;a href=&#34;http://musiciansway.com/blog/&#34;&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt; as well as his &lt;a href=&#34;http://twitter.com/klickstein&#34;&gt;Twitter feed @klickstein&lt;/a&gt;, which have been profoundly inspirational and useful in not only my music practice but also all of my other serious pursuits. He even replies to questions and comments promptly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regarding learning, I will be writing blog posts in the future about my various strategies for learning that I find effective. A recent article talks about &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wired.com/geekdad/2012/01/everything-about-learning/&#34;&gt;interleaving&lt;/a&gt;, which I have used to great effect to &amp;ldquo;parallelize&amp;rdquo; my learning, and I definitely use it in my music practice. I work on many things in one session, not just one thing, because there is no way to just get massively better at one thing during one session, and then do the same for something else at the next session. I have to parallelize, to make small bits of progress every day on something. For example, every day I work on&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;breath&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;intonation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;tone&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;high notes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;dynamics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;articulation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;rhythm: meters, syncopation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;tonguing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;speed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;passage work in keys (scales, arpeggios, thirds)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;tricky fingerings&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;style, expression&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;actual music&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I squeeze as much as I can out of an hour of practice at home. I&amp;rsquo;ve found that there are diminishing returns of all kinds after an hour. Obviously, if I were a music student or professional, I&amp;rsquo;d use multiple sessions to get more hours, but for much of my life these days I use the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pareto_principle&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;80&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;20&lt;/sub&gt; rule&lt;/a&gt; to maximize the returns on my practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;speed&#34;&gt;Speed&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I use the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/29/a-musicians-best-friend/&#34;&gt;metronome&lt;/a&gt; extensively in my practice to gauge my progress, by making note each day of the fastest speed at which I can execute an exercise with the best musical qualities I am capable of currently, and then trying to do it faster the next day. This method worked very well for me when I was learning the recorder from scratch, and it is working for me well now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, here is the record for one of the twenty or so exercises I have worked on in the Rubank book for the past week and a half:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 24: 100&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 25: 106&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 26: 109&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 27: 130&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 28: 131&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 29: 133&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 31: 141&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 24: 120&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 25: 135&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 26: 137&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 27: 139&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 28: 144&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 29: 146&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 30: 148&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 31: 152&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 1: 154&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 25: 95&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 26: 96&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 27: 102&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 28: 106&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 29: 107&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 1: 115&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another (in which I have been finding the series of arpeggios rather difficult):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 25: 100&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 26: 102&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 27: 105&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 29: 106&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 30: 107&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 31: 108&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Where there is a gap in the record, I either did not play that exercise that day, because I chose to work on another, or I did but could not go faster without error.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that the progress is not always linear. Sometimes there are &amp;ldquo;trouble spots&amp;rdquo; that hold me back for a while before I overcome them. Sometimes I am stagnant for a day or even a couple of days before I suddenly get better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keeping detailed records is vital to an objective assessment of where one is in one&amp;rsquo;s practice. I kept detailed records when losing thirty pounds over a decade ago, and when transforming myself from a non-runner into a marathoner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;progress-on-the-bernstein&#34;&gt;Progress on the Bernstein&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As mentioned, I have not practiced the Bernstein music that much, because I devote around 80 or 90 percent of my time to just improving my technique. The &lt;em&gt;fundamentals&lt;/em&gt; matter (I will talk about this in future blog posts) when trying to get good at something. One cannot just rush in without mastering fundamentals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some metronome improvement numbers for sections of the Bernstein music:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 28: 40&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 29: 70&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;January 30: 128 (full speed)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;January 28: 100&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;January 31: 110 (I still need to get up to 128)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;January 30: 100 (I still need to get up to 160!!)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously, my goal for the next rehearsal is to get as much up to full speed as possible in the sections that I need the most work on. If I fail miserably to measure up, I will feel justified in quitting the orchestra. But given my improvement in the Rubank method, I think I have a fighting chance in the next ten days to get much better in the Bernstein music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By deciding to take on the challenge of joining the CMU All-University Orchestra while being pathetically incompetent at flute, I am trying to push the limits of my learning and practice abilities. I will drop out if I only manage to hold back rehearsals or feel that I will play badly at the scheduled concert. But so far, I am still hanging in there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2012-03-12&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-03-12)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ended up &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/12/quitting-the-cmu-all-university-orchestra-one-of-the-hardest-decisions-in-my-life/&#34;&gt;quitting the CMU AUO&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to respond if a child asks you a science question you don&#39;t know the answer to</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/01/19/how-to-respond-if-a-child-asks-you-a-science-question-you-dont-know-the-answer-to/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Jan 2012 22:28:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/01/19/how-to-respond-if-a-child-asks-you-a-science-question-you-dont-know-the-answer-to/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today, I was very sad to see a news article &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/education-16612100&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Children&amp;rsquo;s science questions &amp;ldquo;stump many parents&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I was &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; sad for any of the following reasons:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Oh no, kids these days are receiving a poor science education!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Oh no, the parents received a poor science education when they were young!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was sad because of many of the parents&amp;rsquo; reactions to their children&amp;rsquo;s questions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
...16% told their children to ask their partner and a fifth made up a response or pretended that no one knew the answer.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What are some better alternative responses?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-first-step-to-acting-like-a-scientist-not-knowing&#34;&gt;The first step to acting like a scientist: not knowing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One obvious response that is already by itself profoundly adequate would be to say &lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;I don&amp;rsquo;t know&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;. So easy, so honest, yet many parents refused to use this response. But a parent who replied even in only this minimalist way would be teaching some very important lessons about science:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Science begins with &lt;em&gt;not knowing&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Science is about being &lt;em&gt;honest&lt;/em&gt; about reality and about oneself; it is about deliberately restricting one&amp;rsquo;s ego, recognizing one&amp;rsquo;s limitations, and acknowledging ignorance.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Science proceeds with &lt;em&gt;asking&lt;/em&gt;. The child by asking should be commended for asking, rather than implicitly punished or evaded for possibly embarrassing the parent.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Science proceeds with &lt;em&gt;trying&lt;/em&gt; to find out.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-second-step-to-acting-like-a-scientist-looking-for-an-answer&#34;&gt;The second step to acting like a scientist: looking for an answer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regarding trying to find out, here is another quote from the article:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
About a third of parents said they actively researched answers to their children&#39;s inquiries. 
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would be possible to stop here and praise these parents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But as phrased, this response is not satisfactory either:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Science is not about looking up an &lt;em&gt;answer&lt;/em&gt; somewhere, as one might look up a baseball statistic.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How involved were the children in obtaining the &amp;ldquo;answer&amp;rdquo;? Did the parents fetch the &amp;ldquo;answer&amp;rdquo; and hand it over? Or did the children get actively involved in looking for the answer?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Science is not about sitting back and getting an answer from someone.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Science is not really about answers at all. It is a &lt;em&gt;mindset&lt;/em&gt;, a &lt;em&gt;process&lt;/em&gt; of looking for an answer, and looking for ways to evaluate possible answers for adequacy and some measure of confidence. It is above all a &lt;em&gt;way of life&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-third-step-to-acting-like-a-scientist-being-wrong&#34;&gt;The third step to acting like a scientist: being wrong&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes one settles on an answer, and then later decides it is unsatisfactory. What then?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Science is not about being right.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Science is often about saying &lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;I was wrong&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-third-step-to-acting-like-a-scientist-uncertainty&#34;&gt;The third step to acting like a scientist: uncertainty&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eventually even the notion of &amp;ldquo;answer&amp;rdquo; must be considered flawed. We are never &lt;em&gt;certain&lt;/em&gt; about our theories. Our theories are based on &lt;em&gt;models&lt;/em&gt; that we invent. The models can have explanatory or predictive power or practical applications, but they themselves are transient. The scientific models from two centuries ago are very different from the scientific models of thirty years ago, and the scientific models of today are very different from the scientific models of thirty years ago. What we believed to be the &amp;ldquo;answer&amp;rdquo; thirty years ago looks today to have been an error.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And unless we believe that we are near the &amp;ldquo;end of science&amp;rdquo; (I do not believe this for a moment), we must also take into consideration the plausibility that thirty years from now, we will laugh at the currently favored scientific models of today the way we laugh at the hair and clothing styles of the 1980s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Science is about saying &lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;I am not sure&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best thing that everyone could learn about science, whether one is young or old, child or parent, is what its true nature is: a way of thinking, a way of acting, a way of living. It is not about &amp;ldquo;facts&amp;rdquo; to accumulate, or jargon to memorize.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>