<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Pittsburgh Step Trek on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/pittsburgh-step-trek/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Pittsburgh Step Trek on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/pittsburgh-step-trek/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>9 things you could be doing in Pittsburgh on Saturday, October 5</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/04/9-things-you-could-be-doing-in-pittsburgh-on-saturday-october-5/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2013 00:46:44 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/04/9-things-you-could-be-doing-in-pittsburgh-on-saturday-october-5/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m always frustrated at this time of year because there are so many events of interest to me in Pittsburgh that seem to happen on the first weekend of October. Since I cannot attend all of them, I figured I might as well attempt a public service and mention some of them so that if you are in the Pittsburgh area, maybe you can go and enjoy what I can&amp;rsquo;t attend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So here are 9 of the probably dozens of cool things you could be doing tomorrow, Saturday, October 5, 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;free-concert-allegheny-city-ragtime-orchestra&#34;&gt;Free concert: Allegheny City Ragtime Orchestra&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re interested in ragtime or Latin music, check out &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.shadysideacademy.org/page.cfm?p=12541&#34;&gt;this concert by the Allegheny City Ragtime Orchestra&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some articles in anticipation of it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.post-gazette.com/stories/ae/music/preview-ragtime-orchestra-connects-with-history-705929/&#34;&gt;Post-Gazette&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://triblive.com/aande/music/4763900-74/ragtime-music-concert&#34;&gt;Trib&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I wanted to go, but finally decided that we have too many other activities earlier in the day and need to just stay home and unwind in the evening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;free-conference-podcamp-pittsburgh-8&#34;&gt;Free conference: PodCamp Pittsburgh 8&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 8th annual &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.podcamppittsburgh.com/&#34;&gt;PodCamp Pittsburgh&lt;/a&gt; should be good. If you have any interest in using social media for personal or professional purposes, you should check it out. Interesting talks, opportunities to just socialized and learn new things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I attended in 2010, 2011, 2012, and will attend again for the fourth year. Unfortunately, I will only be able to attend the afternoon sessions. But I didn&amp;rsquo;t want to completely miss it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that PodCamp completely changed my life. For example, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/21/one-month-anniversary-of-my-blog/&#34;&gt;I started this blog in 2011 because of my second PodCamp&lt;/a&gt;, and I became serious about using social media in general, and that led to a total transformation of my life as I learned about local activities and made new friends. (Unfortunately, I didn&amp;rsquo;t get around to finishing my draft reports about my experience at last year&amp;rsquo;s PodCamp 7.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;pittsburgh-south-side-slopes-step-trek&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh South Side Slopes Step Trek&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The annual &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.southsideslopes.org/steptrek/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh South Side Slopes Step Trek&lt;/a&gt; is another event you can attend tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/08/my-god-its-full-of-stairs-pittsburgh-step-trek-2011/&#34;&gt;blog coverage two years ago&lt;/a&gt; as well as my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/09/25/why-you-should-go-out-to-the-pittsburgh-south-side-slopes-step-trek/&#34;&gt;recent update&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, Abby and I will be missing it this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;run-shadyside-5k&#34;&gt;Run Shadyside 5K&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you like to run in races, a fine race is the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.runshadyside.com/&#34;&gt;Run Shadyside 5K&lt;/a&gt;. Fast and flat, with a pancake breakfast and festivities afterwards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not running in it this year, just because I have too many other things to do already for the rest of the day, but here&amp;rsquo;s my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/01/run-shadyside-5k-outrunning-mickey-mouse-and-lending-a-trumpet/&#34;&gt;report from two years ago&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;free-5th-annual-wilkins-school-community-center-ecofest-in-regent-square&#34;&gt;Free: 5th annual Wilkins School Community Center Ecofest in Regent Square&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/ecofest-2013.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;5th annual Wilkins School Community Center Ecofest in Regent Square&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Interested in green living? Check out the &lt;a href=&#34;http://foresthills-regentsquare.patch.com/groups/around-town/p/ecofest-encourages-recycling-green-living&#34;&gt;5th annual Wilkins School Community Center Ecofest in Regent Square&lt;/a&gt;. Abby has regularly attended for the clothing swap. There will also be food, information, and entertainment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that this year, I will also be attending, to perform as a new member of the Steel City Ukuleles. &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/08/23/another-unexpected-life-change-one-month-of-learning-to-play-ukulele/&#34;&gt;I just started playing the ukulele a bit over two months ago&lt;/a&gt;, and have been working hard to help put on an entertaining show!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;ll be performing around 11:30 AM to 12:30 PM. If you come, say hello!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;cmu-donut-dash-2-mile-race&#34;&gt;CMU Donut Dash 2 mile race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, if you are into weird running events, there is the &lt;a href=&#34;http://cmudonutdash.org/&#34;&gt;Carnegie Mellon University Donut Dash&lt;/a&gt;, a 2 mile event serving as a fundraiser for the Children&amp;rsquo;s Hospital of Pittsburgh of UPMC. This is not an event I have ever done, and not one I intend to do, but what the heck, some of you might love this sort of thing!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;national-chess-day-gateway-open-tournament-at-the-pittsburgh-chess-club&#34;&gt;National Chess Day: Gateway Open tournament at the Pittsburgh Chess Club&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did you know that it&amp;rsquo;s time for &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nationalchessday.com/&#34;&gt;National Chess Day&lt;/a&gt;? There will be a tournament at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburghcc.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Chess Club&lt;/a&gt;, the 56th annual Gateway Open. Yes, chess in Pittsburgh has a long and illustrious history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;pittsburgh-perl-workshop&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Perl Workshop&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are a Perl programmer, the &lt;a href=&#34;http://pghpw.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Perl Workshop&lt;/a&gt; is back &lt;a href=&#34;http://pghpw.org/ppw2013/&#34;&gt;this year&lt;/a&gt;. Registration is already closed, so it&amp;rsquo;s not so helpful right now for me to mention it, but in case you didn&amp;rsquo;t know it existed, watch for it next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;ninth-thing&#34;&gt;Ninth thing?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, I guess I miscounted. But there are a whole lot more than nine things to do in Pittsburgh tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, if you are interested in some free stuff to do, there&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.radworkshere.org/interior.php?pageID=64&#34;&gt;RADical Days&lt;/a&gt; listing a whole bunch of stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s no shortage of stuff to do in this great city of Pittsburgh at any time or day of year. I think it&amp;rsquo;s unfortunate that many things I like to do happen to repeatedly fall on the first Saturday of the year, but I&amp;rsquo;m not complaining about an embarrassment of riches. Go out and take advantage of what I can&amp;rsquo;t.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why you should go out to the Pittsburgh South Side Slopes Step Trek</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/09/25/why-you-should-go-out-to-the-pittsburgh-south-side-slopes-step-trek/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Sep 2013 21:37:56 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/09/25/why-you-should-go-out-to-the-pittsburgh-south-side-slopes-step-trek/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Thanks to my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/08/my-god-its-full-of-stairs-pittsburgh-step-trek-2011/&#34;&gt;blog coverage two years ago&lt;/a&gt; of the annual &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.southsideslopes.org/steptrek/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Step Trek&lt;/a&gt;, I was invited, as I was last year also, by the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.southsideslopes.org/&#34;&gt;South Side Slopes Neighborhood Association&lt;/a&gt; to a special preview small group tour of the &amp;ldquo;church route&amp;rdquo;, which includes 820 stairs (379 stairs up, 441 stairs down), led by Brian Oswald.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided to attend for a couple of reasons:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To refresh my memory; I had not been to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/South_Side_Slopes&#34;&gt;South Side Slopes&lt;/a&gt; for probably a year, since Abby and I entertained her visiting sister and her boyfriend by taking them on a tour ourselves, along with &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.carrieplant.com/kitty/&#34;&gt;Kitty&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To take my work colleague John along and show him this unique part of Pittsburgh.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To learn what is new with the maintenance of this unique neighborhood.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To better promote the annual Step Trek event, which is enjoyable and benefits the neighborhood.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s my report on the evening preview tour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;meeting-up&#34;&gt;Meeting up&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;John and I left straight from work to meet up with Brian at the entrance to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.southsideslopes.org/the-neighborhood/south-side-park/&#34;&gt;South Side Park&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A number of other people were supposed to attend, but it turned out only one of them made it, representing &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.popcitymedia.com/&#34;&gt;Pop City&lt;/a&gt;. After waiting around for a while, we had to get going because of the danger of it getting dark before we would finish about an hour hike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;starting&#34;&gt;Starting&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A last view back north toward the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/South_Side_Flats&#34;&gt;South Side Flats&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/step-trek-preview-2013/south-side-flats.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Looking north to South Side Flats&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We started immediately with a staircase underneath the Mission Street Bridge:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/step-trek-preview-2013/mission-street-bridge.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Sample street on the route:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/step-trek-preview-2013/street.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;guided-tour&#34;&gt;Guided tour&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Along the way, Brian served as a tour guide, telling us all about renovations and repairs of various staircases, as well as particular ones that still needed work (such as a handrail that was broken). Two years ago, when Abby and I did the Step Trek event, we followed the nice booklet and route map that had a lot of historical information, but I wasn&amp;rsquo;t aware of all the details of what people like Brian of the South Side Slopes Neighborhood Association do to find funding for neighborhood improvements and keep the staircases functional. It&amp;rsquo;s a challenge getting all the repairs done that are needed. That&amp;rsquo;s why the Step Trek is so important as a fundraiser.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout the tour, we encountered quite a few people who were using the staircases, including runners as well as walking residents who used them simply as the most practical or only way to get from one place to another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;lighting&#34;&gt;Lighting&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One improvement that Brian was particularly proud of showing us was an entire staircase with LED lighting installed, in order to make it particularly usable at night. It also helps against freezing in the winter. (Unfortunately, as we walked down, I forgot to take photos of the LED lights visible from going up.)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/step-trek-preview-2013/leds.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/step-trek-preview-2013/leds-view.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/step-trek-preview-2013/leds-down.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/step-trek-preview-2013/leds-down-more.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;alleys&#34;&gt;Alleys&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some alleys are actually public parts of the route!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/step-trek-preview-2013/public-alleyways.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;churches&#34;&gt;Churches&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lots of churches on this route, hence &amp;ldquo;church route&amp;rdquo;. These are historical reminders of the early days of Pittsburgh with its ethnic churches all over.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/step-trek-preview-2013/church.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;railroad&#34;&gt;Railroad&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Walking on a bridge over railroad tracks:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/step-trek-preview-2013/railroad-tracks.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/step-trek-preview-2013/railroad-bridge.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;more-steps&#34;&gt;More steps&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Steps.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/step-trek-preview-2013/steps-up.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/step-trek-preview-2013/street-steps.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/step-trek-preview-2013/street-steps-2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/step-trek-preview-2013/street-steps-3.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/step-trek-preview-2013/street-steps-4.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/step-trek-preview-2013/street-steps-5.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/step-trek-preview-2013/street-steps-6.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/step-trek-preview-2013/street-steps-7.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;st-paul-of-the-cross-monastery&#34;&gt;St. Paul of the Cross Monastery&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/step-trek-preview-2013/monastery.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a nice view from the parking lot of the St. Paul of the Cross Monastery along the route (on Step Trek day you can enter). (Unfortunately, it was getting dark, so the photo is dark.)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/step-trek-preview-2013/monastery-view.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;billy-buck-hill&#34;&gt;Billy Buck Hill&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of rather hilly roads in this neighborhood. A good workout!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/step-trek-preview-2013/billy-buck-hill.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;views&#34;&gt;Views&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/step-trek-preview-2013/view-down.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;south-side-park&#34;&gt;South Side Park&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brian pointed out the successful planting of new trees as part of the improvement of South Side Park:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/step-trek-preview-2013/trees.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We did not take the steps leading back through South Side Park, which are part of the official Step Trek route:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/step-trek-preview-2013/south-side-park-steps.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Instead, we ventured into the woods. This way can be tricky because of the footing and possible mud, etc.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/step-trek-preview-2013/south-side-park-woods.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The advantage is we could get to a field with a nice view:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/step-trek-preview-2013/south-side-park-field.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;community-garden&#34;&gt;Community garden&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brian showed us another great improvement to the neighborhood, a rather large &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.southsideslopes.org/the-neighborhood/community-garden/&#34;&gt;community garden&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/step-trek-preview-2013/community-garden-above.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It was rapidly getting dark:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/step-trek-preview-2013/dark-view.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We hurried to get back to where we had started, under the Mission Street Bridge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many thanks to Brian for leading this preview tour and answering our questions as we enjoyed a little hike with him through his neighborhood!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;other-improvements&#34;&gt;Other improvements&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brian told us about improvements to the Step Trek event itself. For one thing, they have an improved map booklet out, and also improved support for smartphones. These improvements are not just for the Step Trek event but will be usable for any visitors to the South Side Slopes neighborhood anytime, as well as a valuable reference for residents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, check out this &lt;a href=&#34;http://epro.maps.arcgis.com/apps/MapTour/index.html?appid=289aed3c6a1642f2b1fcedbf3f6abe42&amp;amp;webmap=612e8347783143feb1a1f055552235a4&#34;&gt;great interactive map site&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;for-more-information&#34;&gt;For more information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out the main Web site of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.southsideslopes.org/&#34;&gt;South Side Slopes Neighborhood Association&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, they have an active &lt;a href=&#34;http://twitter.com/sssna&#34;&gt;Twitter account @sssna&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/SouthSideSlopes&#34;&gt;Facebook page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;step-trek-information&#34;&gt;Step Trek information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can register early for the Step Trek &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.showclix.com/event/steptrek&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember, the Step Trek also includes open houses, refreshment stops, and of course you can just hang out in the South Side Slopes checking out food and shopping too. The annual event is a great way to help the neighborhood and experience unique geography and get some exercise in also!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And at the entrance, there will be food trucks and entertainment, so that when you are done with however much hiking you want to do, you can hang out and relax.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more on the Step Trek as experienced in daylight, review my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/08/my-god-its-full-of-stairs-pittsburgh-step-trek-2011/&#34;&gt;blog coverage two years ago&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Pittsburgh South Side Slopes is a unique historical neighborhood that you should check out, and what better way is there than to explore it on foot on Step Trek day?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Fineview Stepathon 2012: Pittsburgh&#39;s grueling urban trail race</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/10/06/the-fineview-stepathon-2012-pittsburghs-grueling-urban-trail-race/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Oct 2012 23:07:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/10/06/the-fineview-stepathon-2012-pittsburghs-grueling-urban-trail-race/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://thenorthsidechronicle.com/UserFiles/Image/stepathon.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Stepathon steps&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Today I ran in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.thenorthsidechronicle.com/2061_php?calendarDate=2012-10-04&#34;&gt;annual&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://stepathon.org/&#34;&gt;Fineview Stepathon&lt;/a&gt;, a truly unique and grueling 5-mile race held in &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fineview_(Pittsburgh)&#34;&gt;Fineview&lt;/a&gt;, a neighborhood in the North Side of Pittsburgh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was not the first time I&amp;rsquo;d run the Stepathon: I&amp;rsquo;d actually done a shorter version of it (supposedly a 5K, but clearly much shorter given how quickly I finished it) in 2006. Originally, I wasn&amp;rsquo;t sure I was going to run another race this year after the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/30/running-my-10th-great-race-10k-obscene-but-in-a-good-way/&#34;&gt;Great Race&lt;/a&gt;, but after telling my buddy Chris about the Stepathon, and his getting excited about the concept, I decided to commit to doing it with him, rain or shine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Note that there was a short 2.5 mile option available, but only six people took it this year.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Web site&amp;rsquo;s description only gives a hint of what this event is like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Are you a runner, about to run the Great Race?   An urban explorer?  A fitness nut?  Or just a masochist?  How fast should you pace yourself, going up a stairway that rises out of view?  How fast can you go?  One thing for sure, the harder you fight the steps, the harder they fight back!  We saved the best for last... the legendary Rising Main stairway.  High as a 17-story building, disorienting as it leans this way and that, your legs feeling like jelly as you near the top... The Stepathon, ready to chew you up and spit you out!
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, the registration form says:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Challenging course includes 12 public staircases over 1600 steps.  Vertical climb 400 feet.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s my report on this fantastic event!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;course&#34;&gt;Course&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The course includes stairways, sidewalk steps, road sections, trail sections, grassy sections, bridges. It&amp;rsquo;s really something else. With all the turns, it was very helpful indeed that signs were put up and arrows drawn on the ground where useful, and several volunteers out on the course also, who pointed the way. I really appreciated the number of volunteers in the Stepathon who made it go smoothly. They not only pointed the way, but gave encouragement, and there were water stations also along the course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a &lt;a href=&#34;https://maps.google.com/maps/ms?hl=en&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;t=h&amp;amp;msa=0&amp;amp;msid=113997026750504519105.000482f8ae0315f705efc&amp;amp;ll=40.46334,-80.002184&amp;amp;spn=0.011428,0.018239&amp;amp;z=15&amp;amp;source=embed&#34;&gt;detailed map of the course&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And here are &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/groups/110502898969170/photos/&#34;&gt;photos from the past&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;preparation&#34;&gt;Preparation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t prepare for this event at all. I had no goal but to do my best and pace myself well. Real preparation, of course, would have involved doing a lot of &lt;strong&gt;stair-climbing&lt;/strong&gt;. It is the case that I &lt;em&gt;almost never&lt;/em&gt; take an elevator or escalator, but take the stairs instead, wherever I go, but I&amp;rsquo;m talking about actual stair-climbing training, of the form I used to engage in, during winter, when I did the summer &lt;a href=&#34;http://rachelcarsontrails.org/rct/challenge&#34;&gt;Rachel Carson Trail Challenge&lt;/a&gt; three years in a row. Of course, the place for such training is the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.tour.pitt.edu/tour-080.html&#34;&gt;Cathedral of Learning&lt;/a&gt;. Once a week, I&amp;rsquo;d do 36 floors, elevation gain of 440 feet, in one straight shot up, no rest: it was a &lt;a href=&#34;http://alltrails.com/events/2010/11/cathedral-of-learning-steps-2&#34;&gt;great workout&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;pre-race&#34;&gt;Pre-race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;food&#34;&gt;Food&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as in the Great Race, I continued my policy of not eating before the race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;clothing&#34;&gt;Clothing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was drizzling rain, but the temperature wasn&amp;rsquo;t too bad. I wore a long-sleeve moisture-wicking shirt, long running pants, my Vibram FiveFingers Bikila LS shoes, and the brand new Great Race cap that was given to all participants of the Great Race this year. This was the first time I&amp;rsquo;d ever worn a cap during a race; I didn&amp;rsquo;t want water getting into my eyes (as happened actually during the Great Race). I also wore some light gloves; in particular, I expected to try to hold onto some cold and wet stairway handrails!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chris also wore his Great Race cap. Since this was a smaller race, with 70 participants, this was the first time in a race we were at a start line together. In the huge July 4 Brentwood 5K race, which was his first 5K race, we didn&amp;rsquo;t start together, and in the even more huge Great Race, his first 10K race, I never even saw him at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I saw some people wearing the yellow Great Race long-sleeve shirts they were also given to all Great Race participants. I still haven&amp;rsquo;t worn mine yet. I wasn&amp;rsquo;t going to wear an unfamiliar shirt for the first time when doing a race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;pep-talk&#34;&gt;Pep talk&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The race director warned us of the hazards in store for us, and told us to be especially careful on the slippery wooden steps and in the trails. There were lots of jokes going around about dragging our broken bodies from the steps. I enjoyed the lighthearted mood. Hey, we all signed the waivers about the dangers of this event!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;description-of-the-race&#34;&gt;Description of the race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;stairs-and-trails&#34;&gt;Stairs and trails&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We started off running on the road for a bit before turning onto the first stairway. Chris was way ahead of me, but I was trying to pace myself for what lay ahead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After doing a bit of &amp;ldquo;running&amp;rdquo; up the stairs, I quickly realized that I was wasting my energy. I started just walking up the stairs instead. The plan was to walk up all stairways, but descend quickly, and run fast on the roads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, I was trying to pull myself up with my arms using the handrails, but it turns out that some handrail sections are missing or &lt;em&gt;loose&lt;/em&gt;. Yup, we were warned!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point, we started going off into the trails. Unfortunately, I had &amp;ldquo;forgotten&amp;rdquo; that there might be mud issues, and I was annoyed that I had worn my Bikila LS shoes instead of my KSO Trek shoes, which would have been much better in these conditions. I had to slow down a lot to avoid slipping and falling in the muddy trails.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I noticed that I was a lot faster descending steps than many people, so I started passing people during the descents. At some point, I caught up to Chris and passed him. But not too long after that, we entered a grassy section of the course, outside the fenced baseball field. I &lt;em&gt;knew&lt;/em&gt; that this was going to be treacherous, so I tried to grab with my right hand onto the fence as I ran, but still, at some point there was a drop and I slipped and fell hard, right on my butt. I picked myself up, luckily not really injured (although I had some hip pain for a day or two after the race), and kept going. After the race, Chris said he had seen me going down. Thanks to the indentation I made in the ground with my body, others behind me knew where not to step!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;roads&#34;&gt;Roads&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did do a good bit of running on the roads, but actually, a lot of walking too, because there were such steep hills along some of the roads. Here&amp;rsquo;s my rule of thumb in these kinds of races: if by walking hard I can keep up with someone who is running up a hill, clearly I am saving more energy than my competitor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;bridges&#34;&gt;Bridges&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were various bridges, but most amusing was the bridge over I-279. When was the last time I ran in a race that crossed an interstate highway? Um, never?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-garden-hose&#34;&gt;The garden hose&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the big stair climb near the end, I noticed while pulling myself up the handrails that one entire section was not only missing, but replaced seamlessly with a &lt;em&gt;garden hose&lt;/em&gt;. Hilarious, but not safe! I didn&amp;rsquo;t touch the hose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;fear-of-getting-lost&#34;&gt;Fear of getting lost&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite all the volunteers and signs and drawn arrows, there were times when I feared getting lost. This proved detrimental to my running speed. During much of the last half hour of the race, I was basically with a pack of two other people, with nobody else in sight ahead of us, and we were taking turns leading. This was fine when I wasn&amp;rsquo;t leading (typically, they were faster than me on the stairs and trails, while I was faster on the roads), but when a long stretch of road came up and I was clearly able to go faster, I was afraid to go as fast as I really could, in case I missed a turn. If I had genuinely prepared for this race, I would have studied and memorized the course map before doing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result of my not going all out when I was clearly strong enough to on the roads, by the time I saw the finish line approaching, no amount of sprinting on my part could get me to catch up with my two closest competitors. I was slightly annoyed with myself for not having applied optimal race tactics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;results&#34;&gt;Results&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://runhigh.com/2012RESULTS/R100612GB.html&#34;&gt;results of the race&lt;/a&gt; show that I finished in 27th place out of 70, in a time of 59:31. The two people I was running in a pack with for much of the second half of the race came in 8 seconds and 4 seconds earlier than me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I cheered Chris on as he came in some minutes later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;post-race&#34;&gt;Post-race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a view from the finish:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://bbbigdawgs.weebly.com/uploads/4/4/9/1/4491611/5685188_orig.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Welcome to Fineview&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://bbbigdawgs.weebly.com/uploads/4/4/9/1/4491611/5390106_orig.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;View from finish&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(It&amp;rsquo;s probably too hard to see my &amp;ldquo;indentation&amp;rdquo; in the ground in this photo outside the fenced ball field where I fell!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a little band playing some &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Old-time_music&#34;&gt;old-time music&lt;/a&gt;. That was a nice touch to this event. I always appreciate it when post-race festivities include some music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many refreshments were available: muffins, fruit, coffee, etc. I was pretty hungry after almost an hour of running (and on an empty stomach), and devoured some muffins and fruit. No coffee for me, though: I need to wind down, not wind up, after a race!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t pay much attention to the raffle prizes being given away, so who knows, I might have missed winning something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I picked up my race bag and a coaster. After I was done eating and chatting with Chris, I was getting cold and walked back to the start line and back to my car to drive home. It was kind of funny going backwards along part of the course, down the rights, down the steps, back to the start line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;other-events-that-took-place-today&#34;&gt;Other events that took place today&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sadly, today was also the day for two other annual events that were on different days last year: the Pittsburgh Step Trek and the Run Shadyside 5K.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I had to miss both of them. Generally, given the choice between doing something that I have enjoyed recently and doing something new (or very old), I will almost always choose what I did least recently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;pittsburgh-step-trek&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Step Trek&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, Abby and I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/08/my-god-its-full-of-stairs-pittsburgh-step-trek-2011/&#34;&gt;did the annual Pittsburgh Step Trek&lt;/a&gt;, which is a self-guided, noncompetitive event that actually gives a similar feel to the Fineview Stepathon, in that it is an exploration of a Pittsburgh neighborhood that has a lot of hills and nooks and crannies, and of course a lot of stairways. This year I was unable to do the Step Trek because of another commitment in the afternoon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.post-gazette.com/stories/local/neighborhoods-city/pittsburgh-steptrek-provides-a-different-view-of-city-656542/&#34;&gt;local writeup of this year&amp;rsquo;s event&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;run-shadyside-5k&#34;&gt;Run Shadyside 5K&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, since it fell on a different day, I also &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/01/run-shadyside-5k-outrunning-mickey-mouse-and-lending-a-trumpet/&#34;&gt;ran the Run Shadyside 5K&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s a nice event, but fast and flat and crowded is not as exciting as a quirky, small Stepathon!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a great time in this year&amp;rsquo;s Fineview Stepathon, and I was delighted to have introduced Chris to this event. This was one of the &lt;em&gt;most fun&lt;/em&gt; races in my life! I&amp;rsquo;m grateful for all the work the volunteers did to get the route ready, handle registration, direct the race, point out directions, give us water, and provide music and food for us at the end. I totally want to do this again next year, even if schedule conflicts arise again. And I hope that maybe I&amp;rsquo;ll do some targeted training in order to really conquer &amp;ldquo;man versus steps&amp;rdquo;!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My God It&#39;s Full of Stairs! Pittsburgh Step Trek 2011</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/10/08/my-god-its-full-of-stairs-pittsburgh-step-trek-2011/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Oct 2011 17:50:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/10/08/my-god-its-full-of-stairs-pittsburgh-step-trek-2011/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today was a beautiful, sunny, warm day, as promised earlier by the weather forecasts.  Abby and I did the 11th annual &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.southsideslopes.org/steptrek&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Step Trek&lt;/a&gt; for the first time. I wish I&amp;rsquo;d known about this event in earlier years! It was a truly unique event, an urban hike of the Pittsburgh &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wqed.org/tv/sebak/neighborhoods/so_side.php&#34;&gt;South Side Slopes&lt;/a&gt;, with all its many staircases, zig-zagging streets, historic buildings, and great views of the city.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/step-trek-stairs-down.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;?&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We did about six miles of fantastic sightseeing (and got a pretty good workout while at it):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We arrived at the registration area in South Side Park, and immediately, people started asking about the &lt;a href=&#34;www.vibramfivefingers.com/&#34;&gt;Vibram FiveFingers&lt;/a&gt; shoes that Abby and I were wearing: Abby was wearing her &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.vibramfivefingers.com/products/Five-Fingers-Sprint-Womens.htm&#34;&gt;Sprint&lt;/a&gt; and I was wearing my &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.vibramfivefingers.com/products/Five-Fingers-KSO-Mens.htm&#34;&gt;KSO&lt;/a&gt;. Throughout the Step Trek we would get asked about them by many other curious trekkers! We always got the same kinds of questions: &amp;ldquo;Are they comfortable?&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Do they provide enough protection/support?&amp;rdquo; The answer is yes, they are pretty comfortable, and yes, they are sufficiently protective and supportive, if you learn to walk more carefully, and develop your foot and leg muscles; and there are different models we use for different terrains and activities.  For example, I have mentioned &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/23/happiness-is-finishing-39th-of-43-men-in-a-race/&#34;&gt;in&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/25/blistered-but-blissful-in-the-burgh/&#34;&gt;previous&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/01/run-shadyside-5k-outrunning-mickey-mouse-and-lending-a-trumpet/&#34;&gt;posts&lt;/a&gt; my running on the roads in Bikila LS, and running and hiking off road in KSO Trek shoes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After we checked in with our tickets (pre-registered earlier) and were given a booklet for the self-guided tour for the Step Trek, we started our trek. There were two looping routes outlined, the Black route (3.02 miles, with 1,250 steps) and the Gold route (2.89 miles, with 1,222 steps). We decided to do one route first and then the other immediately following.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We started off with the Gold route, entering South Side Park and immediately taking the 72 serpentine steps up.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/step-trek-first-steps.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Serpentine steps at South Side Park&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;photos&#34;&gt;Photos&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below is just a minuscule sample of what else we saw. You&amp;rsquo;d have to do the Step Trek to experience it yourself!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a nice view of Pittsburgh during the trek:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/step-trek-view-of-pittsburgh.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Nice view of Pittsburgh&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s another one:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/step-trek-view-of-pittsburgh-2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Another nice view of Pittsburgh&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here is a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paper_street&#34;&gt;paper street&lt;/a&gt;, Caesar Way, which is actually a staircase rather than an actual street! Pittsburgh has a number of these I have encountered before.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/step-trek-caesar-way.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Caesar Way (paper street)&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A typical staircase leading connecting areas of different elevation:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/step-trek-some-steps.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;A staircase&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A beautiful view while descending on a road. The old St. Josaphat church is visible down the road:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/step-trek-descent.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Descent on road&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the bi-level streets we saw, with fencing separating the two levels:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/step-trek-lower-level-street.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;One of the bi-level streets&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Me just enjoying a little break at the Eleanor Street parklet:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/step-trek-franklin-swing.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin on swing at the Eleanor Street parklet&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;done&#34;&gt;Done&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After we returned from finishing both the Gold and Black routes, we enjoyed watermelon slices, oranges, and bananas. Because it was so sunny, we were both slightly sunburned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier, we enjoyed the official rest stops that provided beverages, bite-sized candy bars, and port-a-johns. A very nicely organized event, with clear signs posted periodically along the routes and friendly crossing guards at fast-moving roads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing we particular enjoyed after finishing was looking at the gallery of historic photos in one of the tents. It was eerie seeing those black and white photos of streets we had walked that were once dirt roads for horses, construction of bridges and staircases, old homes that are still standing now (and renovated). I wish there were more of the before/after photos. Maybe decades from now we&amp;rsquo;ll see YouTube time-lapse videos of how things are now in our neighborhoods and how things will be then!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2012-10-06&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-10-06)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following year, sadly, I did not do the Pittsburgh Step Trek again, because of a schedule conflict with &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/10/06/the-fineview-stepathon-2012-pittsburghs-grueling-urban-trail-race/&#34;&gt;the Fineview Stepathon that I did instead&lt;/a&gt;. We&amp;rsquo;ll have to see what the schedules are for 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2013-9-25&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-9-25)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, because of schedule conflicts again, Abby and I will not able to attend Step Trek. It seems that everything in Pittsburgh happens on the weekend of Step Trek.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I attended a special preview tour that enabled me to &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/09/25/why-you-should-go-out-to-the-pittsburgh-south-side-slopes-step-trek/&#34;&gt;catch up on changes and also promote the event&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>