<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Pennsylvania on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/pennsylvania/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Pennsylvania on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/pennsylvania/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Why I voted yet again</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/05/20/why-i-voted-yet-again/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 May 2014 22:52:11 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/05/20/why-i-voted-yet-again/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I voted again, as I&amp;rsquo;ve been doing regularly for some years now.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/voter-receipt-primary-2014.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;2014 PA primary election voter receipt&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But why?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/05/21/voting-in-the-face-of-election-apathy/&#34;&gt;vented a bit about voting&lt;/a&gt; but did so anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year, I paid almost no attention to any media coverage before the election. This included deleting answer machine messages, and summarily recycling all campaign flyers sent to my home, with an attempt not to even see who sent them. I don&amp;rsquo;t know if it&amp;rsquo;s just my imagination, but these flyers have gotten louder and more annoying and inane. I made the mistake of actually seeing &lt;em&gt;one&lt;/em&gt; of these flyers (and therefore know who it was from). In all caps and colored, bold text (if I recall correctly), it said something like&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Mike knows us.

And we know Mike.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That pretty much sums up what political campaigns are. And we know that psychologically, this stuff works. Just slamming someone&amp;rsquo;s name into our brains, creating &amp;ldquo;familiarity&amp;rdquo;, influences votes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yeah, I voted for Mike anyway. After all, &amp;ldquo;I know him&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;governor&#34;&gt;Governor&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I knew very little about the main race, the primary election for Pennsylvania governor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The night before, I did a little bit of research, largely on whom to vote &lt;em&gt;against&lt;/em&gt;. One candidate apparently stood out for pretty harsh negative ads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the whole, such negative ads turn me off. Now, I understand that psychologically, some people are motivated by negative ads to go vote against the target. But it&amp;rsquo;s actually difficult to anticipate exactly what the tradeoff is, in terms of attracting support vs. fueling the opposition. Obviously, I would never make a decision based purely on campaign tactics, but in this case, I figured I would go with someone not particularly different on issues who did &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; engage in this kind of behavior.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;but-why-vote-at-all&#34;&gt;But why vote at all?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wish I could tell you that I feel I&amp;rsquo;m making a difference by voting. I&amp;rsquo;m not sure that&amp;rsquo;s true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wish I could tell you that I feel it is my &amp;ldquo;civic duty&amp;rdquo; to vote, because I have the privilege of having the right to do so as a citizen of the United States. I&amp;rsquo;m not sure I feel that is my duty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The truth is, I vote every election day now simply because I&amp;rsquo;ve developed a &lt;em&gt;habit&lt;/em&gt; of it, and a &lt;em&gt;system&lt;/em&gt; (avoiding media coverage that would piss me off, and doing a bit of homework the night before election day). So, it&amp;rsquo;s just what I do now. I no longer question whether I will get out there and press the big red button. I just do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Do you vote? In every election or just high-profile primary or general elections, such as presidential? Why do you vote or not vote?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Voting in the face of election apathy</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/05/21/voting-in-the-face-of-election-apathy/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 May 2013 19:17:44 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/05/21/voting-in-the-face-of-election-apathy/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/voter-receipt-primary-2013.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;My voter receipt, May 2013&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Those of you who follow my blog know that I have been conflicted about voting, but go and do it anyway, &lt;em&gt;most of the time&lt;/em&gt;, e.g., &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/08/i-dont-know-if-i-should-vote-but-i-did/&#34;&gt;in November 2011 for the municipal election&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/11/06/i-decided-to-resign-myself-to-continue-voting/&#34;&gt;in November 2012 for the general election&lt;/a&gt;, when I felt there were some politicians very important to &lt;em&gt;vote against&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;apathy-or-ignorance&#34;&gt;Apathy or ignorance?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In April 2012&amp;rsquo;s general primary, however, I was sufficiently apathetic that I didn&amp;rsquo;t bother voting, although Abby did. For that election, it seemed to me that the winners were all going to be obvious no matter what I did, and there were no close races where I really cared about who won. I feel that in the absence of an informed opinion, the only rational and moral thing to do is to stay out. It is &lt;em&gt;unfashionable&lt;/em&gt; in our society to admit &lt;a href=&#34;http://opinionator.blogs.nytimes.com/2013/04/29/the-power-of-i-dont-know/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;I don&amp;rsquo;t know&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, but if I truly don&amp;rsquo;t know, then I see no point in participating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Primary_election&#34;&gt;Primary elections&lt;/a&gt; are particularly problematic for me, because I simply oppose the concept and also resent being forced to register for one of the two major American political parties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;may-2013-municipal-primary-choosing-mayor&#34;&gt;May 2013 municipal primary: choosing mayor!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this year&amp;rsquo;s Democratic primary is &lt;em&gt;critical&lt;/em&gt;, because it will basically determine who becomes the next &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pittsburgh_mayoral_election,_2013&#34;&gt;mayor of Pittsburgh&lt;/a&gt;, given that a Democrat will win in the general election in November. And since &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Luke_Ravenstahl&#34;&gt;Luke Ravenstahl&lt;/a&gt; decided to step down, there is a possibility of &lt;em&gt;real change&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I was pretty excited to vote today to make a difference (I hope). This will be the first time I have voted for a &lt;a href=&#34;http://triblive.com/politics/politicalheadlines/4052165-74/percent-mayor-turnout&#34;&gt;mayoral candidate in a primary&lt;/a&gt; in my 15 years as a Pittsburgh resident. For once there may be a crack in the rusty Democratic political machine here?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.post-gazette.com/stories/local/neighborhoods-city/polls-open-for-primary-election-688496/&#34;&gt;Voter turnout today has been crazy low&lt;/a&gt;. There was no line whatsoever when I went to vote or when Abby went. I&amp;rsquo;ve never participated in an election, I think, with such low turnout.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Maybe this low turnout will end up being a good thing&lt;/em&gt;. If people choose not to vote because they don&amp;rsquo;t have informed opinions, then it means that I and the surprisingly large number of people I know who also voted for the same guy I did will &lt;em&gt;win&lt;/em&gt;! (That said, it&amp;rsquo;s sad if &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pittsburghmagazine.com/Best-of-the-Burgh-Blogs/Pitt-Girl/June-2013/Why-You-Must-Vote-in-Pittsburghs-Mayoral-Election/&#34;&gt;only 2 percent of us decide the mayor&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;media-coverage&#34;&gt;Media coverage&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I avoided &lt;em&gt;most&lt;/em&gt; media coverage of the election (hard to avoid everything completely, admittedly) until I had already voted. (Yes, that includes ignoring the basically meaningless &amp;ldquo;endorsements&amp;rdquo; of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.post-gazette.com/&#34;&gt;Post-Gazette&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://triblive.com/&#34;&gt;Tribune-Review&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I enjoyed reading &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pghcitypaper.com/Blogh/archives/2013/05/21/election-day-thoughts&#34;&gt;this little look at what&amp;rsquo;s been going on with the mayoral race&lt;/a&gt;. And tomorrow I am back to ignoring the news.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, I had to recycle probably 30 or so paper flyers during election season. What a waste. And summarily delete dozens of robocalls on the answering machine. Note to everyone who sent me junk or left junk messages on my answering machine: &lt;em&gt;I did not read a single thing you sent, or listen to a single word you spoke; your junk only made me angry and at least partly less likely to vote for you, if I caught your name and remembered it&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;Pathetic.&lt;/strong&gt; I realize this crap works on some people, but I&amp;rsquo;m afraid it doesn&amp;rsquo;t work on me: I&amp;rsquo;m not going to believe that your opponent eats children for breakfast, no matter what large fonts you use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a moment of relief from apathy and cynicism about politics, I eagerly voted today. I hope I&amp;rsquo;ll get to see whether I was justified.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I decided to resign myself to continue voting</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/11/06/i-decided-to-resign-myself-to-continue-voting/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Nov 2012 12:05:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/11/06/i-decided-to-resign-myself-to-continue-voting/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/voter-receipt-2012.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;My voter receipt 2012&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Last year I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/08/i-dont-know-if-i-should-vote-but-i-did/&#34;&gt;wondered aloud about the act of voting&lt;/a&gt;, being unsure about how to justify my annual participation in this ritual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This being a presidential election, avoiding getting sucked in is a perpetual chore, given that it is impossible for me to completely avoid people&amp;rsquo;s political pontifications on their blogs, Twitter, Facebook, Google+, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I even had to stay home from work in order to avoid &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/06/obama-is-speaking-outside-my-office-window-so-why-did-i-stay-home/&#34;&gt;politicians annoyingly disrupting the workplace&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My conclusion was that, for me, the only rational response (that didn&amp;rsquo;t result in my getting frustrated and angry, which seems the tone of most of the politics-related chatter I see on social media) is to spend as little time as possible on politics, spend the evening before an election to do some research, and then go out and vote for the &amp;ldquo;lesser evil&amp;rdquo; for each race (yes, it&amp;rsquo;s not just about President, and in fact, local races are the ones in which voting is most likely to make a difference).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So last night, I held my nose, read up on various PA state candidates, made my choices, and this morning I went and voted. And now I&amp;rsquo;m going to simply proceed with my day. I&amp;rsquo;m not going to follow any election news coverage whatsoever. Instead, I&amp;rsquo;m going to try to get stuff done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, and whoever wins in each of these races, please go and do your job for us the best you can. Get stuff done. Stop blabbering lies and promises.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Living Appalachian music of Southwestern Pennsylvania: Mark Tamsula and Richard Withers with Ellen Gozion </title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/09/23/living-appalachian-music-of-southwestern-pennsylvania/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Sep 2012 22:15:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/09/23/living-appalachian-music-of-southwestern-pennsylvania/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As I periodically do, I went to the Carnegie Library of Pittsburgh on a Sunday afternoon to check out a musical event, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.clpgh.org/events/details.cfm?event_id=69114&#34;&gt;part of the regular World Kaleidoscope series&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.appalachianmusic.net/&#34;&gt;Mark Tamsula and Richard Withers&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://ellengozion.com/&#34;&gt;Ellen Gozion&lt;/a&gt; were there to perform some Appalachian music with very local southwestern Pennsylvanian roots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mark talked a good bit about going through the materials collected by the historian Samuel Bayard. It was interesting to me that his research in reviving the music that Bayard documented forced Mark to get more involved in reading music, since as a traditional musician he was used to learning everything by ear, but nobody is alive any more who originally played some of this music, and all that is left to document it is scores!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/appalachian-music/three.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Mark Tamsula, Richard Withers, Ellen Gozion&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/appalachian-music/irish-flute.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Richard Withers on Irish flute&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The two instrumentalists played quite a variety of instruments: fiddle, banjo, flute, guitar, harmonica, accordion, Irish flute. I enjoyed the variety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ellen Gozion sang some traditional ballads. She has a perfect voice and spirit for this music, singing with great purity and depth of emotional expression. Wow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the little concert, they promoted the new CD &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.upinthebattenhouse.com/&#34;&gt;Up in the Batten House&lt;/a&gt; and talked about upcoming projects.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>