<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Run Around The Square on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/run-around-the-square/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Run Around The Square on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/run-around-the-square/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Reflections on my slowest Run Around the Square 5K in 13 years</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/08/24/reflections-on-my-slowest-run-around-the-square-5k-in-13-years/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Aug 2013 12:45:47 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/08/24/reflections-on-my-slowest-run-around-the-square-5k-in-13-years/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This year was the ninth time I ran in the annual &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.runaroundthesquare.com/&#34;&gt;Run Around The Square 5K race&lt;/a&gt;, and Abby&amp;rsquo;s third year in a row. The conditions were great: cool and dry, in contrast to the usual hot and humid conditions at this time of year. (Last year I reported on &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/08/25/my-eighth-time-doing-run-around-the-square-5k/&#34;&gt;my eighth running of the race&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both Abby and I ran this race rather slowly, but were happy and enjoyed the day. Here&amp;rsquo;s why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;both-of-us-coming-back-from-setbacks&#34;&gt;Both of us coming back from setbacks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing to note is that both Abby and I have been recovering from setbacks this year, as I reported two weeks ago after I ran the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/08/09/getting-up-when-reality-punches-you-in-the-face-running-the-second-liberty-mile-in-pittsburgh/&#34;&gt;second GNC Live Well Liberty Mile&lt;/a&gt; 18 seconds slower than last year. That race had me vowing to get back on track, and the very next day I did &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/08/10/emerging-from-my-three-months-of-illness-self-pitying-and-self-loathing/&#34;&gt;begin getting back on track&lt;/a&gt;. The road back to a regular exercise routine has not been easy in the past two weeks, but I have very gradually ramping up on running as well as minimal strength training every single day since then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, I ran the Run Around The Square 5K in 24:35.6 and was pretty to have recovered from several years of decline in fitness and self-care, by running my best time since 2006. For this year, I wrote, &amp;ldquo;I don&amp;rsquo;t know what goal to set for next year. I suppose I could set a goal of getting yet faster, breaking 24:15. That sounds reasonable to me. Going back down to 24:00 may even be possible. It&amp;rsquo;s too early right now to tell. But one thing is for sure: I have no intention of slowing down from this year to next.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, I did not set a firm enough goal. I have learned the hard way that if you don&amp;rsquo;t make a commitment (and then follow up with the discipline and sacrifices required to achieve it), then even in the absence of accidents, a maybe-goal is worthless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year, I went into the 5K race so untrained (two weeks of slowly ramping up before the race is not enough for any training benefits to kick in) that I basically knew that I was going to be super slow. I figured that since I lost 18 seconds in the mile, I would be happy if I lost only one minute in a 3K. So that was my expectation: finish around 25:36 this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;before-the-race&#34;&gt;Before the race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided that this was the race in which I debut my new orange running singlet, to replace my over-decade use of a blue singlet that Abby has gotten very annoyed with:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-around-the-square-2013/franklin-orange.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin wearing orange singlet&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Also, note that since I bought a SPIbelt earlier this year, I now always run races wearing a SPIbelt to carry my phone. This is particularly convenient when running a race where you have to park far from the start line and want access to your phone after a race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wore my Vibram FiveFingers KSO Trek shoes again. Since last year&amp;rsquo;s fiasco in which I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/30/running-my-10th-great-race-10k-obscene-but-in-a-good-way/&#34;&gt;injured my left foot from having the straps on my left foot too tight&lt;/a&gt;, I never again put the straps on too tight!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hanging out before the race start in Regent Square:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-around-the-square-2013/before.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Before start&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-around-the-square-2013/franklin-ready.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin ready&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Start line just a few minutes before race start:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-around-the-square-2013/start-line.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Start line&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-race&#34;&gt;The race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(&lt;a href=&#34;http://runhigh.com/2013RESULTS/R082413AA.html&#34;&gt;Race results.&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;different-race-logistics&#34;&gt;Different race logistics&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One very important change to the race, and one I greatly appreciated, was the staggered start. Faster runners were told to line up front and start up first. This is very helpful to control the congestion and confusion that happens in a large race when too many slower people start up front and have to be passed (including unfortunately young children that Abby and I have seen trampled on every year!). In particular, it is really tricky to be passing lots of people once in the trails of Frick Park.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;first-mile&#34;&gt;First mile&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of the ridiculous problems I created for myself by going too fast two weeks ago in the Liberty Mile, I vowed to go out at a reasonable pace in this 5K. I found this easy to do because of the staggered start, which meant that there were fewer people to have to accelerate past throwing off one&amp;rsquo;s own internal speedometer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The usual lot of young and old musicians were playing music along the course. What a great neighborhood tradition!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still get confused seeing the champagne stop near the end of the first mile at the entrance into the trails of Frick Park.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did the first mile in a leisurely 8:15 (compared to 7:18 last year).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;second-mile&#34;&gt;Second mile&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did the second mile in 10:17 (compared to 10:11 last year). I did not feel too bad. I was running a bit conservatively, because my training runs had been so slow and short and tough for me in the past two weeks. I wanted to be in position to run really well the final downhill in the third mile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;third-mile&#34;&gt;Third mile&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I let loose in the third mile. Because I had avoided going pukey in the second mile, I covered it in 7:06, actually a second faster than the 7:07 of last year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of the staggered start, there was not bad congestion during the third mile, and I found it safe to pass people at will.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;final-sprint&#34;&gt;Final sprint&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t have a gut-wrenching final sprint. I wasn&amp;rsquo;t even looking at the clock or my watch. This wasn&amp;rsquo;t one of those races in which I put it all out there on the course. Instead, this was a race where I was grateful to be running at all, and had no expectations other than to finish strong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I finished in 25:38, just a bit longer than a minute over last year&amp;rsquo;s 24:35.6. My &lt;em&gt;slowest&lt;/em&gt; Run Around The Square 5K time &lt;em&gt;in 13 years&lt;/em&gt;. But it was a clean finish, and I was so excited to simply be back and running faster than 26 minutes, at least.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;after-the-race&#34;&gt;After the race&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although I was not pukey, I was certainly breathing hard when I finished.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-around-the-square-2013/franklin-after.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin after the race&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I went off to drink water and start eating some food.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-around-the-square-2013/view.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;View&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;improvement&#34;&gt;Improvement&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I went back to the finish line to wait for Abby to finish. I saw Todd and his wife Gabrielle hanging around. Gabrielle said she took my &amp;ldquo;advice&amp;rdquo; (from last year) to go all out to the point of feeling pukey. I admitted that this time around, I didn&amp;rsquo;t follow my own advice. Gabrielle finished over 5 minutes faster this year than last year!! Todd finished over 8 minutes faster!! It&amp;rsquo;s great to see people in their late 40s improve their fitness so much in a single year. I saw the couple running together a couple of times in Frick Park this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;decline&#34;&gt;Decline&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby finished. She was out of breath and pukey, but I was proud of her for finishing. Because of the tremendous decline in health and fitness she has experienced this year, I was not sure she would actually finish the race.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-around-the-square-2013/abby-finish.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby finishing&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;more-food-and-refreshments&#34;&gt;More food and refreshments&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We lined up to sample more food and recovered. It was a beautiful day to be outside.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-around-the-square-2013/abby-recovered.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-around-the-square-2013/franklin-recovered.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The hot dogs and beer line was particularly long, but we finally reached the tables.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-around-the-square-2013/hot-dogs-beer.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Hot dogs and beer&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;walking-out-of-frick-park-back-to-the-car&#34;&gt;Walking out of Frick Park back to the car&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I couldn&amp;rsquo;t help taking a photo of the sign for beer and champagne that was still up on the trail entrance as we passed by:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-around-the-square-2013/beer-champagne.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Dunning&amp;#39;s beer and champagne stop&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;concern-about-abby&#34;&gt;Concern about Abby&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although I was happy that Abby managed to finish the 5K race, I was very concerned about her overall health and fitness, which have continued to be poor this year since she broke her foot in February. Here are her Run Around The Square 5K times since she started doing it with me:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2011: 37:15&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2012: 36:04&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2013: 39:54&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She was almost 4 minutes slower than last year. She&amp;rsquo;s lost &lt;em&gt;several years of fitness&lt;/em&gt; this year, and came in 105th of 116 in her age group. Again, we are grateful she is walking and running at all, but this has been a very bad year for her, and this impacts not only her own life, but ours more generally. We need to work on getting her back on track.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;goal-for-next-year&#34;&gt;Goal for next year?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right now, my real goal is to simply continue my exercise program and not break it again, and that includes the winter slump I usually enter. Last year, I had a slump in the final months of the year, and then woke up and &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/28/meditations-on-climbing-the-36-floors-of-the-pitt-cathedral-of-learning/&#34;&gt;started exercising again around New Year&lt;/a&gt;, and even signed up for the Pittsburgh Marathon as a way to force myself to stay active in the winter. I believe that if I simply avoid self-caused setbacks, I should be able to return myself to a decent level of fitness. I am &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; going to sign up for the Pittsburgh Marathon again. Almost certainly, however, I will sign up for the Pittsburgh Half Marathon! Last winter, I rather enjoyed &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/30/report-on-just-a-short-run-my-first-half-marathon-in-nine-years/&#34;&gt;training for and running the Just A Short Run half marathon&lt;/a&gt;. I reached good fitness through that, but squandered my fitness through overtraining and injury leading up to the marathon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;races-this-year&#34;&gt;Races this year&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the shorter term, I have two races to run in the coming month: the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/07/running-my-8th-pretty-good-race-5k-dealing-with-disappointment/&#34;&gt;CMU Pretty Good Race 5K&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/30/running-my-10th-great-race-10k-obscene-but-in-a-good-way/&#34;&gt;Great Race 10K&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, I did very poorly in the Pretty Good Race 5K because I was injured and exhausted, running 26:05. This year, I expect to do better than that. I&amp;rsquo;m not going to do the 24:36 of 2011, but given that I easily beat 26 minutes today, I will beat 26 minutes two weeks from now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Great Race 10K last year, I was still in a state of exhaustion and undertraining, so I didn&amp;rsquo;t even pay any attention to time goals, and finished slowly in 48:23. I see no reason why, if I continue improving my fitness in the next month (in contrast to last year&amp;rsquo;s dreadful September), I should not be able to run under 48:00.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;update-of-2013-09-06&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-09-06)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/09/06/was-it-worth-sprinting-to-a-terrible-fall-to-finish-25th-in-the-cmu-pretty-good-race-5k/&#34;&gt;my report on running the Pretty Good Race 5K this year&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Run Around The Square continued to thrive and improve, and I&amp;rsquo;m grateful for both the registration cap (to maintain the quality of the event) as well as the staggered start. And all the sponsors feeding us afterwards!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I were happy to have finished the race, even if we are both less fit now than we have been in years. But I think this is a wake up call for us to get back in shape. For example, I miss the long hikes we used to do last year when we had the stamina to actually do and enjoy them. The example Todd and Gabrielle set as they massively improved their fitness in the past year is inspiring. Abby and I should be able to do this too, if we make it a priority.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introducing a friend to the joys of trail running in Frick Park</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/10/13/introducing-a-friend-to-the-joys-of-trail-running-in-frick-park/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Oct 2012 23:14:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/10/13/introducing-a-friend-to-the-joys-of-trail-running-in-frick-park/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today I had the special pleasure of introducing a friend to the joys of trail running in Frick Park.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It all started with a casual comment Chris made in late August that he was thinking of doing some distance work in Frick Park, to get a change of scenery from where he lives and runs, south of Pittsburgh. I said, &amp;ldquo;Hey, let&amp;rsquo;s do this together&amp;rdquo;, and looking at our schedules, we determined that today would be the first day we could sync up for a long run in the morning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So basically, we had this run planned a month and a half ago. And luckily, the weather was great today!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was our first run together, outside of our both having just last week run in the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/10/06/the-fineview-stepathon-2012-pittsburghs-grueling-urban-trail-race/&#34;&gt;Fineview Stepathon&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back in August, Chris had warned me that he might be slow. I said that I did long runs slowly in any case, only speeding up near the end. What I didn&amp;rsquo;t say was that I fully believed that with the training he&amp;rsquo;s been doing toward the goals of his first 10K (which he has done: he did the &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/great-race/&#34;&gt;Great Race 10K&lt;/a&gt; this year), his first half marathon, and his first marathon, he was going to get fast in just a matter of months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I was right! We ended up running 13 miles, and not very slowly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-planned-route&#34;&gt;The planned route&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a basic idea of where to show Chris around in Frick Park. By coincidence, almost exactly a year ago, I actually did a writeup about a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/15/snapshots-of-pittsburgh-from-a-12-mile-run/&#34;&gt;favorite long run of mine in Frick&lt;/a&gt;. I figured that we might do a subset of that run, around 10 miles, this morning. We&amp;rsquo;d improvise to cut the run short or add to it, based on how we were feeling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conditions&#34;&gt;Conditions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The temperature started at around 36 F, but was slated to go over 50 F by the time we expected to be done, and it was sunny. It was perfect fall running conditions!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-experiment-today&#34;&gt;My experiment today&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I have mentioned lately, I have been experimenting, with great success, with &lt;em&gt;fasting&lt;/em&gt; before running in races. Today I extended the experiment by fasting, for the &lt;em&gt;first time&lt;/em&gt; in my life, before doing a long run. I have often fasted before doing a run up to 6 miles, but not much longer than that. Typically, for a long run, I eat something before heading out, and bring a snack of some kind to eat at some point after about an hour. But I have always wondered whether eating (especially any carbs) was just training my body to depend on carbs, etc. What if I could train my body to just go into fat-burning mode and stay there, by avoiding carbs and avoiding food altogether?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So today, I didn&amp;rsquo;t eat before the long run, and although I brought a snack as insurance in case I bonked, I wanted to see how I would feel for the entire duration of a long run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-run&#34;&gt;The run&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We started off at around 10-minute pace for the first hour of the run, taking the Riverview Trail (winding all the way down), the Falls Ravine Trail down into Fern Hollow, then crossing Commercial Street and going up to Summerset at Frick and back down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We didn&amp;rsquo;t go into Duck Hollow because there was a barrier with a sign saying that the section of trail was closed. I didn&amp;rsquo;t know whether to believe that (I&amp;rsquo;ve seen that sign there for a long time now), but didn&amp;rsquo;t want to run into any possible trouble, so we turned back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once back in Frick Park, Chris picked up the pace, to about 9-minute pace. OK. He was running faster than I would have chosen to run myself if I had been on a long run alone. I silently kept up. One thing about running with other people is figuring out what shared pace to adopt. If individuals have fitness levels that are too different, running together might not work too well. In our case, it appeared that Chris was rapidly closing in on my level, and for all I knew, could already be beyond it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, since we had cut short the route that would have led to the Monongahela River, I decided we&amp;rsquo;d do more exploration within Frick Park. We took the Nine Mile Run Trail down to where it emerges in Regent Square, then came back up, then turned onto Braddock Trail. We got off Braddock Trail at the point where the annual &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/08/25/my-eighth-time-doing-run-around-the-square-5k/&#34;&gt;Run Around The Square&lt;/a&gt; turns onto it, and headed back into Fern Hollow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then we went up north on Tranquil Trail, branched off Homewood Trail to pass by the Frick Park Lawn Bowling Greens, see Homewood Cemetery, and head back down. By then, I calculated that we should head back, because we were going to have done about 12 miles total by the time we got back to my place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Going up Falls Ravine Trail, I finally started feeling hungry. But I was OK, not lightheaded or bonking, so I did not eat the snack I had brought. This was already the furthest I&amp;rsquo;d ever run in my life completely without pre-run food or any fuel during the run (I had two or three water fountain stops but that&amp;rsquo;s no calories).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking the Riverview Trail, we reached a point at which I told Chris I liked to go fast for a whole mile uphill, so I sped up and went for it. I was going at under 8-minute pace as though running the last mile of a 10K race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point near the end of that uphill stretch, Chris called for me to wait up. He had gotten some stomach cramps. He said he wasn&amp;rsquo;t used to running at this speed. We walked for a bit before we resumed running out of the park and back to my place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;analysis&#34;&gt;Analysis&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By my estimate, based on my pretty good feel for my pace and subtracting time at water fountains and walking, we ran about 13 miles. My feet were pretty sore (I wore my Vibram FiveFingers KSO Trek shoes, as usual in the trails), but I was feeling great; and I hadn&amp;rsquo;t eaten anything since dinner the previous night! OK, I was hungry and ready to eat a meal, but I had not bonked or anything. This gives me some confidence to try more fasting experiments in future runs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I told Chris that I believed he was fundamentally strong and could run really fast, that he should add long interval training sessions to his current regimen of long runs and hilly speed training. It&amp;rsquo;s the long intervals (running about a mile at 5K pace) that do wonders. We had just gone out and practically run a half marathon casually, so for his first half marathon coming up in months, he should be able to train well and actually set an ambitious time goal for it. I would not be surprised if in his first half marathon he is able to run faster than in my fastest ever half marathon! Put in the long runs and the interval training and one should be able to &lt;em&gt;race&lt;/em&gt; one&amp;rsquo;s first half marathon, not merely finish it. In my experience, if one has done enough training for a half marathon, it can be raced almost as though a &amp;ldquo;long&amp;rdquo; version of a 10K race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The marathon is another story entirely. I may write something up about that some day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a beautiful day for a long run in Frick Park, and I was delighted to introduce Chris to some of my favorite routes in it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, I was pleased that my experiment with fasting worked out.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My eighth time doing Run Around the Square 5K</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/08/25/my-eighth-time-doing-run-around-the-square-5k/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Aug 2012 10:47:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/08/25/my-eighth-time-doing-run-around-the-square-5k/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today Abby and I ran in the annual &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.runaroundthesquare.com/&#34;&gt;Run Around The Square 5K race&lt;/a&gt;. As usual at this time in late August, it was a warm day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This race is special because Run Around The Square was the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/06/06/i-celebrated-national-running-day-in-schenley-park-remembering-how-i-began-to-run-13-year-ago/&#34;&gt;first race I ever ran in my life&lt;/a&gt;, back in 2000, and because it is also the first race Abby ever ran &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/31/reflections-on-2011/&#34;&gt;(just last year, 2011)&lt;/a&gt;: so today was my 128th lifetime race (according to my race log I keep) and Abby&amp;rsquo;s 5th lifetime race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-goal-this-year&#34;&gt;My goal this year&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My goal for the race for this year was to run it faster than I did last year (which also would automatically mean running it faster than any year since six years ago, 2006).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My time from last year was 24:36, and I believed from my last timed interval workout, on Tuesday, that I could run 24:30 today at fastest, so there was little room for error. I had hoped months ago that I would be in shape to run considerably faster in Run Around The Square this year, but travel and other interruptions caused me to train only haphazardly for races this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did I achieve my goal? The story turns out to be more complicated than I expected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-race&#34;&gt;The race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;first-mile&#34;&gt;First mile&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I took care during the first mile of the race not to go out too fast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We all passed by a lot of musicians on the streets, of course: a really fun tradition that goes way back. As I expected, I saw &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/18/fun-at-the-east-end-food-co-op-winterfest/&#34;&gt;Kimberlee Faught&lt;/a&gt; playing violin at one point:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/85802484@N06/7857971836&#34; title=&#34;&amp;quot;Run Around the Square&amp;quot;, Regent Square by sherpes39, on Flickr&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8286/7857971836_496cf2afe7.jpg&#34; width=&#34;375&#34; height=&#34;500&#34; alt=&#34;&amp;quot;Run Around the Square&amp;quot;, Regent Square&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As usual, I ignored all the champagne and beer stops on the race course. That&amp;rsquo;s a charming and venerable tradition at this race, but drinking alcohol would &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; help me run as fast as I can!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;second-mile&#34;&gt;Second mile&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once in the trails of Frick Park, there is no longer any question of going too fast; there is only a question of avoiding going too slow. The uphill is really tough. And I&amp;rsquo;m much better running downhill than running uphill. During the second mile, my only thought is to maintain my effort level rather than my pace, because when the big downhill comes at the end of the race, I need to have enough energy in the tank to blast downhill, however crappy I might already be feeling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, that&amp;rsquo;s false: my other thought is to keep hydrated and cool. I sacrifice a little bit of time during the second mile because up near the tennis courts, I always grab a cup of water from a friendly volunteer and drink some of it while pouring the rest of it over my head and rubbing it through my hair and onto my face and neck. (I don&amp;rsquo;t take any more water after this point in the race.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, about halfway through the race, with more than ten minutes projected to go, I was feeling pretty pukey and my breathing getting harder. &lt;strong&gt;Good&lt;/strong&gt;; that&amp;rsquo;s just a sign that I&amp;rsquo;m following my 5K race game plan. It is impossible to &lt;em&gt;race&lt;/em&gt; a 5K without feeling pukey, whatever your level is. &lt;strong&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re not feeling pukey by the middle of a 5K race, you&amp;rsquo;re not running the race as fast as you&amp;rsquo;re physically capable of running it.&lt;/strong&gt; I realize that many people run just for fun and don&amp;rsquo;t want or need to feel pukey in order to enjoy a race, and there have been races in which I have not gone all out, normally, I run a race in order to test my limits of existence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;third-mile&#34;&gt;Third mile&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Third mile, there&amp;rsquo;s the big downhill on the trail. The tricky thing is how to pass a lot of people. The problem with large trail races is that there are a lot of people who go out too fast early on or are much worse at running downhill than at running uphill; the result is congestion during the downhill parts of the course. I did manage to run downhill well without losing too much in efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;final-sprint&#34;&gt;Final sprint&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My vision was getting fuzzy from the pain, and my mind confused, when I was approaching the finish line. I couldn&amp;rsquo;t tell from the big clock whether I had already missed my chance at beating last year&amp;rsquo;s time. Seriously. It was reading 24:3x as far as I could tell, which meant that I already lost my chance to run 24:30. But was I going to beat 24:36? I had no idea. I thought I was going to see the &amp;ldquo;3&amp;rdquo; digit move to &amp;ldquo;4&amp;rdquo; at any time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of me wanted to shut down and quit and just watch the &amp;ldquo;4&amp;rdquo; digit arrive on the clock. Part of me knew that I still had enough energy to push harder, even as I was already sprinting, for another second or two (or more?!). Reality became distorted, I lost confidence, and I finished the race &lt;em&gt;not knowing whether I had really tried my best at the end&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;after-the-race&#34;&gt;After the race&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I checked my watch after I finished the race and didn&amp;rsquo;t know what to think. Did I succeed or fail at my time goal? My watch made it look like I finished in 24:40, but I wasn&amp;rsquo;t confident that I hit the &amp;ldquo;start&amp;rdquo; at the right time, and I was even less confident that I hit &amp;ldquo;stop&amp;rdquo; right after crossing the finish line (I was guessing that I didn&amp;rsquo;t hit the button until a second or two after actually finishing).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After Abby finished, I kept telling her I was upset that I didn&amp;rsquo;t think I really went all out in the final minute of the race. Then I got over my disappointment and let it go; in the grand scheme of life it hardly matters!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;more-comments-about-the-race&#34;&gt;More comments about the race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby was initially confused that everyone got a medal for the race. It was to commemorate the 30th anniversary of this race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As usual, there were refreshments and snacks after the race provided by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.runaroundthesquare.com/#!sponsors&#34;&gt;many generous sponsors&lt;/a&gt;, and hot dogs and beer (I chose not to take any beer this year). I bumped into a lot of people I knew and met some friends of friends. One of them turned out to be someone who is apparently a friend of two completely different Pittsburgh friends I have. He took photos of Abby and me wearing our Vibram FiveFingers KSO Trek shoes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/85802484@N06/7858001266/&#34; title=&#34;&amp;quot;Run Around the Square&amp;quot;, Regent Square by sherpes39, on Flickr&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7253/7858001266_58020e37f8_z.jpg&#34; width=&#34;640&#34; height=&#34;480&#34; alt=&#34;&amp;quot;Run Around the Square&amp;quot;, Regent Square&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby likes this race because much of it is on the trails of Frick Park and we end in Fern Hollow, where there is a lot of greenery, nature at work (as opposed to some races we&amp;rsquo;ve done, which have been pure road races that end in some parking lot). Whenever I hear positive comments about this area, I am reminded of how long it took to redesign and restore Fern Hollow such that it is &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/15/snapshots-of-pittsburgh-from-a-12-mile-run/&#34;&gt;one of the real pleasures for me when I run in Frick Park&lt;/a&gt;. Ironically, I do remember the early days of Run Around The Square, which did end in Fern Hollow when it wasn&amp;rsquo;t quite as nice as it is now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, we appreciate the new moisture-wicking T-shirts given to those who registered. These shirts are much more practical and useful than the old cotton T-shirts. I&amp;rsquo;ll be happily wearing around the new Run Around The Square T-shirt when getting sweaty in the years to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;so-did-i-in-fact-achieve-my-time-goal&#34;&gt;So did I in fact achieve my time goal?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t know what really happened until many hours after the race when I saw the race results online: apparently my clock time was in fact 24:39.55, so I did finish before the &amp;ldquo;4&amp;rdquo; digit came to view. And my chip time (which is the one I consider my &amp;ldquo;real&amp;rdquo; time) was 24:35.6, nipping last year&amp;rsquo;s chip time of 24:36. I did it!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;running-this-race-over-the-years&#34;&gt;Running this race over the years&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A summary of the eight years that I&amp;rsquo;ve done Run Around The Square:
&lt;table style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 15px&#34;&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;th style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px; font-size: 1.1em&#34;&gt;Index&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;th style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px; font-size: 1.1em&#34;&gt;Year&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;th style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px; font-size: 1.1em&#34;&gt;Chip time&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;th style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px; font-size: 1.1em&#34;&gt;Comment&lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;2000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;27:23&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;First race ever, as part of radically changing my life at age 30&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;20&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;2001&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;23:19&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;4:04 faster after a year! Lost weight, trained seriously.&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;43&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;2002&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;23:01&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;18 seconds faster.&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;104&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;2006&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;23:27&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;Missed 3 years of the race; 26 seconds slower than last time&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;114&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;2008&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;24:39&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;Slow; untrained and unrested the night before race.&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;118&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;2009&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;25:20&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;Untrained; unmotivated to push hard at end.&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;121&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;2011&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;24:36&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;First time Abby ran in a race with me.&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;128&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;2012&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;24:35.6&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;Managed to achieve my best time since 2006!&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;goal-for-next-year&#34;&gt;Goal for next year?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t know what goal to set for next year. I suppose I could set a goal of getting yet faster, breaking 24:15. That sounds reasonable to me. Going back down to 24:00 may even be possible. It&amp;rsquo;s too early right now to tell. But one thing is for sure: I have no intention of slowing down from this year to next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Run Around The Square is a really fun community event and 5K race in Pittsburgh that I try to run every year when I can. It was my first race ever and this year&amp;rsquo;s was my 128th race, and it was Abby&amp;rsquo;s first race. Running a race for so many years allows me to appreciate its quirks, track the state of my fitness, and experience its evolution as an event. I&amp;rsquo;m very thankful for this long-running tradition that just celebrated its 30th anniversary with the help of the Regent Square community and all the sponsors.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I celebrated National Running Day in Schenley Park: remembering how I began to run 13 years ago</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/06/06/i-celebrated-national-running-day-in-schenley-park-remembering-how-i-began-to-run-13-year-ago/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Jun 2012 21:42:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/06/06/i-celebrated-national-running-day-in-schenley-park-remembering-how-i-began-to-run-13-year-ago/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/melissappc/663419600&#34; title=&#34;Schenley Park by Melissa McMasters, on Flickr&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1309/663419600_66449cdcc7.jpg&#34; width=&#34;333&#34; height=&#34;500&#34; alt=&#34;Schenley Park&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I celebrated &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.runningday.org/&#34;&gt;National Running Day&lt;/a&gt; by, uh, going out for a &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/running/&#34;&gt;run&lt;/a&gt;. Here in Pittsburgh, I have come to like most to run in &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburghparks.org/frick&#34;&gt;Frick Park&lt;/a&gt;, but today I decided to run in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pittsburghparks.org/schenley&#34;&gt;Schenley Park&lt;/a&gt; instead, as I was in a sentimental mood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ran the out and back &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~kalp/PGR/&#34;&gt;Pretty Good Race&lt;/a&gt; course on the Panther Hollow Trail in Schenley Park, as I have done at least several dozen times in the past thirteen years. My favorite part is always the long downhill return back to the start, during which I try to really fly down fast, feeling the wind rush past me. It&amp;rsquo;s the reward for having run uphill in the first half of the course!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~kalp/PGR/pg-race.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Pretty Good Race 5K course&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I was not always a runner. I only started to run at age 29, during a turning point in my life. And it turned out that Schenley Park played a vital role in getting me out the door and on my feet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(The details of my story are distilled from my emails and daily journal I kept in 1999-2004.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-and-when-i-started-to-run&#34;&gt;Why and when I started to run&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In early 1999, weighing 30 pounds more than I do now 13 years later (and being probably prediabetic, in retrospect), I decided to change my life by trying to fulfill a childhood dream of becoming a runner. You have to realize that I was completely out of shape at this stage of my life, barely able to run ten seconds without stopping!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I set a concrete goal to work toward in order to motivate myself to improve little by little. It turns out that Carnegie Mellon University has for decades sponsored a 5K race called the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~kalp/PGR/&#34;&gt;Pretty Good Race&lt;/a&gt; (the name inspired by Pittsburgh&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/25/blistered-but-blissful-in-the-burgh/&#34;&gt;Great Race 10K&lt;/a&gt;), held every year on Friday afternoon of the final week of the incoming computer science graduate student orientation program. A good number of incoming graduate students (as well as faculty, staff, and anyone else who is interested) take part in this race every year. The fast runners are very competitive, of course, but many run the race just for fun; there is a party afterwards for everyone who participates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided to aim to run in the Pretty Good Race in September 1999. I had many months to prepare for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-progress-in-running-recruiting-my-friend-john&#34;&gt;My progress in running: recruiting my friend John&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Progress was quite slow, because I had decades of poor conditioning to overcome. On February 10, 1999, I went for my first run with my friend John (a graduate student classmate of mine) for the first time. John was not much of a distance runner (he could sprint), but at least he had run in the Pretty Good Race in 1998 (and finished at the back of the pack). He was patient with me because I had rest quite frequently. &lt;strong&gt;I owe John for encouraging me and accompanying me.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, I was so out of shape that I could only &amp;ldquo;run&amp;rdquo; for ten or fifteen seconds at a time before getting chest and leg pains and having to walk for minutes before starting up again. I had no idea what I was doing. Also, we did this irregularly, not on a daily schedule or anything. So progress was slow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;failure-in-1999&#34;&gt;Failure in 1999&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that I was dealing with various personal problems in the summer of 1999 and also still not fit enough to run continuously for a mile. So in late August, I decided to give up on my goal, and did not run in the Pretty Good Race in 1999&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-new-motivation-in-2000-30th-birthday&#34;&gt;A new motivation in 2000: 30th birthday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In May, on my 30th birthday, I decided that I was going to get serious about running. I could not just continue to do my low-yield unsystematic run/walking with John. The very next day, I pushed myself harder than I had ever done before, running with John.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I shook off my &amp;ldquo;dependency&amp;rdquo; on John, and decided to run &lt;em&gt;every day&lt;/em&gt;, even if it meant doing it alone. I made extensive use of Frick Park near home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;scientific-training&#34;&gt;Scientific training&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started reading &amp;ldquo;The Runner&amp;rsquo;s Handbook&amp;rdquo;, recommended to me by my sister Linda months ago. Exactly nine days after my birthday, I wrote Linda email telling her that I planned to run the Pretty Good Race in September.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book said that a beginner should run at least twenty minutes, preferably thirty minutes, and at least three times a week, preferably five. This was much more than what I&amp;rsquo;d been doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wrote in my journal:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
I think I will aim to successfully run my Frick Park route for a few weeks, till I can comfortably run 20 minutes.  Then I will invent a new addition in Frick Park in order to make the run 30 minutes.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Progress became more noticeable as I focused on putting in the time and distance, going as slowly as required to avoid going anaerobic (my problem when running with John). Learning the science of distance running definitely helped a lot in making my training scientific.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;really-committing-to-running-the-pretty-good-race-in-2000&#34;&gt;Really committing to running the Pretty Good Race in 2000&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I managed to get some friends of mine to commit to also running in the Pretty Good Race for the first time, and we did a little bit of running together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;some-warmup-races&#34;&gt;Some warmup races&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ran the first races of my life right before the Pretty Good Race, in order to get a feel for what it was like racing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;run-around-the-square-5k&#34;&gt;Run Around the Square 5K&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My actual first 5K race was the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.runaroundthesquare.com/&#34;&gt;Run Around the Square&lt;/a&gt; in August 2000, just some weeks before the Pretty Good Race. It was &amp;ldquo;disastrous&amp;rdquo;, because I was completely inexperienced:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
I guess I went too fast, because before I reached the park entrance, I
wasn&#39;t feeling so well, and my right side was beginning to hurt
already.  I didn&#39;t think of myself as going fast, because so many
people were going faster and obviously way ahead.  There was no
crowding problem, because people were getting spread out.

Worse, when I reached the park entrance, I dashed down the steep,
curving hill, passing a lot of people, and almost fell off the trail.
When the uphill came, people started passing me.

I knew I was in trouble when it took me 9 minutes to get to the 1 mile
mark.

As the race progressed, I saw all kinds of people pass me: middle-aged
women, high-schoolers, old men.  It was embarrassing.  I was just
trying to avoid getting sick.  I was moving my feet slowly, and not
pushing off.  The feeling of people passing me was not encouraging.

I ended up grabbing water three times.

I took 18 minutes to get to the 2 mile mark.  At this point, I
believed I would probably take 27 minutes total, and I felt bad.

I didn&#39;t even bother to get in an extra kick when the end was near.  I
just didn&#39;t feel well.  I believe my time was 27:xx.  I took my pulse
right after I ripped off my chip and handed it to someone.  It was
200.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, my time was a very slow 27:23, and I was overambitious in my first race. But that was OK, because the point was to get experience so that in the race that mattered, the Pretty Good Race, hopefully I would do better. I was afraid of finishing dead last in the Pretty Good Race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(For the record, a year later, 2001, I ran 23:19 in this race.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;montour-trail-5k&#34;&gt;Montour Trail 5K&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A week before the Pretty Good Race, I ran in my second 5K race of my life, the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mtchalfmarathon.com/&#34;&gt;Montour Trail 5K&lt;/a&gt;. I did it in 25:30, being much more experienced as a result of the Run Around the Square.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(For the record, a year later, in 2001, I ran the Montour Trail half marathon instead, in 1:47:23, five days after running a 5K race in 21:39. Do the math: in one year I got my 5K time down from 27:23 to 21:39!!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;moment-of-truth-pretty-good-race-2000-http-www-cs-cmu-edu-kalp-pgr-2000-html&#34;&gt;Moment of truth: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~kalp/PGR/2000.html&#34;&gt;Pretty Good Race 2000&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My friends all beat me in the race, some pretty significantly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I finished in 26:26, in agony, in 27th place out of 32 (including the guy who ran backwards the whole way). OK, so I didn&amp;rsquo;t finish in last place after all!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I silently vowed to beat my friends in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~kalp/PGR/2001.html&#34;&gt;2001&lt;/a&gt;. I did. I came in 18th place out of 45, after training really hard for a year to improve my running. My time in 2001 was 22:33, over four minutes faster than in 2000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here I am outsprinting my friend Sungwoo at the finish:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pgr-2001-sungwoo-franklin.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Pretty Good Race 5K, 2001, closeup of Sungwoo and Franklin&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A mutual friend asked me why I was so intent on beating Sungwoo, and asked whether I had something against him. I said no, not at all. It was just a personal challenge, a goal, just like when I first starting running in races, and got beaten by a certain 70-something hunched-over old man repeatedly, I made him a concrete target to surpass in the future, and eventually I did. In this case, I had earlier judged that Sungwoo was closest in speed to me, and therefore I would aim to beat him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;other-years-of-running-the-pretty-good-race&#34;&gt;Other years of running the Pretty Good Race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2000: 26:26 (first time, and 3rd lifetime race)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2001: 22:33 (much better, 23rd race)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2002: did not run, because of half marathon the next day&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2003: did not run, because of half marathon the next day&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2004: simply chose not to run&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2005: 23:16 (little training)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2006: 22:57 (recovered some fitness)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2007: (almost no running this year, health declining)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2008: (almost no running this year, health declining)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2009: 25:52 (almost no running this year, in terrible health)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2010: 26:41 (almost no running this year, in terrible health)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2011: 24:36 (began running again, recovering my health)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-future&#34;&gt;The future&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year, 2012, I aim to get back under 24:00 in the Pretty Good Race, to return to my fitness level of early 2007 before my life was disrupted for half a decade during which I had trouble staying healthy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have done less running so far this year than I would have liked, unfortunately, but just being on the Pretty Good Race course again and feeling great to be out there reminded me to return to a regular running habit. I have three months before the next Pretty Good Race!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;but-why&#34;&gt;But why??&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this blog post I haven&amp;rsquo;t explained why I wanted to run, what my goals were, how they have changed over the years, and why I run now. I will write about those topics in detail later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For now, I&amp;rsquo;ll just say that &lt;strong&gt;I love to run&lt;/strong&gt;. I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t do it if I didn&amp;rsquo;t. (I know people who run but do not love it. I think &lt;a href=&#34;http://jones.wordpress.com/2012/06/04/things-ive-learnt-from-running/&#34;&gt;that is a mistake&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reflections on 2011</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/12/31/reflections-on-2011/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Dec 2011 18:52:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/12/31/reflections-on-2011/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I reflect on my year of 2011 as it ends. Since I did not start blogging until September, I go into more detail of what happened before then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;january&#34;&gt;January&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I continued our project of massively reorganizing our home, a project that began when she moved in during summer 2010. We were very grateful that Abby&amp;rsquo;s father helped out a lot.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I continued getting rid of a lot of stuff, including another eighteen boxes of my books, as I became an initially reluctant &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/minimalism/&#34;&gt;minimalist&lt;/a&gt;. We sold or gave away a &lt;em&gt;huge&lt;/em&gt; number of various of belongings.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby started cooking much more than in the past, and we enjoyed trying new dishes of her making.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I enjoyed some light cross-country skiing in the winter, using the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Schenley_Park_Golf_Course&#34;&gt;Bob O&amp;rsquo;Connor Golf Course at Schenley Park&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I began a weekly Zen &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/meditation/&#34;&gt;meditation&lt;/a&gt; session offered at Carnegie Mellon University.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started moving very gradually toward a &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/paleo/&#34;&gt;paleo&lt;/a&gt; diet and exercise routine, and immediately experienced benefits. &amp;ldquo;The Paleo Solution&amp;rdquo; by &lt;a href=&#34;http://robbwolf.com/&#34;&gt;Robb Wolf&lt;/a&gt; was very useful.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started learning modern &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/javascript/&#34;&gt;JavaScript&lt;/a&gt; for a new project at work, getting into client-side Web development. As part of that, I learned &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/jquery/&#34;&gt;jQuery&lt;/a&gt; through a free &lt;a href=&#34;http://p2pu.org/&#34;&gt;P2PU&lt;/a&gt; course and used it in the project.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started using &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/XQuery&#34;&gt;XQuery&lt;/a&gt; at work to process XML in a clear and concise way. I had used XSLT in the past, but it was very unpleasant.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I decided, for various reasons, to stop writing new &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/perl/&#34;&gt;Perl&lt;/a&gt; scripts and move to &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/python/&#34;&gt;Python&lt;/a&gt; instead.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started playing in my final (and disastrous) &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/chess/&#34;&gt;chess&lt;/a&gt; tournament, the Pittsburgh Chess Club Championship (which I had won in 2006 and 2007).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;february&#34;&gt;February&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pittsburgh was all about the Steelers, and I went to a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Super_Bowl_XLV&#34;&gt;Super Bowl&lt;/a&gt; party for the first time, but we lost!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I read &amp;ldquo;The Art of Non-Conformity&amp;rdquo; by &lt;a href=&#34;http://chrisguillebeau.com/&#34;&gt;Chris Guillebeau&lt;/a&gt; and found it so inspiring that I decided to take action and start making big changes to my life, in my own way.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;One big change: I quit playing chess, cold turkey, after having been unenthusiastic about it for months already (and playing correspondingly poorly). When the passion and enjoyment are gone, there is no point in hanging onto something just because it has been such an important part of my life for years.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;After years of not playing any music at all, I started playing &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/recorder/&#34;&gt;recorder&lt;/a&gt;, and vowed to play every single day if possible. Ten months later, I am still playing recorder.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I began attending a lot of &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/16/pittsburgh-software-developer-communities/&#34;&gt;local software developer group meetings&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started learning the &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/scala/&#34;&gt;Scala&lt;/a&gt; programming language and decided to use it on a small project.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;march&#34;&gt;March&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I continued our meditation practice at CMU, and went to our first mini-&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sesshin&#34;&gt;sesshin&lt;/a&gt; on a Saturday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I continued practicing recorder every single day, and joined the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.andrew.cmu.edu/user/lukas/pcars/Welcome.html&#34;&gt;local chapter of the American Recorder Society&lt;/a&gt;. It was very exciting to meet new people and to get into a wide range of music I had never really listened to or played.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I saw a video of &lt;a href=&#34;http://jakeshimabukuro.com/&#34;&gt;Jake Shimabukuro&lt;/a&gt; playing &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/ukulele/&#34;&gt;ukulele&lt;/a&gt; so beautifully that I was inspired to buy a ukulele and start learning to play it. (Unfortunately, it would turn out that time constraints caused me not to pursue ukulele far. This will change in 2012.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I got pulled into the Ruby programming language because it is well-supported on Mac OS and it is easy to install libraries and tools, of which there are many that are quite useful.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I went to &lt;a href=&#34;http://farmtotablepa.com/&#34;&gt;Farm to Table&lt;/a&gt; in Pittsburgh, and after that, Abby started moving toward paleo eating, with even better results than my smaller experiments earlier.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I started our &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/hiking/&#34;&gt;hiking&lt;/a&gt; season in the spring. Hiking is special to us; it was one of our first shared activities (after initially meeting during salsa dancing), and one we return to again and again. When there is no calendar conflict and the weather is acceptable, we like hiking almost every weekend from spring through fall.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;{% img /images/steves-soup-hike-2011-03-26.jpg Abby in front of me at Steve&amp;rsquo;s Soup Hike %}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;april&#34;&gt;April&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started wearing &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/fivefingers/&#34;&gt;Vibram FiveFingers shoes&lt;/a&gt; almost all the time, whether walking or running (but not yet for hiking).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I went to &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/yoga/&#34;&gt;yoga&lt;/a&gt; at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.clpgh.org/locations/squirrelhill/&#34;&gt;Squirrel Hill Library&lt;/a&gt; for the first time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;may&#34;&gt;May&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I began my experiment with barefoot running, in observation of &lt;a href=&#34;http://barefootrunners.org/ibrd&#34;&gt;International Barefoot Running Day&lt;/a&gt;. I started walking around barefoot at work, ignoring the confused looks or comments of colleagues. (I still go barefoot at work.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I bought a &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/melodica/&#34;&gt;melodica&lt;/a&gt;, inspired by the amazing performances of &lt;a href=&#34;http://jnote.org/&#34;&gt;James Howard Young&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I took a little vacation, spending some days in New York visiting Nathaniel and Yael and their baby. I finally fulfilled my dream (from before marriage) of taking Abby to Coney Island to walk on the boardwalk and at the beach, eating pizza, and riding the Wonder Wheel, just as I once did when I was six years old.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I started doing research into major home renovations for the summer.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I visited my parents, and my sister Linda and her husband Andre also visited, with my mother throwing a delayed reception at home for the both of us who had gotten married in the past two years. Abby got to meet my parents&amp;rsquo; friends, finally. And I went running with my brother-in-law for the first time! Also, I took Abby to the little park in Ann Arbor where as a too-shy teenager I used to go and sit on a particular bench and wish I were sitting with my dream girl. Mission accomplished!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;june&#34;&gt;June&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;John and I did a tough 19-mile training hike on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rachelcarsontrails.org/rct&#34;&gt;Rachel Carson Trail&lt;/a&gt; and decided we&amp;rsquo;d had enough of that trail, and I decided I was probably not going to do the 35-mile &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rachelcarsontrails.org/rct/challenge&#34;&gt;Rachel Carson Trail Challenge&lt;/a&gt; again (having completed it three times in the past).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;{% img /images/rachel-carson-trail-2011-06-05.jpg John on Rachel Carson Trail %}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby started wearing Vibram FiveFingers more and more for walking and running, and even walking barefoot on the streets (something I had not yet seriously done myself at the time).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I stupidly threw out my back during exercise, and my back took weeks to fully recover (I could still run and hike, but not lift weights). Never again, I hope. I felt like a 90-year-old when my back was hurting constantly.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;We started some home improvement projects.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;july&#34;&gt;July&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started gravitating to almost exclusively body weight &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/strength-training/&#34;&gt;strength training&lt;/a&gt;, as a reaction to my having injured my back earlier.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I went kayaking on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kiskiminetas_River&#34;&gt;Kiski River&lt;/a&gt; with &amp;ldquo;Fireman Steve&amp;rdquo; and the kayaking gang.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;On a longish hike, Abby surprised me by wearing Vibram FiveFingers shoes and they worked great for her, making her much faster and less sore, and I made a note to ditch my trail running shoes (which I had been using for years for hiking) in favor of FiveFingers for my next hike (which I did, and I have not gone back to regular shoes for hiking!).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I finally took Abby to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sandhillberries.com/&#34;&gt;Sand Hill Berries&lt;/a&gt; for tasty pie for the first time, always having intended to take her there when dating, but never having been in the vicinity with her then.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Major home renovation finally began, after much research, and we got electrical upgrade, insulation, and bathroom demolition and rebuilding. Very disruptive to our lives for weeks!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I did another mini-&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sesshin&#34;&gt;sesshin&lt;/a&gt; at CMU.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;After a lifetime of almost never drinking coffee (average of maybe three or four cups a year), I became an avid espresso fan (one small cup a day) as a result of my boss getting a machine at work.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started doing more barefoot running.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;august&#34;&gt;August&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bathroom renovation done at last.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I were regularly hiking in Vibram FiveFingers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;{% img /images/abby-franklin-soup-hike-vibram.jpg Abby and Franklin on Steve&amp;rsquo;s Soup Hike part 3 wearing Vibram FiveFingers %}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby joined me to run in her first ever 5K race, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.runaroundthesquare.com/&#34;&gt;Run Around the Square&lt;/a&gt; in Regent Square (mostly on the trails of Frick Park). What a special day! This race was my first ever 5K race when I started running in races in 2000.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started to learn &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/accordion/&#34;&gt;accordion&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;september&#34;&gt;September&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started running to work two or three times a week.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I ran in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~kalp/PGR/&#34;&gt;CMU SCS Pretty Good Race 5K&lt;/a&gt; together, her second 5K race.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I went to &lt;a href=&#34;http://podcamppittsburgh.com/&#34;&gt;PodCamp Pittsburgh&lt;/a&gt;, and after that, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/22/starting-a-new-web-site/&#34;&gt;I started this blog&lt;/a&gt; and proceeded to maintain a habit of posting every day (a routine that has been modified since then).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;october&#34;&gt;October&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started expanding beyond just writing for my blog, and began contributing to the Web through &lt;a href=&#34;http://twitter.com/franklinchen&#34;&gt;my Twitter account&lt;/a&gt; as well as writing comments on other people&amp;rsquo;s blog posts.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started taking Stanford online classes: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ml-class.org/&#34;&gt;Machine Learning&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.db-class.org/&#34;&gt;Introduction to Databases&lt;/a&gt;. (Blog posts on my experiences to appear soon.) Unfortunately, as a result of the extra time commitment, October through December were quite hectic for me.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I continued to move more toward a paleo diet.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;november&#34;&gt;November&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started playing &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/flute/&#34;&gt;flute&lt;/a&gt; again.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Probably because of fatigue and a compromised immune system, I came down with a skin ailment that I got serious treatment for, but it took almost two months to completely clear up and I spent over a month truly miserable &lt;sup&gt;24&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;7&lt;/sub&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;december&#34;&gt;December&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started playing Baroque flute.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started playing tin whistle.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I prepared for and made it through two music performances, playing recorder and flute (and almost tin whistle).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I ended the year completely exhausted, on the verge of getting sick, and took a long break from blogging.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The final week, Abby and I were on a hectic travel schedule that involved meeting up with her parents, my parents, her sister Carrie, Carrie&amp;rsquo;s boyfriend Alain, Alain&amp;rsquo;s parents, Alain&amp;rsquo;s extended family, my sister Linda, and her husband Andre. I am grateful that we got to meet up with so many people (and arranged for various of the individuals to meet up with various of the others!), but the trip was quite stressful to me, because I was not physically or emotionally prepared for it at all. (I will report later on what I learned from the experience.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2011 was quite a year for me and Abby. We had many changes and adventures in our lives: our home, our diet, our exercise, our outdoors activities, travel. For me, the biggest changes were quitting chess, starting music practice and performance, throwing myself into blogging and tweeting, getting more and more active in local software developer groups, applying new (to me) development tools at work, and in the fall, taking Stanford online courses in computer science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although I ended the year in poor shape, because of being overbooked, I am very excited by how many positive changes took place. I have an entirely new set of plans and priorities to formulate soon for 2012 in collaboration with Abby, in hope of learning from the lessons of my failures and omissions of 2011, and restoring balance.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>