<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Henry Purcell on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/henry-purcell/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Henry Purcell on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/henry-purcell/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Chatham Baroque: The Pleasures of Purcell</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/05/12/chatham-baroque-the-pleasures-of-purcell/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 May 2013 23:55:23 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/05/12/chatham-baroque-the-pleasures-of-purcell/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;It was a little crazy, but right after I came home from a mega-long &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/05/12/my-rachel-carson-trail-hike-for-the-year/&#34;&gt;Rachel Carson Trail hike today&lt;/a&gt;, I rushed to shower and change and run over to a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.chathambaroque.org/events/pleasures-purcell&#34;&gt;special concert, &amp;ldquo;The Pleasures of Purcell&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; by the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.chathambaroque.org/&#34;&gt;Chatham Baroque&lt;/a&gt; at the local &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.redeemerpittsburgh.org/&#34;&gt;Church of the Redeemer&lt;/a&gt; in the Squirrel Hill neighborhood. Objectively, I should have just called it a day after the hike, but I love the Chatham Baroque and learning from Annie earlier that they were playing in the neighborhood just several blocks from where I live made me decide to hop over there. (The concert was free to the public, but welcomed donations, of course: please remember to contribute generously when you attend these kinds of community good will events!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I attended in part because the musical genre was basically new to me: choral music by Henry Purcell. This is not my kind of thing, but I&amp;rsquo;m old enough that I&amp;rsquo;ve gotten tired of only listening to &amp;ldquo;my kind of thing&amp;rdquo; rather than exploring what is new to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ran into Annie as I was limping my way toward the church with sore feet. I also noticed that Sam from the Pittsburgh Recorder Society was a guest performer for some of the music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-concert&#34;&gt;The concert&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Chatham Baroque was joined by a choir and solo vocalists and conductor to fill out the forces needed to perform the music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was completely wowed by the bass soloist. The depth and expression of his voice was amazing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for the music itself, I&amp;rsquo;ve already confessed that mostly sacred choral music from this time period is not really my thing. I didn&amp;rsquo;t change my mind, although I was glad to have given it a shot. I have enjoyed playing the instrumental music of Henry Purcell for recorder, but this music for the English court didn&amp;rsquo;t do much for me.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>