<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Races on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/races/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Races on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/races/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Was it worth sprinting to a terrible fall to finish 25th in the CMU Pretty Good Race 5K?</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/09/06/was-it-worth-sprinting-to-a-terrible-fall-to-finish-25th-in-the-cmu-pretty-good-race-5k/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Sep 2013 22:01:27 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/09/06/was-it-worth-sprinting-to-a-terrible-fall-to-finish-25th-in-the-cmu-pretty-good-race-5k/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On a pleasant Friday late afternoon, not too hot or humid, I ran my 9th CMU Pretty Good Race 5K (and this was Abby&amp;rsquo;s 3rd).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two weeks ago, I did the Run Around The Square 5K in my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/08/24/reflections-on-my-slowest-run-around-the-square-5k-in-13-years/&#34;&gt;slowest time in 13 years&lt;/a&gt;. I was happy to be finishing a 5K race at all. I&amp;rsquo;ve improved some in fitness in the past two weeks, but not enough to make a big difference for today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like last year, I was going into this race not optimally fit. However, given that I just ran a 5K two weeks ago, I had a good idea of what I could do in another 5K, how hard I could push myself. Like I said last year, &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;It&amp;rsquo;s not about how fast I went, but how much I gave of what I had&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I never expected just how much I would give this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;before-the-race&#34;&gt;Before the race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I walked over from my office across Flagstaff Hill to Schenley Park.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pretty-good-race-2013/flagstaff-hill.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Flagstaff Hill&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For some reason, Abby decided to use our dinky Razor kick scooter to come in from home for the race. Unfortunately, she showed up before the race with a bloody hand and knee, having had a nasty fall while using the scooter on the way to Schenley Park. Oops. She&amp;rsquo;s been tired a lot lately (I previously mentioned her dangerous &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/08/24/reflections-on-my-slowest-run-around-the-square-5k-in-13-years/&#34;&gt;decline in fitness all year&lt;/a&gt;) and was regretting signing up to do the Pretty Good Race with me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She tried to be a good sport despite the accident coming in.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pretty-good-race-2013/abby-before.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby before race&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here I am in orange:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pretty-good-race-2013/franklin-before.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin before race&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;weather-conditions&#34;&gt;Weather conditions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Temperature and humidity were much, much better than last year. That promised a considerable time advantage relative to last year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-plan&#34;&gt;The plan&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As with last year, my plan was to make the most of the final downhill part of the course, as well as go for a sprint to pass as many people as I possibly could during the final brief but terrible uphill to the finish line. I was going to have to pace myself intelligently to have something left for the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-race&#34;&gt;The race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I paced myself, not going too fast in the first half of the race. I almost entirely ran my own slow race, as there was nobody else really near my steady pace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After turning around, I starting going hard downhill. I was worried that I didn&amp;rsquo;t see Abby at all during the race. At some point, I passed her walking back to the start. She must have dropped out very early on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was pushing really hard in the final part of the race. Near the uphill finish, I saw a guy slowing down, and he raised his arms as though celebrating finishing. This gesture instantly caused me to go into a sprint more furious than any other sprint finish in my entire life. I made up a huge distance and reached the finish chute just a step before he did. And as I did so, the dry gravel and my leaning too far forward caused me to slip and fall, really, really badly. But I had finished ahead of the guy. Mission accomplished.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;injuries&#34;&gt;Injuries&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I lay stunned and in terrible pain for a few seconds. I had to check whether I was seriously broken. It felt like I was not. I was rather injured, but miraculously, no broken bones. I had managed to break my fall not with my teeth or eyes or fingers, but with my left thigh, right knee, left forearm, left palm, and right palm. I was quite badly scraped and bruised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I heard people asking me, &amp;ldquo;Was it worth it?&amp;rdquo; I didn&amp;rsquo;t know how to answer that. I moved on, stumbling in pain as I tried to catch my breath. I had done what I do, give the race my all, and then some. I was gouged and bleeding, and my right knee had swollen up hugely almost instantly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This wasn&amp;rsquo;t the worst falling injury I&amp;rsquo;ve had in my life, but it&amp;rsquo;s probably my worst since a fall off a bike (also spinning off loose gravel) twenty years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pretty-good-race-2013/left-palm.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Left palm&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pretty-good-race-2013/left-thigh.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Left thigh&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pretty-good-race-2013/right-knee.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Right knee&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pretty-good-race-2013/left-arm.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Left arm&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby returned, and had to explain to the volunteers that she wasn&amp;rsquo;t just finishing, but had dropped out earlier. While I was trying to clean myself up some, she said that she had fallen early on during the race and decided that that was enough and she wasn&amp;rsquo;t going to finish the race. So this is her first Did Not Finish (DNF) in a race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;feeling-lucky&#34;&gt;Feeling lucky&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main thing I kept on feeling while we walked back to my office and then back to my car (very slowly; everything around my right knee was just messed up) and went home for both of us to clean up from our injuries: &lt;em&gt;luck&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It could have been much worse for both of us. My most severe damage was not even to my right knee area (even though walking was difficult) but really my left hand, whose heel of palm was basically scraped away and bruised and my wrist was messed up. But no broken fingers or teeth or wrists or ankles. Same with Abby: lucky us!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;was-it-worth-it&#34;&gt;Was it worth it?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I finished officially tied for 25th place with the guy I actually beat, both of us registering as finishing in 25:28 in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~kalp/PGR/2013.html&#34;&gt;official race results&lt;/a&gt;. Well, I ran 37 seconds faster than last year. That&amp;rsquo;s not nothing, although two years ago I ran 24:36.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I knew the time was not going to be great: I just ran 25:36 in Run Around The Square two weeks ago. The real point was that like last year, I gave it my all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But was it worth getting injured for sprinting for no glory whatsoever? It&amp;rsquo;s not like I was running for first place or something &amp;ldquo;important&amp;rdquo;. Or is that the wrong way to think about it? Why is it worth trying your best for first place but not for 25th place instead of 26th place? Let&amp;rsquo;s ignore the (unfortunate?) fact that in some circles, first place is associated with large monetary rewards, when pondering that question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A different question would be, &amp;ldquo;If you knew you would get this injured from this sprint, would you have done it anyway?&amp;rdquo; I guess the question is &amp;ldquo;no&amp;rdquo;. But how could I &lt;em&gt;know&lt;/em&gt;? There is always risk. There is risk crossing the street, or driving on the turnpike. I&amp;rsquo;ve never fallen during a sprint before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another different question: &amp;ldquo;How will this accident change how you run in the future?&amp;rdquo; I suppose my answer is, I&amp;rsquo;ll be more careful to keep my balance. But am I going to stop the sprinting at the end of a race? I don&amp;rsquo;t see how I can. &lt;em&gt;It is in those moments when I can barely breathe and the world is becoming a blur that I am living with most intensity and purity.&lt;/em&gt; These moments don&amp;rsquo;t come often, but when they are available for the taking, why would I not accept these gifts?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will keep sprinting. I will keep trying to beat whoever is beatable in front of me. That&amp;rsquo;s part of the whole point of racing. I admit to feeling a little odd to being so serious about it when others do it much more casually (and it&amp;rsquo;s their right to do so and they&amp;rsquo;re probably smarter and more balanced than me, I concede). But I don&amp;rsquo;t race often, so when I do, I try to make it matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So my response is: I will need to work on maintaining balance and running on tricky surfaces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, Abby and I decided we should make sure to have a first aid kit around in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-next-race&#34;&gt;The next race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My eleventh Great Race 10K is coming up. I want to do considerably better than I did last year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, I have a lot of healing to do. I am more of a wreck right now than the post-race photos indicate. Things are all swollen and messed up and probably will be for an entire week or two. It&amp;rsquo;s just amazing I haven&amp;rsquo;t broken bones or ligaments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I simultaneously had unfortunate falling accidents today. I was proud to have run as hard as I could given my fitness and will. I don&amp;rsquo;t regret sprinting for 25th place, even if it cost me this time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, we both need to heal.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reflections on my slowest Run Around the Square 5K in 13 years</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/08/24/reflections-on-my-slowest-run-around-the-square-5k-in-13-years/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Aug 2013 12:45:47 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/08/24/reflections-on-my-slowest-run-around-the-square-5k-in-13-years/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This year was the ninth time I ran in the annual &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.runaroundthesquare.com/&#34;&gt;Run Around The Square 5K race&lt;/a&gt;, and Abby&amp;rsquo;s third year in a row. The conditions were great: cool and dry, in contrast to the usual hot and humid conditions at this time of year. (Last year I reported on &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/08/25/my-eighth-time-doing-run-around-the-square-5k/&#34;&gt;my eighth running of the race&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both Abby and I ran this race rather slowly, but were happy and enjoyed the day. Here&amp;rsquo;s why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;both-of-us-coming-back-from-setbacks&#34;&gt;Both of us coming back from setbacks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing to note is that both Abby and I have been recovering from setbacks this year, as I reported two weeks ago after I ran the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/08/09/getting-up-when-reality-punches-you-in-the-face-running-the-second-liberty-mile-in-pittsburgh/&#34;&gt;second GNC Live Well Liberty Mile&lt;/a&gt; 18 seconds slower than last year. That race had me vowing to get back on track, and the very next day I did &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/08/10/emerging-from-my-three-months-of-illness-self-pitying-and-self-loathing/&#34;&gt;begin getting back on track&lt;/a&gt;. The road back to a regular exercise routine has not been easy in the past two weeks, but I have very gradually ramping up on running as well as minimal strength training every single day since then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, I ran the Run Around The Square 5K in 24:35.6 and was pretty to have recovered from several years of decline in fitness and self-care, by running my best time since 2006. For this year, I wrote, &amp;ldquo;I don&amp;rsquo;t know what goal to set for next year. I suppose I could set a goal of getting yet faster, breaking 24:15. That sounds reasonable to me. Going back down to 24:00 may even be possible. It&amp;rsquo;s too early right now to tell. But one thing is for sure: I have no intention of slowing down from this year to next.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, I did not set a firm enough goal. I have learned the hard way that if you don&amp;rsquo;t make a commitment (and then follow up with the discipline and sacrifices required to achieve it), then even in the absence of accidents, a maybe-goal is worthless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year, I went into the 5K race so untrained (two weeks of slowly ramping up before the race is not enough for any training benefits to kick in) that I basically knew that I was going to be super slow. I figured that since I lost 18 seconds in the mile, I would be happy if I lost only one minute in a 3K. So that was my expectation: finish around 25:36 this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;before-the-race&#34;&gt;Before the race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided that this was the race in which I debut my new orange running singlet, to replace my over-decade use of a blue singlet that Abby has gotten very annoyed with:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-around-the-square-2013/franklin-orange.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin wearing orange singlet&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Also, note that since I bought a SPIbelt earlier this year, I now always run races wearing a SPIbelt to carry my phone. This is particularly convenient when running a race where you have to park far from the start line and want access to your phone after a race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wore my Vibram FiveFingers KSO Trek shoes again. Since last year&amp;rsquo;s fiasco in which I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/30/running-my-10th-great-race-10k-obscene-but-in-a-good-way/&#34;&gt;injured my left foot from having the straps on my left foot too tight&lt;/a&gt;, I never again put the straps on too tight!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hanging out before the race start in Regent Square:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-around-the-square-2013/before.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Before start&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-around-the-square-2013/franklin-ready.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin ready&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Start line just a few minutes before race start:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-around-the-square-2013/start-line.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Start line&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-race&#34;&gt;The race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(&lt;a href=&#34;http://runhigh.com/2013RESULTS/R082413AA.html&#34;&gt;Race results.&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;different-race-logistics&#34;&gt;Different race logistics&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One very important change to the race, and one I greatly appreciated, was the staggered start. Faster runners were told to line up front and start up first. This is very helpful to control the congestion and confusion that happens in a large race when too many slower people start up front and have to be passed (including unfortunately young children that Abby and I have seen trampled on every year!). In particular, it is really tricky to be passing lots of people once in the trails of Frick Park.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;first-mile&#34;&gt;First mile&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of the ridiculous problems I created for myself by going too fast two weeks ago in the Liberty Mile, I vowed to go out at a reasonable pace in this 5K. I found this easy to do because of the staggered start, which meant that there were fewer people to have to accelerate past throwing off one&amp;rsquo;s own internal speedometer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The usual lot of young and old musicians were playing music along the course. What a great neighborhood tradition!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still get confused seeing the champagne stop near the end of the first mile at the entrance into the trails of Frick Park.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did the first mile in a leisurely 8:15 (compared to 7:18 last year).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;second-mile&#34;&gt;Second mile&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did the second mile in 10:17 (compared to 10:11 last year). I did not feel too bad. I was running a bit conservatively, because my training runs had been so slow and short and tough for me in the past two weeks. I wanted to be in position to run really well the final downhill in the third mile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;third-mile&#34;&gt;Third mile&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I let loose in the third mile. Because I had avoided going pukey in the second mile, I covered it in 7:06, actually a second faster than the 7:07 of last year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of the staggered start, there was not bad congestion during the third mile, and I found it safe to pass people at will.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;final-sprint&#34;&gt;Final sprint&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t have a gut-wrenching final sprint. I wasn&amp;rsquo;t even looking at the clock or my watch. This wasn&amp;rsquo;t one of those races in which I put it all out there on the course. Instead, this was a race where I was grateful to be running at all, and had no expectations other than to finish strong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I finished in 25:38, just a bit longer than a minute over last year&amp;rsquo;s 24:35.6. My &lt;em&gt;slowest&lt;/em&gt; Run Around The Square 5K time &lt;em&gt;in 13 years&lt;/em&gt;. But it was a clean finish, and I was so excited to simply be back and running faster than 26 minutes, at least.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;after-the-race&#34;&gt;After the race&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although I was not pukey, I was certainly breathing hard when I finished.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-around-the-square-2013/franklin-after.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin after the race&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I went off to drink water and start eating some food.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-around-the-square-2013/view.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;View&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;improvement&#34;&gt;Improvement&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I went back to the finish line to wait for Abby to finish. I saw Todd and his wife Gabrielle hanging around. Gabrielle said she took my &amp;ldquo;advice&amp;rdquo; (from last year) to go all out to the point of feeling pukey. I admitted that this time around, I didn&amp;rsquo;t follow my own advice. Gabrielle finished over 5 minutes faster this year than last year!! Todd finished over 8 minutes faster!! It&amp;rsquo;s great to see people in their late 40s improve their fitness so much in a single year. I saw the couple running together a couple of times in Frick Park this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;decline&#34;&gt;Decline&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby finished. She was out of breath and pukey, but I was proud of her for finishing. Because of the tremendous decline in health and fitness she has experienced this year, I was not sure she would actually finish the race.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-around-the-square-2013/abby-finish.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby finishing&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;more-food-and-refreshments&#34;&gt;More food and refreshments&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We lined up to sample more food and recovered. It was a beautiful day to be outside.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-around-the-square-2013/abby-recovered.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-around-the-square-2013/franklin-recovered.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The hot dogs and beer line was particularly long, but we finally reached the tables.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-around-the-square-2013/hot-dogs-beer.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Hot dogs and beer&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;walking-out-of-frick-park-back-to-the-car&#34;&gt;Walking out of Frick Park back to the car&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I couldn&amp;rsquo;t help taking a photo of the sign for beer and champagne that was still up on the trail entrance as we passed by:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-around-the-square-2013/beer-champagne.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Dunning&amp;#39;s beer and champagne stop&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;concern-about-abby&#34;&gt;Concern about Abby&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although I was happy that Abby managed to finish the 5K race, I was very concerned about her overall health and fitness, which have continued to be poor this year since she broke her foot in February. Here are her Run Around The Square 5K times since she started doing it with me:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2011: 37:15&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2012: 36:04&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2013: 39:54&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She was almost 4 minutes slower than last year. She&amp;rsquo;s lost &lt;em&gt;several years of fitness&lt;/em&gt; this year, and came in 105th of 116 in her age group. Again, we are grateful she is walking and running at all, but this has been a very bad year for her, and this impacts not only her own life, but ours more generally. We need to work on getting her back on track.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;goal-for-next-year&#34;&gt;Goal for next year?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right now, my real goal is to simply continue my exercise program and not break it again, and that includes the winter slump I usually enter. Last year, I had a slump in the final months of the year, and then woke up and &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/28/meditations-on-climbing-the-36-floors-of-the-pitt-cathedral-of-learning/&#34;&gt;started exercising again around New Year&lt;/a&gt;, and even signed up for the Pittsburgh Marathon as a way to force myself to stay active in the winter. I believe that if I simply avoid self-caused setbacks, I should be able to return myself to a decent level of fitness. I am &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; going to sign up for the Pittsburgh Marathon again. Almost certainly, however, I will sign up for the Pittsburgh Half Marathon! Last winter, I rather enjoyed &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/30/report-on-just-a-short-run-my-first-half-marathon-in-nine-years/&#34;&gt;training for and running the Just A Short Run half marathon&lt;/a&gt;. I reached good fitness through that, but squandered my fitness through overtraining and injury leading up to the marathon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;races-this-year&#34;&gt;Races this year&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the shorter term, I have two races to run in the coming month: the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/07/running-my-8th-pretty-good-race-5k-dealing-with-disappointment/&#34;&gt;CMU Pretty Good Race 5K&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/30/running-my-10th-great-race-10k-obscene-but-in-a-good-way/&#34;&gt;Great Race 10K&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, I did very poorly in the Pretty Good Race 5K because I was injured and exhausted, running 26:05. This year, I expect to do better than that. I&amp;rsquo;m not going to do the 24:36 of 2011, but given that I easily beat 26 minutes today, I will beat 26 minutes two weeks from now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Great Race 10K last year, I was still in a state of exhaustion and undertraining, so I didn&amp;rsquo;t even pay any attention to time goals, and finished slowly in 48:23. I see no reason why, if I continue improving my fitness in the next month (in contrast to last year&amp;rsquo;s dreadful September), I should not be able to run under 48:00.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;update-of-2013-09-06&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-09-06)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/09/06/was-it-worth-sprinting-to-a-terrible-fall-to-finish-25th-in-the-cmu-pretty-good-race-5k/&#34;&gt;my report on running the Pretty Good Race 5K this year&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Run Around The Square continued to thrive and improve, and I&amp;rsquo;m grateful for both the registration cap (to maintain the quality of the event) as well as the staggered start. And all the sponsors feeding us afterwards!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I were happy to have finished the race, even if we are both less fit now than we have been in years. But I think this is a wake up call for us to get back in shape. For example, I miss the long hikes we used to do last year when we had the stamina to actually do and enjoy them. The example Todd and Gabrielle set as they massively improved their fitness in the past year is inspiring. Abby and I should be able to do this too, if we make it a priority.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Getting up when reality punches you in the face: running the second Liberty Mile in Pittsburgh</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/08/09/getting-up-when-reality-punches-you-in-the-face-running-the-second-liberty-mile-in-pittsburgh/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Aug 2013 20:49:35 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/08/09/getting-up-when-reality-punches-you-in-the-face-running-the-second-liberty-mile-in-pittsburgh/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Last year, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/08/17/the-inaugural-liberty-mile-a-review-of-pittsburghs-first-road-mile-race/&#34;&gt;I reported on the excitement I had running in and watching&lt;/a&gt; the first &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.libertymile.org/&#34;&gt;GNC Live Well Liberty Mile&lt;/a&gt;. I was so excited about running it again that late this May, having mostly recovered from my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/05/06/2013-pittsburgh-marathon-my-135th-race-was-my-worst-i-finished/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Marathon disaster&lt;/a&gt;, I quickly pre-registered for the Liberty Mile for this year. I anticipated training to run well in this year&amp;rsquo;s Liberty Mile, given that I was not really trained last year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, this year I have been in very poor shape since the marathon, because of a whole series of health problems and disruptions in my life resulting from a skin rash I got during a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/05/12/my-rachel-carson-trail-hike-for-the-year/&#34;&gt;Rachel Carson Trail hike in May&lt;/a&gt;. The upshot is that I have been running (and exercising in general) very little in the past three months. As the Liberty Mile approached, I wished that I had not registered for it at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I faced a dilemma: what should I do about the race?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;deciding-to-run-it&#34;&gt;Deciding to run it&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The good thing about the mile is that it&amp;rsquo;s short enough that of course I can finish the thing. So I felt there was no excuse to just bail out and forfeit my pre-registration. I was going to run it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bad thing about the mile is that it is brutal to actually run &lt;em&gt;fast&lt;/em&gt;. I have always felt pukey after running a mile as &amp;ldquo;fast&amp;rdquo; as I can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, I decided to still try to run the Liberty Mile as fast as I could, knowing that I would probably suffer for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In recent weeks I&amp;rsquo;ve been trying to go out periodically for short, slow runs, something like two miles at a time, to gain at least have &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; kind of conditioning. Also, earlier this week I put in some &amp;ldquo;fast&amp;rdquo; repeats of about 300m out in Frick Park: the only &amp;ldquo;fast&amp;rdquo; running I&amp;rsquo;ve done since April!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this whole week I was feeling bad, stress exacerbated by home repair disruptions with the contractors coming over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;support-from-abby&#34;&gt;Support from Abby&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, I went to the race alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year, Abby offered to go downtown with me so she could watch the race and be with me. (In May when I was pre-registering for the race, she had just spent months barely mobile because of a broken foot and was simply not certain she would be able to even run a mile again by August.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really appreciated this because I felt rather vulnerable about this race. We planned to watch the first wave start, and then have me run my heat (again the &amp;ldquo;Unstoppable 40+&amp;rdquo; heat), then hang out afterwards and watch the elite heats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We drove downtown and parked and walked to the packet pickup area in Market Square. I was pleased that it wasn&amp;rsquo;t raining; it had rained earlier in the day, but that was all over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because we arrived later than other people, they had run out of Small T-shirts and so I got a Medium.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/liberty-mile-2013/abby.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby holding my T-shirt&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;changes-in-the-course&#34;&gt;Changes in the course&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I should note that the course was changed from last year. The change makes sense because it considerably simplifies the logistics. Last year, the course was a straight shot down Liberty Ave toward downtown. This year, the course was an almost-loop course, first going out on Penn Ave, then turning to head back in on Liberty Ave. The advantage is that the start and finish are close together, so it is much easier for people to plan to spectate or get back to their cars or whatever. I do like the concept of the straight downhill road course, but understand the logistical difficulties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My plan was to do my best to avoid going out too fast, and try to push hard in the final downhill portion of the race. Easier said than done, because last year I certainly wanted to avoid going out too fast, but did anyway!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;before-the-race&#34;&gt;Before the race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wore my Vibram FiveFingers Bikila LS shoes again.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/liberty-mile-2013/before-start.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin before race&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At the GNC booth, I saw they were giving out free samples of energy bars and other stuff. I was feeling hungry, and although I know that it is best not to race having just eaten, especially unfamiliar foods, I took a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.gnc.com/product/index.jsp?productId=4468895&#34;&gt;GNC Pro Performance Pro Crunch Lite&lt;/a&gt; energy bar, and ate a couple of bites before giving the remainder to Abby to put away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was probably a big mistake to have eaten from the energy bar, because it didn&amp;rsquo;t really agree with me. Oops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;start-and-finish-lines&#34;&gt;Start and finish lines&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We checked out the start and finish lines.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/liberty-mile-2013/start-line.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Start line&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/liberty-mile-2013/finish-line.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Finish line&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;first-heat-at-7-00-pm&#34;&gt;First heat (at 7:00 PM)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We watched as the first &amp;ldquo;fun run&amp;rdquo; heat went.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/liberty-mile-2013/first-heat-start.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-race-heat-at-7-20-pm&#34;&gt;My race (heat at 7:20 PM)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got to the start line and lined up &lt;em&gt;at the back&lt;/em&gt;, where I knew I belonged. I was not sure that I would not be last place in my heat!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/liberty-mile-2013/my-heat-start.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here I am, looking as tired as I in fact was, still taking medication for my skin problem that is not completely gone (usually showing up as spots on my neck or hands and arms):&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/liberty-mile-2013/franklin-before.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin before the race&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As the race began, I tried not to go too fast, but did. 1:34 for the first quarter mile, not good at all! Last year, I ran the mile in 6:39, and went out in 1:29 for the first quarter. This year, I was hoping to go under 7:00 at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I slowed down for the second quarter, then finally found a steady pace for the third quarter. During the final quarter, I saw the finish line and eventually saw the clock ticking up toward 7:00. I was &lt;em&gt;furious&lt;/em&gt; that I might not be able to finish a 7-minute mile. I sprinted all out and didn&amp;rsquo;t actually finish under 7:00 according to the clock (the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.areep.com/events/libertymile/&#34;&gt;official race results&lt;/a&gt; say I finished in 7:02), but my chip time was 6:56, so I actually did run the mile in under 7 minutes!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My splits:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1:34 (went too fast)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1:56 (uphill, deliberately slowed down)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1:46 (steady)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1:40 (final kick)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;more-photos-of-the-liberty-mile&#34;&gt;More photos of the Liberty Mile&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More photos of the entire event can be seen &lt;a href=&#34;http://petemadia.photoshelter.com/gallery/2013-GNC-Live-Well-Liberty-Mile/G0000gQc.MfyoOAE/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;after-my-race&#34;&gt;After my race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Afterwards, I felt really, really crappy:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/liberty-mile-2013/done-in-pain.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin done for a while but still in pain&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In fact, for a full half hour after the race, all I could do was walk and sit around with Abby trying to feel less crappy. &lt;strong&gt;I have never felt so bad for so long after any race of any distance.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;reflections&#34;&gt;Reflections&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mentally, also, I was still very &lt;em&gt;angry&lt;/em&gt; at myself: I came in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.areep.com/events/libertymile/results/13lm_uno.txt&#34;&gt;60th place out of 74&lt;/a&gt;, running a chip time of 6:56, a whopping &lt;em&gt;18 seconds&lt;/em&gt; slower than last year. That&amp;rsquo;s a huge decrease in fitness for a mile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My plan for this year, 2013, was supposed to be to get back into great health and fitness, &amp;ldquo;the shape I was in five years ago&amp;rdquo;. It&amp;rsquo;s why, for the new year, I got into &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/28/meditations-on-climbing-the-36-floors-of-the-pitt-cathedral-of-learning/&#34;&gt;climbing the Cathedral of Learning&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s why I got into running in the winter](/blog/2012/12/31/why-i-went-frick-park-trail-running-in-snowfall-for-the-first-time-in-a-decade/). It&amp;rsquo;s why I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/30/why-and-how-i-am-going-to-run-the-2013-pittsburgh-marathon/&#34;&gt;decided to run the Pittsburgh Marathon&lt;/a&gt;. I blew it my overtraining for the marathon and then suffering freak skin problems after a hike that ended up seeing doctors something like five times, and being put on medication that messed with me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a lot to be angry about. But after I recovered, I became calm and stopped being angry about being punched in the face by reality. I decided that it was motivation for me to turn my life around. I decided that I was going to get back into a regular exercise routine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In just the past three months, I have lost all of my fitness of the past several years. But I have a plan to get back on track, starting &lt;em&gt;tomorrow&lt;/em&gt;. I believe that for 2014, I can still get back into my 2008 shape. It&amp;rsquo;s a matter of making it a priority, over all the other things I have been doing in my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;going-home&#34;&gt;Going home&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After I recovered enough that I felt like eating and walking again, Abby and I went back to our car and we went home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only minutes after getting home did I realize that I had &lt;em&gt;totally forgotten&lt;/em&gt; to stick around to watch the elite runners&amp;rsquo; races!! That was far from my mind when I was feeling nauseous and reflecting on my poor fitness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The race was very well organized, and I&amp;rsquo;m thankful for the continuation of this new Pittsburgh tradition. Although I had a humbling experience in my heat, I totally want to be back for a third try at executing a good mile next year! And I am thankful that I actually ran it, because it gave me the resolve to regain my lost fitness.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Going out too fast yet again in my third Random Distance Run</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/04/19/going-out-too-fast-yet-again-in-my-third-random-distance-run/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Apr 2013 22:38:23 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/04/19/going-out-too-fast-yet-again-in-my-third-random-distance-run/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/random-distance-run-2013.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;CMU Random Distance Run 2013&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For the third time, I ran in the annual &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~RDR/&#34;&gt;Random Distance Run&lt;/a&gt; held on the 400m outdoor track at Carnegie Mellon University. It was a cold, rainy Friday afternoon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was also my first race ever while wearing my Luna Sandals (the 7mm Venado).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;history&#34;&gt;History&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Random Distance Run first came to CMU &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~RDR/results-2003.html&#34;&gt;in 2003&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The concept is very geeky. What happens is that a giant pair of six-sided dice are rolled, and the sum of the rolls is how many laps you have to run around the track: so the minimum number of total laps is 2 (800m) and the maximum is 12 (4.8K).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The catch is that &lt;em&gt;only one die&lt;/em&gt; is rolled before the race begins, and then the second die is rolled only when the fastest runner is about to finish the number of laps from the first die. The second die indicates how many more laps to run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, there is an element of luck to who the winner of the race is: someone who went out very fast and then got lucky with a roll of a 1 for the second die could conceivably beat someone who was a fitter runner but went out conservatively for the first die and then found it too late to sprint for an additional lap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I am not a very fast runner, these gambles don&amp;rsquo;t really apply to me: my most rational strategy (to avoid a lot of suffering while avoiding going much too slow) would seem to be to run at a pace that is correct for the number of laps for the first die plus 3, or something like that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-first-random-distance-run-2003&#34;&gt;My first Random Distance Run (2003)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, in my first Random Distance Run, ten years ago, I accidentally went out too fast even given my intent. Not normally running on a track, I have always found it hard to gauge my pace accurately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rolls were 4 and 2, for a total of 6 laps (2.4K).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the first die, I went out too fast in the first lap, then tried to slow down to a sustainable pace:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1:22.34&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1:38.67&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1:43.68&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1:42.63&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the second die was low, I sped back up to complete the final two laps:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1:37.22&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1:33.07&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The winner of the 2003 Random Distance Run did in fact gamble for the win, shooting out really fast for the first 4 laps, and the gamble paid off, as you can see in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~RDR/results-2003.html&#34;&gt;results&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-second-random-distance-run-2006&#34;&gt;My second Random Distance Run (2006)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~RDR/results-2006.html&#34;&gt;2006&lt;/a&gt;, the rolls were 6 and 5, for a total of 11 laps (4.4K). I still went out too fast in the first lap, but did slow down enough to not completely die.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First die:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1:32.08&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1:42.27&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1:43.90&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1:45.82&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1:44.93&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1:50.55&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second die:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1:50.41&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1:53.89&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1:54.57&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1:51.49&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1:42.85&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The winner in this year, Arjun, scored partially because he was a fast-improving runner who was not known among the favorites who were in the race. They didn&amp;rsquo;t know who he was and let him go ahead thinking he would die, but he was strong and they couldn&amp;rsquo;t catch up in the second half! I still remember them at the end of the race basically asking, &amp;ldquo;Who is this guy?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-third-random-distance-run-2013&#34;&gt;My third Random Distance Run (2013)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, this year, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~RDR/results-2013.html&#34;&gt;2013&lt;/a&gt;, I had no real track training. Furthermore, I am nowhere as fit as I was seven or ten years ago, and in addition, ran the race as part of a very tough final training week for the Pittsburgh Marathon, so this race was just for fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Worst of all, I had eaten a rather large, heavy lunch, thanks to the annual CMU Carnival BBQ:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/cmu-carnival-bbq-2013.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;CMU Carnival BBQ 2013&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Not the kind of food I eat every day, and certain not just before a serious race!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was 3 and 3 for a total of 6 laps (2.4K).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went out too fast, then deliberately slowed down. Actually, I ended up slowing down too much, because in the final lap I sped up and had more left than I gave. I did put in a silly ferocious finishing sprint that resulted in beating two runners ahead of me by almost four seconds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First die:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1:36&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1:48&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1:51&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second die:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1:55&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1:54&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1:44&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amusingly, the runner I beat at the end was the same one I ended up beating near the end of the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/07/running-my-8th-pretty-good-race-5k-dealing-with-disappointment/&#34;&gt;Pretty Good Race&lt;/a&gt; last year. I hadn&amp;rsquo;t actually realized during the race that it was her again that was my target.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My legs felt banged up after the race, from not only the cumulative fatigue of my marathon training for the week, but also because of that sprint I did. It was probably unwise of me to have thrown that in there, given that tomorrow morning I am scheduled to do a tough training run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;cool-t-shirt&#34;&gt;Cool T-shirt&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/random-distance-run-2013-t-shirt-front.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;CMU Random Distance Run 2013 T-shirt front&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/random-distance-run-2013-t-shirt-back.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;CMU Random Distance Run 2013 T-shirt back&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed returning to doing the annual CMU Random Distance Run. Unfortunately, I&amp;rsquo;ve run it poorly each year that I&amp;rsquo;ve done it, going out too fast. I plan to run this race again next year but actually do some preparation ahead of time in order to figure out how to run consistently on the track amidst the mayhem of slow and fast and lapped runners. I guess I&amp;rsquo;ll need to watch what I eat on the day of the race, as well.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Fineview Stepathon 2012: Pittsburgh&#39;s grueling urban trail race</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/10/06/the-fineview-stepathon-2012-pittsburghs-grueling-urban-trail-race/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Oct 2012 23:07:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/10/06/the-fineview-stepathon-2012-pittsburghs-grueling-urban-trail-race/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://thenorthsidechronicle.com/UserFiles/Image/stepathon.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Stepathon steps&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Today I ran in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.thenorthsidechronicle.com/2061_php?calendarDate=2012-10-04&#34;&gt;annual&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://stepathon.org/&#34;&gt;Fineview Stepathon&lt;/a&gt;, a truly unique and grueling 5-mile race held in &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fineview_(Pittsburgh)&#34;&gt;Fineview&lt;/a&gt;, a neighborhood in the North Side of Pittsburgh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was not the first time I&amp;rsquo;d run the Stepathon: I&amp;rsquo;d actually done a shorter version of it (supposedly a 5K, but clearly much shorter given how quickly I finished it) in 2006. Originally, I wasn&amp;rsquo;t sure I was going to run another race this year after the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/30/running-my-10th-great-race-10k-obscene-but-in-a-good-way/&#34;&gt;Great Race&lt;/a&gt;, but after telling my buddy Chris about the Stepathon, and his getting excited about the concept, I decided to commit to doing it with him, rain or shine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Note that there was a short 2.5 mile option available, but only six people took it this year.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Web site&amp;rsquo;s description only gives a hint of what this event is like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Are you a runner, about to run the Great Race?   An urban explorer?  A fitness nut?  Or just a masochist?  How fast should you pace yourself, going up a stairway that rises out of view?  How fast can you go?  One thing for sure, the harder you fight the steps, the harder they fight back!  We saved the best for last... the legendary Rising Main stairway.  High as a 17-story building, disorienting as it leans this way and that, your legs feeling like jelly as you near the top... The Stepathon, ready to chew you up and spit you out!
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, the registration form says:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Challenging course includes 12 public staircases over 1600 steps.  Vertical climb 400 feet.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s my report on this fantastic event!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;course&#34;&gt;Course&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The course includes stairways, sidewalk steps, road sections, trail sections, grassy sections, bridges. It&amp;rsquo;s really something else. With all the turns, it was very helpful indeed that signs were put up and arrows drawn on the ground where useful, and several volunteers out on the course also, who pointed the way. I really appreciated the number of volunteers in the Stepathon who made it go smoothly. They not only pointed the way, but gave encouragement, and there were water stations also along the course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a &lt;a href=&#34;https://maps.google.com/maps/ms?hl=en&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;t=h&amp;amp;msa=0&amp;amp;msid=113997026750504519105.000482f8ae0315f705efc&amp;amp;ll=40.46334,-80.002184&amp;amp;spn=0.011428,0.018239&amp;amp;z=15&amp;amp;source=embed&#34;&gt;detailed map of the course&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And here are &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/groups/110502898969170/photos/&#34;&gt;photos from the past&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;preparation&#34;&gt;Preparation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t prepare for this event at all. I had no goal but to do my best and pace myself well. Real preparation, of course, would have involved doing a lot of &lt;strong&gt;stair-climbing&lt;/strong&gt;. It is the case that I &lt;em&gt;almost never&lt;/em&gt; take an elevator or escalator, but take the stairs instead, wherever I go, but I&amp;rsquo;m talking about actual stair-climbing training, of the form I used to engage in, during winter, when I did the summer &lt;a href=&#34;http://rachelcarsontrails.org/rct/challenge&#34;&gt;Rachel Carson Trail Challenge&lt;/a&gt; three years in a row. Of course, the place for such training is the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.tour.pitt.edu/tour-080.html&#34;&gt;Cathedral of Learning&lt;/a&gt;. Once a week, I&amp;rsquo;d do 36 floors, elevation gain of 440 feet, in one straight shot up, no rest: it was a &lt;a href=&#34;http://alltrails.com/events/2010/11/cathedral-of-learning-steps-2&#34;&gt;great workout&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;pre-race&#34;&gt;Pre-race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;food&#34;&gt;Food&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as in the Great Race, I continued my policy of not eating before the race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;clothing&#34;&gt;Clothing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was drizzling rain, but the temperature wasn&amp;rsquo;t too bad. I wore a long-sleeve moisture-wicking shirt, long running pants, my Vibram FiveFingers Bikila LS shoes, and the brand new Great Race cap that was given to all participants of the Great Race this year. This was the first time I&amp;rsquo;d ever worn a cap during a race; I didn&amp;rsquo;t want water getting into my eyes (as happened actually during the Great Race). I also wore some light gloves; in particular, I expected to try to hold onto some cold and wet stairway handrails!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chris also wore his Great Race cap. Since this was a smaller race, with 70 participants, this was the first time in a race we were at a start line together. In the huge July 4 Brentwood 5K race, which was his first 5K race, we didn&amp;rsquo;t start together, and in the even more huge Great Race, his first 10K race, I never even saw him at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I saw some people wearing the yellow Great Race long-sleeve shirts they were also given to all Great Race participants. I still haven&amp;rsquo;t worn mine yet. I wasn&amp;rsquo;t going to wear an unfamiliar shirt for the first time when doing a race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;pep-talk&#34;&gt;Pep talk&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The race director warned us of the hazards in store for us, and told us to be especially careful on the slippery wooden steps and in the trails. There were lots of jokes going around about dragging our broken bodies from the steps. I enjoyed the lighthearted mood. Hey, we all signed the waivers about the dangers of this event!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;description-of-the-race&#34;&gt;Description of the race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;stairs-and-trails&#34;&gt;Stairs and trails&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We started off running on the road for a bit before turning onto the first stairway. Chris was way ahead of me, but I was trying to pace myself for what lay ahead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After doing a bit of &amp;ldquo;running&amp;rdquo; up the stairs, I quickly realized that I was wasting my energy. I started just walking up the stairs instead. The plan was to walk up all stairways, but descend quickly, and run fast on the roads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, I was trying to pull myself up with my arms using the handrails, but it turns out that some handrail sections are missing or &lt;em&gt;loose&lt;/em&gt;. Yup, we were warned!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point, we started going off into the trails. Unfortunately, I had &amp;ldquo;forgotten&amp;rdquo; that there might be mud issues, and I was annoyed that I had worn my Bikila LS shoes instead of my KSO Trek shoes, which would have been much better in these conditions. I had to slow down a lot to avoid slipping and falling in the muddy trails.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I noticed that I was a lot faster descending steps than many people, so I started passing people during the descents. At some point, I caught up to Chris and passed him. But not too long after that, we entered a grassy section of the course, outside the fenced baseball field. I &lt;em&gt;knew&lt;/em&gt; that this was going to be treacherous, so I tried to grab with my right hand onto the fence as I ran, but still, at some point there was a drop and I slipped and fell hard, right on my butt. I picked myself up, luckily not really injured (although I had some hip pain for a day or two after the race), and kept going. After the race, Chris said he had seen me going down. Thanks to the indentation I made in the ground with my body, others behind me knew where not to step!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;roads&#34;&gt;Roads&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did do a good bit of running on the roads, but actually, a lot of walking too, because there were such steep hills along some of the roads. Here&amp;rsquo;s my rule of thumb in these kinds of races: if by walking hard I can keep up with someone who is running up a hill, clearly I am saving more energy than my competitor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;bridges&#34;&gt;Bridges&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were various bridges, but most amusing was the bridge over I-279. When was the last time I ran in a race that crossed an interstate highway? Um, never?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-garden-hose&#34;&gt;The garden hose&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the big stair climb near the end, I noticed while pulling myself up the handrails that one entire section was not only missing, but replaced seamlessly with a &lt;em&gt;garden hose&lt;/em&gt;. Hilarious, but not safe! I didn&amp;rsquo;t touch the hose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;fear-of-getting-lost&#34;&gt;Fear of getting lost&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite all the volunteers and signs and drawn arrows, there were times when I feared getting lost. This proved detrimental to my running speed. During much of the last half hour of the race, I was basically with a pack of two other people, with nobody else in sight ahead of us, and we were taking turns leading. This was fine when I wasn&amp;rsquo;t leading (typically, they were faster than me on the stairs and trails, while I was faster on the roads), but when a long stretch of road came up and I was clearly able to go faster, I was afraid to go as fast as I really could, in case I missed a turn. If I had genuinely prepared for this race, I would have studied and memorized the course map before doing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result of my not going all out when I was clearly strong enough to on the roads, by the time I saw the finish line approaching, no amount of sprinting on my part could get me to catch up with my two closest competitors. I was slightly annoyed with myself for not having applied optimal race tactics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;results&#34;&gt;Results&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://runhigh.com/2012RESULTS/R100612GB.html&#34;&gt;results of the race&lt;/a&gt; show that I finished in 27th place out of 70, in a time of 59:31. The two people I was running in a pack with for much of the second half of the race came in 8 seconds and 4 seconds earlier than me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I cheered Chris on as he came in some minutes later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;post-race&#34;&gt;Post-race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a view from the finish:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://bbbigdawgs.weebly.com/uploads/4/4/9/1/4491611/5685188_orig.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Welcome to Fineview&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://bbbigdawgs.weebly.com/uploads/4/4/9/1/4491611/5390106_orig.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;View from finish&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(It&amp;rsquo;s probably too hard to see my &amp;ldquo;indentation&amp;rdquo; in the ground in this photo outside the fenced ball field where I fell!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a little band playing some &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Old-time_music&#34;&gt;old-time music&lt;/a&gt;. That was a nice touch to this event. I always appreciate it when post-race festivities include some music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many refreshments were available: muffins, fruit, coffee, etc. I was pretty hungry after almost an hour of running (and on an empty stomach), and devoured some muffins and fruit. No coffee for me, though: I need to wind down, not wind up, after a race!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t pay much attention to the raffle prizes being given away, so who knows, I might have missed winning something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I picked up my race bag and a coaster. After I was done eating and chatting with Chris, I was getting cold and walked back to the start line and back to my car to drive home. It was kind of funny going backwards along part of the course, down the rights, down the steps, back to the start line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;other-events-that-took-place-today&#34;&gt;Other events that took place today&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sadly, today was also the day for two other annual events that were on different days last year: the Pittsburgh Step Trek and the Run Shadyside 5K.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I had to miss both of them. Generally, given the choice between doing something that I have enjoyed recently and doing something new (or very old), I will almost always choose what I did least recently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;pittsburgh-step-trek&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Step Trek&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, Abby and I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/08/my-god-its-full-of-stairs-pittsburgh-step-trek-2011/&#34;&gt;did the annual Pittsburgh Step Trek&lt;/a&gt;, which is a self-guided, noncompetitive event that actually gives a similar feel to the Fineview Stepathon, in that it is an exploration of a Pittsburgh neighborhood that has a lot of hills and nooks and crannies, and of course a lot of stairways. This year I was unable to do the Step Trek because of another commitment in the afternoon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.post-gazette.com/stories/local/neighborhoods-city/pittsburgh-steptrek-provides-a-different-view-of-city-656542/&#34;&gt;local writeup of this year&amp;rsquo;s event&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;run-shadyside-5k&#34;&gt;Run Shadyside 5K&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, since it fell on a different day, I also &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/01/run-shadyside-5k-outrunning-mickey-mouse-and-lending-a-trumpet/&#34;&gt;ran the Run Shadyside 5K&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s a nice event, but fast and flat and crowded is not as exciting as a quirky, small Stepathon!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a great time in this year&amp;rsquo;s Fineview Stepathon, and I was delighted to have introduced Chris to this event. This was one of the &lt;em&gt;most fun&lt;/em&gt; races in my life! I&amp;rsquo;m grateful for all the work the volunteers did to get the route ready, handle registration, direct the race, point out directions, give us water, and provide music and food for us at the end. I totally want to do this again next year, even if schedule conflicts arise again. And I hope that maybe I&amp;rsquo;ll do some targeted training in order to really conquer &amp;ldquo;man versus steps&amp;rdquo;!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Running my 10th Great Race 10K: &#34;obscene but in a good way&#34;</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/09/30/running-my-10th-great-race-10k-obscene-but-in-a-good-way/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Sep 2012 19:08:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/09/30/running-my-10th-great-race-10k-obscene-but-in-a-good-way/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/great-race-2012/great-race-expo.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Great Race quilt&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Today I ran in Pittsburgh&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://rungreatrace.com/&#34;&gt;Great Race 10K&lt;/a&gt; for the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/25/blistered-but-blissful-in-the-burgh/&#34;&gt;tenth time in my life&lt;/a&gt;. For various reasons, I performed a number of experiments for this tenth running of the race, doing things I&amp;rsquo;ve never done before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the race, I heard someone say, as I passed him:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
...obscene... but in a good way!
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It made my day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll explain what might have triggered this reaction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;preparation-and-uncertainty&#34;&gt;Preparation and uncertainty&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/07/running-my-8th-pretty-good-race-5k-dealing-with-disappointment/&#34;&gt;Pretty Good Race 5K&lt;/a&gt;, I was so tired out from my effort that I totally lost the desire to run. Plus my left foot was hurting more again. I ended up not running a single step for two weeks. This meant, of course, that there was no way I was going to go after the goal of beating last year&amp;rsquo;s time in the Great Race 10K.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, there was the question of whether I should even run the Great Race at all this year! Until almost the last minute, Abby and I agreed that if I did not feel up for running it at all, I would just sell my registration. Part of me felt bad about the possibility of breaking &amp;ldquo;tradition&amp;rdquo; and not running the race; I have stubbornly run it while horribly sick in some years! At the same time, it&amp;rsquo;s not really the end of the world if I miss a race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;change-of-purpose-and-plan-enter-the-invisible-shoes&#34;&gt;Change of purpose and plan: enter the Invisible Shoes!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eventually, after my two-week absence from running, my left foot injury resolved itself, and I started running again. The plan was to start road running (since I prefer to trail running) in preparation for the Great Race. The problem is that I actually don&amp;rsquo;t like wearing my road running Vibram FiveFingers shoes, my Bikila LS shoes. In fact, since my taste in footwear has become more and more minimalist over time, the Bikila LS shoes seem like a step totally in the wrong direction. I got them last year really only for the purpose of road racing, since the KSO blisters me and the KSO Trek is for the trails.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just to start running again, I began going out for 2-3 mile casual runs in my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/26/walking-and-running-in-invisible-shoes-a-review/&#34;&gt;Invisible Shoes&lt;/a&gt; that I&amp;rsquo;d been wearing all summer for walking, and sometimes for running. I enjoyed my short runs in these huaraches.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/great-race-2012/invisible-shoes-rolled.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Invisible Shoes rolled up&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Given that I was just getting back into running after such a long break, I never ran more than 3 miles during any of my runs leading up to the Great Race. And I never wore anything other than the Invisible Shoes. So that led me to the idea that since I wasn&amp;rsquo;t going to be able to achieve a goal of running super fast this year, I could set a &lt;em&gt;different goal&lt;/em&gt; for myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My new goal: &lt;em&gt;run the Great Race 10K in 4mm huaraches&lt;/em&gt;. More specifically, I wanted to see how my joints and muscles would hold up, as well as my feet and skin. Also, I&amp;rsquo;d never run fast in huaraches before, so this would also be an experiment in running fast in them. I had every intention of running pretty fast: I simply expected that I would not be able to run as fast as if I were running more protected shoes, because of many factors such as flopping soles and more pounding, resulting in my going more conservatively than if I had already experimented and knew what the limits were.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, originally I had planned to run a 5K race sometime in the huaraches; I had never planned to suddenly run a 10K in them without running a 5K first!! Also, I was going to run this 10K without having run more than 3 miles at a time in an entire month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;last-minute-panic-and-recovery&#34;&gt;Last minute panic and recovery&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Friday, I was coming down with a sore throat, and my boss said he and his son were both sick (they were both signed up for the Great Race this year). Now I was totally uncertain about whether I was going to run on Sunday. I tried to get healthy, and on Saturday, was feeling more stable, although a sore throat kept lingering, and picked up my race packet. Luckily, I was feeling great this morning, with no sign of a sore throat, so apparently my &amp;ldquo;placebos&amp;rdquo; worked (sleep, healthy food, various supplements). I canceled all my Saturday plans (such as going to a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/28/another-french-music-jam-also-announcing-cats-dance/&#34;&gt;French dance workshop&lt;/a&gt;) in order to rest up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other concern was the weather forecast. All week it seemed like it was going to rain sometime this morning. I&amp;rsquo;ve run in rain before, raced in rain before. I can do it. But the last time I ran in Invisible Shoes in the rain, I got into trouble. So now what? I simply decided I was going to deal with rain if it happened. Yet another variable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-race&#34;&gt;The race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;to-eat-or-not-to-eat&#34;&gt;To eat or not to eat?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One experiment I did today that I deem a big success: &lt;em&gt;I ate almost nothing before the race&lt;/em&gt;. I ate a bunch of almonds when I was leaving the house, but that was it. In the past, I always ate something more substantial before a race. Rationally, it does not make sense, but for some reason, I always felt that I should eat a mini-meal. This was completely irrational, a weird clinging behavior I engaged in: after all, when I casually go running in the morning, I do it before breakfast! So why should race day be any different? We human beings have enough fuel stored in our bodies. It&amp;rsquo;s true that when I go for a run of over, say, 8 miles, I get hungry, and like to either have a snack on me to eat, or have eaten right before going on the run, but when it comes to 5K and 10K races, clearly there is no need for me to eat before the race. Experience has shown that it only makes me feel sluggish. So from now on, &lt;em&gt;no more mini-meals before a race of 10K or shorter&lt;/em&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;shoes&#34;&gt;Shoes&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/great-race-2012/franklin-before.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin wearing Invisible Shoes and race number 1853&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/great-race-2012/feet-before.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin wearing Invisible Shoes&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As usual, I jogged a mile from home to the start line as my warmup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;beginning&#34;&gt;Beginning&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The temperature was in the low 50s F: ideal racing temperature, not too cold. Under 50, I would have worn a long-sleeve T-shirt instead of a short-sleeve one. As it was, since I anticipated rain, I did not wear my usual singlet but instead a standard short-sleeve T-shirt. It was not yet raining, thankfully!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some guy stepped on my right toes with his shoes as he wandered through the crowd. I was upset by this and hoped that my toes were OK. They were sore for a few minutes but then I forgot about them and was OK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within the first few minutes, I saw Don Slusser ahead of me; last year I had tracked him and then passed him at the end of the race. This year, he was obviously going much slower, thanks to his shot knees, so I passed him early on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I saw my boss standing on his street corner watching the race. I asked why he wasn&amp;rsquo;t running and he said he was too sick. It&amp;rsquo;s too bad he had to miss the race yet again, after missing it last year because of another commitment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My huaraches seemed to be working pretty well as I ran faster than I had ever run in them. I rather enjoyed being able to feel the ground, as though I were fully barefoot. At 4mm, running with these is pretty close to being barefoot, much closer than wearing Vibram FiveFingers shoes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wasn&amp;rsquo;t paying much attention to any glances or stares at my feet, or remarks people may have been making, although a few runners did directly ask me about my &amp;ldquo;flip flops&amp;rdquo;, with an attitude ranging from incredulity to amusement to admiration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;middle&#34;&gt;Middle&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Near halfway through the race, it started raining fairly steadily. I had to periodically wipe the water away from my eyes. Well, it was in the forecast. One thing I can say is that I was never in danger of overheating in this race! There have been instances of the Great Race in warm conditions under a sun, when even in a singlet I got very warm and had to dump water over my head: ha, today I got free water on my head constantly!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I started the race further back than I usually do, there were very few people running at exactly my pace. I was always either passing or being passed by people. This is one thing annoying about big races where people can cross the start mat at very different times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, at one point, a guy came to be in front of me who was running approximately my pace, so that I was almost a constant distance from him. On downhills I would tend to overtake him, but then he would come back. We would be mostly together for approximately the last two miles. At one point when I slowly passed him, I think I heard him say, &amp;ldquo;That&amp;rsquo;s obscene&amp;hellip; but in a good way!&amp;rdquo; I believe that comment was directed at me and my footwear, and I kind of took it as a compliment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;end&#34;&gt;End&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The water puddles were starting to get to me, as I had earlier feared. I did not feel confident about running any faster than I already was, given the road conditions and the way my huaraches were slipping around. And my toes were getting sore from the pounding. Normally, in the end of a race, I turn it on and try to use up the remaining energy I have, but today, I just did not feel confident in my footing. I continued going reasonably fast, but did not put in any finishing sprint at all. Even if I had wanted to, it would have been difficult, because of so many slower people in front of me. This is a direct consequence of my lining up at the start line far further back than I usually do: what happens is that slower people who started further up are in the way for the entirety of the race!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I did turn it on just enough to pass that guy I had been more or less with for two miles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;result&#34;&gt;Result&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My chip time was 48:23, not too bad given my footwear experimentation and lack of conditioning and failure to go all out in the final mile; last year&amp;rsquo;s time was 47:46. Next year, I would like to go under 47:00. I should be able to do that if I maintain a regular running regimen. 2006 was the last year that I went under 47:00.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;after-the-race&#34;&gt;After the race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got some water, was given two Smiley Cookies, and ate a bagel and a banana also. I hopped on the shuttle bus back to the start line (the ride took 30 minutes), then walked 25 minute (1.5 miles) back home in the cold. In the future, I don&amp;rsquo;t want to do this walk. I should park my car near the start line the night before, so that I can hop off the bus and drive home. It&amp;rsquo;s no fun to be walking so long in the cold when you&amp;rsquo;re tired and you&amp;rsquo;re not sure what the condition of your feet are, except that they hurt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are my feet after I got home:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/great-race-2012/feet-after.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin&amp;#39;s bare feet after race, at home&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It turns out that I got only one blister, and it was exactly where I got a blister last time I ran in the rain in the huaraches: between my first two toes. There was some roughing up of the callouses on the balls of my feet (from wearing the huaraches all summer), but otherwise, my feet were OK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After some more hours of recovery, I was feeling fine. No joint pain whatsoever, no muscle soreness whatsoever, none of that stuff. Even last year I had some stiffness when I got off the shuttle bus. My conclusion is that truly minimalist footwear trains me to land in such a way as to minimize problems to my body. No shin splints, no ankle soreness, no knee pain, no hip pain, no shot quads, no cramping calves, nothing. Just a blister, and toes and forefoot that were sore for a while but right now no longer are. It&amp;rsquo;s amazing what &lt;em&gt;no cushioning for the feet at all&lt;/em&gt; did to prevent the problems I used to face when running. I am so completely sold that I will look into running more races in huaraches, and in optimizing my lacing in order to prevent the flopping limitation and that one blister spot. I am consider going up to the 6mm sole from the 4mm sole, with the idea that 6mm would be more solid for racing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another thought: assuming a race with no rain or extreme cold or hot surfaces, I should run a race &lt;em&gt;barefoot&lt;/em&gt; sometime next year. I&amp;rsquo;ll think about this. I know people who have done this. Why not? Barefoot, one does not have to worry about blisters caused from laces, or sole flopping, or water slipping. One may have other worries instead, but knowing a course ahead of time can help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;photos&#34;&gt;Photos&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Official photos of me in action, including beating the guy I mentioned, are &lt;a href=&#34;http://orders.islandphoto.com/RACE/Proofs.aspx#26561404-00002-0026&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, but since they are copyrighted, I have not inserted them directly into my report here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why I missed the CMU intramural XC race this year</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/09/27/why-i-missed-the-cmu-intramural-xc-race-this-year/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Sep 2012 22:25:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/09/27/why-i-missed-the-cmu-intramural-xc-race-this-year/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;One thing interesting about having been writing in my blog for &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/22/celebrating-this-blogs-one-year-anniversary/&#34;&gt;just over a year now&lt;/a&gt; is the opportunity to look back one year and compare where I was then with where I am now when it comes to seasonal activities and goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, today I was originally planning to run in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://athletics.cmu.edu/intramurals/index&#34;&gt;CMU intramural&lt;/a&gt; men&amp;rsquo;s XC race this year, as &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/23/happiness-is-finishing-39th-of-43-men-in-a-race/&#34;&gt;I had enjoyed doing it last year&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ended up not running it for a couple of reasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been barely running since the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/07/running-my-8th-pretty-good-race-5k-dealing-with-disappointment/&#34;&gt;Pretty Good Race 5K&lt;/a&gt; and therefore untrained, and probably likely to finish dead last, given the very few number of guys preregistered.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It was raining pretty hard, making unpleasant the thought of running outside on the grass and mud.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I was feeling OK yesterday, but today was feeling unusually tired and almost sick, and I&amp;rsquo;m still trying to determine whether to run the Great Race on Sunday &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/25/blistered-but-blissful-in-the-burgh/&#34;&gt;for the tenth time as planned&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some interesting observations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If I had not been feeling sick, I think there was a 30% chance I would have run anyway.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If I had not been feeling sick, and it had not been raining, there was a 95% chance I would have run anyway (my only fear being forgetting the course and losing contact with the second-to-last place guy).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having a long-running blog enables me to remember what I did and what I hoped to do the following year, and compare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year, I didn&amp;rsquo;t manage to do what I planned a year ago. Well, there&amp;rsquo;s always next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2012-09-30&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-09-30)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/30/running-my-10th-great-race-10k-obscene-but-in-a-good-way/&#34;&gt;I did manage to run the Great Race 2012&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Running my 8th Pretty Good Race 5K: dealing with disappointment</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/09/07/running-my-8th-pretty-good-race-5k-dealing-with-disappointment/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Sep 2012 19:47:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/09/07/running-my-8th-pretty-good-race-5k-dealing-with-disappointment/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pretty-good-race-2012/registration.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Registration table&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This year I ran, for the eighth time in my life, the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~kalp/PGR/&#34;&gt;CMU Pretty Good Race 5K&lt;/a&gt;; on National Running Day earlier this year, I described &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/06/06/i-celebrated-national-running-day-in-schenley-park-remembering-how-i-began-to-run-13-year-ago/&#34;&gt;how special this race has been to me&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things did not go as planned, but I made the most of the event anyway, and was happy and even amused by some of the things that happened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;preparation&#34;&gt;Preparation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the big problems was that I was not at all feeling prepared for the race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;foot-problem&#34;&gt;Foot problem&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For one thing, I felt very tired for days after my last race, the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/08/25/my-eighth-time-doing-run-around-the-square-5k/&#34;&gt;Run Around the Square of almost two weeks ago&lt;/a&gt;. I gave so much of myself during that race that afterwards, I just didn&amp;rsquo;t feel like running again for a while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Worse than that, my left foot has been bothering me ever since that race, discouraging me even more from continuing my regular running. I am pretty sure that I injured my arch area because I had the shoe strap of my Vibram FiveFingers KSO Trek shoe too tight. I had it on tighter than during my normal runs, out of &amp;ldquo;fear&amp;rdquo; of the shoe coming off or slipping during the race on the Schenley Park hilly trail. &lt;strong&gt;Shoe too tight was a mistake I will never make again.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;life-intervened&#34;&gt;Life intervened&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, and most significantly, I have spent the last week spending a lot of time on the talk I gave yesterday at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://pghrb.heroku.com/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Ruby group&lt;/a&gt;, as &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/08/07/the-first-steel-city-ruby-conference-an-amazing-experience/&#34;&gt;I had promised I would a month ago&lt;/a&gt;. That took a lot out of me. In fact, if I had not already committed, with Abby, to run the Pretty Good Race this year, I would not have done it at all, after all my energy was drained in the past week. But it would have been unfair to bail out on Abby given that this is one of the few races we have started doing together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suppose I could have decided to give the talk for the October meeting of the Ruby group instead, knowing up front the annual date of the Pretty Good Race. That had crossed my mind, but I also had instantly decided (with no regrets) that giving the talk as soon as possible after I promised to do it was of much higher priority than anything involving any of my races.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;weather-conditions&#34;&gt;Weather conditions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The race was made much more difficult by the unpredictable weather. For days it would be cold, then hot. Well, it turned out that race day was very hot. It had to be like 80F. I was even thinking that this might be the warmest race I&amp;rsquo;ve ever run in, but actually, that&amp;rsquo;s probably not quite true: races in July tend to be pretty hot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-plan&#34;&gt;The plan&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I started the race with no hope whatsoever of surpassing last year&amp;rsquo;s time of 24:36. I was just going to try to run an honest race at steady effort, and use my usual mental tricks of trying to speed up in the second half and try to catch people ahead of me. In particular, the fearsome very long uphill at the end is something that I wanted to have enough energy for to sprint up; in every year up till now, I have waited until the finish line is in sight before I start my sprint. I did not always manage to pass everyone in front of me, and I also at least once let someone sprint past me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year, during some training runs on the course, I experimented with running hard for just the second half and figuring out how much energy to conserve so that I would be able to start the sprint from far beyond that point, from around the curve. That way, I would have the possibility of powering through with nobody able to catch me. &lt;em&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d never started my sprint from so far out before in any race&lt;/em&gt;, so this was going to be an experiment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-race&#34;&gt;The race&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pretty-good-race-2012/franklin-before-race.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin before the race&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;beginning&#34;&gt;Beginning&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went out at a steady pace. After less than a mile, runners had more or less spread out and found their pace. I slowly caught up to someone who was running at approximately my pace. This is when things got interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This runner ahead of me sensed that I was catching up and decided to surge. I was confused by this move, but just kept on going at my pace. Maybe she just preferred running with nobody around her; but I was trying to give her some space by coming up from the side and behind her, rather than directly behind her. Having someone breathe down your neck is not very pleasant, after all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;middle&#34;&gt;Middle&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As she kept increasing her distance from me, I concluded that she was probably just faster than me, found her natural pace, and I would never catch her. There was nobody else visible directly ahead of me, so I had no other target during the first half of the race, but I knew that since it was mostly uphill, and I&amp;rsquo;m stronger downhill than uphill, and a lot of runners go out too fast in the first half of races, it was a question of whom I would start catching during the second half.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then, as I approached the turnaround point (this is an out and back course on Panther Hollow Trail), I noticed that far ahead of me, beyond the designated turnaround point (where there were volunteers directing people to turn around, and some runners were in fact there turning around), was this runner who had blasted past me. Maybe she was in the zone or something, but she missed the turnaround point! She started coming back as I reached the turnaround point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I felt bad that she had made a mistake, but then again, this was a new opportunity for me. I already knew that she was faster than me. But she wasted time and energy falling behind me in the race. Could I actually prevent her from coming past me during the entire second half of the race, given my head start?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t look back once as I focused on running the second half of the race, almost all downhill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;end&#34;&gt;End&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Probably no more than a quarter mile from the end, she passed me and started putting distance between us. But at my targeted location to put in my kick, I &lt;em&gt;screamed&lt;/em&gt;, three or four times, while doing what I&amp;rsquo;d done in training: going into an all-out long sprint. I think I totally freaked her out, because she kind of just stepped aside and started jogging or something (that&amp;rsquo;s what it seemed like as I charged past and then around the curve and then up the steep hill).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I continued throwing out a periodic scream until I finished. For the first hundred or so races in my life, I never screamed, but I started this habit only last year, at &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/01/run-shadyside-5k-outrunning-mickey-mouse-and-lending-a-trumpet/&#34;&gt;Run Shadyside&lt;/a&gt;. I believe it actually helps me a lot when I&amp;rsquo;m in pain and need to &amp;ldquo;wake up&amp;rdquo; into a new gear of existence temporarily. I just worry about whether it scares people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that I finished ten seconds earlier than her. Mission accomplished, after all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-is-important&#34;&gt;What is important&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here I am, shortly after finishing:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pretty-good-race-2012/franklin-exhausted.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin exhausted&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s Abby coming up the hill for the finish:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pretty-good-race-2012/abby-finishing.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby finishing on the uphill&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I was pretty proud of having executed the most demanding sprint finish of my entire life. I know that my final race time of 26:05 is far slower than my 24:36 of last year, but as far as my effort was concerned, I did give it my all. &lt;em&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s not about how fast I went, but how much I gave of what I had.&lt;/em&gt; (Apparently, at the London Olympics, some runner was banned for &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.telegraph.co.uk/sport/olympics/athletics/9456916/Algerian-runner-banned-for-not-trying-hard-enough-at-London-2012.html&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;not trying hard enough&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby, in her second Pretty Good Race, ran 2:07 faster than last year, in more difficult conditions. It&amp;rsquo;s really great how she&amp;rsquo;s improved her fitness so much since she started running. &lt;em&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s not about how fast she ran, but how she&amp;rsquo;s improved.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-next-race&#34;&gt;The next race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next race that I&amp;rsquo;m already committed to is the Great Race 10K, which I&amp;rsquo;m signed up already to run for the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/25/blistered-but-blissful-in-the-burgh/&#34;&gt;tenth time&lt;/a&gt;. I still need to recover my energy for it, and also let my foot pain go away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For various reasons, I was not able to run the Pretty Good Race fast this year. But I had an exciting experience anyway and made the most of it.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My eighth time doing Run Around the Square 5K</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/08/25/my-eighth-time-doing-run-around-the-square-5k/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Aug 2012 10:47:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/08/25/my-eighth-time-doing-run-around-the-square-5k/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today Abby and I ran in the annual &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.runaroundthesquare.com/&#34;&gt;Run Around The Square 5K race&lt;/a&gt;. As usual at this time in late August, it was a warm day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This race is special because Run Around The Square was the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/06/06/i-celebrated-national-running-day-in-schenley-park-remembering-how-i-began-to-run-13-year-ago/&#34;&gt;first race I ever ran in my life&lt;/a&gt;, back in 2000, and because it is also the first race Abby ever ran &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/31/reflections-on-2011/&#34;&gt;(just last year, 2011)&lt;/a&gt;: so today was my 128th lifetime race (according to my race log I keep) and Abby&amp;rsquo;s 5th lifetime race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-goal-this-year&#34;&gt;My goal this year&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My goal for the race for this year was to run it faster than I did last year (which also would automatically mean running it faster than any year since six years ago, 2006).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My time from last year was 24:36, and I believed from my last timed interval workout, on Tuesday, that I could run 24:30 today at fastest, so there was little room for error. I had hoped months ago that I would be in shape to run considerably faster in Run Around The Square this year, but travel and other interruptions caused me to train only haphazardly for races this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did I achieve my goal? The story turns out to be more complicated than I expected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-race&#34;&gt;The race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;first-mile&#34;&gt;First mile&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I took care during the first mile of the race not to go out too fast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We all passed by a lot of musicians on the streets, of course: a really fun tradition that goes way back. As I expected, I saw &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/18/fun-at-the-east-end-food-co-op-winterfest/&#34;&gt;Kimberlee Faught&lt;/a&gt; playing violin at one point:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/85802484@N06/7857971836&#34; title=&#34;&amp;quot;Run Around the Square&amp;quot;, Regent Square by sherpes39, on Flickr&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8286/7857971836_496cf2afe7.jpg&#34; width=&#34;375&#34; height=&#34;500&#34; alt=&#34;&amp;quot;Run Around the Square&amp;quot;, Regent Square&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As usual, I ignored all the champagne and beer stops on the race course. That&amp;rsquo;s a charming and venerable tradition at this race, but drinking alcohol would &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; help me run as fast as I can!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;second-mile&#34;&gt;Second mile&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once in the trails of Frick Park, there is no longer any question of going too fast; there is only a question of avoiding going too slow. The uphill is really tough. And I&amp;rsquo;m much better running downhill than running uphill. During the second mile, my only thought is to maintain my effort level rather than my pace, because when the big downhill comes at the end of the race, I need to have enough energy in the tank to blast downhill, however crappy I might already be feeling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, that&amp;rsquo;s false: my other thought is to keep hydrated and cool. I sacrifice a little bit of time during the second mile because up near the tennis courts, I always grab a cup of water from a friendly volunteer and drink some of it while pouring the rest of it over my head and rubbing it through my hair and onto my face and neck. (I don&amp;rsquo;t take any more water after this point in the race.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, about halfway through the race, with more than ten minutes projected to go, I was feeling pretty pukey and my breathing getting harder. &lt;strong&gt;Good&lt;/strong&gt;; that&amp;rsquo;s just a sign that I&amp;rsquo;m following my 5K race game plan. It is impossible to &lt;em&gt;race&lt;/em&gt; a 5K without feeling pukey, whatever your level is. &lt;strong&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re not feeling pukey by the middle of a 5K race, you&amp;rsquo;re not running the race as fast as you&amp;rsquo;re physically capable of running it.&lt;/strong&gt; I realize that many people run just for fun and don&amp;rsquo;t want or need to feel pukey in order to enjoy a race, and there have been races in which I have not gone all out, normally, I run a race in order to test my limits of existence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;third-mile&#34;&gt;Third mile&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Third mile, there&amp;rsquo;s the big downhill on the trail. The tricky thing is how to pass a lot of people. The problem with large trail races is that there are a lot of people who go out too fast early on or are much worse at running downhill than at running uphill; the result is congestion during the downhill parts of the course. I did manage to run downhill well without losing too much in efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;final-sprint&#34;&gt;Final sprint&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My vision was getting fuzzy from the pain, and my mind confused, when I was approaching the finish line. I couldn&amp;rsquo;t tell from the big clock whether I had already missed my chance at beating last year&amp;rsquo;s time. Seriously. It was reading 24:3x as far as I could tell, which meant that I already lost my chance to run 24:30. But was I going to beat 24:36? I had no idea. I thought I was going to see the &amp;ldquo;3&amp;rdquo; digit move to &amp;ldquo;4&amp;rdquo; at any time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of me wanted to shut down and quit and just watch the &amp;ldquo;4&amp;rdquo; digit arrive on the clock. Part of me knew that I still had enough energy to push harder, even as I was already sprinting, for another second or two (or more?!). Reality became distorted, I lost confidence, and I finished the race &lt;em&gt;not knowing whether I had really tried my best at the end&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;after-the-race&#34;&gt;After the race&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I checked my watch after I finished the race and didn&amp;rsquo;t know what to think. Did I succeed or fail at my time goal? My watch made it look like I finished in 24:40, but I wasn&amp;rsquo;t confident that I hit the &amp;ldquo;start&amp;rdquo; at the right time, and I was even less confident that I hit &amp;ldquo;stop&amp;rdquo; right after crossing the finish line (I was guessing that I didn&amp;rsquo;t hit the button until a second or two after actually finishing).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After Abby finished, I kept telling her I was upset that I didn&amp;rsquo;t think I really went all out in the final minute of the race. Then I got over my disappointment and let it go; in the grand scheme of life it hardly matters!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;more-comments-about-the-race&#34;&gt;More comments about the race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby was initially confused that everyone got a medal for the race. It was to commemorate the 30th anniversary of this race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As usual, there were refreshments and snacks after the race provided by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.runaroundthesquare.com/#!sponsors&#34;&gt;many generous sponsors&lt;/a&gt;, and hot dogs and beer (I chose not to take any beer this year). I bumped into a lot of people I knew and met some friends of friends. One of them turned out to be someone who is apparently a friend of two completely different Pittsburgh friends I have. He took photos of Abby and me wearing our Vibram FiveFingers KSO Trek shoes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/85802484@N06/7858001266/&#34; title=&#34;&amp;quot;Run Around the Square&amp;quot;, Regent Square by sherpes39, on Flickr&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7253/7858001266_58020e37f8_z.jpg&#34; width=&#34;640&#34; height=&#34;480&#34; alt=&#34;&amp;quot;Run Around the Square&amp;quot;, Regent Square&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby likes this race because much of it is on the trails of Frick Park and we end in Fern Hollow, where there is a lot of greenery, nature at work (as opposed to some races we&amp;rsquo;ve done, which have been pure road races that end in some parking lot). Whenever I hear positive comments about this area, I am reminded of how long it took to redesign and restore Fern Hollow such that it is &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/15/snapshots-of-pittsburgh-from-a-12-mile-run/&#34;&gt;one of the real pleasures for me when I run in Frick Park&lt;/a&gt;. Ironically, I do remember the early days of Run Around The Square, which did end in Fern Hollow when it wasn&amp;rsquo;t quite as nice as it is now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, we appreciate the new moisture-wicking T-shirts given to those who registered. These shirts are much more practical and useful than the old cotton T-shirts. I&amp;rsquo;ll be happily wearing around the new Run Around The Square T-shirt when getting sweaty in the years to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;so-did-i-in-fact-achieve-my-time-goal&#34;&gt;So did I in fact achieve my time goal?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t know what really happened until many hours after the race when I saw the race results online: apparently my clock time was in fact 24:39.55, so I did finish before the &amp;ldquo;4&amp;rdquo; digit came to view. And my chip time (which is the one I consider my &amp;ldquo;real&amp;rdquo; time) was 24:35.6, nipping last year&amp;rsquo;s chip time of 24:36. I did it!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;running-this-race-over-the-years&#34;&gt;Running this race over the years&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A summary of the eight years that I&amp;rsquo;ve done Run Around The Square:
&lt;table style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 15px&#34;&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;th style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px; font-size: 1.1em&#34;&gt;Index&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;th style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px; font-size: 1.1em&#34;&gt;Year&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;th style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px; font-size: 1.1em&#34;&gt;Chip time&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;th style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px; font-size: 1.1em&#34;&gt;Comment&lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;2000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;27:23&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;First race ever, as part of radically changing my life at age 30&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;20&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;2001&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;23:19&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;4:04 faster after a year! Lost weight, trained seriously.&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;43&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;2002&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;23:01&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;18 seconds faster.&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;104&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;2006&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;23:27&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;Missed 3 years of the race; 26 seconds slower than last time&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;114&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;2008&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;24:39&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;Slow; untrained and unrested the night before race.&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;118&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;2009&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;25:20&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;Untrained; unmotivated to push hard at end.&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;121&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;2011&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;24:36&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;First time Abby ran in a race with me.&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;128&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;2012&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;24:35.6&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;Managed to achieve my best time since 2006!&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;goal-for-next-year&#34;&gt;Goal for next year?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t know what goal to set for next year. I suppose I could set a goal of getting yet faster, breaking 24:15. That sounds reasonable to me. Going back down to 24:00 may even be possible. It&amp;rsquo;s too early right now to tell. But one thing is for sure: I have no intention of slowing down from this year to next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Run Around The Square is a really fun community event and 5K race in Pittsburgh that I try to run every year when I can. It was my first race ever and this year&amp;rsquo;s was my 128th race, and it was Abby&amp;rsquo;s first race. Running a race for so many years allows me to appreciate its quirks, track the state of my fitness, and experience its evolution as an event. I&amp;rsquo;m very thankful for this long-running tradition that just celebrated its 30th anniversary with the help of the Regent Square community and all the sponsors.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The inaugural Liberty Mile: a review of Pittsburgh&#39;s first road mile race, a great community event</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/08/17/the-inaugural-liberty-mile-a-review-of-pittsburghs-first-road-mile-race/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Aug 2012 21:44:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/08/17/the-inaugural-liberty-mile-a-review-of-pittsburghs-first-road-mile-race/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/liberty-mile-2012.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin&amp;#39;s race number and Bikila LS shoes&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Tonight I was really excited to race in, and also watch, the inaugural &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.libertymile.org/&#34;&gt;GNC Live Well Liberty Mile&lt;/a&gt;, a road race that runs along Liberty Avenue in Pittsburgh, starting from the Strip District and ending downtown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s about time Pittsburgh had a road mile race! Pittsburgh already has the wonderful&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://rungreatrace.com/&#34;&gt;Great Race&lt;/a&gt;, which &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/25/blistered-but-blissful-in-the-burgh/&#34;&gt;I ran for my ninth time last year&lt;/a&gt; and will run for my tenth time this year (good think I pre-registered early, because today it &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburgh.cbslocal.com/2012/08/17/2012-great-race-officially-sold-out/&#34;&gt;already sold out!!&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pittsburghmarathon.com/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Marathon&lt;/a&gt;, which I&amp;rsquo;ve run once.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope this event is here to stay. Here&amp;rsquo;s my report on the event as both a runner and a spectator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-history-in-the-mile&#34;&gt;My history in the mile&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve run a mile race only twice before in my life, and that was on the track at Carnegie Mellon University. A decade ago, in June 2002, I ran in my first track mile, the Pittsylvania Mile on that track, and did it in 6:22. I could have run faster, but because of total inexperience, went out way too fast for the first quarter, doing it in 1:22, and paying the price in the other laps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following year, 2003, in probably my peak condition in my life, I improved, doing the Pittsylvania Mile in 6:10. I still went out too fast, in 1:26, had no sense of rhythm, slowed down a lot to try to compensate for going out too fast, then had too much energy at the end, which was wasted. Again, I had not trained for the mile distance at all, but happened to be in my peak condition anyway just because I was still conditioned from my intense training for the Pittsburgh Marathon that I had just done in May (my lifetime personal best in the 5K of 20:37 was achieved just two weeks after the Pittsburgh Marathon).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I never broke a 6-minute mile during my peak.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That was the last timed mile I ever ran, until tonight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;preparation&#34;&gt;Preparation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, I wasn&amp;rsquo;t prepared for the mile at all. Apart from not having run much because of a non-running injury to my left leg that happened a month ago (from which I have fully recovered), I have just come back from a week of unexpected travel and am still kind of recovering from that. And no speed work to speak of in the past month, other than a few random sprints (which I do for general physical conditioning when I don&amp;rsquo;t do much else).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had no idea what &amp;ldquo;mile pace&amp;rdquo; feels like. I just figured I would run a bit faster than 5K pace (which I always have a reasonable feel for).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hoped to finish somewhere near 6:30.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;dr-vonda-wright&#34;&gt;Dr. Vonda Wright&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://vondawright.com/images/stories/vonda-at-work.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Vonda Wright&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I bumped into &lt;a href=&#34;http://vondawright.com/&#34;&gt;Dr. Vonda Wright&lt;/a&gt; while heading toward the start line, and thanked her for her support of those of us who care about maintaining our health as we get older. I want to plug her great work in promoting lifetime fitness, especially for those over 40. She has written a book &lt;a href=&#34;http://vondawright.com/index.php?option=com_content&amp;amp;view=article&amp;amp;id=62&amp;amp;Itemid=83&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Fitness After 40&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; which is pretty good and has a lot of scientifically-backed tips on remaining strong and vital and even reversing what used to be considered &amp;ldquo;normal aging&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I heard about Dr. Wright from a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/01/20/cmu-fitness-challenge-keynote-lecture-by-vonda-wright-stay-strong-at-any-age/&#34;&gt;CMU &amp;ldquo;healthy campus week&amp;rdquo; talk she gave this January&lt;/a&gt;. Even though I had already known some of what she advocated, I was impressed that she summarized well the whole gamut of what we now know to be effective ways to increase strength and flexibility and avoid injury. Again, I recommend her books to anyone of any age who wants to be smart about diet and exercise and more than that, a whole philosophical approach to living in general.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-race-in-waves&#34;&gt;The race, in waves&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The race was held in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.libertymile.org/Race-Waves.asp&#34;&gt;waves separated by ten or twenty minutes&lt;/a&gt;. This is obviously necessary because of the variation in people&amp;rsquo;s speed. The slower, open waves were held first, and the elite racers were in the final waves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;early-waves&#34;&gt;Early waves&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I arrived to pick up my race number when the first wave was already in progress. There was a bit of confusion in the first two waves because a good number of people arrived late or were unclear about when to run, and therefore missed the first wave. Most of these seemed to be kids. By the way, it was great to see so many kids at the Liberty Mile. Running a 5K (3.1-mile) race can be daunting for a kid, but a single mile is surely a great introduction to many kids (and adults too!) to the joy of running. I think it is really great that the Liberty Mile is not just an elite race, but also a race anyone can participate in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;my-race-in-the-masters-wave&#34;&gt;My race, in the Masters wave&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Masters &amp;ldquo;Winning at 40+&amp;rdquo; wave was the first qualification-required wave.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ran in this serious, competitive wave, not one of the open waves, because I easily qualified to run in this wave, whose requirement was proof of ability to run an 8-minute mile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lining up, I saw a lot of really fit-looking people in this wave, many of whom were clearly well over 40. In any case, anyone who looked anywhere near my age (42) was obviously going to kick my butt all the way to the moon. There was no chance for an age-group prize for me today! No problem: as a non-elite racer, I don&amp;rsquo;t race for prizes, but just to do the best that I can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ended up running &lt;a href=&#34;http://runhigh.com/2012RESULTS/R081712AD.html&#34;&gt;6:38.8&lt;/a&gt;, good for 26th place out of 27 in my age group, ha! I was disappointed that I didn&amp;rsquo;t make 6:30 as I had originally hoped when I signed up a month ago, but that&amp;rsquo;s OK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the first quarter, I ran 1:29; oops, went out too fast yet again! &lt;strong&gt;I hereby pledge that before the next mile race I run, I will actually train and learn not to go out too fast.&lt;/strong&gt; There is no excuse for running three mile races going out too fast. I don&amp;rsquo;t go out too fast in 5K or longer distances, after all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the second and third quarters, 1:46 and 1:46 showed that I had gone out too fast. I did save something for the sprint finish, however, and did the final quarter in 1:38.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A serious and unexpected problem I had while running this race was that my mouth got very dry and I had trouble breathing as a result. It was pretty weird. I don&amp;rsquo;t exactly remember this in my mile races from a decade ago. I did hydrate considerably before the race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, of course, as I do in 5K races, I felt like puking during the final quarter, and my arms were getting tingly and losing sensation. It&amp;rsquo;s just what happens to me in the final push. I believe there is no way to avoid feeling like puking if I&amp;rsquo;m running as hard as I can, but I have a feeling that the problem with my arms has to do with my tightening up (rather than relaxing) and flailing around. I plan to try to fix that for my next races this month and next month; what is required, clearly, is disciplined speed work, which is something I have not done in years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;enjoying-being-a-spectator&#34;&gt;Enjoying being a spectator&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The really cool thing about a mile race held in waves is that you get to be a spectator for the remaining waves after you&amp;rsquo;re done. In a 5K race or longer, there aren&amp;rsquo;t any heats and you never get to be a spectator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was wowed watching the &amp;ldquo;Unstoppable&amp;rdquo; under-40 wave whose qualification time was running faster than 6:00. Watching good, fast running is a real pleasure to me, like watching skilled dancers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also a treat was getting to watch the female elite wave and male elite wave. These &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/27/why-i-do-not-watch-the-olympics-any-more/&#34;&gt;Olympic&lt;/a&gt;-caliber runners looked so elegant with their long, powerful strides.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-shoes&#34;&gt;My shoes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d been considering running a race soon wearing my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/26/walking-and-running-in-invisible-shoes-a-review/&#34;&gt;Invisible Shoes huaraches&lt;/a&gt;, but without testing them out with speed work, I&amp;rsquo;m not ready to go there yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I wore the shoes I&amp;rsquo;ve been &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/23/happiness-is-finishing-39th-of-43-men-in-a-race/&#34;&gt;road racing in for almost a full year now&lt;/a&gt;, the Vibram FiveFingers Bikila LS. They worked out just fine. I didn&amp;rsquo;t get blistered because it was cool and it was only a mile. Next month I&amp;rsquo;ll see whether I get blistered in the Great Race &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/25/blistered-but-blissful-in-the-burgh/&#34;&gt;the way I did last year&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;race-organization&#34;&gt;Race organization&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought the race was pretty well-organized, especially given that this was the first time such a race has been held in Pittsburgh. Thanks go to the sponsors, the timers, the announcers, the volunteers who handed out race numbers and stocked water and bagels at the finish line and handed out goodie bags and T-shirts, the police officers who closed the roads and lanes where necessary and directed traffic and kept Liberty Avenue clear, the spectators who cheered, the providers of the many port-a-johns near the start line, the &lt;a href=&#34;http://bringbackthemile.com/news/detail/Miller_and_Kampf_Win_GNC_Live_Well_Liberty_Mile&#34;&gt;elite runners who put on a display of amazing running&lt;/a&gt;. Everyone without question was helpful and friendly. The whole experience was just wonderful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The inaugural GNC Live Well Liberty Mile was a great event. I hope it is the beginning of a Pittsburgh tradition that, like the Great Race and the Pittsburgh Marathon, will continue for years and decades to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-08-09&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-08-09)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/08/09/getting-up-when-reality-punches-you-in-the-face-running-the-second-liberty-mile-in-pittsburgh/&#34;&gt;I ran the second Liberty Mile a year later.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I celebrated National Running Day in Schenley Park: remembering how I began to run 13 years ago</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/06/06/i-celebrated-national-running-day-in-schenley-park-remembering-how-i-began-to-run-13-year-ago/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Jun 2012 21:42:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/06/06/i-celebrated-national-running-day-in-schenley-park-remembering-how-i-began-to-run-13-year-ago/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/melissappc/663419600&#34; title=&#34;Schenley Park by Melissa McMasters, on Flickr&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1309/663419600_66449cdcc7.jpg&#34; width=&#34;333&#34; height=&#34;500&#34; alt=&#34;Schenley Park&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I celebrated &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.runningday.org/&#34;&gt;National Running Day&lt;/a&gt; by, uh, going out for a &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/running/&#34;&gt;run&lt;/a&gt;. Here in Pittsburgh, I have come to like most to run in &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburghparks.org/frick&#34;&gt;Frick Park&lt;/a&gt;, but today I decided to run in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pittsburghparks.org/schenley&#34;&gt;Schenley Park&lt;/a&gt; instead, as I was in a sentimental mood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ran the out and back &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~kalp/PGR/&#34;&gt;Pretty Good Race&lt;/a&gt; course on the Panther Hollow Trail in Schenley Park, as I have done at least several dozen times in the past thirteen years. My favorite part is always the long downhill return back to the start, during which I try to really fly down fast, feeling the wind rush past me. It&amp;rsquo;s the reward for having run uphill in the first half of the course!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~kalp/PGR/pg-race.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Pretty Good Race 5K course&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I was not always a runner. I only started to run at age 29, during a turning point in my life. And it turned out that Schenley Park played a vital role in getting me out the door and on my feet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(The details of my story are distilled from my emails and daily journal I kept in 1999-2004.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-and-when-i-started-to-run&#34;&gt;Why and when I started to run&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In early 1999, weighing 30 pounds more than I do now 13 years later (and being probably prediabetic, in retrospect), I decided to change my life by trying to fulfill a childhood dream of becoming a runner. You have to realize that I was completely out of shape at this stage of my life, barely able to run ten seconds without stopping!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I set a concrete goal to work toward in order to motivate myself to improve little by little. It turns out that Carnegie Mellon University has for decades sponsored a 5K race called the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~kalp/PGR/&#34;&gt;Pretty Good Race&lt;/a&gt; (the name inspired by Pittsburgh&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/25/blistered-but-blissful-in-the-burgh/&#34;&gt;Great Race 10K&lt;/a&gt;), held every year on Friday afternoon of the final week of the incoming computer science graduate student orientation program. A good number of incoming graduate students (as well as faculty, staff, and anyone else who is interested) take part in this race every year. The fast runners are very competitive, of course, but many run the race just for fun; there is a party afterwards for everyone who participates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided to aim to run in the Pretty Good Race in September 1999. I had many months to prepare for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-progress-in-running-recruiting-my-friend-john&#34;&gt;My progress in running: recruiting my friend John&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Progress was quite slow, because I had decades of poor conditioning to overcome. On February 10, 1999, I went for my first run with my friend John (a graduate student classmate of mine) for the first time. John was not much of a distance runner (he could sprint), but at least he had run in the Pretty Good Race in 1998 (and finished at the back of the pack). He was patient with me because I had rest quite frequently. &lt;strong&gt;I owe John for encouraging me and accompanying me.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, I was so out of shape that I could only &amp;ldquo;run&amp;rdquo; for ten or fifteen seconds at a time before getting chest and leg pains and having to walk for minutes before starting up again. I had no idea what I was doing. Also, we did this irregularly, not on a daily schedule or anything. So progress was slow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;failure-in-1999&#34;&gt;Failure in 1999&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that I was dealing with various personal problems in the summer of 1999 and also still not fit enough to run continuously for a mile. So in late August, I decided to give up on my goal, and did not run in the Pretty Good Race in 1999&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-new-motivation-in-2000-30th-birthday&#34;&gt;A new motivation in 2000: 30th birthday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In May, on my 30th birthday, I decided that I was going to get serious about running. I could not just continue to do my low-yield unsystematic run/walking with John. The very next day, I pushed myself harder than I had ever done before, running with John.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I shook off my &amp;ldquo;dependency&amp;rdquo; on John, and decided to run &lt;em&gt;every day&lt;/em&gt;, even if it meant doing it alone. I made extensive use of Frick Park near home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;scientific-training&#34;&gt;Scientific training&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started reading &amp;ldquo;The Runner&amp;rsquo;s Handbook&amp;rdquo;, recommended to me by my sister Linda months ago. Exactly nine days after my birthday, I wrote Linda email telling her that I planned to run the Pretty Good Race in September.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book said that a beginner should run at least twenty minutes, preferably thirty minutes, and at least three times a week, preferably five. This was much more than what I&amp;rsquo;d been doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wrote in my journal:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
I think I will aim to successfully run my Frick Park route for a few weeks, till I can comfortably run 20 minutes.  Then I will invent a new addition in Frick Park in order to make the run 30 minutes.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Progress became more noticeable as I focused on putting in the time and distance, going as slowly as required to avoid going anaerobic (my problem when running with John). Learning the science of distance running definitely helped a lot in making my training scientific.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;really-committing-to-running-the-pretty-good-race-in-2000&#34;&gt;Really committing to running the Pretty Good Race in 2000&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I managed to get some friends of mine to commit to also running in the Pretty Good Race for the first time, and we did a little bit of running together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;some-warmup-races&#34;&gt;Some warmup races&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ran the first races of my life right before the Pretty Good Race, in order to get a feel for what it was like racing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;run-around-the-square-5k&#34;&gt;Run Around the Square 5K&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My actual first 5K race was the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.runaroundthesquare.com/&#34;&gt;Run Around the Square&lt;/a&gt; in August 2000, just some weeks before the Pretty Good Race. It was &amp;ldquo;disastrous&amp;rdquo;, because I was completely inexperienced:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
I guess I went too fast, because before I reached the park entrance, I
wasn&#39;t feeling so well, and my right side was beginning to hurt
already.  I didn&#39;t think of myself as going fast, because so many
people were going faster and obviously way ahead.  There was no
crowding problem, because people were getting spread out.

Worse, when I reached the park entrance, I dashed down the steep,
curving hill, passing a lot of people, and almost fell off the trail.
When the uphill came, people started passing me.

I knew I was in trouble when it took me 9 minutes to get to the 1 mile
mark.

As the race progressed, I saw all kinds of people pass me: middle-aged
women, high-schoolers, old men.  It was embarrassing.  I was just
trying to avoid getting sick.  I was moving my feet slowly, and not
pushing off.  The feeling of people passing me was not encouraging.

I ended up grabbing water three times.

I took 18 minutes to get to the 2 mile mark.  At this point, I
believed I would probably take 27 minutes total, and I felt bad.

I didn&#39;t even bother to get in an extra kick when the end was near.  I
just didn&#39;t feel well.  I believe my time was 27:xx.  I took my pulse
right after I ripped off my chip and handed it to someone.  It was
200.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, my time was a very slow 27:23, and I was overambitious in my first race. But that was OK, because the point was to get experience so that in the race that mattered, the Pretty Good Race, hopefully I would do better. I was afraid of finishing dead last in the Pretty Good Race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(For the record, a year later, 2001, I ran 23:19 in this race.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;montour-trail-5k&#34;&gt;Montour Trail 5K&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A week before the Pretty Good Race, I ran in my second 5K race of my life, the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mtchalfmarathon.com/&#34;&gt;Montour Trail 5K&lt;/a&gt;. I did it in 25:30, being much more experienced as a result of the Run Around the Square.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(For the record, a year later, in 2001, I ran the Montour Trail half marathon instead, in 1:47:23, five days after running a 5K race in 21:39. Do the math: in one year I got my 5K time down from 27:23 to 21:39!!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;moment-of-truth-pretty-good-race-2000-http-www-cs-cmu-edu-kalp-pgr-2000-html&#34;&gt;Moment of truth: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~kalp/PGR/2000.html&#34;&gt;Pretty Good Race 2000&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My friends all beat me in the race, some pretty significantly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I finished in 26:26, in agony, in 27th place out of 32 (including the guy who ran backwards the whole way). OK, so I didn&amp;rsquo;t finish in last place after all!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I silently vowed to beat my friends in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~kalp/PGR/2001.html&#34;&gt;2001&lt;/a&gt;. I did. I came in 18th place out of 45, after training really hard for a year to improve my running. My time in 2001 was 22:33, over four minutes faster than in 2000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here I am outsprinting my friend Sungwoo at the finish:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pgr-2001-sungwoo-franklin.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Pretty Good Race 5K, 2001, closeup of Sungwoo and Franklin&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A mutual friend asked me why I was so intent on beating Sungwoo, and asked whether I had something against him. I said no, not at all. It was just a personal challenge, a goal, just like when I first starting running in races, and got beaten by a certain 70-something hunched-over old man repeatedly, I made him a concrete target to surpass in the future, and eventually I did. In this case, I had earlier judged that Sungwoo was closest in speed to me, and therefore I would aim to beat him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;other-years-of-running-the-pretty-good-race&#34;&gt;Other years of running the Pretty Good Race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2000: 26:26 (first time, and 3rd lifetime race)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2001: 22:33 (much better, 23rd race)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2002: did not run, because of half marathon the next day&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2003: did not run, because of half marathon the next day&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2004: simply chose not to run&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2005: 23:16 (little training)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2006: 22:57 (recovered some fitness)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2007: (almost no running this year, health declining)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2008: (almost no running this year, health declining)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2009: 25:52 (almost no running this year, in terrible health)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2010: 26:41 (almost no running this year, in terrible health)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2011: 24:36 (began running again, recovering my health)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-future&#34;&gt;The future&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year, 2012, I aim to get back under 24:00 in the Pretty Good Race, to return to my fitness level of early 2007 before my life was disrupted for half a decade during which I had trouble staying healthy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have done less running so far this year than I would have liked, unfortunately, but just being on the Pretty Good Race course again and feeling great to be out there reminded me to return to a regular running habit. I have three months before the next Pretty Good Race!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;but-why&#34;&gt;But why??&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this blog post I haven&amp;rsquo;t explained why I wanted to run, what my goals were, how they have changed over the years, and why I run now. I will write about those topics in detail later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For now, I&amp;rsquo;ll just say that &lt;strong&gt;I love to run&lt;/strong&gt;. I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t do it if I didn&amp;rsquo;t. (I know people who run but do not love it. I think &lt;a href=&#34;http://jones.wordpress.com/2012/06/04/things-ive-learnt-from-running/&#34;&gt;that is a mistake&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Run Shadyside 5K: Outrunning Mickey Mouse and Lending a Trumpet</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/10/01/run-shadyside-5k-outrunning-mickey-mouse-and-lending-a-trumpet/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Oct 2011 09:47:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/10/01/run-shadyside-5k-outrunning-mickey-mouse-and-lending-a-trumpet/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My alarm starts blaring at 6:30 AM on a cold, dark Saturday morning, and I&amp;rsquo;m tired and sleepy, and briefly wonder why I preregistered on Wednesday to run today&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.runshadyside.com/&#34;&gt;Run Shadyside 5K&lt;/a&gt; race. But a commitment is a commitment, so I get, check the weather forecast, get dressed, eat something, and head off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Little do I know that today I will just manage to outrun Mickey Mouse, far exceed my race time goal, and lend someone my trumpet that has been lying around unused!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/franklin-and-mickey-mouse-eric.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin and Eric after the race&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;pre-race&#34;&gt;Pre-race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since it was cold, in the 40s, and there was a possibility it could rain (although things looked clear), I wore a long-sleeve shirt and gloves and a hat along with my shorts and Bikila LS shoes (this was the third race in which I used these shoes).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After my successful &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/25/blistered-but-blissful-in-the-burgh/&#34;&gt;Great Race 10K&lt;/a&gt; toughened me up, I was ready to run a &amp;ldquo;fast&amp;rdquo; 5K race. I had run a 5K in August in 24:36, and another in September in 24:36, but these were mostly off-road and hilly, so I expected that I should definitely go under 24:00 in this mostly flat road race, I targeted 23:30 as an ambitious goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing you have to realize is that I hadn&amp;rsquo;t run a decent 5K in years, so my goal was to really gut it out in this one. My fastest 5K was in 2003, in 20:37. I slowed down gradually to 22:04 in 2007, but later in 2007, as my life entered turmoil, I slowed to 23:30, then 24:39 in 2008, 25:20 in 2009, and 26:41 in 2010. So I have been using races this year as a gauge of my gradual &amp;ldquo;comeback&amp;rdquo; to my former level of fitness (taking aging into account, of course).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-race&#34;&gt;The race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/QslAbd-_TsA&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The gun went off and the race played out for me as most largish races do: I took care not to go out too fast, but a lot of people always act otherwise and pass me like crazy during the first minutes of the race. I just &lt;a href=&#34;http://sethgodin.typepad.com/seths_blog/2011/09/run-your-own-race.html&#34;&gt;run my own race&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a mile, things were mostly settled down. I noticed a guy ahead of me wearing a hat with Mickey Mouse ears.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mickey-mouse-ears-hat-profile.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Mickey Mouse ears hat&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, the gap between the guy and me was ever so slowly increasing. I decided at that moment that with two miles to go, I was going to do what I could to beat this guy. This goal was going to be the single purpose of my life for the next 15 minutes (approximately).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To motivate myself even further, I used the mind trick of publicly proclaiming my goal. I know this technique is &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ted.com/talks/derek_sivers_keep_your_goals_to_yourself.html&#34;&gt;controversial&lt;/a&gt; and can backfire, but I think it depends on context. Every time I found myself running side by side with someone (whether someone I was passing or someone who had caught up to me), I told him that I was going to catch Mickey Mouse. Somehow saying that always gave me a bit of energy each time, and I would pass the guy I just talked with and not look back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I pushed really hard but for the whole second mile had still not yet closed the gap with Mickey Mouse. Sometimes I could not even see him, but I always made sure to find him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Around halfway through the third mile, I started closing on Mickey Mouse. For the first time in the race, I was totally confident that I had what it took to beat him. I finally overtook him when the finish line was in sight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;final-sprint&#34;&gt;Final sprint&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that was not all. I saw the clock and was surprised to find that I was going to come in well under 23:00!  In the excitement, I decided to go wild.  I &lt;strong&gt;screamed&lt;/strong&gt;, as though I were dying, as I launched into a big sprint to pass probably a dozen people as I stumbled over the finish line in something like 22:46.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Man, that was cathartic. This is only the second time I have ever screamed in a race (and I have run in well over a hundred in the past decade). I had let out a scream during a sprint finish at the Pretty Good Race 5K in September, but it was a short scream, not this prolonged seconds-long one that I let out today. I supposed that in the past decade I used to be too shy to do a thing like that, but it felt so good today that I may do it in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was reminded of how in karate class I was instructed on how important it was to use the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kiai&#34;&gt;kiai&lt;/a&gt; shout as a projection of energy. But then I reflected, my scream was not objectively the best way to end a race. If I had enough energy to scream, then I should have been able to run faster before that point, so a smarter race would have been to push even harder before the somewhat wasteful sprint. Nevertheless, at the very moment today, the scream seemed the thing to do, for psychological reasons, at least.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;post-race&#34;&gt;Post-race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mickey Mouse came in seconds later. I went up to him and shook his hand, then grabbed some water and food and started walking back to my car (parked almost a mile away), since I needed to cool down from the race, and wanted to get my camera and warm clothing to bring back to the post-race party.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the way back from my car, I saw Mickey Mouse, but without the ears. He was walking with his family and I approached him and had his mother take a photo of us. His name is &lt;a href=&#34;http://ericbrockmeyer.com/&#34;&gt;Eric&lt;/a&gt; and he said he wasn&amp;rsquo;t the only one with Mickey Mouse ears: a bunch of Disney Research people were all wearing them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got back to the post-race party and happened to see a guy I know from lots of previous races in the past decade, Ron Romanoff, and had him take a photo of me:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-shadyside-2011-franklin.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin after Run Shadyside 5K 2011&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;bumping-into-ben-paul&#34;&gt;Bumping into Ben Paul&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-shadyside-2011-festivities.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Festivities after Run Shadyside 5K 2011&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-shadyside-2011-pancakes.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Pancakes after Run Shadyside 5K 2011&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I saw a sign for pancakes, and suddenly realized that I had totally forgotten about the post-race pancake breakfast. I put away the half-eaten bagel I was munching on and headed toward the pancakes, and whom did I see but &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.communiteach.com/post/10818529188&#34;&gt;Ben Paul&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-shadyside-2011-ben-paul.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Ben Paul with coffee after Run Shadyside 5K 2011&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I had first met and talked with Ben at &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/22/starting-a-new-web-site/&#34;&gt;PodCamp Pittsburgh&lt;/a&gt;, although I had heard his name much earlier since he was one of the founders of &lt;a href=&#34;http://communiteach.com/&#34;&gt;CommuniTeach&lt;/a&gt;. CommuniTeach is a really great concept, providing a way for people who want to learn stuff, or teach it, or both, to get together. Back in June, Abby and I had attended a CommuniTeach session on &lt;a href=&#34;http://communiteach.com/learnitss.php?glid=151&#34;&gt;fermentation&lt;/a&gt;. We learned to make kefir and sauerkraut and experiment with various fermented veggie combinations involving radishes, carrots, zucchini, onion, fennel seeds, you name it. Since July (when our first batch was ready), we&amp;rsquo;ve been enjoying tasty fermented veggies to complement our meals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are curious about teaching or learning anything in the Pittsburgh area, I highly recommend that you sign up on &lt;a href=&#34;http://communiteach.com/&#34;&gt;CommuniTeach&lt;/a&gt; and check it out! I also find the &lt;a href=&#34;http://twitter.com/#!/CommuniTeach&#34;&gt;@CommuniTeach&lt;/a&gt; very useful to follow, and there is also a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.facebook.com/pages/CommuniTeach/99389138220&#34;&gt;Facebook site&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;music&#34;&gt;Music&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I mentioned to Ben that I&amp;rsquo;d been reading about him from the links that he&amp;rsquo;s posted. I&amp;rsquo;d just learned that he played melodica, and I said that I have a melodica too, but have not been playing it. I said I was also learning accordion recently. I asked him about ukulele, since he had mentioned it somewhere, and he suggested that a bunch of us find a way to teach ourselves together. I pointed out that unfortunately, I was already focusing a lot of my musical time on playing recorder and for now my ukulele goals are on hold. He couldn&amp;rsquo;t believe I played recorder, since he hates the sound, ha! I happened to mention that I had too many instruments I didn&amp;rsquo;t play, such as a trumpet. He got excited, because he needs a trumpet to play, and I offered to lend him mine. So we decided that he could meet up at my place to pick it up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We looked at the posted race results and Ben couldn&amp;rsquo;t find himself listed. He was pretty bummed about that. It was his first race! It turned out that he had not attached the race chip to his shoe, but it was still attached to his race number on his shirt. Oops. Nevertheless, in case anyone ever doubts it: I hereby declare myself as a witness to Ben Paul having run his first race today in Shadyside!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;trumpet-finally-finds-a-happy-player&#34;&gt;Trumpet finally finds a happy player!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s Ben with my trumpet. Enjoy playing it, Ben!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/ben-paul-with-franklins-trumpet.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Ben Paul with Franklin&amp;#39;s trumpet&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;rain&#34;&gt;Rain&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It started raining outside just as Ben left with the trumpet. I am &lt;em&gt;so&lt;/em&gt; grateful that it did not rain during the race! I was prepared to deal with it (I have run cold half marathons during which it rained the whole time), but it would not have been so much fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2012-10-06&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-10-06)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following year, sadly, I did not do Run Shadyside again, because of a schedule conflict with &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/10/06/the-fineview-stepathon-2012-pittsburghs-grueling-urban-trail-race/&#34;&gt;the Fineview Stepathon that I did instead&lt;/a&gt;. We&amp;rsquo;ll have to see what the schedules are for 2013.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Running My Ninth Pittsburgh Great Race 10K: Blistered but Blissful in the &#39;Burgh</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/09/25/blistered-but-blissful-in-the-burgh/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Sep 2011 15:28:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/09/25/blistered-but-blissful-in-the-burgh/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m temporarily using a walking stick right now, because of bad blisters I got on my right foot this morning. But I am very happy today, and it was a &lt;a href=&#34;http://rungreatrace.com/&#34;&gt;Great&lt;/a&gt; day in the &amp;lsquo;Burgh.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/franklin-finishing-great-race-10k-2011.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin finishing Great Race 10K (photo by Abby)&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/great-race-2011-official/0020.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin giving it all he has&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/great-race-2011-official/0093.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin crossing finish line&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/great-race-2011-official/0094.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin over finish line&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/great-race-2011-official/0072.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin stopping his watch&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have now run the Pittsburgh &lt;a href=&#34;http://rungreatrace.com/&#34;&gt;Great Race&lt;/a&gt; 10K nine times now, beginning in 2000: I have only missed 2003 (the year it was canceled), 2009, and 2010. I have run it in all kinds of conditions (both in terms of weather and my physical state). There is no other race I have run for so many years, so it is always special to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But beyond that, today&amp;rsquo;s race was special because Abby participated in it, for the first time. She did not run the 10K, but did run the 5K (and took the photo of me above nearing the finish line). She just started running in races with me this year, and I am very proud of her for getting into running! Having once been a non-runner, it gives me great pleasure to encourage others to take up this wonderful form of exercise.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/abby-before-great-race-5k-2011.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby in Oakland before Great Race 5K start&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Of course, right after catching my breath and finding Abby, my first instinct was to ask her, &amp;ldquo;Where are the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.eatnpark.com/smiley.asp&#34;&gt;Smiley Cookies&lt;/a&gt;?&amp;rdquo; I limped over to pick one up, even as sweat was still dripping down my face, and eagerly gobbled it!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/franklin-great-race-2011-smiley-cookie.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin with Smiley Cookie after race&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;tradition&#34;&gt;Tradition&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Great Race is a wonderful Pittsburgh tradition. It is not only thrilling to be on the Boulevard of the Allies heading downtown getting a fine view of our city (although the uphill during mile 5 of the race is admittedly tough), but the sight of so many people participating in this event is heartwarming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/great-race-2011-crowd.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/great-race-2011-crowd-2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-great-race-stats&#34;&gt;My Great Race stats&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was also very happy about my finish time. I had a plan to break 48:00 this year, and I succeeded handily (all times mentioned are &amp;ldquo;chip times&amp;rdquo;, not &amp;ldquo;gun times&amp;rdquo;). My time was, of course, not one of my fastest times in this race (my fastest time was 42:49 nine years ago), but it was faster than my time in 2008. The last three years of my life have been very tough for me physically, so I have enjoyed starting to get back into shape this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s my record in the Great Race 10K over the years:
&lt;table style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 15px&#34;&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;th style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px; font-size: 1.1em&#34;&gt;Year&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;th style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px; font-size: 1.1em&#34;&gt;Chip time&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;th style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px; font-size: 1.1em&#34;&gt;Comment&lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;2000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;53:53&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;First time ever ran more than 3 miles continuously at all!&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;2001&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;45:02&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;Lost weight, trained seriously.&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;2002&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;42:49&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;Trained really hard.&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;2003&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;(not held)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;2004&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;45:36&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;Very sick, but was preregistered, and didn&amp;rsquo;t want to break tradition.&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;2005&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;46:49&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;Was too busy to train.&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;2006&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;46:55&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;Again untrained. Slower and slower.&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;2007&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;47:11&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;Not trained at all; extreme pain halfway, but kept going.&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;2008&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;49:12&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;Not trained at all, left shin hurting, unmotivated.&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;2009&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;(did not run)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;Too untrained to even think of running.&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;2010&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;(did not run)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;Too untrained to even think of running.&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;2011&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;47:46&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;Lightly trained, but put in a genuine effort on race day.&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;details-of-the-race&#34;&gt;Details of the race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My splits (for each mile, then the final 0.22 mile) are below. I tried to run an even effort (till the final mile, when I simply tried to keep going hard despite the pain), accounting for the changes in elevation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;7:40.73&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;7:07.52&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;8:09.14&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;7:23.90&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;8:24.08&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;7:29.08&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1:31.03&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One trick I try to use in a race is to pick someone ahead of me who is running just a bit faster than what I feel I can hold, and see if I can slowly catch up (and maybe overtake eventually). In the Great Race, this is hard to do because there are so many runners, and people starting at different times, so there is always a lot of passing and slowing down going on, unlike in smaller races where things get spread out and you know people are basically running at the pace they can hold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have to work harder in these big races to maintain my own sense of pace. I do this by &amp;ldquo;feel&amp;rdquo;: having run in races from a mile up to the marathon, I know what a sustainable pace feels like. 5K pace gives me a burning, pukey sensation, for example, while half-marathon pace is not at all pukey. 10K pace is in between: uncomfortable but tolerable, till the final mile when I just do whatever I can without completely falling apart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;don-slusser&#34;&gt;Don Slusser&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it was after around two miles that I noticed ahead of me &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.newsandsentinel.com/page/content.detail/id/538234.html&#34;&gt;Don Slusser&lt;/a&gt;, a local legend in the running scene. OK, he is not at all what he used to be, and has had a lot of knee surgeries, but still, I felt it was an honor to be see him out there still running.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As long as Don was still ahead of me, he was going to be my target. He pulled away from me slightly over the next three miles, but was always in my sight. So in the final mile, I finally blasted past him. Then somehow he passed me at one point downtown, and that pushed me to pick up the pace again and finish ahead of him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After he finished, I went up to him and shook his hand. He probably has no idea who I am or why I respect him or how he helped provide focus for me in my own attempt to run as well as I could today, but what can I say, it was a spontaneous gesture on my part. I salute you, Don: you and your wife Tammy have done much for the Pittsburgh running community and I am grateful for that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-note-on-shoes&#34;&gt;A note on shoes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the second race in which I&amp;rsquo;ve run in my &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.vibramfivefingers.com/products/Five-Fingers-BikilaLS-Mens.htm&#34;&gt;Bikila LS&lt;/a&gt; shoes (the first race was &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/23/happiness-is-finishing-39th-of-43-men-in-a-race/&#34;&gt;three days ago&lt;/a&gt;). Unfortunately, these shoes tend to give me blisters if I run over three miles and fast. I&amp;rsquo;ve run a slow eight miles before without blisters, but going fast, and in warm weather, my feet sweat and chafing happens. These shoes are nice but have a ventilation problem. I have never had any problems with my &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.vibramfivefingers.com/products/Five-Fingers-KSO-Trek-Mens.htm&#34;&gt;KSO Trek&lt;/a&gt; shoes that I use for trail running and hiking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see in the photo above that Abby wore her &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.vibramfivefingers.com/products/five-fingers-komodo-sport-ls-mens.htm&#34;&gt;KomodoSport LS&lt;/a&gt; shoes in the race. Wearing &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.vibramfivefingers.com/&#34;&gt;Vibram FiveFingers&lt;/a&gt; shoes for walking, hiking, and running has really improved our lives. (More on that in a later blog post.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;photo-update-on-september-28-2011&#34;&gt;Photo update on September 28, 2011&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some official photos from Island Photography have appeared online. I have to confess that my original plan was to try to spot the cameras and try to look good for any photos of me that might be taken. Unfortunately, I was in such pain in the final mile of the race that I had tunnel vision and could not really perceive anything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve added some of these photos to the beginning of this blog post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2012-09-30&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-09-30)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following year, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/30/running-my-10th-great-race-10k-obscene-but-in-a-good-way/&#34;&gt;I ran in the Great Race again&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Happiness Is: Finishing 39th of 43 Men in a Race!</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/09/23/happiness-is-finishing-39th-of-43-men-in-a-race/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Sep 2011 19:31:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/09/23/happiness-is-finishing-39th-of-43-men-in-a-race/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, on a late, muggy afternoon, I ran in a race, and finished 39th of 43 men in the race. I ran as hard as I could, just as I do in every race: my goal is always to run fast and beat as many competitors as I can. I don&amp;rsquo;t run in a race for &amp;ldquo;fun&amp;rdquo; (in the conventional sense of the word): I race to know pain and to stretch my limits. (I save my &amp;ldquo;fun&amp;rdquo; running for when I&amp;rsquo;m not racing.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So why was I pretty happy, despite getting my butt totally kicked?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For amusement, here is an excerpt of the men&amp;rsquo;s individual results of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cmu.edu/athletics/recreation/intramurals/activities.html&#34;&gt;CMU intramural&lt;/a&gt; XC race yesterday (billed as 2 miles but the course was clearly shorter than that): &lt;ol start=&#34;38&#34;&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;13:17.3&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;13:27.7 (me)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;14:33.7&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;14:33.71&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;14:33.72&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;14:59.9&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, I was happy for a number of reasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For one thing, this is the first &amp;ldquo;cross-country&amp;rdquo; race I have done, so I was just plain excited to do something different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, my expectations were low. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ted.com/talks/barry_schwartz_on_the_paradox_of_choice.html&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Low expectations are the secret to happiness.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; I entered the race knowing there was a definite possibility that I would finish last. I knew many of the runners would be undergrads less than half my age, and a self-selected group too, a group that does not include the (sadly numerous) students I see around every day who take the bus down one or two blocks or take the elevator up one floor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I was one of those students once&lt;/em&gt;. I was not a runner as a child, or in high school, or in college, or even in graduate school. I was sickly as a child, and also I was raised to pay no attention to physical fitness and even to look down on those who were fit (I know, &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sour_grapes&#34;&gt;sour grapes&lt;/a&gt;). I started running only after I left graduate school and embarked on several radical life changes (including losing 30 pounds, altering my diet, and taking up competitive ballroom dancing). So in a way, taking advantage of the opportunity (as CMU staff) to take part in the CMU intramural cross-country race was a way to fill in a gap in my collection of novel and exciting lifetime experiences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can bet I&amp;rsquo;ll be running this race again next year, and with every intention of placing higher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2012-09-27&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-09-27)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/27/why-i-missed-the-cmu-intramural-xc-race-this-year/&#34;&gt;I ended up not running this race in 2012&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-note-on-shoes&#34;&gt;A note on shoes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ran yesterday&amp;rsquo;s race in my &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.vibramfivefingers.com/products/Five-Fingers-BikilaLS-Mens.htm&#34;&gt;Vibram FiveFingers Bikila LS shoes&lt;/a&gt;, the first time I&amp;rsquo;d worn this pair of shoes in a race. I will run the Great Race in these shoes also. (More later on this blog about &amp;ldquo;minimalist shoes&amp;rdquo; and how they saved my life.)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/my-bikila-ls.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin&amp;#39;s Vibram FiveFingers Bikila LS shoes&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;preview-for-sunday&#34;&gt;Preview for Sunday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Sunday I will be running the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rungreatrace.com/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Great Race 10K&lt;/a&gt;. This will be the ninth time I have run the race. Stay tuned for a race report on Sunday!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below is a photo of my running it for the first time, in 2000, as the second race I had ever done (and I had never run more than three miles continuously in my life at that time). It was quite an ordeal. The following year I ran the race better prepared, 8:51 faster.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/great-race-2000.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin nearing the finish of the Great Race in 2000&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2011-09-25&#34;&gt;(Update of 2011-09-25)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/25/blistered-but-blissful-in-the-burgh/&#34;&gt;Great Race 2011 report&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>