<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Latin Music on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/latin-music/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Latin Music on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/latin-music/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Thoughts on Cuba while watching Cuban musicians performing the 1947 bolero &#34;La gloria eres tú&#34;</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/12/13/thoughts-on-cuba-while-watching-cuban-musicians-performing-the-1947-bolero-la-gloria-eres-tu/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Dec 2014 21:01:47 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/12/13/thoughts-on-cuba-while-watching-cuban-musicians-performing-the-1947-bolero-la-gloria-eres-tu/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t expect to be thinking so much about Cuba today. It all started with a random musical itch I was scratching.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;la-comparsa-and-the-wooden-flute-headjoint&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;La comparsa&amp;rdquo; and the wooden flute headjoint&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I was in a Latin music mood as I was playing my flute at home, and started looking up flute versions of music on YouTube for fun and inspiration. One piece that came to mind was the famous &amp;ldquo;La comparsa&amp;rdquo;, by Cuban composer &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ernesto_Lecuona&#34;&gt;Ernesto Lecuona&lt;/a&gt;. Last year when Bebo Valdés died, I wrote about being moved by the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/22/rip-bebo-valdes/&#34;&gt;reunion of Bebo with his son Chucho in a tearful duet performance of this piece on two pianos&lt;/a&gt;, and thinking about their separation as Bebo abandoned his family to flee Cuba for Sweden while his son stayed behind to become one of Cuba&amp;rsquo;s great musicians.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found a really quirky Latin jazz performance of &amp;ldquo;La comparsa&amp;rdquo; on YouTube by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.chipboaz.com/blog/2014/07/10/cuban-flautist-bobby-ramirez-releases-jazz-flute/&#34;&gt;Cuban-American&lt;/a&gt; jazz flutist &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bobbyramirez.com/&#34;&gt;Bobby Ramirez&lt;/a&gt; and Puerto Rican &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.negronistrio.com/&#34;&gt;Jose Negroni&lt;/a&gt; on keyboard:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/4Nro7myJ6Nw&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ramirez on flute was unfortunately out of tune with the keyboard, but what I noticed was his wooden headjoint. I&amp;rsquo;ve never seen the old traditional Cuban wooden &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.descarga.com/cgi-bin/db/archives/Article15&#34;&gt;Charanga flute&lt;/a&gt;, but do see flutists playing the modern Boehm flute with a wooden headjoint for a different sound. In fact, I love and prefer wooden flutes, but they are expensive and I own only one, a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/30/got-my-new-casey-burns-small-handed-irish-flute/&#34;&gt;Casey Burns Irish flute&lt;/a&gt;. So just for the fun of it (I can&amp;rsquo;t really justify the investment right now), I decided to search the Web for makers of wooden headjoints.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;juan-novo-wooden-flute-headjoints&#34;&gt;Juan Novo wooden flute headjoints&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the top Web hits was &lt;a href=&#34;http://jnovoheadjoints.com/&#34;&gt;Juan Novo&lt;/a&gt;. It had the benefit of having an embedded YouTube video with the caption &amp;ldquo;This musician appreciated Mr. Novo’s craftsmanship so much, that this song was dedicated to him.&amp;rdquo; So I checked out the video. Indeed, the young woman playing the flute said, &amp;ldquo;Está para Juan Novo&amp;rdquo;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/kBzrwhpVvDE&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, I noticed that Juan Novo&amp;rsquo;s biography said he was sent from Cuba to the US all alone by his parents in 1962 to &lt;a href=&#34;http://jnovoheadjoints.com/about-juan-novo/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;escape the rampant communist indoctrination&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;la-gloria-eres-tú&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;La gloria eres tú&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was captivated not so much by the flute playing, but by the beautiful singing, of the young woman in this video of the classic bolero &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cancioneros.com/nc/2806/0/la-gloria-eres-tu-jose-antonio-mendez&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;La gloria eres tú&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; written by Cuban composer &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.encaribe.org/es/article/jose-antonio-mendez-garcia/1296&#34;&gt;José Antonio Méndez&lt;/a&gt; in 1947. I was really touched by her clear, unexaggerated but free expression and style, especially in light of much more famous performances of the song in my memory:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;La gloria eres tú&amp;rdquo; is one of my favorite boleros (&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/08/10/rip-eydie/&#34;&gt;my favorite being &amp;ldquo;Sabor a mî&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;) of all time. For comparison:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;luis-miguel&#34;&gt;Luis Miguel&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first exposure to &amp;ldquo;La gloria eres tú&amp;rdquo; was, like probably many others of my generation or younger worlwide, through the revival of the bolero by Mexican pop star &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Luis_Miguel&#34;&gt;Luis Miguel&lt;/a&gt; in the 1990s and onwards. I have all his bolero albums, a result of taking up Latin ballroom dancing in 2000 and hearing him singing in much of the music we practiced, performed, and competed to, including my first discovery of &amp;ldquo;Sabor a mî&amp;rdquo;, which was also on the 1997 album &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Romances_%28Luis_Miguel_album%29&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Romances&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. Luis Miguel is a great musician, I will continue to admit, but in time I drew away from his high-powered, slick performances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here he is live, from his 2000 DVD &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vivo_%28Luis_Miguel_album%29&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Vivo&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, which was the last thing I bought by him before backing away from his work:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/GNldCVbD4b4&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;olga-guillot&#34;&gt;Olga Guillot&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, the gold standard for &amp;ldquo;La gloria eres tú&amp;rdquo; is the performance by Cuban &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Olga_Guillot&#34;&gt;Olga Guillot&lt;/a&gt;, the &amp;ldquo;queen of the bolero&amp;rdquo;. (In 1961, she was yet another musician who fled Cuba.) I like how she alternates between different moods, starting out gently and almost like a prayer, but then gets more and more passionate. She very quickly changes the color of her voice and dynamics. For me it&amp;rsquo;s still the greatest performance of this bolero:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/xEAOX2nxsEo&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;elena-burke&#34;&gt;Elena Burke&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another recording I have of the bolero is from an album by Cuban singer &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elena_Burke&#34;&gt;Elena Burke&lt;/a&gt;. She has her own style, with a low voice, and more staccato delivery:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/yuHpvIvukOg&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elena died in Havana in 2002. Her daughter &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Malena_Burke&#34;&gt;Malena&lt;/a&gt; came to Miami in the US in 1995 with her family. Here is Malena Burke performing the bolero with Arturo Sandoval on piano:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/2_LxxwXda8Y&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Malena Burke&amp;rsquo;s oldest daughter &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lena_Burke&#34;&gt;Lena&lt;/a&gt; is also a musician, a pianist and singer, and has worked with Gloria Estefan and others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s Lena singing the famous 1929 bolero-son &lt;a href=&#34;http://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/L%C3%A1grimas_negras&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Lágrimas negras&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; with Bebo Valdés and others. This is such a weird combo, with her being sixty years younger than Bebo and stylistically very &amp;ldquo;American pop&amp;rdquo;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/x56VtBF6iGo&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;arturo-sandoval&#34;&gt;Arturo Sandoval&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arturo_Sandoval&#34;&gt;Arturo Sandoval&lt;/a&gt;, he defected from Cuba to the US in 2000. I discovered him initially when his biographical film &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/For_Love_or_Country:_The_Arturo_Sandoval_Story&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;For Love or Country&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; about his life before defection came out, and I saw him perform in the Three Rivers Arts Festival in Pittsburgh in 2002.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a Latin jazz version by Arturo Sandoval on flugelhorn, from his 1994 album &amp;ldquo;Tenderly&amp;rdquo;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/AZW15092fx4&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;where-is-blau-colonial-cayo-coco&#34;&gt;Where is Blau Colonial Cayo Coco?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So there were many thoughts and questions already in my mind as a result of listening to this old Cuban bolero, as a result of my remembering past performances by musicians who had left Cuba. When I hear classic boleros, I think about old Cuba, the culture and society that produced this kind of music and musicians, the political upheaval, the consequences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But back to that little band Nucay, captured presumably on a phone outside on a windy day by a random tourist who posted the video on YouTube in 2010. What has life been like for the members of Nucay, and for the charming young flutist/singer?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, what and where is &amp;ldquo;Blau Colonial Cayo Coco&amp;rdquo;? Apparently it&amp;rsquo;s a resort now named just &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cayocococuba.net/hotel_colonialcayococo.html&#34;&gt;Colonial Cayo Coco&lt;/a&gt; on the island of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cayo_Coco&#34;&gt;Cayo Coco&lt;/a&gt; that is part of Cuba. In particular, this place was designed to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cubahotelreservation.com/hotel.asp?hotel_code=sctblacolonial&#34;&gt;look like a village&lt;/a&gt;. This kind of thing makes me uncomfortable. I guess tourists fly in to pretend to have a nice &amp;ldquo;village&amp;rdquo; experience, while the hired musicians are probably paid to look and act the part.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;nucay&#34;&gt;Nucay&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I looked up more performances on YouTube by this band Nucay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;oye-como-va-cha-cha&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Oye como va&amp;rdquo;, cha-cha&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The caption for this video reads, &amp;ldquo;Ramon Almeida and daughter Arleytis [sic] lead this wonderful group of talented Cuban musicians.&amp;rdquo; So now we have some names. I presume the leader with maracas is the father? (Later I determined his daughter&amp;rsquo;s name is actually &amp;ldquo;Arletis&amp;rdquo;: read on.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was a fine performance of the classic cha-cha &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oye_Como_Va&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Oye coma va&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; written by &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tito_Puente&#34;&gt;Tito Puente&lt;/a&gt; in 1963. No, Puente was not Cuban; he was born in New York and was a big force in creating the mambo/salsa scene in the US in the 1950s. A great Latin jazz musician. I should have gone to see him perform live when he was in Pittsburgh in 2000 before he died. His music was great for listening to as well as dancing to; I still remember practicing my dancing to the first album of his I bought, &amp;ldquo;Mambo Birdland&amp;rdquo; (which has an &amp;ldquo;Oye como va&amp;rdquo; track).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I&amp;rsquo;ll confess that hearing performances of this work over a decade ago inspired me to think about taking up flute again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arletis did a fine job on flute here, jazzing things up:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/l4uWBPD7y70&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;ay-maria-merengue&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Ay Maria!&amp;rdquo;, merengue&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The musicians seem to be having fun; how could one not, given the catchy music and all of them singing? I really enjoyed flute action by Arletis in this upbeat classic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Merengue_music&#34;&gt;merengue&lt;/a&gt; is not Cuban, but comes from the Dominican Republic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/tAgVVL_ZTmI&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;sabor-a-mî&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Sabor a mî&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My favorite bolero, performed well. The caption reads &amp;ldquo;Cuban Music with the help of young percussionist from Quebec&amp;rdquo;, but this is wrong: &lt;a href=&#34;http://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sabor_a_m%C3%AD_%28canci%C3%B3n%29&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Sabor a mî&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; was composed in 1959 by a Mexican composer, &lt;a href=&#34;http://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/%C3%81lvaro_Carrillo&#34;&gt;Álvaro Carrillo&lt;/a&gt;. These distinctions matter to me: &amp;ldquo;Latin&amp;rdquo; music is not all the same, any more than the people or the distinct cultures are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/RmOIKdY3LYw&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;some-salsa-song&#34;&gt;Some salsa song&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is some salsa song; I&amp;rsquo;m afraid I cannot identify it offhand, the way I did the other songs. I&amp;rsquo;d have to try to transcribe the lyrics and hope that a Web search finds something, but have my doubts when it comes to salsa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I loved the father-daughter musical interplay here, with Ramón singing and Arletis on flute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/sAMdEezxYJs&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;summary-of-nucay&#34;&gt;Summary of Nucay&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OK, so Nucay is a pretty good band and plays a lot of classics to please the tourists. What else?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;arletis-almeida-sentirse-asi&#34;&gt;Arletis Almeida, &amp;ldquo;Sentirse Asi&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that a search for more Nucay material on YouTube reveals the following slick, professionally produced video uploaded by someone in 2012, promoting Arletis Almeida as a singer, with the caption &amp;ldquo;Arletis Almeida, flutist of Grupo Nucay in Cayo Coco Cuba, with her original song Sentirse Asi written by her father and band member Ramon Almeida&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, she is almost unrecognizable to me, very much made up and glamorous and placed in an urban nightlife setting, with shots of handsome men, alcohol, cigarettes. The contrast between this angsty, sensualized persona and the cheerful flutist playing at Colonial Cayo Coco with her father was quite jarring to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The singing is beautiful, and the song actually breaks out into a standard bolero accompaniment. It&amp;rsquo;s really something hearing bolero singing of this quality from a young person today. My overall feeling when hearing either this newly composed bolero or the classic music in the earlier videos is this: there&amp;rsquo;s some kind of time bubble that can still happen in the world, for better or for worse (a subject bigger than this blog post), and Nucay and Arletis Almeida illustrate it. Here in the US, no young people sing in this way. The many influences from pop, hip hop, and much more result in much more &amp;ldquo;fusion&amp;rdquo;. You saw that above in Lena Burke&amp;rsquo;s singing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/P1PZhDtCmLM&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;thoughts-on-cuba&#34;&gt;Thoughts on Cuba&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After watching this video, I wonder what has become of Arletis Almeida. Does she still play flute? Has she embarked on some kind of lounge career? Who knows? She&amp;rsquo;s in Cuba. Cuba is a world away. It took tourists to make her name even register on the Web, through the links to the YouTube videos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve waited for decades for an end to the senseless &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_States_embargo_against_Cuba&#34;&gt;embargo of Cuba&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;ve already run out of space here to even begin talking about the politics of the Cold War, about the human cost of isolating Cuba. Cuba, a place with a complicated history, but once an advanced nation by any standard, filled with culture, music classical and popular, home of world chess champion &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jos%C3%A9_Ra%C3%BAl_Capablanca&#34;&gt;Capablanca&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;con-los-años-que-me-quedan-and-nostalgia&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Con los años que me quedan&amp;rdquo; and nostalgia&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For some reason, I was reminded of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gloria_Estefan&#34;&gt;Gloria Estefan&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s music video of the bolero &amp;ldquo;Con los años que me quedan&amp;rdquo; from her nostalgic 1993 album &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mi_Tierra&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Mi Tierra&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s an odd kind of nostalgia, given that her parents fled Cuba when she was young. She made this album to embrace her Cuban heritage. But what world is portrayed here? Something like the world the tourists at Cayo Cayo hope to see? And what is Arletis trying to do as she sings boleros today?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, it&amp;rsquo;s definitely a beautiful song, and Estefan sings it soulfully:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/l6LjNOYvhMk&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2014-12-17&#34;&gt;(Update of 2014-12-17)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Totally by coincidence, news has come of the apparent &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2014/12/18/world/americas/us-cuba-relations.html&#34;&gt;plan by President Obama to normalize relations with Cuba&lt;/a&gt; after half a century. I cannot process this news right now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Life for Arletis and her father may well change one day in interesting ways.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Many faces of the bolero &#34;Dos Gardenias&#34;</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/02/10/many-faces-of-the-bolero-dos-gardenias/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2014 21:43:12 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/02/10/many-faces-of-the-bolero-dos-gardenias/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I encountered an intriguing article &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.npr.org/2014/02/10/274687110/brazils-maria-rita-rediscovers-her-mother-through-music&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Brazil&amp;rsquo;s Maria Rita Rediscovers Her Mother Through Music&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;maria-rita&#34;&gt;Maria Rita&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The name &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maria_Rita&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Maria Rita&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; was familiar to me for only one reason: exactly one year ago, by coincidence, right after &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/02/10/attending-j-jam-in-squirrel-hill-but-not-playing-music-in-it/&#34;&gt;attending a music performance&lt;/a&gt;, I was looking up performances of the bolero &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pbs.org/buenavista/music/songs/dos_gardenias.html&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Dos Gardenias&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; on YouTube, in order to see what was out there, and also to find a &amp;ldquo;karaoke&amp;rdquo; version I could use to practice singing to and playing the flute to (I ended up &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/17/finally-doing-some-latin-music-jamming-on-flute/&#34;&gt;playing the piece on flute a month later at a party&lt;/a&gt;), and one of the performances that struck me as notable and unusual was hers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that in this NPR program, when asked to choose a musical selection to end the program with, Maria Rita chose her recording of &amp;ldquo;Dos Gardenias&amp;rdquo;. You can watch a video of a live performance of hers &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4DoBORm4iyE&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; (sorry, the provider did not allow it to be embeddable). Do watch it: I found it strangely mesmerizing. It is understated compared to &amp;ldquo;normal&amp;rdquo; bolero style, yet expressive in its own way. Also, this video has her moving to the music while singing, eyes closed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, it turns out that Maria Rita&amp;rsquo;s mother was the famous Brazilian singer &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elis_Regina&#34;&gt;Elis Regina&lt;/a&gt;, who died at 36. The interview was interesting because it brought up the issue of what it&amp;rsquo;s like being the child of a famous musician, because if you&amp;rsquo;re a musician also, then there are always comparisons and questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what I want to return to my real topic, which is the bolero &amp;ldquo;Dos Gardenias&amp;rdquo;, one of my favorite boleros ever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;love-on-first-listen-ibrahim-ferrer-1999&#34;&gt;Love on first listen: Ibrahim Ferrer, 1999&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I first encountered &amp;ldquo;Dos Gardenias&amp;rdquo; through Ibrahim Ferrer&amp;rsquo;s performance in &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Buena_Vista_Social_Club_%28album%29&#34;&gt;Buena Vista Social Club&lt;/a&gt;, the film and the CD, which I came across in 2000, shortly after it came out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still love this live performance by Ibrahim Ferrer:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/mz_01le5pMs&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here he is from the CD:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/5pKW7qvYSHU&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-i-love-this-song&#34;&gt;Why I love this song&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://lyricstranslate.com/en/dos-gardenias-two-gardenias.html&#34;&gt;lyrics&lt;/a&gt; are singable and comprehensible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The harmonic structure is distinctive, because it uses both the natural minor and the altered harmonic minor (raised 7th). This gives the song both an exotic and unstable feeling, corresponding to the emotional content of the lyrics. Check out when the 7th is raised and when it is not. In addition, the 4th is augmented. All this chromaticism drives well the song&amp;rsquo;s emotional content, implying various different modal regions coinciding with changes in the narrative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The melody has a good dramatic range, and has varying intervals in motion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;antonio-machin-1947&#34;&gt;Antonio Machin, 1947&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m always interested in alternate performances of songs, both new and old. So I went back to the source, the great &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Antonio_Mach%C3%ADn&#34;&gt;Antonio Machin&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/OPq2ye7hJQg&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is faster than Ferrer&amp;rsquo;s rendition. If you examine the history of bolero performance in general, you will find that things have gotten slower and more sentimental over the years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find that there are pluses and minuses to different styles and speeds. I rather like the clarity and drama of the older faster tempo and style, but also like the room for more emotional expressiveness and freedom when slower.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;omara-portuondo-2010&#34;&gt;Omara Portuondo, 2010&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that Abby and I went to a &lt;a href=&#34;http://trustarts.culturaldistrict.org/production/25334&#34;&gt;concert by Omara Portuondo here in Pittsburgh on November 7, 2010&lt;/a&gt;, in which she performed &amp;ldquo;Dos Gardenias&amp;rdquo;. And someone captured that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/9QjS2MnAfR0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was an interesting, very free rendition, without the usual full rhythmic backup, but instead featuring some subtle guitar accompaniment. It was different, but I did not like it so much. I think the regular structure of the song, the way the lyrics fit into the movement, makes it work better when the original motoric bolero rhythm is maintained, with the harmonic motion driving the narrative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;lucrecia-1996&#34;&gt;Lucrecia, 1996&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a random other performance I found. I didn&amp;rsquo;t like it at all. The phrasing seems all weird and distorted, and the song&amp;rsquo;s been reharmonized strangely also.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/zgoEHFgwGes&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;sertab-erener-2007&#34;&gt;Sertab Erener, 2007&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I liked the performance of this Turkish pop singer Sertab Erener. She includes some distinctive middle Eastern styling that are unusual for this Cuban music, but her musicality cannot be denied. (Unfortunately, the &amp;ldquo;dance&amp;rdquo; sequences in this video are not at all bolero. Ignore the video.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/d-0SKj7AjZg&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What can I say, I&amp;rsquo;m obsessed with this beautiful bolero. However you like this song interpreted, it&amp;rsquo;s a must-listen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I haven&amp;rsquo;t sung it outside my home yet, but I guess I should get around to it, maybe at a party in the near future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;postscript-on-elis-regina&#34;&gt;Postscript on Elis Regina&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out Maria Rita&amp;rsquo;s mother, Elis Regina, singing the famous bossa nova song &amp;ldquo;Triste&amp;rdquo; in 1976:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/5wiJPgmEqR0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Appreciating the unique singer La Lupe</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/12/19/appreciating-the-unique-singer-la-lupe/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Dec 2013 21:41:19 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/12/19/appreciating-the-unique-singer-la-lupe/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/la-lupe-cds.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;La Lupe CDs&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I recently listened to a great &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.npr.org/blogs/altlatino/2013/12/19/255282456/la-lupe-queen-of-latin-soul-the-original-alt-latina&#34;&gt;program &amp;ldquo;La Lupe: queen of Latin soul&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; about the black Cuban singer &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/La_Lupe&#34;&gt;La Lupe&lt;/a&gt;, who died in 1992 (born in 1936) well before I was even aware of her existence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(I also then found information on a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pbs.org/independentlens/lalupe/&#34;&gt;film about La Lupe&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;first-encounter&#34;&gt;First encounter&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still remember the exact moment I first heard her electrifying singing, and remember looking her up to find more music sung by her. It was sometime around the year 2003.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was during the final credits of the old 1988 film &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Women_on_the_Verge_of_a_Nervous_Breakdown&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Women on the Verge of a Nervous Breakdown&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pedro_Almod%C3%B3var&#34;&gt;Pedro Almodóvar&lt;/a&gt;. It was a quiet evening alone as I was watching it on DVD in part because I was taking a course on Spanish, finally having decided to learn the language for real after having been exposed to it a lot thanks to Latin ballroom dancing and salsa and tango, listening to a lot of the music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A strident voice rang out at me from the TV screen. I almost want to say &amp;ldquo;harsh&amp;rdquo;, but the unique quality of the voice and the singing were so compelling that I don&amp;rsquo;t want to use the word &amp;ldquo;harsh&amp;rdquo;. This voice came out during the singing of a bolero, the musical genre that I love that usually involves a more smooth kind of voice and delivery. So it was really unusual being captivated by this amazing performance that played up the sense of loss and betrayal that were certainly in the lyrics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It wasn&amp;rsquo;t just that the emotional directness and yet control of the singing that captivated. I was also really pleased that I could &lt;em&gt;hear every word&lt;/em&gt;, even as a beginning student of Spanish. This was a singer with impeccable articulation that could make a song seem as though it were spoken, telling a story. When she sang, it was the complete package: drama, phrasing, silence, a cold stare or a haughty laugh. It was not just notes or words. It was a &lt;em&gt;performance&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The song is so raw that I can&amp;rsquo;t really listen to it very often, but here it is (as linked from the program I just mentioned). I&amp;rsquo;m talking about &amp;ldquo;Puro Teatro&amp;rdquo;, of course. (Here&amp;rsquo;s an &lt;a href=&#34;http://lyricstranslate.com/en/puro-teatro-pure-theater.html&#34;&gt;English translation of the lyrics&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/R-CpdAtgKQY&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;finding-more-of-her-music&#34;&gt;Finding more of her music&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had no idea who La Lupe was at the time when hearing her sing in the film. I managed to order an Almodóvar soundtrack CD that included her &amp;ldquo;Puro Teatro&amp;rdquo;, got her name, then looked her up. Eventually I found more songs by her, buying a CD of just her music. Of course, now with YouTube, it is easy to find anything by anybody. But there was a time when it was much harder to find music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.npr.org/blogs/altlatino/2013/12/19/255282456/la-lupe-queen-of-latin-soul-the-original-alt-latina&#34;&gt;NPR program&lt;/a&gt; has embedded YouTube videos of several of her performances. She was fantastic in all kinds of music, ranging from really fast dance music to more moderate salsa or cha cha or slower boleros. She also sang, in heavily accented English, some songs in the English languages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I am such a fan of slow boleros, here is &amp;ldquo;Que te pedí&amp;rdquo;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/3weAOwmKZXo&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;about-la-lupe&#34;&gt;About La Lupe&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tend not to know a lot about the performers of music I have listened to, because I tend not to read music programs or the like. I did appreciate listening to this NPR program, because I hadn&amp;rsquo;t realized many unique things about La Lupe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She was really revolutionary back in the day: in the 1950s in Cuba, then after leaving Cuba, in the 1960s and 1970s. I had no idea she dated from way back. Not only was she a black Cuban who made it, but also as a woman she was controversial for her sensual presence and musical delivery (which included growls, gasps, sniffs, sighs, orgasmic moans, and a kind of maniacal laugh; you can hear it for yourself, it&amp;rsquo;s still kind of shockingly direct for today I think). She was completely uninhibited. That&amp;rsquo;s why I was surprised she was operating in the 1950s. I would have thought, OK, 1980s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was nice for me to have the opportunity to learn something about an amazing singer who has long since gone, and I hope people continue appreciating the quality of her art.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>9 things you could be doing in Pittsburgh on Saturday, October 5</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/04/9-things-you-could-be-doing-in-pittsburgh-on-saturday-october-5/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2013 00:46:44 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/04/9-things-you-could-be-doing-in-pittsburgh-on-saturday-october-5/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m always frustrated at this time of year because there are so many events of interest to me in Pittsburgh that seem to happen on the first weekend of October. Since I cannot attend all of them, I figured I might as well attempt a public service and mention some of them so that if you are in the Pittsburgh area, maybe you can go and enjoy what I can&amp;rsquo;t attend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So here are 9 of the probably dozens of cool things you could be doing tomorrow, Saturday, October 5, 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;free-concert-allegheny-city-ragtime-orchestra&#34;&gt;Free concert: Allegheny City Ragtime Orchestra&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re interested in ragtime or Latin music, check out &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.shadysideacademy.org/page.cfm?p=12541&#34;&gt;this concert by the Allegheny City Ragtime Orchestra&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some articles in anticipation of it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.post-gazette.com/stories/ae/music/preview-ragtime-orchestra-connects-with-history-705929/&#34;&gt;Post-Gazette&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://triblive.com/aande/music/4763900-74/ragtime-music-concert&#34;&gt;Trib&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I wanted to go, but finally decided that we have too many other activities earlier in the day and need to just stay home and unwind in the evening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;free-conference-podcamp-pittsburgh-8&#34;&gt;Free conference: PodCamp Pittsburgh 8&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 8th annual &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.podcamppittsburgh.com/&#34;&gt;PodCamp Pittsburgh&lt;/a&gt; should be good. If you have any interest in using social media for personal or professional purposes, you should check it out. Interesting talks, opportunities to just socialized and learn new things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I attended in 2010, 2011, 2012, and will attend again for the fourth year. Unfortunately, I will only be able to attend the afternoon sessions. But I didn&amp;rsquo;t want to completely miss it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that PodCamp completely changed my life. For example, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/21/one-month-anniversary-of-my-blog/&#34;&gt;I started this blog in 2011 because of my second PodCamp&lt;/a&gt;, and I became serious about using social media in general, and that led to a total transformation of my life as I learned about local activities and made new friends. (Unfortunately, I didn&amp;rsquo;t get around to finishing my draft reports about my experience at last year&amp;rsquo;s PodCamp 7.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;pittsburgh-south-side-slopes-step-trek&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh South Side Slopes Step Trek&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The annual &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.southsideslopes.org/steptrek/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh South Side Slopes Step Trek&lt;/a&gt; is another event you can attend tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/08/my-god-its-full-of-stairs-pittsburgh-step-trek-2011/&#34;&gt;blog coverage two years ago&lt;/a&gt; as well as my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/09/25/why-you-should-go-out-to-the-pittsburgh-south-side-slopes-step-trek/&#34;&gt;recent update&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, Abby and I will be missing it this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;run-shadyside-5k&#34;&gt;Run Shadyside 5K&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you like to run in races, a fine race is the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.runshadyside.com/&#34;&gt;Run Shadyside 5K&lt;/a&gt;. Fast and flat, with a pancake breakfast and festivities afterwards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not running in it this year, just because I have too many other things to do already for the rest of the day, but here&amp;rsquo;s my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/01/run-shadyside-5k-outrunning-mickey-mouse-and-lending-a-trumpet/&#34;&gt;report from two years ago&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;free-5th-annual-wilkins-school-community-center-ecofest-in-regent-square&#34;&gt;Free: 5th annual Wilkins School Community Center Ecofest in Regent Square&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/ecofest-2013.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;5th annual Wilkins School Community Center Ecofest in Regent Square&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Interested in green living? Check out the &lt;a href=&#34;http://foresthills-regentsquare.patch.com/groups/around-town/p/ecofest-encourages-recycling-green-living&#34;&gt;5th annual Wilkins School Community Center Ecofest in Regent Square&lt;/a&gt;. Abby has regularly attended for the clothing swap. There will also be food, information, and entertainment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that this year, I will also be attending, to perform as a new member of the Steel City Ukuleles. &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/08/23/another-unexpected-life-change-one-month-of-learning-to-play-ukulele/&#34;&gt;I just started playing the ukulele a bit over two months ago&lt;/a&gt;, and have been working hard to help put on an entertaining show!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;ll be performing around 11:30 AM to 12:30 PM. If you come, say hello!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;cmu-donut-dash-2-mile-race&#34;&gt;CMU Donut Dash 2 mile race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, if you are into weird running events, there is the &lt;a href=&#34;http://cmudonutdash.org/&#34;&gt;Carnegie Mellon University Donut Dash&lt;/a&gt;, a 2 mile event serving as a fundraiser for the Children&amp;rsquo;s Hospital of Pittsburgh of UPMC. This is not an event I have ever done, and not one I intend to do, but what the heck, some of you might love this sort of thing!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;national-chess-day-gateway-open-tournament-at-the-pittsburgh-chess-club&#34;&gt;National Chess Day: Gateway Open tournament at the Pittsburgh Chess Club&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did you know that it&amp;rsquo;s time for &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nationalchessday.com/&#34;&gt;National Chess Day&lt;/a&gt;? There will be a tournament at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburghcc.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Chess Club&lt;/a&gt;, the 56th annual Gateway Open. Yes, chess in Pittsburgh has a long and illustrious history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;pittsburgh-perl-workshop&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Perl Workshop&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are a Perl programmer, the &lt;a href=&#34;http://pghpw.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Perl Workshop&lt;/a&gt; is back &lt;a href=&#34;http://pghpw.org/ppw2013/&#34;&gt;this year&lt;/a&gt;. Registration is already closed, so it&amp;rsquo;s not so helpful right now for me to mention it, but in case you didn&amp;rsquo;t know it existed, watch for it next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;ninth-thing&#34;&gt;Ninth thing?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, I guess I miscounted. But there are a whole lot more than nine things to do in Pittsburgh tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, if you are interested in some free stuff to do, there&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.radworkshere.org/interior.php?pageID=64&#34;&gt;RADical Days&lt;/a&gt; listing a whole bunch of stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s no shortage of stuff to do in this great city of Pittsburgh at any time or day of year. I think it&amp;rsquo;s unfortunate that many things I like to do happen to repeatedly fall on the first Saturday of the year, but I&amp;rsquo;m not complaining about an embarrassment of riches. Go out and take advantage of what I can&amp;rsquo;t.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>RIP, Eydie Gormé</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/08/10/rip-eydie/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Aug 2013 23:08:41 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/08/10/rip-eydie/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I learned that American singer &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eydie_Gorm%C3%A9&#34;&gt;Eydie Gormé&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.npr.org/blogs/thetwo-way/2013/08/10/210927460/reports-singer-eydie-gorme-dies-at-84&#34;&gt;just died&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I actually knew very little about her until reading about her death.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But she made a huge difference in my life!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/c/ca/Eydie_Gorme.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Eydie Gormé&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;eydie-gormé-and-los-panchos&#34;&gt;Eydie Gormé and Los Panchos&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know of her only through her famous recordings from the 1960s of Latin music with &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Los_Panchos&#34;&gt;Los Panchos&lt;/a&gt;. They recorded a number of classic &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/bolero/&#34;&gt;boleros&lt;/a&gt; that constantly kept me company when I was doing &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/ballroom-dance/&#34;&gt;ballroom dance&lt;/a&gt; over a decade ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In particular, I really enjoyed their performance of &amp;ldquo;Sabor a mî&amp;rdquo;, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/11/17/a-childhood-dream-come-true-i-am-now-finally-singing-for-real/&#34;&gt;my favorite bolero of all time&lt;/a&gt;, both to listen to and to dance to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/0Uz6ZDJjXvE&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was interesting for me to learn, just now, that her parents were Sephardic Jews, her father from Sicily and her mother from Turkey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;should-i-thank-people-before-they-die&#34;&gt;Should I thank people before they die?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is always strange to me when people die and I realize I barely knew anything about them, but feel deep gratitude for how they&amp;rsquo;ve so much enhanced my life. This was the case with Eydie Gormé.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve never been into &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fandom&#34;&gt;fandom&lt;/a&gt;, but lately I&amp;rsquo;ve been wondering, in an era when it actually is much easier to contact &amp;ldquo;celebrities&amp;rdquo;, whether sending a simple one-shot note to someone expressing gratitude, well before death, might be appropriate. Especially in the case of people who are actually not major celebrities (either because their prime time has passed or because their contribution is in a narrow niche). &lt;strong&gt;What do you think?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>RIP Bebo Valdés, master pianist of Cuban music</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/03/22/rip-bebo-valdes/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Mar 2013 20:08:56 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/03/22/rip-bebo-valdes/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.billboard.com/files/styles/promo_650/public/media/bebo-chucho-valdes-650-430.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Bebo and Chucho&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I just heard about the death of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bebo_Vald%C3%A9s&#34;&gt;Bebo Valdés&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.npr.org/blogs/ablogsupreme/2013/03/22/175080694/bebo-vald-s-giant-of-cuban-music-is-dead?ft=1&amp;amp;f=1039&#34;&gt;at age 94 in Sweden&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I discovered this Cuban musician a decade ago, when, as a big fan of Latin (especially Cuban) dance and music, I bought the documentary &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Calle_54&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Calle 54&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; when it came out. I had heard the playing of his son &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chucho_Vald%C3%A9s&#34;&gt;Chucho&lt;/a&gt; and was very curious how Bebo&amp;rsquo;s playing might differ. The father had a more old-fashioned style, of course. But he was good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most moving scene in the entire film was that of father and son playing together, on two pianos, improvising on the famous Cuban song &amp;ldquo;La Comparsa&amp;rdquo; by &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ernesto_Lecuona&#34;&gt;Ernesto Lecuona&lt;/a&gt;. The communication between them and the interplay and contrasts were quite fascinating and touching to me. They got very emotional during their session and I could not help being moved to tears myself. The scene made me think about the story of Bebo&amp;rsquo;s decision to leave Cuba for Sweden, abandoning his family, and how he met up again with Chucho for this documentary! For me, reflecting on my own relationship with my father over the years (who is still very much alive and well; I see him once or twice a year, and will see him again soon), the scene was electric.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-bebo-chucho-scene-from-calle-54&#34;&gt;The Bebo/Chucho scene from &amp;ldquo;Calle 54&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/enblfWLM4n0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some highlights:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At the beginning, Bebo starts off with flourishes and then the theme, while Chucho provides a little bit of harmonic filler.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Then Chucho starts adding more countermelody.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At 2:01, they smile at each other as Bebo changes the key and lets Chucho take charge. Bebo goes into a lot of elaborate, passionate ornamentation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At 2:46, when the melody goes from minor to major, this is when things start getting intense: watch the two looking at each other with increasing emotion.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At 3:39, Bebo signals to slow things down. They end, slyly without a harmonic resolution. Then Chucho gets up and hugs his father.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rest in peace, Bebo Valdés.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Finally doing some Latin music jamming on flute; also Irish and French</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/03/17/finally-doing-some-latin-music-jamming-on-flute/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Mar 2013 23:36:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/03/17/finally-doing-some-latin-music-jamming-on-flute/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;St. Patrick&amp;rsquo;s Day weekend means, of course, a party at Henry&amp;rsquo;s. Last year Abby and I even went to two of his St. Patrick&amp;rsquo;s Day parties! At the first, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/17/st-patricks-day-party-playing-tin-whistle-and-flute/&#34;&gt;I played tin whistle for the first time&lt;/a&gt;, and I played some easy recorder music &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/30/a-delayed-st-patricks-day-party-playing-tin-whistle-and-alto-recorder/&#34;&gt;at the second&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year, I reflected on how far I&amp;rsquo;ve come musically, and as usual, wanted to do something new and challenging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;irish-music&#34;&gt;Irish music&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I brought my tin whistle and Irish flute ready to jam. It turned out that Barbara had come with violin ready for some Irish jamming also. When she went at it with Henry on piano, she ended up playing &amp;ldquo;Danny Boy&amp;rdquo; (&amp;ldquo;Londonderry Air&amp;rdquo;) as one selection. Unfortunately, I had planned on playing it on flute, &amp;ldquo;redeeming&amp;rdquo; myself after being terrible on flute a year ago &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/17/st-patricks-day-party-playing-tin-whistle-and-flute/&#34;&gt;when I tried it&lt;/a&gt;, so since she had already done it, I quietly scrapped my original plan. No problem: there were many other things to play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Barbara joined me and Henry in some jigs, reels, and waltzes that I pulled out, some of which I did on tin whistle and some of which I did on Irish flute. That was fun, if pretty exhausting: lots and lots of notes, not so easy to just plain sight read. But of course, nobody has to play all the notes. That&amp;rsquo;s the beauty of this music. There never were official notes anyway; these are traditional tunes with a certain recognizable rhythm and shape and harmonic movement, but everyone does the notes differently anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;french-music&#34;&gt;French music&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d asked Vasili to learn on accordion &amp;ldquo;Les Ormeaux&amp;rdquo;, which I had learned just recently &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/02/25/stepping-it-up-at-the-french-and-blues-jam/&#34;&gt;at a French jam&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s not actually a traditional tune, but it&amp;rsquo;s a great one. Unfortunately, it turned out that Vasili had learned it in a different key from the one I was using on modern flute, so one of us (him) transposed on the fly to try to match, and the result therefore wasn&amp;rsquo;t as good as it could have been. Next time! Anyway, Abby and I jammed with Vasili on stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;latin-music&#34;&gt;Latin music&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;bolero&#34;&gt;Bolero&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The musical highlight for me was my debut in playing Latin, or more specifically, Cuban music. I fell in love with this music when I was &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/10/flute-loving-it-again/&#34;&gt;introduced to Latin ballroom dance back in 2000&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started off with an unnamed bolero from a World Music Cuba book I had first encountered &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/02/22/flute-progress-still-hanging-in-there/&#34;&gt;a year ago when I was just barely playing flute&lt;/a&gt;. I got on flute and Henry enthusiastically improvised along on piano and we took a couple of turns. That was great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I pulled out &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pbs.org/buenavista/music/songs/dos_gardenias.html&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Dos Gardenias&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, one of my favorite boleros of all time (and the bolero is one of my favorite musical genres). (By the way, I am working on being ready to sing this and other boleros before too long, making my debut as a bolero singer.) Again, more fun opportunities for inventiveness for Henry and me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;buena-vista-social-club&#34;&gt;Buena Vista Social Club&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, I first encountered &amp;ldquo;Dos Gardenias&amp;rdquo; through Ibrahim Ferrer of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Buena_Vista_Social_Club_%28album%29&#34;&gt;Buena Vista Social Club&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/5pKW7qvYSHU&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Buena Vista Social Club&amp;rdquo; was a very important music recording to me. At a time in my life around thirteen years ago when I was trying to explore Latin music and asked around for suggestions, my grad school classmate Andrej recommended this CD to me and my musical world was changed forever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;cha-cha&#34;&gt;Cha cha&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I pulled out an unnamed cha cha from the World Music Cuba book. We really went wild for this one, especially since Chad, one of Henry&amp;rsquo;s piano students (and a fine improviser) decided to join us and sat at the piano with Henry as both of them played with me and we kept going and going and I became very excited and inspired along with them. Wow. That was one of the most intense musical experiences I&amp;rsquo;ve ever had. It was frightening (didn&amp;rsquo;t know when I&amp;rsquo;d hit the limits of my technique or inventiveness) and exhilarating at the same time. When I was done, I was sweating from all the effort. Abby said she&amp;rsquo;d never seen me so animated before playing music, since she&amp;rsquo;s only ever seen me play Baroque and other such music mainly, or Irish and French. Well, Latin jazz is different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;chess&#34;&gt;Chess&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point in the evening, I needed a break from playing music and from socializing and decided to rest. However, it turned out that my &amp;ldquo;rest&amp;rdquo; consisted of relaxing in a chair while closing my eyes and&amp;hellip; &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/17/my-second-ever-blindfold-chess-game/&#34;&gt;playing blindfold chess&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2014-03-16&#34;&gt;(Update of 2014-03-16)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I couldn&amp;rsquo;t make it to Henry&amp;rsquo;s St. Patrick Day party in 2014. I felt sad about this, but our other plans made earlier made it impractical to try to attend.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Classical Revolution: Pittsburgh&#39;s AquiTango delivers passionate traditional tango</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/11/14/classical-revolution-pittsburghs-aquitango-delivers-passionate-traditional-tango/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Nov 2012 20:48:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/11/14/classical-revolution-pittsburghs-aquitango-delivers-passionate-traditional-tango/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;So I got word of a relatively new movement called &lt;a href=&#34;http://classicalrevolution.org/&#34;&gt;Classical Revolution&lt;/a&gt; that is spreading &lt;a href=&#34;http://classicalrevolution.org/chapters/&#34;&gt;around the world&lt;/a&gt;, and has reached Pittsburgh, which has its &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.classicalrevolutionpgh.org/&#34;&gt;own chapter&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/classicalrevolutionpgh&#34;&gt;Facebook page&lt;/a&gt;). The point of Classical Revolution is to &lt;a href=&#34;http://classicalrevolution.org/about/&#34;&gt;perform chamber music in non-traditional settings&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;tango&#34;&gt;Tango&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I saw that the local Pittsburgh tango group &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.aquitango.com/&#34;&gt;AquiTango&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/AquiTango&#34;&gt;Facebook page&lt;/a&gt;) was &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/events/380553315352985/&#34;&gt;going to perform&lt;/a&gt; at &lt;a href=&#34;http://barmarcopgh.com/&#34;&gt;Bar Marco&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AquiTango was to perform traditional &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Argentine_tango&#34;&gt;Argentine tango&lt;/a&gt; music. I had actually encountered, a decade ago, an earlier incarnation (with some member changes since then) of the group, when I was taking Argentine tango classes and dancing; it was formerly Tangueros de Ley. I remember when Julieta Ugartemendia was in the group, playing clarinet and singing, and she also danced! In any case, the group has been revived after she left, as a quartet.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://lh5.ggpht.com/hopUhptskdqtJ-rQfGKZ2awY2KUwuQS9waErFnvkkmdrot9eRTguZRgn--7a8JHRNfGuU2R73hzDssjWGfO5=s615&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;AquiTango&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I decided to attend, not only to check out what the experience of &amp;ldquo;Classical Revolution&amp;rdquo; in such a venue is like, but also for my own special reason: to be inspired by some good tango performances, because I am actually planning to soon play tango on flute and also sing it for the first time!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So here&amp;rsquo;s my review of the concert.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2012-11-17&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-11-17)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/11/17/a-childhood-dream-come-true-i-am-now-finally-singing-for-real/&#34;&gt;Three days later, I did in fact perform tango, at a party!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-venue&#34;&gt;The venue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second floor of Bar Marco is a nice place for chamber music. Not too big, not too small. The musicians play near the windows, while the audience is seated in folding chairs. Wine was available for those who wanted it (I chose not to have any).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-concert&#34;&gt;The concert&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;dancers&#34;&gt;Dancers?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although I am no longer part of the local tango dance community, I could tell as people arrived that some of them knew each other and were dancers. During the concert, it was easy to tell who were the dancers, because they couldn&amp;rsquo;t keep still and fidgeted in their seats or tapped out rhythms. (OK, I kind of did that too.) I was a little surprised that nobody just got up and danced. Maybe there weren&amp;rsquo;t quite enough dancers, or maybe they thought it was a more formal kind of event at which dancing would not have been appropriate. It was definitely a &amp;ldquo;chamber music recital&amp;rdquo; kind of atmosphere rather than a dance atmosphere. That was fine, but I did miss seeing a little bit of dancing. (Or maybe people were dancing at the back whom I didn&amp;rsquo;t see; I was sitting near the front to better see and hear the musicians.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;musicians-and-music&#34;&gt;Musicians and music&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The quartet (keyboard, violin, bass, accordion/voice) seemed to be having fun playing in this environment. The vibe was fairly informal, with a lot of smiling and banter. They played a lot of classic tangos, waltzes, and milongas, including some I had practiced myself at home, such as &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Por_una_Cabeza&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Por una Cabeza&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed how Ernesto Contenti, who is originally from Argentina actually, talked about his history and the songs he sang (he both sang and played the accordion). He said that when he was growing up, tango was just old-people stuff, and it barely even registered in his youthful existence. It was only after he had left the country and then encountered the passion for tango elsewhere that he really discovered the music of his homeland! When he sang the classic &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mi_Buenos_Aires_querido_(song)&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Mi Buenos Aires querido&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, it seemed to ring out in a deeply personal way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The violinist, Maureen Conlon-Gutierrez, is originally from Mexico, and her classical training showed in the brilliance and polish of her play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bassist, Jose Puentes, providing the foundation for the quartet, is from Venezuela.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pianist, Tom Roberts, joked about his non-Latin heritage, being a local. They have a nickname for him, &amp;ldquo;El Cacho&amp;rdquo;. His keyboard playing was particularly lively and adventurous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AquiTango at some point played some non-traditional pieces also. I enjoyed the added variety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;after-the-concert&#34;&gt;After the concert&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had to leave immediately after the concert, because of many things to do this busy week. It would have been nice to stay and chat with the musicians and other audience members; I saw a lot of people going up to the musicians to chat. One thing great about this informal &amp;ldquo;Classical Revolution&amp;rdquo; format is that there is not as much &amp;ldquo;distance&amp;rdquo; between the performers and audience as in a traditional venue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I left feeling excited about my plans to perform tango music soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;some-videos-online&#34;&gt;Some videos online&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a recent sample of AquiTango in action, performing the tango classic &amp;ldquo;La Cumparsita&amp;rdquo;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/zHaasDMVYYo&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is an older sample of AquiTango, playing on the street in Squirrel Hill:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/6u6RO8c5b8I&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re in the Pittsburgh area and looking for some live traditional tango music performed with precision and fire, check out the AquiTango quartet!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-02-28&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-02-28)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went to Bar Marco again for &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/02/28/another-exciting-concert-at-bar-marco-chris-norman-and-the-chatham-baroque-playing-a-tasty-assortment-of-dynamic-music/&#34;&gt;another enjoyable music performance&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The paradox of practice: it&#39;s harder to go slow than go fast</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/08/02/the-paradox-of-practice-its-harder-to-go-slow-than-go-fast/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Aug 2012 23:09:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/08/02/the-paradox-of-practice-its-harder-to-go-slow-than-go-fast/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently, by coincidence, I&amp;rsquo;ve seen a lot of articles about the benefits of &lt;em&gt;slow&lt;/em&gt; practice of a skill, whether in music or martial arts. Some good links that really apply to all physical skills:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bulletproofmusician.com/is-slow-practice-really-necessary/&#34;&gt;Is slow practice really necessary?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://musiciansway.com/blog/2011/02/a-different-kind-of-slow-practice/&#34;&gt;A different kind of slow practice&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://billplakemusic.org/2012/07/18/keep-this-aim-in-mind-when-practicing-slowly/&#34;&gt;Keep this aim in mind when practicing slowly&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://themartialartscoach.com/train-slow-to-learn-fast&#34;&gt;Train slow to learn fast&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We live in an era of &lt;em&gt;speed&lt;/em&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s gotten to the point that there have arisen some movements against speed, for &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Slow_Movement&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;slow&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a confession to make: it&amp;rsquo;s really hard for me to practice music slowly. I myself am guilty of often practicing music too quickly, not making the most of my practice. For a while, when I was starting to play music again after an absence of three decades, I was pushing myself with a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/29/a-musicians-best-friend/&#34;&gt;metronome&lt;/a&gt;. That was useful for a while, but eventually I realized I had to slow down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am now actually trying to apply the advice in the articles mentioned and &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; slow down in music. Because I know in my heart that slowing down works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I think about it, I have successfully used slow practice in many fields in the past, from ballroom dance to running to chess. I&amp;rsquo;d like to give examples of what slow practice actually means in each of these and how I attribute my success to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;ballroom-dance&#34;&gt;Ballroom dance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was learning &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/ballroom-dance/&#34;&gt;ballroom dance&lt;/a&gt; over a decade ago, I started out as a very uncoordinated, clumsy, confused beginner in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://cmubdc.org/&#34;&gt;Carnegie Mellon University Ballroom Dance Club&lt;/a&gt;. I was &lt;em&gt;very lucky&lt;/em&gt; that I stumbled around only about a month before I started getting quality professional instruction in a small group setting (a benefit of the club) supplementing the large group classes (which I had found barely helpful, frankly).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;rumba-to-cha-cha&#34;&gt;Rumba to cha cha&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will never forget the Latin (International style) dance technique lessons of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.artandstyledancestudio.com/&#34;&gt;Rozana Sweeney&lt;/a&gt;. She basically treated us as she would little kids intending to become professional ballroom dancers. Unlike in the group classes at CMU, where we were just shown steps and patterns and told to go do them, we were shown a very limited repertoire of movements that were broken down to atomic components (so much as that is possible for a continuous art form) and practiced &lt;em&gt;very slowly&lt;/em&gt;. We were not allowed to move on until we had at least some rudimentary &amp;ldquo;mastery&amp;rdquo; of the &amp;ldquo;basics&amp;rdquo;. I&amp;rsquo;d never had any dance experience before, so it was quite eye-opening how effective this stern approach to instruction was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We started off practicing the International rumba basics. We were taught about straight legs, bent legs, foot turnout, hip rotation, contrary motion of body and arms, etc. We went through the movements so slowly (to beats or music much slower than the actual standardized-tempo dance music) that many of us lost balance and tripped over ourselves. &lt;em&gt;It is harder to move slow than fast.&lt;/em&gt; Balance is important. If you go fast, you cheat because you can move without full balance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eventually we moved on to cha cha, which is a rather faster dance, but similar to a sped-up rumba with a very fast extra three &amp;ldquo;cha cha cha&amp;rdquo; steps. I couldn&amp;rsquo;t help noticing how my cha cha &amp;ldquo;magically&amp;rdquo; improved, &lt;em&gt;without ever practicing cha cha&lt;/em&gt;, just from practicing rumba so much. The reason was clear: making the slow precise is the key to making the fast precise. If the slow is not efficient and exact, then going fast will only result in a magnification of inefficiency and sloppiness. I believe nobody can dance a good cha cha who can&amp;rsquo;t also dance a good rumba. That&amp;rsquo;s just how it works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;slow-waltz-and-foxtrot-to-quickstep-and-viennese-waltz&#34;&gt;Slow waltz and foxtrot to quickstep and Viennese waltz&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Focusing on the slow was also true of our International standard dance instruction, which came from some other instructors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We started off with slow waltz and foxtrot, working on the technique in slow motion, before dancing the fast quickstep and Viennese waltz. The fast dances are quite strenuous (as a runner, I compare dancing them with a partner to be as tiring as running) and things fall apart if you haven&amp;rsquo;t figured out how to move efficiently and together slowly first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;results&#34;&gt;Results&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I improved very quickly in ballroom dance once I started having the serious technique lessons and worked on basic movements by myself outside of class, repeatedly. I still feel I had a lot of potential improvement still in me, because of the foundational slow practice, at the time &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/10/flute-loving-it-again/&#34;&gt;when I quit competitive ballroom dancing&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;running&#34;&gt;Running&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I started &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/running/&#34;&gt;running&lt;/a&gt;, I was 29 years old and had been sedentary all my life. I didn&amp;rsquo;t know what I was doing when I first started running. I would just go out and run hard, get out of breath very quickly, stop, and go on. I got sore this way, and also did not actually improve my speed much during my first sloppy year of running. I only got &lt;em&gt;much faster&lt;/em&gt; when I learned the science of how to run &lt;em&gt;slowly&lt;/em&gt;. I got much faster than friends I was running with who were still running the unsystematic way, at a faster training pace than me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is possible to run too slowly for benefit. But the trick is to run slowly enough in order to be relaxed, observe one&amp;rsquo;s form, correct it, and put in the time to slowly build up endurance. Running too fast only led me to go for a shorter period of time, execute with poor form, and get injured.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not actually easy to run slowly, properly. It is trivial to run slowly sloppily. Many people you see on the roads or in the parks who are &amp;ldquo;jogging&amp;rdquo; are going slowly and sloppily. Stomping loudly into the ground, head tilted back, slow long strides: that&amp;rsquo;s not a good way to run slowly. If you want to run slowly, the right way to do it is to adopt a good upright, balanced posture, be aware of landing under the hip, using the glutes and not the knees, and most important, making sure the cadence is &lt;em&gt;not too slow&lt;/em&gt;. In other words, slow doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean everything is slow; it means slowing down some variables but maintaining structural and dynamic integrity of the whole. Taking a super long stride slowly violates the physics of how to move.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Needless to say, for optimal training one must also run fast. Again, here the principle of adjusting variables applies, however. Running very fast for a long time is not the most effective way to train. The most effective way to train is known to be &lt;em&gt;interval training&lt;/em&gt;, in which you run fast but for a short period of time, then rest, then continue. In a sense, here the &amp;ldquo;slow&amp;rdquo; variable is distance covered while not resting. In slow running, the &amp;ldquo;slow&amp;rdquo; variable is the speed, not the distance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;results-1&#34;&gt;Results&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a couple of years, upon finding good running technique books and Web sites, and applying them, I went from nothing to winning age-group medals and trophies in local races in Pittsburgh (admittedly not so competitive in my age group). I am a believer in the importance of having learned to run sufficiently slowly when the training situation calls for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;chess&#34;&gt;Chess&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/chess/&#34;&gt;chess&lt;/a&gt; players, myself included, enjoying playing &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fast_chess&#34;&gt;fast chess&lt;/a&gt;. Five-minute games are exciting and fun because you can play so many of them in a given time and there is little time to think. But we all know that playing too much blitz chess can harm one&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;serious&amp;rdquo; slow chess games, games in which you may get two hours of time on your clock rather than five minutes. The problem, of course, is that getting used to making moves without thinking much does not train you to know how to think more deeply when you have much more time to use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Learning to play chess slowly is a challenge. I was never very good at playing slowly as a child, because I was impatient, and did not have a chess teacher to discipline me. When I returned to playing serious tournament chess, twenty years after not playing a single game, I suffered tremendously, because I had no idea how to make use of time during slow games. But with practice, analyzing games at home slowly in order to simulate the process, I learned how to look more deeply in the tree of possible game continuations. I would give myself three minutes, say, to do an analysis, and then computer-check it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I noticed that getting better at playing slowly actually helped me get better at playing quickly too (to some extent). There is a statistical correlation, indeed, between the regular strength of a chess player (as measured by an official rating) and his or her speed strength (as measured by an official speed rating). This should not be surprising: in distance running, there is a correlation between speed at running a mile and speed at running a marathon. The mile and marathon are very different distances, but a certain kind of fundamental efficiency is involved in both.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;results-2&#34;&gt;Results&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just over a year after I started playing chess again, initially poorly, my practice in playing slow chess at Tuesday night &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburghcc.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Chess Club&lt;/a&gt; tournaments (at two hours per game for each player) in combination with some (but not too much) casual fast chess at the club resulted in my surprising excellence at &amp;ldquo;slow fast&amp;rdquo; chess: I won the &lt;a href=&#34;http://pscfchess.org/results/06040808.htm&#34;&gt;2006 Pennsylvania State Game/29 Championship&lt;/a&gt; with a perfect score, and also won the &lt;a href=&#34;http://pscfchess.org/results/06101414.htm&#34;&gt;2006 Pennsylvania State Action Chess Championship&lt;/a&gt; with a perfect score (at time controls of 29 minutes per game and 30 minutes per game, respectively). Doing well at two-hour games made me even better at 29-minute games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slow practice works. It has worked for me in different fields. I want to make it work for music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slow practice requires much discipline, patience, and metacognitive awareness It is easy to take shortcuts unless one has bootstrapped a skill enough in order to be able to know oneself and to recognize one&amp;rsquo;s weaknesses and deliberately work on correcting them. Wonderful Web sites and books and videos on technique do exist that can help these days, even without a personal instructor.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Another terrifying music jam session but I played a little bit of blues and old time</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/07/07/another-terrifying-music-jam-session-but-i-played-a-little-bit-of-blues-and-old-time/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Jul 2012 23:37:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/07/07/another-terrifying-music-jam-session-but-i-played-a-little-bit-of-blues-and-old-time/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/03/petrified-at-a-music-jam-session-so-i-didnt-play-but-watched-and-listened&#34;&gt;Just earlier this week, I went to a music jam where I was afraid to play&lt;/a&gt; and so I didn&amp;rsquo;t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today Abby and I went to another intimidating potluck/jam session, this time hosted by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.appalasia.com/Mimi.htm&#34;&gt;Mimi Jong&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://classic-sculpture.com/&#34;&gt;Susan Wagner&lt;/a&gt;. Mimi had invited Abby, but hadn&amp;rsquo;t yet met me; I knew who she was through having been to an &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.appalasia.com/&#34;&gt;Appalasia&lt;/a&gt; performance with Abby at some point earlier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This time I played a little bit. I almost didn&amp;rsquo;t, but felt that I had to start with something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;lots-of-music&#34;&gt;Lots of music&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was music going on outside in back of the home. Wow. It was fantastic stuff, what everyone was doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was Mimi on &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Erhu&#34;&gt;erhu&lt;/a&gt;, of course. There was a keyboard and sound system set up. People on bass, guitars, drums of all kinds, claves, banjos, violin, singing, you name it. All kinds of music was being jammed to. A lot of Latin music, sung by someone who seemed a native Spanish speaker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recognized a violinist as being someone who had played Baroque violin at a recital I had been at in April.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, there were clearly a lot of professional musicians here and so I felt really intimidated. I did a lot of watching and listening and quite enjoyed experiencing joy and inventiveness unfold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was fascinating seeing Mimi kicking off &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Summertime_(song)&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Summertime&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; on erhu. Hey, why not?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the Latin and Brazilian songs I knew the melodies for, and if I only knew all lyrics and could actually sing, I would have wanted to join in for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;joining-in&#34;&gt;Joining in&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But Mimi encouraged Abby and me to join in. At some point, Abby did join in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of the problem for me, besides the fact that I felt naked and helpless without a music score to read, was that I&amp;rsquo;d brought one case of instruments this time, which included some recorders as well as a Baroque flute, and it didn&amp;rsquo;t seem like any of these instruments was really suitable for the occasion. In my hurry to arrive at the potluck already running late, I had forgotten to bring my modern flute!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did the best I could and took out my Baroque flute and tried joining in. Some old time music came on and I found it not so difficult to do something for that, although nothing I was proud of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I remember mainly is when Mimi started some blues and at some point I came in and gave it a shot, and although I didn&amp;rsquo;t last very long, I got something in that wasn&amp;rsquo;t totally horrible. Somehow that was very liberating, getting those few seconds in for the evening. At least I didn&amp;rsquo;t walk away from the party this evening without playing anything at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Attending this potluck/jam session was an immensely exciting experience for me. I feel like I am truly expanding my musical world, and getting inspired. I too would like to be singing my favorite Latin songs. And I really like blues improvisation. I will start doing these things eventually; they are no longer just remote possibilities, but what I have seen people doing in front of my own eyes and not in an impersonal concert but at a casual, fun party.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-01-28&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-01-28)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Six months later, I participated in &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/28/my-first-blues-music-jam-happened-after-the-regular-french-music-jam/&#34;&gt;my first blues jam&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-09-28&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-09-28)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over a year later, I reported on &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/09/28/an-erhu-player-and-a-tuba-player-at-a-party-said-lets-jam/&#34;&gt;participating in a music jam at another one of these parties with Mimi&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Flute update: celebrating Bach&#39;s birthday, using a Thumbport, improvising to bossa nova</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/03/21/flute-update-celebrating-bachs-birthday/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Mar 2012 20:57:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/03/21/flute-update-celebrating-bachs-birthday/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s been eleven days since &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/10/flute-loving-it-again/&#34;&gt;my last blog post on my flute progress&lt;/a&gt;. During this time, there have been various changes in my life, including &lt;em&gt;radical&lt;/em&gt; changes in my musical life. It will take me a couple of additional blog posts to discuss these changes, but for now, I&amp;rsquo;ll talk only about today&amp;rsquo;s snapshot of my flute activity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2012-03-12&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-03-12)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had ended up &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/12/quitting-the-cmu-all-university-orchestra-one-of-the-hardest-decisions-in-my-life/&#34;&gt;quitting the CMU AUO&lt;/a&gt;, and then having a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/17/st-patricks-day-party-playing-tin-whistle-and-flute/&#34;&gt;wonderful musical experience a birthday party&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;thumbport&#34;&gt;Thumbport&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.thumbport.com/images/position.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Thumbport&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Today I received a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.thumbport.com/&#34;&gt;Thumbport II&lt;/a&gt; I ordered recently. It&amp;rsquo;s a snap-on device that helps with holding a flute, by making it easier to balance the flute on the right thumb, thereby decreasing rolling of the flute and pressure on the right pinkie finger. I tried it for the first time today and it seems useful. We&amp;rsquo;ll see if it helps a bit with my form and &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/07/flute-taking-a-break-while-clarifying-my-goals/&#34;&gt;injury issues&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;i-celebrated-the-327th-birthday-of-johann-sebastian-bach&#34;&gt;I celebrated the 327th birthday of Johann Sebastian Bach&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t follow celebrity birthdays, but I could not avoid hearing about the birthday of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Johann_Sebastian_Bach&#34;&gt;Johann Sebastian Bach, born in 1685&lt;/a&gt;, thanks to some music blogs I follow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How to celebrate? The last time I celebrated a composer&amp;rsquo;s birthday, it was last October, for Franz Liszt&amp;rsquo;s 200th birthday. Then, I listened to a piece of music by the composer and &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/22/happy-200th-birthday/&#34;&gt;wrote up my impressions of it&lt;/a&gt;. Today, I again had the option to read about Bach or his music, and but I mostly chose to play his music, in order to celebrate as &lt;em&gt;actively&lt;/em&gt; as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;playing-the-cello-suite-no-1-in-g-major-bwv-1007&#34;&gt;Playing the cello suite no. 1 in G major, BWV 1007&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I sight read a bunch of old Bach&amp;rsquo;s music that eventually I should practice seriously to play well, including various minuets and bourrées.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the main piece I sight read was the full &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cello_Suites_(Bach)&#34;&gt;cello suite&lt;/a&gt; no. 1 in G major, using an &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pjb.com.au/mus/arr.html&#34;&gt;arrangement for flute by Peter Billam&lt;/a&gt;. (I had actually obtained this a long time ago intending to play it on alto &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/recorder/&#34;&gt;recorder&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This music is deceptively simple but really quite beautiful. Even visually it is pleasing: check out Bach&amp;rsquo;s handwritten score:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/9/9c/Bachs1a.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Bach cello suite no. 1, first page&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h4 id=&#34;visual-animation&#34;&gt;Visual animation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, you must check out the following unconventional visual animated representation of this music (see the creator&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.chenalexander.com/2011/baroque-bach-cello/&#34;&gt;blog post about its construction&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe src=&#34;http://player.vimeo.com/video/31179423?title=0&amp;amp;byline=0&amp;amp;portrait=0&#34; width=&#34;400&#34; height=&#34;225&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen allowFullScreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://vimeo.com/31179423&#34;&gt;Baroque.me: J.S. Bach - Cello Suite No. 1 - Prelude&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href=&#34;http://vimeo.com/alexanderchen&#34;&gt;Alexander Chen&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&#34;http://vimeo.com&#34;&gt;Vimeo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;bossa-nova&#34;&gt;Bossa nova&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://s3.amazonaws.com/halleonard-closerlook/00843016/00843016FC.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Latin Jazz: 10 Latin Jazz Classics&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Today I also picked up from the public library another play-along score/CD set, this time a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.halleonard.com/product/viewproduct.do?itemid=843016&amp;amp;lid=1&amp;amp;keywords=latin&amp;amp;seriesfeature=JZPLYA&amp;amp;&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Latin jazz&amp;rdquo; collection&lt;/a&gt;. Apart from the famous mambo &amp;ldquo;Ran Kan Kan&amp;rdquo; by Tito Puente, the rest was actually bossa nova, which was what I got it for. Recently I decided to get more into playing jazz and working on improvisation. Since I love the harmonies and tunes of classic bossa nova, I decided this was a good place to get started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a lot of fun playing around with the accompaniment CD. Actually, I would also like to sing this music, but unlike with salsa and bolero, where I am completely comfortable singing in Spanish, I am not proficient in the Portuguese language and it trips me up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I just thought I&amp;rsquo;d provide a short update on some of my current musical activities, until I have time to write about the big changes I&amp;rsquo;ve made in my musical life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-musical-tangent-bach-s-goldberg-variations&#34;&gt;A musical tangent: Bach&amp;rsquo;s Goldberg Variations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In turns out there is a whole series of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.npr.org/blogs/deceptivecadence/148455347/goldberg-week&#34;&gt;posts on the NPR music blog about the Goldberg Variations&lt;/a&gt;. I could not resist dipping into this series, because I am a Goldberg geek. I would like someday to get good enough on piano to play much of it.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Flute: loving it again, remembering why I dance, and how I met my wife!</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/03/10/flute-loving-it-again/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Mar 2012 21:28:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/03/10/flute-loving-it-again/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, after four days of &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/07/flute-taking-a-break-while-clarifying-my-goals&#34;&gt;not even touching my (modern) flute&lt;/a&gt; and having spent the time having fun with my Baroque flute instead, I felt the urge to return to the modern flute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still have not regained the inclination to continue working on the orchestra music I still have to improve a lot on in the coming week, but I rediscovered the joy of simply playing my instrument.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;sound-intonation&#34;&gt;Sound, intonation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The perpetual challenges of getting clean sounds and accurate pitches on the Baroque flute in the past four days have given me an increased appreciation for the modern flute. I picked it up and spent time just trying to make beautiful sounds. Freed from the stress of orchestra practice, I felt much more relaxed on the instrument than I have for a while now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To my surprise (but not really), I have improved considerably on the flute after not playing it for four days. I really needed a break, a consolidation of lessons learned. My production of tones is much improved, and high notes are squeaking less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;music-for-dance&#34;&gt;Music for dance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing I&amp;rsquo;ve truly come to realize is that I particularly enjoy playing rhythmic music suitable for dancing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, every time I attend a dance, and there is live music, I experience a strange internal conflict: I do like to dance, but sometimes, I&amp;rsquo;d rather be on the other side of the dance floor, being the musical performer! The &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; time I&amp;rsquo;ve been on the other side has been at last year&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburghcontra.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Contras and Squares&lt;/a&gt; Holiday Ball.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most recent instance of my wishing I could sometimes stop dancing and just join the musicians has been at the local &lt;a href=&#34;http://coalcountry.org/frenchdance.html&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh French dance workshop and social&lt;/a&gt;, where we&amp;rsquo;ve had live piano, fiddle, and of course, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~gdyke/&#34;&gt;Gregory&lt;/a&gt; on his Irish flute. I wonder whether at some point I might be qualified to play for the event, using either my modern flute or Baroque flute. (By the way, it was held again today, but unfortunately, Abby and I chose not to go because we had too many things to do this weekend.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;remembering-dancing&#34;&gt;Remembering dancing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday I spent time playing along to a score/CD set I&amp;rsquo;ve mentioned before, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/World-Music-Cuba-Flute-play-along/dp/3702465804&#34;&gt;World Music Cuba&lt;/a&gt;. While playing the bolero, cha cha, and mambo pieces in particular, I felt I was returning &amp;ldquo;home&amp;rdquo; in many ways. This was among the first music I heard and saw people dancing to when I was curious and visited the &lt;a href=&#34;http://cmubdc.org/&#34;&gt;CMU Ballroom Dance Club&lt;/a&gt; in 2000, and fell in love with, and learned to dance to. I also played along to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Play-along-Argentina-Flute-World-Music/dp/3702465871&#34;&gt;World Music Argentina&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;some-photos-of-my-ballroom-dance-days&#34;&gt;Some photos of my ballroom dance days&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some photos of me dancing in 2002 with my last dance partner, Amy, before I quit competitive ballroom dancing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here we are at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dcdancesportinferno.com/&#34;&gt;DC DanceSport Inferno&lt;/a&gt; in 2002 doing a hockey stick in international rumba:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/ballroom/dcdi-2002-hockey-stick.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Amy and Franklin at DCDI 2002 in rumba&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And here were are at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://comp.cornelldancesport.org/&#34;&gt;Cornell DanceSport Classic&lt;/a&gt; in 2002 in cha cha, rumba, and tango:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/ballroom/cornell-2002-new-yorker.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Amy and Franklin at Cornell 2002 in cha cha&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/ballroom/cornell-2002-hockey-stick.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Amy and Franklin at Cornell 2002 in rumba&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/ballroom/cornell-2002-tango-promenade.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Amy and Franklin at Cornell 2002 in tango&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;dancing-with-abby&#34;&gt;Dancing with Abby&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But never mind the ballroom dance days. It was through salsa dancing that I met my wife!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;how-i-met-abby&#34;&gt;How I met Abby&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was through dancing that I met Abby in the first place. After quitting dancing in 2003, I never danced again until late 2006, when my friend Jon told me he had recently started salsa dancing (because of a girlfriend who got him into it) and invited me to join him at a free outdoors dance, and I went. Then as I re-entered the Pittsburgh salsa dance scene, I kept running into Abby.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;some-photos-of-us-dancing-salsa&#34;&gt;Some photos of us dancing salsa&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are not many photos of Abby dancing with me, because when I&amp;rsquo;m dancing, I&amp;rsquo;m not holding my camera, but here are some photos a friend took at a big salsa dance weekend at the Palisades in McKeesport in April 2008, a year after we started dating in 2007.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/palisades-2008/abby-franklin.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby and Franklin dancing salsa at Palisades&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/palisades-2008/abby-franklin-hair.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby and Franklin dancing salsa at Palisades, hair flying&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;expression-and-improvisation-in-dance-and-in-music&#34;&gt;Expression and improvisation in dance and in music&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;dance&#34;&gt;Dance&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One reason I gave up ballroom dancing was that I felt there was an overemphasis on &amp;ldquo;syllabus steps&amp;rdquo; (I realize this is an oversimplification of the ballroom dance culture; all very good ballroom dancers go beyond the syllabus mindset). After quitting ballroom dancing, I explored Argentine tango, which is all about improvisation, but I left it because (at the time) it seemed that most of the women in the local scene were very tall, which made dancing awkward for me. I got into salsa because freed from the closed embrace, there was clearly a lot of room for personal improvisation. Ironically, I first got into making stuff up as a result of my imperfect memory: I could never memorize long choreography of step patterns, whether I was doing ballroom dancing or anything else. So I would always make a &amp;ldquo;mistake&amp;rdquo;, then I would make something out of the mistake. I learned that as long as you get back in time with the music, and keep the lead and follow communication strong, there is no such thing really as a mistake. You just keep going, with whatever is happening at the present moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I now have a long-term goal of developing my technique and releasing my inhibitions so that I can improvise musically at will. Yesterday, I played with improvising when playing bolero, cha cha, and tango. It was a lot of fun and profoundly satisfying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;music&#34;&gt;Music&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I actually credit my study of the recorder and the Baroque flute for reawakening me to my dream of free expression and improvisation. Baroque music leaves room for a lot of interpretation of trills and ornamentation and articulation (subject, of course, to &amp;ldquo;good taste&amp;rdquo;). I want to go beyond that, but it has been a great starting point. For some reason, too much exposure to later music (such as Beethoven) had turned me into a score-reader, since such later music has so much already marked up for the performer to simply &lt;em&gt;obey&lt;/em&gt;. The sparse annotations in Renaissance and Baroque music give one much more freedom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am enjoying playing the flute again, now that I know what I really want to do with it. And I would like to merge my dance and music lives, just as Abby has always played the Balkan music she also dances to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2012-03-12&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-03-12)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ended up &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/12/quitting-the-cmu-all-university-orchestra-one-of-the-hardest-decisions-in-my-life/&#34;&gt;quitting the CMU AUO&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2013-01-26&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-01-26)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost a year later, I finally played tangos on flute &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/26/music-i-just-played-for-the-first-time-recorder-sonata-tangos/&#34;&gt;at a party&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2013-03-17&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-03-17)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost exactly a year later, I ended up playing selections from the World Music Cuba book &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/17/finally-doing-some-latin-music-jamming-on-flute/&#34;&gt;at a party&lt;/a&gt;, and improvising freely with two other guys!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Flute progress after one month in orchestra: still hanging in there</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/02/22/flute-progress-still-hanging-in-there/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Feb 2012 20:19:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/02/22/flute-progress-still-hanging-in-there/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It was exactly one month ago, January 22, when &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/02/01/joining-an-orchestra-learning-in-the-face-of-terror/&#34;&gt;I joined&lt;/a&gt; the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.andrew.cmu.edu/user/auo/&#34;&gt;Carnegie Mellon All-University Orchestra&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another week has gone by, and what I thought might be a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/02/14/flute-progress-report-day-of-reckoning-approaches/&#34;&gt;day of reckoning&lt;/a&gt; has come and gone, and I am still playing the flute in the CMU AUO and have not dropped out!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a sample of the hardest music from Bernstein&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Symphonic Dances from West Side Story&amp;rdquo; that I&amp;rsquo;m still struggling to play correctly, cleanly, and in tempo:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/flute-music/west-side-story-fugue.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;West Side Story: Fugue&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/flute-music/west-side-story-rumble.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;West Side Story: Rumble&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It is not very visible from my photos, but I have a huge number of pencil markings on my copy of the score.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story as of now:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;practice-in-the-past-week&#34;&gt;Practice in the past week&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;getting-down-the-basics&#34;&gt;Getting down the basics&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last Wednesday, I continued with focusing purely on improving technique with the Rubank method book. I did not even look at the Gershwin or Bernstein music for orchestra. I simply recognize that I have to focus on making fundamental progress in technique and trust that this will enable me to actually play the hard music at hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have not written much about this strategy, but I feel that it is effective and that many &lt;em&gt;amateurs&lt;/em&gt; do not practice or pursue their various life activities with this discipline, and therefore fall short of reaching their potential. And then typically, we amateurs make excuses, blaming lack of talent or lack of time for our slow progress or quick plateau at a mediocre level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is something in the general culture that encourages immediate gratification at the expense of true &lt;em&gt;craft&lt;/em&gt;. Yes, it is true that we cannot give our all toward our hobbies, the way we might for what we consider our jobs, but at the same time, if you add up the number of hours we spend at our hobbies, they actually do add up, and we might as well have made them count efficiently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me to attack the hard passages of music prematurely without building up technique would be analogous to the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;never running before but aiming to run a marathon in four months, and jumping straight into trying to run 15 miles&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;being a non-programmer and wanting to create a cool Web site in a month, but trying to read a book like &amp;ldquo;Learn Web Programming in 7 Days&amp;rdquo; and not really mastering concepts such as variables and functions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;never having cooked but deciding to make a really fancy and subtle French dish without mastering the basics of knife usage or the properties of butter&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People like shortcuts. But they usually do not succeed, and even if they do, don&amp;rsquo;t provide a sustainable path of growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My real goal isn&amp;rsquo;t just to survive playing in an orchestra concert. That&amp;rsquo;s actually just an incentive for my real goal, which is to improve my overall technique, so that I can continue to play music in any genre, any ensemble, as I wish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;an-off-day&#34;&gt;An off day&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, the next day, Thursday, I was feeling tired and unmotivated for practice. This happens sometimes. In fact, typically it happens once a week. I&amp;rsquo;m human. I can&amp;rsquo;t magically improve a huge amount every single day. Sometimes I&amp;rsquo;m tired. Sometimes I backslide, and notes come out jumbled, slow, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This, too, is a part of life. I&amp;rsquo;ve found the hard way that it&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; best to just push through and waste time and emotional energy. &lt;em&gt;Overtraining&lt;/em&gt; doesn&amp;rsquo;t help. Sometimes it is best to just take a break. I generally prefer to take an &lt;em&gt;active&lt;/em&gt; break.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, on Thursday I decided to put away the technique practice, which was not going well, and instead have fun sight-reading a bunch of music I had gotten out of the library earlier. I played around sight-reading &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Play-Puccini-Arias-Transcribed-Flute/dp/0634046209/&#34;&gt;transcribed opera arias from Puccini&lt;/a&gt; (I secretly love singing them in Italian even though I&amp;rsquo;m not a soprano or female!), &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Debussy-Album-Flute-Piano/dp/9043129712/&#34;&gt;transcriptions from Debussy&amp;rsquo;s piano music&lt;/a&gt; (I want to play the original piano pieces some day), and a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/World-Music-Cuba-Flute-play-along/dp/3702465804&#34;&gt;World Music Cuba&lt;/a&gt; album. It was a lot of fun playing real, lyrical music. I especially liked playing the Cuban music, since I always dreamed about doing that back when I was dancing salsa, rumba, cha cha, and bolero (I also have a goal of seriously singing this genre of music).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: eventually I would like to actually practice some of these music arrangements seriously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;update-of-2012-11-17&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-11-17)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nine months after this blog post, I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/11/17/a-childhood-dream-come-true-i-am-now-finally-singing-for-real/&#34;&gt;sang bolero for the first time in my life, to Abby&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;update-of-2013-03-17&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-03-17)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over a year later, I ended up playing selections from the World Music Cuba book &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/17/finally-doing-some-latin-music-jamming-on-flute/&#34;&gt;at a party&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;continued-practice&#34;&gt;Continued practice&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Friday and Saturday I was back doing technique, and Saturday I finally hit the CMU AUO music again. I noticed that I was playing the high notes on the flute better. Also, of course, I improved my speed and facility at many scales, but I won&amp;rsquo;t bore with listing metronome numbers to indicate my progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;sunday-s-orchestra-rehearsal&#34;&gt;Sunday&amp;rsquo;s orchestra rehearsal&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;sectional-for-woodwinds&#34;&gt;Sectional for woodwinds&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I arrived at 6:30 PM on Sunday for the woodwind sectional, but only one other person was there! People were running late, apparently. I was concerned when only three flutes (plus piccolo) showed up: did we lose another flute? (Later in the full rehearsal, two others joined us.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that in the woodwind sectional, collectively we were still struggling, and therefore I was not as out of place as I had feared I might be. It was a very useful rehearsal, in which many different instruments&amp;rsquo; parts started falling in place. It was at this point that I realized that I was having trouble not only because of my own problems but also because other peoples&amp;rsquo; problems were affecting me. I was having trouble coming in at the right time in many places not only because I was counting badly (although I&amp;rsquo;ve been working steadily at improving my counting) but also because so many other lines were not coming in at the right place either, so I could not rely on listening to others as a way of finding my place. Anyway, we made huge progress in some very difficult music. I actually believe, for the first time, that we might be able to get this stuff working for the concert.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;full-rehearsal&#34;&gt;Full rehearsal&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maria kept on being disappointed in the full rehearsal, asking if we had actually listened to the music, because we were still having so much trouble. (Actually, I have the music and listen to the whole thing at least once every other day.) Perhaps it was a blessing in disguise that so many of us were still unprepared, because it enabled me to not be completely left behind, as we kept the tempos still on the slow side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even so, there were sections in which I simply was unable to keep up. I feel that I really need to master most of them by next rehearsal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;this-week-s-practice&#34;&gt;This week&amp;rsquo;s practice&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My practice this week so far since the rehearsal has been good. I&amp;rsquo;m still focusing on building technique.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Monday, I made significant improvements in my high notes with scales. I worked some with the Bernstein.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Tuesday, I continued Rubank, and went back to some real basics, playing long tones, working on control of dynamics, and relaxation. I did not touch orchestra music at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, I did an abbreviated Rubank practice, then launched into much work on the Bernstein, to make things faster. As I do once or twice a week, I included a &amp;ldquo;test&amp;rdquo; for myself in which I played through all the problematic sections of the piece along with an actual recording. I&amp;rsquo;m doing much, much better now. There is still hope that I might be able to play most of the piece at full speed by Sunday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-look-back-to-three-months-ago&#34;&gt;A look back to three months ago&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is amusing to look back to what I was still having trouble playing, as a flute beginner, three months ago. I was just starting to work through a collection of &amp;ldquo;easy flute classics&amp;rdquo;:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/flute-music/moyse-easy-classics.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Moyse Collection of Easy Flute Classics&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Compare these simple, slow scores with the Bernstein excerpts in the photos at the beginning of this blog post!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;recorder&#34;&gt;Recorder&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Needless to say, I&amp;rsquo;ve completely put away my recorders. I did go to the monthly meeting of the Pittsburgh chapter of the American Recorder Society on Sunday to play, but that is all I will do with recorder until after the April orchestra concert. I would like to get serious about recorder again for late spring and summer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, I felt I was automatically slightly better at playing recorder even without touching it for a month. It&amp;rsquo;s the cross-training effect. Music is music, whichever instrument you&amp;rsquo;re playing: breath control, tone awareness, flexibility of fingers, etc. Even if I did sometimes forget my fingerings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m still enjoying improving at flute and slowly getting closer to being able to play the second flute part of the Bernstein in its entirety. I get less and less panicky about being in the orchestra as I &amp;ldquo;catch up&amp;rdquo; according to plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2012-03-12&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-03-12)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ended up &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/12/quitting-the-cmu-all-university-orchestra-one-of-the-hardest-decisions-in-my-life/&#34;&gt;quitting the CMU AUO&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Video review: Dancing with the Stars: Cardio Dance (2006)</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/12/13/video-review-dancing-with-the-stars-cardio-dance-2006/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Dec 2011 22:46:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/12/13/video-review-dancing-with-the-stars-cardio-dance-2006/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When the weather is cold, I confess that I don&amp;rsquo;t enjoy running outside. I have done so in the past when much more serious about running, but I do not like it much. So I end up doing exercise indoors that is something of a substitute for running. I should really take up swimming (Abby wants to get me to do that), but traditionally, I have enjoyed doing &lt;strong&gt;dance&lt;/strong&gt; workouts to videos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of my favorite dance workout DVDs, which I have used for almost half a decade now since it came out, is &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Dancing-Stars-Cardio-Dance/dp/B000MMMTC8&#34;&gt;Dancing with the Stars: Cardio Dance (2006)&lt;/a&gt;. I have never tired of it (as long as I don&amp;rsquo;t use it all the time, of course; I have a number of other exercise videos I will review later).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://ecx.images-amazon.com/images/I/51j9ihJucML._SL500_AA300_.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Dancing with the Stars: Cardio Dance (2006) DVD&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-tv-show&#34;&gt;The TV show&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The DVD came out, of course, as a result of the popularity of the TV series &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dancing_with_the_Stars_%28U.S._TV_series%29&#34;&gt;Dancing with the Stars&lt;/a&gt;. I had watched several episodes in 2006, out of curiosity, since in 2000-2002 I had been pretty serious about &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/18/disagreement-on-the-use-of-time/&#34;&gt;doing competitive ballroom dancing&lt;/a&gt;, so I wanted to see just how good the celebrities could get, with training. I was actually impressed by how good some of them got, although there were many who were not very good at all and really had no business trying to perform complicated routines rather than mastering basic technique (my instructors were always adamant about our not trying to do what we weren&amp;rsquo;t yet ready for, lest we develop poor habits difficult to unlearn).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-content-of-the-workout&#34;&gt;The content of the workout&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-dancers&#34;&gt;The dancers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One reason I enjoy the workout is that the dancers on video are actually decent. The pro instructors on the video, Kym, Maksim, Ashly, are good, and the other dancers hold up too. I find it important to see good technique at work, because we learn by imitation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, I like that there are a number of different male and female dancers, with different ethnicities and body types. All are in great shape, of course. For me, it was important to see not only Maksim, but two other male dancers. I enjoy exercise videos more when I see men doing stuff, and have role models to emulate. Also, to be frank, the women are always more flexible, and I feel odd whenever I can&amp;rsquo;t quite do something that I see on a video. So I feel comforted seeing men who are more limited and remind me that I&amp;rsquo;m doing OK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a guy on this video who looks kind of Asian. I always like to see someone whose body type seems close to mine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-moves&#34;&gt;The moves&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The moves are basic and real ballroom dance moves put together to form routines. There are very few gimmicky, tricky moves. Things get repetitious, so I can&amp;rsquo;t use this video more than maybe twice a week, but that&amp;rsquo;s fine. I happen to enjoy continuing to refine my technique on the same steps again and again. And I feel that over the years as I&amp;rsquo;ve used this video, I have indeed improved considerably in my technique, speed, stamina, and expressiveness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, I quite like the paso doble workout, because it is all about showing off in macho fashion, by using the arms, twisting, pretending to wield a cape, standing tall. It&amp;rsquo;s a very masculine dance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second dance, the cha cha, is repetitious, and unfortunately is danced on 1 rather than on 2 (obviously for the sake of not confusing beginners), but is a nice workout for the core, if one pays attention to technique and doing crisp cha-cha-cha and proper Latin hip motion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third dance, the samba, is a lot of fun and faster and more strenuous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final dance, the jive, definitely generates a lot of sweat. It&amp;rsquo;s almost like running. My calves get a real workout from the jive. Amusingly, you can see how the non-pros get more and more tired and struggle. I did initially also, but eventually I became more efficient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In each of these dances, the instructors are very enthusiastic, and the other dancers seem to be enjoying themselves also. I really like that vibe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-warmup-and-cooldown&#34;&gt;The warmup and cooldown&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The warmup and cooldown framing the workout are very brief, as typical of these videos, unfortunately. I simply warm up by myself before even popping in the DVD, and I skip the video&amp;rsquo;s cooldown in favor of my own stretching, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;caveats&#34;&gt;Caveats&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, there is a reason ratings for the DVD on Amazon are all over the map. Dance exercise videos can never please everyone, because of differences in people&amp;rsquo;s levels of fitness and technique.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For someone like me, who has had a bit of serious ballroom dance training and is looking for a reasonable workout based on Latin dance, the video is perfect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would &lt;em&gt;not at all&lt;/em&gt; recommend this video for a total newcomer to ballroom dance. There is no instruction on technique. Without proper technique, it&amp;rsquo;s not really possible to get through the workout efficiently and enjoyably. You could get injured, in fact. The samba and jive, in particular, could result in a lot of pounding on joints, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I enjoy this dance workout video very much, but I hesitate to recommend it to anyone other than people who have already at least received rudimentary instruction on each of the dances covered: paso doble, cha cha, samba, jive.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>