<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Saxophone on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/saxophone/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Saxophone on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/saxophone/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>How Ornette Coleman changed my life</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/06/12/how-ornette-coleman-changed-my-life/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jun 2015 23:59:40 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/06/12/how-ornette-coleman-changed-my-life/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The legendary jazz musician
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ornette_Coleman&#34;&gt;Ornette Coleman&lt;/a&gt;
recently died at age 85. He had not been on my radar for a long
time. In fact, I never actually listened to much of his music at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, my immediate first thought on hearing this news was, &lt;strong&gt;Ornette
Coleman permanently changed the course of my life&lt;/strong&gt;. How can this be?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;first-reactions-to-ornette-coleman-s-music&#34;&gt;First reactions to Ornette Coleman&amp;rsquo;s music&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2000, during a huge transition in my life that turned everything
upside down, I began experimenting with listening to a lot of kinds of
music I had never experienced before. I was exploring Cuban,
Brazilian, Argentinian music. I was exploring Western classical music
of the 20th century (I had a fairly narrow taste up till then focused
primarily on the Classical 18th century and Romantic 19th century,
with little before or after this range). In jazz, I was expanding
beyond the swing, bebop, hard bop eras of jazz. I frequently reached
areas that made me confused or disgusted. For example, in jazz I got
&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/23/celebrating-the-birthday-of-john-coltrane/&#34;&gt;as far as I could with John Coltrane&lt;/a&gt;
as Coltrane ventured into &amp;ldquo;free jazz&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided to try out Ornette Coleman for another approach to &amp;ldquo;free
jazz&amp;rdquo;, and checked out the album
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Shape_of_Jazz_to_Come&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Shape of Jazz to Come&amp;rdquo; (1959)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;lonely-woman&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Lonely Woman&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Immediately, I was struck by the track
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lonely_Woman_%28composition%29&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Lonely Woman&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. Conventional
concerns such as being strictly &amp;ldquo;in tune&amp;rdquo; were out the window, in
favor of extremely flexibility of pitch and raw, wailing emotional
expression. It showcased Coleman&amp;rsquo;s lyrical side and was easy to
love. OK, not too weird.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/DNbD1JIH344&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;other-tracks&#34;&gt;Other tracks&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But bam, that was just a warmup. For example, check out
&amp;ldquo;Eventually&amp;rdquo;. It&amp;rsquo;s very free indeed, a lot of notes, an expression of
hyperactive motion, conventional tonality unimportant. Still, not too
harsh, and not totally random.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/WoC69lxnS_Y&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, what I really understood from his music was that he was doing
what came naturally to him. It did not feel forced, it was not to
prove a point. He was enjoying what he was doing. This sense of
&lt;em&gt;freedom&lt;/em&gt; really impressed me. It wasn&amp;rsquo;t reaction, it wasn&amp;rsquo;t
rebellion. I respected that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;free-jazz-a-collective-improvisation&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Free Jazz: A Collective Improvisation&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next album I checked out was
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Free_Jazz:_A_Collective_Improvisation&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Free Jazz: A Collective Improvisation&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was a step beyond, and confusing to me because of the
simultaneous playing that often seemed chaotic. I confess to taking no
huge pleasure in attempting to listen to it all at once (note that
apart from lack of conventional structure, it also keeps going on and
on at length). I found it more enjoyable to listen to only a couple of
random minutes, trying to absorb some stretch of order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, although this was not really my thing, it opened up my mind
to &amp;ldquo;why not?&amp;rdquo; Maybe this particular experiment didn&amp;rsquo;t work, but I
could imagine a simpler setting, say, with fewer instruments, in which
collective improvisation could work out better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check it out yourself:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/xbZIiom9rDA&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;something-else&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Something Else!!!!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I checked out
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Something_Else!!!!&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Something Else!!!!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;,
which actually was his first album and closer to bebop and so forth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t have much to say about it, but it&amp;rsquo;s not too confusing to
enjoy, because of still audible ties to some traditional forms and
styles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;freedom&#34;&gt;Freedom&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, I didn&amp;rsquo;t continue exploring Coleman&amp;rsquo;s music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the sense of &lt;em&gt;freedom&lt;/em&gt;, of &lt;em&gt;permission&lt;/em&gt; to ignore boundaries and
go wherever, musically, really affected me. Was what he was doing
&amp;ldquo;jazz&amp;rdquo;? Listening to him, I made up my mind that I was never again
going to get involved in debates about what jazz &amp;ldquo;really is&amp;rdquo; or what
classical music &amp;ldquo;really is&amp;rdquo; or even what music &amp;ldquo;really is&amp;rdquo;. These
labels stopped being meaningful to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That was what I really learned from him and his life. By coincidence,
I just read this Rolling Stone article,
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rollingstone.com/music/news/vernon-reid-on-ornette-coleman-he-set-a-lot-of-people-free-20150612&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Vernon Reid on Ornette Coleman: &amp;lsquo;He set a lot of people free&amp;rsquo;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;,
that echoes exactly what I felt I learned fifteen years ago from my
brief exposure to him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past year or so, there have been times when, alone and not
likely to bother anyone, I pull out my bass recorder (ha, my lowest
instrument) and just go wild, play some melodic shapes, make up
rhythms, go multiphonic, whatever, for the sheer joy of it. And I&amp;rsquo;m
not embarrassed, because I remember Ornette Coleman and he gave us all
permission to express our unconscious in whatever honest way it comes
out. And he gave us permission to accept and encourage each other to
do that, whether or not we personally like or understand everything
that comes out of tapping the unconscious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hadn&amp;rsquo;t expected to think so much upon hearing of Ornette Coleman&amp;rsquo;s
death. But he set an example that I respected deeply, forever changing
not only my perceptions of music but of what musicians can and should
be allowed to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Are you an Ornette Coleman fan or detractor? Did he change your
  life? If so, how exactly?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Singing and playing tango and jazz at an unexpected music party</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/04/12/singing-and-playing-tango-and-jazz-at-an-unexpected-music-party/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Apr 2013 23:20:59 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/04/12/singing-and-playing-tango-and-jazz-at-an-unexpected-music-party/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/bob-party-2013-04-12/henry-franklin.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Henry and Franklin performing El Choclo&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I suddenly got email from Henry on a Friday afternoon while I was at work. He invited me to join him at some guy&amp;rsquo;s party in the evening to play some tangos, since the party was going to have an &amp;ldquo;Argentina&amp;rdquo; theme. My first thought was that Abby was not going to be able to go, and I myself had made plans to rest up before my very important training run Saturday morning for the Pittsburgh Marathon, but the opportunity to meet some new musicians and other people, and express my love for passionate tango music, made me decide, after consulting with Abby, to attend the party.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The good news was that I had done some tango music earlier, so there was some reuse possible. Last year, I had finally worked up the courage to do some singing, and rather enjoyed singing classic traditional tango in particular, such as &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/11/17/a-childhood-dream-come-true-i-am-now-finally-singing-for-real/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Por una Cabeza&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. And this year, I had finally given a shot at playing &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/26/music-i-just-played-for-the-first-time-recorder-sonata-tangos/&#34;&gt;tango on flute&lt;/a&gt;, playing both &amp;ldquo;El Choclo&amp;rdquo; as well as &amp;ldquo;Por una Cabeza&amp;rdquo; (as a flute-violin duet).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bad news was that someone else was already going to play &amp;ldquo;Por una Cabeza&amp;rdquo; on violin, so that left me with only one other tango I had played with Henry before, &lt;a href=&#34;http://joanveronica.hubpages.com/hub/The-Tango-La-Cumparsita-El-Choclo-and-Mi-Buenos-Aires-Querido&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;El Choclo&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, whose contrasts of staccato/legato and minor/major, with a lot of room for rubato and ornamental bravado quite appeal to me.. I wanted a tango to sing, and by sheer coincidence, I knew exactly which tango I always wanted to sing, but had only half-sung it to myself in private: this was &lt;a href=&#34;http://joanveronica.hubpages.com/hub/Outstanding-Tango-selection-Mi-Buenos-Aires-Querido-Uno-and-Caminito&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Uno&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, by &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mariano_Mores&#34;&gt;Mariano Mores&lt;/a&gt; from 1943.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;uno&#34;&gt;Uno&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By coincidence, only a couple of days ago, the Spanish actress/singer &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sara_Montiel&#34;&gt;Sara Montiel&lt;/a&gt; died, and in her memory I rewatched and &lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/100967806642012078047/posts/6xV5iasmXxj&#34;&gt;reposted&lt;/a&gt; a video clip of her singing &amp;ldquo;Uno&amp;rdquo; in a film:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/5Z7rHztinaM&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe that I first came across &amp;ldquo;Uno&amp;rdquo; by accident when some years ago I found Montiel&amp;rsquo;s performance while searching for other tangos. In any case, it was love at first hearing, and made it to my list of tangos I wanted to sing some day. I&amp;rsquo;d put off this project for some good reasons, but today I decided I wanted to give it a shot!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I hastily found a score, printed out the lyrics, and after eating dinner at home after work, and just an hour or so before the party, I worked on being able to sing the Spanish lyrics without completely stumbling over myself. Most songs in Spanish I can sing with no problem, but &amp;ldquo;Uno&amp;rdquo; features a huge number of words in the lyrics, which means there are considerable challenges:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;pronouncing Spanish at basically spoken speed (I&amp;rsquo;m not that fluent yet)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;breaking up the words into logical and emotional groupings at speed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;singing Spanish in the face of many, many instances of word pairs with vowels in between&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I knew I wasn&amp;rsquo;t going to get everything perfect in time in less than half an hour of determining where to break things up and where to link things, and actually doing this fluently, so I was nervous, but I&amp;rsquo;ve learned that when it comes to music, perfect technique is not the most important thing; I felt I could reasonably well convey the emotional content of this song despite imperfections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-party&#34;&gt;The party&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a great party, with food, music, and conversation, and I was excited to meet a whole bunch of new people of all ages. I hope the next time Bob and his wife host another music party, Abby will be able to attend too!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before the musical part of the party began, Henry and I spent about five minutes in the basement, with him on the upright piano down there, and me singing, trying to read through &amp;ldquo;Uno&amp;rdquo; together so that it would be at least halfway presentable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We performed &amp;ldquo;El Choclo&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Uno&amp;rdquo; near the end of the program (since we were last minute additions that didn&amp;rsquo;t make it onto the printed program). I was physically shaking while doing both of them, because I was in front of a completely new crowd of people and just wasn&amp;rsquo;t as prepared as I would have preferred. But it was a friendly crowd, and the audience seemed to enjoy our music-making. I was happy to have contributed something to the &amp;ldquo;Argentina&amp;rdquo; theme with some authentic Golden Age tango music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What was really enjoyable about this music party was that so many of the guests participated in performing something: young and old, amateur and professional. This welcoming atmosphere was wonderful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;jazz-improvisation&#34;&gt;Jazz, improvisation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the official music program ended, some people continued to jam. This guy I met, Keith, was particularly interesting to me, as he is a wind player, and played both soprano saxophone and flute on the program, and then after the program, was doing jazz standards on alto saxophone. I was so inspired by this that I decided I wanted to do some jazz also. I bring a little binder of music nowadays when I go to musical parties, just in case, and happened to have on me &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jazzstandards.com/compositions-0/sweetlorraine.htm&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Sweet Lorraine&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, which I had never played before other than to myself with a CD track. So I got Henry to the piano so that we could just go for it and improvise to the chord changes. We totally got into it and I really enjoyed the jamming. I really enjoy nothing more than improvisation, and appreciate that Henry is game for doing this with me, as when we were doing it with Latin jazz (bolero and cha cha) &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/17/finally-doing-some-latin-music-jamming-on-flute/&#34;&gt;last month&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had tremendous fun attending Bob&amp;rsquo;s party, seeing so many people sing or play an instrument, all of us sharing our love of music together. I was very inspired by everyone who contributed something of their unique soul there, and I feel like this is what life is all about.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Attending the annual Pitt Jazz Seminar for the first time: day 1</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/11/02/attending-the-annual-pitt-jazz-seminar-for-the-first-time-day-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Nov 2012 23:53:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/11/02/attending-the-annual-pitt-jazz-seminar-for-the-first-time-day-1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.music.pitt.edu/sites/default/files/jazz-2012-cropped.jpg?1350921512&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;42nd Pitt Jazz Seminar poster&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This year I decided to attend events of the 42nd annual &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.music.pitt.edu/events/november-3-2012-42nd-annual-jazz-se120813&#34;&gt;Pitt Jazz Seminar&lt;/a&gt; for the first time. I&amp;rsquo;ve never had any instruction in jazz, and frankly have only a little bit of experience trying to play it myself, so I enjoyed the opportunity to attend presentations by great performers who could talk about what they do, where they&amp;rsquo;ve come from, and demonstrate their craft.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went in to Pitt campus on a Friday morning to learn from some master musicians.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;yotam-silbertein-http-yotammusic-com-guitar&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://yotammusic.com/&#34;&gt;Yotam Silbertein&lt;/a&gt;, guitar&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought it was interesting that an Israeli musician, Yotam Silbertein, kicked off the morning of seminars. Of course, as he emphasized in his talk, jazz is an international phenomenon. It happens in Israel, it happens in Japan, it happens in Europe. It may have started off in the United States, but it is everywhere now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, he did eventually have to head to New York, the place to be. He even speaks English with a New York style accent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He emphasized that it&amp;rsquo;s necessary to go where the action is and learn from the best.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;javon-jackson-http-www-javonjackson-com-tenor-saxophone&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.javonjackson.com/&#34;&gt;Javon Jackson&lt;/a&gt;, tenor saxophone&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Javon Jackson spoke a lot about being a professional in music: how you behave, how you work with others, and develop a career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, he pointed out that he wears a suit because it projects a professional image.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;that-s-it-for-the-day&#34;&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s it for the day&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was another session later in the afternoon, but I skipped it because I needed to return to work.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Latin jazz in Pittsburgh: Puro Queso</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/08/26/latin-jazz-in-pittsburgh-puro-queso/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Aug 2012 22:31:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/08/26/latin-jazz-in-pittsburgh-puro-queso/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One great thing about Pittsburgh is the free cultural programs at the Carnegie Library. Abby and I checked out a local Latin jazz quartet, &lt;a href=&#34;http://puroquesojazz.com/&#34;&gt;Puro Queso&lt;/a&gt;, performing at the main branch of the library in Oakland, as part of their regular &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.carnegielibrary.org/events/details.cfm?event_id=69113&#34;&gt;Sunday afternoon World Kaleidoscope series&lt;/a&gt;. This event was also posted on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/pittsburgh-free/events/77709582/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Free and Almost Free in Pittsburgh&amp;rdquo; meetup group&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was amused to notice that when we arrived, I recognized the saxophonist! It was someone I had seen around a lot on campus at work at CMU. I figured he must be staff or faculty. (I looked him up and sure enough, he is &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.history.cmu.edu/faculty/eiss.html&#34;&gt;Paul Eiss, professor in the history department&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/puro-queso/soprano-sax.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Paul Eiss on soprano sax&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/puro-queso/tenor-sax.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Paul Eiss on tenor sax&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As usual at these library events, where time is limited and the purpose is to spark interest not only in the music but also to encourage concert attendance and CD purchases, the mustical selections tended toward well-known classic crowd pleasers, rather than more adventurous material or wilder improvisation. In any case, it was fun, and Abby and I danced a little too. Some of the selections I recognized:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;bossa nova: Song of the Jet (&lt;a href=&#34;http://letras.mus.br/tom-jobim/49065/&#34;&gt;Samba do Avião&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;bossa nova: &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mas_que_Nada&#34;&gt;Mas Que Nada&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;bolero: &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/B%C3%A9same_Mucho&#34;&gt;Besame mucho&lt;/a&gt;, featuring a female vocalist&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a Cuban &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Son_%28music%29&#34;&gt;son&lt;/a&gt; whose name I have forgotten&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>