<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Schenley Park on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/schenley-park/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Schenley Park on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/schenley-park/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Was it worth sprinting to a terrible fall to finish 25th in the CMU Pretty Good Race 5K?</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/09/06/was-it-worth-sprinting-to-a-terrible-fall-to-finish-25th-in-the-cmu-pretty-good-race-5k/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Sep 2013 22:01:27 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/09/06/was-it-worth-sprinting-to-a-terrible-fall-to-finish-25th-in-the-cmu-pretty-good-race-5k/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On a pleasant Friday late afternoon, not too hot or humid, I ran my 9th CMU Pretty Good Race 5K (and this was Abby&amp;rsquo;s 3rd).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two weeks ago, I did the Run Around The Square 5K in my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/08/24/reflections-on-my-slowest-run-around-the-square-5k-in-13-years/&#34;&gt;slowest time in 13 years&lt;/a&gt;. I was happy to be finishing a 5K race at all. I&amp;rsquo;ve improved some in fitness in the past two weeks, but not enough to make a big difference for today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like last year, I was going into this race not optimally fit. However, given that I just ran a 5K two weeks ago, I had a good idea of what I could do in another 5K, how hard I could push myself. Like I said last year, &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;It&amp;rsquo;s not about how fast I went, but how much I gave of what I had&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I never expected just how much I would give this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;before-the-race&#34;&gt;Before the race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I walked over from my office across Flagstaff Hill to Schenley Park.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pretty-good-race-2013/flagstaff-hill.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Flagstaff Hill&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For some reason, Abby decided to use our dinky Razor kick scooter to come in from home for the race. Unfortunately, she showed up before the race with a bloody hand and knee, having had a nasty fall while using the scooter on the way to Schenley Park. Oops. She&amp;rsquo;s been tired a lot lately (I previously mentioned her dangerous &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/08/24/reflections-on-my-slowest-run-around-the-square-5k-in-13-years/&#34;&gt;decline in fitness all year&lt;/a&gt;) and was regretting signing up to do the Pretty Good Race with me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She tried to be a good sport despite the accident coming in.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pretty-good-race-2013/abby-before.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby before race&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here I am in orange:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pretty-good-race-2013/franklin-before.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin before race&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;weather-conditions&#34;&gt;Weather conditions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Temperature and humidity were much, much better than last year. That promised a considerable time advantage relative to last year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-plan&#34;&gt;The plan&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As with last year, my plan was to make the most of the final downhill part of the course, as well as go for a sprint to pass as many people as I possibly could during the final brief but terrible uphill to the finish line. I was going to have to pace myself intelligently to have something left for the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-race&#34;&gt;The race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I paced myself, not going too fast in the first half of the race. I almost entirely ran my own slow race, as there was nobody else really near my steady pace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After turning around, I starting going hard downhill. I was worried that I didn&amp;rsquo;t see Abby at all during the race. At some point, I passed her walking back to the start. She must have dropped out very early on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was pushing really hard in the final part of the race. Near the uphill finish, I saw a guy slowing down, and he raised his arms as though celebrating finishing. This gesture instantly caused me to go into a sprint more furious than any other sprint finish in my entire life. I made up a huge distance and reached the finish chute just a step before he did. And as I did so, the dry gravel and my leaning too far forward caused me to slip and fall, really, really badly. But I had finished ahead of the guy. Mission accomplished.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;injuries&#34;&gt;Injuries&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I lay stunned and in terrible pain for a few seconds. I had to check whether I was seriously broken. It felt like I was not. I was rather injured, but miraculously, no broken bones. I had managed to break my fall not with my teeth or eyes or fingers, but with my left thigh, right knee, left forearm, left palm, and right palm. I was quite badly scraped and bruised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I heard people asking me, &amp;ldquo;Was it worth it?&amp;rdquo; I didn&amp;rsquo;t know how to answer that. I moved on, stumbling in pain as I tried to catch my breath. I had done what I do, give the race my all, and then some. I was gouged and bleeding, and my right knee had swollen up hugely almost instantly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This wasn&amp;rsquo;t the worst falling injury I&amp;rsquo;ve had in my life, but it&amp;rsquo;s probably my worst since a fall off a bike (also spinning off loose gravel) twenty years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pretty-good-race-2013/left-palm.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Left palm&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pretty-good-race-2013/left-thigh.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Left thigh&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pretty-good-race-2013/right-knee.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Right knee&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pretty-good-race-2013/left-arm.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Left arm&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby returned, and had to explain to the volunteers that she wasn&amp;rsquo;t just finishing, but had dropped out earlier. While I was trying to clean myself up some, she said that she had fallen early on during the race and decided that that was enough and she wasn&amp;rsquo;t going to finish the race. So this is her first Did Not Finish (DNF) in a race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;feeling-lucky&#34;&gt;Feeling lucky&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main thing I kept on feeling while we walked back to my office and then back to my car (very slowly; everything around my right knee was just messed up) and went home for both of us to clean up from our injuries: &lt;em&gt;luck&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It could have been much worse for both of us. My most severe damage was not even to my right knee area (even though walking was difficult) but really my left hand, whose heel of palm was basically scraped away and bruised and my wrist was messed up. But no broken fingers or teeth or wrists or ankles. Same with Abby: lucky us!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;was-it-worth-it&#34;&gt;Was it worth it?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I finished officially tied for 25th place with the guy I actually beat, both of us registering as finishing in 25:28 in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~kalp/PGR/2013.html&#34;&gt;official race results&lt;/a&gt;. Well, I ran 37 seconds faster than last year. That&amp;rsquo;s not nothing, although two years ago I ran 24:36.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I knew the time was not going to be great: I just ran 25:36 in Run Around The Square two weeks ago. The real point was that like last year, I gave it my all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But was it worth getting injured for sprinting for no glory whatsoever? It&amp;rsquo;s not like I was running for first place or something &amp;ldquo;important&amp;rdquo;. Or is that the wrong way to think about it? Why is it worth trying your best for first place but not for 25th place instead of 26th place? Let&amp;rsquo;s ignore the (unfortunate?) fact that in some circles, first place is associated with large monetary rewards, when pondering that question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A different question would be, &amp;ldquo;If you knew you would get this injured from this sprint, would you have done it anyway?&amp;rdquo; I guess the question is &amp;ldquo;no&amp;rdquo;. But how could I &lt;em&gt;know&lt;/em&gt;? There is always risk. There is risk crossing the street, or driving on the turnpike. I&amp;rsquo;ve never fallen during a sprint before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another different question: &amp;ldquo;How will this accident change how you run in the future?&amp;rdquo; I suppose my answer is, I&amp;rsquo;ll be more careful to keep my balance. But am I going to stop the sprinting at the end of a race? I don&amp;rsquo;t see how I can. &lt;em&gt;It is in those moments when I can barely breathe and the world is becoming a blur that I am living with most intensity and purity.&lt;/em&gt; These moments don&amp;rsquo;t come often, but when they are available for the taking, why would I not accept these gifts?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will keep sprinting. I will keep trying to beat whoever is beatable in front of me. That&amp;rsquo;s part of the whole point of racing. I admit to feeling a little odd to being so serious about it when others do it much more casually (and it&amp;rsquo;s their right to do so and they&amp;rsquo;re probably smarter and more balanced than me, I concede). But I don&amp;rsquo;t race often, so when I do, I try to make it matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So my response is: I will need to work on maintaining balance and running on tricky surfaces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, Abby and I decided we should make sure to have a first aid kit around in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-next-race&#34;&gt;The next race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My eleventh Great Race 10K is coming up. I want to do considerably better than I did last year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, I have a lot of healing to do. I am more of a wreck right now than the post-race photos indicate. Things are all swollen and messed up and probably will be for an entire week or two. It&amp;rsquo;s just amazing I haven&amp;rsquo;t broken bones or ligaments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I simultaneously had unfortunate falling accidents today. I was proud to have run as hard as I could given my fitness and will. I don&amp;rsquo;t regret sprinting for 25th place, even if it cost me this time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, we both need to heal.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On overtraining and feeling injured two weeks before the Pittsburgh Marathon</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/04/20/on-overtraining-and-feeling-injured-two-weeks-before-the-pittsburgh-marathon/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Apr 2013 22:25:40 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/04/20/on-overtraining-and-feeling-injured-two-weeks-before-the-pittsburgh-marathon/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/04/13/my-final-16-mile-long-run-before-pittsburgh-marathon-featured-two-radical-experiments/&#34;&gt;Last week&amp;rsquo;s 16-mile run with the Steel City Road Runners&lt;/a&gt; was my longest run during the past two months of training for the Pittsburgh Marathon. I knew that it was about time to start &lt;a href=&#34;http://running.competitor.com/2012/08/training/the-art-of-the-marathon-taper_57754&#34;&gt;tapering&lt;/a&gt;, but I felt that because of my relatively low mileage (mostly under 30 miles a week), I should put in one last hard week of training, and then have two weeks of tapering before the marathon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, this week I overdid things and &lt;a href=&#34;http://steelcityrrc.org/scrrcevents?eventId=619965&#34;&gt;today&amp;rsquo;s 11-mile run&lt;/a&gt; was very revealing. I ended that run with a whole slew of real problems that I need to immediately fix, or else I will not be able to even make it to the start line of the marathon in two weeks!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;this-week-s-workouts&#34;&gt;This week&amp;rsquo;s workouts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;monday&#34;&gt;Monday&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/04/19/commuting-on-foot-during-cmu-carnival-week-as-cross-training-for-the-pittsburgh-marathon/&#34;&gt;walking 2 miles to work&lt;/a&gt;, I did a tough &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/02/03/my-favorite-running-workout/&#34;&gt;high-intensity Billat workout&lt;/a&gt; on the CMU track, thinking that having taken Sunday off from running, I was ready to get back into action. After doing about 12 minutes of this workout (after warming up first, of course), I was beat. I was feeling pressure on my knees and shins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically, I was not sufficiently recovered from my 16-miler on Saturday, and I made a mistake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, I walked 2 miles back home from work, with sore legs and feet, and still wearing Luna Sandals all day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;tuesday&#34;&gt;Tuesday&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did an easy 6-mile run, which included 1 mile of running to work, 4 miles of running in Schenley Park on the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/07/running-my-8th-pretty-good-race-5k-dealing-with-disappointment/&#34;&gt;Pretty Good Race course&lt;/a&gt;, and 1 mile on the CMU track. Despite taking this run slowly, I felt rather sore afterwards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;wednesday&#34;&gt;Wednesday&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided to take a day completely off from running, and off from Luna Sandals, to give my legs and feet a rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;thursday&#34;&gt;Thursday&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ran 5 miles in Frick Park.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;friday&#34;&gt;Friday&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did the annual &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/04/19/going-out-too-fast-yet-again-in-my-third-random-distance-run/&#34;&gt;Random Distance Run&lt;/a&gt;. By this time, I was quite looking forward to getting Saturday&amp;rsquo;s run over with and then resting on Sunday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;11-mile-run&#34;&gt;11-mile run&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided to make the Saturday run a kind of dress rehearsal for the marathon. I would wake up at approximately the same time, and dress and eat as though running the marathon, and run at marathon pace, and the only difference would be that I would do 11 miles, not 26.2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I ate some salted, boiled potatoes for breakfast, and took a gel pack to eat right before the run, and planned to take a gel during the run also.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was really cold yet again (temperature below 40F, and I saw some stray snowflakes), even colder than last week, so I substituted a short-sleeve T-shirt and shell and long pants in place of the long-sleeve T-shirt and shorts I wore last Saturday. I still had the glove liners and hat, of course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wore, for the first time, my &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cepcompression.com/1922-Allsports-Sleeves.aspx&#34;&gt;calf sleeves&lt;/a&gt; that had just arrived, and that I plan to wear during the marathon:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/scrr-2013-04-20/cep-compression-calf-sleeves.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;CEP Compression calf sleeves&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;moment-of-silence-for-boston&#34;&gt;Moment of silence for Boston&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The whole week has been very weird for me because the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/04/15/boston-marathon-tragedy-please-avoid-the-news-porn/&#34;&gt;Boston Marathon bombing on Monday has been on my mind&lt;/a&gt;; I did what I could to avoid media coverage of the hunt for the bombers. It turned out that just last night, they caught the remaining official suspect, so that brought a little closure to the whole thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The training run was preceded by a moment of silence for Boston as well as updates on changes to the Pittsburgh Marathon setup for increased security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this run, I wore blue as well as a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.races2remember.com/PrintBib.php?bib=BOSTON2013&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;We are all Boston Marathoners at heart&amp;rdquo; bib&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/scrr-2013-04-20/boston-marathoners-at-heart.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;We are all Boston Marathoners at heart&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-run&#34;&gt;The run&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/scrr-2013-04-20/start.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Waiting to start run&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I intended to try to follow a 9-minute pace group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that the group went out pretty fast. I could not tell whether it felt fast because it really &lt;em&gt;was&lt;/em&gt; faster than 9-minute pace, or because I was so fatigued from my week of training.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point, I did speed up (as I usually seem to do in my runs, starting out slowly before I&amp;rsquo;m all warmed up and ready to go faster). Then the problem was that I didn&amp;rsquo;t know what the route was exactly, once I started passing people! Yes, I got the printed map right before the run, but that&amp;rsquo;s never a great time for me to study and memorize the map, and I hate pulling out the map while running.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;getting-lost&#34;&gt;Getting &amp;ldquo;lost&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At one point when we reached downtown again in Pittsburgh, and we were supposed to eventually cross over north, I asked some runners around me what the route was, and unfortunately, one guy made some assumption and we followed him. Later I learned he made the wrong assumption. In fact, since I ran past him and was following some other people ahead of me, I got myself into more trouble. At one point, I saw someone behind me go right, while the guy ahead of me by a block kept going straight. I immediately smelled that the guy was &lt;em&gt;not part of our group&lt;/em&gt; (lots of people were out running, I could tell), and sure enough, I looked back and everyone was taking a shortcut through someone&amp;rsquo;s back yard to get back to Liberty Avenue and cross the 16th Street Bridge, and so I backtracked and followed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By that time, I was tired and demoralized by all the weird twists and turns the route had become after having reached downtown earlier, and now that I knew where I was, I just slowed down and didn&amp;rsquo;t bother to catch up to any pack again, and took some photos:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/scrr-2013-04-20/bridge.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;View from Sixteenth Street Bridge&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/scrr-2013-04-20/16th-street-bridge.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Crossing Sixteenth Street Bridge&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t really know how far I ran or how fast. It just seemed really intense to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;after-the-run&#34;&gt;After the run&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/scrr-2013-04-20/after.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;After run&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;After the run, I ate two bananas and some cookies and went inside to stretch and inspect the damage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;feet&#34;&gt;Feet&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My Luna Sandals:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/scrr-2013-04-20/luna-venado.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Luna Venado&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h4 id=&#34;tops-of-feet&#34;&gt;Tops of feet&lt;/h4&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/scrr-2013-04-20/feet.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Feet&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My right foot felt OK, despite some indentations from tight laces:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/scrr-2013-04-20/right.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Right foot&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But my left foot took a lot of damage, with skin scraped and some blood; the problem was that the strap had been loose, but I had neglected to stop and tighten and readjust it, and as a result, it shifted around and therefore chafed me:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/scrr-2013-04-20/left.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Left foot&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It was good to learn this lesson once and for all: I will be more careful in the future to make sure the laces are tight enough, and also not ignore sensations of chafing, and take the time to stop and readjust if I really have to. I could not have run a full marathon with my left foot being chafed in this fashion for the whole distance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;soles-of-feet&#34;&gt;Soles of feet&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My soles revealed some developing problems from the entire week.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/scrr-2013-04-20/soles.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Soles of feet&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My left sole was basically OK, despite some dry skin that I should really deal with, but my right sole had more serious dry and cracking skin problems. In particular, near my big toe, there was a noticeable crack that caused me discomfort with every step:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/scrr-2013-04-20/right-sole.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Right sole of foot&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;calves&#34;&gt;Calves&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe the calf sleeves did help me, even in just an 11-miler. They were not obtrusive at all as I wore them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;knee&#34;&gt;Knee&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later in the afternoon at home, I noticed that I had developed a debilitating left knee problem. I have no idea what exactly caused it, but the general overtraining had clearly caught up to me. When I put weight on my left leg at certain angles, the pain is excruciating. This particular happens when I go down the stairs. On the other hand, I can control whether I feel pain, by stepping very carefully. Something is loose and out of alignment, clearly. This has happened to me before, so I&amp;rsquo;m not as worried as I could be, but just two weeks away from the marathon, it is not good news.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;recovery-plans&#34;&gt;Recovery plans?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My left knee is my highest priority right now. I am immediately taking a break from running. I will take tomorrow off, and possibly Monday as well. I will do whatever it takes to get the knee all good again, because there is no way I would even go to the start line of the marathon with the knee being as it is today!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really need to fix my feet, and especially the right one. I really dried out my feet by wearing the Luna Sandals exclusively for running (and almost exclusively for walking) in the past week. So I&amp;rsquo;m putting lotion on my feet and deciding to wear socks and cushioned shoes for a while. There&amp;rsquo;s more I&amp;rsquo;m going to have to do for my feet also. I&amp;rsquo;ve never in my life had this dry skin problem before on my feet, because in the past when it&amp;rsquo;s been cold and dry, I&amp;rsquo;ve always worn socks and closed toe shoes, whether of the usual monotoed variety or Vibram FiveFingers. I&amp;rsquo;ve never had my feet so exposed before. Especially, running in temperatures of the 30s with huaraches seemed to cause some of my problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, the next two weeks really are supposed to be tapering for me. I will be running easy and short and slow for the most part, just to maintain some fitness, but do not plan on doing any super hard workouts any more. We all know that the body takes about two weeks to adapt to any training, and so no hard training I do now will have an effect on my performance in the marathon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I yet again pushed myself to the edge and overtrained, and have some real knee and feet problems to solve as quickly as possible. I am so ready to dial down the training and get the marathon over with. I don&amp;rsquo;t want to sound pessimistic or depressed, but that&amp;rsquo;s the reality of how I&amp;rsquo;m feeling at this moment. I hope that within the next couple of days, I&amp;rsquo;ll have recovered from this low point.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My first interval workout before the Pittsburgh Marathon</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/04/09/my-first-interval-workout-before-the-pittsburgh-marathon/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Apr 2013 20:41:57 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/04/09/my-first-interval-workout-before-the-pittsburgh-marathon/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s less than one month less before the Pittsburgh Marathon, yet I have done no interval training for it until today. In ordinary circumstances, I would have been doing weekly interval training for some time now, but I had a late start with training in the winter, and so I simply have not felt ready for hard interval training until this week! Up till now, I have simply been scrambling to increase mileage and survive the long runs without injury and burnout, and this has been challenging enough: last week, I was fortunate to &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/04/06/comeback-from-pittsburgh-marathon-overtraining/&#34;&gt;bounce back from clear overtraining&lt;/a&gt;. But now I&amp;rsquo;m actually starting to feel strong, so it&amp;rsquo;s time to sharpen up with interval training.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-interval-training&#34;&gt;Why interval training?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Interval_training&#34;&gt;Interval training&lt;/a&gt; is well-known from research to be extremely beneficial for improving performance at distance running. It builds the body as well as the mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-workout&#34;&gt;My workout&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A decade ago, I used to do interval training on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://athletics.cmu.edu/facilities/gesling&#34;&gt;CMU track of Gesling Stadium&lt;/a&gt;, but I never really liked running around a synthetic track. There are other options, of course. I have good memories of running around the 1K dirt track (not the synthetic 400m track) at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pittsburghparks.org/schenley-sports&#34;&gt;oval in Schenley Park&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But nowadays, I find that the most convenient place for interval training is a trail loop near home in Frick Park that just happens to be very close to 800m in length. The drawback, of course, is that the length of this loop means I can only do intervals of multiples of 800m. Unfortunately, I prefer doing 1200m long intervals, while I find 1600m to be on the brutal side for an interval workout. But 800m will do for my first interval workout of the year!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ended up doing 6x800. Oh, and it turned out to be a heat training workout too, because it suddenly got very warm, like summer already. I really hope that it cools down quickly and stays cool for the Pittsburgh Marathon! I don&amp;rsquo;t want summer conditions to come until &lt;em&gt;after&lt;/em&gt; the marathon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After 15 minutes of easy running, I launched into the intervals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Purely by subjective feel, I ended up running these intervals in an average of about 3:37 each, with 1:50 timed recovery:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3:38, 1:54&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3:40, 1:51&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3:37, 1:47&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3:34, 1:50&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3:35, 1:53&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3:39&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The numbers don&amp;rsquo;t mean much to me right now, except as a checkpoint for the future. The workout was pretty tough. I felt semi-pukey and exhausted by the end!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;footwear&#34;&gt;Footwear&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am now running only in Luna Sandals. I still have chafing issues, but we&amp;rsquo;ll see if they clear up with time.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/luna-sandals-2013-04-09/wearing.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Wearing Luna Sandals&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/luna-sandals-2013-04-09/luna-sandals.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Luna Sandals&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/luna-sandals-2013-04-09/feet.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Bare feet&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-about-high-intensity-interval-training&#34;&gt;What about high-intensity interval training?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/High-intensity_interval_training&#34;&gt;High-intensity interval training&lt;/a&gt; has become very popular in recent years, and for good reason. I was doing some on the treadmill in the winter in order to kickstart my running, but then put it aside when I left the treadmill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I expect to start incorporating serious HIIT into my training to get even sharper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s good to finally be back to interval training, after basically some years of not being serious and strong and disciplined enough to do it systematically.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My first Steel City Road Runners winter 5K race</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/03/03/my-first-steel-city-road-runners-winter-5k-race/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Mar 2013 18:33:03 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/03/03/my-first-steel-city-road-runners-winter-5k-race/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today was the first time I ever ran Vibram FiveFingers for a winter race! As planned &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/02/24/2013-pittsburgh-marathon-training-progress-since-signing-up-three-weeks-ago/&#34;&gt;last week&lt;/a&gt;, I ran in a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.steelcityrrc.org/scrrcevents?eventId=620982&amp;amp;EventViewMode=2&amp;amp;CalendarViewType=1&amp;amp;SelectedDate=3/16/2013&#34;&gt;Steel City Road Runners 5K race&lt;/a&gt; to gauge my current fitness level while training for the 2013 Pittsburgh Marathon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was a little disappointed by how &amp;ldquo;slow&amp;rdquo; I ran, but actually, given the amount of training I&amp;rsquo;ve had so far this winter, I&amp;rsquo;m not doing too badly.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/scrrc-5k-2013-03-04/franklin-finish.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin finishing 5K&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(explanation of misleading clock time below)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-route&#34;&gt;The route&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The route was actually kind of a complement to the &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/pretty-good-race/&#34;&gt;Pretty Good Race 5K&lt;/a&gt; course, overlapping the turnaround point of that race but on the same trail in Schenley Park.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe id=&#34;mapmyfitness_route&#34; src=&#34;http://www.mapmyrun.com/routes/view/embedded/176780548?width=560&amp;height=400&amp;&amp;line_color=7f0000ff&amp;distance_markers=1&amp;map_mode=TERRAIN&#34; height=&#34;420px&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: right; padding-right: 20px;&#34;&gt;&lt;a target=&#34;_blank&#34; href=&#34;http://mapmyrun.com/routes/create/&#34;&gt;Create Maps&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a target=&#34;_blank&#34; href=&#34;http://mapmyrun.com/routes/&#34;&gt;search&lt;/a&gt; from 80 million at &lt;a href=&#34;http://mapmyrun.com&#34;&gt;MapMyRun&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;shoes&#34;&gt;Shoes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because there is still some snow (and ice and mud) on the ground in the trails, I wore my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/08/28/five-reasons-we-just-stocked-up-on-vibram-fivefingers-kso-trek-shoes/&#34;&gt;Vibram FiveFingers KSO Trek shoes&lt;/a&gt;. Also, because of the cold temperature and the water on the ground, I wore Injinji socks, to prevent frostbite! For any run longer than a 5K, I would not even wear the FiveFingers with socks at this temperature. But I figured that I would generate enough heat during a 5K to keep my toes sufficiently warm to avoid frostbite even when wet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-race&#34;&gt;The race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;before-the-race&#34;&gt;Before the race&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I happened to bump into &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/02/20/pittsburgh-chess-club-championship-2013-round-6-winning-as-black-like-a-madman/&#34;&gt;Kurt&lt;/a&gt;, who said he was there because his daughter was running in the race. Pittsburgh is small; I always keep encountering familiar faces in new contexts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I encountered Pattye Stragar, who is so instrumental in the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/02/08/public-shame-a-great-way-to-maintain-a-habit/&#34;&gt;fitness program at CMU&lt;/a&gt;, and in publicizing the Pittsburgh Marathon and the Steel City Road Runners, and notifying the CMU community of the special deal that I ended up taking advantage of. I asked her if she was doing the marathon and she said she did it the year it came back (it was canceled 2004-2008 and came back in 2009) and she was done with marathons.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://pbs.twimg.com/media/BEek8kdCYAAcX2v.jpg:large&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Pattye Stragar and others&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;during-the-race&#34;&gt;During the race&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, my feet did get wet, but I did not have any problems with them freezing. Also, although there were some slippery, icy spots and wet, muddy spots on the trails, they were not too bad. After I got home, my shoes and socks looked like this:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/scrrc-5k-2013-03-04/vibram-and-injinji.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Shoes and socks afterwards&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The race course was hilly and not so easy, even if it weren&amp;rsquo;t slippery out there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After about the first mile, I noticed a guy running around my pace ahead of me. I decided he was going to be my target to beat in the race. There was plenty of time to make up the gap. It turned out that I actually passed him at one point, but later he passed me; I am used to this kind of thing because I tend to run downhills much better than I run uphills. In the final quarter mile or so, I took off and passed him for the last time. You can see him way back in this photo of me crossing the finish line:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/scrrc-5k-2013-03-04/franklin-finish.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin finishing 5K&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;An explanation about the clock: the race was held in two ways, with bib numbers 1-50 arbitrarily assigned to the first wave, then the rest (including me) assigned to the second wave two minutes later, to avoid congestion on the trails. So in fact, my official finish time was 25:11. I&amp;rsquo;d hoped I would be in shape to run faster than that, but this number is important real data to have, in forming my expectations for how fast I might be able to do the Pittsburgh Marathon. I think it is unlikely I&amp;rsquo;ll be in shape to attempt a four-hour marathon in two months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/steelcityrrc&#34;&gt;Steel City Road Runners Facebook site&lt;/a&gt; is a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/media/set/?set=a.419910474770437.1073741825.391728257588659&amp;amp;type=1&#34;&gt;photo album of the race&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;after-the-race&#34;&gt;After the race&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was water set out for us to drink after the race. Also, bags of potato chips, plates of cookies, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dibellas.com/&#34;&gt;DiBella&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/a&gt; subs! Tasty and filling!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to the Steel City Road Runners for putting on this race, having the people on the course to direct us, and feeding us afterwards! I had a really fun experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;signing-up-for-another-race&#34;&gt;Signing up for another race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, a couple of days ago I decided to commit to doing &lt;a href=&#34;http://eliterunners.com/just-a-short-run/&#34;&gt;Just A Short Run&lt;/a&gt; in late March. I will be doing the half marathon version of it as a final checkpoint of my fitness before the marathon, which is a month later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will be my first half marathon race in nine years: my last half marathon was in 2004.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have actually done Just A Short Run four times in my life so far:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2001: I did the 5K&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2002: I did the half marathon (the course ended up actually a bit long)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2003: I attempted the 30K as part of training for the 2003 Pittsburgh Marathon, but I was very ill and dropped out after running around 13 miles (my only DNF)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2004: I did the 5K&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do not know yet whether I will be &lt;em&gt;racing&lt;/em&gt; Just A Short Run or just using it as part of training. &lt;em&gt;Objectively&lt;/em&gt;, I should not be all-out racing such a distance while marathon training, because recovery from racing a half marathon will only cut into valuable marathon training time. However, there may be psychological benefits in doing well in a half marathon, if I am sufficiently fit to attempt that. I will decide when the time is nearer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not doing any other races, because they would interfere with my long run progression plans. I will wait until after the marathon to enjoy training for and running 5K and 10K races. So this year I&amp;rsquo;m going to skip the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.marthadixon.org/&#34;&gt;Martha&amp;rsquo;s Run 10K&lt;/a&gt; that I&amp;rsquo;ve only ever done once (in 2004), as well as &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.montourtrail.org/events/displayevent.asp?id=1&#34;&gt;Burgh&amp;rsquo;s Pizza and Wings Pub 10K&lt;/a&gt; that I also did once (in 2004). Since I&amp;rsquo;m not going to be doing the Pittsburgh Marathon again next year, maybe next year I can run these races.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-03-30&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-03-30)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ended up partially racing Just A Short Run, which I think was the correct decision. I had a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/30/report-on-just-a-short-run-my-first-half-marathon-in-nine-years/&#34;&gt;great experience&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Doing my first 5K race this year was a confidence booster for me, being a hard workout. It was also an opportunity to start really quantifying my progress and realistic timeline of improvement over the next months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2014-03-01&#34;&gt;(Update of 2014-03-01)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did not run in 2014&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.steelcityrrc.org/events?eventId=797046&amp;amp;EventViewMode=EventDetails&#34;&gt;Steel City Road Runners Campus Challenge 5K&lt;/a&gt;, sadly, because I have not been running much this winter, thanks to not signing up for either the Pittsburgh Marathon (or half marathon) or even for the annual CMU Fitness Challenge.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2013 Pittsburgh Marathon training progress since signing up three weeks ago: finally coming up with a plan!</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/02/24/2013-pittsburgh-marathon-training-progress-since-signing-up-three-weeks-ago/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Feb 2013 19:00:09 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/02/24/2013-pittsburgh-marathon-training-progress-since-signing-up-three-weeks-ago/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today, I finally started creating an &lt;em&gt;actual&lt;/em&gt; training plan for myself for the 2013 &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburghmarathon.com/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Marathon&lt;/a&gt;, three whole weeks after &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/30/why-and-how-i-am-going-to-run-the-2013-pittsburgh-marathon/&#34;&gt;signing up&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why so &lt;em&gt;late&lt;/em&gt; in the game (the marathon is just two months away, basically), and is it too late to start serious training?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-late&#34;&gt;Why late&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My excuse is that life seriously got in the way this February.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was out of town for days at &lt;a href=&#34;http://nescala.org/&#34;&gt;NE Scala&lt;/a&gt; [during one week]((/blog/2013/02/10/ne-scala-2013-my-first-scala-conference/). Then immediately after I came back, Abby broke her foot, throwing our lives into considerable disarray for about two weeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I never actually formulated a marathon training plan until today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-running-status-so-far&#34;&gt;My running status so far&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been tracking my total weekly mileage from Monday through Sunday. I have mostly been trying to build up a base by running slowly, doing only short spurts of faster running to stimulate some strength and efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;week-of-february-4&#34;&gt;Week of February 4&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Got in only 10 miles, including one session of early morning hotel treadmill running at the conference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;week-of-february-11&#34;&gt;Week of February 11&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Got in 18 miles, while dealing with the situation of Abby&amp;rsquo;s broken foot; long run was 8 miles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I skipped the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.steelcityrrc.org/scrrcevents?eventId=619944&amp;amp;EventViewMode=2&amp;amp;CalendarViewType=1&amp;amp;SelectedDate=2/16/2013&#34;&gt;Steel City Road Runners 15-mile Saturday training run&lt;/a&gt; because I simply was not in any shape to run that long.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;week-of-february-18&#34;&gt;Week of February 18&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Got in 13 miles, while continuing to spend much of time helping Abby; long run was 12 miles (I managed to squeeze in no other running this week besides a 1 mile treadmill run).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I skipped the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.steelcityrrc.org/scrrcevents?eventId=619948&amp;amp;EventViewMode=2&amp;amp;CalendarViewType=1&amp;amp;SelectedDate=2/16/2013&#34;&gt;Steel City Road Runners 10-mile Sunday training run&lt;/a&gt; (it was Sunday because of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://eliterunners.com/spring-thaw/&#34;&gt;Spring Thaw&lt;/a&gt; race on Saturday) because it just didn&amp;rsquo;t fit in my schedule for today, so I did my long run on my own yesterday instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-plan-for-the-pittsburgh-marathon&#34;&gt;The plan for the Pittsburgh Marathon&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that Abby and I have adapted sufficiently to her situation and she is regaining mobility, I finally have the time and energy to gather myself and try to figure out how to proceed with marathon training.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I casually mentioned &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/30/why-and-how-i-am-going-to-run-the-2013-pittsburgh-marathon/&#34;&gt;when I signed up&lt;/a&gt; that it would be nice to finish close to the &amp;ldquo;completely arbitrary magic number of 4:00:00&amp;rdquo;. I now believe that is very unlikely, and therefore it is no longer really a goal. My goal is to get enough training in so that I can actually survive the marathon experience without doing too much damage to myself. There is no way I can build up either huge mileage or a lot of fast training in the time that I have left, so I&amp;rsquo;m going to focus on ramping up both bit by bit and monitoring myself, watching out for overtraining.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, I want to finally start making it to some Steel City Road Runners training runs, in order to better simulate the experience of running with groups of people on roads in the morning, since that will be the situation on race day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;hansons-marathon-method&#34;&gt;Hansons Marathon Method&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The plan I have created is my own not-enough-time modification of &amp;ldquo;beginner program&amp;rdquo; in &lt;a href=&#34;http://hansonscoachingservices.com/hansons-marathon-method-the-book/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Hansons Marathon Method&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, something I&amp;rsquo;ve heard about over the years. The primary &amp;ldquo;renegade&amp;rdquo; idea behind the book is that the super-long-run that is advocated by &amp;ldquo;traditional&amp;rdquo; training programs is not ideal. Sometimes the training philosophy is oversimplified to being about the &lt;a href=&#34;http://hansonscoachingservices.com/hansons-marathon-method-the-16-miler/&#34;&gt;16-mile long run&lt;/a&gt;, but really what it&amp;rsquo;s about is not the number of miles, but the amount of wear and tear on your body during long runs that leaves you less ready to bounce back immediately and continue training. The Hansons method focuses on building &amp;ldquo;cumulative fatigue&amp;rdquo; by avoiding cycles of training so hard that you need a lot of down time. So my focus will be on running more days per week, while keeping more runs shorter and easier, while putting in an honest long run per week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So actually, this is, relatively speaking, a high mileage training method, rather than a low mileage method: instead of doing a whole lot of hard work in fewer days, you spread out the work over more days and run more. So I am in fact deciding to back away from what I thought I would experiment with when I signed up, and I am substituting a different experiment: choosing not to do any long runs of more than about 16 miles (in practice, since the toll on the body is really about time, this means that I don&amp;rsquo;t really want to run for longer than about 2.5 hours in training; it was these kinds of runs that ten years ago really left me worn out).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;schedule&#34;&gt;Schedule&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I plan to run the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.steelcityrrc.org/scrrcevents?eventId=620982&amp;amp;EventViewMode=2&amp;amp;CalendarViewType=1&amp;amp;SelectedDate=2/16/2013&#34;&gt;Steel City Road Runners 5K race in Schenley Park&lt;/a&gt; as a way to gauge my current level of fitness (and also count it as a tempo workout).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also figured out my tentative weekend schedules for the next nine weeks till marathon day, to make sure I can get in the training I need. When training for a marathon, you kind of have to arrange your life around your training! I will be so happy when the marathon is over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes we face setbacks of various kinds when trying to achieve some goal. We have to bounce back by adapting: changing up our expectations as well as the details of our plans. The way I&amp;rsquo;ve done this is to go back to my original motivations and priorities and examine how to modify them. It&amp;rsquo;s easier to deal with setbacks when you already decided up front, before the setbacks, what your priorities are. In my case, &lt;em&gt;finish time&lt;/em&gt; was the least of my priorities, and the easiest to let go of.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Running my 8th Pretty Good Race 5K: dealing with disappointment</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/09/07/running-my-8th-pretty-good-race-5k-dealing-with-disappointment/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Sep 2012 19:47:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/09/07/running-my-8th-pretty-good-race-5k-dealing-with-disappointment/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pretty-good-race-2012/registration.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Registration table&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This year I ran, for the eighth time in my life, the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~kalp/PGR/&#34;&gt;CMU Pretty Good Race 5K&lt;/a&gt;; on National Running Day earlier this year, I described &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/06/06/i-celebrated-national-running-day-in-schenley-park-remembering-how-i-began-to-run-13-year-ago/&#34;&gt;how special this race has been to me&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things did not go as planned, but I made the most of the event anyway, and was happy and even amused by some of the things that happened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;preparation&#34;&gt;Preparation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the big problems was that I was not at all feeling prepared for the race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;foot-problem&#34;&gt;Foot problem&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For one thing, I felt very tired for days after my last race, the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/08/25/my-eighth-time-doing-run-around-the-square-5k/&#34;&gt;Run Around the Square of almost two weeks ago&lt;/a&gt;. I gave so much of myself during that race that afterwards, I just didn&amp;rsquo;t feel like running again for a while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Worse than that, my left foot has been bothering me ever since that race, discouraging me even more from continuing my regular running. I am pretty sure that I injured my arch area because I had the shoe strap of my Vibram FiveFingers KSO Trek shoe too tight. I had it on tighter than during my normal runs, out of &amp;ldquo;fear&amp;rdquo; of the shoe coming off or slipping during the race on the Schenley Park hilly trail. &lt;strong&gt;Shoe too tight was a mistake I will never make again.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;life-intervened&#34;&gt;Life intervened&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, and most significantly, I have spent the last week spending a lot of time on the talk I gave yesterday at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://pghrb.heroku.com/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Ruby group&lt;/a&gt;, as &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/08/07/the-first-steel-city-ruby-conference-an-amazing-experience/&#34;&gt;I had promised I would a month ago&lt;/a&gt;. That took a lot out of me. In fact, if I had not already committed, with Abby, to run the Pretty Good Race this year, I would not have done it at all, after all my energy was drained in the past week. But it would have been unfair to bail out on Abby given that this is one of the few races we have started doing together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suppose I could have decided to give the talk for the October meeting of the Ruby group instead, knowing up front the annual date of the Pretty Good Race. That had crossed my mind, but I also had instantly decided (with no regrets) that giving the talk as soon as possible after I promised to do it was of much higher priority than anything involving any of my races.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;weather-conditions&#34;&gt;Weather conditions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The race was made much more difficult by the unpredictable weather. For days it would be cold, then hot. Well, it turned out that race day was very hot. It had to be like 80F. I was even thinking that this might be the warmest race I&amp;rsquo;ve ever run in, but actually, that&amp;rsquo;s probably not quite true: races in July tend to be pretty hot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-plan&#34;&gt;The plan&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I started the race with no hope whatsoever of surpassing last year&amp;rsquo;s time of 24:36. I was just going to try to run an honest race at steady effort, and use my usual mental tricks of trying to speed up in the second half and try to catch people ahead of me. In particular, the fearsome very long uphill at the end is something that I wanted to have enough energy for to sprint up; in every year up till now, I have waited until the finish line is in sight before I start my sprint. I did not always manage to pass everyone in front of me, and I also at least once let someone sprint past me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year, during some training runs on the course, I experimented with running hard for just the second half and figuring out how much energy to conserve so that I would be able to start the sprint from far beyond that point, from around the curve. That way, I would have the possibility of powering through with nobody able to catch me. &lt;em&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d never started my sprint from so far out before in any race&lt;/em&gt;, so this was going to be an experiment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-race&#34;&gt;The race&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pretty-good-race-2012/franklin-before-race.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin before the race&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;beginning&#34;&gt;Beginning&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went out at a steady pace. After less than a mile, runners had more or less spread out and found their pace. I slowly caught up to someone who was running at approximately my pace. This is when things got interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This runner ahead of me sensed that I was catching up and decided to surge. I was confused by this move, but just kept on going at my pace. Maybe she just preferred running with nobody around her; but I was trying to give her some space by coming up from the side and behind her, rather than directly behind her. Having someone breathe down your neck is not very pleasant, after all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;middle&#34;&gt;Middle&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As she kept increasing her distance from me, I concluded that she was probably just faster than me, found her natural pace, and I would never catch her. There was nobody else visible directly ahead of me, so I had no other target during the first half of the race, but I knew that since it was mostly uphill, and I&amp;rsquo;m stronger downhill than uphill, and a lot of runners go out too fast in the first half of races, it was a question of whom I would start catching during the second half.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then, as I approached the turnaround point (this is an out and back course on Panther Hollow Trail), I noticed that far ahead of me, beyond the designated turnaround point (where there were volunteers directing people to turn around, and some runners were in fact there turning around), was this runner who had blasted past me. Maybe she was in the zone or something, but she missed the turnaround point! She started coming back as I reached the turnaround point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I felt bad that she had made a mistake, but then again, this was a new opportunity for me. I already knew that she was faster than me. But she wasted time and energy falling behind me in the race. Could I actually prevent her from coming past me during the entire second half of the race, given my head start?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t look back once as I focused on running the second half of the race, almost all downhill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;end&#34;&gt;End&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Probably no more than a quarter mile from the end, she passed me and started putting distance between us. But at my targeted location to put in my kick, I &lt;em&gt;screamed&lt;/em&gt;, three or four times, while doing what I&amp;rsquo;d done in training: going into an all-out long sprint. I think I totally freaked her out, because she kind of just stepped aside and started jogging or something (that&amp;rsquo;s what it seemed like as I charged past and then around the curve and then up the steep hill).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I continued throwing out a periodic scream until I finished. For the first hundred or so races in my life, I never screamed, but I started this habit only last year, at &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/01/run-shadyside-5k-outrunning-mickey-mouse-and-lending-a-trumpet/&#34;&gt;Run Shadyside&lt;/a&gt;. I believe it actually helps me a lot when I&amp;rsquo;m in pain and need to &amp;ldquo;wake up&amp;rdquo; into a new gear of existence temporarily. I just worry about whether it scares people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that I finished ten seconds earlier than her. Mission accomplished, after all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-is-important&#34;&gt;What is important&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here I am, shortly after finishing:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pretty-good-race-2012/franklin-exhausted.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin exhausted&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s Abby coming up the hill for the finish:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pretty-good-race-2012/abby-finishing.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby finishing on the uphill&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I was pretty proud of having executed the most demanding sprint finish of my entire life. I know that my final race time of 26:05 is far slower than my 24:36 of last year, but as far as my effort was concerned, I did give it my all. &lt;em&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s not about how fast I went, but how much I gave of what I had.&lt;/em&gt; (Apparently, at the London Olympics, some runner was banned for &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.telegraph.co.uk/sport/olympics/athletics/9456916/Algerian-runner-banned-for-not-trying-hard-enough-at-London-2012.html&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;not trying hard enough&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby, in her second Pretty Good Race, ran 2:07 faster than last year, in more difficult conditions. It&amp;rsquo;s really great how she&amp;rsquo;s improved her fitness so much since she started running. &lt;em&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s not about how fast she ran, but how she&amp;rsquo;s improved.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-next-race&#34;&gt;The next race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next race that I&amp;rsquo;m already committed to is the Great Race 10K, which I&amp;rsquo;m signed up already to run for the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/25/blistered-but-blissful-in-the-burgh/&#34;&gt;tenth time&lt;/a&gt;. I still need to recover my energy for it, and also let my foot pain go away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For various reasons, I was not able to run the Pretty Good Race fast this year. But I had an exciting experience anyway and made the most of it.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Walking and running in Invisible Shoes: a review of the Connect</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/07/26/walking-and-running-in-invisible-shoes-a-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jul 2012 21:28:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/07/26/walking-and-running-in-invisible-shoes-a-review/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;For three weeks now, I have been wearing a pair of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.invisibleshoe.com/&#34;&gt;Invisible Shoes&lt;/a&gt; huaraches almost exclusively when walking and running outside. I have worn them daily walking, and I have run in them on roads, on sidewalks, on grass, and in park trails.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a review of the 4mm sole Connect model (I might get a 6mm sole Contact later).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is what the shoes look like with &amp;ldquo;slip-on/slip-off&amp;rdquo; lacing:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/invisible-shoes-connect/without-feet.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/invisible-shoes-connect/bottom.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As you can see, the sole is quite thin, just 4mm:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/invisible-shoes-connect/side-view.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here are some photos of me wearing the shoes:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/invisible-shoes-connect/grass.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/invisible-shoes-connect/asphalt.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-wear-such-a-thin-shoe&#34;&gt;Why wear such a thin shoe?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ten years ago, in 2002, I learned about the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tarahumara_people&#34;&gt;Tarahumara&lt;/a&gt; Native Americans who live in Mexico and are famed for long-distance running. I was fascinated that they chose to run in minimalist huaraches. At the time, I was doing a lot of serious &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/running/&#34;&gt;running&lt;/a&gt;, and perpetually had problems with running shoes. I figured out from trial and error that the more minimalist I got, the more I enjoyed the feel of running and the fewer injuries I received, but I didn&amp;rsquo;t know how minimalist I could really get before the cons outweighed the pros. By 2002, I had gotten as far as wearing racing flats by New Balance and Asics for races and some of my training runs, but no shoe was perfect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had also tried wearing a variety of ordinary sandals for walking and running, but they had all kinds of ergonomic problems that led me to give up on them. The strapping systems, the substantial (by my standards) heels, and the curved &amp;ldquo;arch support&amp;rdquo; all caused discomfort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fast-forward to 2009, when I bought my first pair of Vibram FiveFingers minimalist shoes. These changed my life, being sufficiently minimalist to defeat a number of problems I&amp;rsquo;ve had with traditional mono-toed shoes. As long-time readers of &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/fivefingers/&#34;&gt;this blog know&lt;/a&gt;, I&amp;rsquo;ve been wearing them exclusively for all kinds of activities, ranging from regular everyday walking to running on roads, running on trails, hiking, kayaking, rafting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past year, I have tried a little bit of &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/barefoot-running/&#34;&gt;barefoot running&lt;/a&gt;, but that is still too extreme for me to do often or for a long period of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I decided that now was the time to try to get more minimalist than FiveFingers, toward the &amp;ldquo;barefoot&amp;rdquo; feel, but without the most glaring drawbacks of being barefoot. Luckily, the surprising popularity of &lt;a href=&#34;http://chrismcdougall.com/&#34;&gt;Chris McDougall&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/a&gt; book &amp;ldquo;Born to Run&amp;rdquo; has resulted in a good number of people selling minimalist huaraches for running.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;buying&#34;&gt;Buying&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Barefoot Ted had long sold his version of huaraches, the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lunasandals.com/&#34;&gt;Luna Sandals&lt;/a&gt;. I decided to try, instead, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.invisibleshoe.com/&#34;&gt;Invisible Shoes&lt;/a&gt;, because these are more minimalist than the Luna, which in its classic form has a 6mm sole as well as a foot bed. I may well try the Luna at some point, but my goal for now is to approximate the barefoot feel, rather than pick the best huaraches for serious rugged use, and work up from there. So I went for the 4mm Connect version of the Invisible Shoes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For now, instead of buying a DIY kit, I decided that the simplest hassle-free way to break into huaraches was to buy a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lunasandals.com/&#34;&gt;custom-made&lt;/a&gt; shoe that had the soles cut and punched and laced up, ready to immediately wear. I traced my foot, scanned the trace, and emailed it, and quickly received my pair in the mail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are interested in trying out huaraches, I recommend following this route if the thought of DIY problems might otherwise discourage you. I may go DIY in the future, now that I see the final product.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;tying&#34;&gt;Tying&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question of how to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.invisibleshoe.com/tying/&#34;&gt;tie&lt;/a&gt; laces always pops up. For now, I have not experimented with different methods in order to evaluate what works best for me for secureness and comfort. I have been using the slip-on/slip-off system that came with the shoe, adjusting it as needed when my foot feels too tight or too loose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;walking&#34;&gt;Walking&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I got Invisible Shoes, my regular walking shoes were my Vibram FiveFingers KSO shoes. But once I got the Invisible Shoes, I completely stopped wearing the KSO for everyday walking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;pros&#34;&gt;Pros&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My toes have real freedom. Toe shoes like the Vibram FiveFingers compartmentalize the toes, so although they solve my wide-foot problem, they do not give me total freedom of the whole front of the foot that I like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good ventilation, like being barefoot. FiveFingers get hot in summer, resulting in sweat and sometimes blisters. I don&amp;rsquo;t get blisters walking in Invisible Shoes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the slip-on/slip-off system, I really can slip on and off easily. Since I like going barefoot indoors, it&amp;rsquo;s a plus to be able to slip on and off the shoes so easily.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;cons&#34;&gt;Cons&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is some rubbing at key points on the foot: the knot in the lacing system on top of the foot, and the lacing that passes between the big toe and the second toe. In practice, none of this has been a real problem except when it&amp;rsquo;s raining and my feet get wet, in which case I get chafed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The soles, being so thin, flop around a bit. Occasionally a sole will fold under and cause me to trip, but this happens very rarely. The main problem is mostly social: the flopping sound draws attention; I prefer to walk very silently (which I can do in most closed shoes).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The thinness of the soles also result in my feet getting very hot when I&amp;rsquo;m just standing for a period of time on hot asphalt or concrete (this is the same problem as I have when going barefoot). So standing at a street intersection waiting for a long light or in a parking lot while putting stuff into a car is not so pleasant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The thinness of the soles means walking over rough terrain is not always pleasant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that all the problems with the thinness of the soles might not be present if I had the 6mm sole rather than the 4mm sole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;running&#34;&gt;Running&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Disclaimer: I have run only four or five times in these shoes so far, so I will accumulate more experience as I continue to run in them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;pros-1&#34;&gt;Pros&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Running in these shoes on the roads and sidewalks is predictable and pleasant, very much like running barefoot. I am considering doing more tests to determine whether to run a road race 5K or 10K in these shoes! I have not run at race pace in these shoes yet. I may need to adjust lacing systems in order to feel confident about running at maximum speed without a flopping or lace-loosening problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;cons-1&#34;&gt;Cons&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is sole flopping when running. Actually there is less flopping than when walking, though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Running in the trails has not worked too smoothly. The 4mm sole really is quite thin for trail running. I noticed this when running in Frick Park, where some of the trails are more rocky than others. I also noticed this even when running in &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/06/18/walking-the-scenic-route-through-schenley-park-to-work/&#34;&gt;Schenley Park on the Pretty Good Race course&lt;/a&gt;, where the downhill section had me periodically hitting rocks harder than comfortable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is also the annoyance of stuff getting between the foot and the sole when running in the trails. Since I don&amp;rsquo;t like stopping, I&amp;rsquo;ve tried to simply flex my foot to let the material slide back out during the next couple of strides, and this mostly works. But I got one blister during a run on the trails, possibly because of loose material that got between my foot and the sole that I didn&amp;rsquo;t bother completely shaking out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 4mm Connect model of Invisible Shoes is great for walking around in. For running, I need to do more tests to find out how they hold up in more demanding conditions of speed and terrain. I would also like to compare the 4mm Connect model with the 6mm Contact model.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Walking the scenic route through Schenley Park to work</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/06/18/walking-the-scenic-route-through-schenley-park-to-work/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Jun 2012 22:08:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/06/18/walking-the-scenic-route-through-schenley-park-to-work/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Two months ago, I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/04/16/one-week-of-commuting-on-foot-because-of-cmu-carnival/&#34;&gt;spent a whole week&lt;/a&gt; commuting to work at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cmu.edu/&#34;&gt;Carnegie Mellon University&lt;/a&gt; by walking instead of driving, because of the annoyances of parking during Carnival week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because I enjoyed that experience so much, since then, I have walked to/from work at least once a week! Usually my route has included either Forbes Avenue or Schenley Drive, but once I went on other roads through Schenley Park.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last week I started making the trails of Schenley Park part of my walk. This adds probably half a mile to the walk (for a total of just less than 2.5 miles from home to work); time efficiency was why I had not taken this indirect route before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some photos of my walk to CMU last week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;going-barefoot-to-schenley-park&#34;&gt;Going barefoot to Schenley Park&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went barefoot the entire way from home to Schenley Park.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/commute-schenley-park/barefoot.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Barefoot&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Reaching the Schenley Park sign on Hobart Street:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/commute-schenley-park/hobart.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Schenley Park sign on Hobart Street&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;About to enjoy barefoot running on the grass to cross Beacon Street and Bartlett Street to reach the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.examiner.com/article/schenley-park-bartlett-street-playground&#34;&gt;Bartlett Playground&lt;/a&gt;. Note that the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.tour.pitt.edu/tour-080.html&#34;&gt;Cathedral of Learning&lt;/a&gt; is visible in the background.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/commute-schenley-park/beacon-bartlett-grass.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Grass at Hobart Street and Beacon Street&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Arriving at the Bartlett Shelter sign:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/commute-schenley-park/bartlett-shelter.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Sign for Bartlett Shelter&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Right behind the playground is the entrance to the Panther Hollow Trail:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/commute-schenley-park/bartlett-panther-hollow-trail.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Sign for Panther Hollow Trail&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;panther-hollow-trail-to-schenley-park-cafe-and-visitor-center&#34;&gt;Panther Hollow Trail to Schenley Park Cafe and Visitor Center&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This section of the Panther Hollow Trail that I followed all the way to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pittsburghparks.org/schenleyparkcafe&#34;&gt;Schenley Park Cafe and Visitor Center&lt;/a&gt; is the all-downhill section of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~kalp/PGR/&#34;&gt;Pretty Good Race 5K&lt;/a&gt; course that I ran on to &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/06/06/i-celebrated-national-running-day-in-schenley-park-remembering-how-i-began-to-run-13-year-ago/&#34;&gt;celebrate National Running Day on June 6&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My apologies to the barefoot purists, but I immediately found the trail too rough for my bare feet and put on my Vibram FiveFingers KSO shoes:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/commute-schenley-park/vibram-fivefingers-kso.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Vibram FiveFingers KSO shoes on Panther Hollow Trail&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A typical view while running downhill on the Panther Hollow Trail for about 0.9 mile:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/commute-schenley-park/panther-hollow-trail-downhill.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Panther Hollow Trail going downhill&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A sign at the base of the steps that lead up to the Schenley Park Cafe and Visitor Center. I appreciate the renovations in the Pittsburgh parks in the past several years that include such features as the new signs that I think help visitors a lot.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/commute-schenley-park/steps-sign.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Schenley Park sign at base of steps&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Finally out of the trail:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/commute-schenley-park/schenley-park-cafe-and-visitor-center.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Schenley Park Cafe and Visitor Center&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;across-flagstaff-hill-to-my-office-at-carnegie-mellon-university&#34;&gt;Across Flagstaff Hill to my office at Carnegie Mellon University&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A view of Phipps Conservatory as well as the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.tour.pitt.edu/tour-080.html&#34;&gt;Cathedral of Learning&lt;/a&gt; in the distance:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/commute-schenley-park/phipps-cathedral.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Phipps Conservatory&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One is probably not supposed to do so, but I climbed up the stone border (about four feet high) to enter Flagstaff Hill. The more circuitous route to my office would be to take Schenley Drive, which curves around, but it&amp;rsquo;s shorter (and also more scenic and strenuous) to go up the hill directly and steeply, and then descend.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/commute-schenley-park/flagstaff-hill.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Flagstaff Hill&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Taking in the view of the Cathedral of Learning against the lovely blue sky, while running through the grass on Flagstaff Hill:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/commute-schenley-park/cathedral-of-learning-from-flagstaff-hill.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Cathedral of Learning visible from Flagstaff Hill&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My office is barely visible through the trees as I descend:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/commute-schenley-park/office-through-trees.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Office visible through trees&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A convenient path to Frew Street:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/commute-schenley-park/path-to-frew-street.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Path to Frew Street&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At my office building:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/commute-schenley-park/office-building.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;My office building&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a lot of fun on a nice day to walk to work the &amp;ldquo;long&amp;rdquo; way that goes through the trails of Schenley Park and also Flagstaff Hill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am so grateful that Pittsburgh is friendly and stimulating for walking in. And, of course, I am grateful that &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mary_Schenley&#34;&gt;Mary Schenley&lt;/a&gt; donated the land to Pittsburgh way back that became Schenley Park.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I celebrated National Running Day in Schenley Park: remembering how I began to run 13 years ago</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/06/06/i-celebrated-national-running-day-in-schenley-park-remembering-how-i-began-to-run-13-year-ago/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Jun 2012 21:42:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/06/06/i-celebrated-national-running-day-in-schenley-park-remembering-how-i-began-to-run-13-year-ago/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/melissappc/663419600&#34; title=&#34;Schenley Park by Melissa McMasters, on Flickr&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm2.staticflickr.com/1309/663419600_66449cdcc7.jpg&#34; width=&#34;333&#34; height=&#34;500&#34; alt=&#34;Schenley Park&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I celebrated &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.runningday.org/&#34;&gt;National Running Day&lt;/a&gt; by, uh, going out for a &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/running/&#34;&gt;run&lt;/a&gt;. Here in Pittsburgh, I have come to like most to run in &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburghparks.org/frick&#34;&gt;Frick Park&lt;/a&gt;, but today I decided to run in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pittsburghparks.org/schenley&#34;&gt;Schenley Park&lt;/a&gt; instead, as I was in a sentimental mood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ran the out and back &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~kalp/PGR/&#34;&gt;Pretty Good Race&lt;/a&gt; course on the Panther Hollow Trail in Schenley Park, as I have done at least several dozen times in the past thirteen years. My favorite part is always the long downhill return back to the start, during which I try to really fly down fast, feeling the wind rush past me. It&amp;rsquo;s the reward for having run uphill in the first half of the course!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~kalp/PGR/pg-race.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Pretty Good Race 5K course&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I was not always a runner. I only started to run at age 29, during a turning point in my life. And it turned out that Schenley Park played a vital role in getting me out the door and on my feet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(The details of my story are distilled from my emails and daily journal I kept in 1999-2004.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-and-when-i-started-to-run&#34;&gt;Why and when I started to run&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In early 1999, weighing 30 pounds more than I do now 13 years later (and being probably prediabetic, in retrospect), I decided to change my life by trying to fulfill a childhood dream of becoming a runner. You have to realize that I was completely out of shape at this stage of my life, barely able to run ten seconds without stopping!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I set a concrete goal to work toward in order to motivate myself to improve little by little. It turns out that Carnegie Mellon University has for decades sponsored a 5K race called the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~kalp/PGR/&#34;&gt;Pretty Good Race&lt;/a&gt; (the name inspired by Pittsburgh&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/25/blistered-but-blissful-in-the-burgh/&#34;&gt;Great Race 10K&lt;/a&gt;), held every year on Friday afternoon of the final week of the incoming computer science graduate student orientation program. A good number of incoming graduate students (as well as faculty, staff, and anyone else who is interested) take part in this race every year. The fast runners are very competitive, of course, but many run the race just for fun; there is a party afterwards for everyone who participates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided to aim to run in the Pretty Good Race in September 1999. I had many months to prepare for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-progress-in-running-recruiting-my-friend-john&#34;&gt;My progress in running: recruiting my friend John&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Progress was quite slow, because I had decades of poor conditioning to overcome. On February 10, 1999, I went for my first run with my friend John (a graduate student classmate of mine) for the first time. John was not much of a distance runner (he could sprint), but at least he had run in the Pretty Good Race in 1998 (and finished at the back of the pack). He was patient with me because I had rest quite frequently. &lt;strong&gt;I owe John for encouraging me and accompanying me.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, I was so out of shape that I could only &amp;ldquo;run&amp;rdquo; for ten or fifteen seconds at a time before getting chest and leg pains and having to walk for minutes before starting up again. I had no idea what I was doing. Also, we did this irregularly, not on a daily schedule or anything. So progress was slow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;failure-in-1999&#34;&gt;Failure in 1999&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that I was dealing with various personal problems in the summer of 1999 and also still not fit enough to run continuously for a mile. So in late August, I decided to give up on my goal, and did not run in the Pretty Good Race in 1999&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-new-motivation-in-2000-30th-birthday&#34;&gt;A new motivation in 2000: 30th birthday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In May, on my 30th birthday, I decided that I was going to get serious about running. I could not just continue to do my low-yield unsystematic run/walking with John. The very next day, I pushed myself harder than I had ever done before, running with John.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I shook off my &amp;ldquo;dependency&amp;rdquo; on John, and decided to run &lt;em&gt;every day&lt;/em&gt;, even if it meant doing it alone. I made extensive use of Frick Park near home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;scientific-training&#34;&gt;Scientific training&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started reading &amp;ldquo;The Runner&amp;rsquo;s Handbook&amp;rdquo;, recommended to me by my sister Linda months ago. Exactly nine days after my birthday, I wrote Linda email telling her that I planned to run the Pretty Good Race in September.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book said that a beginner should run at least twenty minutes, preferably thirty minutes, and at least three times a week, preferably five. This was much more than what I&amp;rsquo;d been doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wrote in my journal:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
I think I will aim to successfully run my Frick Park route for a few weeks, till I can comfortably run 20 minutes.  Then I will invent a new addition in Frick Park in order to make the run 30 minutes.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Progress became more noticeable as I focused on putting in the time and distance, going as slowly as required to avoid going anaerobic (my problem when running with John). Learning the science of distance running definitely helped a lot in making my training scientific.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;really-committing-to-running-the-pretty-good-race-in-2000&#34;&gt;Really committing to running the Pretty Good Race in 2000&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I managed to get some friends of mine to commit to also running in the Pretty Good Race for the first time, and we did a little bit of running together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;some-warmup-races&#34;&gt;Some warmup races&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ran the first races of my life right before the Pretty Good Race, in order to get a feel for what it was like racing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;run-around-the-square-5k&#34;&gt;Run Around the Square 5K&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My actual first 5K race was the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.runaroundthesquare.com/&#34;&gt;Run Around the Square&lt;/a&gt; in August 2000, just some weeks before the Pretty Good Race. It was &amp;ldquo;disastrous&amp;rdquo;, because I was completely inexperienced:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
I guess I went too fast, because before I reached the park entrance, I
wasn&#39;t feeling so well, and my right side was beginning to hurt
already.  I didn&#39;t think of myself as going fast, because so many
people were going faster and obviously way ahead.  There was no
crowding problem, because people were getting spread out.

Worse, when I reached the park entrance, I dashed down the steep,
curving hill, passing a lot of people, and almost fell off the trail.
When the uphill came, people started passing me.

I knew I was in trouble when it took me 9 minutes to get to the 1 mile
mark.

As the race progressed, I saw all kinds of people pass me: middle-aged
women, high-schoolers, old men.  It was embarrassing.  I was just
trying to avoid getting sick.  I was moving my feet slowly, and not
pushing off.  The feeling of people passing me was not encouraging.

I ended up grabbing water three times.

I took 18 minutes to get to the 2 mile mark.  At this point, I
believed I would probably take 27 minutes total, and I felt bad.

I didn&#39;t even bother to get in an extra kick when the end was near.  I
just didn&#39;t feel well.  I believe my time was 27:xx.  I took my pulse
right after I ripped off my chip and handed it to someone.  It was
200.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, my time was a very slow 27:23, and I was overambitious in my first race. But that was OK, because the point was to get experience so that in the race that mattered, the Pretty Good Race, hopefully I would do better. I was afraid of finishing dead last in the Pretty Good Race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(For the record, a year later, 2001, I ran 23:19 in this race.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;montour-trail-5k&#34;&gt;Montour Trail 5K&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A week before the Pretty Good Race, I ran in my second 5K race of my life, the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mtchalfmarathon.com/&#34;&gt;Montour Trail 5K&lt;/a&gt;. I did it in 25:30, being much more experienced as a result of the Run Around the Square.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(For the record, a year later, in 2001, I ran the Montour Trail half marathon instead, in 1:47:23, five days after running a 5K race in 21:39. Do the math: in one year I got my 5K time down from 27:23 to 21:39!!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;moment-of-truth-pretty-good-race-2000-http-www-cs-cmu-edu-kalp-pgr-2000-html&#34;&gt;Moment of truth: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~kalp/PGR/2000.html&#34;&gt;Pretty Good Race 2000&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My friends all beat me in the race, some pretty significantly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I finished in 26:26, in agony, in 27th place out of 32 (including the guy who ran backwards the whole way). OK, so I didn&amp;rsquo;t finish in last place after all!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I silently vowed to beat my friends in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~kalp/PGR/2001.html&#34;&gt;2001&lt;/a&gt;. I did. I came in 18th place out of 45, after training really hard for a year to improve my running. My time in 2001 was 22:33, over four minutes faster than in 2000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here I am outsprinting my friend Sungwoo at the finish:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pgr-2001-sungwoo-franklin.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Pretty Good Race 5K, 2001, closeup of Sungwoo and Franklin&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A mutual friend asked me why I was so intent on beating Sungwoo, and asked whether I had something against him. I said no, not at all. It was just a personal challenge, a goal, just like when I first starting running in races, and got beaten by a certain 70-something hunched-over old man repeatedly, I made him a concrete target to surpass in the future, and eventually I did. In this case, I had earlier judged that Sungwoo was closest in speed to me, and therefore I would aim to beat him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;other-years-of-running-the-pretty-good-race&#34;&gt;Other years of running the Pretty Good Race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2000: 26:26 (first time, and 3rd lifetime race)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2001: 22:33 (much better, 23rd race)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2002: did not run, because of half marathon the next day&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2003: did not run, because of half marathon the next day&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2004: simply chose not to run&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2005: 23:16 (little training)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2006: 22:57 (recovered some fitness)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2007: (almost no running this year, health declining)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2008: (almost no running this year, health declining)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2009: 25:52 (almost no running this year, in terrible health)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2010: 26:41 (almost no running this year, in terrible health)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2011: 24:36 (began running again, recovering my health)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-future&#34;&gt;The future&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year, 2012, I aim to get back under 24:00 in the Pretty Good Race, to return to my fitness level of early 2007 before my life was disrupted for half a decade during which I had trouble staying healthy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have done less running so far this year than I would have liked, unfortunately, but just being on the Pretty Good Race course again and feeling great to be out there reminded me to return to a regular running habit. I have three months before the next Pretty Good Race!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;but-why&#34;&gt;But why??&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this blog post I haven&amp;rsquo;t explained why I wanted to run, what my goals were, how they have changed over the years, and why I run now. I will write about those topics in detail later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For now, I&amp;rsquo;ll just say that &lt;strong&gt;I love to run&lt;/strong&gt;. I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t do it if I didn&amp;rsquo;t. (I know people who run but do not love it. I think &lt;a href=&#34;http://jones.wordpress.com/2012/06/04/things-ive-learnt-from-running/&#34;&gt;that is a mistake&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reflections on 2011</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/12/31/reflections-on-2011/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Dec 2011 18:52:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/12/31/reflections-on-2011/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I reflect on my year of 2011 as it ends. Since I did not start blogging until September, I go into more detail of what happened before then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;january&#34;&gt;January&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I continued our project of massively reorganizing our home, a project that began when she moved in during summer 2010. We were very grateful that Abby&amp;rsquo;s father helped out a lot.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I continued getting rid of a lot of stuff, including another eighteen boxes of my books, as I became an initially reluctant &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/minimalism/&#34;&gt;minimalist&lt;/a&gt;. We sold or gave away a &lt;em&gt;huge&lt;/em&gt; number of various of belongings.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby started cooking much more than in the past, and we enjoyed trying new dishes of her making.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I enjoyed some light cross-country skiing in the winter, using the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Schenley_Park_Golf_Course&#34;&gt;Bob O&amp;rsquo;Connor Golf Course at Schenley Park&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I began a weekly Zen &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/meditation/&#34;&gt;meditation&lt;/a&gt; session offered at Carnegie Mellon University.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started moving very gradually toward a &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/paleo/&#34;&gt;paleo&lt;/a&gt; diet and exercise routine, and immediately experienced benefits. &amp;ldquo;The Paleo Solution&amp;rdquo; by &lt;a href=&#34;http://robbwolf.com/&#34;&gt;Robb Wolf&lt;/a&gt; was very useful.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started learning modern &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/javascript/&#34;&gt;JavaScript&lt;/a&gt; for a new project at work, getting into client-side Web development. As part of that, I learned &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/jquery/&#34;&gt;jQuery&lt;/a&gt; through a free &lt;a href=&#34;http://p2pu.org/&#34;&gt;P2PU&lt;/a&gt; course and used it in the project.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started using &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/XQuery&#34;&gt;XQuery&lt;/a&gt; at work to process XML in a clear and concise way. I had used XSLT in the past, but it was very unpleasant.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I decided, for various reasons, to stop writing new &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/perl/&#34;&gt;Perl&lt;/a&gt; scripts and move to &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/python/&#34;&gt;Python&lt;/a&gt; instead.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started playing in my final (and disastrous) &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/chess/&#34;&gt;chess&lt;/a&gt; tournament, the Pittsburgh Chess Club Championship (which I had won in 2006 and 2007).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;february&#34;&gt;February&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pittsburgh was all about the Steelers, and I went to a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Super_Bowl_XLV&#34;&gt;Super Bowl&lt;/a&gt; party for the first time, but we lost!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I read &amp;ldquo;The Art of Non-Conformity&amp;rdquo; by &lt;a href=&#34;http://chrisguillebeau.com/&#34;&gt;Chris Guillebeau&lt;/a&gt; and found it so inspiring that I decided to take action and start making big changes to my life, in my own way.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;One big change: I quit playing chess, cold turkey, after having been unenthusiastic about it for months already (and playing correspondingly poorly). When the passion and enjoyment are gone, there is no point in hanging onto something just because it has been such an important part of my life for years.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;After years of not playing any music at all, I started playing &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/recorder/&#34;&gt;recorder&lt;/a&gt;, and vowed to play every single day if possible. Ten months later, I am still playing recorder.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I began attending a lot of &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/16/pittsburgh-software-developer-communities/&#34;&gt;local software developer group meetings&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started learning the &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/scala/&#34;&gt;Scala&lt;/a&gt; programming language and decided to use it on a small project.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;march&#34;&gt;March&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I continued our meditation practice at CMU, and went to our first mini-&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sesshin&#34;&gt;sesshin&lt;/a&gt; on a Saturday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I continued practicing recorder every single day, and joined the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.andrew.cmu.edu/user/lukas/pcars/Welcome.html&#34;&gt;local chapter of the American Recorder Society&lt;/a&gt;. It was very exciting to meet new people and to get into a wide range of music I had never really listened to or played.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I saw a video of &lt;a href=&#34;http://jakeshimabukuro.com/&#34;&gt;Jake Shimabukuro&lt;/a&gt; playing &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/ukulele/&#34;&gt;ukulele&lt;/a&gt; so beautifully that I was inspired to buy a ukulele and start learning to play it. (Unfortunately, it would turn out that time constraints caused me not to pursue ukulele far. This will change in 2012.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I got pulled into the Ruby programming language because it is well-supported on Mac OS and it is easy to install libraries and tools, of which there are many that are quite useful.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I went to &lt;a href=&#34;http://farmtotablepa.com/&#34;&gt;Farm to Table&lt;/a&gt; in Pittsburgh, and after that, Abby started moving toward paleo eating, with even better results than my smaller experiments earlier.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I started our &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/hiking/&#34;&gt;hiking&lt;/a&gt; season in the spring. Hiking is special to us; it was one of our first shared activities (after initially meeting during salsa dancing), and one we return to again and again. When there is no calendar conflict and the weather is acceptable, we like hiking almost every weekend from spring through fall.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;{% img /images/steves-soup-hike-2011-03-26.jpg Abby in front of me at Steve&amp;rsquo;s Soup Hike %}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;april&#34;&gt;April&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started wearing &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/fivefingers/&#34;&gt;Vibram FiveFingers shoes&lt;/a&gt; almost all the time, whether walking or running (but not yet for hiking).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I went to &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/yoga/&#34;&gt;yoga&lt;/a&gt; at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.clpgh.org/locations/squirrelhill/&#34;&gt;Squirrel Hill Library&lt;/a&gt; for the first time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;may&#34;&gt;May&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I began my experiment with barefoot running, in observation of &lt;a href=&#34;http://barefootrunners.org/ibrd&#34;&gt;International Barefoot Running Day&lt;/a&gt;. I started walking around barefoot at work, ignoring the confused looks or comments of colleagues. (I still go barefoot at work.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I bought a &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/melodica/&#34;&gt;melodica&lt;/a&gt;, inspired by the amazing performances of &lt;a href=&#34;http://jnote.org/&#34;&gt;James Howard Young&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I took a little vacation, spending some days in New York visiting Nathaniel and Yael and their baby. I finally fulfilled my dream (from before marriage) of taking Abby to Coney Island to walk on the boardwalk and at the beach, eating pizza, and riding the Wonder Wheel, just as I once did when I was six years old.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I started doing research into major home renovations for the summer.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I visited my parents, and my sister Linda and her husband Andre also visited, with my mother throwing a delayed reception at home for the both of us who had gotten married in the past two years. Abby got to meet my parents&amp;rsquo; friends, finally. And I went running with my brother-in-law for the first time! Also, I took Abby to the little park in Ann Arbor where as a too-shy teenager I used to go and sit on a particular bench and wish I were sitting with my dream girl. Mission accomplished!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;june&#34;&gt;June&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;John and I did a tough 19-mile training hike on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rachelcarsontrails.org/rct&#34;&gt;Rachel Carson Trail&lt;/a&gt; and decided we&amp;rsquo;d had enough of that trail, and I decided I was probably not going to do the 35-mile &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rachelcarsontrails.org/rct/challenge&#34;&gt;Rachel Carson Trail Challenge&lt;/a&gt; again (having completed it three times in the past).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;{% img /images/rachel-carson-trail-2011-06-05.jpg John on Rachel Carson Trail %}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby started wearing Vibram FiveFingers more and more for walking and running, and even walking barefoot on the streets (something I had not yet seriously done myself at the time).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I stupidly threw out my back during exercise, and my back took weeks to fully recover (I could still run and hike, but not lift weights). Never again, I hope. I felt like a 90-year-old when my back was hurting constantly.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;We started some home improvement projects.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;july&#34;&gt;July&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started gravitating to almost exclusively body weight &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/strength-training/&#34;&gt;strength training&lt;/a&gt;, as a reaction to my having injured my back earlier.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I went kayaking on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kiskiminetas_River&#34;&gt;Kiski River&lt;/a&gt; with &amp;ldquo;Fireman Steve&amp;rdquo; and the kayaking gang.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;On a longish hike, Abby surprised me by wearing Vibram FiveFingers shoes and they worked great for her, making her much faster and less sore, and I made a note to ditch my trail running shoes (which I had been using for years for hiking) in favor of FiveFingers for my next hike (which I did, and I have not gone back to regular shoes for hiking!).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I finally took Abby to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sandhillberries.com/&#34;&gt;Sand Hill Berries&lt;/a&gt; for tasty pie for the first time, always having intended to take her there when dating, but never having been in the vicinity with her then.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Major home renovation finally began, after much research, and we got electrical upgrade, insulation, and bathroom demolition and rebuilding. Very disruptive to our lives for weeks!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I did another mini-&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sesshin&#34;&gt;sesshin&lt;/a&gt; at CMU.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;After a lifetime of almost never drinking coffee (average of maybe three or four cups a year), I became an avid espresso fan (one small cup a day) as a result of my boss getting a machine at work.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started doing more barefoot running.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;august&#34;&gt;August&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bathroom renovation done at last.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I were regularly hiking in Vibram FiveFingers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;{% img /images/abby-franklin-soup-hike-vibram.jpg Abby and Franklin on Steve&amp;rsquo;s Soup Hike part 3 wearing Vibram FiveFingers %}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby joined me to run in her first ever 5K race, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.runaroundthesquare.com/&#34;&gt;Run Around the Square&lt;/a&gt; in Regent Square (mostly on the trails of Frick Park). What a special day! This race was my first ever 5K race when I started running in races in 2000.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started to learn &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/accordion/&#34;&gt;accordion&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;september&#34;&gt;September&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started running to work two or three times a week.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I ran in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~kalp/PGR/&#34;&gt;CMU SCS Pretty Good Race 5K&lt;/a&gt; together, her second 5K race.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I went to &lt;a href=&#34;http://podcamppittsburgh.com/&#34;&gt;PodCamp Pittsburgh&lt;/a&gt;, and after that, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/22/starting-a-new-web-site/&#34;&gt;I started this blog&lt;/a&gt; and proceeded to maintain a habit of posting every day (a routine that has been modified since then).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;october&#34;&gt;October&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started expanding beyond just writing for my blog, and began contributing to the Web through &lt;a href=&#34;http://twitter.com/franklinchen&#34;&gt;my Twitter account&lt;/a&gt; as well as writing comments on other people&amp;rsquo;s blog posts.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started taking Stanford online classes: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ml-class.org/&#34;&gt;Machine Learning&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.db-class.org/&#34;&gt;Introduction to Databases&lt;/a&gt;. (Blog posts on my experiences to appear soon.) Unfortunately, as a result of the extra time commitment, October through December were quite hectic for me.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I continued to move more toward a paleo diet.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;november&#34;&gt;November&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started playing &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/flute/&#34;&gt;flute&lt;/a&gt; again.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Probably because of fatigue and a compromised immune system, I came down with a skin ailment that I got serious treatment for, but it took almost two months to completely clear up and I spent over a month truly miserable &lt;sup&gt;24&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;7&lt;/sub&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;december&#34;&gt;December&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started playing Baroque flute.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started playing tin whistle.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I prepared for and made it through two music performances, playing recorder and flute (and almost tin whistle).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I ended the year completely exhausted, on the verge of getting sick, and took a long break from blogging.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The final week, Abby and I were on a hectic travel schedule that involved meeting up with her parents, my parents, her sister Carrie, Carrie&amp;rsquo;s boyfriend Alain, Alain&amp;rsquo;s parents, Alain&amp;rsquo;s extended family, my sister Linda, and her husband Andre. I am grateful that we got to meet up with so many people (and arranged for various of the individuals to meet up with various of the others!), but the trip was quite stressful to me, because I was not physically or emotionally prepared for it at all. (I will report later on what I learned from the experience.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2011 was quite a year for me and Abby. We had many changes and adventures in our lives: our home, our diet, our exercise, our outdoors activities, travel. For me, the biggest changes were quitting chess, starting music practice and performance, throwing myself into blogging and tweeting, getting more and more active in local software developer groups, applying new (to me) development tools at work, and in the fall, taking Stanford online courses in computer science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although I ended the year in poor shape, because of being overbooked, I am very excited by how many positive changes took place. I have an entirely new set of plans and priorities to formulate soon for 2012 in collaboration with Abby, in hope of learning from the lessons of my failures and omissions of 2011, and restoring balance.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>