<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Dance on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/dance/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Dance on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/dance/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Revisiting Bach&#39;s Air on G String, from a singing and dancing viewpoint</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/06/10/revisiting-bachs-air-on-g-string-from-a-singing-and-dancing-viewpoint/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jun 2015 23:46:26 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/06/10/revisiting-bachs-air-on-g-string-from-a-singing-and-dancing-viewpoint/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Three years ago, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/14/passion-of-bachs-air-on-the-g-string-three-different-interpretations/&#34;&gt;I wrote a post comparing three very different
performance styles&lt;/a&gt;
for Johann Sebastian Bach&amp;rsquo;s famous music,
&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Air_on_the_G_String&#34;&gt;Air on G String&lt;/a&gt;
and indicating which I preferred.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have received an unexpected number comments over the years, and
thought it was time to write an update of my thoughts in response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Primarily, I am responding to those who (correctly) criticized the
unfortunately chosen exemplar of the style that I preferred. I tried
to find better versions that might illustrate my perceptions. I also
integrated some thoughts based on how I perceive music as a singer and
as a dancer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;better-than-the-rushed-croatian-baroque-ensemble-s-performance&#34;&gt;Better than the rushed Croatian Baroque Ensemble&amp;rsquo;s performance?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I agreed quickly with the first commenters that the Croatian
ensemble&amp;rsquo;s performance was too perfunctory, even downright brutal and
unpleasant in various ways. I wish I had
chosen a better example of what I actually &lt;em&gt;like&lt;/em&gt; rather than &lt;em&gt;prefer
to the other two versions&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I searched YouTube for period-style performances that are
closer to what I envision than either the Croatian ensemble&amp;rsquo;s or
Koopman&amp;rsquo;s. It proved impossible for me to find a perfect performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-period-performance-i-like-more-christopher-hogwood&#34;&gt;A period performance I like more: Christopher Hogwood&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like this version by the late &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christopher_Hogwood&#34;&gt;Christopher Hogwood&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s Academy of
Ancient Music:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/nrtdhH8_47k&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a sweetness and &lt;em&gt;bouncy lightness&lt;/em&gt; to this version that I
like, but it is also somewhat anemic. Personally, I would play up more
contrast and fullness of sound and passion, but the overall tempo and
breathing to this version seems right to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;voices-of-music-richer-sound&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Voices of Music&amp;rdquo;: richer sound&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Voices of Music&amp;rdquo; here in a good performance:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/pzlw6fUux4o&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like the richness of sound in this performance. I miss the lighter,
more bouncy feeling that Hogwood brought out though. This performance
is a bit too legato for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;i-care-about-singing&#34;&gt;I care about singing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I approach this music from the viewpoint of singing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bouncy lightness is very important to me, along with the rhythmic
characterization. I feel this music as a song (it is an &amp;ldquo;air&amp;rdquo;, after
all), and I cannot help singing along when I hear it. Therefore, when
it&amp;rsquo;s taken too slow for me to sing and make it to natural breathing
points in phrases, that considerably lessens my pleasure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;yehudi-menuhin-solo-violin&#34;&gt;Yehudi Menuhin, solo violin&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s an interesting old black and white video of a performance by a young Yehudi Menuhin on violin with
accompaniment. It&amp;rsquo;s not a period performance, but moves along at a
decent &amp;ldquo;singing&amp;rdquo; tempo, as befits violin, that singing instrument.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34;
src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/08bDiKXW0gg&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;
allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I confess that I rather like this performance for its virtues,
although it distorts Bach&amp;rsquo;s music by so emphasizing just the musical
line, at the expense of the balance of the other voices and the
essential character of the dissonances among the voices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;more-menuhin-but-as-conductor&#34;&gt;More Menuhin, but as conductor&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s Yehudi Menuhin not as violin soloist but as conductor of the
Bath Festival Orchestra in 1960. Again, not a period performance, but
he takes the music briskly, and has the violins create sufficient
phrase delineations that I feel the music alertly as though it sings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s direct and clear, maybe not the most subtle and warm,
but I like it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/kaBAE4stNIo&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;dancing-is-possible-too&#34;&gt;Dancing is possible too&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also like to dance to expressive music. A pioneer of modern dance,
Doris Humphrey, famously choreographed a dance to a slowish
performance of this music:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/NjwJyaSIRqY&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not how I would dance to it, because I feel the music
differently. Surprisingly, I could find few examples on YouTube of
dancing to this music. I may consider choreographing a dance myself as
a project to express my own personal vision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing I would like to mention is that I feel that the &lt;em&gt;walking bass&lt;/em&gt;
is very important in this music and gives it the impetus. When played
too slow, the walking bass no longer feels like it&amp;rsquo;s walking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel this music in my legs, not just in my lungs. Yes, I have
actually hummed it to myself while walking in time to the bass
leisurely in the local park. There is a limit to how &amp;ldquo;leisurely&amp;rdquo; I can
walk without feeling frustrated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;ice-dancing&#34;&gt;Ice dancing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found this somewhat frenetic but nevertheless beautiful ice dancing
performance from the 1992 World Figure Skating Championships:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/1JjbwtM_E3g&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;recorder-quartet&#34;&gt;Recorder quartet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A final performance to enjoy: the Japanese &amp;ldquo;Sekishi Recorder Quartet&amp;rdquo;
playing their hearts out in 2009. I think it&amp;rsquo;s lovely: impeccable
phrasing, transparency,
and rich ensemble balance and tone. (As a twist, the melody line performer adds
his own ornamentations.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/pRRRK0UClNs&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was inspired by the accumulated comments on my previous post on
Bach&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Air on G String&amp;rdquo; that I decided to flesh out my thoughts by
using more example performances, as well as relate the orchestral
music to singing and dancing. I hope you have enjoyed these
explorations. There is no single &amp;ldquo;right&amp;rdquo; way to experience music, but
I wanted to share how I experience it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;ve read my previous post, does this one help clarify where
  I&amp;rsquo;m coming from with my musical values? Do you dance
  or sing? Does this affect how you perceive this piece of music and
  like to perform it or hear it performed?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Copland&#39;s Appalachian Spring danced by the orchestra musicians: confronting my memories of boredom four years ago</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/05/28/coplands-appalachian-spring-danced-by-the-orchestra-musicians-confronting-my-memories-of-boredom-four-years-ago/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2014 22:23:26 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/05/28/coplands-appalachian-spring-danced-by-the-orchestra-musicians-confronting-my-memories-of-boredom-four-years-ago/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I follow Greg Sandow&amp;rsquo;s blog on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.artsjournal.com/sandow/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;future of classical music&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. He posted an &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.artsjournal.com/sandow/2014/05/essential-video.html&#34;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; that got me thinking: he was all excited about an unorthodox performance of Aaron Copland&amp;rsquo;s half-hour-long &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Appalachian_Spring&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Appalachian Spring&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; by the University of Maryland Symphony Orchestra in which the students of the orchestra actually moved around and danced as well as played their instruments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a confession to make: back almost four years ago, in November 2010, I went to a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cmu.edu/news/archive/2010/November/nov15_cmunightwithpso.shtml&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Carnegie Mellon Night at the Symphony&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; in which &amp;ldquo;Appalachian Spring&amp;rdquo; was on the program. &lt;strong&gt;I got very bored during the piece.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing to remember is that the orchestra suite was actually arranged by Copland from his original piece that was an actual ballet for Martha Graham! So it&amp;rsquo;s actually kind of unnatural to experience this music &amp;ldquo;purely&amp;rdquo; as music. To me the suite is rather long and redundant without some kind of &amp;ldquo;story&amp;rdquo; to go along with it. So I watched the video of the orchestra-danced performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was definitely more interesting seeing action. At the same time, I got bored eventually anyway, after about 15 minutes. But I lasted longer with the physical action. However, I was also distracted by thoughts of how difficult it must have been for the orchestra to pull this off. I mean, marching band is one thing, but this is an orchestra and there was a ton of choreography and it&amp;rsquo;s not just marching.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s interesting that a commenter on Sandow&amp;rsquo;s blog criticized the
effort, writing: &lt;em&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s nicely done, I suppose, if you must do this
sort of thing. But when I go to an orchestral concert, I&amp;rsquo;m there for
the music, not for this sort of thing. To me, this doesn&amp;rsquo;t tell the
audience &amp;ldquo;this music is worth your time and attention,&amp;rdquo; it tells them
&amp;ldquo;we have so little faith that you’ll enjoy the music that we feel
compelled to trick it out with distractions.&amp;rdquo; I used to sing in a
chorus that was fond of &amp;ldquo;chorusography,&amp;rdquo; and it annoyed me as a
performer, too.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What do you think? Do you like this idea or does it annoy you?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Judge for yourself:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/jGSctM_8K_E&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My first time at an English country dance music jam</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/01/25/my-first-time-at-english-country-dance-music-jam/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Jan 2014 19:39:03 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/01/25/my-first-time-at-english-country-dance-music-jam/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Relatively recently, a new English country dance music jam in the Pittsburgh area has been organized by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amarillismusic.com/aboutus.html&#34;&gt;Maro Avakian&lt;/a&gt;, whom I first met through joining in playing for the Holiday Ball &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/16/playing-recorder-and-flute-at-the-holiday-ball/&#34;&gt;two years ago&lt;/a&gt;. I was unable to make it to the first couple of meetings, but finally, on a nasty snowy Saturday, my schedule happened to be open, so I went.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not completely new to English country dance music. It was almost two years ago when I first encountered it, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/31/my-first-sampling-of-english-country-dance-and-contra-dance/&#34;&gt;as a dancer&lt;/a&gt;. As has happened several times now in my life, becoming familiar with the dance got me interested in the &lt;em&gt;music&lt;/em&gt; and in the idea of actually playing the music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that I&amp;rsquo;d already played some of this kind of music for myself as a result of my study of the Baroque flute, because method books I have for the instrument include a good amount of dance music from the era. In any case, the book we use for many tunes is the volume by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.canispublishing.com/&#34;&gt;Peter Barnes&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://mysite.verizon.net/peterabarnes/books.htm&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Barnes Book of English Country Dance Tunes&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, a fine anthology. Actually, I ordered my copy only last week and was lucky it arrived in the mail just in time!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://mysite.verizon.net/peterabarnes/Book1.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;instruments&#34;&gt;Instruments&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had a pretty good turnout given the weather. Apart from Maro on piano, we had people playing flute, Baroque flute, recorders, ukulele, mandolin, percussion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d brought my flute, Baroque flute, and soprano, alto, tenor recorders, but since there were already two others on modern flute and soprano recorder, I ended up playing just the Baroque flute, alto recorder, and tenor recorder. The Baroque flute is pretty hard to play in some of the keys, and also is kind of soft, so I mostly played the alto and tenor recorders. I gradually gravitated toward improvising inner voices with the tenor recorder. I think I will do that in the future also. In addition, I should bring my bass recorder, to add a yet lower instrument to our group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;improvisation&#34;&gt;Improvisation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had great discussions about tips and tricks for improvising lines and filling out chords. Needless to say, I was botching up a lot of stuff as I experimented, but you can&amp;rsquo;t learn if you don&amp;rsquo;t try!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It looks like I have a new musical outlet, English country dance music. I hope to continue participating in it. As with French traditional dance music, I like the improvisational nature of working with a tune with repetition.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Watching &#34;Hable con ella&#34; (&#34;Talk to her&#34;) (2002): thoughts on art, crime, and ethics</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/12/26/hable-con-ella-talk-to-her-thoughts-on-art/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Dec 2013 10:38:33 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/12/26/hable-con-ella-talk-to-her-thoughts-on-art/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/4/43/Talk_to_Her_English_movie_poster_fairuse.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Talk to her&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;After a decade of putting it off, I finally watched &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pedro_Almod%C3%B3var&#34;&gt;Pedro Almodóvar&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s 2002 film, &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Talk_to_Her&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Hable con ella&amp;rdquo; (&amp;ldquo;Talk to her&amp;rdquo;)&lt;/a&gt;. I was actually on the verge of going to a local movie theater to watch it a decade ago when circumstances in my life changed and I put it on hold. But Abby and I just watched it together, partially because Almodóvar has been on my mind since &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/12/19/appreciating-the-unique-singer-la-lupe/&#34;&gt;I re-listened to some music sung by La Lupe a couple of days ago&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out to be a fantastic film, totally gripping and moving, no slow or pointless moments, really tight. One of my favorite films of all time, surely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was also disturbing on many levels, as great art often is. Abby and I had some conversations about some of the issues, but there was even more still on my mind, so I decided to share them here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: there are some serious &lt;strong&gt;spoilers&lt;/strong&gt; in this post, so if you haven&amp;rsquo;t watched the film yet, please stop reading now and &lt;em&gt;go watch it&lt;/em&gt; first. In any case, I am skipping important plot elements in order to focus on particular themes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-rape&#34;&gt;The rape&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s cut to the chase. In this film, a really weird guy, Benigno, who is depicted as unhealthily obsessed with a young woman ends up being one of her primary caretakers (he is a nurse) in the hospital when she slips into a coma after an accident. When we encounter him in the story, he&amp;rsquo;s already been taking care of her for four years. We see him bathing her and massaging her in a way that might be considered loving and caring, but also creepy and too intimate, especially given how he had secretly stalked her before the whole accident. Everyone thinks he&amp;rsquo;s gay (he lied to fool her father), so nobody seems to seriously question his care of her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the story, we are led to believe (it was not depicted) that during the course of the story, he raped her and got her pregnant. Miraculously, at some point after her pregnancy was discovered, she woke from her four-year coma, but the child was stillborn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;my-reaction&#34;&gt;My reaction&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can go online and see a lot of reactions to this rape, say, the IMDB forums. Some disbelieve, some try to justify her awakening as making up for his crime, others say they refuse to watch the film because they heard what the story is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Myself, I disbelieved at first, despite the very clear signal straight from the film director himself. I thought, maybe it was the other main character, or the other man besides him. I thought this even though I knew it could not be. I found it &lt;em&gt;very interesting&lt;/em&gt; that despite the obvious (except that I didn&amp;rsquo;t see it happen), I &lt;em&gt;did not want to believe&lt;/em&gt; that his man, even though he was clearly weird and inappropriately obsessed with the comatose woman, did this. I examined myself and asked why I did not want to believe. One reason was that other being all weird, he came across as being very gentle and caring, both towards her (taking care of her inert body) and to the other main character Marco, who became a close friend of his. For all we knew, he was still a virgin. And she hadn&amp;rsquo;t gotten pregnant after four years of his care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, my &amp;ldquo;reasoning&amp;rdquo; was completely ridiculous. How did I know that he wasn&amp;rsquo;t molesting her for four years, and just being careful about it, and only accidentally slipping up one night after watching that silent film he talked to her about?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I was very uncomfortable that aspects of his personality and behavior that made me feel sympathetic to him &lt;em&gt;in general&lt;/em&gt; led me to doubt that he was capable of something horrible. This brought up memories of being confused and cynical in the light of revelations in recent years that some people&amp;rsquo;s heroes were in fact very flawed: for example, the big Penn State scandal involving &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jerry_Sandusky&#34;&gt;Jerry Sandusky&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joe_Paterno&#34;&gt;Joe Paterno&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s apparent role in concealing Sandusky&amp;rsquo;s repeated sexual abuse of young boys. Or &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lance_Armstrong&#34;&gt;Lance Armstrong&lt;/a&gt; finally confessing to being a drug doper in sport. Or the history of sexual abuse by priests and other leaders in many religious institutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that I was detached from all those cases, not having any emotional involvement with the &amp;ldquo;heroes&amp;rdquo; in question, so it was easy for me to scoff at those who went out of their way to demonize the victims and proclaim their heroes innocent. So I was pretty disturbed that just through skillful storytelling, the film director here was able, for a split second, to cause me to doubt the obvious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;bullfighting-and-respect-for-different-cultures&#34;&gt;Bullfighting and respect for different cultures&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another thing that disturbed me was the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bullfighting&#34;&gt;bullfighting&lt;/a&gt;. I am hardly a member of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.peta.org/issues/animals-in-entertainment/animals-used-entertainment-factsheets/bullfighting-tradition-tragedy/&#34;&gt;PETA&lt;/a&gt;, but I find bullfighting frightening and perverse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, I am slightly ambivalent about this attitude. But only slightly. OK, it&amp;rsquo;s an important cultural institution in Spain, and I am definitely not one to lightly dismiss long-standing traditions that clearly have served a purpose of some kind over centuries, even millennia. But I&amp;rsquo;m not a relativist who thinks everything&amp;rsquo;s OK somewhere. For example, there are long traditions of human slavery that &amp;ldquo;we&amp;rdquo; (in, say, the US where I live and grew up) consider &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; to be OK, and &amp;ldquo;we&amp;rdquo; believe that women should have the right to vote, that &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Female_genital_mutilation&#34;&gt;female genital mutilation&lt;/a&gt; is unacceptable, that the ancient Chinese &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Foot_binding&#34;&gt;foot binding&lt;/a&gt; of women was an atrocity, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You could argue that it&amp;rsquo;s just sheer cultural conditioning that I happen to believe in what &amp;ldquo;we&amp;rdquo; believe, but nevertheless, I feel justified in my judgment and can&amp;rsquo;t apologize for it. So if you&amp;rsquo;re reading this and you&amp;rsquo;re Spanish and offended, I don&amp;rsquo;t know how to sugarcoat it, but bullfighting freaks me out. The best I can say is, there are probably things I believe in or do that you find disgusting also.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;cognitive-dissonance-and-hypocrisy&#34;&gt;Cognitive dissonance and hypocrisy?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The weird thing is, even as I felt disgust at seeing all the blood during the bullfighting scenes in the film, I felt unease at my participating in a very sanitized version of the whole thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m talking about the ballroom dance &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pasodoble&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;paso doble&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, which is a kind of weird, transformed re-enactment of a bullfight theme. I have never actually danced paso doble in competition, but have practiced basic steps and movements, and have &lt;em&gt;fantasized&lt;/em&gt; about being some kind of macho bullfighter. See, in most of the standard ballroom dances, the focus of display and movement is almost entirely on the follower, the woman. In &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; the paso doble, the man is really the focus, being the bullfighter. (The follower is, bizarrely, his cape: the bull is invisible and only implied.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still periodically do a paso doble &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/13/video-review-dancing-with-the-stars-cardio-dance-2006/&#34;&gt;dance workout&lt;/a&gt;. When I do this dance workout, you can bet I&amp;rsquo;m not thinking about bloody bulls or the possibility of being gored to death. Somehow the whole thing has been sanitized. I feel slightly weird about this &amp;ldquo;Anglo&amp;rdquo; appropriation of a cultural tradition. I would say I feel slightly weird about the other sanitized and standardized Latin ballroom dances too (rumba, cha cha, samba) that have &amp;ldquo;authentic&amp;rdquo; roots from, for example, Cuba and Brazil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I feel only &amp;ldquo;slightly&amp;rdquo; weird, because cultural borrowing and appropriation is something that has always happened. I don&amp;rsquo;t think we can or ought to stop it, any more than I can go around sniffing that a lot of &amp;ldquo;Chinese food&amp;rdquo; in American restaurants is not much like what I know to be more &amp;ldquo;authentic&amp;rdquo;. The best I can do is &lt;em&gt;know the difference&lt;/em&gt;, rather than reject evolution or borrowing of traditions. So, for example, I have watched videos of Cuban salsa, which differs from urban North American studio or club salsa. I did study &amp;ldquo;Argentine tango&amp;rdquo; after engaging in the heavily stylized and very different ballroom tango. I think these can all reasonably coexist, as long as one knows what each is and not pretend something is what it is not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;gender-roles&#34;&gt;Gender roles&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then somehow everything brought me to the issue of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gender_role&#34;&gt;gender roles&lt;/a&gt;. In the film, the bullfighter main character is a woman, Lydia. Unusual. That led me to think about other weird issues I have dealt with concerning ballroom dancing, and couple dancing in general where there is a clear separation between leader and follower. Are these dances a weird kind of anachronism? I have definitely met women who rejected or were openly uneasy about taking part in this kind of dancing, but obviously, as Abby and I have gone out dancing, we know of plenty of women who are OK with it. In fact, we often see women dancing the leader role, and admittedly less often, men dancing the follower role. I tend to think there&amp;rsquo;s not really a problem with this kind of dancing, given that people really can and do switch roles these days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;do-the-ends-justify-the-means&#34;&gt;Do the ends justify the means?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some final thoughts: what happens when we accept that something is disturbing? Especially when we rationalize away our discomfort?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, why did Almodóvar tell a story about a rapist who some would like to say possibly &amp;ldquo;helped&amp;rdquo; a comatose woman awake? What if that were true? Does it make his crime any less bad? And what about intent? Does intent matter in an action? Fodder for your philosophy classes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And what about the film itself? What is the response to those who refuse to watch this film because of a rape? Has Almodóvar committed a crime by making the character a sympathetic, tragic one? Or is this &amp;ldquo;only&amp;rdquo; art? Or is it because it is high art that it is justified?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that reminds me of the controversy over &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roman_Polanski&#34;&gt;Roman Polanski&lt;/a&gt;, many of whose beautiful, profound films I have enjoyed through my life? He fled the US in 1977 after statutory rape of a 13-year-old girl. In 2009 there was controversy after the US tried to extradite him, and a lot of film fans apparently came to his defense. Were they making the mistake of making an allowance for a great film maker that they would not have made for some random guy? Is my continuing to watch his films a crime? Should I be boycotting his films?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of questions, and I think no easy answers. Of course, our actions reveal our implicit answers. What we say does not matter. What we do does.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-science-added-2014-01-05&#34;&gt;The science (added 2014-01-05)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing I forgot to discuss was the matter of whether people in vegetative states are actually aware of what is going on around them. Assuming they have some awareness, that makes a lot of what happened in the film kind of creepy (but also, what happens in real life in hospitals).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a recent post about &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.spring.org.uk/2014/01/patients-in-vegetative-state-can-respond-emotionally-to-loved-ones.php&#34;&gt;emotional awareness in patients in a vegetative state&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2014-04-27&#34;&gt;(Update of 2014-04-27)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A great article on &lt;a href=&#34;http://mosaicscience.com/story/mind-readers&#34;&gt;vegetative states&lt;/a&gt; just came my way, reminding me of the discomfort I felt when watching this film.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, a great film is one that somehow makes me think about life and humanity in the broadest possible ways, even though I didn&amp;rsquo;t really want to. I guess Pedro Almodóvar struck a home run with this film.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not the kind of film I want to watch every night, because then I end up spending hours thinking about stuff. But there it is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Do you find this kind of film too disturbing to watch or to think about? Are you concerned by inaccurate scientific portrayals in film? Are you concerned about films that make you sympathetic toward someone who is not only disturbed but also a criminal?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>100th anniversary: remembering the first time I heard Stravinsky&#39;s &#34;The Rite of Spring&#34;</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/05/29/100th-anniversary-remembering-the-first-time-i-heard-stravinskys-rite-of-spring/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 May 2013 22:52:45 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/05/29/100th-anniversary-remembering-the-first-time-i-heard-stravinskys-rite-of-spring/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s been a crazy amount of media coverage about the 100th anniversary of the performance of Igor Stravinsky&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Rite_of_Spring&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Rite of Spring&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; that caused riots (what great publicity then and even now). I&amp;rsquo;ve been bombarded with a lot of commentary. Some of it was interesting and insightful, but eventually I got tired of reading any further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided to go back to the source, and listen to it again, and also actually &lt;em&gt;watch&lt;/em&gt; it for the first time ever!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-first-time&#34;&gt;My first time&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I totally remember the first time I ever heard excerpts of &amp;ldquo;The Rite of Spring&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was in a music class in college in around 1989 or 1990.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was taking a two-semester music theory course sequence for non-majors. The instructor at one point played back for us excerpts of this music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was very startling music to me, very harsh and chaotic and confusing. I couldn&amp;rsquo;t say I hated it, but I certainly did &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; enjoy it at all. I had a rather conservative musical taste in college.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But you know what, I was quite stimulated in that our instructor didn&amp;rsquo;t require us to love it, but just put it on, showed his enthusiasm, and &lt;em&gt;analyzed&lt;/em&gt; what was going on in some of the music, such as the changing irregular meters; the random accents; the bizarre orchestration; the deliberate violation of conventional harmonic voice leading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Noticing some of the structural characteristics of the music didn&amp;rsquo;t always make them less harsh on my ear, but at least let me understand that this wasn&amp;rsquo;t just noise but was really thought out for a purpose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t voluntarily listen to this music again for another quarter of a century, but those excerpts still stuck in my mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;today-a-quarter-of-a-century-later&#34;&gt;Today, a quarter of a century later&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;ballet&#34;&gt;Ballet&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main thing I decided was to actually watch the music as intended for ballet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;YouTube made this easy. Here&amp;rsquo;s the Joffrey Ballet:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/ewOBXph0hP4&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will confess that watching the ballet made the music much more engaging, because of correlations with action, and especially the drawn out repetitive nature of the music get boring for me in the absence of &amp;ldquo;something&amp;rdquo; going on, a story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was struck by how much I enjoy this music now. The textures Stravinsky creates are fresh and transparent, gorgeous even. The music emerges as though from the world itself. Many moods are portrayed, from the mysterious to the somber to the creepy to the deadly to the ecstatic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s clearly not something I&amp;rsquo;d listen to every day, but I would happily revisit it now and then as I would a favorite film. This music lights my brain on fire!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;computer-animation&#34;&gt;Computer animation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other thing I did was check out a computer animation of the score by Stephen Malinowski, thanks to an &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.npr.org/blogs/deceptivecadence/2013/05/27/186461168/watch-a-mind-blowing-visualization-of-the-rite-of-spring&#34;&gt;NPR blog post I saw mentioning it&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I loved it! Being able to see all the parts and how the voices flow with or against one another gave me a real thrill, an added dimension to just listening. You can see what is regular, what is irregular, what is sheer freedom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;selected-commentary&#34;&gt;Selected commentary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I said I quickly got tired of reading commentary. Nevertheless, here are some interesting links:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.therestisnoise.com/2013/05/rite-100.html&#34;&gt;Alex Ross&amp;rsquo;s blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.npr.org/blogs/deceptivecadence/2013/05/26/186486269/why-jazz-musicians-love-the-rite-of-spring&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Why jazz musicians love The Rite of Spring&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.npr.org/blogs/deceptivecadence/2013/05/24/186443524/the-cocktail-party-guide-to-igor-stravinsky&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Cocktail Party Guide to Igor Stravinsky&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://soundcheck.wnyc.org/2013/may/14/rite-spring/&#34;&gt;Leon Botstein&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.the-tls.co.uk/tls/public/article1275660.ece&#34;&gt;Robert Craft&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was interesting to revisit strange music after a quarter of a century to find that my musical enjoyment had changed considerably. When I was in college, I thought &amp;ldquo;The Rite of Spring&amp;rdquo; was weird; now, I think it is a work of amazing beauty, expression, and creative freedom. Wow. And that was a hundred years ago. How could music ever be the same again after that!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Another exciting concert at Bar Marco: Chris Norman and the Chatham Baroque playing a tasty assortment of dynamic music</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/02/28/another-exciting-concert-at-bar-marco-chris-norman-and-the-chatham-baroque-playing-a-tasty-assortment-of-dynamic-music/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Feb 2013 23:47:52 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/02/28/another-exciting-concert-at-bar-marco-chris-norman-and-the-chatham-baroque-playing-a-tasty-assortment-of-dynamic-music/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Just this week, Annie of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/PittsburghRecorderSociety&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Recorder Society&lt;/a&gt; sent out email reminding us of upcoming musical performances of interest, including some by the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.chathambaroque.org/&#34;&gt;Chatham Baroque&lt;/a&gt; joined by visiting &lt;a href=&#34;http://chrisnorman.com/&#34;&gt;Chris Norman&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://chrisnorman.com/images/home_feature.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Chris Norman&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When I heard that Chris Norman was coming, I frantically started rethinking my schedule for the week, because I really wanted to see him playing his wooden flutes. He has been one of my primary musical heroes since I first encountered him at a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/04/21/my-first-time-in-a-public-music-jam-intense-fun-with-chris-norman-and-david-greenberg/&#34;&gt;public music jam session last year&lt;/a&gt; sponsored by the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rbsp.org/&#34;&gt;Renaissance and Baroque of Pittsburgh&lt;/a&gt;. That day was one of the most important days of my life, which I will never forget, because not only did I see and hear a real master, but also was encouraged to participate myself in playing music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve always also been a big fan of Chatham Baroque, for their lively, alert performances of the standard repertoire as well as &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/10/04/chatham-baroque-thoughts-on-playing-new-non-baroque-music-on-baroque-instruments/&#34;&gt;new collaborations and projects&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I managed to attend one of this week&amp;rsquo;s concerts, and I was not disappointed!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-i-rarely-attend-concerts&#34;&gt;Why I rarely attend concerts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, a reminder: nowadays, I rarely attend concerts (or even listen to recorded music). &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/02/i-love-music-but-rarely-listen-to-it-now/&#34;&gt;I explained why over a year ago&lt;/a&gt;: time is limited (on weekdays and particularly on weekends). Furthermore, when I do attend concerts, I am much pickier about what I attend, because when I think about it, in the past I have often been disappointed by concerts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;bar-marco-and-nature-of-music-venues&#34;&gt;Bar Marco and nature of music venues&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing I came to realize is that the standard &amp;ldquo;classical music&amp;rdquo; concert is not to my taste. First of all, the programs tend to be very long, such as two hours with an intermission, which, frankly, taxes both my attention span as well as takes up an entire block of time in an evening. Second, and most important actually, is that there is a sense of &amp;ldquo;distance&amp;rdquo; and even formality in the standard concert. This is reinforced by certain choices of clothing and demeanor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: I&amp;rsquo;m speaking as one who did not grow up in &amp;ldquo;classical music&amp;rdquo; culture, but only really discovered and fell in love with Western art music upon &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/10/rip-charles-rosen/&#34;&gt;attending college&lt;/a&gt;. So there have always been things about the culture that initially struck me as strange, and are probably at least partially responsible for the relative lack of popularity of the music among younger people (just peek into the average classical music concert hall and you&amp;rsquo;ll see geezers and middle-aged people).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I rather enjoyed the use of Bar Marco last fall as non-traditional music venue, where &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/11/14/classical-revolution-pittsburghs-aquitango-delivers-passionate-traditional-tango/&#34;&gt;I saw AquiTango performing, and sat up close&lt;/a&gt; and enjoyed the relative intimacy and informality of the occasion. Not only that, but from a technical, performance point of view (now that I play music myself), it is extremely educational for me to be up front seeing what the musicians do and relating to it and learning from it, whether it&amp;rsquo;s cues and signals among them or details of physical technique. This is stuff you can&amp;rsquo;t get sitting far away in a big concert hall, and you certainly can&amp;rsquo;t get at all from audio recordings or even videos really. You have to be there, anticipating, thinking actively, hearing the breaths, seeing the faces, in real time. Music is not just sound, not just wave forms or digital bits. It&amp;rsquo;s a live, active creation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I jumped at the opportunity to see &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.showclix.com/event/3745641&#34;&gt;Chris Norman and Chatham Baroque also at Bar Marco&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This venue has its limitations, of course. Primarily, the bar downstairs is very noisy, and it would be nice if there were a barrier to avoid the noise and music blasting downstairs from so easily being heard upstairs. That said, for the most part I wasn&amp;rsquo;t too bothered by the noise, because I sat up front very near the musicians, and so when they were playing, I didn&amp;rsquo;t hear the noise. But in moments of dead silence the distraction was real. I would suggest putting up a temporary barrier at the stairway during performances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-music&#34;&gt;The music&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A single hour of musical selections was presented (a good length for me; as I mentioned earlier, two hours is a very long time).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;scottish-baroque-james-osvald&#34;&gt;Scottish Baroque: James Osvald&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The concert started out with a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scottish_Baroque_music&#34;&gt;Scottish Baroque&lt;/a&gt; sonata by &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_Oswald_%28composer%29&#34;&gt;James Osvald&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was interested to actually see Scottish Baroque music being performed live because up till now, I had only &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/08/finally-performing-some-sonatas-for-baroque-flute/&#34;&gt;played it without listening to it, through a &amp;ldquo;Baroque Around the World&amp;rdquo; series of books&lt;/a&gt;. And I had played it on flute, even though the music was clearly geared toward violin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;instruments&#34;&gt;Instruments&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chris played the same keyed wooden &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.oldflutes.com/classical.htm&#34;&gt;classical flute&lt;/a&gt; for the most part through the concert, although in the slow movement of just this sonata he switched to a deeper alto flute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout the concert, Andrew Fouts played Baroque violin, while Patrician Halverson played different sizes of viola da gamba, and Scott Pauley played theorbo as well as a banjo and a Baroque guitar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;no-program-notes&#34;&gt;No program notes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were no program notes for this concert, by the way: &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/11/on-not-reading-concert-program-notes/&#34;&gt;just how I like it&lt;/a&gt;! Instead, Chris introduced each piece before he and Chatham Baroque performed it. I liked how he added colorful and humorous touches to his brief introductions. &lt;em&gt;All concerts should work this way&lt;/em&gt;. Long program notes are as pointless, in my opinion, as voluminous printed slides at a lecture: they are only a distraction from the presentation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;american-old-time-music&#34;&gt;American old-time music&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then they switched things up and played some American &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Old-time_music&#34;&gt;old-time music&lt;/a&gt;, including &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Man_of_Constant_Sorrow&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Man of Constant Sorrow&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. It was interesting hearing Baroque instruments used for this kind of music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chris was really in his element playing this folk music. He became very expressive and walked around and stamped his feet. You can&amp;rsquo;t experience this kind of concentration and passion just sitting at home listening to some CD or music file: you had to be there, up front! This is what I want to live when I attend a concert.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;back-to-scottish-baroque-william-mcgibbon&#34;&gt;Back to Scottish Baroque: William McGibbon&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another name familiar to me (because of having played on flute one of his sonatas) came up, the Scottish Baroque composer &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_McGibbon&#34;&gt;William McGibbon&lt;/a&gt;. Apparently the composer was inspired by the Italian style and incorporated into his piece, a sonata in the style of Corelli. I think it&amp;rsquo;s important to remember that even back in the 18th century, musicians were eager to learn from their counterparts in remote places in the world. Think of how much effort it took to visit or get word of what was going on in Italy, from Scotland!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;maritime-canada&#34;&gt;Maritime Canada&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then we entered the world of Chris&amp;rsquo;s own heritage: he is from &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Music_of_the_Maritimes&#34;&gt;Maritime Canada&lt;/a&gt;. He did some singing in French as well as flute playing. It was the first time I had ever heard him sing, and it sounded similar to Cajun singing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;back-to-osvald&#34;&gt;Back to Osvald&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then we returned to Osvald, for the &amp;ldquo;Hawthorn&amp;rdquo; sonata. I was very curious to hear this because I had never heard it played, but had &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/08/finally-performing-some-sonatas-for-baroque-flute/&#34;&gt;played it myself on Baroque flute with Henry on piano&lt;/a&gt;, and run into problems because it was clearly meant for violin, given the crazy fast jig movement at the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that Chris took a break and sat out most of this sonata, ha! I enjoyed the opportunity to observe how Andrew on Baroque violin would play the first movement, to compare his style and choice of ornamentations with what I&amp;rsquo;ve done myself. He played it rather differently than how I play it. This is one of the fascinating things I like about Baroque music: there is a good deal of personal choice in how we feel and interpret it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To my amusement, Chris did come in for the brief but crazy fast jig that was the third movement, showing off his triple-tonguing chops on flute. Whew!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;scottish-smallpipes&#34;&gt;Scottish smallpipes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We ended with Chris pulling out his &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scottish_smallpipes&#34;&gt;Scottish smallpipes&lt;/a&gt; and playing on them. I had never seen this instrument before and was fascinated. In contrast to mouth-blown bagpipes, these are played with the arms only. A vigorous conclusion to the concert!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;afterwards&#34;&gt;Afterwards&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I chatted with Chris Norman a little afterwards. He seemed to recognize me from the jam session a year ago; that surprised me since I was just some quiet guy in the crowd who was still quite a beginner and didn&amp;rsquo;t play all that much. Anyway, I told him I was inspired by that jam session to not only play more traditional music of the kind that he plays (I got into Irish and French, buying myself an &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/irish-flute/&#34;&gt;Irish flute&lt;/a&gt;), but also improving my technique considerably on &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/baroque-flute/&#34;&gt;Baroque flute&lt;/a&gt;. I asked him about his new work on making wooden flutes; I thought it was really cool that he not only plays them, but now makes them too, and why not, if you&amp;rsquo;re interested in the engineering aspects of creating the kind of sounds you want? This utter physicality of (non-digital) music is something that I&amp;rsquo;ve come to particularly appreciate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a really great time at the concert at Bar Marco by Chris Norman and Chatham Baroque. I left inspired again to continue my own music-making and improve on it and incorporate my own personality into it, the way these fine musicians do. It was an hour well-spent.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pittsburgh Contras and Squares Holiday Ball 2012</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/12/14/pittsburgh-contras-and-squares-holiday-ball-2012/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Dec 2012 23:50:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/12/14/pittsburgh-contras-and-squares-holiday-ball-2012/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/holiday-ball-2012/grand-march.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Grand March&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So this year I joined Abby again to play in the &amp;ldquo;Holiday Ball Orchestra&amp;rdquo; as I had &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/16/playing-recorder-and-flute-at-the-holiday-ball/&#34;&gt;done for the first time last year&lt;/a&gt;, for the annual &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/pages/Pittsburgh-Holiday-Ball/283731778337030&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Contras and Squares Holiday Ball&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My experience at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/events/383908395031216/&#34;&gt;this year&amp;rsquo;s event&lt;/a&gt; compared to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/events/308706299154491/&#34;&gt;last year&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/a&gt;, and thoughts about the future:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;preparation&#34;&gt;Preparation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, I was much more &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/11/24/preparing-to-play-irish-flute-in-the-holiday-ball/&#34;&gt;prepared&lt;/a&gt; this second time than the first time. Not only have I been playing any music at all for an entire extra year, but also, I had prior knowledge of and access to most of the music that is played every year, so I could start my practice well before the event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;costumes&#34;&gt;Costumes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby wanted me to dress up again. Since people enjoyed my wearing red pants last year, I wore them again this year. I was tired of the whole green thing, however, and so I wore a pink shirt and red vest to go all out on the red theme. I added a sport jacket also, one that had been too big for me my whole life till now; it turns out that my blazer that I wore last year is too small now, as my chest has noticeably expanded in the past year (probably because of weight lifting, posture changes, and playing wind instruments). I added a beret that I&amp;rsquo;d never worn before.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/holiday-ball-2012/franklin.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Abby came up with her own colorful outfit.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/holiday-ball-2012/abby-octave-mandolin.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;venue&#34;&gt;Venue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was afraid that Swisshelm Park Community Center would be super cold again like last year, but I did bring my Handeze fingerless gloves just in case. It turned out that the place was warm (it&amp;rsquo;s been a very warm &amp;ldquo;winter&amp;rdquo;), and so I did not have any problems feeling cold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;on-stage&#34;&gt;On stage&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year I think there were somewhat fewer musicians in the Holiday Ball Orchestra than last year. I thought this was actually a good thing. Last year there were some real problems with space and also with ensemble balance (there were a whole lot of violins last year, for example).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;instruments&#34;&gt;Instruments&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I brought my modern flute, wooden keyless Irish flute, and tin whistle. Last year I had played primarily recorder, but this year I chose not to play recorder at all: the Irish flute was what I wanted to use as much as possible for this music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also brought my melodica! I had practiced playing the Hallelujah Chorus part of the Grand March using it and was excited to make my melodica debut. I also planned to use it in some of the Christmas songs, such as &amp;ldquo;Frosty the Snowman&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby brought an &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Octave_mandolin&#34;&gt;octave mandolin&lt;/a&gt; she had been borrowing. She started playing mandolin just this year, and octave mandolin just in the past couple of weeks, I think. This instrument is so much better suited to the music, she says, than her tamburitza she played last year.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/holiday-ball-2012/instruments.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Our instruments&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Several &amp;ldquo;kazumpets&amp;rdquo; (kazoo trumpets) were also provided by Lynette and Jim, and passed out to whoever wanted to play them during certain songs. Abby took one.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/holiday-ball-2012/abby-kazumpet.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby with kazumpet&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;dancing&#34;&gt;Dancing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since Abby and I have now actually done some &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/10/07/my-first-contra-dance-workshop-unexpected-fun/&#34;&gt;contra dancing together&lt;/a&gt;, there was a question of whether we would do any dancing. Abby and I discussed this before the event; Abby was very excited to play music on octave mandolin, and so she did not want to dance, so we did no dancing. Like I said last year: &amp;ldquo;We can always dance some other time.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the other musicians were very excited about dancing and pre-arranged to spend one half or the other of the time dancing instead of playing music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I saw a lot of familiar faces among the dancers, thanks to having met some of them when doing French and contra dances at CMU, and others I met from non-dance contexts elsewhere in the past year in Pittsburgh. It was nice to see my friend Henry and his girlfriend Gina at the dance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;off-and-running&#34;&gt;Off and running&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marlin was the caller again as usual and the evening proceeded with the Grand March and then the whole big assortment of jigs, reels, waltzes, Christmas songs, and a couple of interesting new pieces for this year.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/holiday-ball-2012/grand-march.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Grand March&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t have additional interesting photos or videos to share from during the event, because I took none: after the initial Grand March, I was entirely focused just on playing music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;overall-experience&#34;&gt;Overall experience&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was far less nervous than I was last year. Also, I positioned myself near, rather than deliberately far away from, a microphone, in order to be more audible. I don&amp;rsquo;t actually know what I sounded like, but some dancers during intermission commented that they liked the sound of the wooden Irish flute, so I guess it must have been audible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Playing music for hours is tiring, especially when it is so fast and there are so many notes. Of course, nobody is required to play all the notes all the time. I picked and chose when to take breaks, typically alternating repeats or entire sections. And there is definitely a limit to how long I can play flutes before my mouth gives up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the second half, a guy who had danced during the first half played a keyed Irish flute and tin whistle with us. I hadn&amp;rsquo;t seen him at the two of three rehearsals I had attended, so I hadn&amp;rsquo;t known someone else would be playing those instruments. As a result, I changed some things up in the second half, by playing the tin whistle sometimes when he was playing the flute, and vice versa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did play the melodica as planned, but noticed that the intonation was poor in the lower notes, so I backed off. I&amp;rsquo;ll have to fix this problem before I do more melodica playing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I chose not to force myself to &amp;ldquo;achieve&amp;rdquo; some of the &amp;ldquo;goals&amp;rdquo; I set last year, which were to do some solos and nontrivial ornamentation/improvisation. I felt that because of the natural of my musical focus all this year, I hadn&amp;rsquo;t had time to devote to getting good enough to really justify taking the spotlight for some tunes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The music is still crazy fast: I am still not able to play everything quite properly at the appropriate tempo. Frustrating, but that&amp;rsquo;s OK. I expect to continue to improve my technique; I&amp;rsquo;m already so much better than I was last year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I very much enjoyed performing for the Holiday Ball this year. And I feel like the Holiday Ball Orchestra sounded better this year than we did last year, and some dancers remarked on this also. I think there are several reasons for this. One is that we had some people coming back for the second time (like me), much improved. Another is that there were slightly fewer people, which I think creates a tighter ensemble.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;goals-for-the-future&#34;&gt;Goals for the future&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right now, I&amp;rsquo;m just totally exhausted and happy to be done with music performance of any kind this year. It&amp;rsquo;s been a very tough week, a very tough month, and a very tough two months in my life, with all the things that piled up on me since the end of October.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because December always ends up being so frantic for me, for next year I need to better plan what activities I pursue during this time of year. Last year, I was totally set on playing again this year in the Holiday Ball. Now, I am not sure whether I will continue for next year. It&amp;rsquo;s a question of priorities, and I need to plan what I will be doing next year in December. If I do it again next year, then clearly I want to be doing some solos!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;thank-yous&#34;&gt;Thank yous&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, I have to thank Lynette for organizing the music scores and putting it into booklets for everyone. Jim made the kazumpets. Donna, Allison, and Maro led the rehearsals as well as conducted and played their instruments with enthusiasm; I&amp;rsquo;ve been really happy to have met them a year ago, because I&amp;rsquo;ve been encountering them in other musical contexts in Pittsburgh in the past year too!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We play for the dancers, and so I really appreciate it when they take note of our playing and respond to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And none of this would happened without Abby, who got me into the whole scene in the first place. I&amp;rsquo;ve met so many musicians and dancers, and tried out different instruments and musical styles and dances in the past year, thanks to Abby!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dan Possumato and friends playing Irish, Scottish, French music</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/11/25/dan-possumato-and-friends-playing-irish-scottish-french-music/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Nov 2012 21:42:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/11/25/dan-possumato-and-friends-playing-irish-scottish-french-music/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/dan-possumato/flyer.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;World Kaleidoscope Flyer&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Abby and I checked out a musical performance at the Carnegie Library of Pittsburgh, main branch. They have a regular Sunday afternoon &amp;ldquo;World Kaleidoscope&amp;rdquo; series featuring world sounds from local musicians: two months ago I reported on some delightful &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/23/living-appalachian-music-of-southwestern-pennsylvania/&#34;&gt;local Appalachian music&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.carnegielibrary.org/events/details.cfm?event_id=69116&#34;&gt;Today&amp;rsquo;s performance&lt;/a&gt; was by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.danpossumato.com&#34;&gt;Dan Possumato&lt;/a&gt; and friends, featuring mostly Irish music, with Dan on button accordion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had a good time. Among the selections:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scottish music&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Irish jigs and reels&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Irish waltz &amp;ldquo;Planxty Irwin&amp;rdquo; that Abby and I danced to&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a French &lt;a href=&#34;http://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hanter-dro&#34;&gt;hanter dro&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/dan-possumato/back.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;View from back&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/dan-possumato/right.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;View from right&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/dan-possumato/dan-possumato.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Dan Possumato&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Preparing to play Irish flute in the Holiday Ball</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/11/24/preparing-to-play-irish-flute-in-the-holiday-ball/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Nov 2012 20:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/11/24/preparing-to-play-irish-flute-in-the-holiday-ball/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://pittsburghcontra.org/wp-content/uploads/2011/12/contra_header21.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Pittsburgh Contras and Squares&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A very important event for me last year was joining Abby in playing music at the annual &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburghcontra.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Contras and Squares&lt;/a&gt; Holiday Ball at the Swisshelm Park Community Center as part of the &amp;ldquo;Holiday Ball Orchestra&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I started to prepare to play music for the Holiday Ball (Friday, December 14) again: I have three weeks to practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What progress have I made in the past year on the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/16/playing-recorder-and-flute-at-the-holiday-ball/&#34;&gt;goals I listed after last year&amp;rsquo;s event&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;improvement-at-instruments&#34;&gt;Improvement at instruments&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, I wrote: &amp;ldquo;I want to be much better at all the instruments I would play in it (recorder, flute, tin whistle)&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My status this year:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m better at &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/recorder/&#34;&gt;recorder&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m much better at &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/flute/&#34;&gt;flute&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve only barely worked on &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/tin-whistle/&#34;&gt;tin whistle&lt;/a&gt;, but am automatically better at it because of getting better at other instruments.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I unexpectedly got an &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/irish-flute/&#34;&gt;Irish flute&lt;/a&gt;, which I have mostly been playing for &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/french-dance/&#34;&gt;French dance&lt;/a&gt;, but which &lt;strong&gt;I intend to be my main instrument for the Holiday Ball&lt;/strong&gt;!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From a sound and style point of view, the Irish flute is clearly the best of my instruments to use for the Holiday Ball. So I read through my copies of the Holiday Ball music (lots of jigs, reels, waltzes) tonight at speed, to see where I stand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, I could play (on any instrument) barely any of the music at speed, even on my best instrument at the time, which was soprano recorder. I was reduced to sitting out some tunes or playing just a single note each measure, when I otherwise would have been unable to continue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, I found that I could get through most of the selections OK at speed, but somewhat sloppily and inaccurately. I would &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; be happy to have to perform this music at speed tonight; I would rather sit out or simplify rather than try to play something beyond me. But I have three weeks to improve significantly, and I believe I can improve enough that when the time comes, I won&amp;rsquo;t be sitting out most of the tunes the way I kind of did last year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the fingering of the tin whistle is the same as for my keyless Irish flute, I can also choose to use the tin whistle where I feel appropriate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;microphone&#34;&gt;Microphone&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, I wrote: &amp;ldquo;I want to be proficient and confident enough to sit by a microphone&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea of being in the foreground is still a bit daunting to me, but I think after I get in some good practice over the next week or so, I&amp;rsquo;ll feel confident about not just being in the background the way I was last year. I do think it would be nice to have an audible Irish flute in our performance for the dancers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;solos&#34;&gt;Solos&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, I wrote: &amp;ldquo;I want to do some solos, with stylistically appropriate improvisations&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even scarier. I&amp;rsquo;ve been working through &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/_posts/2012/06/12/ordered-the-casey-burns-small-handed-irish-flute/&#34;&gt;Grey Larsen&amp;rsquo;s book&lt;/a&gt;, which is amazingly detailed and good, but as Irish music has &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; at all been my focus during this year of music for me, I&amp;rsquo;m nowhere at the level of passing for a traditional Irish musician. Still, there is time to work up a sound basic practical level of ornamentation, I think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll have to evaluate, after a week or two, what I feel comfortable doing on stage. The basic rule is: better to play an melody simply and beautifully, unornamented, rather than do something badly and in poor taste and technique!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;dance&#34;&gt;Dance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, I wrote: &amp;ldquo;Maybe I should learn some of the dances and perform some too&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that in fact, I did learn some &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/10/07/my-first-contra-dance-workshop-unexpected-fun/&#34;&gt;contra dance&lt;/a&gt;, so depending on how Abby would like to split up playing music and dancing, I would be, unlike last year, totally up for participating as a dancer as well as a musician.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a lot of fun playing music at the Holiday Ball last year and hope to enjoy it again, and this time with a higher level of musicality and a higher level of contribution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re in the Pittsburgh area and like contra dancing, make sure to put Friday, December 14 on your calendar already, and come to the Holiday Ball!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Classical Revolution: Pittsburgh&#39;s AquiTango delivers passionate traditional tango</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/11/14/classical-revolution-pittsburghs-aquitango-delivers-passionate-traditional-tango/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Nov 2012 20:48:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/11/14/classical-revolution-pittsburghs-aquitango-delivers-passionate-traditional-tango/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;So I got word of a relatively new movement called &lt;a href=&#34;http://classicalrevolution.org/&#34;&gt;Classical Revolution&lt;/a&gt; that is spreading &lt;a href=&#34;http://classicalrevolution.org/chapters/&#34;&gt;around the world&lt;/a&gt;, and has reached Pittsburgh, which has its &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.classicalrevolutionpgh.org/&#34;&gt;own chapter&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/classicalrevolutionpgh&#34;&gt;Facebook page&lt;/a&gt;). The point of Classical Revolution is to &lt;a href=&#34;http://classicalrevolution.org/about/&#34;&gt;perform chamber music in non-traditional settings&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;tango&#34;&gt;Tango&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I saw that the local Pittsburgh tango group &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.aquitango.com/&#34;&gt;AquiTango&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/AquiTango&#34;&gt;Facebook page&lt;/a&gt;) was &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/events/380553315352985/&#34;&gt;going to perform&lt;/a&gt; at &lt;a href=&#34;http://barmarcopgh.com/&#34;&gt;Bar Marco&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AquiTango was to perform traditional &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Argentine_tango&#34;&gt;Argentine tango&lt;/a&gt; music. I had actually encountered, a decade ago, an earlier incarnation (with some member changes since then) of the group, when I was taking Argentine tango classes and dancing; it was formerly Tangueros de Ley. I remember when Julieta Ugartemendia was in the group, playing clarinet and singing, and she also danced! In any case, the group has been revived after she left, as a quartet.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://lh5.ggpht.com/hopUhptskdqtJ-rQfGKZ2awY2KUwuQS9waErFnvkkmdrot9eRTguZRgn--7a8JHRNfGuU2R73hzDssjWGfO5=s615&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;AquiTango&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I decided to attend, not only to check out what the experience of &amp;ldquo;Classical Revolution&amp;rdquo; in such a venue is like, but also for my own special reason: to be inspired by some good tango performances, because I am actually planning to soon play tango on flute and also sing it for the first time!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So here&amp;rsquo;s my review of the concert.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2012-11-17&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-11-17)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/11/17/a-childhood-dream-come-true-i-am-now-finally-singing-for-real/&#34;&gt;Three days later, I did in fact perform tango, at a party!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-venue&#34;&gt;The venue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second floor of Bar Marco is a nice place for chamber music. Not too big, not too small. The musicians play near the windows, while the audience is seated in folding chairs. Wine was available for those who wanted it (I chose not to have any).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-concert&#34;&gt;The concert&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;dancers&#34;&gt;Dancers?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although I am no longer part of the local tango dance community, I could tell as people arrived that some of them knew each other and were dancers. During the concert, it was easy to tell who were the dancers, because they couldn&amp;rsquo;t keep still and fidgeted in their seats or tapped out rhythms. (OK, I kind of did that too.) I was a little surprised that nobody just got up and danced. Maybe there weren&amp;rsquo;t quite enough dancers, or maybe they thought it was a more formal kind of event at which dancing would not have been appropriate. It was definitely a &amp;ldquo;chamber music recital&amp;rdquo; kind of atmosphere rather than a dance atmosphere. That was fine, but I did miss seeing a little bit of dancing. (Or maybe people were dancing at the back whom I didn&amp;rsquo;t see; I was sitting near the front to better see and hear the musicians.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;musicians-and-music&#34;&gt;Musicians and music&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The quartet (keyboard, violin, bass, accordion/voice) seemed to be having fun playing in this environment. The vibe was fairly informal, with a lot of smiling and banter. They played a lot of classic tangos, waltzes, and milongas, including some I had practiced myself at home, such as &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Por_una_Cabeza&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Por una Cabeza&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed how Ernesto Contenti, who is originally from Argentina actually, talked about his history and the songs he sang (he both sang and played the accordion). He said that when he was growing up, tango was just old-people stuff, and it barely even registered in his youthful existence. It was only after he had left the country and then encountered the passion for tango elsewhere that he really discovered the music of his homeland! When he sang the classic &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mi_Buenos_Aires_querido_(song)&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Mi Buenos Aires querido&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, it seemed to ring out in a deeply personal way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The violinist, Maureen Conlon-Gutierrez, is originally from Mexico, and her classical training showed in the brilliance and polish of her play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bassist, Jose Puentes, providing the foundation for the quartet, is from Venezuela.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pianist, Tom Roberts, joked about his non-Latin heritage, being a local. They have a nickname for him, &amp;ldquo;El Cacho&amp;rdquo;. His keyboard playing was particularly lively and adventurous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AquiTango at some point played some non-traditional pieces also. I enjoyed the added variety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;after-the-concert&#34;&gt;After the concert&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had to leave immediately after the concert, because of many things to do this busy week. It would have been nice to stay and chat with the musicians and other audience members; I saw a lot of people going up to the musicians to chat. One thing great about this informal &amp;ldquo;Classical Revolution&amp;rdquo; format is that there is not as much &amp;ldquo;distance&amp;rdquo; between the performers and audience as in a traditional venue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I left feeling excited about my plans to perform tango music soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;some-videos-online&#34;&gt;Some videos online&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a recent sample of AquiTango in action, performing the tango classic &amp;ldquo;La Cumparsita&amp;rdquo;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/zHaasDMVYYo&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is an older sample of AquiTango, playing on the street in Squirrel Hill:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/6u6RO8c5b8I&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re in the Pittsburgh area and looking for some live traditional tango music performed with precision and fire, check out the AquiTango quartet!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-02-28&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-02-28)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went to Bar Marco again for &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/02/28/another-exciting-concert-at-bar-marco-chris-norman-and-the-chatham-baroque-playing-a-tasty-assortment-of-dynamic-music/&#34;&gt;another enjoyable music performance&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>French music jam with unexpected new musicians</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/10/15/french-music-jam-with-unexpected-new-musicians/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Oct 2012 23:45:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/10/15/french-music-jam-with-unexpected-new-musicians/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Tonight was my fourth participation in &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/28/another-french-music-jam-also-announcing-cats-dance/&#34;&gt;Lisa&amp;rsquo;s French traditional dance music jam&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The evening started quietly, because only Lisa and John and I were present at first, and nobody else. Apparently people were either in classes or had other engagements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We always love having more people join us in making music, so it was great that unexpectedly, we got two people into playing with us before I had to leave after two hours! So where did they come from?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;three-of-us&#34;&gt;Three of us&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it was just the three of us, Lisa and John played over some new tunes they had worked on earlier, so that I could pick them up. I&amp;rsquo;m much better now at learning music by ear. I&amp;rsquo;m still not very fast at picking up tunes, but I&amp;rsquo;m definitely better. Furthermore, although they had scribbled down some scores on paper to keep track of the different new songs, I found the handwritten attempts sufficiently difficult to decipher that I chose to completely ignore them. This is a new attitude for me: in the past, I would have scrambled to get a written score if possible. Now, I&amp;rsquo;ve grown used to doing without, and not worrying about making mistakes or learning more slowly than if I had a score. It took me &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/05/14/playing-french-music-for-first-time-and-dancing-blues-for-first-time/&#34;&gt;five months&lt;/a&gt; to reach this point of relative comfort with uncertainty, confusion, and imperfection, ha!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;dancers&#34;&gt;Dancers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Very few dancers showed up at all during the evening. As a result, the ones that did show up expecting to dance started watching us continue to play music instead. But then John started saying, &amp;ldquo;Hey, grab an instrument and join us!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Someone I hadn&amp;rsquo;t met before, Georgia, had started learning some chords on mandolin recently, and she got sucked into joining us as John handed her his mandolin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later, Leslie arrived. She regularly attends to dance. Since there were hardly any dancers around, we said, hey, want to play? John pointed to two banjo cases he had on the floor, so she went and tried one banjo and then switched to the other, and the next thing we knew, we were all playing together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Georgia and Leslie do play other musical instruments and sing, but they just happen not to &amp;ldquo;really&amp;rdquo; play mandolin or banjo. I thought it was pretty cool that the unfortunate lack of dancers led to their unexpectedly joining us as musicians. I guess we&amp;rsquo;ll see whether they start playing more with us!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The small number of musicians and dancers might have made the evening less interesting than past sessions, but it was great that we spontaneously added to our musical group for the evening.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My first contra dance workshop: unexpected fun!</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/10/07/my-first-contra-dance-workshop-unexpected-fun/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Oct 2012 21:19:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/10/07/my-first-contra-dance-workshop-unexpected-fun/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/first-contra-dance/motion.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Dancers in motion&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Today Abby and I attended the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/events/374623475947550/&#34;&gt;first CMU contra dance workshop&lt;/a&gt; put on by the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/catsdancepgh&#34;&gt;Carnegie Alliance of Traditional and Social Dance&lt;/a&gt;, as I mentioned we might when I wrote about the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/28/another-french-music-jam-also-announcing-cats-dance/&#34;&gt;formation of CATS Dance&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have to understand that for years I &lt;em&gt;resisted&lt;/em&gt; the idea of ever doing contra dancing. I had some bad memories of being forced to do a bit of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Square_dance&#34;&gt;square dancing&lt;/a&gt; in elementary school, I have a tendency to resist choreographed patterns, and frankly, I associated contra dancing with old, maybe clumsy people. In the past year, having met plenty of people who mentioned doing contra dancing, and who clearly are not old and clumsy (some are old but far from clumsy), I&amp;rsquo;d gotten interested in giving it a try.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The seed was first planted just from happening to get pulled into &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/11/learning-another-instrument-the-tin-whistle/&#34;&gt;playing music for contra dancing ten months ago&lt;/a&gt;. But I didn&amp;rsquo;t act on it, other than participating a little bit impromptu &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/31/my-first-sampling-of-english-country-dance-and-contra-dance/&#34;&gt;at a birthday party&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I finally went for a full four-hour workshop, held at CMU.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a great time, way beyond my expectations!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;turnout&#34;&gt;Turnout&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The turnout was great. I estimate there were about thirty to forty participants. Most of them appeared to be undergrad or grad students; others were older people, many of whom Abby and I already knew from elsewhere, including the &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/french-dance/&#34;&gt;French dance workshops we&amp;rsquo;ve attended in the past several months&lt;/a&gt;. The predominance of young people was a good sign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;caller&#34;&gt;Caller&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.cdss.org/system/html/gayefifer-579cfde1.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Gaye Fifer&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We were really blessed today to have a great caller, &lt;a href=&#34;http://wa64.com/Waltz.html&#34;&gt;Gaye Fifer&lt;/a&gt;, who is not only clear in her instruction and calling, but also was always very observant and helpful to anyone who was in her line of sight. Whenever I was near her and messing up, she noticed and efficiently got me back on track. She did that for everyone, not just me. Given the size of the crowd, I found that care and attention to detail really impressive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gaye made the whole learning experience effective, friendly, and joyful!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;band&#34;&gt;Band&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/first-contra-dance/gallimaufry.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Gallimaufry&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We also had a fantastic live band, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/gallimaufryband&#34;&gt;Gallimaufry&lt;/a&gt;, from Oberlin. This is a group of five youthful and very skilled musicians playing a whole bunch of instruments. I saw fiddle, cello, electric guitar, accordion, piano, drums.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They played with great rhythm and sheer exuberance and expression, and seamless ensemble work. Wow. They were rocking out. They knew how to ramp it up to get the dancers moving and smiling!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;participants&#34;&gt;Participants&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The energy level and enthusiasm of the dancers today was great. I have been in dance situations in which some of the dancers were not fully engaged, not really getting into the music or the movement, or choosing to remain distant with those they rotated around to dance with. I think it&amp;rsquo;s really important, for this kind of dance to work, for everyone to be fully present and open to the experience, and open to dancing with everyone else. It&amp;rsquo;s a communal experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a mix of beginners (like myself) as well as those who clearly already knew what they were doing. This was actually very helpful because those who knew what they were doing kept the rest of us on the right track, both through personal example and through verbal and physical reminders of what to do. As a result, typically after repeating a pattern ten times (down one end of the room to the next and then back) while the music went on and on, I was able to improve during each iteration to the point that by the end of each dance we learned, I more or less knew what to do and how to do it (not that I necessarily remembered it exactly or executed it smoothly).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, I got pretty sweaty during the four-hour workshop. It was intense. This isn&amp;rsquo;t just shuffling around: it&amp;rsquo;s real exercise, with the music being lively and everyone being in constant motion. I was starving and dehydrated after the first two hours!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;watching&#34;&gt;Watching&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/first-contra-dance/abby-david.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby partnering with David&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There was a snack break halfway through, but I took other breaks to catch my breath and rest my mind, since the dances got progressively more complicated and faster (counting in four rather than eight, for example, and traveling more). It was fun to take a break and watch people dance, because the more experienced dancers added their own ornaments and spins and looked so smooth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the caller pointed out, the subtlety and the fun in contra dancing comes from making all the &lt;em&gt;transitions&lt;/em&gt; smooth and coordinated. I have a lot of work to do to continue improving, but during the hours of the workshop as I learned to be more aware of my immediate circle and relative positions and movements, I got a real sense of how I could really improve my experience of and enjoyment of contra dance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;french-dance-during-break&#34;&gt;French dance during break&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, during the break, Lisa taught some basic French dance to those who just couldn&amp;rsquo;t get too much dancing. Hopefully this will translate into increased participation in the upcoming French dance workshops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;waltzes&#34;&gt;Waltzes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a nice typical touch, each of the two sets were concluded with a waltz. Abby and I enjoyed the opportunity to dance together, just the two of us, during the waltzes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-next&#34;&gt;What next?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I have known for a while, of course, about the regular &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburghcontra.org/&#34;&gt;Friday night contra dance by the Pittsburgh Contras and Squares&lt;/a&gt;. That&amp;rsquo;s not a great time and day, unfortunately, because going out late on a Friday night does not appeal to me. I like the weekend afternoon schedule of the CMU French and contra dance workshops, currently held 4-7 PM. Being held at CMU also has the large advantages of being very close to home as well as encouraging a good turnout of young people to keep the energy up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the current CMU schedule continues, that makes it much more likely that we&amp;rsquo;ll continue to do French and contra dancing regularly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, I expect to play music at the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/16/playing-recorder-and-flute-at-the-holiday-ball/&#34;&gt;annual holiday ball&lt;/a&gt; again this year. This time, I am sure I will have no fear about maybe taking part in the dancing!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had an unforgettable dance experience today. I never expected to enjoy contra dancing so much, but because of how friendly all of the workshop participants were, and the caller, and the amazing band, I feel like I now have a taste of why people do this, and I hope to do more!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Another French music jam; also, announcing CATS Dance</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/09/28/another-french-music-jam-also-announcing-cats-dance/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Sep 2012 20:55:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/09/28/another-french-music-jam-also-announcing-cats-dance/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://thebridge.cmu.edu/images/W170xL170/0/noshadow/Organization/603b06cbdc7847018dce159a5ed99543.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;CATS Dance photo&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;On Monday I participated for my third time in Lisa&amp;rsquo;s French traditional dance music jam.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/08/27/my-second-french-music-jam-playing-my-irish-flute-in-public-for-the-first-time/&#34;&gt;Last time&lt;/a&gt;, I started playing my &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/irish-flute/&#34;&gt;Irish flute&lt;/a&gt; at the jam, continued playing my &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/baroque-flute/&#34;&gt;Baroque flute&lt;/a&gt;, and left my modern flute at home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This time, I changed things up. Also, we got a new musician playing a new instrument!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;instruments-and-musicians&#34;&gt;Instruments and musicians&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lisa was on fiddle as usual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we had John, who brought and used various kinds of accordions and his mandolin. (He had also brought recorders, in case I wanted to play with him, but I did not bring my recorders.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Allison was on piano.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Donna was on fiddle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most exciting to me was that Cindy came and played &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Autoharp&#34;&gt;autoharp&lt;/a&gt;. I think the addition of the harmonic accompaniment and countermelodies she provided was really nice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-instruments&#34;&gt;My instruments&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; bring my Baroque flute this time. I made a decision this week that I was no longer going to try to play my Baroque flute in most public situations. I have been frustrated that its soft sound gets drowned out by other instruments and just by people talking and socializing at parties. Therefore, when playing the Baroque flute in public, I will reserve it for very quiet performance situations only.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did bring my Irish flute, which served well when we were playing in appropriate keys.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have begun caving in and bringing my modern flute. It can be played more easily in all kinds of keys, and has the power to actually be heard. Maybe one day I&amp;rsquo;ll have a keyed wooden flute to play traditional music on, but that day is not near at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So after some experimentation, I believe I&amp;rsquo;m come to the right instrument(s) for different situations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;carnegie-alliance-of-traditional-and-social-dance-cats-dance&#34;&gt;Carnegie Alliance of Traditional and Social Dance (CATS Dance)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d like to take this opportunity to promote the new CMU-based dance group, the &lt;a href=&#34;http://thebridge.cmu.edu/organization/catsdance&#34;&gt;Carnegie Alliance of Traditional and Social Dance&lt;/a&gt;. Check out also their &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/catsdancepgh&#34;&gt;Facebook page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This group has been formed in order to grow a local community of people interested in all kinds of traditional and social dance, French dance being just one example; contra dancing and other folk dancing are also being explored.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In particular, this group exists because there is increasing interest among young people in these kinds of dances and music. The Pittsburgh dance scene has sometimes been dominated by older people, and it&amp;rsquo;s good to get younger people involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last week CATS Dance organized an outing to the regular &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburghcontra.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Contras and Squares&lt;/a&gt; Friday dance. Tomorrow there will be a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/events/105195582969170/&#34;&gt;French dance workshop and social dance&lt;/a&gt; held directly on CMU campus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These workshops and dances are, of course, open to everyone, not just CMU students. Abby and I are not CMU students, but &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/01/23/discovering-french-traditional-dance-in-pittsburgh/&#34;&gt;started attending&lt;/a&gt; these workshops at CMU in January. All ages and levels of dancers are always welcome! If you&amp;rsquo;re curious, drop by and check it out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first contra dance workshop to be hosted at CMU has also already been scheduled, for Sunday, October 7. Since I&amp;rsquo;ve never been to a contra dance workshop (although I had a sampling of contra dance at a birthday party &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/31/my-first-sampling-of-english-country-dance-and-contra-dance&#34;&gt;six months ago&lt;/a&gt;; I was very confused by it then), I hope Abby and I will make it to this workshop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2012-10-07&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-10-07)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/10/07/my-first-contra-dance-workshop-unexpected-fun/&#34;&gt;Abby and I did make it to the contra dance workshop&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I continue to greatly enjoy the regular French music jam and meeting and playing with more musicians. Meanwhile, although I have not done much dancing lately, I am excited about the creation of CATS Dance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2012-10-15&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-10-15)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out the latest update on the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/10/15/french-music-jam-with-unexpected-new-musicians/&#34;&gt;French music jam&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My second French music jam: playing my Irish flute in public for the first time</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/08/27/my-second-french-music-jam-playing-my-irish-flute-in-public-for-the-first-time/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Aug 2012 22:37:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/08/27/my-second-french-music-jam-playing-my-irish-flute-in-public-for-the-first-time/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Tonight I participated for the second time in a new little &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/groups/182324948478861/&#34;&gt;French traditional dance&lt;/a&gt; music jam session that &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/02/my-first-french-music-jam-anxious-but-excited/&#34;&gt;started up in July&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This time, I played not only my &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/baroque-flute/&#34;&gt;Baroque flute&lt;/a&gt; (which happens to be the instrument I&amp;rsquo;ve mostly been playing for the past two months), but also my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/30/got-my-new-casey-burns-small-handed-irish-flute/&#34;&gt;new Irish flute I got a month ago&lt;/a&gt;. I did &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; bring my modern flute at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we did the last time, after we played around for an hour or so, we then played for dancers for another hour. I enjoyed the experience a lot, and was less nervous than I was the first time. I am slowly improving at learning a tune, without a score, while someone is playing it, and then imitating the melodic line or filling in a harmonically sensible line on the fly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;instruments-and-musicians&#34;&gt;Instruments and musicians&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I finally received my Irish flute a month ago and have spent some minutes every day breaking it in at home. Tonight was its &amp;ldquo;debut&amp;rdquo; in public. I enjoyed the louder, stronger sound.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still used the Baroque flute, for key signatures that my keyless Irish flute does not work well for (half-holing is a pain).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also had fiddles, melodeon, guitar, mandolin (not all at the same time, since John was switching between melodeon and mandolin depending on the key of the song, given the limitations of the melodeon), and I felt that the Irish flute was balanced pretty well with the other instruments, better than the Baroque flute did in the first session in July (when it was often drowned out).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We lost some musicians from last time, because one of them left town, and the clarinetist has a class in the evening and therefore cannot arrive till later, when she comes to dance. But we had two new people!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our little French music group is gaining momentum. I&amp;rsquo;m very excited! Also, as the CMU fall semester starts, there are plans to really promote French and other traditional music and dance in the form of an official CMU student organization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2012-09-28&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-09-28)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/28/another-french-music-jam-also-announcing-cats-dance/&#34;&gt;CATS Dance successfully launched in September&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My first French music jam: anxious but excited</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/07/02/my-first-french-music-jam-anxious-but-excited/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jul 2012 23:45:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/07/02/my-first-french-music-jam-anxious-but-excited/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Tonight I participated for the first time in a new local &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/groups/182324948478861/&#34;&gt;French traditional dance&lt;/a&gt; music jam session that is getting off the ground, organized by Lisa. I was really excited about the formation of our group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How did this come about?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;inspired-by-gregory&#34;&gt;Inspired by Gregory&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What happened was that after &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/05/14/playing-french-music-for-first-time-and-dancing-blues-for-first-time/&#34;&gt;Gregory left us this summer&lt;/a&gt;, I told Lisa that I really wanted to do the kind of thing Gregory had been doing, playing French music for dancers. Lisa was excited about this and thought it would be cool for herself to start playing fiddle again. She found some other people who were interested in playing French music together, and so we met up!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;instruments&#34;&gt;Instruments&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tonight, I played both my &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/baroque-flute/&#34;&gt;Baroque flute&lt;/a&gt; and my modern flute. I didn&amp;rsquo;t really want to play the modern flute, but there were times when we played some music in keys I wasn&amp;rsquo;t comfortable with on Baroque flute. Meanwhile, it will take a long time for the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/06/12/ordered-the-casey-burns-small-handed-irish-flute/&#34;&gt;Irish flute I ordered&lt;/a&gt; to be made and shipped. I really want to use the louder Irish flute when feasible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lisa had her fiddle, and someone else also had a fiddle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A guy brought his melodeon (button accordion), which unfortunately is limited in the keys it can play in. He sometimes used the old upright piano also. There was someone else who also used the piano.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there was someone on clarinet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-it-went&#34;&gt;How it went&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was quite nervous, because much of what we did was not from printed scores, but from people&amp;rsquo;s memories of their favorite tunes. I in fact ended up using my phone to send Lisa a PDF of Gregory&amp;rsquo;s French music score compilation so that she could print it out for some of us!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I quickly noticed that my Baroque flute was being drowned out by the other instruments. So I pulled out my modern flute sometimes in order to be heard more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We went on for quite some time as the dancers arrived and became restless, and then we played for them for about an hour. Actually, I was heard better then, because Lisa and some other musicians gave introductory lessons or themselves wanted to dance. The result was that after a while, it was just Donna on fiddle, John on melodeon, and me on Baroque flute playing for the dancers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s really a joy playing music for people to dance to. I feel like I&amp;rsquo;m starting to fulfill my dream that &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/10/flute-loving-it-again/&#34;&gt;I dared to mention in March: that of being the musician rather than the dancer at a dance&lt;/a&gt;. During his time here in Pittsburgh, I was really inspired by the example of Gregory (who has finished his stay in the country and gone back to Europe) to start learning tunes by ear, ornamenting, and improvising. I&amp;rsquo;m still quite a beginner at this approach to music, but this is what I&amp;rsquo;ve always wanted to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first French music jam and new format for the French dance (live music instead of iTunes) was a great start of something new. We were all so excited that we definitely want to continue doing this. I look forward to continuing to play together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2012-08-27&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-08-27)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And less than two months later, I am &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/08/27/my-second-french-music-jam-playing-my-irish-flute-in-public-for-the-first-time/&#34;&gt;still involved in the new French music jam&lt;/a&gt;, and finally with my own Irish flute!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>