<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Invisible Shoes on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/invisible-shoes/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Invisible Shoes on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/invisible-shoes/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Running my 10th Great Race 10K: &#34;obscene but in a good way&#34;</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/09/30/running-my-10th-great-race-10k-obscene-but-in-a-good-way/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Sep 2012 19:08:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/09/30/running-my-10th-great-race-10k-obscene-but-in-a-good-way/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/great-race-2012/great-race-expo.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Great Race quilt&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Today I ran in Pittsburgh&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://rungreatrace.com/&#34;&gt;Great Race 10K&lt;/a&gt; for the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/25/blistered-but-blissful-in-the-burgh/&#34;&gt;tenth time in my life&lt;/a&gt;. For various reasons, I performed a number of experiments for this tenth running of the race, doing things I&amp;rsquo;ve never done before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the race, I heard someone say, as I passed him:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
...obscene... but in a good way!
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It made my day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll explain what might have triggered this reaction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;preparation-and-uncertainty&#34;&gt;Preparation and uncertainty&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/07/running-my-8th-pretty-good-race-5k-dealing-with-disappointment/&#34;&gt;Pretty Good Race 5K&lt;/a&gt;, I was so tired out from my effort that I totally lost the desire to run. Plus my left foot was hurting more again. I ended up not running a single step for two weeks. This meant, of course, that there was no way I was going to go after the goal of beating last year&amp;rsquo;s time in the Great Race 10K.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, there was the question of whether I should even run the Great Race at all this year! Until almost the last minute, Abby and I agreed that if I did not feel up for running it at all, I would just sell my registration. Part of me felt bad about the possibility of breaking &amp;ldquo;tradition&amp;rdquo; and not running the race; I have stubbornly run it while horribly sick in some years! At the same time, it&amp;rsquo;s not really the end of the world if I miss a race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;change-of-purpose-and-plan-enter-the-invisible-shoes&#34;&gt;Change of purpose and plan: enter the Invisible Shoes!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eventually, after my two-week absence from running, my left foot injury resolved itself, and I started running again. The plan was to start road running (since I prefer to trail running) in preparation for the Great Race. The problem is that I actually don&amp;rsquo;t like wearing my road running Vibram FiveFingers shoes, my Bikila LS shoes. In fact, since my taste in footwear has become more and more minimalist over time, the Bikila LS shoes seem like a step totally in the wrong direction. I got them last year really only for the purpose of road racing, since the KSO blisters me and the KSO Trek is for the trails.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just to start running again, I began going out for 2-3 mile casual runs in my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/26/walking-and-running-in-invisible-shoes-a-review/&#34;&gt;Invisible Shoes&lt;/a&gt; that I&amp;rsquo;d been wearing all summer for walking, and sometimes for running. I enjoyed my short runs in these huaraches.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/great-race-2012/invisible-shoes-rolled.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Invisible Shoes rolled up&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Given that I was just getting back into running after such a long break, I never ran more than 3 miles during any of my runs leading up to the Great Race. And I never wore anything other than the Invisible Shoes. So that led me to the idea that since I wasn&amp;rsquo;t going to be able to achieve a goal of running super fast this year, I could set a &lt;em&gt;different goal&lt;/em&gt; for myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My new goal: &lt;em&gt;run the Great Race 10K in 4mm huaraches&lt;/em&gt;. More specifically, I wanted to see how my joints and muscles would hold up, as well as my feet and skin. Also, I&amp;rsquo;d never run fast in huaraches before, so this would also be an experiment in running fast in them. I had every intention of running pretty fast: I simply expected that I would not be able to run as fast as if I were running more protected shoes, because of many factors such as flopping soles and more pounding, resulting in my going more conservatively than if I had already experimented and knew what the limits were.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, originally I had planned to run a 5K race sometime in the huaraches; I had never planned to suddenly run a 10K in them without running a 5K first!! Also, I was going to run this 10K without having run more than 3 miles at a time in an entire month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;last-minute-panic-and-recovery&#34;&gt;Last minute panic and recovery&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Friday, I was coming down with a sore throat, and my boss said he and his son were both sick (they were both signed up for the Great Race this year). Now I was totally uncertain about whether I was going to run on Sunday. I tried to get healthy, and on Saturday, was feeling more stable, although a sore throat kept lingering, and picked up my race packet. Luckily, I was feeling great this morning, with no sign of a sore throat, so apparently my &amp;ldquo;placebos&amp;rdquo; worked (sleep, healthy food, various supplements). I canceled all my Saturday plans (such as going to a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/28/another-french-music-jam-also-announcing-cats-dance/&#34;&gt;French dance workshop&lt;/a&gt;) in order to rest up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other concern was the weather forecast. All week it seemed like it was going to rain sometime this morning. I&amp;rsquo;ve run in rain before, raced in rain before. I can do it. But the last time I ran in Invisible Shoes in the rain, I got into trouble. So now what? I simply decided I was going to deal with rain if it happened. Yet another variable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-race&#34;&gt;The race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;to-eat-or-not-to-eat&#34;&gt;To eat or not to eat?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One experiment I did today that I deem a big success: &lt;em&gt;I ate almost nothing before the race&lt;/em&gt;. I ate a bunch of almonds when I was leaving the house, but that was it. In the past, I always ate something more substantial before a race. Rationally, it does not make sense, but for some reason, I always felt that I should eat a mini-meal. This was completely irrational, a weird clinging behavior I engaged in: after all, when I casually go running in the morning, I do it before breakfast! So why should race day be any different? We human beings have enough fuel stored in our bodies. It&amp;rsquo;s true that when I go for a run of over, say, 8 miles, I get hungry, and like to either have a snack on me to eat, or have eaten right before going on the run, but when it comes to 5K and 10K races, clearly there is no need for me to eat before the race. Experience has shown that it only makes me feel sluggish. So from now on, &lt;em&gt;no more mini-meals before a race of 10K or shorter&lt;/em&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;shoes&#34;&gt;Shoes&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/great-race-2012/franklin-before.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin wearing Invisible Shoes and race number 1853&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/great-race-2012/feet-before.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin wearing Invisible Shoes&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As usual, I jogged a mile from home to the start line as my warmup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;beginning&#34;&gt;Beginning&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The temperature was in the low 50s F: ideal racing temperature, not too cold. Under 50, I would have worn a long-sleeve T-shirt instead of a short-sleeve one. As it was, since I anticipated rain, I did not wear my usual singlet but instead a standard short-sleeve T-shirt. It was not yet raining, thankfully!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some guy stepped on my right toes with his shoes as he wandered through the crowd. I was upset by this and hoped that my toes were OK. They were sore for a few minutes but then I forgot about them and was OK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within the first few minutes, I saw Don Slusser ahead of me; last year I had tracked him and then passed him at the end of the race. This year, he was obviously going much slower, thanks to his shot knees, so I passed him early on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I saw my boss standing on his street corner watching the race. I asked why he wasn&amp;rsquo;t running and he said he was too sick. It&amp;rsquo;s too bad he had to miss the race yet again, after missing it last year because of another commitment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My huaraches seemed to be working pretty well as I ran faster than I had ever run in them. I rather enjoyed being able to feel the ground, as though I were fully barefoot. At 4mm, running with these is pretty close to being barefoot, much closer than wearing Vibram FiveFingers shoes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wasn&amp;rsquo;t paying much attention to any glances or stares at my feet, or remarks people may have been making, although a few runners did directly ask me about my &amp;ldquo;flip flops&amp;rdquo;, with an attitude ranging from incredulity to amusement to admiration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;middle&#34;&gt;Middle&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Near halfway through the race, it started raining fairly steadily. I had to periodically wipe the water away from my eyes. Well, it was in the forecast. One thing I can say is that I was never in danger of overheating in this race! There have been instances of the Great Race in warm conditions under a sun, when even in a singlet I got very warm and had to dump water over my head: ha, today I got free water on my head constantly!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I started the race further back than I usually do, there were very few people running at exactly my pace. I was always either passing or being passed by people. This is one thing annoying about big races where people can cross the start mat at very different times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, at one point, a guy came to be in front of me who was running approximately my pace, so that I was almost a constant distance from him. On downhills I would tend to overtake him, but then he would come back. We would be mostly together for approximately the last two miles. At one point when I slowly passed him, I think I heard him say, &amp;ldquo;That&amp;rsquo;s obscene&amp;hellip; but in a good way!&amp;rdquo; I believe that comment was directed at me and my footwear, and I kind of took it as a compliment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;end&#34;&gt;End&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The water puddles were starting to get to me, as I had earlier feared. I did not feel confident about running any faster than I already was, given the road conditions and the way my huaraches were slipping around. And my toes were getting sore from the pounding. Normally, in the end of a race, I turn it on and try to use up the remaining energy I have, but today, I just did not feel confident in my footing. I continued going reasonably fast, but did not put in any finishing sprint at all. Even if I had wanted to, it would have been difficult, because of so many slower people in front of me. This is a direct consequence of my lining up at the start line far further back than I usually do: what happens is that slower people who started further up are in the way for the entirety of the race!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I did turn it on just enough to pass that guy I had been more or less with for two miles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;result&#34;&gt;Result&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My chip time was 48:23, not too bad given my footwear experimentation and lack of conditioning and failure to go all out in the final mile; last year&amp;rsquo;s time was 47:46. Next year, I would like to go under 47:00. I should be able to do that if I maintain a regular running regimen. 2006 was the last year that I went under 47:00.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;after-the-race&#34;&gt;After the race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got some water, was given two Smiley Cookies, and ate a bagel and a banana also. I hopped on the shuttle bus back to the start line (the ride took 30 minutes), then walked 25 minute (1.5 miles) back home in the cold. In the future, I don&amp;rsquo;t want to do this walk. I should park my car near the start line the night before, so that I can hop off the bus and drive home. It&amp;rsquo;s no fun to be walking so long in the cold when you&amp;rsquo;re tired and you&amp;rsquo;re not sure what the condition of your feet are, except that they hurt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are my feet after I got home:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/great-race-2012/feet-after.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin&amp;#39;s bare feet after race, at home&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It turns out that I got only one blister, and it was exactly where I got a blister last time I ran in the rain in the huaraches: between my first two toes. There was some roughing up of the callouses on the balls of my feet (from wearing the huaraches all summer), but otherwise, my feet were OK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After some more hours of recovery, I was feeling fine. No joint pain whatsoever, no muscle soreness whatsoever, none of that stuff. Even last year I had some stiffness when I got off the shuttle bus. My conclusion is that truly minimalist footwear trains me to land in such a way as to minimize problems to my body. No shin splints, no ankle soreness, no knee pain, no hip pain, no shot quads, no cramping calves, nothing. Just a blister, and toes and forefoot that were sore for a while but right now no longer are. It&amp;rsquo;s amazing what &lt;em&gt;no cushioning for the feet at all&lt;/em&gt; did to prevent the problems I used to face when running. I am so completely sold that I will look into running more races in huaraches, and in optimizing my lacing in order to prevent the flopping limitation and that one blister spot. I am consider going up to the 6mm sole from the 4mm sole, with the idea that 6mm would be more solid for racing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another thought: assuming a race with no rain or extreme cold or hot surfaces, I should run a race &lt;em&gt;barefoot&lt;/em&gt; sometime next year. I&amp;rsquo;ll think about this. I know people who have done this. Why not? Barefoot, one does not have to worry about blisters caused from laces, or sole flopping, or water slipping. One may have other worries instead, but knowing a course ahead of time can help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;photos&#34;&gt;Photos&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Official photos of me in action, including beating the guy I mentioned, are &lt;a href=&#34;http://orders.islandphoto.com/RACE/Proofs.aspx#26561404-00002-0026&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, but since they are copyrighted, I have not inserted them directly into my report here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The inaugural Liberty Mile: a review of Pittsburgh&#39;s first road mile race, a great community event</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/08/17/the-inaugural-liberty-mile-a-review-of-pittsburghs-first-road-mile-race/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Aug 2012 21:44:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/08/17/the-inaugural-liberty-mile-a-review-of-pittsburghs-first-road-mile-race/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/liberty-mile-2012.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin&amp;#39;s race number and Bikila LS shoes&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Tonight I was really excited to race in, and also watch, the inaugural &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.libertymile.org/&#34;&gt;GNC Live Well Liberty Mile&lt;/a&gt;, a road race that runs along Liberty Avenue in Pittsburgh, starting from the Strip District and ending downtown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s about time Pittsburgh had a road mile race! Pittsburgh already has the wonderful&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://rungreatrace.com/&#34;&gt;Great Race&lt;/a&gt;, which &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/25/blistered-but-blissful-in-the-burgh/&#34;&gt;I ran for my ninth time last year&lt;/a&gt; and will run for my tenth time this year (good think I pre-registered early, because today it &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburgh.cbslocal.com/2012/08/17/2012-great-race-officially-sold-out/&#34;&gt;already sold out!!&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pittsburghmarathon.com/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Marathon&lt;/a&gt;, which I&amp;rsquo;ve run once.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope this event is here to stay. Here&amp;rsquo;s my report on the event as both a runner and a spectator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-history-in-the-mile&#34;&gt;My history in the mile&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve run a mile race only twice before in my life, and that was on the track at Carnegie Mellon University. A decade ago, in June 2002, I ran in my first track mile, the Pittsylvania Mile on that track, and did it in 6:22. I could have run faster, but because of total inexperience, went out way too fast for the first quarter, doing it in 1:22, and paying the price in the other laps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following year, 2003, in probably my peak condition in my life, I improved, doing the Pittsylvania Mile in 6:10. I still went out too fast, in 1:26, had no sense of rhythm, slowed down a lot to try to compensate for going out too fast, then had too much energy at the end, which was wasted. Again, I had not trained for the mile distance at all, but happened to be in my peak condition anyway just because I was still conditioned from my intense training for the Pittsburgh Marathon that I had just done in May (my lifetime personal best in the 5K of 20:37 was achieved just two weeks after the Pittsburgh Marathon).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I never broke a 6-minute mile during my peak.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That was the last timed mile I ever ran, until tonight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;preparation&#34;&gt;Preparation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, I wasn&amp;rsquo;t prepared for the mile at all. Apart from not having run much because of a non-running injury to my left leg that happened a month ago (from which I have fully recovered), I have just come back from a week of unexpected travel and am still kind of recovering from that. And no speed work to speak of in the past month, other than a few random sprints (which I do for general physical conditioning when I don&amp;rsquo;t do much else).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had no idea what &amp;ldquo;mile pace&amp;rdquo; feels like. I just figured I would run a bit faster than 5K pace (which I always have a reasonable feel for).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hoped to finish somewhere near 6:30.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;dr-vonda-wright&#34;&gt;Dr. Vonda Wright&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://vondawright.com/images/stories/vonda-at-work.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Vonda Wright&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I bumped into &lt;a href=&#34;http://vondawright.com/&#34;&gt;Dr. Vonda Wright&lt;/a&gt; while heading toward the start line, and thanked her for her support of those of us who care about maintaining our health as we get older. I want to plug her great work in promoting lifetime fitness, especially for those over 40. She has written a book &lt;a href=&#34;http://vondawright.com/index.php?option=com_content&amp;amp;view=article&amp;amp;id=62&amp;amp;Itemid=83&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Fitness After 40&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; which is pretty good and has a lot of scientifically-backed tips on remaining strong and vital and even reversing what used to be considered &amp;ldquo;normal aging&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I heard about Dr. Wright from a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/01/20/cmu-fitness-challenge-keynote-lecture-by-vonda-wright-stay-strong-at-any-age/&#34;&gt;CMU &amp;ldquo;healthy campus week&amp;rdquo; talk she gave this January&lt;/a&gt;. Even though I had already known some of what she advocated, I was impressed that she summarized well the whole gamut of what we now know to be effective ways to increase strength and flexibility and avoid injury. Again, I recommend her books to anyone of any age who wants to be smart about diet and exercise and more than that, a whole philosophical approach to living in general.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-race-in-waves&#34;&gt;The race, in waves&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The race was held in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.libertymile.org/Race-Waves.asp&#34;&gt;waves separated by ten or twenty minutes&lt;/a&gt;. This is obviously necessary because of the variation in people&amp;rsquo;s speed. The slower, open waves were held first, and the elite racers were in the final waves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;early-waves&#34;&gt;Early waves&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I arrived to pick up my race number when the first wave was already in progress. There was a bit of confusion in the first two waves because a good number of people arrived late or were unclear about when to run, and therefore missed the first wave. Most of these seemed to be kids. By the way, it was great to see so many kids at the Liberty Mile. Running a 5K (3.1-mile) race can be daunting for a kid, but a single mile is surely a great introduction to many kids (and adults too!) to the joy of running. I think it is really great that the Liberty Mile is not just an elite race, but also a race anyone can participate in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;my-race-in-the-masters-wave&#34;&gt;My race, in the Masters wave&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Masters &amp;ldquo;Winning at 40+&amp;rdquo; wave was the first qualification-required wave.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ran in this serious, competitive wave, not one of the open waves, because I easily qualified to run in this wave, whose requirement was proof of ability to run an 8-minute mile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lining up, I saw a lot of really fit-looking people in this wave, many of whom were clearly well over 40. In any case, anyone who looked anywhere near my age (42) was obviously going to kick my butt all the way to the moon. There was no chance for an age-group prize for me today! No problem: as a non-elite racer, I don&amp;rsquo;t race for prizes, but just to do the best that I can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ended up running &lt;a href=&#34;http://runhigh.com/2012RESULTS/R081712AD.html&#34;&gt;6:38.8&lt;/a&gt;, good for 26th place out of 27 in my age group, ha! I was disappointed that I didn&amp;rsquo;t make 6:30 as I had originally hoped when I signed up a month ago, but that&amp;rsquo;s OK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the first quarter, I ran 1:29; oops, went out too fast yet again! &lt;strong&gt;I hereby pledge that before the next mile race I run, I will actually train and learn not to go out too fast.&lt;/strong&gt; There is no excuse for running three mile races going out too fast. I don&amp;rsquo;t go out too fast in 5K or longer distances, after all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the second and third quarters, 1:46 and 1:46 showed that I had gone out too fast. I did save something for the sprint finish, however, and did the final quarter in 1:38.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A serious and unexpected problem I had while running this race was that my mouth got very dry and I had trouble breathing as a result. It was pretty weird. I don&amp;rsquo;t exactly remember this in my mile races from a decade ago. I did hydrate considerably before the race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, of course, as I do in 5K races, I felt like puking during the final quarter, and my arms were getting tingly and losing sensation. It&amp;rsquo;s just what happens to me in the final push. I believe there is no way to avoid feeling like puking if I&amp;rsquo;m running as hard as I can, but I have a feeling that the problem with my arms has to do with my tightening up (rather than relaxing) and flailing around. I plan to try to fix that for my next races this month and next month; what is required, clearly, is disciplined speed work, which is something I have not done in years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;enjoying-being-a-spectator&#34;&gt;Enjoying being a spectator&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The really cool thing about a mile race held in waves is that you get to be a spectator for the remaining waves after you&amp;rsquo;re done. In a 5K race or longer, there aren&amp;rsquo;t any heats and you never get to be a spectator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was wowed watching the &amp;ldquo;Unstoppable&amp;rdquo; under-40 wave whose qualification time was running faster than 6:00. Watching good, fast running is a real pleasure to me, like watching skilled dancers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also a treat was getting to watch the female elite wave and male elite wave. These &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/27/why-i-do-not-watch-the-olympics-any-more/&#34;&gt;Olympic&lt;/a&gt;-caliber runners looked so elegant with their long, powerful strides.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-shoes&#34;&gt;My shoes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d been considering running a race soon wearing my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/26/walking-and-running-in-invisible-shoes-a-review/&#34;&gt;Invisible Shoes huaraches&lt;/a&gt;, but without testing them out with speed work, I&amp;rsquo;m not ready to go there yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I wore the shoes I&amp;rsquo;ve been &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/23/happiness-is-finishing-39th-of-43-men-in-a-race/&#34;&gt;road racing in for almost a full year now&lt;/a&gt;, the Vibram FiveFingers Bikila LS. They worked out just fine. I didn&amp;rsquo;t get blistered because it was cool and it was only a mile. Next month I&amp;rsquo;ll see whether I get blistered in the Great Race &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/25/blistered-but-blissful-in-the-burgh/&#34;&gt;the way I did last year&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;race-organization&#34;&gt;Race organization&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought the race was pretty well-organized, especially given that this was the first time such a race has been held in Pittsburgh. Thanks go to the sponsors, the timers, the announcers, the volunteers who handed out race numbers and stocked water and bagels at the finish line and handed out goodie bags and T-shirts, the police officers who closed the roads and lanes where necessary and directed traffic and kept Liberty Avenue clear, the spectators who cheered, the providers of the many port-a-johns near the start line, the &lt;a href=&#34;http://bringbackthemile.com/news/detail/Miller_and_Kampf_Win_GNC_Live_Well_Liberty_Mile&#34;&gt;elite runners who put on a display of amazing running&lt;/a&gt;. Everyone without question was helpful and friendly. The whole experience was just wonderful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The inaugural GNC Live Well Liberty Mile was a great event. I hope it is the beginning of a Pittsburgh tradition that, like the Great Race and the Pittsburgh Marathon, will continue for years and decades to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-08-09&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-08-09)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/08/09/getting-up-when-reality-punches-you-in-the-face-running-the-second-liberty-mile-in-pittsburgh/&#34;&gt;I ran the second Liberty Mile a year later.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Walking and running in Invisible Shoes: a review of the Connect</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/07/26/walking-and-running-in-invisible-shoes-a-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jul 2012 21:28:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/07/26/walking-and-running-in-invisible-shoes-a-review/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;For three weeks now, I have been wearing a pair of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.invisibleshoe.com/&#34;&gt;Invisible Shoes&lt;/a&gt; huaraches almost exclusively when walking and running outside. I have worn them daily walking, and I have run in them on roads, on sidewalks, on grass, and in park trails.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a review of the 4mm sole Connect model (I might get a 6mm sole Contact later).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is what the shoes look like with &amp;ldquo;slip-on/slip-off&amp;rdquo; lacing:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/invisible-shoes-connect/without-feet.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/invisible-shoes-connect/bottom.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As you can see, the sole is quite thin, just 4mm:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/invisible-shoes-connect/side-view.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here are some photos of me wearing the shoes:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/invisible-shoes-connect/grass.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/invisible-shoes-connect/asphalt.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-wear-such-a-thin-shoe&#34;&gt;Why wear such a thin shoe?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ten years ago, in 2002, I learned about the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tarahumara_people&#34;&gt;Tarahumara&lt;/a&gt; Native Americans who live in Mexico and are famed for long-distance running. I was fascinated that they chose to run in minimalist huaraches. At the time, I was doing a lot of serious &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/running/&#34;&gt;running&lt;/a&gt;, and perpetually had problems with running shoes. I figured out from trial and error that the more minimalist I got, the more I enjoyed the feel of running and the fewer injuries I received, but I didn&amp;rsquo;t know how minimalist I could really get before the cons outweighed the pros. By 2002, I had gotten as far as wearing racing flats by New Balance and Asics for races and some of my training runs, but no shoe was perfect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had also tried wearing a variety of ordinary sandals for walking and running, but they had all kinds of ergonomic problems that led me to give up on them. The strapping systems, the substantial (by my standards) heels, and the curved &amp;ldquo;arch support&amp;rdquo; all caused discomfort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fast-forward to 2009, when I bought my first pair of Vibram FiveFingers minimalist shoes. These changed my life, being sufficiently minimalist to defeat a number of problems I&amp;rsquo;ve had with traditional mono-toed shoes. As long-time readers of &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/fivefingers/&#34;&gt;this blog know&lt;/a&gt;, I&amp;rsquo;ve been wearing them exclusively for all kinds of activities, ranging from regular everyday walking to running on roads, running on trails, hiking, kayaking, rafting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past year, I have tried a little bit of &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/barefoot-running/&#34;&gt;barefoot running&lt;/a&gt;, but that is still too extreme for me to do often or for a long period of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I decided that now was the time to try to get more minimalist than FiveFingers, toward the &amp;ldquo;barefoot&amp;rdquo; feel, but without the most glaring drawbacks of being barefoot. Luckily, the surprising popularity of &lt;a href=&#34;http://chrismcdougall.com/&#34;&gt;Chris McDougall&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/a&gt; book &amp;ldquo;Born to Run&amp;rdquo; has resulted in a good number of people selling minimalist huaraches for running.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;buying&#34;&gt;Buying&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Barefoot Ted had long sold his version of huaraches, the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lunasandals.com/&#34;&gt;Luna Sandals&lt;/a&gt;. I decided to try, instead, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.invisibleshoe.com/&#34;&gt;Invisible Shoes&lt;/a&gt;, because these are more minimalist than the Luna, which in its classic form has a 6mm sole as well as a foot bed. I may well try the Luna at some point, but my goal for now is to approximate the barefoot feel, rather than pick the best huaraches for serious rugged use, and work up from there. So I went for the 4mm Connect version of the Invisible Shoes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For now, instead of buying a DIY kit, I decided that the simplest hassle-free way to break into huaraches was to buy a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lunasandals.com/&#34;&gt;custom-made&lt;/a&gt; shoe that had the soles cut and punched and laced up, ready to immediately wear. I traced my foot, scanned the trace, and emailed it, and quickly received my pair in the mail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are interested in trying out huaraches, I recommend following this route if the thought of DIY problems might otherwise discourage you. I may go DIY in the future, now that I see the final product.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;tying&#34;&gt;Tying&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question of how to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.invisibleshoe.com/tying/&#34;&gt;tie&lt;/a&gt; laces always pops up. For now, I have not experimented with different methods in order to evaluate what works best for me for secureness and comfort. I have been using the slip-on/slip-off system that came with the shoe, adjusting it as needed when my foot feels too tight or too loose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;walking&#34;&gt;Walking&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I got Invisible Shoes, my regular walking shoes were my Vibram FiveFingers KSO shoes. But once I got the Invisible Shoes, I completely stopped wearing the KSO for everyday walking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;pros&#34;&gt;Pros&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My toes have real freedom. Toe shoes like the Vibram FiveFingers compartmentalize the toes, so although they solve my wide-foot problem, they do not give me total freedom of the whole front of the foot that I like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good ventilation, like being barefoot. FiveFingers get hot in summer, resulting in sweat and sometimes blisters. I don&amp;rsquo;t get blisters walking in Invisible Shoes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the slip-on/slip-off system, I really can slip on and off easily. Since I like going barefoot indoors, it&amp;rsquo;s a plus to be able to slip on and off the shoes so easily.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;cons&#34;&gt;Cons&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is some rubbing at key points on the foot: the knot in the lacing system on top of the foot, and the lacing that passes between the big toe and the second toe. In practice, none of this has been a real problem except when it&amp;rsquo;s raining and my feet get wet, in which case I get chafed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The soles, being so thin, flop around a bit. Occasionally a sole will fold under and cause me to trip, but this happens very rarely. The main problem is mostly social: the flopping sound draws attention; I prefer to walk very silently (which I can do in most closed shoes).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The thinness of the soles also result in my feet getting very hot when I&amp;rsquo;m just standing for a period of time on hot asphalt or concrete (this is the same problem as I have when going barefoot). So standing at a street intersection waiting for a long light or in a parking lot while putting stuff into a car is not so pleasant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The thinness of the soles means walking over rough terrain is not always pleasant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that all the problems with the thinness of the soles might not be present if I had the 6mm sole rather than the 4mm sole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;running&#34;&gt;Running&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Disclaimer: I have run only four or five times in these shoes so far, so I will accumulate more experience as I continue to run in them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;pros-1&#34;&gt;Pros&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Running in these shoes on the roads and sidewalks is predictable and pleasant, very much like running barefoot. I am considering doing more tests to determine whether to run a road race 5K or 10K in these shoes! I have not run at race pace in these shoes yet. I may need to adjust lacing systems in order to feel confident about running at maximum speed without a flopping or lace-loosening problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;cons-1&#34;&gt;Cons&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is sole flopping when running. Actually there is less flopping than when walking, though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Running in the trails has not worked too smoothly. The 4mm sole really is quite thin for trail running. I noticed this when running in Frick Park, where some of the trails are more rocky than others. I also noticed this even when running in &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/06/18/walking-the-scenic-route-through-schenley-park-to-work/&#34;&gt;Schenley Park on the Pretty Good Race course&lt;/a&gt;, where the downhill section had me periodically hitting rocks harder than comfortable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is also the annoyance of stuff getting between the foot and the sole when running in the trails. Since I don&amp;rsquo;t like stopping, I&amp;rsquo;ve tried to simply flex my foot to let the material slide back out during the next couple of strides, and this mostly works. But I got one blister during a run on the trails, possibly because of loose material that got between my foot and the sole that I didn&amp;rsquo;t bother completely shaking out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 4mm Connect model of Invisible Shoes is great for walking around in. For running, I need to do more tests to find out how they hold up in more demanding conditions of speed and terrain. I would also like to compare the 4mm Connect model with the 6mm Contact model.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mideast Early Music Workshop 2012: a life-changing experience!!</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/07/21/mideast-early-music-workshop-a-life-changing-experience/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Jul 2012 22:43:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/07/21/mideast-early-music-workshop-a-life-changing-experience/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The whole past week (July 15-21, 2012), I attended my first ever music camp, the annual &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mideastearlymusic.addr.com/&#34;&gt;Mideast early music workshop&lt;/a&gt; held at LaRoche College. It totally changed my life!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A big report, with photos and videos:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-i-decided-to-attend&#34;&gt;Why I decided to attend&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have loved music all my life, but never had any private instruction, or any intensive group instruction either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;old&#34;&gt;Old?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After passing age 40, I started thinking about mortality, and making a list of what my biggest regrets in life would be if I died soon. On the &lt;em&gt;very top&lt;/em&gt; of the list was my lifelong regret that I never had the courage to get serious about music. I had made excuse after excuse to downplay following my musical dreams (in part a legacy of my internalizing my parents&amp;rsquo; constant discouragement of music as a &amp;ldquo;waste of time&amp;rdquo;, but also because I was &lt;em&gt;not willing to make the required sacrifices as a very busy adult&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So before I turned 41, I decided to finally start the process of getting serious about music, and in February 2011 (less than one and a half years ago), I started to learn to play &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/recorder/&#34;&gt;recorder&lt;/a&gt; because it was easy to get started on, was new to me (without the baggage of my difficult experiences with flute and piano) and most of all, because of the existence of the Pittsburgh Recorder Society as a friendly place to finally play with other people. I mentioned this in &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/22/byron-janis-on-overcoming-adversity/&#34;&gt;one of my first posts on this blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;first-hearing-of-the-workshop&#34;&gt;First hearing of the workshop&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In March 2011, I went to the meeting of the Pittsburgh Recorder Society &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/26/i-dont-feel-like-practicing-but-im-gonna-do-it-anyway/&#34;&gt;for the first time&lt;/a&gt;. At the April 2011 meeting, Helen passed out flyers for the Mideast workshop. I was interested in it and asked her and others about it, but as a total beginner felt that it was not worth attending until I got much better first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After another year, I did in fact improve significantly on recorder (and musically in general), and therefore &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/31/my-first-sampling-of-english-country-dance-and-contra-dance/&#34;&gt;decided this past March&lt;/a&gt; to attend the workshop. I pegged myself as finally having reached a beginner/intermediate level suitable for benefiting from the workshop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;gary-marcus&#34;&gt;Gary Marcus&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also turns out that just this February, I picked up Gary Marcus&amp;rsquo;s book &lt;a href=&#34;http://garymarcus.com/books/guitarzero.html&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Guitar Zero&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; and read it. It is about his experience finally immersing himself in music at the age of 40. This book helped me decide to attend the workshop this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;instruments&#34;&gt;Instruments&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that you have to choose a primary instrument (from among recorder, viol, and (Baroque) flute), but can also study secondary instruments. I decided that because of my strong interest in flute (both Baroque flute and modern flute), I would choose &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/baroque-flute/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Baroque flute&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; as my primary instrument.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Possible secondary instruments are recorder, viol, harp, voice, and capped reeds (for Renaissance band): I chose &lt;em&gt;recorder&lt;/em&gt; (of course), &lt;strong&gt;but also&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;voice&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was deathly scared of getting into singing, but felt that this was my chance to finally jump into it!! I have &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; sung with anyone before (in elementary and middle school, I basically lip-synced when supposed to sing), and have almost never sung in the presence of any other human being (I believe I sang for Abby once). I had a definitely goal of unobtrusively getting my start in singing here, in an informal group setting, and then moving forward from there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;classes&#34;&gt;Classes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The classes I tentatively planned to take were:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Baroque flute technique&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;recorder consort&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;all-workshop ensemble&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;bass recorder ensemble&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;improvisation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;voice class&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;English country dance&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I expected it to be a pretty intense schedule, and it definitely was!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;evening-before-informal-dinner-at-helen-s&#34;&gt;Evening before: informal dinner at Helen&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Helen hosted dinner at her place for both locals and out-of-towners arriving in town for the workshop. About a dozen of us showed up, and Abby came along. Since most of the attendees and instructors already knew each other for years (decades in most cases!), I found it a great way to start getting to know some people. Yes, this is an &amp;ldquo;old people&amp;rdquo; music camp. At age 42, I was by far the baby of the entire group. It seems that a good number of retired people attend the camp. Some of the instructors are younger than me, but it appeared that all the students were going to be older than me. I have to confess that last year, when I was &amp;ldquo;warned&amp;rdquo; that this was an &amp;ldquo;old people&amp;rdquo; camp, I had reservations, but the fact is, music is for any age, and interestingly, since getting involved in music last year, I have been consistently surprised and delighted by how younger-looking or younger-acting musicians tend to be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;day-1-sunday-july-15&#34;&gt;Day 1: Sunday (July 15)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sunday afternoon, I drove up to LaRoche College to check in and pay the registration balance, and got my key to the dorm room where I would be staying for the week. Mike of the Pittsburgh Recorder Society had agreed to share a room with me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dinner in the LaRoche dining hall was varied and tasty, as I expected given the excellent lunch I had enjoyed at LaRoche during &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/06/09/report-on-the-first-pittsburgh-techfest-2012/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh TechFest in June&lt;/a&gt;! I was starving, having become considerably underweight in the past couple of weeks because of being really busy and stressed, and welcomed the opportunity to chow down. I ate not only a whole lot of healthy food, but also couldn&amp;rsquo;t help myself and ate a cupcake, a cookie, and ice cream also!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;introduction-and-all-workshop-ensemble&#34;&gt;Introduction and all-workshop ensemble&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The introduction to the workshop happened after dinner&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marilyn introduced the workshop, along with the instructors. Marilyn has been the organizer of this workshop for something like 45 years, I believe: wow!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/intro.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Instructors on the left&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/intro2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;The rest of the instructors&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Immediately following the introduction was the first meeting of the all-workshop ensemble. We had substantial-looking spiral-bound books of ensemble music and I wondered how much of it we would go through!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/all-workshop-music.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Book and people ready to play&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;english-country-dance&#34;&gt;English country dance&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After that was the first meeting of English country dance. I was sad not to be dancing with Abby (she was not enrolled in the workshop because this isn&amp;rsquo;t her kind of music), but enjoyed learning something new and getting a bit of exercise. Since it started from scratch, it was less intimidating than &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/31/my-first-sampling-of-english-country-dance-and-contra-dance/&#34;&gt;my first experience with English country dance four months ago&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, given that I was the young baby of the bunch, going a bit slowly was helpful to me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/english-country-dance.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;day-2-monday-july-16&#34;&gt;Day 2: Monday (July 16)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed a fine breakfast, including eggs, sausages, and potatoes, and felt myself regaining some much-needed weight. Also, regarding the dorm rooms: they have air-conditioning, much appreciated given the hot and muggy summer!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;baroque-flute-technique&#34;&gt;Baroque flute technique&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I felt very intimidated in Majbritt&amp;rsquo;s morning Baroque flute technique class. There were six of us in the class, and I was clearly the least experienced. My flute playing (whether modern or flute) is at a beginner&amp;rsquo;s level, as I have been playing for only a few months really. In fact, this is &lt;em&gt;exactly&lt;/em&gt; why I chose flute as my &lt;em&gt;primary&lt;/em&gt; instrument in the workshop: to get good instruction in technique before I progressed too far on my won. Even with recorder, I had to unlearn some bad habits early on that I had developed from working on it myself for a month or so before joining the Pittsburgh Recorder Society!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In class we had a &amp;ldquo;review&amp;rdquo; of basic concepts of Baroque flute technique such as the correct &lt;em&gt;embouchure&lt;/em&gt; adjustments to get the intonation right of all the various notes: for example, the F is sharp unless you adjust the embouchure, and the F-sharp is flat unless you adjust the embouchure in the other way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then we talked about &lt;em&gt;articulation&lt;/em&gt;. One new thing I learned here was to be aware of the &lt;em&gt;end&lt;/em&gt; of a note, very important compared with playing modern instruments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I took a lot of notes, as well as made annotations in the music we got.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;voice-class&#34;&gt;Voice class&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eric taught voice class. There was a good balance of men and women. He handed us spiral-bound books of musical selections.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/voice-eric.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Eric Haas&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/voice-men.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Other men in voice class&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We went through a bunch of songs, and I . It was tremendous fun. I had never in my life sight-sung before (!!!), so I was very nervous. I tried not to let on that I was a total novice (unlike everyone else there). I took a lot of notes on what was tricky and marked up the song book for further study.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The somewhat nerve-wracking thing was that no men were really tenors, and a bunch sang bass, so Eric, Chris, and I sang tenor. I&amp;rsquo;m a baritone, not a tenor: the high notes were scary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;lunch&#34;&gt;Lunch&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I totally stuffed myself for lunch. So much good food.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/monday-lunch.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;recorder-consort&#34;&gt;Recorder consort&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Emily was the instructor for my recorder consort class. I was put into a lower-level class because of being relatively new (having played recorder for less than two years). I didn&amp;rsquo;t mind, because I knew that I had much to learn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Emily focused a lot on things like where to breathe, and in paying attention to others in an ensemble. I learned to write in commas for breathing in music scores (in the flute class, Majbritt also emphasized finding the phrasing and the breathing, and this has been a theme at Pittsburgh Recorder Society meetings as well). I realized that I still had a lot to absorb from these lessons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Emily also told us to find the narrative in any music we played. It&amp;rsquo;s not just isolated notes; music has a push and pull.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;bass-ensemble&#34;&gt;Bass ensemble&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;James (whom I amusingly first encountered online through his &lt;a href=&#34;http://jnote.org/&#34;&gt;fantastic multi-track melodica videos&lt;/a&gt; before finding out that he teaches recorder at the Mideast workshop) led the bass ensemble. I still play bass recorder only very infrequently, so I was nervous, but joined the bass ensemble because I thought it would be fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;improvisation&#34;&gt;Improvisation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alan taught improvisation. I had never actually specifically learned improvisation techniques before, but want to eventually get truly serious about improvisation, so I was excited to take this class, which was quite participatory. He would describe a concept, such as the pentatonic scale, and then have us do something with it. The class was enthusiastic. I was actually pretty moved by how individual everyone&amp;rsquo;s inventiveness was, even doing basic things, and that helped me loosen up as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;medieval-fiddle&#34;&gt;Medieval fiddle&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a whim, I checked out the medieval fiddle class. I borrowed a medieval fiddle to take back to my room after class. (But it would turn out that the instrument had problems, and I had too much other stuff to do, and had never played a string instrument before, so I ended up returning it and not returning to the class.)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/medieval-fiddle.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;A medieval fiddle&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;dinner&#34;&gt;Dinner&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby came up to visit and joined me for dinner while on her way to mandolin orchestra rehearsal, which is actually close by.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ate an ice cream cone, but realizing that I was gaining a lot of weight already after 24 hours at LaRoche, I chose not to eat cake or cupcakes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;all-workshop-ensemble&#34;&gt;All-workshop ensemble&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Intense stuff. I took pages and pages of notes as Eric talked about different styles, phrasing, &amp;ldquo;painting&amp;rdquo;, dissonances, imitation, counterpoint, the significance of words in text, changes in meter, etc. We read through a lot of pieces to work on for the week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;english-country-dance-1&#34;&gt;English country dance&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We learned more stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;study&#34;&gt;Study!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, after all the classes into the evening, I got to spend some hours in my dorm room or across the hall in an empty meeting room used for classes in the day (since sometimes Mike was in the dorm room or going to bed earlier than me) doing what review of my notes I could, as well as practicing for each of my classes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was intense: I had been given so much to learn already after a single day! I was right in choosing to live on site rather than take the commuter option, because the commute from Pittsburgh would have been stressful and time-consuming for me, taking away energy and time I could spend on classes and preparation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;day-3-tuesday-july-17&#34;&gt;Day 3: Tuesday (July 17)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;flute&#34;&gt;Flute&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I learned about &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Notes_in%C3%A9gales&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;ingal&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; for the first time. I hadn&amp;rsquo;t know that this &amp;ldquo;swinging&amp;rdquo; of notes (familiar in jazz) also applied to Baroque music!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We continued our study of articulation. I learned a huge amount about &amp;ldquo;t&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;d&amp;rdquo; and runs of notes as well as leaps. It was very difficult for me to execute all this, so I tried to focus on one aspect at a time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;voice&#34;&gt;Voice&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More work, and a lot of fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;recorder-consort-1&#34;&gt;Recorder consort&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reinforcing the technique points we learned yesterday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;bass-class&#34;&gt;Bass class&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It continued being a challenge for me to alternate between reading bass clef for bass recorder and reading treble clef for it as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;improvisation-1&#34;&gt;Improvisation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Musical structure such as ABA, ABACA (rondo).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;nap-time&#34;&gt;Nap time&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cutting out medieval violin meant having a block of nap time, much-needed!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;dinner-1&#34;&gt;Dinner&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I created a pattern of eating ice cream every day at dinner, and continued to gain weight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;all-workshop-ensemble-singing&#34;&gt;All-workshop ensemble: singing?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the pieces we went through could optionally be sung, so Eric asked us to think of whether we wanted to sing or play an instrument for our performance on Friday. I was intrigued by the option to sing. &amp;ldquo;Ecco l&amp;rsquo;Aurora&amp;rdquo; was very interesting to sing, but also rather challenging to me, with its leaps and modulations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But because of the relative lack of tenor volunteers, I decided I would switch from playing tenor recorder and work on singing it on Friday. I was partly inspired by Chris&amp;rsquo;s example, and also by the guy sitting next to me who decided to sing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;english-country-dance-2&#34;&gt;English country dance&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We learned a new dance, but also started focusing on improving on a particular dance for Friday&amp;rsquo;s performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;study-1&#34;&gt;Study&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was practicing in the empty meeting room until at 11 PM, Charles, whose dorm room was actually right next door, told me he was going to sleep. Oops! If I didn&amp;rsquo;t do English country dance, I could practice earlier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;day-4-wednesday-july-18&#34;&gt;Day 4: Wednesday (July 18)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;flute-1&#34;&gt;Flute&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Very detailed articulation instruction. Also, notes on hemiolas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;master-class&#34;&gt;Master class&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was very excited to attend the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Master_class&#34;&gt;master class&lt;/a&gt;. I had never attended a master class before, actually, although I had seen some videos of the concept.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that Karen had prepared a piece for Baroque flute for the master class, and Mike had prepared a piece for recorder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I took a huge number of notes. For each of them, I first took notes while they played their pieces, then I took more notes as the instructors gave feedback. I found it quite useful to compare what they observed with what I had observed independently (or not noticed at all). The whole experience was tremendously instructive for me, giving me a huge amount of information to apply to my own playing. I don&amp;rsquo;t know if I have the courage to expose myself to scrutiny in public like this. I&amp;rsquo;m certainly appreciative of Karen and Mike doing so!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I noticed some observations in common among the instructors and for both Karen and Mike. The gist of the advice:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;add more variety in &lt;em&gt;articulation&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;play with more &lt;em&gt;freedom&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;find and express the &lt;em&gt;shape&lt;/em&gt; and melodic line&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;look for the meaning of leaps and &lt;em&gt;dissonance&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found these insights profoundly useful, and found it inspiring to see Karen and Mike work to make some changes in their playing in response to the instructors&amp;rsquo; feedback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;karen&#34;&gt;Karen&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Karen prepared one of the twelve &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/12_Fantasias_for_Solo_Flute_%28Telemann%29&#34;&gt;Telemann fantasias for solo flute&lt;/a&gt;, no. 2.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/master-class-karen.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Karen&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/master-class-karen-majbritt.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Majbritt feedback for Karen&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h4 id=&#34;mike&#34;&gt;Mike&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By coincidence, Mike played another of the Telemann fantasias for solo flute, no. 10, but he played it on alto recorder instead of flute.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/master-class-mike.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Mike&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There was a funny moment in which Mike used his leg to play a high F-sharp. Later, Emily and James showed him a good technique hint, preparing the F-sharp by bringing up the leg already in anticipation, and then bringing the head down toward the leg instead of vice versa.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/master-class-mike-james-leg.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Mike raising leg, with James and Emily&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;lunch-1&#34;&gt;Lunch&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After lunch, Mike and I helped Chris move his harpsichord. (Chris drove his own harpsichord up from home and it&amp;rsquo;s used for many sessions at the workshop.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;recorder-consort-2&#34;&gt;Recorder consort&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People had been leaving our recorder consort class one by one; Wednesday, we were down to five! I wondered why this was going on. Admittedly, we were moving slowly through the music, because a couple of us were more on the beginner side and had trouble sight reading, staying with the score, keeping fingerings straight. I myself had silently considered switching, but I found the &amp;ldquo;slower&amp;rdquo; pace an opportunity to really focus on trying to work on various basic things that are more important than &amp;ldquo;getting through&amp;rdquo; a lot of musical selections. I really needed to get down what I was learning about breath, resonance, and intonation, as well as ensemble unity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;free-time&#34;&gt;Free time!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wednesday there is scheduled &amp;ldquo;free time&amp;rdquo; during which there are no classes. I was totally exhausted by this point in the week and napped for two and a half hours!! Then I finally went outside for a 40-minute run, in my new Invisible Shoes (which I wore around daily and got a lot of comments on); I had originally intended to get regular exercise in every day while at camp, but had simply felt overwhelmed by the desire to make the most of my music classes and practice (at least I did do an hour of English country dance every evening).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;white-elephant-sale&#34;&gt;White Elephant Sale&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After dinner, I browsed around at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/White_Elephant_Sale&#34;&gt;White Elephant Sale&lt;/a&gt;. I kicked myself for having totally forgotten to bring some stuff to donate to it. I was amused that Helen managed to get rid of a particular item that she had wanted out of her home for some time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;chris-and-harpsichord&#34;&gt;Chris and harpsichord&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had been so busy that I had not bothered to think about signing up for playing with Chris on harpsichord. Unfortunately, by the time I checked the signup sheet, I saw that it was full (empty slots conflicted with my class time).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/harpsichord-signup.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Chris harpsichord signup sheet&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There were signup sheets all along for other stuff too, such as people wanting to find others to play with. That is actually a large part of the appeal of the workshop. I didn&amp;rsquo;t participate in any of that because as a newcomer, I was focused on exploring classes. But obviously, those who had come to the workshop for years and decades did not necessarily need or want to spend all their time on classes.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/other-signup.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Other signup sheets&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;faculty-concert&#34;&gt;Faculty concert&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another highlight of Wednesday was the faculty concert. This was great. Bagpipes, recorders, Renaissance flutes, Baroque flutes, harpsichord, viola da gamba, even sackbut! It was a real treat to see all our instructors performing.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/bagpipes.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Alan on bagpipes&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/faculty-concert-2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Group&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/faculty-concert-3.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Group&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/faculty-concert-james-majbritt.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;James and Majbritt in duet&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I was intrigued by Emily playing Debussy&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Syrinx&amp;rdquo; on a special tenor recorder.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/emily-syrinx.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Emily playing Syrinx on special tenor recorder&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/chris-harpsichord.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Chris solo on harpsichord&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/faculty-concert-flutes.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Eric, Emily, Majbritt on flutes&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/judith-viol.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Judith on viol&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A short video clip from the faculty concert (I found out that my phone made an unstoppable annoying click when taking video, so I never used my phone again for video after this; other videos I post here came from the camera Abby brought on Friday):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/vpXVEf7NfSw&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;practice&#34;&gt;Practice&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally I got time to practice. There was a lot of stuff to prepare for the Friday concert.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;day-5-thursday-july-19&#34;&gt;Day 5: Thursday (July 19)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;breakfast&#34;&gt;Breakfast&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of the considerable weight gain (approximately &lt;em&gt;four pounds&lt;/em&gt; so far since arrival), I decided to stop eating potatoes (which seemed to be available in some form at every meal).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;flute-2&#34;&gt;Flute&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More technique. Lip and tongue placement, different scales. We finally decided on what to play for the concert, a selection by Dittersdorf. I was one of those on the easiest part, the third part of the trio, playing &amp;ldquo;bass&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;voice-1&#34;&gt;Voice&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We worked through a bunch more selections while continuing to refine the one we had decided to perform on Friday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, it came in really handy this week that I have at least basic competence in French, Italian, Latin, and German, because we sang in all these languages!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;bass&#34;&gt;Bass&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got to class early enough (a rarity, since usually I was rushing from voice class) to take a photo.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/bass-setup.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Mike and James&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;By the way, since I had hardly played bass before coming to this workshop, I hadn&amp;rsquo;t realized that my bass tended to be sharp and I learned I had to keep the head joint pulled out to a certain degree. Useful to finally find that out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;improvisation-2&#34;&gt;Improvisation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We did blues stuff, and Alan pulled out his guitar to give us chords as the rest of us took turns on recorder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;special-mini-class-on-practice-techniques&#34;&gt;Special mini-class on practice techniques&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I attended a one-session class on practice techniques by Emily. I found this tremendously useful and took a lot of notes. Some of the key ideas:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;don&amp;rsquo;t practice a mistake&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;importance of warmup with focus (physical but also mental)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;go slow, do it right&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;break down difficult tasks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it all starts with the mind: first decide and know what you want to accomplish, then figure out the physical means&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;repetition and grouping into units&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;isolation of aspects of technique&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;classify goals as long, medium, and short term&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;all-workshop-ensemble-1&#34;&gt;All-workshop ensemble&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had a shorter session, in order to make more time for the following ad hoc student concert.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eric had singers lined up in front so that we would run through &amp;ldquo;Ecco l&amp;rsquo;Aurora&amp;rdquo; as it was going to be presented on Friday: I stood with Chris for tenor and found it tremendously helpful to have him at my side so that when I was uncertain or got lost, I had someone to anchor back to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instrumentalists were reminded to play as though singing, articulating consistently with the words of the text.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;ad-hoc-student-concert&#34;&gt;Ad hoc student concert&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of participants in the workshop look forward to this as one of their highlights of the experience. I did not sign up to perform for this because I was focused entirely on classes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each selection was short, and there were a whole lot of individuals and groups that came up to present something. Some people had prepared something before the workshop. Others had met up and were playing for the first time together. It was a fun time.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/ad-hoc-audience.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Ad hoc student concert audience&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;practice-1&#34;&gt;Practice&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally at 10 PM I started music practice!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;day-6-friday-july-20-final-day&#34;&gt;Day 6: Friday (July 20), final day&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;flute-3&#34;&gt;Flute&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We reviewed what we were playing for the concert, but also moved on to work some more on music we were not performing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;voice-2&#34;&gt;Voice&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We went over the two pieces we were to perform at the concert, then closed the class with work on some more pieces in the book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;recorder-consort-3&#34;&gt;Recorder consort&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Final review.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;bass-1&#34;&gt;Bass&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We did a lot of intonation adjustment, since many of us were sharp!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;James had particular ideas about performance presentation, and told us to hold up our instruments after we were done playing, watch out for extraneous sucking, and refrain from bringing too much junk (extra clothing, shoe boxes, etc.) with us. Also, we were to bring only the two pages of music we were to play, not binders of all our music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;improvisation-3&#34;&gt;Improvisation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Final class. We did not plan to perform as a group in the concert.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;dinner-2&#34;&gt;Dinner&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby had come up for dinner on Monday. I hadn&amp;rsquo;t seen her since then, and she came up to see the final concert. I was happy she was able to make it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;final-concert&#34;&gt;Final concert&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final student concert showcased what everyone had worked on so hard for the week. Because I took so many classes, I was in several groups that performed. Here are just a sample of photos and videos from the concert. I apologize for not having full coverage, but as I was occupied with performing, after my first performance, I completely stopped messing around with my phone and just focused on enjoying others&amp;rsquo; performances and getting ready to switch in when one of my groups was up! Abby did take some photos and videos, but only when I was involved!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/harps.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/recorder-eric.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/recorder-eric-2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h4 id=&#34;me-in-flute&#34;&gt;Me in flute&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby took this photo of me in Majbritt&amp;rsquo;s flute group:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/flute-majbritt.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h4 id=&#34;me-in-voice-ensemble&#34;&gt;Me in voice ensemble&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eric tuning for the voice ensemble (I&amp;rsquo;m standing next to Chris as usual):&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/voice-tuning.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Clips from our two selections:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/SfptMbkdwsw&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/nF-5ph82sJ4&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Immediately after the voice ensemble performance, Abby commented to me that during performance, I ended up &amp;ldquo;hiding&amp;rdquo; with my score in my hands rising up and up, partially covering my face. Admittedly, I was very nervous, but also, I was trying to cover up my inability to keep a straight face while barking on the tenor dog line!! (For the final all-workshop ensemble performance, I made sure not to hide.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;bass-ensemble-1&#34;&gt;Bass ensemble&lt;/h4&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/bass-final.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.mideastearlymusic.addr.com/P1160081.jpeg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/NY8YQfYErfc&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;concluding-all-workshop-ensemble-performance&#34;&gt;Concluding all-workshop ensemble performance&lt;/h4&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/all-workshop-final.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Me and Chris:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/all-workshop-final-franklin-chris.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.mideastearlymusic.addr.com/P1160084.jpeg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;All-workshop ensemble&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.mideastearlymusic.addr.com/P1160083.jpeg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;All-workshop ensemble&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/CBGZlAWB7BI&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;party&#34;&gt;Party&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a party afterwards with unique tasty treats that Abby and I attended, and she got to meet more of my instructors and classmates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People started to pack up and prepare to leave. It was a long week, but what a fun one!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was, of course, asked whether I planned to come back next year. I said I would like to, but could not yet commit to that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;more-photos&#34;&gt;More photos&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More photos of the whole workshop week can be found &lt;a href=&#34;http://mideastearlymusic.addr.com/newpglogo.htm&#34;&gt;here at the workshop site&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;saturday-at-home-thoughts&#34;&gt;Saturday at home: thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I weighed myself the next day. I&amp;rsquo;d gained a total of &lt;em&gt;seven pounds&lt;/em&gt; in five days. On the one hand, I had gone in underweight, so it was good I finally made up for that, but now I was a bit overweight, as Abby noticed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reflecting on the week, I resolved to put into practice everything I had learned at the workshop. It was going to take time to develop new habits, make use of new awareness, but I now knew of the path forward. Before attending the workshop, I had gotten advice here and there that was useful, and I had read up on things by myself, but there is nothing like being immersed in an environment of total learning, feedback, and collaboration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Attending this workshop has given me fresh concrete direction and musical goals as well as the determination to push on and not settle for anything less than doing what I can to musically express myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;thanks&#34;&gt;Thanks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am grateful to Marilyn, all the instructors (especially those of my classes: Majbritt, Emily, Eric, James, Alan), my classmates (especially Chris for voice, without whom I would have felt lost), the staff of LaRoche College, and the members of the Pittsburgh Recorder Society who first told me of this workshop and also attended (Helen, Annie, Mike, Sam, Maggie who danced with me). Mike was a considerate dorm roommate for the week. And I am particularly grateful that Abby supported me in my quest to improve my musicianship and enabled me to attend the workshop, and also visited me twice for dinner and to see me in the final student concert.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had an amazing time at the Mideast early music workshop. I am going to continue my study of Baroque flute and recorder, and voice as well, and do more with improvisation. Now that I have seen and worked with more really good musicians up front (both instructors and students at the workshop: I noticed that quite a few of the students themselves are actually professional musicians on non-early instruments), I have a much clearer idea of how I want to sound and what kind of technique I need to develop in order to make that into reality. Mostly, I feel that some kind of psychological block has been removed and that I now have real courage where I still didn&amp;rsquo;t have it before attending the workshop: courage to experiment, to fail, to continue.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>