<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Barber on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/barber/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Barber on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/barber/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>The growth of loyalty after seventeen years</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/07/22/the-growth-of-loyalty-after-seventeen-years/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2014 21:44:11 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/07/22/the-growth-of-loyalty-after-seventeen-years/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Tonight I finally got a haircut.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For two weeks I&amp;rsquo;d been looking for my &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/barber/&#34;&gt;barber&lt;/a&gt; Joe, of Harry&amp;rsquo;s Barber Shoppe in Squirrel Hill; I was due for my haircut. I&amp;rsquo;d called Joe&amp;rsquo;s phone number from work in the afternoon. I&amp;rsquo;d driven by on the way home (the shop is just a block away from home). I&amp;rsquo;d taken a walk on Saturday to see if he was open. No sign of him. I was worried. I began imagining the worst.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not kidding when I tell people that I don&amp;rsquo;t know what I&amp;rsquo;d do without Joe to cut my hair. He&amp;rsquo;s been the only one to cut my hair in the past seventeen years, apart from that one time he broke his hand and was out of commission for a while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first thought when I wondered whether Joe was OK was, if he was gone, I would miss not only a great cut (after the first couple of times in 1997, he figured out how to do things just the way I like), but also some kind of relationship. Since Joe is a lot older than me, I know that one day I will have to find a new barber; I was just thinking that when that day comes, I don&amp;rsquo;t want just a haircut, but I want some kind of relationship. Joe doesn&amp;rsquo;t just cut my hair. He asks me how my life is going; he was there before I was married, and now he inquires about Abby, whom he&amp;rsquo;s met, that time when I was waiting so long for my turn that she walked over and brought me dinner. He knows the structure of my head and the properties of my hair more than I do. We take turns guessing who&amp;rsquo;s singing the songs on his favorite radio station; I&amp;rsquo;ve absorbed some of his oldies into my consciousness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;lucky&#34;&gt;Lucky&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The whole haircut experience is about much more than my walking out with less hair. That&amp;rsquo;s why I was relieved to find him accidentally after an evening run in Frick Park that ended with my spotting in the distance the light in Joe&amp;rsquo;s shop and stopping by and seeing him there. It was already late in the evening, nearly 8:00 PM already, but he said he would take me (he was finishing up one guy in the chair), so I ran back home to change out of my running gear and get my wallet and return to the shop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joe said he was OK. He&amp;rsquo;s continued to have back trouble and reduced his work, but he&amp;rsquo;s still around. It does not even occur to me to get angry with him for causing me to look for him for two weeks. I&amp;rsquo;m simply grateful he&amp;rsquo;s OK and able to work and cheerful. He thanks me for being patient and returning to him again and again. That is all. The rest is philosophical banter about what is important in life, and chuckling to myself as I easily identify &amp;ldquo;drunky&amp;rdquo; Dean Martin on the radio singing &amp;ldquo;Ain&amp;rsquo;t That a Kick in the Head?&amp;rdquo; Such a dated song, I think, but it has a certain charm and who else could sing it in perfect character besides Dean Martin?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/2zBszbgkH8g&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;questions&#34;&gt;Questions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Are you loyal to someone who cuts your hair? What would you do (or have done) if that person is no longer present in your life?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A haircut leading to my playing &#34;I&#39;ll Always Love You&#34; on flute</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/08/08/a-haircut-leading-to-my-playing-ill-always-love-you-on-flute/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Aug 2013 22:17:12 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/08/08/a-haircut-leading-to-my-playing-ill-always-love-you-on-flute/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/haircut-2013-08-08/floor.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;New floor&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/haircut-2013-08-08/wall.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Celebrity wall&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I got a haircut from my barber Joe, whom I have been seeing &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/29/my-favorite-barber/&#34;&gt;for sixteen years now&lt;/a&gt; since moving to Pittsburgh. Unexpectedly, this led me to &amp;ldquo;discovering&amp;rdquo; a piece of music and going home to play it on flute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was happy to arrive with only one other person in line, just getting into the chair, because Joe has a policy of not taking reservations, and &amp;ldquo;if you leave, you lose your turn&amp;rdquo;:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/haircut-2013-08-08/lose-your-turn.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Lose your turn&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In practice, Joe usually takes 20-25 minutes per person, I figured on being out within 50 minutes. Since I was pretty exhausted because of a tough week, I took the opportunity to do some napping. In practice, I don&amp;rsquo;t really sleep, but do get rest. Since Joe always has his oldies radio station on, I try to enjoy the music (which is not the kind of music I ordinarily listen to these days) and identify songs and singers I recognize.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;music&#34;&gt;Music&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I heard someone sing a song that I recognized but had never truly known. I think it&amp;rsquo;s a beautiful song, actually (from a melodic and harmonic point of view), although horribly cheesy if you pay attention to the lyrics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recognized the song as being in &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/17/st-patricks-day-party-playing-tin-whistle-and-flute/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;I Used to Play Flute&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, although I did not remember the title. I did remember really enjoying playing it on flute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this evening, after dinner, I found the song in the book. It&amp;rsquo;s called &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/I%27ll_Always_Love_You_%28Taylor_Dayne_song%29&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;ll Always Love You&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. I played through the song with the CD track accompaniment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also looked for a sung performance on YouTube, and found one, by the musician who actually created it in 1987, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.taylordayne.com/&#34;&gt;Taylor Dayne&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/0bGdnMnq40s&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t think this this is who I heard on Joe&amp;rsquo;s radio station. Taylor Dayne sings more wildly than whoever was on the radio (or maybe in my half-asleep state, I wasn&amp;rsquo;t paying enough attention). This is not the kind of music I was listening to in 1988, and I have to confess I cringed when watching this video, because although the performance is quite good, her style of singing is just not really to my taste! I prefer the song as an instrumental.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;tito-nieves&#34;&gt;Tito Nieves&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was very amused to find a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jukebo.com/tito-nieves/music-clip,i-ll-always-love-you,u8quz.html&#34;&gt;salsa cover of this song&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tito_Nieves&#34;&gt;Tito Nieves&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s pretty good, actually:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;width:480px;&#34;&gt;&lt;iframe src=&#34;http://www.ultimedia.com/swf/iframe_pub.php?width=480&amp;height=385&amp;id=u8quz&amp;url_artist=http://www.jukebo.com/tito-nieves/music-clip,i-ll-always-love-you,u8quz.html&amp;autoplay=0&amp;mdtk=04516441&amp;site=.fr&#34; width=&#34;480&#34; height=&#34;385&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; scrolling=&#34;no&#34; marginwidth=&#34;0&#34; marginheight=&#34;0&#34; hspace=&#34;0&#34; vspace=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;SPAN style=&#34;color:#000000; font:bold 11px verdana;&#34;&gt;See all &lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jukebo.com/tito-nieves/music-clip,i-ll-always-love-you,u8quz.html&#34; style=&#34;color:#000000;text-decoration:underline;  font:bold 11px verdana;&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;music videos Tito Nieves&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;haircut-photos&#34;&gt;Haircut photos&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, I was delighted not only to have gotten a haircut, but also learned something about a piece of music that had up till now only been a CD track and a flute part that I had played through months ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/haircut-2013-08-08/before.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin before haircut&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;After:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/haircut-2013-08-08/after.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin after haircut&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Boston Marathon tragedy: please avoid the news porn</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/04/15/boston-marathon-tragedy-please-avoid-the-news-porn/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Apr 2013 19:49:22 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/04/15/boston-marathon-tragedy-please-avoid-the-news-porn/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Since I am a runner (and happening to be in the last stages of training for my second Pittsburgh Marathon, which is coming in less than three weeks), I woke up this morning knowing that it was Boston Marathon day. Also, by sheer coincidence, a fellow Pittsburgher I have never met but follow on Twitter happened to tweet a photo of his running gear while ready to run in Boston, and happened to mention some sock sleeves that he wears that I had never seen before, and I tweeted him for the first time in my life, and I got a reply from him after he finished, and I went and ordered a pair of these &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cepcompression.com/1922-Allsports-Sleeves.aspx&#34;&gt;sock sleeves online&lt;/a&gt;, since I have a tendency toward calf cramping in long distance races.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it was particularly eerie and somewhat personal to me when in the afternoon I heard from my office mate at work that the Boston Marathon had been bombed and people were dead and horribly injured.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first thought was, &lt;strong&gt;this is fucking insane&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My second thought was extreme anger that criminals would do such a thing, and sadness for the runners and spectators who were so victimized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My third thought was, &amp;ldquo;Uh oh, here we go again: time for news porn&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;9-11-and-news&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;9&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;11&lt;/sub&gt; and news&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because I remember &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/September_11_attacks&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;9&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;11&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some excerpts from my journal on September 11, 2001 (at this time in my life I was jotting down journal entries regularly during the waking day):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;11:12: &amp;ldquo;Oh G-d!!!!!!!!!!!  The World Trade Center has been destroyed.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;11:36: &amp;ldquo;Things will never be the same again in this country.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;12:11: &amp;ldquo;Can&amp;rsquo;t let terrorists disrupt my life.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;18:28: &amp;ldquo;Wait, are we attacking Afghanistan??????&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;22:14: &amp;ldquo;Watched some TV footage for the first time.  Disturbing.  Especially people jumping out of the buildings.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;23:31: &amp;ldquo;Other people on &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zephyr_%28protocol%29&#34;&gt;zephyr&lt;/a&gt; [an internal chat system at Carnegie Mellon University] are saying they watched more TV today than all year.  Same with me.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, during this whole time, I did immediately try to call my sister who lived and worked in New York City, and of course failed. She reached me eventually and said she was OK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I realized something that day. I realized that I could not let relentless news porn rule my life. There was no benefit to my seeing again and again footage about the tragic terrorist attacks and all the speculations, the anger, the crying. I did not quit watching TV that evening, but did realize that I was being manipulated in a way that did not help me or help the world, really.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much later, I learned that a high school classmate of mine had died on &lt;sup&gt;9&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;11&lt;/sub&gt;. And a college classmate was across the street when it happened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;news&#34;&gt;News&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point, years later, I did completely quit following news. By this, I mean that I stopped watching news on TV, I stopped reading printed newspapers, and I stopped reading online news sites as well. Seriously. It has improved my life. Periodically I try to spread the message of news avoidance, having seen the damage that following news has done to some family members and friends, without noticeable benefit in return.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, just yesterday on Twitter I retweeted &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.guardian.co.uk/media/2013/apr/12/news-is-bad-rolf-dobelli&#34;&gt;yet another article on news avoidance&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you haven&amp;rsquo;t done the experiment of avoiding news, your first thought might be, &amp;ldquo;Franklin must be an ignoramus who doesn&amp;rsquo;t care about the world or know what goes on in it&amp;rdquo;. But actually, I am not completely ignorant of news: I simply have some filters. I do actively follow blogs, Twitter, Facebook, and Google+, and so I implicitly get a curated summary of whatever news is forwarded around through those channels. I see links and check the headlines, and I can choose to ignore or follow up on the news. And I selectively retweet what I find interesting and &lt;em&gt;useful&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, the social media has for the past couple of hours become overwhelmingly dominated by a lot of emotions over the Boston Marathon terrorist attack, so as I write this, I am imposing a complete blackout on blogs, Twitter, Facebook, and Google+.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;local&#34;&gt;Local&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The local and federal authorities are, I presume, doing what they can to aid the victims and seek out the criminals, and following their every move would not help me be useful. If this tragedy had happened in Pittsburgh, then I would be monitoring the situation much more closely, in case I can actually be of direct aid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;couldn-t-avoid-tv-today&#34;&gt;Couldn&amp;rsquo;t avoid TV today&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, by coincidence, I could not avoid TV today. This evening, I was in the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/10/26/yet-another-haircut-from-joe-always-worth-the-wait/&#34;&gt;barber shop&lt;/a&gt; getting a haircut, and not only could people not refrain from commenting on the tragedy, but he also had the radio on and turned on his TV as well. I refused to look at the TV screen, but could not help repeatedly hearing about body parts being blown off, eardrums being perforated, panic, the audio clips of explosions and screaming, again and again. I remained silent and maintained my composure until my haircut was done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-media-blackout&#34;&gt;A media blackout&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am taking a break from the Web overall for the rest of the evening. Last I checked my social media feeds, they are now all about the Boston Marathon attacks. I cannot help anyone by sitting in front of my computer getting all emotional and confused following all these feeds. I humbly recommend that you consider doing this also.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have not found news porn to be useful in helping me cope with tragedy or in enabling me be of aid to those who need help. Given that, I am opting out of the news frenzy.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Yet another haircut from Joe: always worth the wait</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/10/26/yet-another-haircut-from-joe-always-worth-the-wait/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Oct 2012 19:39:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/10/26/yet-another-haircut-from-joe-always-worth-the-wait/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;So today I got another haircut from Joe Feldman, at Harry&amp;rsquo;s Barber Shoppe in Squirrel Hill. Almost exactly a year ago, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/29/my-favorite-barber/&#34;&gt;I fondly described my visit to Joe&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/a&gt;. Today, I still make the time to get my haircuts from him, after &lt;strong&gt;fifteen years&lt;/strong&gt; now of having my hair cut only by him (other than one occasion when he was closed because of breaking his hand), on average of once every two months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today was probably my longest wait ever, &lt;em&gt;over two hours&lt;/em&gt;! But it was worth it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-wait&#34;&gt;The wait&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Late in the afternoon, I had called from work to verify that he was open, and he had said that nobody was in line, so I rushed to leave work early to take advantage of the opportunity for a shorter wait, but by the time I arrived, there were already &lt;em&gt;six&lt;/em&gt; people ahead of me in line, one in the chair. Since I knew from experience that he takes about twenty minutes per person, I knew I was in for a two-hour wait, and I was right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And guys kept on coming in who clearly were going to have to wait for up to three hours. Wow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-i-spent-the-time&#34;&gt;How I spent the time&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;smartphone&#34;&gt;Smartphone&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tend to get my haircut from Joe on Friday if possible, to end the work week relaxing. Since &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/22/paradox-i-will-observe-the-national-day-of-unplugging-but-just-bought-my-first-smartphone-this-week/&#34;&gt;I have had a smartphone now for seven months&lt;/a&gt;, many occasions that used to involve my idly &amp;ldquo;waiting&amp;rdquo; are now opportunities to be productive. I caught up on reading and writing a lot of email (yes, it has actually become feasible to do this since I bought &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.swiftkey.net/&#34;&gt;SwiftKey&lt;/a&gt;), as well as reading archived Web links that I had saved up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;nap&#34;&gt;Nap&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I took a nap. It&amp;rsquo;s been a long week, and it&amp;rsquo;s going to be a long weekend!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;music&#34;&gt;Music&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After I was done napping, I kind of sat back and listened to the oldies music that Joe always has on. It&amp;rsquo;s an interesting game trying to identify who is singing, because all the music is &amp;ldquo;before my time&amp;rdquo; (as Joe pointed out even to another guy sitting near me who was older than me, who was also playing this game). That said, I can and did easily identify Frank Sinatra, Nat King Cole, Elvis, and various others from their voices and styles. I did not identify Englebert Humperdinck; I still don&amp;rsquo;t really know who he is, and have never actively listened to his music (unlike the vocalists I just mentioned).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amusingly, there was one song in which I didn&amp;rsquo;t actually immediately identify the singer, but a guy gave a hint, and then I easily got the answer: &lt;a href=&#34;http://olivianewton-john.com/&#34;&gt;Olivia Newton-John&lt;/a&gt;. For once, someone who is not as far removed from &amp;ldquo;my time&amp;rdquo;! I saw her as a kid when my friend Lisa in elementary school in second/third grades invited me to go with her to see the premiere of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grease_(film)&#34;&gt;Grease&lt;/a&gt; (her mother took us to see it). It was way too grown-up a movie for me to get at the time, but the tunes were catchy (and for quite some time all my classmates were singing them at school). So I actually have some nostalgia for Olivia Newton-John&amp;rsquo;s singing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;politics&#34;&gt;Politics&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I generally stay out of political discussions, especially during election times such as these. But two guys were expressing various opinions. I kept my mouth shut.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;place-in-line&#34;&gt;Place in line&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the guys said he needed to go out for five minutes and would come back. There was a very brief and slight scene in which Joe warned him that if somebody came in the meantime, he would lose his place, because there are no reservations and that&amp;rsquo;s the rule. After the guy colorfully called Joe a &amp;ldquo;gangster&amp;rdquo;, Joe explained how being too lenient in the past had led to bad situations in which people came and went and wanted their place back, etc. I can totally imagine that. Rules are rules. Joe has his rules, and I respect them, and they work, however anachronistic and demanding they might be in this fast-paced, multitasking age.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, I had actually lost my &amp;ldquo;original&amp;rdquo; place in line today, because I had showed up expecting no line, when I saw five in line. So I had gone back home (just a block away) to get a snack to bring to eat, and a book to maybe read, and when I got back, a guy walked in the door a split second before I did, so I became seventh in line rather than sixth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I treasure my visits to Joe once every two months. I get not only a &lt;em&gt;terrific&lt;/em&gt; haircut, but also enjoy the periodic trip down memory lane through the oldies radio station and the chance to enjoy the &lt;em&gt;slowness&lt;/em&gt; of life that the space encourages and even enforces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;bonus-videos&#34;&gt;Bonus videos&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In honor of Olivia Newton-John, here&amp;rsquo;s a 1978 live performance by her of &amp;ldquo;Hopelessly Devoted to You&amp;rdquo;. Laugh if you want, but I &lt;em&gt;love&lt;/em&gt; this song, and I love her performance above all other singers&amp;rsquo; covers, even to this day!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/lR93L8sUMNg&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But here&amp;rsquo;s some random guy on YouTube who sings it really quite beautifully while playing the guitar:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/3T75DDSa48k&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My favorite barber; fourteen years of haircuts and counting</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/10/29/my-favorite-barber/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Oct 2011 23:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/10/29/my-favorite-barber/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I got a haircut today from Joe. Every two months (with one exception) for the past fourteen years since moving to Pittsburgh, I have walked down to &lt;a href=&#34;http://trueslant.com/matthewnewton/2010/06/18/swan-songs-joe-feldman-and-the-legacy-of-harrys-barber-shoppe/&#34;&gt;Harry&amp;rsquo;s Barber Shoppe&lt;/a&gt; in Squirrel Hill, to take a seat and wait in line for my turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joe Feldman doesn&amp;rsquo;t take appointments or reservations. You come, you stay, and depending on how many people are in front of you in line, you might sit around for up to two hours. In this fast-paced world, why would anyone wait so long?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A world of reasons.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/haircut/franklin-before.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin before haircut&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;history&#34;&gt;History&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To step into the door from busy Murray Avenue is to enter a time machine. There are faded memorabilia everywhere.  Letters of thanks on the wall, signed posters of Pittsburgh icons who are no longer with us, other celebrities, children&amp;rsquo;s artwork.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it&amp;rsquo;s not just artwork. Joe always has his radio playing, tuned to his favorite oldies station. It is impossible not to be transported back to the days of Frank Sinatra, Johnny Mathis, and earlier musicians who go so far back that I have no idea who they are. Another time, another place? But not another place: Joe has always been in Pittsburgh, and his late father Harry (of the shop&amp;rsquo;s name) before him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The atmosphere here varies, depending on who is in. Today, on a late Saturday afternoon shortly before closing time, it&amp;rsquo;s just a young guy in the chair finishing up, me, and an older guy waiting after me. It&amp;rsquo;s not always like this. Maybe it&amp;rsquo;s the snow. Sometimes it&amp;rsquo;s six guys waiting (hence the two hour wait). Sometimes there are really old guys who need help getting up and through the door. Sometimes there&amp;rsquo;s a kid. Sometimes there are (gasp!) women present, either waiting or just in to chat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;men&#34;&gt;Men&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it&amp;rsquo;s when there are no women and children when the old-time atmosphere is most entertaining and touching. This is a place where we men seem to end up talking about personal matters in our lives, whether marriages or relationships or jobs or failing health or being proud new grandparents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joe always shares his quiet humor and wisdom: sometimes talk gets raunchy, sometimes it gets loud and angry; but Joe has seen it all. He has a gift for understanding where people are coming from, and keeping things under control while letting us be ourselves, be human, be men. The old-fashioned barber shop is one of the places where men feel an invisible bond even with strangers, where we allow ourselves to be vulnerable with them because we know, no matter what our race is, our age, our religion, we are brothers!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;today&#34;&gt;Today&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The guy in the chair is young, from Turkey. From what I can gather, he arrived in Pittsburgh just a few months ago. A lot of graduate students come to Joe for a haircut. (Heck, I was a graduate student when I started getting a haircut from him.)  He and Joe are engaged in lively conversation about all sorts of things that, well, I cannot share here. It is amazing how private topics are so easy to discuss in the shop, even with someone you just met.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tend not to talk much here (I&amp;rsquo;m more of a listener and observer), although I remember when, in a rare moment of self-disclosure some years ago, I brought up my anxieties about proposing to Abby.  I don&amp;rsquo;t actually remember what I said or what Joe said in response, but one way or another he calmed me down.  I also remember when I told him I was getting my last haircut before my wedding, and he spent a lot of time giving me the best haircut he could.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not that he doesn&amp;rsquo;t always give me a great haircut!  Apart from perhaps the first two times when I was new, and he was still trying to figure out my hair (all my barbers in my life have had to adapt to my coarse and stubborn hair that tends to stick out when very short) and my preferences, I&amp;rsquo;ve had nothing to complain about at all. He knows how I like it, and doesn&amp;rsquo;t have to ask anything any more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-one-time-i-missed-his-haircut&#34;&gt;The one time I missed his haircut&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One winter I found that Joe&amp;rsquo;s shop was closed for a long time. I worried, because twice in my life, before I moved to Pittsburgh, a favorite barber of mine had closed up because of death! So I had to get my hair cut elsewhere, and I went to a local SuperCuts, where the whole experience was sterile and cold, plus I got a crappy haircut.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was so happy that the next time I was due, I saw Joe working again. He had slipped on ice that season and broken his hand!  But he had recovered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here I am, done after half an hour in the chair:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/haircut/franklin-after.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin after haircut&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You can see in the mirror the guy after me taking my photo for me. He said he used to get his hair cut by Joe&amp;rsquo;s father Harry here sixty years ago. Now that&amp;rsquo;s history!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2012-10-26&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-10-26)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A year later, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/10/26/yet-another-haircut-from-joe-always-worth-the-wait/&#34;&gt;another haircut to remember&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>