<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Vonda Wright on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/vonda-wright/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Vonda Wright on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/vonda-wright/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>A comeback from Pittsburgh Marathon overtraining</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/04/06/comeback-from-pittsburgh-marathon-overtraining/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Apr 2013 15:59:23 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/04/06/comeback-from-pittsburgh-marathon-overtraining/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Last week I reported on running Just A Short Run, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/30/report-on-just-a-short-run-my-first-half-marathon-in-nine-years/&#34;&gt;my first half marathon in nine years&lt;/a&gt;. One very real concern I had &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/03/my-first-steel-city-road-runners-winter-5k-race/&#34;&gt;when I put this race on my calendar a month ago&lt;/a&gt; was that recovery from it might interfere with my marathon training. Although I did not race Just A Short Run all out, I did put in a hard effort, and sure enough I did end up having a really tough training week afterwards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the overtraining this week was partly my doing. Here I explain how I ended up feeling like I was falling apart, and how I recovered and felt pretty good during today&amp;rsquo;s long run.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/wow-run.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Pittsburgh Marathon Warmup on Walnut run&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;after-the-half-marathon&#34;&gt;After the half marathon&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned in my report, I had some issues after the race: my right lower calf/Achilles area seized up for a bit, and also my right second and third toes did as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sure enough, a day later, I was feeling very sore in my right lower calf and second toe. I should mention that I have &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Morton%27s_toe&#34;&gt;Morton&amp;rsquo;s toe&lt;/a&gt; on both feet, although my left second toe is only barely longer than the big toe, while it is my right second toe that is noticeably longer than the big toe and therefore has a real tendency to cause me some problems:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mortons-toe.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;My Morton&amp;#39;s toes&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So I did take a day off running after the half marathon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;monday-trying-to-be-careful&#34;&gt;Monday: trying to be careful&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But even on Monday, I was still feeling sore. I decided that I should do some light running anyway, to avoid two days off completely from running.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, I very much wanted to finally start running in my new Luna Sandals, which I had received last week but put aside because of the half marathon. These are the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lunasandals.com/products/33-venado&#34;&gt;Venado with ATS laces and MGT footbed&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/lunastore/images/255/full.jpg?1351720427&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Luna Sandals: Venado, ATS laces, MGT footbed&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I ended up running just an easy 2 miles on the treadmill in the morning in my Vibram FiveFingers Bikila LS shoes, and then after work, running 1.5 miles in the Luna Sandals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;tuesday-new-shoes&#34;&gt;Tuesday: new shoes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tuesday, I was still not yet completely recovered either from the half marathon, but I felt I was ready to go for a normal run. I decided to do a real run in the Luna Sandals and did 5 miles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I encountered various problems while trying out the Luna Sandals, beginning to break them in. I got chafed in various places from the straps and buckle:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/luna-sandals-2013-04-02/feet.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Feet chafed&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/luna-sandals-2013-04-02/side.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Side view&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/luna-sandals-2013-04-02/wearing.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Feet in&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/luna-sandals-2013-04-02/heel.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;View of heel&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And it was tricky keeping the sandals on at all. I fidgeted a lot with the laces to try to keep my heels from slipping. I kept on having problems with my right heel slipping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, although my calf was healing up, I was more worried about my right second toe, which seemed sore and sensitive. I noticed that my tendency to impact the second toe (after all, it is my longest toe) was causing trouble. I had not really encountered any problems until after the half marathon, but the intensity of that effort, and the fact that my Bikila LS shoes were getting worn down at the toes, must have exposed this biomechanical weakness finally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;wednesday-overexcited&#34;&gt;Wednesday: overexcited&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wednesday, I was excited about running, and used the Luna Sandals again. I still had slippage and chafing issues, but figured that there was a break-in process. The soles were starting to shape to my feet, for example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, I accidentally (because of taking impromptu routes in Homewood Cemetery) ran 9 miles when I had originally intended to run more like 7.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My second toe was startling to tingle and really complain: even normal walking triggered pain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;thursday-admission-of-overtraining&#34;&gt;Thursday: admission of overtraining&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thursday was one of those days when I truly &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/14/three-questions-to-ask-yourself-when-you-dont-feel-like-doing-your-scheduled-workout/&#34;&gt;had to ask myself three questions&lt;/a&gt;. I was simply feeling &lt;em&gt;exhausted&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I forced myself to completely take Thursday off from running (or strength training, for that matter), while evaluating my situation. This was no longer just about my toe, but about my overall fatigue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, I had to fix this toe problem somehow, and soon, because I had a long run planned for Saturday. So I observed myself closely while walking. I noticed that I had a tendency to do a weird retracting motion on the toe when walking, a motion I do not use on my left foot. I questioned the purpose of this reflex. I found that I could &lt;em&gt;choose&lt;/em&gt; not to perform the retracting motion. It was difficult to make this choice, but if I really focused, I could control how I &lt;em&gt;used&lt;/em&gt; my foot. I remembered lessons from &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alexander_technique&#34;&gt;Alexander technique&lt;/a&gt; about observing and unlearning habits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, I discovered the reason my right hip has sometimes felt sore: my right hip has sagged in my posture. I also found that correcting this shifted the balance of weight on my right foot, and alleviated the pressure on my second toe, shifting more weight where it should be, more toward the big toe under the ball of the foot. These were very interesting discoveries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, I felt so tired that I decided to go ahead and cancel my Sunday plan to play in the final round of the Pittsburgh Chess League season; I had really wanted to put in one final appearance for our team, after not having actually played for us since &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/11/11/pittsburgh-chess-league-round-3-back-to-chess-after-a-month-off/&#34;&gt;last November&lt;/a&gt;, because something kept on coming up every month since then, but I had little confidence that I would be mentally alert on Sunday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;friday-still-playing-it-safe&#34;&gt;Friday: still playing it safe&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Friday, I was feeling energetic enough to run, but I forced myself to take another day off for the sake of my right toe. It was not easy, but I reminded myself that &lt;em&gt;not being able to do my long run&lt;/em&gt; was not worth one more missed day of training.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of running, I did one rep of the Cathedral of Learning stair climb, just to get some activity in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;saturday-my-14-mile-long-run&#34;&gt;Saturday: my 14-mile long run&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saturday morning, I felt my right toe had recovered sufficiently that I was going to be OK doing my planned long run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Steel City Road Runners had a 10-mile run lined up starting in Shadyside after a program of dynamics warmups by Dr. Vonda Wright, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pittsburghmarathon.com/wow.asp&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Warmup on Walnut&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, outside of sponsor &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.truerunner.com/&#34;&gt;True Runner&lt;/a&gt;. My plan was to skip that program, but create a 14-mile run by running 2 miles from home to the Shadyside point and then joining the group run and then running 2 miles back home afterwards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is the 10-mile loop:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe id=&#34;mapmyfitness_route&#34; src=&#34;http://snippets.mapmycdn.com/routes/view/embedded/187175578?width=560&amp;height=400&amp;elevation=true&amp;info=true&amp;line_color=E60f0bdb&amp;rgbhex=DB0B0E&amp;distance_markers=1&amp;unit_type=imperial&amp;map_mode=TERRAIN&amp;last_updated=2013-04-01T09:44:11-04:00&#34; height=&#34;590px&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: right; padding-right: 20px;&#34;&gt;&lt;a target=&#34;_blank&#34; href=&#34;http://mapmyrun.com/routes/create/&#34;&gt;Create Maps&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a target=&#34;_blank&#34; href=&#34;http://mapmyrun.com/routes/&#34;&gt;search&lt;/a&gt; from 80 million at &lt;a href=&#34;http://mapmyrun.com&#34;&gt;MapMyRun&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;my-goal&#34;&gt;My goal&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My goal for this long run was to make it a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mcmillanrunning.com/index.php/articlePages/article/2&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;fast finish long run&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. In particular, in planning my run, I had noted that the last 5 miles of the course involved a steady uphill as well as a steeper uphill through Oakland on Forbes Avenue. In the 2003 Pittsburgh Marathon ten years ago, this uphill had proved a bit discouraging to me (because I had, frankly, gone out too fast). In any case, for psychological and physiological reasons, I wanted to do this whole uphill fast and strong in this particular workout. In the actual marathon in a month, of course, I don&amp;rsquo;t plan to run it as fast, but I did want to remember the landmarks and mental state of doing something difficult but in a relaxed way. I wanted to focus on applying my newly discovered knowledge about my posture and stride asymmetry and &amp;ldquo;run tall&amp;rdquo; up the hill, with balanced hips, while monitoring my right second toe to make sure it did not get battered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was still not comfortable with the Luna Sandals, so I fell back to the shoes I&amp;rsquo;ve been wearing for almost all of my runs in the past three months, the Bikila LS shoes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;showed-up-late&#34;&gt;Showed up late&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, I strangely miscalculated my departure from home to run 2 miles to Aiken Avenue and Walnut Street, and showed up 4 minutes late, just as runners were already heading off. I grabbed a printed map and picked up the pace so that I could try to catch up to the 10:00 pace group. I did, realizing of course that I was making my task in the final miles of my run more difficult as a result.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;conquering-the-oakland-hill&#34;&gt;Conquering the Oakland hill&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I managed the Oakland hill pretty well, being very focused. I continued going hard all the way back to True Runner in Shadyside. Near the end, I felt my calves getting tight, just as in the half marathon last week when my right calf seized up after I was walking after the finish line. I thought it was very useful to have triggered this exact sensation and knowing where it was, because it meant that maybe I would be able to train my body to accept that state of fatigue (after running 12 miles) and continue. Also, the feeling cleared up fairly quickly after I stopped to walk, so I think last week the real trigger was my pointless little sprint near the end. If I avoid any sprinting during the marathon, I might well be able to avoid cramping. At least, that is the plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;a-decision-about-gatorade&#34;&gt;A decision about Gatorade&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I drank some more Gatorade back at Walnut Street, then ran home. I was really quite tired by this point and my stomach wasn&amp;rsquo;t feeling so great. I ate some actual food and eventually recovered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During this run, no gels were provided, so I drank Gatorade as my only fuel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is my final conclusion, solidifying a thought I had last week in the half marathon: &lt;em&gt;Gatorade is bad for me&lt;/em&gt;, and I should &lt;em&gt;completely&lt;/em&gt; avoid it in future runs and in the Pittsburgh Marathon! It was good to learn this for sure now. In fact, it is quite possible that some of the issues I had in the 2003 Pittsburgh Marathon were a result of Gatorade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GU gel works OK for me, but according to the official &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburghmarathon.com/Course.asp&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Marathon fluid station table&lt;/a&gt;, GU is provided only starting at mile 9.7. Therefore, I am going to pack some gels to ingest during the first 10 miles of the marathon! I will &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; drink any Gatorade!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After some ill-advised overtraining and injury this week after my half marathon, I forced myself to take two days off to recover, and used the time to diagnose possible causes of my biomechanical problems. I found some good hypotheses and possible solutions, and managed a high quality &amp;ldquo;fast finish long run&amp;rdquo; and am optimistic about my continuing training for the Pittsburgh Marathon.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The inaugural Liberty Mile: a review of Pittsburgh&#39;s first road mile race, a great community event</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/08/17/the-inaugural-liberty-mile-a-review-of-pittsburghs-first-road-mile-race/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Aug 2012 21:44:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/08/17/the-inaugural-liberty-mile-a-review-of-pittsburghs-first-road-mile-race/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/liberty-mile-2012.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin&amp;#39;s race number and Bikila LS shoes&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Tonight I was really excited to race in, and also watch, the inaugural &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.libertymile.org/&#34;&gt;GNC Live Well Liberty Mile&lt;/a&gt;, a road race that runs along Liberty Avenue in Pittsburgh, starting from the Strip District and ending downtown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s about time Pittsburgh had a road mile race! Pittsburgh already has the wonderful&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://rungreatrace.com/&#34;&gt;Great Race&lt;/a&gt;, which &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/25/blistered-but-blissful-in-the-burgh/&#34;&gt;I ran for my ninth time last year&lt;/a&gt; and will run for my tenth time this year (good think I pre-registered early, because today it &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburgh.cbslocal.com/2012/08/17/2012-great-race-officially-sold-out/&#34;&gt;already sold out!!&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pittsburghmarathon.com/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Marathon&lt;/a&gt;, which I&amp;rsquo;ve run once.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope this event is here to stay. Here&amp;rsquo;s my report on the event as both a runner and a spectator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-history-in-the-mile&#34;&gt;My history in the mile&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve run a mile race only twice before in my life, and that was on the track at Carnegie Mellon University. A decade ago, in June 2002, I ran in my first track mile, the Pittsylvania Mile on that track, and did it in 6:22. I could have run faster, but because of total inexperience, went out way too fast for the first quarter, doing it in 1:22, and paying the price in the other laps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following year, 2003, in probably my peak condition in my life, I improved, doing the Pittsylvania Mile in 6:10. I still went out too fast, in 1:26, had no sense of rhythm, slowed down a lot to try to compensate for going out too fast, then had too much energy at the end, which was wasted. Again, I had not trained for the mile distance at all, but happened to be in my peak condition anyway just because I was still conditioned from my intense training for the Pittsburgh Marathon that I had just done in May (my lifetime personal best in the 5K of 20:37 was achieved just two weeks after the Pittsburgh Marathon).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I never broke a 6-minute mile during my peak.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That was the last timed mile I ever ran, until tonight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;preparation&#34;&gt;Preparation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, I wasn&amp;rsquo;t prepared for the mile at all. Apart from not having run much because of a non-running injury to my left leg that happened a month ago (from which I have fully recovered), I have just come back from a week of unexpected travel and am still kind of recovering from that. And no speed work to speak of in the past month, other than a few random sprints (which I do for general physical conditioning when I don&amp;rsquo;t do much else).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had no idea what &amp;ldquo;mile pace&amp;rdquo; feels like. I just figured I would run a bit faster than 5K pace (which I always have a reasonable feel for).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hoped to finish somewhere near 6:30.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;dr-vonda-wright&#34;&gt;Dr. Vonda Wright&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://vondawright.com/images/stories/vonda-at-work.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Vonda Wright&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I bumped into &lt;a href=&#34;http://vondawright.com/&#34;&gt;Dr. Vonda Wright&lt;/a&gt; while heading toward the start line, and thanked her for her support of those of us who care about maintaining our health as we get older. I want to plug her great work in promoting lifetime fitness, especially for those over 40. She has written a book &lt;a href=&#34;http://vondawright.com/index.php?option=com_content&amp;amp;view=article&amp;amp;id=62&amp;amp;Itemid=83&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Fitness After 40&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; which is pretty good and has a lot of scientifically-backed tips on remaining strong and vital and even reversing what used to be considered &amp;ldquo;normal aging&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I heard about Dr. Wright from a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/01/20/cmu-fitness-challenge-keynote-lecture-by-vonda-wright-stay-strong-at-any-age/&#34;&gt;CMU &amp;ldquo;healthy campus week&amp;rdquo; talk she gave this January&lt;/a&gt;. Even though I had already known some of what she advocated, I was impressed that she summarized well the whole gamut of what we now know to be effective ways to increase strength and flexibility and avoid injury. Again, I recommend her books to anyone of any age who wants to be smart about diet and exercise and more than that, a whole philosophical approach to living in general.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-race-in-waves&#34;&gt;The race, in waves&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The race was held in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.libertymile.org/Race-Waves.asp&#34;&gt;waves separated by ten or twenty minutes&lt;/a&gt;. This is obviously necessary because of the variation in people&amp;rsquo;s speed. The slower, open waves were held first, and the elite racers were in the final waves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;early-waves&#34;&gt;Early waves&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I arrived to pick up my race number when the first wave was already in progress. There was a bit of confusion in the first two waves because a good number of people arrived late or were unclear about when to run, and therefore missed the first wave. Most of these seemed to be kids. By the way, it was great to see so many kids at the Liberty Mile. Running a 5K (3.1-mile) race can be daunting for a kid, but a single mile is surely a great introduction to many kids (and adults too!) to the joy of running. I think it is really great that the Liberty Mile is not just an elite race, but also a race anyone can participate in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;my-race-in-the-masters-wave&#34;&gt;My race, in the Masters wave&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Masters &amp;ldquo;Winning at 40+&amp;rdquo; wave was the first qualification-required wave.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ran in this serious, competitive wave, not one of the open waves, because I easily qualified to run in this wave, whose requirement was proof of ability to run an 8-minute mile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lining up, I saw a lot of really fit-looking people in this wave, many of whom were clearly well over 40. In any case, anyone who looked anywhere near my age (42) was obviously going to kick my butt all the way to the moon. There was no chance for an age-group prize for me today! No problem: as a non-elite racer, I don&amp;rsquo;t race for prizes, but just to do the best that I can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ended up running &lt;a href=&#34;http://runhigh.com/2012RESULTS/R081712AD.html&#34;&gt;6:38.8&lt;/a&gt;, good for 26th place out of 27 in my age group, ha! I was disappointed that I didn&amp;rsquo;t make 6:30 as I had originally hoped when I signed up a month ago, but that&amp;rsquo;s OK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the first quarter, I ran 1:29; oops, went out too fast yet again! &lt;strong&gt;I hereby pledge that before the next mile race I run, I will actually train and learn not to go out too fast.&lt;/strong&gt; There is no excuse for running three mile races going out too fast. I don&amp;rsquo;t go out too fast in 5K or longer distances, after all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the second and third quarters, 1:46 and 1:46 showed that I had gone out too fast. I did save something for the sprint finish, however, and did the final quarter in 1:38.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A serious and unexpected problem I had while running this race was that my mouth got very dry and I had trouble breathing as a result. It was pretty weird. I don&amp;rsquo;t exactly remember this in my mile races from a decade ago. I did hydrate considerably before the race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, of course, as I do in 5K races, I felt like puking during the final quarter, and my arms were getting tingly and losing sensation. It&amp;rsquo;s just what happens to me in the final push. I believe there is no way to avoid feeling like puking if I&amp;rsquo;m running as hard as I can, but I have a feeling that the problem with my arms has to do with my tightening up (rather than relaxing) and flailing around. I plan to try to fix that for my next races this month and next month; what is required, clearly, is disciplined speed work, which is something I have not done in years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;enjoying-being-a-spectator&#34;&gt;Enjoying being a spectator&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The really cool thing about a mile race held in waves is that you get to be a spectator for the remaining waves after you&amp;rsquo;re done. In a 5K race or longer, there aren&amp;rsquo;t any heats and you never get to be a spectator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was wowed watching the &amp;ldquo;Unstoppable&amp;rdquo; under-40 wave whose qualification time was running faster than 6:00. Watching good, fast running is a real pleasure to me, like watching skilled dancers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also a treat was getting to watch the female elite wave and male elite wave. These &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/27/why-i-do-not-watch-the-olympics-any-more/&#34;&gt;Olympic&lt;/a&gt;-caliber runners looked so elegant with their long, powerful strides.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-shoes&#34;&gt;My shoes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d been considering running a race soon wearing my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/26/walking-and-running-in-invisible-shoes-a-review/&#34;&gt;Invisible Shoes huaraches&lt;/a&gt;, but without testing them out with speed work, I&amp;rsquo;m not ready to go there yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I wore the shoes I&amp;rsquo;ve been &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/23/happiness-is-finishing-39th-of-43-men-in-a-race/&#34;&gt;road racing in for almost a full year now&lt;/a&gt;, the Vibram FiveFingers Bikila LS. They worked out just fine. I didn&amp;rsquo;t get blistered because it was cool and it was only a mile. Next month I&amp;rsquo;ll see whether I get blistered in the Great Race &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/25/blistered-but-blissful-in-the-burgh/&#34;&gt;the way I did last year&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;race-organization&#34;&gt;Race organization&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought the race was pretty well-organized, especially given that this was the first time such a race has been held in Pittsburgh. Thanks go to the sponsors, the timers, the announcers, the volunteers who handed out race numbers and stocked water and bagels at the finish line and handed out goodie bags and T-shirts, the police officers who closed the roads and lanes where necessary and directed traffic and kept Liberty Avenue clear, the spectators who cheered, the providers of the many port-a-johns near the start line, the &lt;a href=&#34;http://bringbackthemile.com/news/detail/Miller_and_Kampf_Win_GNC_Live_Well_Liberty_Mile&#34;&gt;elite runners who put on a display of amazing running&lt;/a&gt;. Everyone without question was helpful and friendly. The whole experience was just wonderful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The inaugural GNC Live Well Liberty Mile was a great event. I hope it is the beginning of a Pittsburgh tradition that, like the Great Race and the Pittsburgh Marathon, will continue for years and decades to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-08-09&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-08-09)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/08/09/getting-up-when-reality-punches-you-in-the-face-running-the-second-liberty-mile-in-pittsburgh/&#34;&gt;I ran the second Liberty Mile a year later.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CMU Fitness Challenge keynote lecture by Vonda Wright: Stay strong at any age</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/01/20/cmu-fitness-challenge-keynote-lecture-by-vonda-wright-stay-strong-at-any-age/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Jan 2012 22:32:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/01/20/cmu-fitness-challenge-keynote-lecture-by-vonda-wright-stay-strong-at-any-age/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://athletics.cmu.edu/athletics/directory/headshots/vonda_wright_hs.jpg?max_height=200&amp;amp;max_width=150&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Dr. Vonda Wright&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I attended a &lt;a href=&#34;http://athletics.cmu.edu/generalnews/2011-2012/vondawright&#34;&gt;much-anticipated talk at CMU&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.drvondawright.com/&#34;&gt;Dr. Vonda Wright&lt;/a&gt; of UPMC in McConomy Auditorium, given to the CMU community as a keynote lecture for the CMU Fitness Challenge I participate in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Dr. Wright is an orthopedic surgeon at UPMC and an author and researcher. She focuses on the master athlete and living a healthy lifestyle, having conducted extensive research on the benefits of remaining active throughout one&amp;rsquo;s lifetime.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a fascinating and inspiring talk! Dr. Wright was a high-energy speaker, very passionate and direct. She spoke on many topics, actually, not just about physical exercise. And she spoke frankly about personal experiences in her life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;focus-on-over-40&#34;&gt;Focus on over 40&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Wright was particularly speaking to the older staff members in attendance. She argued that there was no reason one should not remain strong and vital well into what some might consider old age. She indicated that research showed that significant decline does not need to kick in until the &amp;ldquo;cutoff&amp;rdquo; point of age 70, which is when it seems that even very health people start a significant downward slope.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She said that as someone going on age 45 (she certainly looked a lot more fit than most people that age!), she learned that there is not enough research on active people over age 40, because of a bias in favor of studying young athletes. The result is that people have made wrong assumptions about what it is like to grow older.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Her favorite phrase seems to be &amp;ldquo;bash your bones&amp;rdquo;: she emphasized that weight-bearing exercise is particularly important and stimulating for older people. She showed photos of how inactivity can result in &amp;ldquo;fat in muscle&amp;rdquo; (yuck).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;business-principles&#34;&gt;Business principles&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One interesting perspective she wanted to share was that she urged us to apply &amp;ldquo;business principles&amp;rdquo; to our personal health: after all, if we pay a lot of attention to our careers and jobs, how come we don&amp;rsquo;t treat our own health as a serious job too? Furthermore, it&amp;rsquo;s not just our physical health, narrowly construed: she asked, &amp;ldquo;What do we really want?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without plans, she said, we are just laying bricks, not building a movement. Whatever we take seriously, we must think ahead five to ten years, and do nothing that is not part of the goal. We must learn to say &amp;ldquo;No&amp;rdquo; to what is unimportant. If we focus on what is most important to us, &amp;ldquo;everything else falls into place&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She told a personal story illustrating what she meant. She had an opportunity at one point in her career to just continue working hard and become chair of the department. But she realized she didn&amp;rsquo;t want to be chair and followed her own path instead, choosing what interested her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;books&#34;&gt;Books&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Wright openly promoted &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.drvondawright.com/fitness-author/&#34;&gt;her books&lt;/a&gt; throughout the talk. I made a note to look them up at the library.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought it was great that CMU had Dr. Vonda Wright come give a talk for the CMU Fitness Challenge this year. Many ideas she shared, I found inspirational. And as a master athlete herself, she is a great role model.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>