<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Trumpet on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/trumpet/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Trumpet on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/trumpet/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>A fine trumpet recital by Erin Yanacek</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/11/25/a-fine-trumpet-recital-by-erin-yanacek/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Nov 2013 22:24:39 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/11/25/a-fine-trumpet-recital-by-erin-yanacek/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://static.erinyanacek.com/img/home_page_new_photo_3.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Erin Yanacek&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I attended a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.music.cmu.edu/events/282&#34;&gt;graduate trumpet recital&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&#34;http://erinyanacek.com/&#34;&gt;Erin Yanacek&lt;/a&gt;, in which she performed works of Robert Planel, Camille Saint-Saens, George Enescu, Franz Joseph Haydn, and Herbert L. Clarke.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2014-07-28&#34;&gt;(Update of 2014-07-28)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Erin has posted a video of the Herbert L. Clarke work from her recital:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/oBV4u360Ats&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-little-about-erin&#34;&gt;A little about Erin&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I first encountered Erin, without yet knowing who she was, from &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/04/29/attending-my-first-cmu-baroque-ensemble-concert/&#34;&gt;attending a CMU Baroque Ensemble Concert for the first time over a year ago&lt;/a&gt;. Then, some months later, without knowing the name or connecting it with anyone I had seen before, I saw a heartfelt article she wrote for a new blog on the arts, &lt;a href=&#34;http://musedialogue.org/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Muse Dialogue&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://musedialogue.org/2013/02/11/seeking-the-love-of-music-that-i-once-felt/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Seeking the love of music that I once felt&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. Then I bumped into her at a party Abby and I attended, and I finally connected the dots. It also turned out that she is a serious runner, and we&amp;rsquo;ve accidentally crossed paths while both running in the trails of Frick Park. And she&amp;rsquo;s also a cyclist and has done the wildly difficult Pittsburgh &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dannychew.com/dd_11.html&#34;&gt;Dirty Dozen&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, if you&amp;rsquo;re a fan of Pittsburgh&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rivercitybrass.org/&#34;&gt;River City Brass&lt;/a&gt;, you may have seen her recently, as she is now a cornet player there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;it-s-about-the-music&#34;&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s about the music&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I rather enjoy Erin&amp;rsquo;s playing. She&amp;rsquo;s a versatile and sensitive musician, adept at different styles and different moods, exploring and showcasing what the trumpet can express. Whether it&amp;rsquo;s pure brilliance, classical elegance, tender and lyrical romanticism, or jazzy/bluesy attitude and rhythm, I&amp;rsquo;m pretty impressed by the range of what Erin can do using a trumpet to communicate. Erin&amp;rsquo;s program was a tasty sampler of trumpet delight. I especially like the way she shapes phrases, really making the instrument sing and speak.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pittsburgh is blessed to have Erin as part of the local community of excellent musicians, and I hope to continue seeing her perform when I can! Check her out.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Celebrating Claude Debussy&#39;s 151st birthday through unusual performances of Syrinx</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/08/23/celebrating-claude-debussys-151st-birthday-through-unusual-performances-of-syrinx/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Aug 2013 23:49:25 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/08/23/celebrating-claude-debussys-151st-birthday-through-unusual-performances-of-syrinx/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;There was &lt;a href=&#34;http://jessicamusic.blogspot.com/2013/08/stop-dumbing-down-debussy.html&#34;&gt;much ado&lt;/a&gt; over Google&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;celebrating&amp;rdquo; Claude Debussy&amp;rsquo;s 151st birthday through a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.slate.com/blogs/browbeat/2013/08/22/claude_debussy_google_doodles_claire_de_lune_for_composer_s_151st_birthday.html&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Claire de Lune&amp;rdquo; doodle&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that I do totally love this piece of music, but it may well be true that many people do not know much about a lot of the other great music he wrote.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;syrinx&#34;&gt;Syrinx&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I decided to celebrate the birthday in my own way. I chose Debussy&amp;rsquo;s famous work for solo flute, &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Syrinx_%28Debussy%29&#34;&gt;Syrinx&lt;/a&gt;, as a starting point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two years ago, I already linked to a fine performance of it on flute &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/22/james-galway-made-me-hate-flute/&#34;&gt;by Emmannuel Pahud&lt;/a&gt;. There are many other good performances on flute, but inspired by &lt;a href=&#34;http://emilysdomain.org/&#34;&gt;Emily O&amp;rsquo;Brien&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/21/mideast-early-music-workshop-a-life-changing-experience/&#34;&gt;performance that I attended last year of Syrinx on tenor recorder&lt;/a&gt;, I looked for other non-flute performances of this music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found two intriguing ones to share.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;tenor-recorder&#34;&gt;Tenor recorder&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One is another tenor recorder performance, by Kenjiro Hibi. This Japanese musician made it seem as though it were traditional Japanese shakuhachi music!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/6e0kag3K86Y&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;trumpet&#34;&gt;Trumpet&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I found this amazing performance on trumpet, by &lt;a href=&#34;http://alisonbalsom.com/&#34;&gt;Alison Balsom&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/FW-8vC9Kpfw&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found this through &lt;a href=&#34;http://musicalassumptions.blogspot.com/2013/08/the-many-faces-of-syrinx-for-debussys.html&#34;&gt;someone else&amp;rsquo;s blog post on Syrinx for Debussy&amp;rsquo;s birthday&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;more-on-syrinx&#34;&gt;More on Syrinx&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is some interesting discussion of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flutefocus.com/232-syrinx-by-debussy.html&#34;&gt;interpretation and editions&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point, of course, I must work on this piece and play it on flute. But not yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a fascination with music played in a context other than the original, such as on a different instrument. It was fun discovering some performances of Debussy&amp;rsquo;s Syrinx on recorder and trumpet.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Special treat: Dutch jazz trumpeter Eric Vloeimans performed in Pittsburgh!</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/12/19/special-treat-dutch-jazz-trumpeter-eric-vloeimans-performed-in-pittsburgh/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Dec 2012 23:42:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/12/19/special-treat-dutch-jazz-trumpeter-eric-vloeimans-performed-in-pittsburgh/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.pghcitypaper.com/imager/b/original/1596939/9540/music2_50.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Eric Vloeimans&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A while ago, I heard through a fantastic &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pghcitypaper.com/pittsburgh/jazz-goes-dutch/Content?oid=1596938&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh City paper article&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/Pittsburgh-Jazz-Fan-Meetup-Group/events/93376692&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Jazz Fan meetup&lt;/a&gt; about Dutch jazz trumpeter &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ericvloeimans.com/&#34;&gt;Eric Vloeimans&lt;/a&gt; coming to Pittsburgh to perform as part of an &amp;ldquo;international progressive jazz trio&amp;rdquo; including himself, German &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.florianweber.net/&#34;&gt;Florian Weber&lt;/a&gt; on piano, and Syrian &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.kinanazmeh.com&#34;&gt;Kinan Azmeh&lt;/a&gt; on clarinet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had never heard of these musicians before, but the article intrigued me enough to do some research, and Abby and I ended up attending his concert.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;i-did-research&#34;&gt;I did research&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the great things about this era, I think, is that you can learn something about musicians&amp;rsquo; work before deciding to invest in attending a concert. Things were much less certain before the whole Internet; you had to be deeply connected to some community of people that gave you information and advice, and it was harder to randomly hear about and explore new things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Upon checking out &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/user/ericvloeimans&#34;&gt;Eric Vloeimans&amp;rsquo;s YouTube channel&lt;/a&gt; for samples of his work, I decided that I was intrigued by his music, and I loved his contrasts, moving between loud, wild improvisation and a soft lyrical style, but always with beautiful tone. Also, I liked that he comes from the classical world and is interested in all kinds of music and brings it all together to create his own style.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;attending-the-concert-in-pittsburgh&#34;&gt;Attending the concert in Pittsburgh&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby mostly thinks jazz is chaotic, so I didn&amp;rsquo;t know whether I could convince her to go to the concert with me, but found this lyrical side of Vloeimans to show her:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/3Y0izaxU8YQ?list=UUuNCeR2oWKiCdcGZ4NwZv2w&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I got a pair of tickets, and Abby and I went to the trio&amp;rsquo;s concert in the First Unitarian Church. Attendance was, as I expected, sparse. Sadly, this kind of music is not so popular here in Pittsburgh. On the plus side, the small audience made the whole experience feel very intimate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, I loved the concert. This being a jazz program with many different experiments, of course there were moments or ideas that did not work for me, but overall, I was inspired by what the three created together on the spot, working with all they had from pre-agreed themes and technique, and the demands of the moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The concert warmed up with a lyrical piece that showed off Vloeimans&amp;rsquo;s classical training.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things got going right after that, with the second piece starting out with an atonal intro by Weber on piano, and then rhythmically ended up being some kind of tango. Vloeimans is a very physically expressive performer. He started stamping his feet in rhythm while playing, and at some point both Weber and Vloeimans were going at it physically, adding vocalizations to the mix. Great energy and fun!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Azmeh on clarinet then played a lovely duet with Vloeimans on trumpet. I could see how attentive they were to each other as they created a dialogue on the spot, combining turn-taking with simultaneous improvisation. It was an unusual combination of sound to me, the clarinet-trumpet duet. Azmeh also being classically trained, you could hear the working out in real time of subtle contrapuntal and harmonic ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then all three played together as a trio. This used a backdrop of minimalist repetition and literally made their performance sound like a train ride of industrial sounds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then came Azmeh with a long clarinet solo as intro into a piece that unfolded finally into a trio. I loved the meditative and exploratory quality of the solo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then came something very animated, which sounded like it was based on Cuban rhythms, but also somehow sounded Asian. Things got really animated, and Weber started hitting at the piano, and of course Vloeimans was stamping his feet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After that, something that sounded Jewish. Weber prepared the piano and made it sound tinny.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, they closed with telling a story about an encounter with Hindustani music in India, and then launching into music created as a result of that inspiration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a great evening of music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;for-more&#34;&gt;For more&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of what Vloeimans and Weber did came from their album &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Live-Concertgebouw-Vloeimans-Florian-Weber/dp/B005H4T9XI&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Live at the Concertgebouw&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, which &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.allaboutjazz.com/live-at-the-concertgebouw-eric-vloeimans-challenge-records-review-by-john-kelman.php&#34;&gt;you may want to check out&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2014-08-06&#34;&gt;(Update of 2014-08-06)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was looking up the trio again and found this video that gives a good idea of some of the kind of thing they did when they were in Pittsburgh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/WqlJmWd5j3g&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Attending the annual Pitt Jazz Seminar for the first time: day 2</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/11/03/attending-the-annual-pitt-jazz-seminar-for-the-first-time/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Nov 2012 20:52:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/11/03/attending-the-annual-pitt-jazz-seminar-for-the-first-time/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.music.pitt.edu/sites/default/files/jazz-2012-cropped.jpg?1350921512&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;42nd Pitt Jazz Seminar poster&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/11/02/attending-the-annual-pitt-jazz-seminar-for-the-first-time-day-1/&#34;&gt;Yesterday&lt;/a&gt;, I attended some morning sessions of the annual Pitt Jazz Seminar. I went back for more today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-tribute-to-miles&#34;&gt;A tribute to Miles&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;randy-brecker-http-randybrecker-com-trumpet&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://randybrecker.com/&#34;&gt;Randy Brecker&lt;/a&gt;, trumpet&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I liked how Randy Brecker talked about how he got into music. He listened to a lot of records as a kid, and at some point he started improvising during piano solos, by ear. He started with ballads (by Miles, Chet, etc.) and played with his brother &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.michaelbrecker.com/&#34;&gt;Michael&lt;/a&gt; (who sadly died some years ago).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;lew-soloff-http-www-lewsoloff-com-trumpet&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lewsoloff.com/&#34;&gt;Lew Soloff&lt;/a&gt;, trumpet&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lew Soloff came from a very different world. He stopped piano lessons at ten because his teachers did not emphasize &lt;em&gt;music&lt;/em&gt;, but &amp;ldquo;holding the hand a certain way&amp;rdquo;. He wanted trumpet because it was &lt;em&gt;shiny&lt;/em&gt;. Ha! Reminded me that it doesn&amp;rsquo;t matter why you start doing something; often you have a perhaps superficial reason, and find deeper reasons later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His uncle emphasized the importance of &lt;em&gt;practice&lt;/em&gt; and admonished him for being interested in too many things. Some tips on mental attitudes: never say &amp;ldquo;I can&amp;rsquo;t&amp;rdquo;, and also drop your &lt;em&gt;ego&lt;/em&gt;: learn from your peers. So in one summer, he went from last chair to first chair, practicing one and a half hours each day!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lew had a classical music training and therefore at first was scared to improvise. He had to overcome that fear. He also had to learn to articulate in &amp;ldquo;doodle tongue&amp;rdquo; rather than in the classical way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He said he eventually became open to all kinds of music, where in the past he was closed. He has a different take than Duke Ellington&amp;rsquo;s famous quote, &amp;ldquo;There are two kinds of music, good music and the other kind&amp;rdquo;: instead, Lew likes to think that the two kinds are the &lt;em&gt;honest&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;dishonest&lt;/em&gt;. I like this formulation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Randy piped in saying that he became musically open because that was just the way things were in Philadelphia, where there are so many styles.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Advice: when learning ballads, first play them &lt;em&gt;without&lt;/em&gt; improvisation, focusing on purity and honesty, and expressing emotion as though singing. Learn the lyrics and understand them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;artistry-in-rhythm-winard-harper-http-www-winardharper-com-drums&#34;&gt;Artistry in rhythm: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.winardharper.com/&#34;&gt;Winard Harper&lt;/a&gt;, drums&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Winard Harper spoke of coming from a musical family and playing at clubs by the time he was five years old. He emphasized the importance of relationships in making music come together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He&amp;rsquo;s really into an African instrument that I never heard of before called a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Balafon&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;balafon&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. More generally, he is interested in all kinds of world music, whether from Africa, Australia, Japan. He urged everyone to honor tradition, learn history, and do a lot of playing and listening. &amp;ldquo;The more you know, the more you can use&amp;rdquo;. He summed up with the message that as a drummer, when jamming, you have to face all kinds of situations, drums that are not yours, etc., and you have to learn to deal, because it&amp;rsquo;s not about you but about music. Sounds wise no matter what instrument we play!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-piano-in-jazz-george-cables-http-georgecables-com&#34;&gt;The piano in jazz: &lt;a href=&#34;http://georgecables.com/&#34;&gt;George Cables&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;George Cables emphasized that jazz is living music, through which everyone can become a &amp;ldquo;co-composer&amp;rdquo; through arranging and improvising.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a pianist, he didn&amp;rsquo;t want to be a soloist so much as a good side man. He was most inspired by Wynton Kelly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Musically, he emphasized that the piano is a percussion instrument. He also gave a history lesson on the piano in jazz, starting from Scott Joplin and moving forward from there. He said the progression was toward &amp;ldquo;freeing the bass&amp;rdquo;, allowing the left hand to do a lot more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(I had to leave this session a little early because I wanted to make it to a special recorder concert elsewhere in town.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found it very interesting and useful attending Pitt Jazz Seminar sessions these past two days, featuring very different musicians on different instruments, getting a broad perspective on how they operate and what they value and what they have to teach. I hope to continue attending this annual event!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Attending my first CMU Baroque Ensemble concert: enjoying Bach&#39;s Brandenburg 2</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/04/29/attending-my-first-cmu-baroque-ensemble-concert/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Apr 2012 23:44:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/04/29/attending-my-first-cmu-baroque-ensemble-concert/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I attended a free concert of the CMU Baroque Ensemble for the very first time!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The CMU Baroque Ensemble under &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.stephenschultz.net/&#34;&gt;Stephen Schultz&lt;/a&gt; has been around for over a decade, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.stephenschultz.net/teaching.html&#34;&gt;starting in 2002&lt;/a&gt;, but I had never attended one of their concerts, because basically, until I started playing recorder last year, I had very little interest in Baroque music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But now I&amp;rsquo;m really immersing myself in Baroque music, so I decided to check out the student ensemble. Also, I&amp;rsquo;d never seen Stephen Schultz in action before outside the CMU lecture hall (I took his &amp;ldquo;Survey of Western Musical History&amp;rdquo; in 2006) and his CD recordings of Baroque flute music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The students played modern instruments, but Schultz clearly aimed to evoke a crisp, Baroque style of play from the ensemble. He is an enthusiastic and clear conductor and it is enjoyable watching him direct this music he clearly loves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;bach-s-brandenburg-2&#34;&gt;Bach&amp;rsquo;s Brandenburg 2&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Various pieces were performed in this concert, but the highlight for me was Bach&amp;rsquo;s Brandenburg concerto no. 2, which I have recently come to love. I had ignored the Brandenburg concertos for much of my life, but when I started playing recorder last year, I found that one of the method books I used, a two-volume method by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.aswltd.com/adultmet.htm#begin&#34;&gt;Mario Duschenes&lt;/a&gt;, ends with challenging solo recorder parts for the Brandenburg concerto no. 2 and no. 4, and I aspired to be able to play these, and listened to some recordings I found of them, and truly fell in love with the music! (Note: the CMU Baroque Ensemble did not use recorder, but flute, in the Brandenburg 2.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was thrilling for me to watch the Brandenburg 2 performed live, because of the prominent &lt;a href=&#34;http://abel.hive.no/trumpet/bach/brandenburg/&#34;&gt;high trumpet part&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;d never seen this in action before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, here&amp;rsquo;s a performance of the first movement of the Brandenburg 2, on historical instruments (rather than the modern instruments played in the CMU Baroque Ensemble concert). Check out the recorder and trumpet!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/EC1E4_imS0A&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed the concert and will probably continue to attend more by the CMU Baroque Ensemble, to continue my Baroque &amp;ldquo;education&amp;rdquo;. It is, of course, not a professional ensemble, but it is great to see CMU students dedicated to performing Baroque music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-11-25&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-11-25)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fine trumpet player in this concert was &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/11/25/a-fine-trumpet-recital-by-erin-yanacek&#34;&gt;Erin Yanacek&lt;/a&gt;, whom I&amp;rsquo;d later coincidentally encounter through her writings and from meeting her by accident.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The beautiful, melancholy Indian Summer of Chet Baker</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/11/20/the-beautiful-melancholy-indian-summer-of-chet-baker/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Nov 2011 20:25:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/11/20/the-beautiful-melancholy-indian-summer-of-chet-baker/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;For some reason, today I felt like listening (for the hundredth time?) to the ballad &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Indian_Summer_%28Victor_Herbert_song%29&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Indian Summer&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; as performed by the tragically self-destructive jazz trumpet player (and vocalist) &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chet_Baker&#34;&gt;Chet Baker&lt;/a&gt;. I have been obsessed with this beautiful performance since the day I first heard it on the radio maybe fifteen years ago while driving. Eventually I got hold of a CD including the track. Thanks to YouTube, you can listen to the five-minute thing of beauty here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/_KFw6gd_66w&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;trumpet&#34;&gt;Trumpet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe &amp;ldquo;Indian Summer&amp;rdquo; came to mind today because at monthly recorder society practice, I was reflecting on my (canceled) hope to play jazz trumpet and felt a little sad. Who ever sounded as &lt;em&gt;achingly beautiful&lt;/em&gt; on trumpet as Chet Baker? Yes, I love Louis Armstrong, Miles Davis, and many other greats of the trumpet, but it is always Chet Baker&amp;rsquo;s aesthetic that I identify with: the &amp;ldquo;cool&amp;rdquo;, lyrical emotional intensity. He expressed so much with drawn-out, smooth whispers and reflective silences and sighs: the lilting fragility of life, the beauty and desolation of passing through the transient stream that is Time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;voice&#34;&gt;Voice&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a haunting video of Chet Baker singing the heartbreaking &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m a Fool to Want You&amp;rdquo; and playing his horn too (skip to around 0:40 for the music to begin):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/2ZK8TnDIe2w&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Taking up flute again after decades?!</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/11/09/taking-up-flute-again-after-decades/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Nov 2011 20:08:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/11/09/taking-up-flute-again-after-decades/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/franklins-flute.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin&amp;#39;s flute&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Tonight, on a whim, I decided to try out my flute yet again.  Every couple of months for several years now I have pulled it out to see if I might want to start playing it again.  Each time, I encountered serious problems with producing a decent sound at all, and thought that maybe I wasn&amp;rsquo;t meant to play the flute, because the embouchure is such a problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, for the first time in several years, I found that maybe I can get back into playing flute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This possibility pleases me, because the story of me and flutes goes back decades, and is actually rather sad but perhaps instructive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;elementary-school&#34;&gt;Elementary school&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story starts in the last year of elementary school, 5th grade, when a bunch of us students were given the opportunity to choose and start playing a musical instrument. I can still remember Mr. Peters, the music teacher, asking each of us individually what we wanted to play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this time in my life (ten years old), I had received minimal musical instruction so far. I did not grow up in a sufficiently privileged family to receive formal musical lessons, and in fact had never even touched or seen in real life any other musical instrument than the upright piano we just got at home because my mother and younger sister wanted one. I did not listen to any music, had never gone to any kind of musical concert or event before, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d asked my mother earlier what I should ask Mr. Peters to play, so I was ready to answer him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I timidly asked, &amp;ldquo;Piano?&amp;rdquo; Mr. Peters smiled and said, no, that&amp;rsquo;s not something available in the music program. I then asked, &amp;ldquo;Violin?&amp;rdquo; Again, no. I was getting really embarrassed now, because I didn&amp;rsquo;t even know what a violin was: I&amp;rsquo;d never heard one or seen one, but it was a word planted in my head by my mother! (Only many years later did I find out that all Asian kids are supposed to play piano or violin.) Finally, I said, &amp;ldquo;Flute?&amp;rdquo; Yes, flute was an option.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So that&amp;rsquo;s how I started out on flute. I had never encountered a flute before. It was just a word to me. To this day I don&amp;rsquo;t know why my mother had this instrument in her mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;renting-an-instrument&#34;&gt;Renting an instrument&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of my classmates and I ended up renting instruments through the school. My father was not at all interested in my playing music and only because my mother thought I should learn a musical instrument did he cough up the cash to rent a flute for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t particularly like the flute, but I did enjoy getting started playing it. Mostly, I enjoyed the new social group I had: those of use who started on an instrument would gather and learn to play together. That was new to me, and fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;practice&#34;&gt;Practice&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I did not like practicing. I &lt;em&gt;hated&lt;/em&gt; it. Worse, we were given time sheets to fill out indicating how much time we spent practicing at home every day, and have that signed by our parents as witnesses. Well, I wasn&amp;rsquo;t practicing enough, and got scolded by Mr. Peters. I started lying or padding my estimate of how much time I practiced (I still remember writing in &amp;ldquo;30&amp;rdquo; for minutes practiced inside little boxes). What did my father know anyway about what happened when I supposed got started practicing at home and then ended half an hour later?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;middle-school&#34;&gt;Middle school&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When middle school began, I took 6th grade band. Band ended up being the basis of my social life as it was. I still wasn&amp;rsquo;t really practicing flute. Furthermore, I had come to &lt;em&gt;hate&lt;/em&gt; flute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;bad-instrument&#34;&gt;Bad instrument&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing that happened was that flute rental was over, and I had my father buy me a flute. Of course, he bought a totally beat up piece of crap from some garage sale or something somewhere. It was a horrible instrument. The pads got sticky, the mouthpiece was bent, and it was just no fun to play, it was hard to make a good sound out of it, and I knew it was a lot worse than my elementary school rental.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used that flute for another two years before I stopped playing it, forever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;girly-instrument&#34;&gt;Girly instrument&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another thing that happened was that most of the other kids playing flute was girls. Oops, I had ended up with a girly instrument! This was not a trivial matter, given that puberty was starting to kick in, along with a lot of social awareness and anxiety that I never had in elementary school.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-instrument-i-really-wanted-to-play&#34;&gt;The instrument I really wanted to play&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, finally being exposed to a whole bunch of different instruments, hearing them, especially hearing the really good kids, I realized that I really wanted to play the cornet (from which there was a clear path to trumpet).  I liked that the cornet/trumpet was prominent, loud, got the main melodies, everyone could hear it (not always the case with the flute parts!), and of course, it was &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; girly (although, interestingly, a number of girls did play it and were really good at it, and I had a crush on all of them).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, I knew there was no chance my parents would allow me to switch to trumpet. So all I did was dream about playing trumpet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I played flute in the 6th grade, and then in the 7th grade.  I played without &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; enjoyment of the flute during those two years. I did enjoy the social bonding from band, but that was basically it. Also, playing in band allowed one to place out of physical education (don&amp;rsquo;t ask me why), and I dreaded gym class, so I stuck to music to get out of gym (a big mistake, in retrospect).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;high-school&#34;&gt;High school&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;9th-grade&#34;&gt;9th grade&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I skipped the 8th grade of middle school (for reasons beyond the scope of this blog post), and started the 9th grade of high school. Again, I took band in order to avoid gym. It was a miserable experience. Not only did I have to wake up super early to have my mother drive me to marching band practice at 5 AM before school classes started at 7 AM, but also, as a young 9th grader I felt particularly out of place among students who were as much as four years older than me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall the 9th grade was a miserable part of my life, and band was just one part of that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;10th-grade-through-12th-grade&#34;&gt;10th grade through 12th grade&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the 9th grade, because I threatened to drop out of school, the family moved to a different city and a different school after that, and I started 10th grade in a 10-12 high school.  Because of my miserable experiences with flute and with band, and the fact that there was no longer a gym exception for being in band, it never even occurred to me to look into joining a band at the new high school. Of course, that was perfectly OK with my father, who never liked my wasting my time on music anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This high school also had an orchestra, which I knew nothing about other than that it existed (remember, I had still never seen a violin in real life, upon reaching high school).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rest of high school was another miserable part of my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;college&#34;&gt;College&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I fell in love with music all over again in college, because of a kind of accident. There was a requirement to take courses from a &amp;ldquo;core curriculum&amp;rdquo;, and first semester of freshman year, I randomly signed up for &amp;ldquo;Piano Music of the 19th Century&amp;rdquo;. It was a great class. Combined with making new friends who listened to classical music, I started listening to a lot of music. I also started trying to teach myself piano. In retrospect, I should have tried to get real instruction, but I knew that there was no parental support for my &amp;ldquo;wasting my life&amp;rdquo; on a new musical hobby.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;buying-a-new-flute&#34;&gt;Buying a new flute&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another decade or so after college, I got the idea that maybe I should try out flute again! After all, the adolescent days of thinking it was &amp;ldquo;girly&amp;rdquo; were over. The flute has still never been my favorite instrument to listen to, but I already had a head start on it, and various other instruments are more expensive to play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I bought a brand new flute (the one pictured in this blog post). Unfortunately, I kept on having a hard time making decent sounds on it, until tonight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;trumpet&#34;&gt;Trumpet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I had the wild idea of finally realizing my childhood dream and learning trumpet. I bought a trumpet. I started practicing, but realized a couple of things.  One was that it is a &lt;em&gt;very loud&lt;/em&gt; instrument. I have neighbors and stuff. I got a mute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More seriously, I found the pressure on my lips unpleasant, and the pressure in general gave me a headache. Reluctantly, I concluded that it was not healthy for me to really play the trumpet, and put it aside. Recently, I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/01/run-shadyside-5k-outrunning-mickey-mouse-and-lending-a-trumpet/&#34;&gt;lent&lt;/a&gt; it to someone who is hopefully making more use of the instrument than I was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-future&#34;&gt;The future&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regarding taking up the flute again as a result of tonight: I already started playing a new musical instrument this year, the &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/recorder/&#34;&gt;recorder&lt;/a&gt;, and I already spend an average of an hour a day practicing it.  (I also got started on &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/accordion/&#34;&gt;accordion&lt;/a&gt;, but have not had time so far to continue with it.) So it&amp;rsquo;s unclear to me how much I can devote to restarting the flute. I&amp;rsquo;d like to spend some time at least messing around in order to evaluate whether it&amp;rsquo;s worth restarting. One nice thing about the flute is that it is very versatile and if I were to get competent at playing it, I could play it in more contexts than I can currently play the recorder in. I enjoy the recorder, but it has various limitations as an instrument (which is why in Bach&amp;rsquo;s time the Baroque flute came to replace the use of the recorder, and then the modern flute was invented).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Run Shadyside 5K: Outrunning Mickey Mouse and Lending a Trumpet</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/10/01/run-shadyside-5k-outrunning-mickey-mouse-and-lending-a-trumpet/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Oct 2011 09:47:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/10/01/run-shadyside-5k-outrunning-mickey-mouse-and-lending-a-trumpet/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My alarm starts blaring at 6:30 AM on a cold, dark Saturday morning, and I&amp;rsquo;m tired and sleepy, and briefly wonder why I preregistered on Wednesday to run today&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.runshadyside.com/&#34;&gt;Run Shadyside 5K&lt;/a&gt; race. But a commitment is a commitment, so I get, check the weather forecast, get dressed, eat something, and head off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Little do I know that today I will just manage to outrun Mickey Mouse, far exceed my race time goal, and lend someone my trumpet that has been lying around unused!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/franklin-and-mickey-mouse-eric.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin and Eric after the race&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;pre-race&#34;&gt;Pre-race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since it was cold, in the 40s, and there was a possibility it could rain (although things looked clear), I wore a long-sleeve shirt and gloves and a hat along with my shorts and Bikila LS shoes (this was the third race in which I used these shoes).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After my successful &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/25/blistered-but-blissful-in-the-burgh/&#34;&gt;Great Race 10K&lt;/a&gt; toughened me up, I was ready to run a &amp;ldquo;fast&amp;rdquo; 5K race. I had run a 5K in August in 24:36, and another in September in 24:36, but these were mostly off-road and hilly, so I expected that I should definitely go under 24:00 in this mostly flat road race, I targeted 23:30 as an ambitious goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing you have to realize is that I hadn&amp;rsquo;t run a decent 5K in years, so my goal was to really gut it out in this one. My fastest 5K was in 2003, in 20:37. I slowed down gradually to 22:04 in 2007, but later in 2007, as my life entered turmoil, I slowed to 23:30, then 24:39 in 2008, 25:20 in 2009, and 26:41 in 2010. So I have been using races this year as a gauge of my gradual &amp;ldquo;comeback&amp;rdquo; to my former level of fitness (taking aging into account, of course).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-race&#34;&gt;The race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/QslAbd-_TsA&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The gun went off and the race played out for me as most largish races do: I took care not to go out too fast, but a lot of people always act otherwise and pass me like crazy during the first minutes of the race. I just &lt;a href=&#34;http://sethgodin.typepad.com/seths_blog/2011/09/run-your-own-race.html&#34;&gt;run my own race&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a mile, things were mostly settled down. I noticed a guy ahead of me wearing a hat with Mickey Mouse ears.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mickey-mouse-ears-hat-profile.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Mickey Mouse ears hat&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, the gap between the guy and me was ever so slowly increasing. I decided at that moment that with two miles to go, I was going to do what I could to beat this guy. This goal was going to be the single purpose of my life for the next 15 minutes (approximately).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To motivate myself even further, I used the mind trick of publicly proclaiming my goal. I know this technique is &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ted.com/talks/derek_sivers_keep_your_goals_to_yourself.html&#34;&gt;controversial&lt;/a&gt; and can backfire, but I think it depends on context. Every time I found myself running side by side with someone (whether someone I was passing or someone who had caught up to me), I told him that I was going to catch Mickey Mouse. Somehow saying that always gave me a bit of energy each time, and I would pass the guy I just talked with and not look back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I pushed really hard but for the whole second mile had still not yet closed the gap with Mickey Mouse. Sometimes I could not even see him, but I always made sure to find him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Around halfway through the third mile, I started closing on Mickey Mouse. For the first time in the race, I was totally confident that I had what it took to beat him. I finally overtook him when the finish line was in sight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;final-sprint&#34;&gt;Final sprint&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that was not all. I saw the clock and was surprised to find that I was going to come in well under 23:00!  In the excitement, I decided to go wild.  I &lt;strong&gt;screamed&lt;/strong&gt;, as though I were dying, as I launched into a big sprint to pass probably a dozen people as I stumbled over the finish line in something like 22:46.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Man, that was cathartic. This is only the second time I have ever screamed in a race (and I have run in well over a hundred in the past decade). I had let out a scream during a sprint finish at the Pretty Good Race 5K in September, but it was a short scream, not this prolonged seconds-long one that I let out today. I supposed that in the past decade I used to be too shy to do a thing like that, but it felt so good today that I may do it in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was reminded of how in karate class I was instructed on how important it was to use the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kiai&#34;&gt;kiai&lt;/a&gt; shout as a projection of energy. But then I reflected, my scream was not objectively the best way to end a race. If I had enough energy to scream, then I should have been able to run faster before that point, so a smarter race would have been to push even harder before the somewhat wasteful sprint. Nevertheless, at the very moment today, the scream seemed the thing to do, for psychological reasons, at least.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;post-race&#34;&gt;Post-race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mickey Mouse came in seconds later. I went up to him and shook his hand, then grabbed some water and food and started walking back to my car (parked almost a mile away), since I needed to cool down from the race, and wanted to get my camera and warm clothing to bring back to the post-race party.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the way back from my car, I saw Mickey Mouse, but without the ears. He was walking with his family and I approached him and had his mother take a photo of us. His name is &lt;a href=&#34;http://ericbrockmeyer.com/&#34;&gt;Eric&lt;/a&gt; and he said he wasn&amp;rsquo;t the only one with Mickey Mouse ears: a bunch of Disney Research people were all wearing them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got back to the post-race party and happened to see a guy I know from lots of previous races in the past decade, Ron Romanoff, and had him take a photo of me:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-shadyside-2011-franklin.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin after Run Shadyside 5K 2011&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;bumping-into-ben-paul&#34;&gt;Bumping into Ben Paul&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-shadyside-2011-festivities.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Festivities after Run Shadyside 5K 2011&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-shadyside-2011-pancakes.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Pancakes after Run Shadyside 5K 2011&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I saw a sign for pancakes, and suddenly realized that I had totally forgotten about the post-race pancake breakfast. I put away the half-eaten bagel I was munching on and headed toward the pancakes, and whom did I see but &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.communiteach.com/post/10818529188&#34;&gt;Ben Paul&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-shadyside-2011-ben-paul.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Ben Paul with coffee after Run Shadyside 5K 2011&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I had first met and talked with Ben at &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/22/starting-a-new-web-site/&#34;&gt;PodCamp Pittsburgh&lt;/a&gt;, although I had heard his name much earlier since he was one of the founders of &lt;a href=&#34;http://communiteach.com/&#34;&gt;CommuniTeach&lt;/a&gt;. CommuniTeach is a really great concept, providing a way for people who want to learn stuff, or teach it, or both, to get together. Back in June, Abby and I had attended a CommuniTeach session on &lt;a href=&#34;http://communiteach.com/learnitss.php?glid=151&#34;&gt;fermentation&lt;/a&gt;. We learned to make kefir and sauerkraut and experiment with various fermented veggie combinations involving radishes, carrots, zucchini, onion, fennel seeds, you name it. Since July (when our first batch was ready), we&amp;rsquo;ve been enjoying tasty fermented veggies to complement our meals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are curious about teaching or learning anything in the Pittsburgh area, I highly recommend that you sign up on &lt;a href=&#34;http://communiteach.com/&#34;&gt;CommuniTeach&lt;/a&gt; and check it out! I also find the &lt;a href=&#34;http://twitter.com/#!/CommuniTeach&#34;&gt;@CommuniTeach&lt;/a&gt; very useful to follow, and there is also a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.facebook.com/pages/CommuniTeach/99389138220&#34;&gt;Facebook site&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;music&#34;&gt;Music&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I mentioned to Ben that I&amp;rsquo;d been reading about him from the links that he&amp;rsquo;s posted. I&amp;rsquo;d just learned that he played melodica, and I said that I have a melodica too, but have not been playing it. I said I was also learning accordion recently. I asked him about ukulele, since he had mentioned it somewhere, and he suggested that a bunch of us find a way to teach ourselves together. I pointed out that unfortunately, I was already focusing a lot of my musical time on playing recorder and for now my ukulele goals are on hold. He couldn&amp;rsquo;t believe I played recorder, since he hates the sound, ha! I happened to mention that I had too many instruments I didn&amp;rsquo;t play, such as a trumpet. He got excited, because he needs a trumpet to play, and I offered to lend him mine. So we decided that he could meet up at my place to pick it up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We looked at the posted race results and Ben couldn&amp;rsquo;t find himself listed. He was pretty bummed about that. It was his first race! It turned out that he had not attached the race chip to his shoe, but it was still attached to his race number on his shirt. Oops. Nevertheless, in case anyone ever doubts it: I hereby declare myself as a witness to Ben Paul having run his first race today in Shadyside!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;trumpet-finally-finds-a-happy-player&#34;&gt;Trumpet finally finds a happy player!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s Ben with my trumpet. Enjoy playing it, Ben!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/ben-paul-with-franklins-trumpet.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Ben Paul with Franklin&amp;#39;s trumpet&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;rain&#34;&gt;Rain&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It started raining outside just as Ben left with the trumpet. I am &lt;em&gt;so&lt;/em&gt; grateful that it did not rain during the race! I was prepared to deal with it (I have run cold half marathons during which it rained the whole time), but it would not have been so much fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2012-10-06&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-10-06)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following year, sadly, I did not do Run Shadyside again, because of a schedule conflict with &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/10/06/the-fineview-stepathon-2012-pittsburghs-grueling-urban-trail-race/&#34;&gt;the Fineview Stepathon that I did instead&lt;/a&gt;. We&amp;rsquo;ll have to see what the schedules are for 2013.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>