<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Thanksgiving on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/thanksgiving/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Thanksgiving on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/thanksgiving/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Report on my fourth day of Stoic Week 2014: virtue and relationships with others</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/27/report-on-my-fourth-day-of-stoic-week-2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2014 21:47:45 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/27/report-on-my-fourth-day-of-stoic-week-2014/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today was Thanksgiving in the US, a surprisingly appropriate day to be in the middle of observing Stoic Week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;thanksgiving-dinner&#34;&gt;Thanksgiving dinner&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/11/27/report-on-my-third-day-of-stoic-week-2014/&#34;&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve reported on yesterday&amp;rsquo;s theme&lt;/a&gt; of self-discipline and simplicity. At Thanksgiving dinner this year, I decided for the very first time to limit what I ate. I&amp;rsquo;ve always overeaten in the past, with poor results. It was just something I did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year, I did not eat any of the cake or pumpkin pie that was offered. For dessert (after the turkey etc.), I limited myself to one scoop of pistachio gelato and one cookie. Actually, I ended up regretting that cookie, because it was more substantial and sugary than I expected, so I&amp;rsquo;ve made a note to watch myself with the cookies. The gelato I may not have needed, but I enjoyed it all the more knowing it was the one main dessert I was allowing myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;fourth-day-of-health-habits&#34;&gt;Fourth day of health habits&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s my fourth day now of daily meditation and exercise. Actually, I overdid it on the exercise today, but not intentionally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been increasing the intensity of my short (seven-minute or so) daily workouts every day, lifting heavier weights and working more muscles. What I didn&amp;rsquo;t expect was that at the Thanksgiving party, two young sisters (of ages around five and two) were bored and wanted to play, and I rather exerted myself. The older one was the ringleader. We played at scaring each other and I pretended to be sitting on the couch sleeping and suddenly spring up and boo or growl, and I accidentally pulled something in my right arm during one of these explosive, sudden movements. I also pulled my left shoulder when the two challenged me to lift them repeatedly, and the older one (tall for her age) was heavier than I expected and not so easy to repeatedly lift, given that I&amp;rsquo;d already had a workout in the morning at home. All in good fun, but left me a bit overextended.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;on-today-s-theme&#34;&gt;On today&amp;rsquo;s theme&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find sensible the Stoic teaching of developing our &amp;ldquo;natural affection&amp;rdquo;, and expanding outward from ourselves. I feel I have been the beneficiary of much good from many people in my life and am grateful for this. The Thanksgiving dinner that Abby and I went to today is one we have attended for some years now. The hosts I met through Abby, who met them (and other dinner guests) through music and dance circles. I appreciate and deeply admire the generosity that they have shown us and to many others. I look up to them as role models for the kind of genuine affection that human beings can display and share, not only with immediate family or closest friends but outward to larger communities (such as local music communities) and beyond.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tragic shooting and death that happened this year in &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shooting_of_Michael_Brown&#34;&gt;Ferguson, Missouri&lt;/a&gt; has been in the news for some months now, and this week the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shooting_of_Michael_Brown#Announcement_of_no_bill&#34;&gt;grand jury decided not to indict&lt;/a&gt;. I haven&amp;rsquo;t commented in public or in private on any of these events, or on any of the commentary about them, but I do not dismiss what has happened as irrelevant to my life. In fact, I feel that what has happened has been so important, in the biggest possible picture of what has been going on in American history for a long time, that I cannot afford to lightly spew sound bites about it. I do ask myself, how can I best talk about what I am feeling? How can I make a positive difference, in the Stoic &amp;ldquo;cosmopolitan&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;love of all humanity&amp;rdquo;? I don&amp;rsquo;t know the answer yet, but I know what is not the answer: fanning the flames of passion. But simply being silent is also not the answer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2015-01-19&#34;&gt;(Update of 2015-01-19)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wrote something in &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2015/01/19/for-martin-luther-king-jr-day-some-black-american-voices-that-spoke-to-me-recently/&#34;&gt;observation of Martin Luther King, Jr. Day&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I take seriously the Stoic call that we are ethically responsible for more than just ourselves, that we are to develop ourselves outward (not just on inner virtues) and work to honestly consider all human beings our brothers and sisters. I see how I have been treated in such a way by others through my life and aspire to expand beyond myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How do you feel about cosmopolitanism? Do you feel it is naive, that it is best to just look out after family and clan? If you have been following the Ferguson tragedy, do you easily choose a simple &amp;ldquo;side&amp;rdquo;, an &amp;ldquo;us&amp;rdquo; versus &amp;ldquo;them&amp;rdquo;?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thanking the best of all possible worlds</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/11/22/thanking-the-best-of-all-possible-worlds/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Nov 2012 21:55:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/11/22/thanking-the-best-of-all-possible-worlds/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Happy Thanksgiving, everyone!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-Lc7Oc2PreKI/T3U0A6pSPBI/AAAAAAAABxY/iTXcrFFn1sQ/s1600/tumblr_kx61vvQHfG1qz82gvo1_500.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Oppenheimer quote&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Today, on a sunny Thanksgiving, I surprised myself by spontaneously deciding to thank this world, and go as far as to call it &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Best_of_all_possible_worlds&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;the best of all possible worlds&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;m still not entirely sure what I mean by that, but somehow, I &amp;ldquo;believe&amp;rdquo; it; more precisely, it&amp;rsquo;s an &lt;em&gt;attitude&lt;/em&gt; I now have that I have never really had in my life up till now. Even &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/23/every-day-is-thanksgiving/&#34;&gt;a year ago&lt;/a&gt;, I would have thought it silly to adopt such an attitude.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A friend of mine asked, &amp;ldquo;Dr. Pangloss?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, am I being a fool?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;being-dr-pangloss&#34;&gt;Being Dr. Pangloss?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Pangloss is a fictional character from &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Voltaire&#34;&gt;Voltaire&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s satirical novella &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Candide&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Candide&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; that was required reading in high school French. I remember reading that novella in high school, of course: it was a &lt;em&gt;profound&lt;/em&gt; influence on me at the time, instilling a certain cynicism in me that lasted years. Voltaire wrote this novella as a direct attempt to refute &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gottfried_Wilhelm_Leibniz&#34;&gt;Leibniz&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s philosophy of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Best_of_all_possible_worlds&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;best of all possible worlds&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;: Pangloss is a buffoonish character who spouts parodies of Leibniz&amp;rsquo;s reasoning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No question about it, Candide is a wickedly entertaining satire, and Voltaire is a towering figure from the French Enlightenment, one who exposed a lot of hypocrisy and was an advocate of many social reforms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;philosophy-vs-attitude&#34;&gt;Philosophy vs. attitude&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I have over the years come to believe that the Enlightenment emphasis on Reason is not by itself the panacea to the mysteries and problems of life. In particular, I perceive that often, this emphasis leads to arrogance, anger, and selective blindness. There doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem any logical &lt;em&gt;reason&lt;/em&gt; that &lt;em&gt;Reason&lt;/em&gt; should lead to this, but it really happens. It happened to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I have not by any means abandoned &lt;em&gt;reason&lt;/em&gt;, but I have long since abandoned &lt;em&gt;Reason&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, I&amp;rsquo;m going to confess that Leibniz&amp;rsquo;s philosophical work does not make a whole lot of sense to me. So my adopting an &lt;em&gt;attitude&lt;/em&gt; of &amp;ldquo;this is the best of all possible worlds&amp;rdquo; is in no way an endorsement of any belief in Leibniz&amp;rsquo;s philosophical/theological system. And I certainly have also observed that there are people who do accept Leibniz&amp;rsquo;s purported solution to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Problem_of_evil&#34;&gt;problem of evil&lt;/a&gt;, who seem to use it as a way to turn a blind eye to the injustices that still occur in our world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short, I am taking an &lt;em&gt;attitude&lt;/em&gt; that I find helps me function in a positive way in the world, without tying myself to a fully worked out philosophy about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;related-ideas&#34;&gt;Related ideas&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A related idea is &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amor_fati&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;amor fati&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (&amp;ldquo;love of fate&amp;rdquo;), popularized by Nietzsche but coming from &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stoicism&#34;&gt;Stoicism&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Steve Pavlina wrote today about &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.stevepavlina.com/blog/2012/11/this-is-heaven/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;heaven&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;application&#34;&gt;Application&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That I have adopted the &lt;em&gt;optimistic&lt;/em&gt; attitude toward life, after having a mostly &lt;em&gt;pessimistic&lt;/em&gt; one during most of my years, has practical applications. Being &lt;em&gt;grateful&lt;/em&gt; every single day for every positive thing that happens enables me to more easily overcome the negative. My attitude is a choice I have made, and nurtured through various techniques, as mentioned &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/23/every-day-is-thanksgiving/&#34;&gt;last Thanksgiving&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being optimistic does not mean ignoring the negative. It means maintaining the energy to do things, to set things right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have embrace this world as &lt;em&gt;my&lt;/em&gt; world. This is my choice, my attitude. May it be yours as well.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Happy Thanksgiving and a call to action</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/11/24/happy-thanksgiving-and-a-call-to-action/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Nov 2011 10:38:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/11/24/happy-thanksgiving-and-a-call-to-action/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Happy Thanksgiving, everyone! Please take time out to give thanks today, whether out loud or silently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday I wrote about how &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/23/every-day-is-thanksgiving/&#34;&gt;every day is Thanksgiving&lt;/a&gt;. At the end of the post, I wondered about further improving my gratitude practice. I woke up today with a burning desire to take action. I&amp;rsquo;d like to know what you think of my specific ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;gratitude-letters&#34;&gt;Gratitude letters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I first heard about gratitude letters from the fantastic book &lt;a href=&#34;http://chass.ucr.edu/faculty_book/lyubomirsky/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The How of Happiness&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.faculty.ucr.edu/~sonja/index.html&#34;&gt;Sonja Lyubomirsky&lt;/a&gt;. The idea is to directly write a letter of gratitude to an individual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought about this in the context of all the free and open source software I use regularly for work or for personal purposes. I was thinking that I should start taking the time to thank, one by one, each of the developers or teams of such software.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, I follow a lot of blogs. Many of them don&amp;rsquo;t have many followers, so commenting more and offering gratitude would probably be very welcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;gratitude-themed-blog-post&#34;&gt;Gratitude-themed blog post&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps I could reserve one day a week of my blog for the gratitude theme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;gratitude-in-every-blog-post&#34;&gt;Gratitude in every blog post&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or I could find a way to express gratitude in every blog post I write.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;gratitude-tweets&#34;&gt;Gratitude tweets&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe I could tweet gratitude more often. I don&amp;rsquo;t want to annoy my Twitter followers with too much though. And I admit I don&amp;rsquo;t like the length restriction. I guess I don&amp;rsquo;t see as much value in tweeting gratitude as in writing even a decent one-paragraph email to someone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;integrate-into-digital-sabbath&#34;&gt;Integrate into Digital Sabbath&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently I began to observe a little bit of a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/12/starting-a-mini-digital-sabbath/&#34;&gt;Digital Sabbath&lt;/a&gt; on which I do not write a blog post. Maybe I could reserve the day after the Digital Sabbath for a gratitude-oriented post?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;other-ideas&#34;&gt;Other ideas&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lyubomirsky has other ideas, some of which are in &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.beliefnet.com/beyondblue/2010/05/5-ways-to-practice-gratitude-a.html&#34;&gt;this interview&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;your-ideas&#34;&gt;Your ideas&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What ideas do you have about how to integrate more gratitude into your life, starting this Thanksgiving? Or ideas you have about how &lt;em&gt;I&lt;/em&gt; should integrate more gratitude into my life, into my blog?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;postscript&#34;&gt;Postscript&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will be observing an extended Digital Sabbath till the end of the weekend. There will be a lot of turkey, and a lot of friends and family to see again.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Every day is Thanksgiving</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/11/23/every-day-is-thanksgiving/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Nov 2011 23:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/11/23/every-day-is-thanksgiving/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;So tomorrow is &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Thanksgiving&#34;&gt;Thanksgiving&lt;/a&gt;, the American holiday that is so unfortunate for turkeys. Thanksgiving is a traditional time for pausing and giving thanks for all that we are grateful for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I briefly considered creating a little list of some of my reasons for thanks and posting the list here. I changed my mind after realizing that for every item I put on the list, I would be omitting a thousand other items and implicitly suggesting they were less important. Therefore, I decided to not have a list at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, let me advocate making &lt;strong&gt;every day&lt;/strong&gt; Thanksgiving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;negativity&#34;&gt;Negativity&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a time in my life when I easily fell into a persistently cynical, negative mood, and thought happiness and gratitude were for chumps who didn&amp;rsquo;t realize how crappy the world was. I would often feel angry about some injustice in the world, or some injustice done to me. I would wish I had more stuff or were smarter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I realized that this attitude was not helpful, so I tried changing it through reasoning, but the results were never long-lasting. Negative emotions would pop up and create a cycle of anger, envy, resentment, greed, etc. I never experienced an overall sense of harmony and acceptance and gratitude.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;happiness-and-gratitude&#34;&gt;Happiness and gratitude&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things started changing when I started reading about happiness and &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Positive_psychology&#34;&gt;positive psychology&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But one of the few sources that really got me on a path of permanent change was a deeply personal, accessible, and &lt;em&gt;practical&lt;/em&gt; book by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.talbenshahar.com/&#34;&gt;Tal Ben-Shahar&lt;/a&gt;, &amp;ldquo;Happier: Learn the Secrets to Daily Joy and Lasting Fulfillment&amp;rdquo;, published in 2007.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the practical suggestions by Ben-Shahar was that of maintaining a &lt;strong&gt;gratitude journal&lt;/strong&gt; regularly. I thought, OK, this sounds cheesy, but I&amp;rsquo;ll give it a shot.  So I got some blank notebooks, and every day before going to bed, I would write down five thoughts of gratitude that I had genuinely observed arising in myself that day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Years later, I am still writing in my gratitude journal every day&lt;/strong&gt;. When packing for travel, the first thing on my packing list is always my gratitude journal. I&amp;rsquo;ve almost never missed a day of writing in my gratitude journal. The couple of times in the past years when I missed a day were when my life was obviously in considerable disorder and just recognizing my omission was enough to get me back the next day. Yes, I write in my gratitude journal even when I have what seems like a really terrible day, because there is always something that could have been worse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Completely unexpectedly, this simple ritual, the gratitude journal, slowly began to change my life. The changes were subtle but real. Just being aware that there is so much good going on in life, even when it is terrible, keeps me from ever sinking into the kind of depression that I was prone to in my younger days. My negative emotions became more controllable, and my overall outlook on life is positive, and instead of just taking for granted all that is good, I have reset myself so that I appreciate what is good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-goes-into-the-gratitude-journal&#34;&gt;What goes into the gratitude journal?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might be wondering what kinds of things I write about in my gratitude journal. As I mentioned, I simply write down what really comes to mind, relatively spontaneously. Some days I have a lot more exciting items rushing to my mind, and other days I have to struggle to find five. I just happen to always put down at least five, for the sake of regularity, and for the sake of deepening my search for little things that I might not have been conscious of during a day but maybe I could appreciate more fully.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few random shorter examples from my gratitude journals of the past years:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Made decent butternut squash and navy bean soup! First time really.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Got in a lot of walking today as exercise and mental relaxation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Got a haircut from Joe.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It was a peaceful, sunny day.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jim Weirich was great at the Pittsburgh Ruby presentation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Had the last red tea bag in the can, refreshing and awakening.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tasty beef fajitas by Abby for dinner.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Had time to catch up on emails with (long-distance) friends.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Made up with Abby after argument.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shoveling snow today was not too tedious.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Someone had extra water for me on the hike.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nothing seems permanently broken after my big fall.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Still sick, but feel better than yesterday.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Caught up on sleep last night.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given my gratitude journal, every day is in a sense Thanksgiving, but I think something is still missing. I am now considering changing things up with the gratitude journal, because sometimes I take the easy way out and repeat myself with similar items that, yes, matter a lot to me, but are a bit mundane. The gratitude journal is like tweeting. I would like to write longer essays giving thanks. On my to-do list for the blog!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>