<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Practice on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/practice/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Practice on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/practice/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>When I don&#39;t have time to sit and breathe, something is wrong with my life</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/12/30/when-i-dont-have-time-to-sit-and-breathe-something-is-wrong-with-my-life/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Dec 2012 16:35:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/12/30/when-i-dont-have-time-to-sit-and-breathe-something-is-wrong-with-my-life/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/zafus.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Our two zafus&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s been a long time since I&amp;rsquo;ve mentioned &lt;em&gt;meditation&lt;/em&gt; here. In fact, it&amp;rsquo;s been &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/02/23/saying-no-in-order-to-say-yes/&#34;&gt;ten months&lt;/a&gt;! This despite my knowledge of &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/02/02/2-new-daily-habits-of-mine-in-a-distracting-world/&#34;&gt;how beneficial it is&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a reason: I completely lost my &lt;em&gt;meditation practice&lt;/em&gt; at some point this year. I don&amp;rsquo;t even remember when I lost it. It may have had something to do with the fact that the iPad app we had been using as a meditation timer suddenly stopped making sound and we didn&amp;rsquo;t know why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yeah, what a sad excuse. But this is &lt;em&gt;exactly&lt;/em&gt; how, when one&amp;rsquo;s practice is already in trouble, any trivial glitch (so easily solved one way or another) is an excuse to stop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I have periodically &amp;ldquo;tried&amp;rdquo; to get back on, but as Yoda wisely said,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Try not! Do, or do not. There is no try.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/BQ4yd2W50No&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So now what?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;do&#34;&gt;Do&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;ve decided to &amp;ldquo;do&amp;rdquo;. This meant having to discuss the various reasons and chain reactions that lead to not doing meditation, and how to head them off. Meditation &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/02/10/meditation-is-hard/&#34;&gt;can be hard&lt;/a&gt;, but really, sitting and breathing for just &lt;em&gt;ten minutes&lt;/em&gt; in the morning is, objectively, not so hard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s not hard to realize that if I am so &amp;ldquo;busy&amp;rdquo; that I don&amp;rsquo;t have time to sit and breathe for ten minutes, &lt;em&gt;something is wrong with my life&lt;/em&gt;. Something has become unbalanced. Abby and I have had quite a year of many activities and experiences, but at some point, I started neglecting some basics. In particular, the last two months of this year have been something of a blur. Abby has tried to get us back to meditating, but I&amp;rsquo;ve resisted with some pretty bad excuses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But as of today, we are back. Being too &amp;ldquo;busy&amp;rdquo; means priorities are out of whack: did I really need to read those blog posts or tweets for ten minutes, instead of meditating? The answer is embarrassingly obvious when the mind is clear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, and as for the iPad meditation app: I checked the app and it&amp;rsquo;s making the start and end sounds just fine now. And if it didn&amp;rsquo;t, that wouldn&amp;rsquo;t stop us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meditation is good, and I&amp;rsquo;m back. In order to commit myself to keeping up the practice, I have decided that I should write about meditation on this blog at least once a month! It&amp;rsquo;s on my calendar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-02-01&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-02-01)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A report on &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/02/01/a-report-on-one-month-of-daily-meditation/&#34;&gt;my meditation in January 2013&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-03-01&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-03-01)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A report on &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/01/dealing-with-setbacks-during-my-second-month-of-meditation/&#34;&gt;my meditation in February 2013&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Playing recorder in a group</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/10/21/playing-recorder-in-a-group/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Oct 2012 19:23:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/10/21/playing-recorder-in-a-group/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Today was the second meeting of the current season of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.andrew.cmu.edu/user/lukas/pcars/Welcome.html&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh chapter of the American Recorder Society&lt;/a&gt;. I reported last month on &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/16/excited-by-the-new-season-of-the-pittsburgh-recorder-society/&#34;&gt;how excited I was to begin the new season&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-recorder-dessert.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Pittsburgh Recorder Society dessert by Helen&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And it&amp;rsquo;s not just about the tasty desserts that Helen makes for us every month, of course (which basically compel me to exercise &lt;em&gt;before&lt;/em&gt; going to the meeting).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had some new people joining us today, including a woman who had been a member of the recorder society three decades ago, and now was retired and getting back into playing the recorder. It was great having her on board. We have some really good music selections from our director Fred to work on, hopefully toward a holiday performance by our group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She mentioned it being different and hard playing in an ensemble, since she was used to playing piano alone. Her comments made me immediately think back to where I was a year ago. Coincidentally, almost exactly a year ago, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/30/harder-to-play-in-a-group-than-alone/&#34;&gt;I wrote about the challenges of playing in a group&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m so grateful for the opportunity to play with others. It makes me realize that I spent far too much of my life being alone, doing everything alone, and that I was really missing out. Yes, being with others may be more difficult sometimes, but it completely changes my experience of life, making it so much richer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;fred-s-tips-i-appreciated-today&#34;&gt;Fred&amp;rsquo;s tips I appreciated today&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On one of the pieces we are working on, I&amp;rsquo;m playing the alto 1 line. Fred gave me really useful feedback. He noted that I was holding back and not playing &lt;em&gt;all out&lt;/em&gt;. I said that I was afraid of going squeaky on the high G. He said that we should always play all out, and that this alto 1 part is &amp;ldquo;glorious&amp;rdquo; and should &amp;ldquo;ring&amp;rdquo;. Furthermore, he also reminded us that when we practice (either at home or in a group), we should go &lt;em&gt;beyond&lt;/em&gt; what we&amp;rsquo;d do in performance, and exaggerate the elements of music that we want to bring out. There are a number of reasons for this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We must do more in practice so that when we are ready to perform, what we do will actually be easier than what we&amp;rsquo;ve done already again and again in private.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Our subjective perception of how we sound is inaccurate: what sounds like &amp;ldquo;overdoing&amp;rdquo; to us (without actually recording ourselves) may not sound like much to an actual audience.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The paradox of practice: it&#39;s harder to go slow than go fast</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/08/02/the-paradox-of-practice-its-harder-to-go-slow-than-go-fast/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Aug 2012 23:09:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/08/02/the-paradox-of-practice-its-harder-to-go-slow-than-go-fast/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently, by coincidence, I&amp;rsquo;ve seen a lot of articles about the benefits of &lt;em&gt;slow&lt;/em&gt; practice of a skill, whether in music or martial arts. Some good links that really apply to all physical skills:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bulletproofmusician.com/is-slow-practice-really-necessary/&#34;&gt;Is slow practice really necessary?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://musiciansway.com/blog/2011/02/a-different-kind-of-slow-practice/&#34;&gt;A different kind of slow practice&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://billplakemusic.org/2012/07/18/keep-this-aim-in-mind-when-practicing-slowly/&#34;&gt;Keep this aim in mind when practicing slowly&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://themartialartscoach.com/train-slow-to-learn-fast&#34;&gt;Train slow to learn fast&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We live in an era of &lt;em&gt;speed&lt;/em&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s gotten to the point that there have arisen some movements against speed, for &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Slow_Movement&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;slow&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a confession to make: it&amp;rsquo;s really hard for me to practice music slowly. I myself am guilty of often practicing music too quickly, not making the most of my practice. For a while, when I was starting to play music again after an absence of three decades, I was pushing myself with a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/29/a-musicians-best-friend/&#34;&gt;metronome&lt;/a&gt;. That was useful for a while, but eventually I realized I had to slow down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am now actually trying to apply the advice in the articles mentioned and &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; slow down in music. Because I know in my heart that slowing down works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I think about it, I have successfully used slow practice in many fields in the past, from ballroom dance to running to chess. I&amp;rsquo;d like to give examples of what slow practice actually means in each of these and how I attribute my success to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;ballroom-dance&#34;&gt;Ballroom dance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was learning &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/ballroom-dance/&#34;&gt;ballroom dance&lt;/a&gt; over a decade ago, I started out as a very uncoordinated, clumsy, confused beginner in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://cmubdc.org/&#34;&gt;Carnegie Mellon University Ballroom Dance Club&lt;/a&gt;. I was &lt;em&gt;very lucky&lt;/em&gt; that I stumbled around only about a month before I started getting quality professional instruction in a small group setting (a benefit of the club) supplementing the large group classes (which I had found barely helpful, frankly).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;rumba-to-cha-cha&#34;&gt;Rumba to cha cha&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will never forget the Latin (International style) dance technique lessons of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.artandstyledancestudio.com/&#34;&gt;Rozana Sweeney&lt;/a&gt;. She basically treated us as she would little kids intending to become professional ballroom dancers. Unlike in the group classes at CMU, where we were just shown steps and patterns and told to go do them, we were shown a very limited repertoire of movements that were broken down to atomic components (so much as that is possible for a continuous art form) and practiced &lt;em&gt;very slowly&lt;/em&gt;. We were not allowed to move on until we had at least some rudimentary &amp;ldquo;mastery&amp;rdquo; of the &amp;ldquo;basics&amp;rdquo;. I&amp;rsquo;d never had any dance experience before, so it was quite eye-opening how effective this stern approach to instruction was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We started off practicing the International rumba basics. We were taught about straight legs, bent legs, foot turnout, hip rotation, contrary motion of body and arms, etc. We went through the movements so slowly (to beats or music much slower than the actual standardized-tempo dance music) that many of us lost balance and tripped over ourselves. &lt;em&gt;It is harder to move slow than fast.&lt;/em&gt; Balance is important. If you go fast, you cheat because you can move without full balance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eventually we moved on to cha cha, which is a rather faster dance, but similar to a sped-up rumba with a very fast extra three &amp;ldquo;cha cha cha&amp;rdquo; steps. I couldn&amp;rsquo;t help noticing how my cha cha &amp;ldquo;magically&amp;rdquo; improved, &lt;em&gt;without ever practicing cha cha&lt;/em&gt;, just from practicing rumba so much. The reason was clear: making the slow precise is the key to making the fast precise. If the slow is not efficient and exact, then going fast will only result in a magnification of inefficiency and sloppiness. I believe nobody can dance a good cha cha who can&amp;rsquo;t also dance a good rumba. That&amp;rsquo;s just how it works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;slow-waltz-and-foxtrot-to-quickstep-and-viennese-waltz&#34;&gt;Slow waltz and foxtrot to quickstep and Viennese waltz&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Focusing on the slow was also true of our International standard dance instruction, which came from some other instructors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We started off with slow waltz and foxtrot, working on the technique in slow motion, before dancing the fast quickstep and Viennese waltz. The fast dances are quite strenuous (as a runner, I compare dancing them with a partner to be as tiring as running) and things fall apart if you haven&amp;rsquo;t figured out how to move efficiently and together slowly first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;results&#34;&gt;Results&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I improved very quickly in ballroom dance once I started having the serious technique lessons and worked on basic movements by myself outside of class, repeatedly. I still feel I had a lot of potential improvement still in me, because of the foundational slow practice, at the time &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/10/flute-loving-it-again/&#34;&gt;when I quit competitive ballroom dancing&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;running&#34;&gt;Running&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I started &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/running/&#34;&gt;running&lt;/a&gt;, I was 29 years old and had been sedentary all my life. I didn&amp;rsquo;t know what I was doing when I first started running. I would just go out and run hard, get out of breath very quickly, stop, and go on. I got sore this way, and also did not actually improve my speed much during my first sloppy year of running. I only got &lt;em&gt;much faster&lt;/em&gt; when I learned the science of how to run &lt;em&gt;slowly&lt;/em&gt;. I got much faster than friends I was running with who were still running the unsystematic way, at a faster training pace than me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is possible to run too slowly for benefit. But the trick is to run slowly enough in order to be relaxed, observe one&amp;rsquo;s form, correct it, and put in the time to slowly build up endurance. Running too fast only led me to go for a shorter period of time, execute with poor form, and get injured.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not actually easy to run slowly, properly. It is trivial to run slowly sloppily. Many people you see on the roads or in the parks who are &amp;ldquo;jogging&amp;rdquo; are going slowly and sloppily. Stomping loudly into the ground, head tilted back, slow long strides: that&amp;rsquo;s not a good way to run slowly. If you want to run slowly, the right way to do it is to adopt a good upright, balanced posture, be aware of landing under the hip, using the glutes and not the knees, and most important, making sure the cadence is &lt;em&gt;not too slow&lt;/em&gt;. In other words, slow doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean everything is slow; it means slowing down some variables but maintaining structural and dynamic integrity of the whole. Taking a super long stride slowly violates the physics of how to move.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Needless to say, for optimal training one must also run fast. Again, here the principle of adjusting variables applies, however. Running very fast for a long time is not the most effective way to train. The most effective way to train is known to be &lt;em&gt;interval training&lt;/em&gt;, in which you run fast but for a short period of time, then rest, then continue. In a sense, here the &amp;ldquo;slow&amp;rdquo; variable is distance covered while not resting. In slow running, the &amp;ldquo;slow&amp;rdquo; variable is the speed, not the distance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;results-1&#34;&gt;Results&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a couple of years, upon finding good running technique books and Web sites, and applying them, I went from nothing to winning age-group medals and trophies in local races in Pittsburgh (admittedly not so competitive in my age group). I am a believer in the importance of having learned to run sufficiently slowly when the training situation calls for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;chess&#34;&gt;Chess&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/chess/&#34;&gt;chess&lt;/a&gt; players, myself included, enjoying playing &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fast_chess&#34;&gt;fast chess&lt;/a&gt;. Five-minute games are exciting and fun because you can play so many of them in a given time and there is little time to think. But we all know that playing too much blitz chess can harm one&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;serious&amp;rdquo; slow chess games, games in which you may get two hours of time on your clock rather than five minutes. The problem, of course, is that getting used to making moves without thinking much does not train you to know how to think more deeply when you have much more time to use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Learning to play chess slowly is a challenge. I was never very good at playing slowly as a child, because I was impatient, and did not have a chess teacher to discipline me. When I returned to playing serious tournament chess, twenty years after not playing a single game, I suffered tremendously, because I had no idea how to make use of time during slow games. But with practice, analyzing games at home slowly in order to simulate the process, I learned how to look more deeply in the tree of possible game continuations. I would give myself three minutes, say, to do an analysis, and then computer-check it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I noticed that getting better at playing slowly actually helped me get better at playing quickly too (to some extent). There is a statistical correlation, indeed, between the regular strength of a chess player (as measured by an official rating) and his or her speed strength (as measured by an official speed rating). This should not be surprising: in distance running, there is a correlation between speed at running a mile and speed at running a marathon. The mile and marathon are very different distances, but a certain kind of fundamental efficiency is involved in both.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;results-2&#34;&gt;Results&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just over a year after I started playing chess again, initially poorly, my practice in playing slow chess at Tuesday night &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburghcc.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Chess Club&lt;/a&gt; tournaments (at two hours per game for each player) in combination with some (but not too much) casual fast chess at the club resulted in my surprising excellence at &amp;ldquo;slow fast&amp;rdquo; chess: I won the &lt;a href=&#34;http://pscfchess.org/results/06040808.htm&#34;&gt;2006 Pennsylvania State Game/29 Championship&lt;/a&gt; with a perfect score, and also won the &lt;a href=&#34;http://pscfchess.org/results/06101414.htm&#34;&gt;2006 Pennsylvania State Action Chess Championship&lt;/a&gt; with a perfect score (at time controls of 29 minutes per game and 30 minutes per game, respectively). Doing well at two-hour games made me even better at 29-minute games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slow practice works. It has worked for me in different fields. I want to make it work for music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slow practice requires much discipline, patience, and metacognitive awareness It is easy to take shortcuts unless one has bootstrapped a skill enough in order to be able to know oneself and to recognize one&amp;rsquo;s weaknesses and deliberately work on correcting them. Wonderful Web sites and books and videos on technique do exist that can help these days, even without a personal instructor.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mideast Early Music Workshop 2012: a life-changing experience!!</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/07/21/mideast-early-music-workshop-a-life-changing-experience/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Jul 2012 22:43:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/07/21/mideast-early-music-workshop-a-life-changing-experience/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The whole past week (July 15-21, 2012), I attended my first ever music camp, the annual &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mideastearlymusic.addr.com/&#34;&gt;Mideast early music workshop&lt;/a&gt; held at LaRoche College. It totally changed my life!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A big report, with photos and videos:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-i-decided-to-attend&#34;&gt;Why I decided to attend&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have loved music all my life, but never had any private instruction, or any intensive group instruction either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;old&#34;&gt;Old?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After passing age 40, I started thinking about mortality, and making a list of what my biggest regrets in life would be if I died soon. On the &lt;em&gt;very top&lt;/em&gt; of the list was my lifelong regret that I never had the courage to get serious about music. I had made excuse after excuse to downplay following my musical dreams (in part a legacy of my internalizing my parents&amp;rsquo; constant discouragement of music as a &amp;ldquo;waste of time&amp;rdquo;, but also because I was &lt;em&gt;not willing to make the required sacrifices as a very busy adult&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So before I turned 41, I decided to finally start the process of getting serious about music, and in February 2011 (less than one and a half years ago), I started to learn to play &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/recorder/&#34;&gt;recorder&lt;/a&gt; because it was easy to get started on, was new to me (without the baggage of my difficult experiences with flute and piano) and most of all, because of the existence of the Pittsburgh Recorder Society as a friendly place to finally play with other people. I mentioned this in &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/22/byron-janis-on-overcoming-adversity/&#34;&gt;one of my first posts on this blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;first-hearing-of-the-workshop&#34;&gt;First hearing of the workshop&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In March 2011, I went to the meeting of the Pittsburgh Recorder Society &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/26/i-dont-feel-like-practicing-but-im-gonna-do-it-anyway/&#34;&gt;for the first time&lt;/a&gt;. At the April 2011 meeting, Helen passed out flyers for the Mideast workshop. I was interested in it and asked her and others about it, but as a total beginner felt that it was not worth attending until I got much better first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After another year, I did in fact improve significantly on recorder (and musically in general), and therefore &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/31/my-first-sampling-of-english-country-dance-and-contra-dance/&#34;&gt;decided this past March&lt;/a&gt; to attend the workshop. I pegged myself as finally having reached a beginner/intermediate level suitable for benefiting from the workshop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;gary-marcus&#34;&gt;Gary Marcus&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also turns out that just this February, I picked up Gary Marcus&amp;rsquo;s book &lt;a href=&#34;http://garymarcus.com/books/guitarzero.html&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Guitar Zero&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; and read it. It is about his experience finally immersing himself in music at the age of 40. This book helped me decide to attend the workshop this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;instruments&#34;&gt;Instruments&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that you have to choose a primary instrument (from among recorder, viol, and (Baroque) flute), but can also study secondary instruments. I decided that because of my strong interest in flute (both Baroque flute and modern flute), I would choose &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/baroque-flute/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Baroque flute&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; as my primary instrument.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Possible secondary instruments are recorder, viol, harp, voice, and capped reeds (for Renaissance band): I chose &lt;em&gt;recorder&lt;/em&gt; (of course), &lt;strong&gt;but also&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;voice&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was deathly scared of getting into singing, but felt that this was my chance to finally jump into it!! I have &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; sung with anyone before (in elementary and middle school, I basically lip-synced when supposed to sing), and have almost never sung in the presence of any other human being (I believe I sang for Abby once). I had a definitely goal of unobtrusively getting my start in singing here, in an informal group setting, and then moving forward from there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;classes&#34;&gt;Classes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The classes I tentatively planned to take were:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Baroque flute technique&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;recorder consort&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;all-workshop ensemble&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;bass recorder ensemble&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;improvisation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;voice class&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;English country dance&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I expected it to be a pretty intense schedule, and it definitely was!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;evening-before-informal-dinner-at-helen-s&#34;&gt;Evening before: informal dinner at Helen&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Helen hosted dinner at her place for both locals and out-of-towners arriving in town for the workshop. About a dozen of us showed up, and Abby came along. Since most of the attendees and instructors already knew each other for years (decades in most cases!), I found it a great way to start getting to know some people. Yes, this is an &amp;ldquo;old people&amp;rdquo; music camp. At age 42, I was by far the baby of the entire group. It seems that a good number of retired people attend the camp. Some of the instructors are younger than me, but it appeared that all the students were going to be older than me. I have to confess that last year, when I was &amp;ldquo;warned&amp;rdquo; that this was an &amp;ldquo;old people&amp;rdquo; camp, I had reservations, but the fact is, music is for any age, and interestingly, since getting involved in music last year, I have been consistently surprised and delighted by how younger-looking or younger-acting musicians tend to be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;day-1-sunday-july-15&#34;&gt;Day 1: Sunday (July 15)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sunday afternoon, I drove up to LaRoche College to check in and pay the registration balance, and got my key to the dorm room where I would be staying for the week. Mike of the Pittsburgh Recorder Society had agreed to share a room with me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dinner in the LaRoche dining hall was varied and tasty, as I expected given the excellent lunch I had enjoyed at LaRoche during &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/06/09/report-on-the-first-pittsburgh-techfest-2012/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh TechFest in June&lt;/a&gt;! I was starving, having become considerably underweight in the past couple of weeks because of being really busy and stressed, and welcomed the opportunity to chow down. I ate not only a whole lot of healthy food, but also couldn&amp;rsquo;t help myself and ate a cupcake, a cookie, and ice cream also!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;introduction-and-all-workshop-ensemble&#34;&gt;Introduction and all-workshop ensemble&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The introduction to the workshop happened after dinner&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marilyn introduced the workshop, along with the instructors. Marilyn has been the organizer of this workshop for something like 45 years, I believe: wow!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/intro.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Instructors on the left&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/intro2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;The rest of the instructors&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Immediately following the introduction was the first meeting of the all-workshop ensemble. We had substantial-looking spiral-bound books of ensemble music and I wondered how much of it we would go through!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/all-workshop-music.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Book and people ready to play&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;english-country-dance&#34;&gt;English country dance&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After that was the first meeting of English country dance. I was sad not to be dancing with Abby (she was not enrolled in the workshop because this isn&amp;rsquo;t her kind of music), but enjoyed learning something new and getting a bit of exercise. Since it started from scratch, it was less intimidating than &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/31/my-first-sampling-of-english-country-dance-and-contra-dance/&#34;&gt;my first experience with English country dance four months ago&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, given that I was the young baby of the bunch, going a bit slowly was helpful to me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/english-country-dance.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;day-2-monday-july-16&#34;&gt;Day 2: Monday (July 16)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed a fine breakfast, including eggs, sausages, and potatoes, and felt myself regaining some much-needed weight. Also, regarding the dorm rooms: they have air-conditioning, much appreciated given the hot and muggy summer!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;baroque-flute-technique&#34;&gt;Baroque flute technique&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I felt very intimidated in Majbritt&amp;rsquo;s morning Baroque flute technique class. There were six of us in the class, and I was clearly the least experienced. My flute playing (whether modern or flute) is at a beginner&amp;rsquo;s level, as I have been playing for only a few months really. In fact, this is &lt;em&gt;exactly&lt;/em&gt; why I chose flute as my &lt;em&gt;primary&lt;/em&gt; instrument in the workshop: to get good instruction in technique before I progressed too far on my won. Even with recorder, I had to unlearn some bad habits early on that I had developed from working on it myself for a month or so before joining the Pittsburgh Recorder Society!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In class we had a &amp;ldquo;review&amp;rdquo; of basic concepts of Baroque flute technique such as the correct &lt;em&gt;embouchure&lt;/em&gt; adjustments to get the intonation right of all the various notes: for example, the F is sharp unless you adjust the embouchure, and the F-sharp is flat unless you adjust the embouchure in the other way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then we talked about &lt;em&gt;articulation&lt;/em&gt;. One new thing I learned here was to be aware of the &lt;em&gt;end&lt;/em&gt; of a note, very important compared with playing modern instruments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I took a lot of notes, as well as made annotations in the music we got.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;voice-class&#34;&gt;Voice class&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eric taught voice class. There was a good balance of men and women. He handed us spiral-bound books of musical selections.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/voice-eric.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Eric Haas&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/voice-men.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Other men in voice class&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We went through a bunch of songs, and I . It was tremendous fun. I had never in my life sight-sung before (!!!), so I was very nervous. I tried not to let on that I was a total novice (unlike everyone else there). I took a lot of notes on what was tricky and marked up the song book for further study.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The somewhat nerve-wracking thing was that no men were really tenors, and a bunch sang bass, so Eric, Chris, and I sang tenor. I&amp;rsquo;m a baritone, not a tenor: the high notes were scary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;lunch&#34;&gt;Lunch&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I totally stuffed myself for lunch. So much good food.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/monday-lunch.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;recorder-consort&#34;&gt;Recorder consort&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Emily was the instructor for my recorder consort class. I was put into a lower-level class because of being relatively new (having played recorder for less than two years). I didn&amp;rsquo;t mind, because I knew that I had much to learn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Emily focused a lot on things like where to breathe, and in paying attention to others in an ensemble. I learned to write in commas for breathing in music scores (in the flute class, Majbritt also emphasized finding the phrasing and the breathing, and this has been a theme at Pittsburgh Recorder Society meetings as well). I realized that I still had a lot to absorb from these lessons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Emily also told us to find the narrative in any music we played. It&amp;rsquo;s not just isolated notes; music has a push and pull.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;bass-ensemble&#34;&gt;Bass ensemble&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;James (whom I amusingly first encountered online through his &lt;a href=&#34;http://jnote.org/&#34;&gt;fantastic multi-track melodica videos&lt;/a&gt; before finding out that he teaches recorder at the Mideast workshop) led the bass ensemble. I still play bass recorder only very infrequently, so I was nervous, but joined the bass ensemble because I thought it would be fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;improvisation&#34;&gt;Improvisation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alan taught improvisation. I had never actually specifically learned improvisation techniques before, but want to eventually get truly serious about improvisation, so I was excited to take this class, which was quite participatory. He would describe a concept, such as the pentatonic scale, and then have us do something with it. The class was enthusiastic. I was actually pretty moved by how individual everyone&amp;rsquo;s inventiveness was, even doing basic things, and that helped me loosen up as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;medieval-fiddle&#34;&gt;Medieval fiddle&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a whim, I checked out the medieval fiddle class. I borrowed a medieval fiddle to take back to my room after class. (But it would turn out that the instrument had problems, and I had too much other stuff to do, and had never played a string instrument before, so I ended up returning it and not returning to the class.)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/medieval-fiddle.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;A medieval fiddle&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;dinner&#34;&gt;Dinner&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby came up to visit and joined me for dinner while on her way to mandolin orchestra rehearsal, which is actually close by.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ate an ice cream cone, but realizing that I was gaining a lot of weight already after 24 hours at LaRoche, I chose not to eat cake or cupcakes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;all-workshop-ensemble&#34;&gt;All-workshop ensemble&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Intense stuff. I took pages and pages of notes as Eric talked about different styles, phrasing, &amp;ldquo;painting&amp;rdquo;, dissonances, imitation, counterpoint, the significance of words in text, changes in meter, etc. We read through a lot of pieces to work on for the week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;english-country-dance-1&#34;&gt;English country dance&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We learned more stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;study&#34;&gt;Study!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, after all the classes into the evening, I got to spend some hours in my dorm room or across the hall in an empty meeting room used for classes in the day (since sometimes Mike was in the dorm room or going to bed earlier than me) doing what review of my notes I could, as well as practicing for each of my classes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was intense: I had been given so much to learn already after a single day! I was right in choosing to live on site rather than take the commuter option, because the commute from Pittsburgh would have been stressful and time-consuming for me, taking away energy and time I could spend on classes and preparation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;day-3-tuesday-july-17&#34;&gt;Day 3: Tuesday (July 17)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;flute&#34;&gt;Flute&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I learned about &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Notes_in%C3%A9gales&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;inégal&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; for the first time. I hadn&amp;rsquo;t know that this &amp;ldquo;swinging&amp;rdquo; of notes (familiar in jazz) also applied to Baroque music!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We continued our study of articulation. I learned a huge amount about &amp;ldquo;t&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;d&amp;rdquo; and runs of notes as well as leaps. It was very difficult for me to execute all this, so I tried to focus on one aspect at a time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;voice&#34;&gt;Voice&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More work, and a lot of fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;recorder-consort-1&#34;&gt;Recorder consort&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reinforcing the technique points we learned yesterday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;bass-class&#34;&gt;Bass class&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It continued being a challenge for me to alternate between reading bass clef for bass recorder and reading treble clef for it as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;improvisation-1&#34;&gt;Improvisation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Musical structure such as ABA, ABACA (rondo).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;nap-time&#34;&gt;Nap time&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cutting out medieval violin meant having a block of nap time, much-needed!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;dinner-1&#34;&gt;Dinner&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I created a pattern of eating ice cream every day at dinner, and continued to gain weight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;all-workshop-ensemble-singing&#34;&gt;All-workshop ensemble: singing?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the pieces we went through could optionally be sung, so Eric asked us to think of whether we wanted to sing or play an instrument for our performance on Friday. I was intrigued by the option to sing. &amp;ldquo;Ecco l&amp;rsquo;Aurora&amp;rdquo; was very interesting to sing, but also rather challenging to me, with its leaps and modulations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But because of the relative lack of tenor volunteers, I decided I would switch from playing tenor recorder and work on singing it on Friday. I was partly inspired by Chris&amp;rsquo;s example, and also by the guy sitting next to me who decided to sing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;english-country-dance-2&#34;&gt;English country dance&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We learned a new dance, but also started focusing on improving on a particular dance for Friday&amp;rsquo;s performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;study-1&#34;&gt;Study&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was practicing in the empty meeting room until at 11 PM, Charles, whose dorm room was actually right next door, told me he was going to sleep. Oops! If I didn&amp;rsquo;t do English country dance, I could practice earlier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;day-4-wednesday-july-18&#34;&gt;Day 4: Wednesday (July 18)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;flute-1&#34;&gt;Flute&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Very detailed articulation instruction. Also, notes on hemiolas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;master-class&#34;&gt;Master class&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was very excited to attend the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Master_class&#34;&gt;master class&lt;/a&gt;. I had never attended a master class before, actually, although I had seen some videos of the concept.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that Karen had prepared a piece for Baroque flute for the master class, and Mike had prepared a piece for recorder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I took a huge number of notes. For each of them, I first took notes while they played their pieces, then I took more notes as the instructors gave feedback. I found it quite useful to compare what they observed with what I had observed independently (or not noticed at all). The whole experience was tremendously instructive for me, giving me a huge amount of information to apply to my own playing. I don&amp;rsquo;t know if I have the courage to expose myself to scrutiny in public like this. I&amp;rsquo;m certainly appreciative of Karen and Mike doing so!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I noticed some observations in common among the instructors and for both Karen and Mike. The gist of the advice:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;add more variety in &lt;em&gt;articulation&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;play with more &lt;em&gt;freedom&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;find and express the &lt;em&gt;shape&lt;/em&gt; and melodic line&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;look for the meaning of leaps and &lt;em&gt;dissonance&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found these insights profoundly useful, and found it inspiring to see Karen and Mike work to make some changes in their playing in response to the instructors&amp;rsquo; feedback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;karen&#34;&gt;Karen&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Karen prepared one of the twelve &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/12_Fantasias_for_Solo_Flute_%28Telemann%29&#34;&gt;Telemann fantasias for solo flute&lt;/a&gt;, no. 2.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/master-class-karen.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Karen&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/master-class-karen-majbritt.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Majbritt feedback for Karen&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h4 id=&#34;mike&#34;&gt;Mike&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By coincidence, Mike played another of the Telemann fantasias for solo flute, no. 10, but he played it on alto recorder instead of flute.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/master-class-mike.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Mike&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There was a funny moment in which Mike used his leg to play a high F-sharp. Later, Emily and James showed him a good technique hint, preparing the F-sharp by bringing up the leg already in anticipation, and then bringing the head down toward the leg instead of vice versa.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/master-class-mike-james-leg.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Mike raising leg, with James and Emily&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;lunch-1&#34;&gt;Lunch&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After lunch, Mike and I helped Chris move his harpsichord. (Chris drove his own harpsichord up from home and it&amp;rsquo;s used for many sessions at the workshop.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;recorder-consort-2&#34;&gt;Recorder consort&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People had been leaving our recorder consort class one by one; Wednesday, we were down to five! I wondered why this was going on. Admittedly, we were moving slowly through the music, because a couple of us were more on the beginner side and had trouble sight reading, staying with the score, keeping fingerings straight. I myself had silently considered switching, but I found the &amp;ldquo;slower&amp;rdquo; pace an opportunity to really focus on trying to work on various basic things that are more important than &amp;ldquo;getting through&amp;rdquo; a lot of musical selections. I really needed to get down what I was learning about breath, resonance, and intonation, as well as ensemble unity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;free-time&#34;&gt;Free time!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wednesday there is scheduled &amp;ldquo;free time&amp;rdquo; during which there are no classes. I was totally exhausted by this point in the week and napped for two and a half hours!! Then I finally went outside for a 40-minute run, in my new Invisible Shoes (which I wore around daily and got a lot of comments on); I had originally intended to get regular exercise in every day while at camp, but had simply felt overwhelmed by the desire to make the most of my music classes and practice (at least I did do an hour of English country dance every evening).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;white-elephant-sale&#34;&gt;White Elephant Sale&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After dinner, I browsed around at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/White_Elephant_Sale&#34;&gt;White Elephant Sale&lt;/a&gt;. I kicked myself for having totally forgotten to bring some stuff to donate to it. I was amused that Helen managed to get rid of a particular item that she had wanted out of her home for some time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;chris-and-harpsichord&#34;&gt;Chris and harpsichord&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had been so busy that I had not bothered to think about signing up for playing with Chris on harpsichord. Unfortunately, by the time I checked the signup sheet, I saw that it was full (empty slots conflicted with my class time).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/harpsichord-signup.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Chris harpsichord signup sheet&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There were signup sheets all along for other stuff too, such as people wanting to find others to play with. That is actually a large part of the appeal of the workshop. I didn&amp;rsquo;t participate in any of that because as a newcomer, I was focused on exploring classes. But obviously, those who had come to the workshop for years and decades did not necessarily need or want to spend all their time on classes.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/other-signup.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Other signup sheets&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;faculty-concert&#34;&gt;Faculty concert&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another highlight of Wednesday was the faculty concert. This was great. Bagpipes, recorders, Renaissance flutes, Baroque flutes, harpsichord, viola da gamba, even sackbut! It was a real treat to see all our instructors performing.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/bagpipes.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Alan on bagpipes&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/faculty-concert-2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Group&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/faculty-concert-3.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Group&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/faculty-concert-james-majbritt.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;James and Majbritt in duet&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I was intrigued by Emily playing Debussy&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Syrinx&amp;rdquo; on a special tenor recorder.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/emily-syrinx.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Emily playing Syrinx on special tenor recorder&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/chris-harpsichord.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Chris solo on harpsichord&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/faculty-concert-flutes.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Eric, Emily, Majbritt on flutes&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/judith-viol.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Judith on viol&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A short video clip from the faculty concert (I found out that my phone made an unstoppable annoying click when taking video, so I never used my phone again for video after this; other videos I post here came from the camera Abby brought on Friday):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/vpXVEf7NfSw&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;practice&#34;&gt;Practice&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally I got time to practice. There was a lot of stuff to prepare for the Friday concert.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;day-5-thursday-july-19&#34;&gt;Day 5: Thursday (July 19)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;breakfast&#34;&gt;Breakfast&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of the considerable weight gain (approximately &lt;em&gt;four pounds&lt;/em&gt; so far since arrival), I decided to stop eating potatoes (which seemed to be available in some form at every meal).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;flute-2&#34;&gt;Flute&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More technique. Lip and tongue placement, different scales. We finally decided on what to play for the concert, a selection by Dittersdorf. I was one of those on the easiest part, the third part of the trio, playing &amp;ldquo;bass&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;voice-1&#34;&gt;Voice&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We worked through a bunch more selections while continuing to refine the one we had decided to perform on Friday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, it came in really handy this week that I have at least basic competence in French, Italian, Latin, and German, because we sang in all these languages!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;bass&#34;&gt;Bass&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got to class early enough (a rarity, since usually I was rushing from voice class) to take a photo.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/bass-setup.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Mike and James&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;By the way, since I had hardly played bass before coming to this workshop, I hadn&amp;rsquo;t realized that my bass tended to be sharp and I learned I had to keep the head joint pulled out to a certain degree. Useful to finally find that out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;improvisation-2&#34;&gt;Improvisation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We did blues stuff, and Alan pulled out his guitar to give us chords as the rest of us took turns on recorder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;special-mini-class-on-practice-techniques&#34;&gt;Special mini-class on practice techniques&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I attended a one-session class on practice techniques by Emily. I found this tremendously useful and took a lot of notes. Some of the key ideas:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;don&amp;rsquo;t practice a mistake&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;importance of warmup with focus (physical but also mental)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;go slow, do it right&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;break down difficult tasks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it all starts with the mind: first decide and know what you want to accomplish, then figure out the physical means&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;repetition and grouping into units&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;isolation of aspects of technique&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;classify goals as long, medium, and short term&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;all-workshop-ensemble-1&#34;&gt;All-workshop ensemble&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had a shorter session, in order to make more time for the following ad hoc student concert.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eric had singers lined up in front so that we would run through &amp;ldquo;Ecco l&amp;rsquo;Aurora&amp;rdquo; as it was going to be presented on Friday: I stood with Chris for tenor and found it tremendously helpful to have him at my side so that when I was uncertain or got lost, I had someone to anchor back to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instrumentalists were reminded to play as though singing, articulating consistently with the words of the text.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;ad-hoc-student-concert&#34;&gt;Ad hoc student concert&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of participants in the workshop look forward to this as one of their highlights of the experience. I did not sign up to perform for this because I was focused entirely on classes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each selection was short, and there were a whole lot of individuals and groups that came up to present something. Some people had prepared something before the workshop. Others had met up and were playing for the first time together. It was a fun time.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/ad-hoc-audience.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Ad hoc student concert audience&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;practice-1&#34;&gt;Practice&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally at 10 PM I started music practice!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;day-6-friday-july-20-final-day&#34;&gt;Day 6: Friday (July 20), final day&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;flute-3&#34;&gt;Flute&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We reviewed what we were playing for the concert, but also moved on to work some more on music we were not performing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;voice-2&#34;&gt;Voice&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We went over the two pieces we were to perform at the concert, then closed the class with work on some more pieces in the book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;recorder-consort-3&#34;&gt;Recorder consort&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Final review.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;bass-1&#34;&gt;Bass&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We did a lot of intonation adjustment, since many of us were sharp!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;James had particular ideas about performance presentation, and told us to hold up our instruments after we were done playing, watch out for extraneous sucking, and refrain from bringing too much junk (extra clothing, shoe boxes, etc.) with us. Also, we were to bring only the two pages of music we were to play, not binders of all our music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;improvisation-3&#34;&gt;Improvisation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Final class. We did not plan to perform as a group in the concert.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;dinner-2&#34;&gt;Dinner&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby had come up for dinner on Monday. I hadn&amp;rsquo;t seen her since then, and she came up to see the final concert. I was happy she was able to make it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;final-concert&#34;&gt;Final concert&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final student concert showcased what everyone had worked on so hard for the week. Because I took so many classes, I was in several groups that performed. Here are just a sample of photos and videos from the concert. I apologize for not having full coverage, but as I was occupied with performing, after my first performance, I completely stopped messing around with my phone and just focused on enjoying others&amp;rsquo; performances and getting ready to switch in when one of my groups was up! Abby did take some photos and videos, but only when I was involved!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/harps.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/recorder-eric.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/recorder-eric-2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h4 id=&#34;me-in-flute&#34;&gt;Me in flute&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby took this photo of me in Majbritt&amp;rsquo;s flute group:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/flute-majbritt.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h4 id=&#34;me-in-voice-ensemble&#34;&gt;Me in voice ensemble&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eric tuning for the voice ensemble (I&amp;rsquo;m standing next to Chris as usual):&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/voice-tuning.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Clips from our two selections:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/SfptMbkdwsw&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/nF-5ph82sJ4&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Immediately after the voice ensemble performance, Abby commented to me that during performance, I ended up &amp;ldquo;hiding&amp;rdquo; with my score in my hands rising up and up, partially covering my face. Admittedly, I was very nervous, but also, I was trying to cover up my inability to keep a straight face while barking on the tenor dog line!! (For the final all-workshop ensemble performance, I made sure not to hide.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;bass-ensemble-1&#34;&gt;Bass ensemble&lt;/h4&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/bass-final.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.mideastearlymusic.addr.com/P1160081.jpeg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/NY8YQfYErfc&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;concluding-all-workshop-ensemble-performance&#34;&gt;Concluding all-workshop ensemble performance&lt;/h4&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/all-workshop-final.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Me and Chris:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mideast-workshop-2012/all-workshop-final-franklin-chris.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.mideastearlymusic.addr.com/P1160084.jpeg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;All-workshop ensemble&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.mideastearlymusic.addr.com/P1160083.jpeg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;All-workshop ensemble&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/CBGZlAWB7BI&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;party&#34;&gt;Party&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a party afterwards with unique tasty treats that Abby and I attended, and she got to meet more of my instructors and classmates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People started to pack up and prepare to leave. It was a long week, but what a fun one!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was, of course, asked whether I planned to come back next year. I said I would like to, but could not yet commit to that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;more-photos&#34;&gt;More photos&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More photos of the whole workshop week can be found &lt;a href=&#34;http://mideastearlymusic.addr.com/newpglogo.htm&#34;&gt;here at the workshop site&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;saturday-at-home-thoughts&#34;&gt;Saturday at home: thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I weighed myself the next day. I&amp;rsquo;d gained a total of &lt;em&gt;seven pounds&lt;/em&gt; in five days. On the one hand, I had gone in underweight, so it was good I finally made up for that, but now I was a bit overweight, as Abby noticed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reflecting on the week, I resolved to put into practice everything I had learned at the workshop. It was going to take time to develop new habits, make use of new awareness, but I now knew of the path forward. Before attending the workshop, I had gotten advice here and there that was useful, and I had read up on things by myself, but there is nothing like being immersed in an environment of total learning, feedback, and collaboration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Attending this workshop has given me fresh concrete direction and musical goals as well as the determination to push on and not settle for anything less than doing what I can to musically express myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;thanks&#34;&gt;Thanks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am grateful to Marilyn, all the instructors (especially those of my classes: Majbritt, Emily, Eric, James, Alan), my classmates (especially Chris for voice, without whom I would have felt lost), the staff of LaRoche College, and the members of the Pittsburgh Recorder Society who first told me of this workshop and also attended (Helen, Annie, Mike, Sam, Maggie who danced with me). Mike was a considerate dorm roommate for the week. And I am particularly grateful that Abby supported me in my quest to improve my musicianship and enabled me to attend the workshop, and also visited me twice for dinner and to see me in the final student concert.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had an amazing time at the Mideast early music workshop. I am going to continue my study of Baroque flute and recorder, and voice as well, and do more with improvisation. Now that I have seen and worked with more really good musicians up front (both instructors and students at the workshop: I noticed that quite a few of the students themselves are actually professional musicians on non-early instruments), I have a much clearer idea of how I want to sound and what kind of technique I need to develop in order to make that into reality. Mostly, I feel that some kind of psychological block has been removed and that I now have real courage where I still didn&amp;rsquo;t have it before attending the workshop: courage to experiment, to fail, to continue.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My first time in a public music jam: intense fun with Chris Norman and David Greenberg</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/04/21/my-first-time-in-a-public-music-jam-intense-fun-with-chris-norman-and-david-greenberg/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Apr 2012 13:44:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/04/21/my-first-time-in-a-public-music-jam-intense-fun-with-chris-norman-and-david-greenberg/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://fbcdn-sphotos-a.akamaihd.net/hphotos-ak-ash3/544714_10150682065771513_55075526512_9775036_876594193_n.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;David Greenberg and Chris Norman and the rest of us&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Friday evening, Abby and I packed up various musical instruments of ours, and attended an event that I had been eagerly awaiting for over three weeks since I first found out about it from Annie of the local &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.andrew.cmu.edu/user/lukas/pcars/Welcome.html&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh recorder gang&lt;/a&gt;: a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rbsp.org/Jam%20Session%20Flyer.pdf&#34;&gt;jam session open to the public&lt;/a&gt; being offered by &lt;a href=&#34;http://chrisnorman.com/&#34;&gt;Chris Norman&lt;/a&gt;, flutist, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.davidgreenberg.ca/&#34;&gt;David Greenberg&lt;/a&gt;, violinist the day before &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rbsp.org/11-12c6.aspx&#34;&gt;their concert&lt;/a&gt; the next evening to close the current season of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rbsp.org/&#34;&gt;Renaissance and Baroque of Pittsburgh&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was so excited by this opportunity to jam with such esteemed musicians. Norman and Greenberg specialize in playing Irish, Scottish, Cape Breton and Baroque music. I&amp;rsquo;ve come to love playing the rhythmic, danceable music of the old days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I learned a lot from the experience, and would like to share what I learned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;some-photos-of-the-event&#34;&gt;Some photos of the event&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/pages/Pittsburgh-Renaissance-and-Baroque/55075526512&#34;&gt;Facebook page of the Pittsburgh Renaissance and Baroque&lt;/a&gt; has a bunch of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/media/set/?set=a.10150682065546513.394216.55075526512&amp;amp;type=3&#34;&gt;photos of the event&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;ve used a couple of these here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;preparation&#34;&gt;Preparation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;my-instruments&#34;&gt;My instruments&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been spending most of my daily music practice all year working on the modern &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/flute/&#34;&gt;flute&lt;/a&gt;; I have not reported on my progress in over a month because I&amp;rsquo;ve been too busy &lt;em&gt;doing&lt;/em&gt; rather than &lt;em&gt;writing&lt;/em&gt;, but will catch up with the writing sometime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But for this jam session, I had decided very quickly that I was &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; going to be bringing my modern flute to play, because I do prefer to play older music on other instruments; I planned to bring the following instruments instead:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;my &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/tin-whistle/&#34;&gt;tin whistle&lt;/a&gt;, which I bought the week of St. Patrick&amp;rsquo;s Day in March (for a party I haven&amp;rsquo;t written about yet but which radically changed my life)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;an assortment of &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/recorder/&#34;&gt;recorders&lt;/a&gt;: I decided to just bring my soprano and alto&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;my &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/baroque-flute/&#34;&gt;Baroque flute&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, interspersed with my continuing work on the modern flute, I have also done some maintenance practice of tin whistle and recorders. The most difficult challenge was trying to get serious about Baroque flute: the one-keyed flute is &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.oldflutes.com/charts/onekey/index.htm&#34;&gt;very, very, very tricky to play in tune&lt;/a&gt;. Sometimes I wonder whether it&amp;rsquo;s worth the bother. But I tend to be inspired by quirky challenges whose benefit I don&amp;rsquo;t fully understand immediately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ideally, I would own an &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.caseyburnsflutes.com/cat_d.php&#34;&gt;Irish flute&lt;/a&gt;, preferably with a number of keys to aid with intonation and fingering, but given that I don&amp;rsquo;t currently intend to specialize in Irish music, and am still working with the tin whistle anyway, I cannot at all justify buying an Irish flute at this time. So I&amp;rsquo;ve been working on using the related Baroque flute instead, for traditional Irish or Scottish music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;abby-s-instruments&#34;&gt;Abby&amp;rsquo;s instruments&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby started learning mandolin just this year, joining the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pittsburghmandolinsociety.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Mandolin Orchestra&lt;/a&gt;, so I was excited that she decided early on to bring it to the jam session. (And I look forward to seeing her play for the first time in the orchestra&amp;rsquo;s concert on Mother&amp;rsquo;s Day coming up in three weeks!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She also brought a frame drum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-event&#34;&gt;The event!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;arrival&#34;&gt;Arrival&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I arrived a little late, so I scrambled to get ready while a whole bunch of people were already gathered. Many people were sitting in back just to watch and listen, while maybe twenty of us were armed with instruments of all kinds, ready to have some fun!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://fbcdn-sphotos-a.akamaihd.net/hphotos-ak-prn1/541085_10150682067126513_55075526512_9775042_292845062_n.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;We played lots of different instruments&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We ran into half a dozen people we knew from various of our musical circles, including Annie from recorder, a guy Abby knew from mandolin, and some fellow &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/16/playing-recorder-and-flute-at-the-holiday-ball/&#34;&gt;Holiday Ball&lt;/a&gt; musicians.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was intrigued by the couple of people who had actual keyed Irish flutes and eager to hear them play (it would turn out, of course, that they were very, very good).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;music-scores&#34;&gt;Music scores&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So each of us got a packet of around twenty pages of music. We didn&amp;rsquo;t play all of it, of course, but it was a good basis for sight reading along with Chris and David leading the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much of the music went at breakneck pace that I&amp;rsquo;m still not proficient enough to sight reading perfectly, but my (yet unreported) musical adventures in the past month have made me far less self-conscious about perfection and figure out ways to cope:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it&amp;rsquo;s not necessary to play all the notes; in fast music, you can contribute just fine playing only one main note per measure or harmony change&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;you can also substitute a different, easier melodic line that is compatible with the chords&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;since sections are repeated many times, you can add more during repetitions as you feel ready to&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it&amp;rsquo;s not the end of the world to miscalculate sometimes and squeak out a harsh dissonant error; the music just keeps going, so don&amp;rsquo;t look back, only forward&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;learning-by-ear-improvisation&#34;&gt;Learning by ear, improvisation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I expected, much of the time we didn&amp;rsquo;t play music from the handed out scores at all. This was the fun I was anticipating all along (I had not really expected music scores at all, actually).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost half the time, Chris would ask us for music suggestions to offer up &lt;em&gt;by example&lt;/em&gt;, so that the volunteer would play (or sing) the melody, then the rest of us would start &amp;ldquo;learning&amp;rdquo; it by ear and join in and continue with repetitions. I had not anticipated the call for volunteers, else I would have come prepared with some favorite tunes to offer!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some people were more familiar with various tunes being offered up than I was, since they had a lot more experience with Irish, Scottish and other such music than me, so I felt awkward and lost trying to learn and play on the spot, without written music, but it was part of the whole fun, really stretching what I have usually been doing with music (very oriented toward following a written score).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve mentioned before my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/10/flute-loving-it-again/&#34;&gt;poor memory&lt;/a&gt; having a considerable impact on my life, and I worked around it again, given that I could not quickly learn the details of a melody, by just giving up and improvising around the harmony changes instead. I would like to find ways to improve my memory, but for now, I work around my limitations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;a-charming-tangent-involving-an-oboe&#34;&gt;A charming tangent involving an oboe&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it turned out that a young woman among us had come with a Baroque oboe tuned to A415 instead of the modern A440 tuning. This caused confusion, of course, when she tried to play from written scores. I&amp;rsquo;m not sure what she ended up doing: the only choices were to mentally transpose from the written scores (when we were playing music from them) or just ignore the scores and learn by ear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, Chris and David repeatedly wanted to play with her and asked her what music she had on her, and she had a variety of Baroque music scores with her (she said she was actually giving a recital the next day), and so they tried to play some stuff just with her while doing their own mental transposition so that she would get to play without mental transposition! Check out Chris hovering over the score trying to do the really hard work of transposing on the fly:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://fbcdn-sphotos-a.akamaihd.net/hphotos-ak-ash4/s720x720/295215_10150682067841513_395463764_n.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Baroque oboist with Chris and David&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;dancing&#34;&gt;Dancing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Periodically, a number of people got up to dance in the space at the side, especially when we played waltzes. It was nice to see people moving.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://fbcdn-sphotos-a.akamaihd.net/hphotos-ak-ash3/529154_10150682066471513_55075526512_9775039_758574985_n.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;A couple dancing&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;i-m-caught-on-a-photo-playing-baroque-flute&#34;&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m caught on a photo playing Baroque flute&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spent a fair amount of time playing the tin whistle, and some time on my recorders, but in the end gravitated toward the Baroque flute because it was mellower and I could draw less attention to my mistakes by playing it instead!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that a photo was taken that included me when I was playing my Baroque flute. In this photo, you can also see a guy playing tin whistle (this guy also at one point volunteered to sing a tune, and did so with quite a powerful voice, a great rendition).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://fbcdn-sphotos-a.akamaihd.net/hphotos-ak-ash2/35507_10150682067581513_55075526512_9775044_1738151368_n.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;A fellow tin whistle player, and me on Baroque flute&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My posture is really bad here. I need to sit up straight and keep my head over my body rather than straining over my neck. My only excuse is that this photo was probably taken two hours into the jam session when it was almost over, and I was having energy issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-note-on-energy-requirements&#34;&gt;A note on energy requirements&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was totally exhausted after the jam session. After Abby and I drove back home, we both had to eat something. We were starving. We should have taken a snack break at the jam session.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I weighed myself and I had lost weight. The mental demands on me were considerable, and I had really spent myself. Given that I have lost weight before when taking exams in school, or playing in chess tournaments, or doing similar activities that combine both mental demands and personal anxiety, I should have been better prepared with fuel at the event. I get the impression that I burn more energy by thinking hard than by running.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was my first time ever at a public music jam session, and I quite enjoyed it. I am grateful to Chris Norman and David Greenberg, and the Pittsburgh Renaissance and Baroque, for providing it to the community. I am always very happy for opportunities to play music with Abby, and keep remembering how she got me into this particular early traditional dance music world, through our first musical time together at the Holiday Ball.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got self-feedback about musical shortcomings for me to keep working on in order to enjoy future jam sessions, and I learned that I really need food to keep me fueled for optimal musicality!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Flute: loving it again, remembering why I dance, and how I met my wife!</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/03/10/flute-loving-it-again/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Mar 2012 21:28:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/03/10/flute-loving-it-again/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, after four days of &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/07/flute-taking-a-break-while-clarifying-my-goals&#34;&gt;not even touching my (modern) flute&lt;/a&gt; and having spent the time having fun with my Baroque flute instead, I felt the urge to return to the modern flute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still have not regained the inclination to continue working on the orchestra music I still have to improve a lot on in the coming week, but I rediscovered the joy of simply playing my instrument.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;sound-intonation&#34;&gt;Sound, intonation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The perpetual challenges of getting clean sounds and accurate pitches on the Baroque flute in the past four days have given me an increased appreciation for the modern flute. I picked it up and spent time just trying to make beautiful sounds. Freed from the stress of orchestra practice, I felt much more relaxed on the instrument than I have for a while now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To my surprise (but not really), I have improved considerably on the flute after not playing it for four days. I really needed a break, a consolidation of lessons learned. My production of tones is much improved, and high notes are squeaking less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;music-for-dance&#34;&gt;Music for dance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing I&amp;rsquo;ve truly come to realize is that I particularly enjoy playing rhythmic music suitable for dancing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, every time I attend a dance, and there is live music, I experience a strange internal conflict: I do like to dance, but sometimes, I&amp;rsquo;d rather be on the other side of the dance floor, being the musical performer! The &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; time I&amp;rsquo;ve been on the other side has been at last year&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburghcontra.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Contras and Squares&lt;/a&gt; Holiday Ball.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most recent instance of my wishing I could sometimes stop dancing and just join the musicians has been at the local &lt;a href=&#34;http://coalcountry.org/frenchdance.html&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh French dance workshop and social&lt;/a&gt;, where we&amp;rsquo;ve had live piano, fiddle, and of course, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~gdyke/&#34;&gt;Gregory&lt;/a&gt; on his Irish flute. I wonder whether at some point I might be qualified to play for the event, using either my modern flute or Baroque flute. (By the way, it was held again today, but unfortunately, Abby and I chose not to go because we had too many things to do this weekend.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;remembering-dancing&#34;&gt;Remembering dancing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday I spent time playing along to a score/CD set I&amp;rsquo;ve mentioned before, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/World-Music-Cuba-Flute-play-along/dp/3702465804&#34;&gt;World Music Cuba&lt;/a&gt;. While playing the bolero, cha cha, and mambo pieces in particular, I felt I was returning &amp;ldquo;home&amp;rdquo; in many ways. This was among the first music I heard and saw people dancing to when I was curious and visited the &lt;a href=&#34;http://cmubdc.org/&#34;&gt;CMU Ballroom Dance Club&lt;/a&gt; in 2000, and fell in love with, and learned to dance to. I also played along to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Play-along-Argentina-Flute-World-Music/dp/3702465871&#34;&gt;World Music Argentina&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;some-photos-of-my-ballroom-dance-days&#34;&gt;Some photos of my ballroom dance days&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some photos of me dancing in 2002 with my last dance partner, Amy, before I quit competitive ballroom dancing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here we are at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dcdancesportinferno.com/&#34;&gt;DC DanceSport Inferno&lt;/a&gt; in 2002 doing a hockey stick in international rumba:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/ballroom/dcdi-2002-hockey-stick.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Amy and Franklin at DCDI 2002 in rumba&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And here were are at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://comp.cornelldancesport.org/&#34;&gt;Cornell DanceSport Classic&lt;/a&gt; in 2002 in cha cha, rumba, and tango:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/ballroom/cornell-2002-new-yorker.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Amy and Franklin at Cornell 2002 in cha cha&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/ballroom/cornell-2002-hockey-stick.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Amy and Franklin at Cornell 2002 in rumba&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/ballroom/cornell-2002-tango-promenade.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Amy and Franklin at Cornell 2002 in tango&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;dancing-with-abby&#34;&gt;Dancing with Abby&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But never mind the ballroom dance days. It was through salsa dancing that I met my wife!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;how-i-met-abby&#34;&gt;How I met Abby&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was through dancing that I met Abby in the first place. After quitting dancing in 2003, I never danced again until late 2006, when my friend Jon told me he had recently started salsa dancing (because of a girlfriend who got him into it) and invited me to join him at a free outdoors dance, and I went. Then as I re-entered the Pittsburgh salsa dance scene, I kept running into Abby.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;some-photos-of-us-dancing-salsa&#34;&gt;Some photos of us dancing salsa&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are not many photos of Abby dancing with me, because when I&amp;rsquo;m dancing, I&amp;rsquo;m not holding my camera, but here are some photos a friend took at a big salsa dance weekend at the Palisades in McKeesport in April 2008, a year after we started dating in 2007.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/palisades-2008/abby-franklin.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby and Franklin dancing salsa at Palisades&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/palisades-2008/abby-franklin-hair.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby and Franklin dancing salsa at Palisades, hair flying&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;expression-and-improvisation-in-dance-and-in-music&#34;&gt;Expression and improvisation in dance and in music&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;dance&#34;&gt;Dance&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One reason I gave up ballroom dancing was that I felt there was an overemphasis on &amp;ldquo;syllabus steps&amp;rdquo; (I realize this is an oversimplification of the ballroom dance culture; all very good ballroom dancers go beyond the syllabus mindset). After quitting ballroom dancing, I explored Argentine tango, which is all about improvisation, but I left it because (at the time) it seemed that most of the women in the local scene were very tall, which made dancing awkward for me. I got into salsa because freed from the closed embrace, there was clearly a lot of room for personal improvisation. Ironically, I first got into making stuff up as a result of my imperfect memory: I could never memorize long choreography of step patterns, whether I was doing ballroom dancing or anything else. So I would always make a &amp;ldquo;mistake&amp;rdquo;, then I would make something out of the mistake. I learned that as long as you get back in time with the music, and keep the lead and follow communication strong, there is no such thing really as a mistake. You just keep going, with whatever is happening at the present moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I now have a long-term goal of developing my technique and releasing my inhibitions so that I can improvise musically at will. Yesterday, I played with improvising when playing bolero, cha cha, and tango. It was a lot of fun and profoundly satisfying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;music&#34;&gt;Music&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I actually credit my study of the recorder and the Baroque flute for reawakening me to my dream of free expression and improvisation. Baroque music leaves room for a lot of interpretation of trills and ornamentation and articulation (subject, of course, to &amp;ldquo;good taste&amp;rdquo;). I want to go beyond that, but it has been a great starting point. For some reason, too much exposure to later music (such as Beethoven) had turned me into a score-reader, since such later music has so much already marked up for the performer to simply &lt;em&gt;obey&lt;/em&gt;. The sparse annotations in Renaissance and Baroque music give one much more freedom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am enjoying playing the flute again, now that I know what I really want to do with it. And I would like to merge my dance and music lives, just as Abby has always played the Balkan music she also dances to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2012-03-12&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-03-12)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ended up &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/12/quitting-the-cmu-all-university-orchestra-one-of-the-hardest-decisions-in-my-life/&#34;&gt;quitting the CMU AUO&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2013-01-26&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-01-26)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost a year later, I finally played tangos on flute &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/26/music-i-just-played-for-the-first-time-recorder-sonata-tangos/&#34;&gt;at a party&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2013-03-17&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-03-17)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost exactly a year later, I ended up playing selections from the World Music Cuba book &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/17/finally-doing-some-latin-music-jamming-on-flute/&#34;&gt;at a party&lt;/a&gt;, and improvising freely with two other guys!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Flute: taking a break while clarifying my goals</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/03/07/flute-taking-a-break-while-clarifying-my-goals/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Mar 2012 21:41:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/03/07/flute-taking-a-break-while-clarifying-my-goals/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is my first blog post in over a week. I&amp;rsquo;ve been very busy, and therefore have had to recently &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/02/23/saying-no-in-order-to-say-yes/&#34;&gt;say &amp;ldquo;no&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; to blogging while saying &amp;ldquo;yes&amp;rdquo; to many other activities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another thing I&amp;rsquo;ve said &amp;ldquo;no&amp;rdquo; to in the past three days has been playing the (modern) flute. In my last blog post I was worried about flute &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/02/27/flute-practice-dealing-with-burnout-and-injury&#34;&gt;burnout and injury&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a flute status update.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;injury&#34;&gt;Injury&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I fixed some things in how I was handling my flute so that I would experience less stress on my left hand, so I believe I have for now avoided serious injury, although I am still planning to investigate buying a more suitably shaped flute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;last-sunday-s-orchestra-rehearsal&#34;&gt;Last Sunday&amp;rsquo;s orchestra rehearsal&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I felt rather demoralized after &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.andrew.cmu.edu/user/auo/&#34;&gt;CMU AUO&lt;/a&gt; rehearsal three days ago. I had had a really packed weekend and therefore was quite drained after rehearsal, which lasted from 7:30 PM to 10:00 PM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The orchestra was still struggling to get things in place. We do get better, but very slowly. Our director is visibly impatient, and rightly so. I have wondered whether to describe my own complaints, because I wish no harm and am still committed to doing my best to contribute to the concert on April 15. But I think that what I share here will probably not be very surprising.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;immaturity-and-dishonesty&#34;&gt;Immaturity and dishonesty&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The experience of being in this non-audition orchestra composed primarily of undergraduates reminds me a lot of my negative experiences in band when I was a pre-teen. There is a lot of disruptive chatting during rehearsal that is quite &amp;ldquo;unprofessional&amp;rdquo;; I take music seriously and given the huge investment of two and a half hours on a Sunday evening every week, would like to make the most of the time. I realize that these are not music major students, and therefore many treat this activity as a casual hobby.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was demoralizing when the director had to confront the orchestra and note that every week, after the break halfway in the rehearsal, suddenly there are more empty seats, meaning that people have been leaving, after having checked in (there is a strict attendance policy). Also, I have noticed people regularly not showing up in the first half, and coming in only for the second half. Yes, it is true that sometimes a student may have some other commitment, but still, the absences affect our rehearsal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, the girl who is in charge of attendance sternly said after the rehearsal that she had done some counting and noticed that some instrument sections had more check marks than people she actually saw; in other words, people were signing in for friends who weren&amp;rsquo;t showing up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;lack-of-passion&#34;&gt;Lack of passion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another fundamental problem is the lack of passion many of the orchestra members have for the music. This Bernstein and Gershwin music we&amp;rsquo;re playing is good music: it&amp;rsquo;s very rhythmic, syncopated, and a lot of us are playing it in some kind of sleepy, tentative way. I find this lack of spirit extremely offensive, frankly. Why waste time playing music if you&amp;rsquo;re not going to breathe it and be moved by it? It boggles my mind. My attitude, whether running a 5K race or writing a computer program or cooking or playing music or dancing, is that my time and energy are precious, and if I&amp;rsquo;m going to do it, I want to give it my all, the moment that I&amp;rsquo;m doing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;summary-of-my-orchestra-experience&#34;&gt;Summary of my orchestra experience&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So as far as the atmosphere in the orchestra is concerned, I find it completely at odds with what I&amp;rsquo;m looking for in an ensemble. This is not much of a surprise, but it is disappointing anyway. However, I will continue to get and give all I can to our rehearsals and upcoming performance, for the experience, and then I don&amp;rsquo;t really expect to continue in the orchestra when the fall term arrives. I have many musical goals that I already have lined up for the summer and beyond; more on that in a later post, where I will also discuss why I don&amp;rsquo;t really fit in an orchestra, even if I played much better and everyone had a professional attitude toward rehearsal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;for-now-off-the-modern-flute-to-the-baroque-flute&#34;&gt;For now: off the modern flute to the Baroque flute&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next Sunday there is no orchestra rehearsal because of spring break. So the pressure to keep on trying to improve my play (I still have a lot of work to do, especially in the Gershwin because I have not practiced it much) is lessened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of all the recent negative associations, I decided to take a short break from the modern flute altogether. For fun, I finally started getting serious about the Baroque flute.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://static.musiciansfriend.com/derivates/18/001/590/857/DV016_Jpg_Large_464489.901_black_matte.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Aulos Baroque flute A440&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve begun practicing the Baroque flute, starting with D major work and now adding G major also. The technique is rather different from that for the modern flute. I have to admit it is a frustrating instrument, but it has its own odd charm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I feel like it again (probably by next Monday), I&amp;rsquo;ll return to continuing practicing modern flute, getting prepared for the next orchestra rehearsal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m having some musical rough spots, but I&amp;rsquo;m still very much in love with music and always find some outlet somehow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2012-03-12&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-03-12)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ended up &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/12/quitting-the-cmu-all-university-orchestra-one-of-the-hardest-decisions-in-my-life/&#34;&gt;quitting the CMU AUO&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Flute practice: dealing with burnout and injury</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/02/27/flute-practice-dealing-with-burnout-and-injury/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Feb 2012 11:27:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/02/27/flute-practice-dealing-with-burnout-and-injury/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/left-hand.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin&amp;#39;s left hand&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, I attended yet another &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/02/22/flute-progress-still-hanging-in-there/&#34;&gt;rehearsal&lt;/a&gt; of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.andrew.cmu.edu/user/auo/&#34;&gt;Carnegie Mellon All-University Orchestra&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did this while feeling burned out and injured.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;burnout-and-injury&#34;&gt;Burnout and injury&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past couple of days, I have experienced decreased desire to practice flute, although by changing up my material, I did manage to get some decent sessions in. Still, I could tell that I was beginning to risk burnout.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to mental fatigue, my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/02/14/flute-progress-report-day-of-reckoning-approaches/&#34;&gt;left forefinger soreness&lt;/a&gt; got worse in the past couple of days, such that yesterday, I didn&amp;rsquo;t practice before rehearsal. I started experiencing &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jennifercluff.com/lineup.htm#indentation&#34;&gt;tingling and numbness&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://theskooloflife.com/wordpress/sometimes-its-best-to-call-it-a-day/&#34;&gt;Sometimes it&amp;rsquo;s best to call it a day.&lt;/a&gt; So I decided yesterday that today, I would take a day completely off from practicing my flute, the first break I have given myself since January 19.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;injury&#34;&gt;Injury&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clearly I need a real strategy to take care of the side of my left finger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is pretty easy to get injured playing music. There are many unnatural positions and movements to work with to make as relaxed as possible. My favorite book for musicians, &lt;a href=&#34;http://musiciansway.com/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Musician&amp;rsquo;s Way&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; has two entire chapters on injury prevention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next time I pick up my flute, I will focus on what I might be doing that causes particular stress on my left finger, and try to adjust. Earlier in my practice, I had problems with my right pinkie finger and solved them, so I have hope of treating my left finger better also. I have read about balance points, using the chin, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-instrument&#34;&gt;My instrument&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One problem that I definitely have is that the instrument I have is not optimal for me, and I know it. My main fundamental problem (and this has been a problem for me with piano, guitar, ukulele) is that I have a small hand and short fingers. There are solutions to this problem for the flute. One very common option that would immediately solve some of my problems is the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flutesonline.com/in_offg.htm&#34;&gt;offset G&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.flutesonline.com/shopping/in_offg.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Offset G flute&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve always thought that I would like to get an offset G flute when I &amp;ldquo;upgrade&amp;rdquo; from my intermediate student flute. &lt;strong&gt;Now I&amp;rsquo;m thinking I should do this sooner rather than later.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;no-excuse&#34;&gt;No excuse&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another book on music practice that I enjoy, Madeline Bruser&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://artofpracticing.com/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Art of Practicing&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, has an anecdote (page 107) about a flutist, Janet Weiss, who found that the traditional flute did not fit her hand, and became a pioneer in redesigning it. Weiss was quoted as saying, &amp;ldquo;The instrument we&amp;rsquo;re playing is incorrect for many people&amp;hellip; it&amp;rsquo;s like trying to dance in a pair of shoes that don&amp;rsquo;t fit.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed! If we love music enough, we should take the initiative to make sure that we are not hampered by our instruments. Just as, I love running and hiking, and struggled with bad footwear for years, decades, until I solved most of my problems, by moving toward &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/fivefingers/&#34;&gt;Vibram FiveFingers&lt;/a&gt; shoes that do not cramp my very wide feet and do not introduce cushioning that causes me to mess up my knees and shins and ankles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have to do what we have to do. We can&amp;rsquo;t just complain that other people are lucky and mass-produced clothing and tools work for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-orchestra-rehearsal-last-night&#34;&gt;The orchestra rehearsal last night&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was still struggling at rehearsal last night. I still cannot play all of the music at full speed. If it were entirely up to me, I would improve at my own pace, rather than feel forced to tackle material that is currently more beyond me than I&amp;rsquo;d like. But in real life, we often have to cut corners. The question is, which corners?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One option is to just bumble through everything in an equally mediocre way. I don&amp;rsquo;t see how that would help the orchestra&amp;rsquo;s concert performance or my own long-term development. So I have chosen to refine what is easiest, and get that working fully, while &amp;ldquo;giving up&amp;rdquo;, at least temporarily, on what is most out of reach. I&amp;rsquo;ve been closing the gap, and believe that I can close it within another three weeks. That would mean I will feel fully ready probably two weeks before the actual concert.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone else is also still improving. We don&amp;rsquo;t sound very good right now, even at slowish speeds. But we are sounding better every week! That&amp;rsquo;s what matters. It&amp;rsquo;s exciting to feel us coming together more and more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m dealing with a temporary setback in motivation and physical condition right now, but hope to bounce back tomorrow. &lt;strong&gt;The show must go on.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2012-03-12&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-03-12)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ended up &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/12/quitting-the-cmu-all-university-orchestra-one-of-the-hardest-decisions-in-my-life/&#34;&gt;quitting the CMU AUO&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Flute progress after one month in orchestra: still hanging in there</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/02/22/flute-progress-still-hanging-in-there/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Feb 2012 20:19:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/02/22/flute-progress-still-hanging-in-there/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It was exactly one month ago, January 22, when &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/02/01/joining-an-orchestra-learning-in-the-face-of-terror/&#34;&gt;I joined&lt;/a&gt; the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.andrew.cmu.edu/user/auo/&#34;&gt;Carnegie Mellon All-University Orchestra&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another week has gone by, and what I thought might be a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/02/14/flute-progress-report-day-of-reckoning-approaches/&#34;&gt;day of reckoning&lt;/a&gt; has come and gone, and I am still playing the flute in the CMU AUO and have not dropped out!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a sample of the hardest music from Bernstein&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Symphonic Dances from West Side Story&amp;rdquo; that I&amp;rsquo;m still struggling to play correctly, cleanly, and in tempo:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/flute-music/west-side-story-fugue.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;West Side Story: Fugue&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/flute-music/west-side-story-rumble.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;West Side Story: Rumble&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It is not very visible from my photos, but I have a huge number of pencil markings on my copy of the score.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story as of now:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;practice-in-the-past-week&#34;&gt;Practice in the past week&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;getting-down-the-basics&#34;&gt;Getting down the basics&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last Wednesday, I continued with focusing purely on improving technique with the Rubank method book. I did not even look at the Gershwin or Bernstein music for orchestra. I simply recognize that I have to focus on making fundamental progress in technique and trust that this will enable me to actually play the hard music at hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have not written much about this strategy, but I feel that it is effective and that many &lt;em&gt;amateurs&lt;/em&gt; do not practice or pursue their various life activities with this discipline, and therefore fall short of reaching their potential. And then typically, we amateurs make excuses, blaming lack of talent or lack of time for our slow progress or quick plateau at a mediocre level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is something in the general culture that encourages immediate gratification at the expense of true &lt;em&gt;craft&lt;/em&gt;. Yes, it is true that we cannot give our all toward our hobbies, the way we might for what we consider our jobs, but at the same time, if you add up the number of hours we spend at our hobbies, they actually do add up, and we might as well have made them count efficiently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me to attack the hard passages of music prematurely without building up technique would be analogous to the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;never running before but aiming to run a marathon in four months, and jumping straight into trying to run 15 miles&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;being a non-programmer and wanting to create a cool Web site in a month, but trying to read a book like &amp;ldquo;Learn Web Programming in 7 Days&amp;rdquo; and not really mastering concepts such as variables and functions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;never having cooked but deciding to make a really fancy and subtle French dish without mastering the basics of knife usage or the properties of butter&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People like shortcuts. But they usually do not succeed, and even if they do, don&amp;rsquo;t provide a sustainable path of growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My real goal isn&amp;rsquo;t just to survive playing in an orchestra concert. That&amp;rsquo;s actually just an incentive for my real goal, which is to improve my overall technique, so that I can continue to play music in any genre, any ensemble, as I wish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;an-off-day&#34;&gt;An off day&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, the next day, Thursday, I was feeling tired and unmotivated for practice. This happens sometimes. In fact, typically it happens once a week. I&amp;rsquo;m human. I can&amp;rsquo;t magically improve a huge amount every single day. Sometimes I&amp;rsquo;m tired. Sometimes I backslide, and notes come out jumbled, slow, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This, too, is a part of life. I&amp;rsquo;ve found the hard way that it&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; best to just push through and waste time and emotional energy. &lt;em&gt;Overtraining&lt;/em&gt; doesn&amp;rsquo;t help. Sometimes it is best to just take a break. I generally prefer to take an &lt;em&gt;active&lt;/em&gt; break.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, on Thursday I decided to put away the technique practice, which was not going well, and instead have fun sight-reading a bunch of music I had gotten out of the library earlier. I played around sight-reading &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Play-Puccini-Arias-Transcribed-Flute/dp/0634046209/&#34;&gt;transcribed opera arias from Puccini&lt;/a&gt; (I secretly love singing them in Italian even though I&amp;rsquo;m not a soprano or female!), &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Debussy-Album-Flute-Piano/dp/9043129712/&#34;&gt;transcriptions from Debussy&amp;rsquo;s piano music&lt;/a&gt; (I want to play the original piano pieces some day), and a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/World-Music-Cuba-Flute-play-along/dp/3702465804&#34;&gt;World Music Cuba&lt;/a&gt; album. It was a lot of fun playing real, lyrical music. I especially liked playing the Cuban music, since I always dreamed about doing that back when I was dancing salsa, rumba, cha cha, and bolero (I also have a goal of seriously singing this genre of music).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: eventually I would like to actually practice some of these music arrangements seriously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;update-of-2012-11-17&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-11-17)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nine months after this blog post, I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/11/17/a-childhood-dream-come-true-i-am-now-finally-singing-for-real/&#34;&gt;sang bolero for the first time in my life, to Abby&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;update-of-2013-03-17&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-03-17)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over a year later, I ended up playing selections from the World Music Cuba book &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/17/finally-doing-some-latin-music-jamming-on-flute/&#34;&gt;at a party&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;continued-practice&#34;&gt;Continued practice&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Friday and Saturday I was back doing technique, and Saturday I finally hit the CMU AUO music again. I noticed that I was playing the high notes on the flute better. Also, of course, I improved my speed and facility at many scales, but I won&amp;rsquo;t bore with listing metronome numbers to indicate my progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;sunday-s-orchestra-rehearsal&#34;&gt;Sunday&amp;rsquo;s orchestra rehearsal&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;sectional-for-woodwinds&#34;&gt;Sectional for woodwinds&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I arrived at 6:30 PM on Sunday for the woodwind sectional, but only one other person was there! People were running late, apparently. I was concerned when only three flutes (plus piccolo) showed up: did we lose another flute? (Later in the full rehearsal, two others joined us.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that in the woodwind sectional, collectively we were still struggling, and therefore I was not as out of place as I had feared I might be. It was a very useful rehearsal, in which many different instruments&amp;rsquo; parts started falling in place. It was at this point that I realized that I was having trouble not only because of my own problems but also because other peoples&amp;rsquo; problems were affecting me. I was having trouble coming in at the right time in many places not only because I was counting badly (although I&amp;rsquo;ve been working steadily at improving my counting) but also because so many other lines were not coming in at the right place either, so I could not rely on listening to others as a way of finding my place. Anyway, we made huge progress in some very difficult music. I actually believe, for the first time, that we might be able to get this stuff working for the concert.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;full-rehearsal&#34;&gt;Full rehearsal&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maria kept on being disappointed in the full rehearsal, asking if we had actually listened to the music, because we were still having so much trouble. (Actually, I have the music and listen to the whole thing at least once every other day.) Perhaps it was a blessing in disguise that so many of us were still unprepared, because it enabled me to not be completely left behind, as we kept the tempos still on the slow side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even so, there were sections in which I simply was unable to keep up. I feel that I really need to master most of them by next rehearsal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;this-week-s-practice&#34;&gt;This week&amp;rsquo;s practice&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My practice this week so far since the rehearsal has been good. I&amp;rsquo;m still focusing on building technique.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Monday, I made significant improvements in my high notes with scales. I worked some with the Bernstein.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Tuesday, I continued Rubank, and went back to some real basics, playing long tones, working on control of dynamics, and relaxation. I did not touch orchestra music at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, I did an abbreviated Rubank practice, then launched into much work on the Bernstein, to make things faster. As I do once or twice a week, I included a &amp;ldquo;test&amp;rdquo; for myself in which I played through all the problematic sections of the piece along with an actual recording. I&amp;rsquo;m doing much, much better now. There is still hope that I might be able to play most of the piece at full speed by Sunday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-look-back-to-three-months-ago&#34;&gt;A look back to three months ago&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is amusing to look back to what I was still having trouble playing, as a flute beginner, three months ago. I was just starting to work through a collection of &amp;ldquo;easy flute classics&amp;rdquo;:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/flute-music/moyse-easy-classics.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Moyse Collection of Easy Flute Classics&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Compare these simple, slow scores with the Bernstein excerpts in the photos at the beginning of this blog post!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;recorder&#34;&gt;Recorder&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Needless to say, I&amp;rsquo;ve completely put away my recorders. I did go to the monthly meeting of the Pittsburgh chapter of the American Recorder Society on Sunday to play, but that is all I will do with recorder until after the April orchestra concert. I would like to get serious about recorder again for late spring and summer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, I felt I was automatically slightly better at playing recorder even without touching it for a month. It&amp;rsquo;s the cross-training effect. Music is music, whichever instrument you&amp;rsquo;re playing: breath control, tone awareness, flexibility of fingers, etc. Even if I did sometimes forget my fingerings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m still enjoying improving at flute and slowly getting closer to being able to play the second flute part of the Bernstein in its entirety. I get less and less panicky about being in the orchestra as I &amp;ldquo;catch up&amp;rdquo; according to plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2012-03-12&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-03-12)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ended up &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/12/quitting-the-cmu-all-university-orchestra-one-of-the-hardest-decisions-in-my-life/&#34;&gt;quitting the CMU AUO&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Flute progress report: day of reckoning approaches</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/02/14/flute-progress-report-day-of-reckoning-approaches/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Feb 2012 20:47:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/02/14/flute-progress-report-day-of-reckoning-approaches/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/02/01/joining-an-orchestra-learning-in-the-face-of-terror/&#34;&gt;Two weeks ago, I wrote&lt;/a&gt; about joining the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.andrew.cmu.edu/user/auo/&#34;&gt;Carnegie Mellon All-University Orchestra&lt;/a&gt;, the first orchestra I have ever been in. I wrote of my terror as I realized that as a total beginner at flute, I was basically unable to play &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; of the music handed out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided to work very hard at improving my flute skills to see whether I could get good enough in time to make it to the April 15 concert in respectable shape. &lt;strong&gt;I believe this is the most ambitious goal I have ever set for myself in my entire life.&lt;/strong&gt; Not because it is the &lt;em&gt;hardest&lt;/em&gt; goal to achieve, but because of the &lt;em&gt;time&lt;/em&gt; pressure involved. If I were given eight months, I would say, yes, I can do it; it took me eight months to start playing the recorder and then be sufficiently skilled (at merely an intermediate level) to play easy music in a concert. But &lt;em&gt;two&lt;/em&gt; months is another story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, the day of reckoning is not April 15. I feel it is next Sunday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-day-of-reckoning&#34;&gt;A day of reckoning&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More precisely, next Sunday is the first day on which I might be in a lot of trouble if I can&amp;rsquo;t reach a certain level. The woodwind section will have a sectional before the main rehearsal to iron out our special problems. All of us flutes will be pretty naked at the sectional. I know where I&amp;rsquo;m still falling short.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;good-news&#34;&gt;Good news&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The good news is that I have made &lt;em&gt;huge&lt;/em&gt; progress in the past two weeks. Whereas two weeks ago I classified myself as a &amp;ldquo;beginner&amp;rdquo;, now I would classify myself as an &amp;ldquo;advanced beginner&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There have been exciting days during which I made a lot of progress and bad days during which I felt that I made little progress or backslid, but I kept the faith and kept going. I&amp;rsquo;ve put aside various other personal projects in order to work as much on flute as possible: some days I have practiced two hours instead of one, and sometimes even three or four hours (on weekends). My left forefinger is permanently sore!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also good news is that we were down to four flutes and one piccolo as of two weeks ago, but this week were have not lost more flutes! I expect the rest of us are in it for the long haul: two of us on first flute, two of us on second flute, and one of us on piccolo. I&amp;rsquo;m not sure if I should, but I would feel very uncertain if I were the only second flute remaining now. It&amp;rsquo;s nice to know someone else may be sharing my pain, and maybe we can help each other in the sectionals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;practice-details&#34;&gt;Practice details&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bulk of my practice has been continuing to get down basic technique by working through the Rubank intermediate method. I keep on filling in gaps, adding new exercises while continuing to improve on exercises I have begun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;high-notes&#34;&gt;High notes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the music that we are playing for the concert, it has been of very high priority that I manage to play the very high notes (of the third register) effectively. This has been quite, quite difficult. It takes time to learn to form the embouchure and use it; what has been helpful has been looking at Web resources and reminding myself to &lt;em&gt;relax&lt;/em&gt;. Undirected powering through, like powering through in any other activity, from running to rowing to programming, doesn&amp;rsquo;t work. I still have difficulty producing the kinds of notes in the third register I would like (our director Maria has repeatedly told us flutes collectively to work on our intonation, and you bet that in Sunday&amp;rsquo;s sectional I will be doing what I can to get it where it needs to be), but at least I now know the fingerings for A-flat, A, B-flat, and B, and am still hard at work practicing scales and arpeggios way up there. It is only this week, actually, that I managed to be able to get B-flat and B out of my instrument at all. A-flat remains weird, but A is clean. Also, F, F-sharp, and G were shaky for me at last report, but I&amp;rsquo;m more or less getting them now. E does not speak so well, unfortunately; I think this is partially an inherent flute matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;dynamics&#34;&gt;Dynamics&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maria also repeatedly reminded the whole orchestra that we were not very good with dynamics, and generally played at some kind of nondescript mezzo-forte. We need to be able to play pianissimo and crescendo to fortissimo, etc., for expression and effect as indicated in the score.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve improved on dynamics, but it is still very hard for me to play high notes softly, for example. I know the theory, but making my mouth and breath do this is taking time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;rhythm&#34;&gt;Rhythm&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maria works with the entire group large on rhythm. The music we have to play is jazzy and swings and has all kinds of syncopations, accents that have to be felt and interpreted. It is indeed more effective to listen and copy these rhythms rather than try to play the notations in the score. She tells us not to play so square, ha!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Needless to say, I still have anxiety about coming in at the wrong times, and blasting a note where there is supposed to be a rest. So you bet I am working on getting the tricky rhythms down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;speed&#34;&gt;Speed&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maria has been ramping up the speeds in the rehearsals. Unfortunately, last Sunday an important section of the Bernstein was run through at a speed exceeding what I could handle at the time. So I have been working on that. I feel I am always playing catch-up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For development of speed, there is no substitute for just plain foundational technique work with the metronome. The metronome does not lie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;progress-on-old-exercises&#34;&gt;Progress on old exercises&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some examples of progress:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last week I gave a record of speed progress on an exercise:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 24: 100&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 25: 106&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 26: 109&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 27: 130&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 28: 131&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 29: 133&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 31: 141&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Add to that the following improvements, which get me to roughly where I feel I need to be:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 2: 143&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 6: 145&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 7: 146&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 8: 147&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 11: 148&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 14: 149&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the Pareto rule, I will not seek further improvement on this exercise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 25: 95&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 26: 96&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 27: 102&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 28: 106&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 29: 107&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 1: 115&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve improved on this one to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 2: 118&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 3: 119&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 6: 120&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 7: 122&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 8: 123&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 10: 124&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve topped out there too for now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s an interesting exercise from last time that I had found rather difficult:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 25: 100&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 26: 102&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 27: 105&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 29: 106&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 30: 107&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 31: 108&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have made radical improvements as a result of noticing the need for relaxation and for adjusting my holding of the instrument and the alignment of my right wrist (and many other things I still keep on refining):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 2: 110&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 3: 114&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 6: 120&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 7: 136&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 8: 138&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 11: 139&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 14: 140&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will stop trying to improve on this also.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a difficult arpeggio study at which I have made a big leap:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 27: 70&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 31: 71&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 1: 72&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 2: 73&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 3: 74&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 6: 78&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 7: 94&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 10: 95&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that in a single day, something clicked and I was able to go much faster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s an exercise that is wicked and works the right ring finger and other stuff:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 31: 86&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 1: 87&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 2: 110&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 3: 112&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 6: 114&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 7: 116&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 8: 118&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 10: 122&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 11: 123&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 12: 124&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 14: 126&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;new-exercises&#34;&gt;New exercises&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously, I have also attacked brand new exercises since my last post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s one on thirds:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 7: 110&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 11: 130&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 12: 132&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 14: 136&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another on thirds:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 8: 92&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 10: 120&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 11: 130&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 12: 132&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 14: 136&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rapid improvement on these new exercises comes because, as I have admitted, I have been a total beginner with almost no technique at all, never having practiced scales or arpeggios in any key, so when I&amp;rsquo;m learning a new key, I start off all confused but then make progress quickly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the Bernstein and Gershwin music have all kinds of keys, changes of key, accidentals, the works, so there is no escaping mastering everything. I&amp;rsquo;m working particularly on A major and A-flat major now, with their four sharps and four flats, respectively. The scariest, fastest section of the Bernstein actually has a key signature with six sharps (although I have to wonder why, because the music is full of accidentals and almost atonal).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;motivation&#34;&gt;Motivation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are times when I do not feel motivated to practice the concert music at all. I have a confession to make: playing flute in an orchestra is not my favorite musical activity by a long shot. It&amp;rsquo;s something I&amp;rsquo;m doing because it is novel to me and because I hope to enjoy being a part of a group effort in which we somehow manage to sound on April 15 a lot better than we sound now. Also, having a goal, and having the threat of social shame, has proved sometimes to be an effective motivator for me to achieve my &amp;ldquo;real&amp;rdquo; goals as a side effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I really like doing, and aim to do more of, is playing music in very small groups. I like playing recorder with one or two or three or four others. So sometimes when I&amp;rsquo;m practicing I feel frustrated that I&amp;rsquo;m working on a second flute part of a large orchestral piece, rather than on a duet or something like that. Amusingly, the fact that there are only two of us second flutes left helps me feel like I am &amp;ldquo;making a difference&amp;rdquo;, however.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m still hanging in there with my crazy attempt to just jump into a new level of flute playing, with a hard deadline. It would be less stressful if I were just trying to improve at my own pace, but I have to admit that from November through December, when I was working on the flute, the fact that I did not have a concrete level of mastery as a goal definitely made my practice less effective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2012-03-12&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-03-12)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ended up &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/12/quitting-the-cmu-all-university-orchestra-one-of-the-hardest-decisions-in-my-life/&#34;&gt;quitting the CMU AUO&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Meditation is hard</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/02/10/meditation-is-hard/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Feb 2012 21:18:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/02/10/meditation-is-hard/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;About two weeks ago Abby and I started a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/02/02/2-new-daily-habits-of-mine-in-a-distracting-world/&#34;&gt;daily meditation practice&lt;/a&gt; in the morning. We&amp;rsquo;re still at it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently I&amp;rsquo;ve seen some articles about meditation &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.susanpiver.com/wordpress/2012/02/08/habit-2/&#34;&gt;habits&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wildmind.org/blogs/on-practice/how-we-use-effort-to-get-to-a-state-of-effortless-meditation&#34;&gt;difficulty&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The plain fact is that meditation is hard. There might be some kind of stereotype of meditation as &amp;ldquo;relaxing&amp;rdquo; or as blissing out or some such thing, but actually, meditation is quite hard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why is it so hard, and does putting effort into it somehow violate the point of it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;difficulty-of-meditation&#34;&gt;Difficulty of meditation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;physical&#34;&gt;Physical&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, there is always some &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/28/staring-at-the-wall-with-nowhere-to-go/&#34;&gt;physical difficulty&lt;/a&gt; in doing sitting meditation. Sitting &amp;ldquo;perfectly upright&amp;rdquo; is not easy for me when my legs are crossed and on the floor, because I&amp;rsquo;m not all that flexible where it matters (I&amp;rsquo;ve been working on that for years, with real incremental progress).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And because of asymmetry, I use a different &amp;ldquo;dominant&amp;rdquo; leg alternating
days. Trying to relax is difficult because the default result is
slumping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;mental&#34;&gt;Mental&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I slip into daydreams and weird thoughts very easily during meditation. I&amp;rsquo;ll have thoughts about things I need to do for the day, things I needed to do yesterday, or events coming up in weeks, or events in the past. In a single ten-minute session of meditation I might experience sadness over something, anxiety, anger, disgust, relief, excitement, you name it! My mind will go all over the place. If there are people who are blissing out doing meditation, I don&amp;rsquo;t know if I&amp;rsquo;m the same species as them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Way back when I first started meditation, my main problem was actually that I would get disappointed and disgusted about my thoughts during meditation, and this of course created a cycle of more unrest during meditation. I got one important insight out of this: that I had a lifelong habit of hating myself, of perfectionism that I needed to let go of. When I realized this, I was able to break the cycle, both in meditation and in my &amp;ldquo;regular&amp;rdquo; life. I still have silly thoughts during meditation, but the difference now is that I don&amp;rsquo;t let them take over. They are what they are, and I return to the breath, return to posture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, a year ago when I first started sitting with people, I got very self-conscious and worried about what they thought about my posture or breathing or whatever. After a couple of months, that anxiety completely disappeared. I&amp;rsquo;m doing what I&amp;rsquo;m doing; what is the point of adding extraneous thoughts and worries?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;effort&#34;&gt;Effort&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What level of effort do I apply when meditating? I think I go by feel. Basically, if I believe that putting a certain amount of effort in will disrupt me worse than the chaos that already exists, then I pull back. If I&amp;rsquo;m perpetually adjusting my shoulders or legs, then that will dominate the whole experience and I will be unsettled. If I try too hard to control my mind and make sure it doesn&amp;rsquo;t wander too far, then that can backfire too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I currently do more modest things that I believe from experience will not backfire. I&amp;rsquo;ll straighten my back enough to reboot my breath and awareness, but then let go of focusing on my back, and move to something else instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also helpful to me has been returning to an awareness of external noises (such as humming of appliances or traffic outside). This is because in the past, sometimes I would zone out and not be aware of external noises, and when the ending bell sounded, I would be startled and know instantly that I had zoned out instead of being present. Paying attention to physical sensations in my body as well as external noises outside my control has been helpful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meditation is hard work. There is no shortage of instruction on how to do it, but like everything else, I don&amp;rsquo;t really know any way to do it other than honest personal trial and error and experience.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On playing my first games of chess in a year</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/02/07/on-playing-my-first-games-of-chess-in-a-year/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Feb 2012 22:46:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/02/07/on-playing-my-first-games-of-chess-in-a-year/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Lately there has been a lot of attention paid to &lt;a href=&#34;http://expertenough.com/1423/deliberate-practice&#34;&gt;deliberate practice&lt;/a&gt;. I thought I&amp;rsquo;d give one example of my practice habits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over a week ago, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/01/27/a-new-friends-very-musical-birthday-party-changed-my-life/&#34;&gt;at a birthday party&lt;/a&gt;, I ended up playing two casual games of &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/chess/&#34;&gt;chess&lt;/a&gt;, my first games of chess in an entire year since I completely quit playing the game (either in tournaments or casually) in order to focus on rebooting my passion for playing &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/music/&#34;&gt;music&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first game was against someone who opened with 1 h4, immediately marking himself as a beginner, and I won quickly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second game was much harder, because while my opponent was clearly not a strong player, and as White started off with an inferior opening, I had a hard time coming up with a crushing advantage. In fact, I found myself embarking on a slow, misguided plan that led to an equal middle game. It was only after a terrible blunder on his part that I immediately had a won position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So overall, these casual games were quite one-sided.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the next morning, the first thing I did was enter the moves of both games into my computer and briefly analyze the games with &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cruxis.com/chess/houdini.htm&#34;&gt;Houdini&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why did I do this?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;self-analysis-for-improvement&#34;&gt;Self-analysis for improvement&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing I learned when considerably improving my game of chess was that the only true way to improve is to learn from your own mistakes. These could be classified in many different ways. I was not as rigorous as I could have been (should have been) in analyzing mistakes and making sure not to repeat them, else I would have made &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chess_master&#34;&gt;National Master&lt;/a&gt; long ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t play in chess tournaments any more, but I could not help myself when i decided to remember my casual games from the party and enter them into the computer the next morning. It&amp;rsquo;s a &lt;em&gt;habit&lt;/em&gt;. When I was playing chess seriously, I was going to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburghcc.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Chess Club&lt;/a&gt; every week and playing blitz. Some people play blitz as throwaway fun. Not me. These blitz were actually excellent material for me to learn from. I would go home after playing a dozen or so games of blitz and enter all the interesting games into my computer in order to analyze them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2015-12-21&#34;&gt;(Update of 2015-12-21)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three years later, I made a focused push, temporarily putting many
things aside in my life, in the fall of 2015 to &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2016/01/22/on-finally-achieving-the-us-national-master-chess-title-at-age-45-part-1&#34;&gt;achieve my US Chess
National Master title&lt;/a&gt;, and finally made it, a dream come true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, I have been teaching private lessons since 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-i-look-for-when-analyzing-a-game-i-played&#34;&gt;What I look for when analyzing a game I played&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It doesn&amp;rsquo;t matter whether I win or lose a game. I thirst to find out where &lt;em&gt;I could have done better&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;losing&#34;&gt;Losing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously, when I lose a game, I try to figure out why. Sometimes it&amp;rsquo;s just one bad move. Sometimes it&amp;rsquo;s a series of bad moves that reveal a completely flawed conception of what was going on. Sometimes the errors reveal physical fatigue, psychological barriers, raw technical knowledge, or simple calculational carelessness. The causes differ, so it is important to find out what the specific causes are. Without knowing the specific cause, applying effort toward a remedy may be a futile waste of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;winning&#34;&gt;Winning&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t get much pleasure from just winning a game, or winning a tournament. In itself, &lt;em&gt;winning means nothing to me&lt;/em&gt;. I need to know that &lt;em&gt;I deserved to win&lt;/em&gt; (for some definition of &amp;ldquo;deserve&amp;rdquo;). I analyze games that I won, to see whether I actually made an error during an attack that &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; have left me lost (if I had been playing against someone who saw through my error). Also, it is important to see whether, during a winning game, I missed a much quicker and decisive win, and instead took a long route unnecessarily.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be sure, sometimes for practical reasons it is wise to win in a clear and easy way rather than the most brilliant, quick way. But other times, I have won the long way in which my opponent could have come back fighting (but just happened not to), and therefore I really should have looked for the killer knockout that existed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;uncertainty&#34;&gt;Uncertainty&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the case of the second casual game I played at the party, I was plagued during the middle game with the thought that I knew I could have made more of my opening advantage, but squandered it. There was no loss or win straight out of the opening, but I had to go and determine how my entire opening plan was ineffective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even in a casual game of chess, I take it pretty seriously, and treat it as a learning opportunity. I feel slightly odd admitting this in public, and hope that it doesn&amp;rsquo;t result in people no longer wanting to play casual games with me, but is it wrong to want to know the truth of the situation in the game? Is it any sillier than when I know I got every answer on a final exam in a class right except for one, and therefore I have my A+ locked up, but I want to know how to solve the problem that confused me?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Joining an orchestra: learning in the face of terror</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/02/01/joining-an-orchestra-learning-in-the-face-of-terror/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2012 19:29:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/02/01/joining-an-orchestra-learning-in-the-face-of-terror/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have not written about my &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/flute/&#34;&gt;flute activities&lt;/a&gt; since &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/01/08/finding-and-using-my-childhood-flute-books/&#34;&gt;a month ago&lt;/a&gt;, but that&amp;rsquo;s not for lack of action: in fact, I&amp;rsquo;ve been spending a lot of time on the flute, at the expense of other personal projects, including writing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two months ago, I mentioned that I was &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/01/im-going-to-perform-music-much-sooner-than-i-expected-monday/&#34;&gt;considering joining&lt;/a&gt; the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.andrew.cmu.edu/user/auo/&#34;&gt;Carnegie Mellon All-University Orchestra&lt;/a&gt;, which I claimed was &amp;ldquo;not very good&amp;rdquo; and that &amp;ldquo;I don&amp;rsquo;t have to be super good to be a part of it.&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;I take back those comments&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I joined the CMU AUO two Sundays ago, attending the first rehearsal then, and &lt;strong&gt;it was one of the most frightening experiences in my entire life&lt;/strong&gt;. I almost left before even entering the rehearsal room. But I went in, stayed for the two and a half hours, and last Sunday, I went to the second rehearsal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me put it this way: at the first rehearsal, there were about ten flutes and one piccolo in the flute section. At the second rehearsal, we are down to four flutes and one piccolo. I hope that we don&amp;rsquo;t lose any more flutes at the next rehearsal. OK, maybe some students happened to be busy and will be returning. Or maybe some of them had the same reaction that I had: &lt;em&gt;absolute terror&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me explain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-music-we-are-to-play-for-the-april-15-concert&#34;&gt;The music we are to play for the April 15 concert&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the door of the rehearsal room, we got to pick up the music for the concert scheduled for April 15. There are four works, but one is for brass and percussion only, and the other for strings only, so there are only two I would play in on flute:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;George Gershwin, &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rhapsody_in_Blue&#34;&gt;Rhapsody in Blue&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Leonard Bernstein, &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/West_Side_Story#Symphonic_Dances_from_West_Side_Story&#34;&gt;Symphonic Dances from West Side Story&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On inspection at the door, I immediately realized that I could not play &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; of this music. Both the Gershwin and Bernstein were totally out of my current abilities. Worse, the Bernstein piece looked particularly insanely hard to me, even though I picked up the &amp;ldquo;flute 2&amp;rdquo; part, not the &amp;ldquo;flute 1&amp;rdquo; part. There were a lot syncopations, accents, extreme dynamics, very high notes (some of which I had not yet even learned the fingerings for yet), and the music was very fast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was filled with terror. I almost left without entering the room and signing in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-i-stayed&#34;&gt;Why I stayed&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went in anyway. I decided that I needed to see what this orchestra was about, since I have never been in an orchestra in my life (I stopped my feeble playing of the flute at age 13 and never played again after that).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a &amp;ldquo;fail fast&amp;rdquo; plan: if I really felt I couldn&amp;rsquo;t make a decent contribution in this orchestra, I would walk out as soon as I felt I was a hopeless burden to the team. &lt;em&gt;Forget ego&lt;/em&gt;: what I do or do not do must be based entirely on objective considerations. I wasn&amp;rsquo;t going to walk away already just because I believed (and still believe!) that I must be the worst musician in the entire orchestra, nor would I be afraid to walk away in the future if I found that I was harming the team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-first-rehearsal&#34;&gt;The first rehearsal&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ended up surviving the first rehearsal, in that we did a sight-reading session in which although I could barely play any of the music, I sat there trying to learn and did what I could, playing a few notes here and there when I could, and sitting out when there was just no way I could get anything right at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, I sat next to a guy who was playing piccolo, and he seemed to nail everything, although I had asked him earlier how long he&amp;rsquo;d been playing flute and he said twelve years. Note: I have been playing flute seriously for only three months, and on the membership form for the orchestra, it asked for a self-rating of experience level, ranging from Beginner to Advanced Beginner to Intermediate to Advanced, and with all honesty I checked off &lt;strong&gt;Beginner&lt;/strong&gt; (not even Advanced Beginner).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, it gave me some hope when I realized that everyone was having a hard time with the music. I&amp;rsquo;m sure nobody was having as hard a time as me, but we were struggling while sight reading at a very slow tempo. It also gave me hope that the director, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sellner.org/maria/Home.html&#34;&gt;Maria Sensi Sellner&lt;/a&gt;, happened to mention that we were tackling probably the hardest work the orchestra had attempted in its history, because she is leaving after this season and wanted to do something ambitious. OK, so it wasn&amp;rsquo;t just me thinking this music was hard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, she seemed to me very effective in helping us get started with the music. She worked out the tricky rhythms with us, and the music began to make more sense to me during the rehearsal. She told us that we should listen to recordings and check out the West Side Story musical so that we would understand the music in the context of the action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I left the rehearsal still shell-shocked, but I reasoned to myself that it would be stupid to quit this early on, before having had a chance to study the score more, continue to improve my technique, etc. I had grave doubts that I would return for the second rehearsal, but I had &lt;em&gt;one week&lt;/em&gt; to decide whether I should even come back. (Note that the orchestra has an attendance policy, so that anyone missing too many rehearsals may not play in the concert.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-sample-auo-performance&#34;&gt;A sample AUO performance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For fun, here is the CMU AUO performing last fall Bernstein&amp;rsquo;s Overture to Candide. They weren&amp;rsquo;t bad. That gives me hope, because we sounded pretty bad sight reading the Symphonic Dances from West Side Story, so I actually have faith that Sellner can get us into reasonable shape in two months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/ZelG_nJ-QvE&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-practice-strategy-for-a-week-after-the-first-rehearsal&#34;&gt;My practice strategy for a week after the first rehearsal&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All January I had been working really hard for three weeks on flute practice, in anticipation of the first CMU AUO rehearsal that occurred on January 22. I was making a &lt;em&gt;huge&lt;/em&gt; amount of progress working through &amp;ldquo;easy&amp;rdquo; stuff. Flute is much, much harder to play than &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/recorder/&#34;&gt;recorder&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the first rehearsal, I decided that there was no way I could ever play the Gershwin or Bernstein without focusing really hard on pure technique. So the bulk of my practice was beginning to systematically work through the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Rubank-Intermediate-Method-Piccolo-Educational/dp/1423444221&#34;&gt;Rubank Intermediate Method: Flute or Piccolo&lt;/a&gt; that I mentioned &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/01/08/finding-and-using-my-childhood-flute-books/&#34;&gt;finding in early January&lt;/a&gt; and never having used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spent a little bit of time trying to play excerpts from the Gershwin and Bernstein at a very slow tempo, but frankly, these attempts were very frustrating because I was still having problems just playing the high notes at all, for example. &lt;strong&gt;I had to learn the fingerings for some notes I had never played in my life.&lt;/strong&gt; I also had to improve my embouchure in order to produce those notes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(By the way, I have almost completely stopped playing recorder for a month. I am still attending the monthly meetings of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.andrew.cmu.edu/user/lukas/pcars/Welcome.html&#34;&gt;local recorder group&lt;/a&gt;, and practicing a little before attending, but I cannot devote any more time to improving on recorder while trying to get successfully to the April 15 CMU AUO concert.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-second-rehearsal&#34;&gt;The second rehearsal&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the second rehearsal approached, I wondered what we were supposed to be preparing for it. I sent email to the guy I had contacted last year about joining the orchestra, asking him if I had been put on the announcement mailing list yet, and he apologized, saying that he hadn&amp;rsquo;t, and he put me on. So it was only hours before the second rehearsal that I learned we were supposed to have been for days watching some YouTube videos and working on the two very hardest sections of the Bernstein!!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I almost didn&amp;rsquo;t go to the second rehearsal, as a result. I had not even looked at the hardest sections of the Bernstein yet: during the entire week, I had worked on the sections just up till those hardest sections!! I spent half an hour before the Sunday evening rehearsal trying to do a little work on the hardest sections, but failing pretty miserably. Oh well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went to the second rehearsal anyway. I half expected that I would be asked to leave after being found out to be completely incompetent (as well as not doing my homework).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that many of us had not done our homework, or had done it but were still having a lot of problems. The director was patient and slowed things down a lot and again focused on our getting the rhythms and syncopation right, and all the instruments just staying together at all. Because we were so unprepared, we ran out of time to work on the Gershwin, which she had originally planned to cover as well as the Bernstein.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, we lost most of our flutists!! In fact, with only four flutes and a piccolo left, during a flute-dominated passage of the Bernstein, we found out that only one of us was playing &amp;ldquo;flute 1&amp;rdquo;. The director asked for someone else to join her, and so I guess now we have two on &amp;ldquo;flute 1&amp;rdquo;, and me and the other person on &amp;ldquo;flute 2&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-practice-strategy-for-this-week-after-the-second-rehearsal&#34;&gt;My practice strategy for this week after the second rehearsal&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we were having a rehearsal again next Sunday, I would be seriously worried and contemplate probably having to drop out of the orchestra then. Luckily, we are skipping Super Bowl Sunday. &lt;strong&gt;This gives me two weeks, rather than one, to improve drastically.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The director had said it was up to us individually and in the upcoming sections to get our act together on the Bernstein sections in question. So I have at least one concrete goal for the next rehearsal: being prepared to play reasonably accurately the difficult Bernstein sections, and at tempo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For three days now so far this week, I have continued with working through the Rubank intermediate method. I have made so much progress that I think that in another couple of days I may consider myself an Advanced Beginner at flute rather than just a Beginner, ha!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;deliberate-practice&#34;&gt;Deliberate practice&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am putting in the focused, &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Practice_%28learning_method%29#Deliberate_practice&#34;&gt;deliberate practice&lt;/a&gt; to improve as rapidly and efficiently as I can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, I have to put in a plug for Gerald Klickstein, author of the wonderful book &lt;a href=&#34;http://musiciansway.com/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Musician&amp;rsquo;s Way&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, and his &lt;a href=&#34;http://musiciansway.com/blog/&#34;&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt; as well as his &lt;a href=&#34;http://twitter.com/klickstein&#34;&gt;Twitter feed @klickstein&lt;/a&gt;, which have been profoundly inspirational and useful in not only my music practice but also all of my other serious pursuits. He even replies to questions and comments promptly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regarding learning, I will be writing blog posts in the future about my various strategies for learning that I find effective. A recent article talks about &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wired.com/geekdad/2012/01/everything-about-learning/&#34;&gt;interleaving&lt;/a&gt;, which I have used to great effect to &amp;ldquo;parallelize&amp;rdquo; my learning, and I definitely use it in my music practice. I work on many things in one session, not just one thing, because there is no way to just get massively better at one thing during one session, and then do the same for something else at the next session. I have to parallelize, to make small bits of progress every day on something. For example, every day I work on&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;breath&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;intonation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;tone&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;high notes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;dynamics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;articulation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;rhythm: meters, syncopation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;tonguing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;speed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;passage work in keys (scales, arpeggios, thirds)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;tricky fingerings&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;style, expression&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;actual music&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I squeeze as much as I can out of an hour of practice at home. I&amp;rsquo;ve found that there are diminishing returns of all kinds after an hour. Obviously, if I were a music student or professional, I&amp;rsquo;d use multiple sessions to get more hours, but for much of my life these days I use the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pareto_principle&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;80&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;20&lt;/sub&gt; rule&lt;/a&gt; to maximize the returns on my practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;speed&#34;&gt;Speed&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I use the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/29/a-musicians-best-friend/&#34;&gt;metronome&lt;/a&gt; extensively in my practice to gauge my progress, by making note each day of the fastest speed at which I can execute an exercise with the best musical qualities I am capable of currently, and then trying to do it faster the next day. This method worked very well for me when I was learning the recorder from scratch, and it is working for me well now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, here is the record for one of the twenty or so exercises I have worked on in the Rubank book for the past week and a half:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 24: 100&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 25: 106&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 26: 109&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 27: 130&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 28: 131&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 29: 133&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 31: 141&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 24: 120&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 25: 135&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 26: 137&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 27: 139&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 28: 144&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 29: 146&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 30: 148&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 31: 152&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 1: 154&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 25: 95&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 26: 96&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 27: 102&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 28: 106&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 29: 107&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 1: 115&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another (in which I have been finding the series of arpeggios rather difficult):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 25: 100&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 26: 102&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 27: 105&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 29: 106&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 30: 107&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 31: 108&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Where there is a gap in the record, I either did not play that exercise that day, because I chose to work on another, or I did but could not go faster without error.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that the progress is not always linear. Sometimes there are &amp;ldquo;trouble spots&amp;rdquo; that hold me back for a while before I overcome them. Sometimes I am stagnant for a day or even a couple of days before I suddenly get better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keeping detailed records is vital to an objective assessment of where one is in one&amp;rsquo;s practice. I kept detailed records when losing thirty pounds over a decade ago, and when transforming myself from a non-runner into a marathoner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;progress-on-the-bernstein&#34;&gt;Progress on the Bernstein&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As mentioned, I have not practiced the Bernstein music that much, because I devote around 80 or 90 percent of my time to just improving my technique. The &lt;em&gt;fundamentals&lt;/em&gt; matter (I will talk about this in future blog posts) when trying to get good at something. One cannot just rush in without mastering fundamentals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some metronome improvement numbers for sections of the Bernstein music:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 28: 40&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 29: 70&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;January 30: 128 (full speed)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;January 28: 100&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;January 31: 110 (I still need to get up to 128)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;January 30: 100 (I still need to get up to 160!!)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously, my goal for the next rehearsal is to get as much up to full speed as possible in the sections that I need the most work on. If I fail miserably to measure up, I will feel justified in quitting the orchestra. But given my improvement in the Rubank method, I think I have a fighting chance in the next ten days to get much better in the Bernstein music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By deciding to take on the challenge of joining the CMU All-University Orchestra while being pathetically incompetent at flute, I am trying to push the limits of my learning and practice abilities. I will drop out if I only manage to hold back rehearsals or feel that I will play badly at the scheduled concert. But so far, I am still hanging in there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2012-03-12&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-03-12)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ended up &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/12/quitting-the-cmu-all-university-orchestra-one-of-the-hardest-decisions-in-my-life/&#34;&gt;quitting the CMU AUO&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Finding and using my childhood flute books</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/01/08/finding-and-using-my-childhood-flute-books/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Jan 2012 11:40:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/01/08/finding-and-using-my-childhood-flute-books/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/belwin-home-practice-record.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;My 5th grade flute book practice record&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I was in my basement looking for stuff and happened to find three of my childhood &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/flute/&#34;&gt;flute&lt;/a&gt; books:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Belwin-Band-Builder-Part-Flute/dp/B000M0CLSW&#34;&gt;Belwin Band Builder part 1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Rubank-Intermediate-Method-Piccolo-Educational/dp/1423444221&#34;&gt;Rubank Intermediate Method: Flute or Piccolo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Marcel-Franks-Classical-Tunes-Flute/dp/B002JVQCWI&#34;&gt;Marcel Frank&amp;rsquo;s 95 Classical Tunes For The Flute&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are my memories of my usage of these books and how I might use them now, three decades later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;belwin-band-builder&#34;&gt;Belwin Band Builder&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Belwin Band Builder is a completely trivial and boring beginning band method that I used when learning flute in the 5th grade under Mr. Peters. The amusing thing is the &amp;ldquo;home practice record&amp;rdquo; at the back of the book, which still has my father&amp;rsquo;s signatures, as you can see from the photo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see, my memory in my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/09/taking-up-flute-again-after-decades/&#34;&gt;blog post about starting flute up again&lt;/a&gt; of being delinquent with practice has been completely validated! There are a lot of &amp;ldquo;0 minutes&amp;rdquo; written down, on days when I didn&amp;rsquo;t even touch the flute and couldn&amp;rsquo;t even get myself to write down an exaggerated number of minutes of practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notice that only the first six weeks were graded by Mr. Peters, and in the first week, I had gotten a B- that I had tried to erase. At some point, Mr. Peters&amp;rsquo; health problems got bad, I think, and he stopped paying attention to our practice record. My father did keep on signing, for sixteen weeks, and I put down three final weeks that I didn&amp;rsquo;t even have him sign, because Mr. Peters wasn&amp;rsquo;t checking anything any more anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;rubank-intermediate-method&#34;&gt;Rubank Intermediate Method&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I recall correctly, Mr. Peters started teaching 6th grade band when he suddenly got so ill he had to retire, and our subsitute Mr. McLaughlin became permanent band director (I had him for the rest of 6th grade band and in intermediate band after that).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before Mr. Peters left, he gave me a list of two flute method books he recommended, and I dutifully gave the list to my father, who ordered them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that I never used them. I may have glanced at them, and fooled around a few minutes with them, but I never used them!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Rubank Intermediate Method was one of these books. Despite the physical age of my copy, the only evidence that I ever touched it is my name crudely written in marker on the front cover. I just started using the method and had to bend back on stapled binding so that the book would open flat for my music stand! The method looks useful to me now, with lots of technical exercises for all keys, interspersed with some musical excerpts such as gavottes and minuets, but back when I was eleven years old and not a classical music fan, this book must have seemed to me&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;foreign&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;boring&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;hard&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;pointless&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At that age, I was mostly interested in playing&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;marches&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;syncopated rock&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;big band swing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;marcel-frank-s-95-classical-tunes-for-the-flute&#34;&gt;Marcel Frank&amp;rsquo;s 95 Classical Tunes For The Flute&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is all classical stuff. Enough said: my eleven-year-old self did not find much of this music interesting. There are exceptions, however! Flipping through this book, I recognize some excerpts as music I definitely tried playing at the time. Some examples:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A Song of India&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sleeping Beauty&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Roses from the South&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Radetzky March&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My explanation is quite simple:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I loved &lt;em&gt;marches&lt;/em&gt; of any kind (hence my later joining marching band).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I loved fast &lt;em&gt;waltzes&lt;/em&gt;, through exposure to them from TV cartoons such as &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tom_and_Jerry&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Tom and Jerry&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There were pieces I &lt;em&gt;recognized&lt;/em&gt; as having heard (such as &amp;ldquo;A Song of India&amp;rdquo;) because of random &amp;ldquo;Greatest Classical Masterpieces&amp;rdquo; types of LP records (and there were many varieties of this kind of material) that my mother sometimes bought at garage sales and flea markets and brought home. Being familiar with a tune (and liking it) definitely was a motivation to at least try playing it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, I do not particularly like the selections or length (each just a single page) in this compilation. So I don&amp;rsquo;t expect to use this book much. I have other flute music already I have been enjoying practicing, especially the music that comes with a good accompaniment CD (this makes such a big difference).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-reflections&#34;&gt;My reflections&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s funny to me that even now, thirty years later, my mind still operates in a similar way. I still like marches. I still like fast waltzes (and even originally took up &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/ballroom-dance/&#34;&gt;ballroom dance&lt;/a&gt; specifically because I wanted to eventually dance the Viennese waltz. I still am more motivated to play something new if I&amp;rsquo;ve heard it before and like it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I&amp;rsquo;m also more mature now, more open. I&amp;rsquo;ve listened to a whole lot more and whole lot more variety of music since I was a child. And I&amp;rsquo;m willing to try listening to or playing any kind of music now. In fact, just last year, most of the music I&amp;rsquo;ve played on any instrument has been completely new to me, as a listener or performer. And that&amp;rsquo;s great. It&amp;rsquo;s part of the whole fun of living, experiencing more and different music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was amusing rediscovering my old flute books. The intermediate method looks like a good one to use for practice. It&amp;rsquo;s never too late to continue where I left off as a child, with a different mindset and more mature self-discipline!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Much progress playing flute</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/12/20/much-progress-playing-flute/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Dec 2011 21:35:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/12/20/much-progress-playing-flute/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Starting yesterday, I finally returned to practicing &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/flute/&#34;&gt;flute&lt;/a&gt;. I had played very little flute in ten days, as a result of focusing my musical practice almost entirely on soprano &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/recorder/&#34;&gt;recorder&lt;/a&gt; for the performance at the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/16/playing-recorder-and-flute-at-the-holiday-ball/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Contras and Squares Holiday Ball on Friday&lt;/a&gt;. I did play flute just a little bit at the Holiday Ball, but nothing I needed practice on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was surprised how much better I was at flute yesterday (and today) despite no practice in ten days. How did this happen?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My path in improving at flute has been much different from my path in improving at recorder (which I continue to do, practicing alto on Saturday and then playing mostly tenor at the monthly local recorder group meeting on Sunday). I think there are a lot of reasons for the differences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;physical-demands&#34;&gt;Physical demands&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel that the physical demands of the flute have been considerable, such that I have simply required time for my body to adjust. I was limited in what I could do while I was adjusting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The flute is bigger and heavier than the very light recorders I have focused on (soprano and alto) and holding it is more awkward. My left finger joint and right pinkie take the hit, in particular. Also, when playing the recorder, one does not curl the fingers, but that is correct and necessary for the flute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The embouchure really needs to be developed. I still feel awkward about playing higher notes with a decent tone and in tune, but that is precisely what has become much better in the past ten days. It&amp;rsquo;s taken over a month to reach this point of what I consider &amp;ldquo;acceptability&amp;rdquo;! &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Patience_Is_A_Virtue&#34;&gt;Patience is a virtue.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am still working on improving my breathing capacity and control sufficiently to play as legato as I would like for pieces that want it.  Definite improvements there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Creating a nice tone is of course what the flute is all about. On the recorder, there is relatively little one can do with its sound, other than to make it clean. I&amp;rsquo;ve been working hard on improving my tone and developing a natural, tasteful vibrato.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;methods-and-accompaniment-cds&#34;&gt;Methods and accompaniment CDs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did not and do not use any music accompaniment CDs when practicing recorder. I know they exist, but I had not believed it necessary to order them from a specialty shop online. At best, I have listened to recorded music featuring musicians playing recorder, and played along to some tracks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, I have found many flute method books with accompaniment CDs at the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/30/free-to-the-people-since-1895/&#34;&gt;library&lt;/a&gt; and have been making great use of them!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had started out with &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.musicminusone.com/used-play-flute-innovative-method-adults-returning-play-p-60414222.html&#34;&gt;I Used to Play Flute&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, which I&amp;rsquo;m still using now. Then I got hold of the &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.boosey.com/shop/prod/Morgan-Chris-Boosey-Woodwind-Method-Flute-Book-1/702022&#34;&gt;Boosey Woodwind Method: Flute Book 1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.boosey.com/shop/prod/Morgan-Chris-Boosey-Woodwind-Method-Flute-Book-2/706166&#34;&gt;Boosey Woodwind Method: Flute Book 2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, and also the &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.halleonard.com/product/viewproduct.do?itemid=50489868&#34;&gt;Moyse Collection of Easy Flute Classics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have made my way through most of this material. I had expected to make slower progress, but then again, I benefit from having played flute some as a child and also &amp;ldquo;cross-trained&amp;rdquo; by all my recorder playing that has developed my general, non-flute musical skills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;varied-repertoire&#34;&gt;Varied repertoire&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I an enjoying the varied repertoire in the books I mentioned above. There is classical stuff, marches, ballads, swinging jazz, Bosnian and Israeli traditional songs, the works. That&amp;rsquo;s why I took up the flute again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;technical-exercises&#34;&gt;Technical exercises&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing I have not done &lt;em&gt;at all&lt;/em&gt; yet is the kind of technical exercises I began doing on recorder long ago: scales, arpeggios, increasing the speed significantly. I want to feel vaguely guilty for not beginning such exercises, but I think I have had good reasons to avoid them for now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One is that I wanted to get a &amp;ldquo;taste&amp;rdquo; of fun, of playing real music immediately, to gauge where I am.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another is that frankly, until my body adapted to the physical demands, I felt I was not in any condition to benefit optimally from plunging directly into that kind of practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am very happy with my flute progress and expect to hunker down after my month-long &amp;ldquo;beginner&amp;rdquo; exploratory phase, by developing a plan for serious technical practice. I will scope out recommended technique books and switch my focus from &amp;ldquo;real music&amp;rdquo; to exercises, so that I can play the &amp;ldquo;real music&amp;rdquo; better eventually.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>