<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Snow on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/snow/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Snow on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/snow/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>How to gut out the tough workout</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/01/27/how-to-gut-out-the-tough-workout/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Jan 2013 17:36:07 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/01/27/how-to-gut-out-the-tough-workout/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today I had a really tough workout. It was &lt;em&gt;unexpectedly&lt;/em&gt; tough, not &lt;em&gt;expectedly&lt;/em&gt; tough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went for a run in the trails of Frick Park. The route was my usual 5-mile rather hilly out and back (down to Fern Hollow and back up) that is a staple for me, and which I last did &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/31/why-i-went-frick-park-trail-running-in-snowfall-for-the-first-time-in-a-decade/&#34;&gt;almost a month ago&lt;/a&gt;. As I mentioned then, in winter I have not usually run in the trails of Frick Park, because of snow or ice, but this winter, I&amp;rsquo;m trying to do more trail running when feasible, because &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/17/winter-running-in-vibram-fivefingers-shoes-revisited/&#34;&gt;road running&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/01/05/how-to-enjoy-treadmill-running-treat-it-as-a-meditative-practice/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;treadmilling&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; (because of some friends using the term recently, I&amp;rsquo;ve recently decided to use it myself and no longer call it &amp;ldquo;running&amp;rdquo; at all, since the biomechanics are so different) are not as fun for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The run quickly turned out to be very challenging. I thought of bailing out. Here&amp;rsquo;s how I gutted it out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;should-i-even-gut-it-out-at-all&#34;&gt;Should I even gut it out at all?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first question we should ask when thinking about whether to gut it out is whether we actually &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Ego&lt;/em&gt; often prevents us from asking the question. Sometimes there definitely are legitimate reasons for just &amp;ldquo;following orders&amp;rdquo; and turning off the mind and doing what one has planned to do. If you&amp;rsquo;re trapped in the wilderness and need to &lt;em&gt;survive&lt;/em&gt;, you need to stay focused on doing what needs to be done, and never once question whether you should, because else you will probably die. We should definitely always be prepared to do what we need to do, without question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, in the case of a workout that is not a matter of life and death, I have come to believe that it is wise to question what one is doing. This is tricky, because it takes energy to make decisions, while it takes no energy to just follow orders. In a previous post I&amp;rsquo;ve tried to break down the dilemma into &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/14/three-questions-to-ask-yourself-when-you-dont-feel-like-doing-your-scheduled-workout/&#34;&gt;three questions&lt;/a&gt; when you doubt your planned workout. Also, I have described situations in which I have backed away in &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/25/notes-on-exercising-while-sick-or-tired/&#34;&gt;one controlled manner or another&lt;/a&gt; from the planned workout.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is about the case when you know you don&amp;rsquo;t have a truly valid excuse to back out. You feel healthy, you feel you can probably accomplish the task, but something physical or mental is hurting and tempts you to back down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-difficulty-today&#34;&gt;My difficulty today&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My friend &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.chrisumbel.com/&#34;&gt;Chris&lt;/a&gt; recently started a running blog, and just today he put up a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/http://www.runoverit.com/yet-another-winter-running-post/&#34;&gt;great post about his experiences with winter running&lt;/a&gt;. In the comments I noted in agreement that running in snow is tough. Amusingly, this gave me the idea to go out and test just how tough running in snow is, when in the hilly trails of Frick Park. Trail running in anything other than a trivial layer snow is not something I have done recently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, it&amp;rsquo;s really tough. &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/28/meditations-on-climbing-the-36-floors-of-the-pitt-cathedral-of-learning/&#34;&gt;Running up hills has never been my strong point&lt;/a&gt; in any case, but with snow and little traction, running uphill proved to be immensely difficult. I felt like I was sliding while inching uphill, while my quads and inner thighs were burning with the effort to stabilize my body while pushing uphill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given that I knew how hilly the rest of the course would be, I had concerns about whether I would give out early.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;analysis-physical-then-mental&#34;&gt;Analysis: physical, then mental&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So my doubt started with some physical anxiety, followed by a mental anxiety combined with projections and calculations in my head. What to do?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing to remember is that it is not possible to trust on-the-fly mental anxieties. We do not only fool ourselves self-servingly in various ways when we are under physical duress. Our bodies may also be fooled by our minds even against our wishes. There is a hypothesis that has been gaining favor in the endurance sports communities that there is a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Central_governor&#34;&gt;central governor&lt;/a&gt; that works to try to protect us from overdoing ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe the central governor could &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; have been an issue for me in my workout, which was really not all that terrible, but I think it may have been an issue in long races where I really have pushed myself to my limits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;objectivity&#34;&gt;Objectivity&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you feel like maybe you won&amp;rsquo;t finish what you set out to do, it is easy to get emotional and lose objectivity. Frustration, anger, shame, anxiety, too easily arise, if one is serious about one&amp;rsquo;s exercise program, and especially if there is some concrete milestone or goal to achieve, like a big race you&amp;rsquo;ve sacrificed a lot of time and energy (and maybe money) for. But it&amp;rsquo;s important to remember that whatever you&amp;rsquo;ve already put in is a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sunk_costs&#34;&gt;sunk cost&lt;/a&gt;. The rational thing to do is to examine the &lt;em&gt;present&lt;/em&gt;, not the &lt;em&gt;past&lt;/em&gt; or the &lt;em&gt;future&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;think-of-the-worst-case-scenarios&#34;&gt;Think of the worst case scenarios&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To avoid wishful thinking, I find it useful to examine the worst case scenarios and ask whether they are so bad. If so, then scale back and examine the &lt;em&gt;probable&lt;/em&gt; scenarios. If the worst case scenario is not so bad, then I tend to push through, because I don&amp;rsquo;t have that much to lose. &amp;ldquo;Negative thinking&amp;rdquo; is a useful trick that is a cornerstone of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stoicism&#34;&gt;Stoic philosophy&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, for example, today, the temperature was something like 35F, which is not bad at all. If I got too tired to run and had to walk, I would not be in any danger of hypothermia or anything. So it was totally worth pushing on in order to test my limits even if I had to stop eventually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, needless to say, there is no shame in walking. I have very rarely had to resort to walking during a run that I planned, but it has happened before. No big deal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;change-some-variable-to-make-your-workout-more-likely-to-succeed&#34;&gt;Change some variable to make your workout more likely to &amp;ldquo;succeed&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once I realized that my run was going to be very tough, I redefined my workout. I slowed down and focused on the goal of maintaining a steady (and still considerable) effort and not having to walk, and finishing strong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Learning to fail is laudable and useful, but so is learning to accept small successes. Small successes breed confidence and therefore the foundation for attempting larger successes. So despite what I just said about walking being OK, in my experience it does have a demoralizing or questioning effect, so I prefer to finish strong at a lesser task rather than fail to finish a more ambitious task.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes it&amp;rsquo;s a judgment call. But one thing for sure is that I was very excited to emerge from Frick Park with my quads having burned for an hour but still able to pick up the pace back on the roads home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An advantage of succeeding at a lesser task is that there is a clear path toward upping the difficulty. If you fail, it&amp;rsquo;s harder to find out where to scale down the difficulty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;endurance-vs-strength&#34;&gt;Endurance vs. strength&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here I&amp;rsquo;ve been talking about tasks of &lt;em&gt;endurance&lt;/em&gt;. When it comes to &lt;em&gt;strength&lt;/em&gt;, the &lt;em&gt;opposite&lt;/em&gt; is true: you want to fail in order to determine the parameters. You want to lift weights to failure, rather than mindlessly doing twenty reps of some light weight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a pretty good run today despite initially not being sure I should go through with it. I reasoned that it was worth a shot and that I had backup plans for both my body and mind if I didn&amp;rsquo;t make it. I look forward to doing more super-hard snowy uphill trail running this winter. It will make me stronger.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why I went Frick Park trail running in snowfall for the first time in a decade</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/12/31/why-i-went-frick-park-trail-running-in-snowfall-for-the-first-time-in-a-decade/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Dec 2012 23:22:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/12/31/why-i-went-frick-park-trail-running-in-snowfall-for-the-first-time-in-a-decade/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/asics-gel-flash-ds-snow.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Asics Gel Flash DS in the snow&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Today, New Year&amp;rsquo;s Eve, I went for my last &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/running/&#34;&gt;run&lt;/a&gt; of 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was also my first run (as far as I can remember) in about two months, because of the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/28/meditations-on-climbing-the-36-floors-of-the-pitt-cathedral-of-learning/&#34;&gt;total destruction of my exercise routine in the last months of the year&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was also my first real winter run in probably three years, since at some point I had gotten soft and stopped running in winter, despite a failed attempt &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/01/02/new-experiment-for-a-new-year-winter-running-in-vibram-fivefingers-shoes/&#34;&gt;just a year ago&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, this was also my first trail run in snow in probably a decade. At some point, I had decided that it was too unsafe or uncomfortable to run in the trails in winter when there was snow, mainly because of ice concerns, and when I was running in winter at all, I would choose the roads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So why the sudden change?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;i-need-to-run&#34;&gt;I need to run&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like running, but I haven&amp;rsquo;t been doing it in the winter. So I decided that I was going to take it up again. More specifically, when I&amp;rsquo;m on a full, consistent exercise schedule, I like to alternate running with strength training. Today was a &amp;ldquo;running&amp;rdquo; day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;shoes&#34;&gt;Shoes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have not worn monotoed shoes for running in well over a year now, since having converted to wearing minimalist shoes such as &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/fivefingers/&#34;&gt;Vibram FiveFingers&lt;/a&gt; and Xero Shoes (formerly known as &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/invisible-shoes/&#34;&gt;Invisible Shoes&lt;/a&gt; for all outdoor activities in sufficiently warm weather.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it&amp;rsquo;s just not practical wearing FiveFingers, even with socks, when it&amp;rsquo;s freezing outside. So I went down to the basement to look at my old monotoed running shoes to find something to wear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found a pair of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.roadrunnersports.com/rrs/products/ASC754/&#34;&gt;Asics Gel Flash DS&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ldquo;lightweight trainer&amp;rdquo; shoes that I was wearing some years ago. The shoes still fit, although my feet have expanded every year in the past decade, so I had to loosen the laces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;no-excuses&#34;&gt;No excuses&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remember that last winter I really was intending to do some running outside, but after my discouragement with the FiveFingers experiment, I gave up. &amp;ldquo;Instead&amp;rdquo;, I embarked (successfully, actually) on a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/01/09/starting-the-100-up-exercise-for-running-30-day-challenge/&#34;&gt;100-up running exercise&lt;/a&gt;. I don&amp;rsquo;t regret taking the time to do the 100-up challenge, and in fact, it did wonders for helping me balance out my left and right sides of my body and work on some other things, but in retrospect, I also used it as an excuse not to actually run!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is too easy, when adding something to your life, to use it as an excuse not to do something else. One way to deal with this temptation is to be conscious that given limited time and energy, if you add something new, you should also deliberately remove something old, instead of &amp;ldquo;accidentally&amp;rdquo; losing something old. For example, it is useful to identify a &lt;em&gt;bad habit&lt;/em&gt; to get rid of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my case, of creating new habits for 2013, I am getting rid of bad habits that include too frequently checking email, reading blogs, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-run&#34;&gt;The run&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I headed out the door without really knowing what I was going to do. I decided to check out Frick Park to see if it was runnable. If not, I could always go back out to the roads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that the trails of Frick were not too bad. The snow was packed down, and although patches of ice existed, they were visible and also mostly easily avoided by running to the side on non-icy snow. So I kept going. I decided that instead of being &lt;em&gt;fearful&lt;/em&gt; pre-emptively of bad conditions, I would actually just go and see what the &lt;em&gt;reality&lt;/em&gt; was, and if reality hit me in the face, I always had the option of adapting and backing out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My run followed exactly my &amp;ldquo;usual&amp;rdquo; 5-mile run from home &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/12/i-love-trail-running-in-frick-park/&#34;&gt;down into Fern Hollow and back up&lt;/a&gt;. I saw children sledding and sliding around while their parents encouraged and monitored them (one little boy slid down and almost collided with me as I was running). I saw the dogs running with their owners. I also saw two cross-country skiers heading down toward Fern Hollow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was some snow falling, not very heavily, but enough to keep hitting my glasses and sticking, with icy spots forming, etc. That reminds me that a decade ago when I did have a habit of running all through winter, I wore contact lenses to avoid this problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;2013-plans-for-running&#34;&gt;2013 plans for running&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have no idea how long the trails of Frick Park will be runnable for me, but I don&amp;rsquo;t need to have an &amp;ldquo;idea&amp;rdquo;: I can just continue to go and then back out if I need to. In the past in winter, I would run on Beechwood Boulevard and then into Homewood Cemetery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To encourage myself to keep up my running habit, I&amp;rsquo;ve decided to plan on a race schedule for 2013. 2006 was the last year in which I had a semblance of race schedule: I ran in nine races that year. In 2013, I would like to start running in races by late February, if weather permits, and definitely do some in March and onward. I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t expect to run fast in my first races, but possibly by late March I could be starting to get in good shape for the spring/summer season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went for a run because I hadn&amp;rsquo;t done that in months, and I chose to do something different in order to get over my excuses of the past for shutting down or constraining my running options. I&amp;rsquo;m excited to be back, and hope to see some of my running buddies at races next year!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2003-03-03&#34;&gt;(Update of 2003-03-03)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had some setbacks in running, and ended up not running any races by late February, but did end up deciding in late January, totally unexpected, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/30/why-and-how-i-am-going-to-run-the-2013-pittsburgh-marathon/&#34;&gt;to run the Pittsburgh Marathon&lt;/a&gt;, in order to give myself even more motivation to continue running, then ran in a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/03/my-first-steel-city-road-runners-winter-5k-race/&#34;&gt;5K&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2003-03-30&#34;&gt;(Update of 2003-03-30)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In late March, I ran &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/30/report-on-just-a-short-run-my-first-half-marathon-in-nine-years/&#34;&gt;my first half marathon in nine years&lt;/a&gt; and enjoyed the experience.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New experiment for a new year: winter running in Vibram FiveFingers shoes</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/01/02/new-experiment-for-a-new-year-winter-running-in-vibram-fivefingers-shoes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jan 2012 21:37:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/01/02/new-experiment-for-a-new-year-winter-running-in-vibram-fivefingers-shoes/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I first started wearing &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/fivefingers/&#34;&gt;Vibram FiveFingers&lt;/a&gt; minimalist shoes in October of 2009, but every year, I have not worn them in the winter months when the temperature drops below freezing and there is snow or ice on the ground (January, February).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Somehow, today as I saw a bit of snow fall outside (with very little accumulation), I decided to do a short run (less than two miles) in my Bikila LS shoes while returning some items to the local library, to get a taste of whether it is practical to try regular winter running in these shoes, as the temperature drops and more snow falls.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/vibram-fivefingers-winter-new-year-2012.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin wearing Vibram FiveFingers Bikila LS with snow on the ground&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Last year, sometime in early spring, I ran in regular mono-toed running shoes for the last time in my life. Every &amp;ldquo;normal&amp;rdquo; running shoe I have ever used (and I have worn probably two dozen different models in the past decade) had caused me some kind of disappointment. Switching completely to Vibram FiveFingers shoes had solved all my problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been fearful, however, of winter running in FiveFingers. Would my feet freeze? How would I handle cold water? Snow? Ice?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I decided that the only way to answer the questions would be to go out there and start experimenting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I chose the Bikila LS because of the three models of FiveFingers I have (Bikila LS, KSO, KSO Trek), it is the most padded, least minimalist shoe. In fact, I wish it were more minimalist, because in the summer, my feet get so hot and sweaty (the ventilation is poor) that I get blisters if I run very fast or long. I speculated that these limitations might be virtues in colder conditions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On my run today, I had to watch my footing because there were invisible icy spots on the roads. I am unsure of the traction of the Bikila LS shoes in case of ice, I must admit. However, my feet did not feel particularly uncomfortable. To be sure, it was a very short run, and the temperature of 29F was not very low.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I returned home and took off my shoes, I noticed that my feet were very cold. I&amp;rsquo;m not sure whether to worry about that. I suspect that on longer runs with lower temperatures, I might have something to worry about, but I have to do more experiments. One option I have is to wear &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.injinji.com/&#34;&gt;Injinji&lt;/a&gt; toe socks, of which I have a couple pairs. I don&amp;rsquo;t ordinarily wear these socks because they somewhat get in the way and bunch up when I wear them with FiveFingers shoes, but for winter they might be a lesser evil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, for traction, I might want to try running in my KSO Trek, although I have tried to save those just for trail running and hiking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-about-mono-toed-shoes&#34;&gt;How about mono-toed shoes?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even so, it is possible that I will end up investigating a mono-toed minimalist shoe to keep my toes warm. I still don&amp;rsquo;t own a pair, although I have tried on some New Balance Minimus and Merrell Glove models. I did not like the feel of any of them, although I have not yet encountered the newer &lt;a href=&#34;http://barefootrunninguniversity.com/2011/12/06/new-balance-minimus-zero-road-review/&#34;&gt;New Balance Minimus Zero&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.irunfar.com/2011/12/new-balance-minimus-trail-zero-and-road-zero-review.html&#34;&gt;shoes&lt;/a&gt; (to come out in February 2012) that might work better for me than the original Minimus line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2013-01-17&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-01-17)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/17/winter-running-in-vibram-fivefingers-shoes-revisited/&#34;&gt;A year later&lt;/a&gt;, I reported on restarting winter running in FiveFingers under milder conditions (so far).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>