<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Pittsburgh Symphony Orchestra on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/pittsburgh-symphony-orchestra/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Pittsburgh Symphony Orchestra on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/pittsburgh-symphony-orchestra/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>The one thing I remember Lorin Maazel for</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/07/13/the-one-thing-i-remember-lorin-maazel-for/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Jul 2014 19:36:07 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/07/13/the-one-thing-i-remember-lorin-maazel-for/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;RIP, &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lorin_Maazel&#34;&gt;Lorin Maazel&lt;/a&gt;. A music conductor of fame and longevity has died (at age 84), generating no shortage of obituaries, such as &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2014/07/14/arts/music/lorin-maazel-brilliant-intense-and-enigmatic-conductor-dies-at-84.html&#34;&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Very often famous people die without my really having known much about them, and of course, this case was no exception. But this post isn&amp;rsquo;t about what I didn&amp;rsquo;t know, but what I do know, and &lt;em&gt;remember&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-ring-without-words&#34;&gt;The &amp;ldquo;Ring&amp;rdquo; Without Words&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lorin Maazel may have had a long and illustrious career, but actually, I don&amp;rsquo;t believe I have listened to a single of his recordings (I never saw him in performance) other than one, his &amp;ldquo;Ring Without Words&amp;rdquo; purely orchestral arrangement of Richard Wagner&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Der_Ring_des_Nibelungen&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Ring&amp;rdquo; cycle of operas&lt;/a&gt; that fits in a CD-length 75-minute &amp;ldquo;summary&amp;rdquo; of the epic operatic cycle (which takes more like 17 hours for a complete performance, spread out over four separate operas).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So he touched my life in a single, unusual, but quite &lt;em&gt;positive&lt;/em&gt; way. Ironically, the example obituary I mentioned does not even mention this work of Maazel&amp;rsquo;s. This illustrates that obituaries hardly tell the whole story of the contributions of someone to people&amp;rsquo;s lives. They may tell what is most prestigious or most scandalous, but may miss interesting quirky projects that have less measurable impact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-story&#34;&gt;My story&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://ecx.images-amazon.com/images/I/51lK9-us16L._SY300_.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;The Ring Without Words&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In my senior year of college, I came across a CD in the campus library on the Telarc label of Maazel&amp;rsquo;s recording of the &amp;ldquo;Ring Without Words&amp;rdquo;. At the time, I knew fairly little about Richard Wagner or his music, but I was intrigued by the concept, since I was &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; an opera fan, and didn&amp;rsquo;t mind trying out what some immediately criticized as a gimmicky &amp;ldquo;Reader&amp;rsquo;s Digest&amp;rdquo; concept by Maazel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I very much enjoyed the recording and listened to clips here and there without the &amp;ldquo;guilt&amp;rdquo; or confusion of choosing and listening to selected portions of recordings of the actual original operas. Basically, I appreciated Maazel&amp;rsquo;s role as a curator and summarizer that brought in curious new listeners like me. I still believe there is a role for &amp;ldquo;popularizers&amp;rdquo; of &amp;ldquo;classical music&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I just looked on YouTube and found this very short clip of a performance by Maazel of the &amp;ldquo;Ring Without Words&amp;rdquo;, so you can check it out to get an idea of how it works:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/h9ObRSy3D1E&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;authorial-intent&#34;&gt;Authorial intent&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I mentioned last year in &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/05/22/reflections-on-richard-wagners-200th-birthday/&#34;&gt;my post for Wagner&amp;rsquo;s 200th birthday&lt;/a&gt; that I had, before encountering Maazel&amp;rsquo;s CD, tried to watch the Metropolitan Opera&amp;rsquo;s four-evening TV broadcast in the summer of the &amp;ldquo;Ring&amp;rdquo; cycle and found it hard going. My overall philosophy was, and is, that &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/05/24/why-i-will-always-pronounce-gif-like-gift-and-not-like-jif/&#34;&gt;authorial intent is overrated&lt;/a&gt;. Fact is, if we were really serious about authorial intent, Wagner actually originally &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parsifal#The_ban_on_Parsifal_outside_Bayreuth&#34;&gt;forbade his opera &amp;ldquo;Parsifal&amp;rdquo; from being performed anywhere except in Bayreuth&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not saying we shouldn&amp;rsquo;t respect to one degree or other a composer&amp;rsquo;s original setting or wishes. Actually, I&amp;rsquo;m probably more respectful than most other people, because of my involvement with early music! I&amp;rsquo;m just saying that alternative arrangements and excerpts are always possible, and as long as they do not misrepresent themselves, I have no problem with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;pittsburgh&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might expect me to say something how Maazel turned the Pittsburgh Symphony Orchestra into a world-class orchestra, but actually, I moved to Pittsburgh in 1997 after Maazel had just left, so when I started attending PSO concerts, it was &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/06/08/heinz-hall-memories-at-the-pittsburgh-symphony-being-shocked-out-of-my-mind-upon-experiencing-prokofievs-second-piano-concerto-for-the-first-time/&#34;&gt;under Mariss Jansons&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the &lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.pittsburghsymphony.org/2014/07/statement-on-the-death-of-former-pittsburgh-symphony-orchestra-music-director-lorin-maazel/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Symphony Orchestra&amp;rsquo;s official statement on the passing of Lorin Maazel&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever else Lorin Maazel may have done in his life, one thing he did was bring Wagner to people like me, through his &amp;ldquo;Ring Without Words&amp;rdquo;. I am grateful he carried out this project. Also, more indirectly, he shaped the Pittsburgh Symphony Orchestra into the world-class orchestra it was by the time I moved to Pittsburgh, so I benefited from something he did that I never personally saw.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Copland&#39;s Appalachian Spring danced by the orchestra musicians: confronting my memories of boredom four years ago</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/05/28/coplands-appalachian-spring-danced-by-the-orchestra-musicians-confronting-my-memories-of-boredom-four-years-ago/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2014 22:23:26 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/05/28/coplands-appalachian-spring-danced-by-the-orchestra-musicians-confronting-my-memories-of-boredom-four-years-ago/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I follow Greg Sandow&amp;rsquo;s blog on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.artsjournal.com/sandow/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;future of classical music&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. He posted an &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.artsjournal.com/sandow/2014/05/essential-video.html&#34;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; that got me thinking: he was all excited about an unorthodox performance of Aaron Copland&amp;rsquo;s half-hour-long &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Appalachian_Spring&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Appalachian Spring&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; by the University of Maryland Symphony Orchestra in which the students of the orchestra actually moved around and danced as well as played their instruments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a confession to make: back almost four years ago, in November 2010, I went to a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cmu.edu/news/archive/2010/November/nov15_cmunightwithpso.shtml&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Carnegie Mellon Night at the Symphony&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; in which &amp;ldquo;Appalachian Spring&amp;rdquo; was on the program. &lt;strong&gt;I got very bored during the piece.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing to remember is that the orchestra suite was actually arranged by Copland from his original piece that was an actual ballet for Martha Graham! So it&amp;rsquo;s actually kind of unnatural to experience this music &amp;ldquo;purely&amp;rdquo; as music. To me the suite is rather long and redundant without some kind of &amp;ldquo;story&amp;rdquo; to go along with it. So I watched the video of the orchestra-danced performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was definitely more interesting seeing action. At the same time, I got bored eventually anyway, after about 15 minutes. But I lasted longer with the physical action. However, I was also distracted by thoughts of how difficult it must have been for the orchestra to pull this off. I mean, marching band is one thing, but this is an orchestra and there was a ton of choreography and it&amp;rsquo;s not just marching.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s interesting that a commenter on Sandow&amp;rsquo;s blog criticized the
effort, writing: &lt;em&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s nicely done, I suppose, if you must do this
sort of thing. But when I go to an orchestral concert, I&amp;rsquo;m there for
the music, not for this sort of thing. To me, this doesn&amp;rsquo;t tell the
audience &amp;ldquo;this music is worth your time and attention,&amp;rdquo; it tells them
&amp;ldquo;we have so little faith that you’ll enjoy the music that we feel
compelled to trick it out with distractions.&amp;rdquo; I used to sing in a
chorus that was fond of &amp;ldquo;chorusography,&amp;rdquo; and it annoyed me as a
performer, too.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What do you think? Do you like this idea or does it annoy you?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Judge for yourself:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/jGSctM_8K_E&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Chamber music concert at CMU featured Bach&#39;s Goldberg Variations arranged for string trio</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/11/19/chamber-music-concert-at-cmu-featured-bachs-goldberg-variations-arranged-for-string-trio/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Nov 2013 23:04:37 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/11/19/chamber-music-concert-at-cmu-featured-bachs-goldberg-variations-arranged-for-string-trio/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.cmu.edu/news/stories/archives/2013/november/images/chamber-recital_400x340.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;David Harding, Noah Bendix-Balgley, Lorna McGhee, Amit Peled&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I attended a special &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cmu.edu/news/stories/archives/2013/november/nov8_chambermusic.html&#34;&gt;chamber music concert at CMU&lt;/a&gt; that featured some truly excellent musicians.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-musicians&#34;&gt;The musicians&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was particularly interested in seeing &lt;a href=&#34;http://trioverlaine.com/bios/lorna-mcghee/&#34;&gt;Lorna McGhee&lt;/a&gt;, the current principal flute of the Pittsburgh Symphony Orchestra, and violinist &lt;a href=&#34;http://noahbendixbalgley.com/&#34;&gt;Noah Bendix-Balgley&lt;/a&gt;, the concertmaster, both of whom are relatively recent additions to the orchestra. The other two musicians, also fantastic, were violist and CMU professor &lt;a href=&#34;http://trioverlaine.com/bios/david-harding/&#34;&gt;David Harding&lt;/a&gt; and cellist &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amitpeled.com/&#34;&gt;Amit Peled&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;mozart-s-flute-quartet-no-1-in-d-major&#34;&gt;Mozart&amp;rsquo;s flute quartet no. 1 in D major&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lorna McGhee played in the first part of the program, which was Mozart&amp;rsquo;s first flute quartet. I was very curious how she would approach the work, because I&amp;rsquo;m very picky nowadays about the performance of music from the 18th century or earlier, which I far prefer to be both on period instruments and in period style. The typical &amp;ldquo;modern&amp;rdquo; performance I can no longer enjoy, because of stylistic anachronisms that in my mind invalidate the beauty and freshness of early music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed the quartet&amp;rsquo;s performance of the Mozart. The playing was crisp, lively, and transparent. There was little to quibble with in Lorna McGhee&amp;rsquo;s performance: she played with verve, sensitivity, and clarity. In some phrases she held a legato longer than I would like, but overall I quite liked the performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;bach-s-goldberg-variations-arranged-for-string-trio-by-dmitry-sitkovetsky&#34;&gt;Bach&amp;rsquo;s Goldberg Variations arranged for string trio by Dmitry Sitkovetsky&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bulk of the program was devoted to a performance by the string trio of the entire Goldberg Variations by Bach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past quarter century, I&amp;rsquo;ve listened to countless performances of the Goldberg Variations on all kinds of keyboard instrument, including harpsichord, fortepiano, and modern piano, but until tonight, I hadn&amp;rsquo;t bothered listening to Sitkovetsky&amp;rsquo;s arrangement for string trio that came out several years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought it worked out pretty well tonight, with the three string players working really hard to create dynamism and contrast along with unity in this monumental work. I couldn&amp;rsquo;t help but think that it&amp;rsquo;s actually harder to pull off as a trio than as a solo keyboard piece. What was particularly interesting was visually seeing and hearing (in the different tonal qualities) all the different voices in the music. They are there in the original version, of course, but experiencing the spatial separation just made me even more amazed by Bach&amp;rsquo;s creation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I appreciate the time the four musicians took to perform in this chamber music recital free to the public, and thank you, CMU, for bringing them in for these invigorating performances of Mozart and Bach!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Flute master class: becoming a great ensemble player</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/03/25/flute-master-class-becoming-a-great-ensemble-player/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Mar 2013 23:41:31 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/03/25/flute-master-class-becoming-a-great-ensemble-player/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Jennifer Conner, second flute with Pittsburgh Symphony Orchestra, presented a lecture and master class entitled &amp;ldquo;Becoming a Great Ensemble Player and a Valued Colleague in an Orchestra&amp;rdquo; at CMU.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was the second master class I&amp;rsquo;ve attended in my life (the first one being at the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/21/mideast-early-music-workshop-a-life-changing-experience/&#34;&gt;Mideast early music workshop last summer&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I took a lot of notes while observing and reflecting on what she said and demonstrated and what the music students did. It was a very educational experience for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2014-01-16&#34;&gt;(Update of 2014-01-16)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an unfinished post that is one of many in the past two years that lay unfinished because I had originally planned to write a very detailed report but never got around to it. I decided that I might as well release all these unfinished posts rather than leave them completely out of the record.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Heinz Hall Memories: at the Pittsburgh Symphony, being shocked out of my mind upon experiencing Prokofiev&#39;s second piano concerto for the first time; also, a note on human memory</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/06/08/heinz-hall-memories-at-the-pittsburgh-symphony-being-shocked-out-of-my-mind-upon-experiencing-prokofievs-second-piano-concerto-for-the-first-time/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Jun 2012 21:01:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/06/08/heinz-hall-memories-at-the-pittsburgh-symphony-being-shocked-out-of-my-mind-upon-experiencing-prokofievs-second-piano-concerto-for-the-first-time/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Last month, the Pittsburgh Symphony Orchestra on its blog called for people to &lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.pittsburghsymphony.org/2012/05/heinz-hall-memories/&#34;&gt;share their Heinz Hall memories for the 40th anniversary celebration&lt;/a&gt;. Upon reading that, two memories immediately came to my mind. I describe one of them here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;prokofiev-s-second-piano-concerto&#34;&gt;Prokofiev&amp;rsquo;s second piano concerto&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was in Heinz Hall for the Pittsburgh Symphony on January 21, 2000. It was a dreary winter day, with snow and poor driving conditions, but I felt compelled to use my ticket and go downtown for the concert.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the program at the concert were &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Piano_Concerto_No._2_(Prokofiev)&#34;&gt;Prokofiev&amp;rsquo;s second piano concerto&lt;/a&gt; and Bruckner&amp;rsquo;s fourth symphony. The Prokofiev was played by Mikhail Rudy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I remember is my jaw dropping while Rudy played the first movement of the Prokofiev concerto. I had never heard this concerto before; I had listened to the first, third, and fifth concertos many times before on cassette tape as well as CD but I had never owned a recording of the second or fourth!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This concerto was really dark and virtuosic, with violent dissonances and runs, quite unlike the more widely known concertos. When the solo cadenza began, I got restless and astounded as the cadenza kept going and going, as though taking up half of the entire first movement. This seemed outrageously long, and the music just got wilder and I thought the piano was taking a real beating, but I was truly fascinated by the perverseness of Prokofiev&amp;rsquo;s conception.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the whole concert ended, I walked out in a daze (in fact, I was so mentally disrupted that I was lucky to make it home alive driving on the parkway under really bad winter conditions).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will always remember that visceral experience with the Prokofiev concerto, and every time I hear it now, I can imagine myself back in Heinz Hall experiencing it for the very first time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;an-example-of-the-fragility-of-memory&#34;&gt;An example of the fragility of memory&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A confession: I had to look up my email archive and my journal to get my story completely correct above, after the first draft that I wrote without consulting them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am always a little suspicious when people tell of their memories from long ago (or even not so long ago), because human memory is not like computer memory. Human memory involves re-creation and simply cannot be trusted without hard evidence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, my immediate &amp;ldquo;memory&amp;rdquo; of the concert I just described, when I was not relying on any external sources, was &lt;em&gt;false&lt;/em&gt; in several ways. I was lucky to be able to locate old email archives and my daily journal from twelve years ago in order to determine what really happened!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-friend-who-wasn-t-there-part-1&#34;&gt;The friend who wasn&amp;rsquo;t there (part 1)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, I was very confident that I had gone to a concert with a particular friend, and that we had looked at each other in amazement during the cadenza. It turns out that I had not gone to this concert with my friend, and I had driven to it alone! It was easy for me to &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Confabulation&#34;&gt;confabulate&lt;/a&gt; because back in around 1997-1999, I had in fact gone to many PSO concerts in Heinz Hall on Fridays with him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, I did correctly remember discussing my experience with him. It turns out that I reported back to him about the Prokofiev concerto, and we talked about it, and in fact, he lent me a CD of it to listen to as a result.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Note: please read part 2 of &amp;ldquo;the friend who wasn&amp;rsquo;t there&amp;rdquo; below.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-wrong-pianist&#34;&gt;The wrong pianist&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my struggle to remember, I had thought that the pianist was probably &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pittsburghsymphony.org/pghsymph.nsf/bios/yefim+bronfman&#34;&gt;Yefim Bronfman&lt;/a&gt;. I was not actually confident about this, however. I was right not to be confident, because in fact, it was Mikhail Rudy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have an explanation for this mistake. It turns out that the CD I borrowed from my friend was Bronfman playing the concerto, and according to my journal, I listened to this CD on February 4, 2000!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, I did correctly remember seeing Bronfman playing in Heinz Hall. Again, my journal shows that on May 12, 2000, the final concert of the season, Yefim Bronfman played Beethoven under Mariss Jansons, and I was very impressed with the concert:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
I actually stood up to applaud Bronfman and Jansons for the Beethoven and the Stravinsky, something I have never done at a PSO concert.  It was a special concert.  Jansons seemed inspired, possibly because it was the season finale and the place was packed?  I mean, I&#39;m not a Stravinsky fan, but the Stravinsky was just so well played.  The Beethoven was fantastic.  I thought I&#39;d be all jaded from knowing this concerto inside out since first listening to it in 1988, but the performance was amazing.  The whole piece was great, but especially the first movement, in which Bronfman and Jansons and the orchestra were like one mind, the interplay seamless.

One thing about Bronfman:  he had a lot of energy, but seemed kind of percussive or heavy sometimes.  A minor complaint about a pianist who seemed great from the performance I saw.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-correctness-of-memory&#34;&gt;The correctness of memory&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;my-reaction&#34;&gt;My reaction&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My journal entry for the day of the concert included this comment I jotted down into my &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Palm_(PDA)&#34;&gt;Palm PDA&lt;/a&gt; at intermission:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Intermission.  There was an encore by Mikhail Rudy.  The Prokofiev piano concerto no. 2 is the most bizarre piano concerto I&#39;ve ever heard.  Quite perverse.  The clashing harmonies are one thing, but the organization is another.  Long, extended solo passages.  Huge cadenza in the first movement.  Just freakish.  I will have to look it up on the Web.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think I fairly accurately remembered my impression of the music that I wrote at the beginning of this post before I consulted my journal entry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;my-friend-who-was-there-part-2&#34;&gt;My friend who was there (part 2)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After writing a draft of this blog post, I told my friend about my false memory, but he replied that he too remembers the concert!! He just doesn&amp;rsquo;t remember going to it with me. This is quite possible. By 2000, because of other social circles and logistics, we did not always go to the concerts together, even if we both did end up there, sitting in different places.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He remembers this concert being eye-opening also, in that although he had listened to the concerto on recordings (as I mentioned, he lent me one shortly after this concert), it had not connected with him deeply until the live concert.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it appears that my memory was partially correct: although we had not sat together at the concert, most likely we chatted during intermission and shared our amazement then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The exercise of trying to get accurate the details of a memorable Heinz Hall experience from twelve years ago turned into a fascinating exploration of the malleability of human memory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But even if some details were fuzzy, my falling in love with Prokofiev&amp;rsquo;s wayward second piano concerto remains an eternal truth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;bonus-video&#34;&gt;Bonus video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I&amp;rsquo;ve never seen Yefim Bronfman playing Prokofiev&amp;rsquo;s second piano concerto, but YouTube comes to the rescue. If you want to check out the wild cadenza I mentioned, it occurs between 5:00 and 9:19 in this video:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/CCeo1vyewEg&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2013-11-08&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-11-08)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I happened to see on the PSO blog &lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.pittsburghsymphony.org/2013/11/the-most-amazing-rendition-of-prokofievs-second-piano-concerto/&#34;&gt;a post about someone else&amp;rsquo;s experience with a recent performance of this concerto with the PSO&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>