<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Erin Yanacek on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/erin-yanacek/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Erin Yanacek on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/erin-yanacek/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>A fine trumpet recital by Erin Yanacek</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/11/25/a-fine-trumpet-recital-by-erin-yanacek/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Nov 2013 22:24:39 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/11/25/a-fine-trumpet-recital-by-erin-yanacek/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://static.erinyanacek.com/img/home_page_new_photo_3.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Erin Yanacek&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I attended a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.music.cmu.edu/events/282&#34;&gt;graduate trumpet recital&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&#34;http://erinyanacek.com/&#34;&gt;Erin Yanacek&lt;/a&gt;, in which she performed works of Robert Planel, Camille Saint-Saens, George Enescu, Franz Joseph Haydn, and Herbert L. Clarke.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2014-07-28&#34;&gt;(Update of 2014-07-28)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Erin has posted a video of the Herbert L. Clarke work from her recital:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/oBV4u360Ats&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-little-about-erin&#34;&gt;A little about Erin&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I first encountered Erin, without yet knowing who she was, from &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/04/29/attending-my-first-cmu-baroque-ensemble-concert/&#34;&gt;attending a CMU Baroque Ensemble Concert for the first time over a year ago&lt;/a&gt;. Then, some months later, without knowing the name or connecting it with anyone I had seen before, I saw a heartfelt article she wrote for a new blog on the arts, &lt;a href=&#34;http://musedialogue.org/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Muse Dialogue&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://musedialogue.org/2013/02/11/seeking-the-love-of-music-that-i-once-felt/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Seeking the love of music that I once felt&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. Then I bumped into her at a party Abby and I attended, and I finally connected the dots. It also turned out that she is a serious runner, and we&amp;rsquo;ve accidentally crossed paths while both running in the trails of Frick Park. And she&amp;rsquo;s also a cyclist and has done the wildly difficult Pittsburgh &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dannychew.com/dd_11.html&#34;&gt;Dirty Dozen&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, if you&amp;rsquo;re a fan of Pittsburgh&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rivercitybrass.org/&#34;&gt;River City Brass&lt;/a&gt;, you may have seen her recently, as she is now a cornet player there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;it-s-about-the-music&#34;&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s about the music&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I rather enjoy Erin&amp;rsquo;s playing. She&amp;rsquo;s a versatile and sensitive musician, adept at different styles and different moods, exploring and showcasing what the trumpet can express. Whether it&amp;rsquo;s pure brilliance, classical elegance, tender and lyrical romanticism, or jazzy/bluesy attitude and rhythm, I&amp;rsquo;m pretty impressed by the range of what Erin can do using a trumpet to communicate. Erin&amp;rsquo;s program was a tasty sampler of trumpet delight. I especially like the way she shapes phrases, really making the instrument sing and speak.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pittsburgh is blessed to have Erin as part of the local community of excellent musicians, and I hope to continue seeing her perform when I can! Check her out.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Attending my first CMU Baroque Ensemble concert: enjoying Bach&#39;s Brandenburg 2</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/04/29/attending-my-first-cmu-baroque-ensemble-concert/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Apr 2012 23:44:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/04/29/attending-my-first-cmu-baroque-ensemble-concert/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I attended a free concert of the CMU Baroque Ensemble for the very first time!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The CMU Baroque Ensemble under &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.stephenschultz.net/&#34;&gt;Stephen Schultz&lt;/a&gt; has been around for over a decade, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.stephenschultz.net/teaching.html&#34;&gt;starting in 2002&lt;/a&gt;, but I had never attended one of their concerts, because basically, until I started playing recorder last year, I had very little interest in Baroque music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But now I&amp;rsquo;m really immersing myself in Baroque music, so I decided to check out the student ensemble. Also, I&amp;rsquo;d never seen Stephen Schultz in action before outside the CMU lecture hall (I took his &amp;ldquo;Survey of Western Musical History&amp;rdquo; in 2006) and his CD recordings of Baroque flute music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The students played modern instruments, but Schultz clearly aimed to evoke a crisp, Baroque style of play from the ensemble. He is an enthusiastic and clear conductor and it is enjoyable watching him direct this music he clearly loves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;bach-s-brandenburg-2&#34;&gt;Bach&amp;rsquo;s Brandenburg 2&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Various pieces were performed in this concert, but the highlight for me was Bach&amp;rsquo;s Brandenburg concerto no. 2, which I have recently come to love. I had ignored the Brandenburg concertos for much of my life, but when I started playing recorder last year, I found that one of the method books I used, a two-volume method by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.aswltd.com/adultmet.htm#begin&#34;&gt;Mario Duschenes&lt;/a&gt;, ends with challenging solo recorder parts for the Brandenburg concerto no. 2 and no. 4, and I aspired to be able to play these, and listened to some recordings I found of them, and truly fell in love with the music! (Note: the CMU Baroque Ensemble did not use recorder, but flute, in the Brandenburg 2.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was thrilling for me to watch the Brandenburg 2 performed live, because of the prominent &lt;a href=&#34;http://abel.hive.no/trumpet/bach/brandenburg/&#34;&gt;high trumpet part&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;d never seen this in action before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, here&amp;rsquo;s a performance of the first movement of the Brandenburg 2, on historical instruments (rather than the modern instruments played in the CMU Baroque Ensemble concert). Check out the recorder and trumpet!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/EC1E4_imS0A&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed the concert and will probably continue to attend more by the CMU Baroque Ensemble, to continue my Baroque &amp;ldquo;education&amp;rdquo;. It is, of course, not a professional ensemble, but it is great to see CMU students dedicated to performing Baroque music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-11-25&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-11-25)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fine trumpet player in this concert was &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/11/25/a-fine-trumpet-recital-by-erin-yanacek&#34;&gt;Erin Yanacek&lt;/a&gt;, whom I&amp;rsquo;d later coincidentally encounter through her writings and from meeting her by accident.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>