<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Mayor on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/mayor/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Mayor on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/mayor/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Voting in the face of election apathy</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/05/21/voting-in-the-face-of-election-apathy/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 May 2013 19:17:44 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/05/21/voting-in-the-face-of-election-apathy/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/voter-receipt-primary-2013.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;My voter receipt, May 2013&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Those of you who follow my blog know that I have been conflicted about voting, but go and do it anyway, &lt;em&gt;most of the time&lt;/em&gt;, e.g., &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/08/i-dont-know-if-i-should-vote-but-i-did/&#34;&gt;in November 2011 for the municipal election&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/11/06/i-decided-to-resign-myself-to-continue-voting/&#34;&gt;in November 2012 for the general election&lt;/a&gt;, when I felt there were some politicians very important to &lt;em&gt;vote against&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;apathy-or-ignorance&#34;&gt;Apathy or ignorance?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In April 2012&amp;rsquo;s general primary, however, I was sufficiently apathetic that I didn&amp;rsquo;t bother voting, although Abby did. For that election, it seemed to me that the winners were all going to be obvious no matter what I did, and there were no close races where I really cared about who won. I feel that in the absence of an informed opinion, the only rational and moral thing to do is to stay out. It is &lt;em&gt;unfashionable&lt;/em&gt; in our society to admit &lt;a href=&#34;http://opinionator.blogs.nytimes.com/2013/04/29/the-power-of-i-dont-know/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;I don&amp;rsquo;t know&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, but if I truly don&amp;rsquo;t know, then I see no point in participating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Primary_election&#34;&gt;Primary elections&lt;/a&gt; are particularly problematic for me, because I simply oppose the concept and also resent being forced to register for one of the two major American political parties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;may-2013-municipal-primary-choosing-mayor&#34;&gt;May 2013 municipal primary: choosing mayor!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this year&amp;rsquo;s Democratic primary is &lt;em&gt;critical&lt;/em&gt;, because it will basically determine who becomes the next &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pittsburgh_mayoral_election,_2013&#34;&gt;mayor of Pittsburgh&lt;/a&gt;, given that a Democrat will win in the general election in November. And since &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Luke_Ravenstahl&#34;&gt;Luke Ravenstahl&lt;/a&gt; decided to step down, there is a possibility of &lt;em&gt;real change&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I was pretty excited to vote today to make a difference (I hope). This will be the first time I have voted for a &lt;a href=&#34;http://triblive.com/politics/politicalheadlines/4052165-74/percent-mayor-turnout&#34;&gt;mayoral candidate in a primary&lt;/a&gt; in my 15 years as a Pittsburgh resident. For once there may be a crack in the rusty Democratic political machine here?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.post-gazette.com/stories/local/neighborhoods-city/polls-open-for-primary-election-688496/&#34;&gt;Voter turnout today has been crazy low&lt;/a&gt;. There was no line whatsoever when I went to vote or when Abby went. I&amp;rsquo;ve never participated in an election, I think, with such low turnout.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Maybe this low turnout will end up being a good thing&lt;/em&gt;. If people choose not to vote because they don&amp;rsquo;t have informed opinions, then it means that I and the surprisingly large number of people I know who also voted for the same guy I did will &lt;em&gt;win&lt;/em&gt;! (That said, it&amp;rsquo;s sad if &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pittsburghmagazine.com/Best-of-the-Burgh-Blogs/Pitt-Girl/June-2013/Why-You-Must-Vote-in-Pittsburghs-Mayoral-Election/&#34;&gt;only 2 percent of us decide the mayor&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;media-coverage&#34;&gt;Media coverage&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I avoided &lt;em&gt;most&lt;/em&gt; media coverage of the election (hard to avoid everything completely, admittedly) until I had already voted. (Yes, that includes ignoring the basically meaningless &amp;ldquo;endorsements&amp;rdquo; of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.post-gazette.com/&#34;&gt;Post-Gazette&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://triblive.com/&#34;&gt;Tribune-Review&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I enjoyed reading &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pghcitypaper.com/Blogh/archives/2013/05/21/election-day-thoughts&#34;&gt;this little look at what&amp;rsquo;s been going on with the mayoral race&lt;/a&gt;. And tomorrow I am back to ignoring the news.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, I had to recycle probably 30 or so paper flyers during election season. What a waste. And summarily delete dozens of robocalls on the answering machine. Note to everyone who sent me junk or left junk messages on my answering machine: &lt;em&gt;I did not read a single thing you sent, or listen to a single word you spoke; your junk only made me angry and at least partly less likely to vote for you, if I caught your name and remembered it&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;Pathetic.&lt;/strong&gt; I realize this crap works on some people, but I&amp;rsquo;m afraid it doesn&amp;rsquo;t work on me: I&amp;rsquo;m not going to believe that your opponent eats children for breakfast, no matter what large fonts you use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a moment of relief from apathy and cynicism about politics, I eagerly voted today. I hope I&amp;rsquo;ll get to see whether I was justified.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>