<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Spibelt on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/spibelt/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Spibelt on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/spibelt/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Reflections on my slowest Run Around the Square 5K in 13 years</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/08/24/reflections-on-my-slowest-run-around-the-square-5k-in-13-years/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Aug 2013 12:45:47 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/08/24/reflections-on-my-slowest-run-around-the-square-5k-in-13-years/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This year was the ninth time I ran in the annual &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.runaroundthesquare.com/&#34;&gt;Run Around The Square 5K race&lt;/a&gt;, and Abby&amp;rsquo;s third year in a row. The conditions were great: cool and dry, in contrast to the usual hot and humid conditions at this time of year. (Last year I reported on &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/08/25/my-eighth-time-doing-run-around-the-square-5k/&#34;&gt;my eighth running of the race&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both Abby and I ran this race rather slowly, but were happy and enjoyed the day. Here&amp;rsquo;s why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;both-of-us-coming-back-from-setbacks&#34;&gt;Both of us coming back from setbacks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing to note is that both Abby and I have been recovering from setbacks this year, as I reported two weeks ago after I ran the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/08/09/getting-up-when-reality-punches-you-in-the-face-running-the-second-liberty-mile-in-pittsburgh/&#34;&gt;second GNC Live Well Liberty Mile&lt;/a&gt; 18 seconds slower than last year. That race had me vowing to get back on track, and the very next day I did &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/08/10/emerging-from-my-three-months-of-illness-self-pitying-and-self-loathing/&#34;&gt;begin getting back on track&lt;/a&gt;. The road back to a regular exercise routine has not been easy in the past two weeks, but I have very gradually ramping up on running as well as minimal strength training every single day since then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, I ran the Run Around The Square 5K in 24:35.6 and was pretty to have recovered from several years of decline in fitness and self-care, by running my best time since 2006. For this year, I wrote, &amp;ldquo;I don&amp;rsquo;t know what goal to set for next year. I suppose I could set a goal of getting yet faster, breaking 24:15. That sounds reasonable to me. Going back down to 24:00 may even be possible. It&amp;rsquo;s too early right now to tell. But one thing is for sure: I have no intention of slowing down from this year to next.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, I did not set a firm enough goal. I have learned the hard way that if you don&amp;rsquo;t make a commitment (and then follow up with the discipline and sacrifices required to achieve it), then even in the absence of accidents, a maybe-goal is worthless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year, I went into the 5K race so untrained (two weeks of slowly ramping up before the race is not enough for any training benefits to kick in) that I basically knew that I was going to be super slow. I figured that since I lost 18 seconds in the mile, I would be happy if I lost only one minute in a 3K. So that was my expectation: finish around 25:36 this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;before-the-race&#34;&gt;Before the race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided that this was the race in which I debut my new orange running singlet, to replace my over-decade use of a blue singlet that Abby has gotten very annoyed with:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-around-the-square-2013/franklin-orange.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin wearing orange singlet&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Also, note that since I bought a SPIbelt earlier this year, I now always run races wearing a SPIbelt to carry my phone. This is particularly convenient when running a race where you have to park far from the start line and want access to your phone after a race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wore my Vibram FiveFingers KSO Trek shoes again. Since last year&amp;rsquo;s fiasco in which I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/30/running-my-10th-great-race-10k-obscene-but-in-a-good-way/&#34;&gt;injured my left foot from having the straps on my left foot too tight&lt;/a&gt;, I never again put the straps on too tight!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hanging out before the race start in Regent Square:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-around-the-square-2013/before.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Before start&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-around-the-square-2013/franklin-ready.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin ready&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Start line just a few minutes before race start:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-around-the-square-2013/start-line.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Start line&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-race&#34;&gt;The race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(&lt;a href=&#34;http://runhigh.com/2013RESULTS/R082413AA.html&#34;&gt;Race results.&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;different-race-logistics&#34;&gt;Different race logistics&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One very important change to the race, and one I greatly appreciated, was the staggered start. Faster runners were told to line up front and start up first. This is very helpful to control the congestion and confusion that happens in a large race when too many slower people start up front and have to be passed (including unfortunately young children that Abby and I have seen trampled on every year!). In particular, it is really tricky to be passing lots of people once in the trails of Frick Park.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;first-mile&#34;&gt;First mile&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of the ridiculous problems I created for myself by going too fast two weeks ago in the Liberty Mile, I vowed to go out at a reasonable pace in this 5K. I found this easy to do because of the staggered start, which meant that there were fewer people to have to accelerate past throwing off one&amp;rsquo;s own internal speedometer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The usual lot of young and old musicians were playing music along the course. What a great neighborhood tradition!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still get confused seeing the champagne stop near the end of the first mile at the entrance into the trails of Frick Park.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did the first mile in a leisurely 8:15 (compared to 7:18 last year).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;second-mile&#34;&gt;Second mile&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did the second mile in 10:17 (compared to 10:11 last year). I did not feel too bad. I was running a bit conservatively, because my training runs had been so slow and short and tough for me in the past two weeks. I wanted to be in position to run really well the final downhill in the third mile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;third-mile&#34;&gt;Third mile&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I let loose in the third mile. Because I had avoided going pukey in the second mile, I covered it in 7:06, actually a second faster than the 7:07 of last year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of the staggered start, there was not bad congestion during the third mile, and I found it safe to pass people at will.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;final-sprint&#34;&gt;Final sprint&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t have a gut-wrenching final sprint. I wasn&amp;rsquo;t even looking at the clock or my watch. This wasn&amp;rsquo;t one of those races in which I put it all out there on the course. Instead, this was a race where I was grateful to be running at all, and had no expectations other than to finish strong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I finished in 25:38, just a bit longer than a minute over last year&amp;rsquo;s 24:35.6. My &lt;em&gt;slowest&lt;/em&gt; Run Around The Square 5K time &lt;em&gt;in 13 years&lt;/em&gt;. But it was a clean finish, and I was so excited to simply be back and running faster than 26 minutes, at least.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;after-the-race&#34;&gt;After the race&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although I was not pukey, I was certainly breathing hard when I finished.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-around-the-square-2013/franklin-after.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin after the race&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I went off to drink water and start eating some food.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-around-the-square-2013/view.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;View&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;improvement&#34;&gt;Improvement&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I went back to the finish line to wait for Abby to finish. I saw Todd and his wife Gabrielle hanging around. Gabrielle said she took my &amp;ldquo;advice&amp;rdquo; (from last year) to go all out to the point of feeling pukey. I admitted that this time around, I didn&amp;rsquo;t follow my own advice. Gabrielle finished over 5 minutes faster this year than last year!! Todd finished over 8 minutes faster!! It&amp;rsquo;s great to see people in their late 40s improve their fitness so much in a single year. I saw the couple running together a couple of times in Frick Park this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;decline&#34;&gt;Decline&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby finished. She was out of breath and pukey, but I was proud of her for finishing. Because of the tremendous decline in health and fitness she has experienced this year, I was not sure she would actually finish the race.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-around-the-square-2013/abby-finish.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby finishing&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;more-food-and-refreshments&#34;&gt;More food and refreshments&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We lined up to sample more food and recovered. It was a beautiful day to be outside.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-around-the-square-2013/abby-recovered.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-around-the-square-2013/franklin-recovered.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The hot dogs and beer line was particularly long, but we finally reached the tables.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-around-the-square-2013/hot-dogs-beer.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Hot dogs and beer&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;walking-out-of-frick-park-back-to-the-car&#34;&gt;Walking out of Frick Park back to the car&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I couldn&amp;rsquo;t help taking a photo of the sign for beer and champagne that was still up on the trail entrance as we passed by:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-around-the-square-2013/beer-champagne.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Dunning&amp;#39;s beer and champagne stop&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;concern-about-abby&#34;&gt;Concern about Abby&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although I was happy that Abby managed to finish the 5K race, I was very concerned about her overall health and fitness, which have continued to be poor this year since she broke her foot in February. Here are her Run Around The Square 5K times since she started doing it with me:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2011: 37:15&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2012: 36:04&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2013: 39:54&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She was almost 4 minutes slower than last year. She&amp;rsquo;s lost &lt;em&gt;several years of fitness&lt;/em&gt; this year, and came in 105th of 116 in her age group. Again, we are grateful she is walking and running at all, but this has been a very bad year for her, and this impacts not only her own life, but ours more generally. We need to work on getting her back on track.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;goal-for-next-year&#34;&gt;Goal for next year?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right now, my real goal is to simply continue my exercise program and not break it again, and that includes the winter slump I usually enter. Last year, I had a slump in the final months of the year, and then woke up and &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/28/meditations-on-climbing-the-36-floors-of-the-pitt-cathedral-of-learning/&#34;&gt;started exercising again around New Year&lt;/a&gt;, and even signed up for the Pittsburgh Marathon as a way to force myself to stay active in the winter. I believe that if I simply avoid self-caused setbacks, I should be able to return myself to a decent level of fitness. I am &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; going to sign up for the Pittsburgh Marathon again. Almost certainly, however, I will sign up for the Pittsburgh Half Marathon! Last winter, I rather enjoyed &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/30/report-on-just-a-short-run-my-first-half-marathon-in-nine-years/&#34;&gt;training for and running the Just A Short Run half marathon&lt;/a&gt;. I reached good fitness through that, but squandered my fitness through overtraining and injury leading up to the marathon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;races-this-year&#34;&gt;Races this year&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the shorter term, I have two races to run in the coming month: the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/07/running-my-8th-pretty-good-race-5k-dealing-with-disappointment/&#34;&gt;CMU Pretty Good Race 5K&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/30/running-my-10th-great-race-10k-obscene-but-in-a-good-way/&#34;&gt;Great Race 10K&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, I did very poorly in the Pretty Good Race 5K because I was injured and exhausted, running 26:05. This year, I expect to do better than that. I&amp;rsquo;m not going to do the 24:36 of 2011, but given that I easily beat 26 minutes today, I will beat 26 minutes two weeks from now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Great Race 10K last year, I was still in a state of exhaustion and undertraining, so I didn&amp;rsquo;t even pay any attention to time goals, and finished slowly in 48:23. I see no reason why, if I continue improving my fitness in the next month (in contrast to last year&amp;rsquo;s dreadful September), I should not be able to run under 48:00.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;update-of-2013-09-06&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-09-06)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/09/06/was-it-worth-sprinting-to-a-terrible-fall-to-finish-25th-in-the-cmu-pretty-good-race-5k/&#34;&gt;my report on running the Pretty Good Race 5K this year&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Run Around The Square continued to thrive and improve, and I&amp;rsquo;m grateful for both the registration cap (to maintain the quality of the event) as well as the staggered start. And all the sponsors feeding us afterwards!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I were happy to have finished the race, even if we are both less fit now than we have been in years. But I think this is a wake up call for us to get back in shape. For example, I miss the long hikes we used to do last year when we had the stamina to actually do and enjoy them. The example Todd and Gabrielle set as they massively improved their fitness in the past year is inspiring. Abby and I should be able to do this too, if we make it a priority.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2013 Pittsburgh Marathon: my 135th race was the worst I finished, but I did!</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/05/06/2013-pittsburgh-marathon-my-135th-race-was-my-worst-i-finished/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 May 2013 20:23:08 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/05/06/2013-pittsburgh-marathon-my-135th-race-was-my-worst-i-finished/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/runner-of-steel.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin Chen, runner of steel&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/lying-down.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin lying down&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, for my birthday, I ran the Pittsburgh Marathon for the second time. The first time was &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/30/why-and-how-i-am-going-to-run-the-2013-pittsburgh-marathon/&#34;&gt;ten years ago, in 2003&lt;/a&gt;. That was an ordeal in which I had aimed at finishing in 3:30 and in fact run the first half in 1:45, but then faltered badly to struggle to finish in a &lt;a href=&#34;http://runhigh.com/.2003%20Results%20A/R050403AA.html&#34;&gt;chip time of 3:53:25&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My second Pittsburgh Marathon went even worse. I had wanted to finish in 4:00, but instead &lt;a href=&#34;http://results.active.com/events/dicks-sporting-goods-pittsburgh-marathon&#34;&gt;finished in 4:38:21&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was my 135th race in my life, and the worst of them all that I actually finished (I failed to finish one 30K race because of severe illness that should have kept me from going to the start line at all).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s my report on what happened, why, my thankfulness for all the good that came from the experience, and my running plans for the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;coming-back-from-injury-and-burnout&#34;&gt;Coming back from injury and burnout&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it&amp;rsquo;s important to understand that my poor performance did not come from nowhere. I had battled injury and burnout &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/05/04/i-spent-the-past-week-not-knowing-whether-i-could-run-in-the-2013-pittsburgh-marathon-tomorrow/&#34;&gt;for some time&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Logically&lt;/em&gt;, I should not have gone to the start line at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;night-before&#34;&gt;Night before&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got zero sleep the night before the race. Terrible, but my body was probably confused by the carb-loaded diet as well as my insistence on spending the whole day napping because I was so tired. I had felt that I had to do that napping because I was not going to be able to sleep well at night anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;early-morning-on-race-day&#34;&gt;Early morning on race day&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Super early, Abby drove us to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.visitpittsburgh.com/essentials/neighborhoods/north-shore/&#34;&gt;North Shore&lt;/a&gt; to park. Then we napped for a bit before heading to the nearest &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pittsburgh_Light_Rail&#34;&gt;light rail (aka &amp;ldquo;T&amp;rdquo;)&lt;/a&gt; station to wait for a ride downtown:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/go-downtown.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby and I wait for T&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We got downtown finally, I dropped off a bag of post-race flip-flops at Gear Check, time was starting to run out, and I got in line for a Port-a-pottie:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/port-a-potties.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Port-a-potties&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It was 15 minutes before I did what I needed to do. Then I had to quickly head to my corral.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;clothing&#34;&gt;Clothing&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/franklin-before-marathon.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin before marathon&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What I wore:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the &lt;em&gt;same blue singlet&lt;/em&gt; I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/30/why-and-how-i-am-going-to-run-the-2013-pittsburgh-marathon/&#34;&gt;wore in the 2003 Pittsburgh Marathon ten years ago&lt;/a&gt; (my favorite running shirt that I have actually worn for probably at least 70 of my races in over a decade, as well as most of my warm-weather casual runs also!!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Brooks Infiniti Short III that I bought at Elite Runners and Walkers before the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/30/report-on-just-a-short-run-my-first-half-marathon-in-nine-years/&#34;&gt;Just A Short Run half marathon in March&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Luna Sandals (Venado) that I&amp;rsquo;ve been wearing for almost all of my runs in the past month, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/04/13/my-final-16-mile-long-run-before-pittsburgh-marathon-featured-two-radical-experiments/&#34;&gt;maximum distance of 16 miles&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CEP compression calf sleeves, which I had worn just &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/04/20/on-overtraining-and-feeling-injured-two-weeks-before-the-pittsburgh-marathon/&#34;&gt;one other time&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/22/paradox-i-will-observe-the-national-day-of-unplugging-but-just-bought-my-first-smartphone-this-week/&#34;&gt;phone&lt;/a&gt;, in a SPIbelt.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;on my back, I pinned a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/04/20/on-overtraining-and-feeling-injured-two-weeks-before-the-pittsburgh-marathon/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;We are all Boston Marathoners at heart&amp;rdquo; bib&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a long-sleeve T-shirt on top of my singlet, since it was cold (under 50 degrees F?) before the race; the plan was to discard this T-shirt before the race (and hope that people collect it and find a good home for it!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;entering-the-corral&#34;&gt;Entering the corral&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the second race in my life in which I have carried a phone. I planned to use it only in case of emergency, and in order to meet up with Abby afterwards, but as you can see, while I had a chance, I took some photos also.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/corral-c.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Corral C&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I was assigned to corral C because of my estimated finish time of 4:00 that I had written down when signing up for the marathon months ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This was my first mistake.&lt;/em&gt; Given my comeback from injury and inactivity, the truly logical thing for me to have done was to set a very conservative goal of simply finishing the marathon without terrible suffering. Given that I ended up finishing in 4:38, I might as well have moved back into another corral and &lt;em&gt;planned&lt;/em&gt; to finish in the 4:20-4:30 range, in which case I bet I would have done that with minimal pain and suffering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the future, I resolve to face the facts on the ground in any event as strenuous as a marathon. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t make any sense what I did, especially given that I was perfectly smart when &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/30/report-on-just-a-short-run-my-first-half-marathon-in-nine-years/&#34;&gt;in March I did my first half marathon in nine years and ran it conservatively and had a great experience&lt;/a&gt;! I am capable of logical reasoning and have actually executed it in the past. But apparently the marathon puts me into a hyper-emotional frame of mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;pace&#34;&gt;Pace?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, I had chosen not to sign up to follow an &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pittsburghmarathon.com/pace-team&#34;&gt;official pacer&lt;/a&gt;, because on all my long training runs, I had found my own pace by feel, and done well ignoring pacers. My plan was simply to go slow and then get faster. I did look around for pace signs. I only saw one from where I was standing: a sign near the front of the corral for finishing in 3:50. I looked back and saw no other signs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This was my second mistake.&lt;/em&gt; Given that I had not done any serious running for ten days, with my longest run being only two miles, and my last &amp;ldquo;long&amp;rdquo; run was an eleven-mile run fifteen days ago, I should have realized that whatever &amp;ldquo;feel&amp;rdquo; I had for pace was gone, and I should have moved back in the corral till I found a 4:00-finishing pacer, at least (but as mentioned earlier, what I should have done was move into a slower corral altogether and then found a suitable pacer there).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;race-start&#34;&gt;Race start&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a moment of silence for Boston.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Star-Spangled Banner, then the waves began. A photo as mine was approaching the start line, around 7:05 AM:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/start-line.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;About to reach the start line&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Then we went.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;wrong-pace&#34;&gt;Wrong pace&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I honestly thought I was going slow. I was hardly breathing at all. I was going so &amp;ldquo;slow&amp;rdquo; that I pulled out my phone to take some photos. But then I got very confused, because the 3:50 pacer was still in my sight after many minutes:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/early.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Early in the marathon&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I could not process this information. Part of me wanted to slow down, but I felt like I was barely running. Part of me believed that the pacer must be slow, but come on, these pacers are supposed to be reliable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I &lt;em&gt;made the mistake&lt;/em&gt; of not trusting the pacer. It sounds crazy, but I really felt like I was going too slow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;slowing-down&#34;&gt;Slowing down?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point, I lost sight of the pacer, so I felt reassured that I must have slowed down properly. Here&amp;rsquo;s another problem: I did not keep track of my mile splits because the mass of people made it hard for me to actually reliably spot any mile markers on the course; I don&amp;rsquo;t even know how many actually existed.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/bridge.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Crossing bridge&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I even took a photo of myself 40 minutes into the marathon feeling fine.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/franklin-early.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There were spectators on bridges, some of them positioned seemingly precariously.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/spectators-on-bridges.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Spectators on bridge&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At some point I realized that I could see the 3:50 pacer up ahead. I got worried. It was unlikely that I was magically super-fit now. But I didn&amp;rsquo;t feel like slowing down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point I must have started slowing down, because eventually I saw a 3:55 pacer pass me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still, it appears from the alert system that I signed up for (to notify my parents by email, and Abby by text message, and my Facebook friends and Twitter followers), that I did the first 10K (6.2 miles) in 55:29, meaning an average pace of 8:56 and estimated finish time of 3:54:04. That&amp;rsquo;s much faster than the 9:08 pace I had intended for a 4:00 finish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;really-slowing-down&#34;&gt;Really slowing down&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started really slowing down before even reaching the Birmingham Bridge. I knew I was getting into serious trouble. It was crazy, but my left knee was bothering me, and my left quads had started to twitch. So I had gone only about 11 miles and I was already struggling.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/birmingham-bridge.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;On Birmingham Bridge&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You have to understand how &lt;em&gt;nonsensical&lt;/em&gt; it is for me to be having muscle cramping after running only 11 miles at a pace that is actually slow for an 11-mile run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if we assumed, falsely, that I got to mile 11 at the same pace as during my first 6.2 miles (8:56), note that I ran an entire half marathon (13.1 miles) in late March, only in the beginning of marathon training, at an average of 8:28 pace, and was totally fine with no cramping during the race. And after a couple of weeks of further training, I had felt much stronger during a 16-mile run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So basically, it was a cruel joke I played on myself that I was in such poor condition that I was cramping up after 11 miles at a slow pace. I was very angry at myself that I had made a complete &lt;em&gt;travesty&lt;/em&gt; of my marathon, &lt;em&gt;just like in 2003&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;halfway-and-change-of-plan&#34;&gt;Halfway, and change of plan&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I slowed down more in Oakland to keep the left quad twitching under control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the alert system, I got halfway in 1:59:46, average pace of 9:09, and estimated finish time of 3:59:31. But of course, by then, I knew that I was done for. I was just going to continue slowing down and suffering, for &lt;em&gt;over two more hours&lt;/em&gt;, if I finished at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I finally saw the 4:00 pace group pass me, somehow that was a real blow to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At 9:27 AM, not too long after the halfway point, I texted Abby: &amp;ldquo;Severe pain. Very slow, just aim finish. Maybe 4:30.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now my main thought was to focus on making it to Annie (of the Pittsburgh Recorder Society), who was going to watch for me in Highland Park, just before mile 20. I had told her to expect me around 10 AM, and Annie had even posted to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/photo.php?fbid=463404163737512&amp;amp;set=a.368839359860660.86924.330712777006652&amp;amp;type=1&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Recorder Society Facebook page&lt;/a&gt; telling everyone I was running.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was so not going to make it for 10 AM. But I wanted to go slowly enough that I could hold off the quad cramping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;despair&#34;&gt;Despair&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At around 9:49 AM, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.runoverit.com/&#34;&gt;Chris&lt;/a&gt; passed me and said hello. I told him I was doing very badly. He wasn&amp;rsquo;t doing as well as he had hoped, but was moving along, unlike me. Here&amp;rsquo;s a photo I had the presence of mind to take only as he had already gone way ahead (in the blue shirt):&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/chris.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Chris up ahead in blue shirt&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At 9:54 AM, I made a video statement on my phone, just for myself: &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m after mile 17 or something, in Homewood. I&amp;rsquo;m doing really badly, but I&amp;rsquo;m still running, and that&amp;rsquo;s all I can say about that.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/12inzKGZGRU&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/despair.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Despair after mile 17 in Pittsburgh Marathon&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;annie&#34;&gt;Annie&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At 10:11 AM, not yet at Annie&amp;rsquo;s, I was contemplating quitting, because the pains I was experiencing (right quads twitching also, and even my arms and hands, mysteriously, in spots where I had old injuries years ago, plus a really bad blister on my right foot where I had all those skin problems earlier, and less bad but very annoying constant chafing of the Luna Sandals straps) were so terrible. I decided to just take a break at a fluid station and squat and stretch. I texted Abby: &amp;ldquo;Very bad shape. Rested some.&amp;rdquo; I also finally &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/franklin.chen/posts/10201315392704609&#34;&gt;posted to Facebook&lt;/a&gt;, &amp;ldquo;In very bad shape. Trying to finish anyway.&amp;rdquo; I was not actively reading Facebook during the marathon at all, but did notice a lot of notifications, and assumed they were words of encouragement from my friends; I didn&amp;rsquo;t want to read them until I was done, because I felt I might let them down. Abby replied, &amp;ldquo;What is your plan?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At 10:19, I said, &amp;ldquo;Don&amp;rsquo;t know. Walking, blister and cramping.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A note on the blistering and chafing: it got really warm and I got sweaty, so that was part of the problem. I had not run in these sandals in such conditions before: I had mostly run in dry, cold conditions of 35-50 degrees F. Also, I had forgotten about road hazards: there were cups of water and Gatorade all over around the aid stations and my feet were sticky and wet for much of the marathon. It was a rather unpleasant feeling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I kept running/walking. I saw Annie. I decided there and then, seeing her, that I was going to finish, rather than just bail out and crash on her couch or something pathetic like that. I shouted that I was in severe pain but planned to continue on! She took a photo of me, which I knew was going to be on Facebook before too long, so I&amp;rsquo;d better make good on my promise to her!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/franklin-in-highland-park.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin in Highland Park&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At 10:29, I texted Abby: &amp;ldquo;Got to Annie. Running again.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I then focused on just continuing to move, slowing to a walk if I needed to in order to deal with cramping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;mile-22&#34;&gt;Mile 22&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At 10:51, I reached S Aiken, just before mile 22. This is an important point in the course for me, not only because it begins a downhill, but also because it is where my friend Nathaniel cheered me on ten years ago when I was also suffering.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/aiken.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;S Aiken&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;strip-district&#34;&gt;Strip District&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point, I was getting discouraged again and started walking, when I accidentally spotted Deb and Mark watching. Seeing familiar faces among the spectators is definitely helpful! Upon seeing them, I felt ashamed of my walking and my negative thoughts. I went up to them, and they were going to take a picture of me, and I got all determined, and &lt;em&gt;screamed&lt;/em&gt;, &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m going to finish this thing!!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/im-going-to-finish-this-thing.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin determined to finish&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I kept on running, and did not stop, even though I saw many people walking, and also saw many relay runners zooming by. I decided that I was not only going to finish (it was now clear that I could), but that I was going to finish as strong as I could, even though it would count for nothing. I was going to run at the edge of quad twitching, all the way to the end. It was going to hurt far more than if I just ran very slowly to finish, but I didn&amp;rsquo;t come this far just to walk if I could run. I was determined to push.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/franklin-in-strip.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin in Strip District&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As I got closer and closer, I periodically texted Abby the street I had just crossed, so that she would know roughly when I was going to finish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;finish-line&#34;&gt;Finish line&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so I finished. I finished in a state of my quads twitching like firecrackers. I got my medal. I kept on walking. I grabbed a bag of chips and water. I forgot to look for other stuff, like Smiley Cookies (that Abby later said she saw were being handed out). I just wanted to stop the twitching, get my bag from Gear Check, get out of my Luna Sandals into some comfortable, cushioned flip-flops, use a Port-a-potty, and finally find Abby and the &amp;ldquo;CMU tent&amp;rdquo;, which I assumed was just a section of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pittsburghmarathon.com/PCC&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Corporate Challenge Tent&lt;/a&gt;. (I had bought a bracelet for Abby earlier so that she could have access to the tent.)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/after.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;After finishing&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I could barely walk after I started cooling down, because I got stiffer and stiffer. It took me forever to make it to the Finish Line Festival area, and I was so mentally drained that I had to call Abby to have her tell me where the tent was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;videos-update-of-2013-05-23&#34;&gt;Videos (update of 2013-05-23)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburgh.cbslocal.com/2013/05/05/2013-marathon-finish-line-videos/&#34;&gt;Videos of the Pittsburgh Marathon have been posted&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found myself in &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburgh.cbslocal.com/video/8844851-2013-marathon-finish-line-44000-45000/&#34;&gt;one of the sets of videos&lt;/a&gt;, for those who finished in a clock time between 4:40:00 and 4:50:00.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see me at around 4:44:35 and finishing at about 4:44:40 here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&#39;text/javascript&#39; src=&#39;http://CBSPIT.images.worldnow.com/interface/js/WNVideo.js?rnd=998125;hostDomain=video.pittsburgh.cbslocal.com;playerWidth=615;playerHeight=365;isShowIcon=true;clipId=8844851;flvUri=;partnerclipid=;adTag=Sport;advertisingZone=CBS.PITTS%252Fworldnowplayer;enableAds=true;landingPage=;islandingPageoverride=false;playerType=STANDARD_EMBEDDEDscript;controlsType=fixed&#39;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://video.pittsburgh.cbslocal.com&#34; title=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-tent-and-the-pittsburgh-campus-challenge&#34;&gt;The tent and the Pittsburgh Campus Challenge&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I signed up for the Pittsburgh Campus Challenge through Carnegie Mellon University, there was advertised to be &amp;ldquo;gourmet food, private massages, and more&amp;rdquo; in the tent. The reality was actually quite different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby said it was a good thing she made it to the tent before too late (she had gone back to nap in the car after seeing me off), because by 10 AM, half marathoners had eaten much of the food already, and she had remembered to save some for me for later! There was still food left, but much of the good stuff was gone. And it wasn&amp;rsquo;t really &amp;ldquo;gourmet&amp;rdquo;. There was dry fried chicken, rolls, pasta left, as far as I could tell, other than the pancakes Abby had saved from earlier, and  a Panera Bread sandwiches she also saved for me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/abby.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/tent-food.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Tent food&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There was a signup sheet for massage by Massage Envy, however, and a very long wait, as I got my massage after one hour and twenty minutes, which was actually OK because I was so sore I simply needed to be left alone for a while to just eat and eat and rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;cmu-won&#34;&gt;CMU won!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I came into the tent, there was confusion because I didn&amp;rsquo;t have a sticker on my bib indicating that I had access to the tent. Apparently I was supposed to have gotten a sticker at some point, but I don&amp;rsquo;t remember getting instructions about that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When they learned I was with CMU, however, they gave me the prize for CMU winning the Pittsburgh Campus Challenge, to hand over to Pattye at CMU. We beat Pitt!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/pittsburgh-campus-challenge.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Pittsburgh Campus Challenge prize&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;feet&#34;&gt;Feet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My feet were terribly sore. I got one blood-filled blister:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/blister.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Blister on right foot&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But otherwise, the damage was not as bad as I had thought. During the marathon, I had wondered sometimes about all the stickiness I felt on my feet, but it was not blood after all; it was a mixture of energy gel, Gatorade, orange juice, and whatever else was left on the road that got onto my feet:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/feet.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I had two chafing spots from the straps, but they were not serious. All in all, my feet were in much condition after wearing the Luna Sandals than they were ten years ago after wearing standard socks and running shoes. The drawback is that my feet were horribly sore, although after one night of rest, the foot soreness is actually all gone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;one-day-later&#34;&gt;One day later&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I do have a different problem: one day later, numbness in my left foot remains, because I had adjusted my strap for my left foot too tightly, out of fear of it coming off. &lt;em&gt;Overly tight strap was a big mistake.&lt;/em&gt; I did make an adjustment at some point during the race, but I could at least have loosened the strap earlier when I felt discomfort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In all my previous runs, my left foot has never fallen out. I hope the numbness goes away in another day.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/feet-day-after.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;My feet the day after&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;legs&#34;&gt;Legs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My legs were utterly trashed, as might be expected given how I had tortured them for so long. At first, I thought it was just my quads and hamstrings, but once I pulled off the calf sleeves, I realized that my calves were trashed too, but had &lt;em&gt;completely&lt;/em&gt; avoided cramping because of the compression. I count this as a total success for the calf sleeves, because in the marathon ten years ago, my calves were seizing up in the second half, not just my quads. &lt;em&gt;I will always wear calf sleeves in the future in long runs or hikes&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Em of Massage Envy was very helpful in getting me able to sort of walk, so that I could go with Abby back over to the North Shore to our car (I had to walk across the bridge, then waited as she brought the car over).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/massage-envy.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Massage Envy&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Overall, I think wearing the Luna Sandals was the correct decision, despite the drawbacks. I did &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; have toe jamming, toe blistering, toe cramping that I believe I would have had in other footwear. I did not have ankle soreness of any kind. Or shin splints. I did not have any right knee pain at all, just left (and almost certainly because of my fall on Thursday). I could have used more cushioning though. But my order of the thicker Luna Sandals (the new Mono model) has not yet shipped.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;thanks&#34;&gt;Thanks!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a lot to be thankful for even though in some sense this marathon was truly a debacle for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am thankful that this race returned to Pittsburgh after suspension in 2004-2008, as Dick&amp;rsquo;s Sporting Goods rose up to be the title sponsor. I am amazed by how large and popular the Pittsburgh Marathon has become since I last ran it ten years ago. I think it&amp;rsquo;s great that the city has this annual celebration of its neighborhoods and of the running community. The Pittsburgh Marathon is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; just about the marathon, but about just regular fitness running, free workshops on health and exercise, and celebrating a sport that brings everyone together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am thankful to Pattye Stragar for spreading word of the Pittsburgh Campus Challenge through the CMU fitness mailing list.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am thankful to Steel City Road Runners for their well-organized Saturday long runs that got me out during the cold months when I otherwise might have chosen to just sleep in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am thankful to my friends who encouraged me as I progressed through my training and in my discouraging days before the marathon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am thankful to Annie and Deb and Mark for being spectators I saw and knew who gave me additional motivation to keep going.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am thankful to all the spectators and volunteers I don&amp;rsquo;t know who offered cheers, water, orange slices, music, and everything else that reminded me that humanity is caring and helpful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And of course, I am particularly thankful to my wife Abby, who has been so patient these months as I have pursued this marathon thing that she thinks is crazy (OK, I know it is crazy), and helped me every single day. Abby, this whole experience has truly deepened my appreciation of you, and I will never forget what we went through together to make this birthday present happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;did-i-achieve-my-goals&#34;&gt;Did I achieve my goals?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s go back to &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/30/why-and-how-i-am-going-to-run-the-2013-pittsburgh-marathon/&#34;&gt;my blog post from three months ago where I stated my goals for the marathon&lt;/a&gt;. What did I actually achieve?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;maintain a smart pace: failed (totally)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;finish strong: succeeded (insofar as I pushed as hard as I could for the last three miles approximately)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;avoid leg muscle cramping: failed miserably with the quads, succeeded with the calves&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;avoid foot blistering: failed (got one bad blister)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;conquer the hills: neutral (didn&amp;rsquo;t feel particularly bad at hills as such)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it would seem that I basically failed, as far as the marathon itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I think I succeeded, in a larger context:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t expect to be wearing huaraches for a marathon, but I did wear Luna Sandals! I proved to myself it could be done.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As a side effect of marathon training, I got myself into much better shape than I have been in for the past half decade, and did my first half marathon in nine years, and set up exercise habits I hope to make permanent independent of any future marathoning.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Abby&amp;rsquo;s help as I took on the task of training made a profound impression on me.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The outpouring of support from friends was a welcome surprise to me, because in my last Pittsburgh Marathon, I mostly went about it alone, telling only a few people about it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-did-i-fail-so-miserably&#34;&gt;Why did I fail so miserably?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe I failed mostly because I didn&amp;rsquo;t have the proper training. I started too late, I didn&amp;rsquo;t have enough time to more gradually absorb increased training volume, I could have used an extra month or two of more long runs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also did not adapt properly to setbacks that should have led me to change my goals drastically. There was a downward spiral in terms of injury, fatigue, and loss of calm reason.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-next&#34;&gt;What next?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;done-with-the-marathon&#34;&gt;Done with the marathon&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I told Abby that this is it: no more racing marathons again, ever. I mean it. I&amp;rsquo;m facing the reality that this is not the right event for me. I believe I could do a good marathon, but what it would take is not worth the effort. The sacrifices that I made, and Abby made, were considerable. There are other things we could be doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I look forward to our returning to &amp;ldquo;normal&amp;rdquo; life as I recover.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;running&#34;&gt;Running&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, I totally enjoyed getting back into year-round running. I will never go into winter hibernation again. I still have to figure out ideal footwear for the coldest and snow/ice/water-ridden conditions for next winter, of course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;half-marathons&#34;&gt;Half marathons&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Doing Just A Short Run again gave me confidence that I can &amp;ldquo;master&amp;rdquo; the half marathon distance. I would like to continue doing half marathons. I have decided to do the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mtchalfmarathon.com/&#34;&gt;Montour Trail Half Marathon&lt;/a&gt; in September. This means I will have to skip the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~kalp/PGR/&#34;&gt;CMU Pretty Good Race&lt;/a&gt;, which is always held the Friday before this Saturday race, but it&amp;rsquo;s time for me to get back into doing half marathon and 10K and 5K (and even mile) races, distances that I can actually work on being able to run well without wrecking myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heck, I might even run the Pittsburgh Half Marathon a year from now! (Although I don&amp;rsquo;t actually want to think about that for a while.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In isolation, the 2013 Pittsburgh Marathon may be considered to be a total debacle for me, the worst race I&amp;rsquo;ve finished out of the 135 races I&amp;rsquo;ve showed up for in my life. But I&amp;rsquo;m glad I went through the process of training for it, and I&amp;rsquo;m grateful for it as a vehicle of self-discovery: I faced some unpleasant truths about various poor decisions I made. And I&amp;rsquo;m grateful for the opportunity to share my journey with friends and family.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.guardian.co.uk/sport/blog/2012/jun/22/50-olympic-stunning-moments-emil-zatopek&#34;&gt;Emil Zatopek&lt;/a&gt; said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
If you want to run, run a mile. If you want to experience a different life, run a marathon.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-05-09&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-05-09)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second day after the marathon, I was still in physical and emotional pain, and wrote a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/05/07/why-i-feel-sad-when-people-congratulate-me-for-finishing-the-pittsburgh-marathon/&#34;&gt;little rant expressing my disappointment&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third day, I was able to walk normally and was emotionally recovering as well and was embarrassed by my rant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fourth day, I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/05/09/back-to-what-running-is-really-about-for-me/&#34;&gt;went out for a short run and reflected on what running is really about for me&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-12-22&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-12-22)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I just wanted to point out a much healthier attitude and experience of a marathon gone badly: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.letsrun.com/news/2013/11/time-life/&#34;&gt;this is a really beautiful article&lt;/a&gt; that every disappointed racer should read.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recognize that I trapped myself during March and April with increasingly unbalanced expectations of my marathon, and lost all calmness and perspective. I still don&amp;rsquo;t know whether I will run a marathon again, but if I do, I vow to do it with a clear mind and body.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Report on Just A Short Run: my first half marathon in nine years!</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/03/30/report-on-just-a-short-run-my-first-half-marathon-in-nine-years/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Mar 2013 15:06:18 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/03/30/report-on-just-a-short-run-my-first-half-marathon-in-nine-years/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;(Updated 2013-05-09 with official race videos!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until today, I had not run a half marathon in nine years. This distance had given me a lot of trouble the five times I did it in 2001-2004. So I was very anxious about running &lt;a href=&#34;http://eliterunners.com/just-a-short-run/&#34;&gt;Just A Short Run&lt;/a&gt; this morning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s why I feared it, and how I ended up unexpectedly pleased with the experience, including finishing over four minutes faster than my goal time.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/just-a-short-run-2013/franklin.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin done&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;past-participation-in-just-a-short-run&#34;&gt;Past participation in Just A Short Run&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was the fifth time I participated in Just A Short Run. This race began in 2001, when &lt;a href=&#34;http://eliterunners.com/running-shoes-pittsburgh/about-running-store/&#34;&gt;Kevin Smith&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href=&#34;http://eliterunners.com/&#34;&gt;Elite Runners and Walkers&lt;/a&gt; created in in memory of his younger brother who died of leukemia, to &lt;a href=&#34;http://eliterunners.com/just-a-short-run-about/&#34;&gt;support the Leukemia and Lymphoma Society&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/ipDidl-_qpM&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until today I have done the Just A Short Run four times:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;5K in 2001&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;half marathon in 2002&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;30K in 2003 (my only DNF in my life, because I went into it sick)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;5K in 2004&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;past-half-marathons&#34;&gt;Past half marathons&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have only once ever partly successfully executed a half marathon race, and even then, some things went rather wrong. Here&amp;rsquo;s a summary of what went wrong in each of my half marathons up till today:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;ikea-montour-trail-half-marathon-2001&#34;&gt;Ikea Montour Trail half marathon, 2001&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was my very first half marathon, after having run some good 5K races earlier in the year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went out too fast (because of an initial downhill that got me too excited), and paid the price. I finished in 1:47:23. My splits for the 13.1 miles:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;6:31.94&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;7:59.53&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;8:09.44&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;8:16.53&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;8:16.99&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;8:19.28&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;8:19.64&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;7:44.85&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;8:01.41&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;8:23.29&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;8:28.72&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;8:42.36&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;9:17.34&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;0:49.85&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was just struggling in the last miles, and very demoralized. I almost collapsed on my buddy Jude&amp;rsquo;s shoulder after I finished. Also, I had major blisters during the race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;just-a-short-run-half-marathon-2002&#34;&gt;Just A Short Run half marathon, 2002&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did this race without any real training at all, just because it was there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got blisters in the race, and also had to deal with weird existential thoughts like &amp;ldquo;Why am I running this?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I finished in 1:49:34, but actually, the course was found to be long by about a tenth of a mile, so that number does not mean much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;ikea-montour-trail-half-marathon-2002&#34;&gt;Ikea Montour Trail half marathon, 2002&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got my revenge in this race, actually training hard specifically for the distance, doing long intervals and a lot of tempo and race-pace runs. Overall I did very well, finishing in 1:38:48, but the experience was marred by some serious problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ran mile 4 too fast, but since I was carefully monitoring on my watch, I slowed down for mile 5. Still, one pays the price eventually for going too fast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, I still was not fueling consistently. I erred by taking both water and energy drink, resulting in dilution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In mile 12, my calves started cramping up and I had to stop at one point. I lost about half a minute because of this. In mile 13, I had to run conservatively to avoid cramps. It was very frustrating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, after I finished, while getting on the shuttle bus, I cramped up quite severely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;ikea-montour-trail-half-marathon-2003&#34;&gt;Ikea Montour Trail half marathon, 2003&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A total disaster. I finished in 1:45:32, which is 7:44 slower than the previous year. This was while having a 5K fitness similar to the previous year&amp;rsquo;s. Something just went wrong. I felt sluggish throughout, and I cramped up in mile 10. And I had digestive problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;chamber-classic-half-marathon-2004&#34;&gt;Chamber Classic half marathon, 2004&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1:46:12. No real training for it, just did it because it was there and I had not been able to do the Montour Trail one. A fiasco, in which I struggled with my usual problems (slowing down in the final miles, cramping).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;preparation&#34;&gt;Preparation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did not go into this race truly prepared to &lt;em&gt;race&lt;/em&gt; the half marathon. I know what it takes to race a half marathon for time: long tempo and race-pace runs, long intervals. I have done little of that so far this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My hardest training run so far has been &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/16/18-miles-in-vibram-fivefingers-training-for-the-pittsburgh-marathon/&#34;&gt;16 miles with the Steel City Road Runners, two weeks ago, on an 18 mile course&lt;/a&gt;. I did not truly taper for the half marathon race, although this week including the race I have a reduced mileage of 25 (easy 6, easy 3, speed ladder 3, and then the race).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather, what I am really training for is the Pittsburgh Marathon, but I felt that I should do a half marathon race in order to get a taste of what it is like to run in a long race. I have been doing long runs every week for a while now, so running the half marathon distance is not a problem: the challenge for me was to figure out if I could partially &lt;em&gt;race&lt;/em&gt; it, to find my limits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I wanted to fix the problems I had in my previous half marathons:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;blistering&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;going out too fast&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;slowing way down&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;cramping&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;digestive problems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;blistering&#34;&gt;Blistering&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Solving the problem of blistering has been trivial for me since I switched to wearing Vibram FiveFingers shoes. I just don&amp;rsquo;t get serious blisters any more; my feet have adapted completely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, I just got my Luna Sandals two days ago, but have not run in them yet. Friends helpfully convinced me that it would be crazy to wear them in the race without any actual test of them (I knew that, but just needed validation).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the &lt;em&gt;first half marathon&lt;/em&gt; I&amp;rsquo;m running in Vibram FiveFingers. Up till now, the longest distance I&amp;rsquo;ve raced in FiveFingers has been &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/25/blistered-but-blissful-in-the-burgh/&#34;&gt;10K, when I was still getting blistered by the Bikila LS&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;going-out-too-fast&#34;&gt;Going out too fast&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By not treating this as an all-out race whose goal is to minimize time, I could afford to run more conservatively and plan on negative-splitting. I decide to target a time of 1:55:00 (reasonable given &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/03/my-first-steel-city-road-runners-winter-5k-race/&#34;&gt;my recent 5K&lt;/a&gt; time of 25:11), with the idea of speeding up if it felt right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;slowing-way-down&#34;&gt;Slowing way down&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I consciously carb-loaded for this half marathon and had a race fueling plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;cramping&#34;&gt;Cramping&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have no idea how to really solve this problem. I think I must be genetically predisposed to cramping. People like to claim electrolyte deficiency is the cause, but I don&amp;rsquo;t believe this at all, because I have tried loading up on electrolytes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;digestive-problems&#34;&gt;Digestive problems&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have concluded that it is safest to avoid Gatorade and the like on the course because people mix it in funny proportions. Sticking with predictable gels and water is my new plan. One gel before starting the race, and then one gel every 45 minutes after that (which in the case of a half marathon means two gels on the course).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, I used to drink too much water, resulting in sloshing in the stomach. So I drink less now during a race, and drink more well before it starts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-route&#34;&gt;The route&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;iframe id=&#34;mapmyfitness_route&#34; src=&#34;http://snippets.mapmycdn.com/routes/view/embedded/24782?width=560&amp;height=400&amp;elevation=true&amp;info=true&amp;line_color=E60f0bdb&amp;rgbhex=DB0B0E&amp;distance_markers=1&amp;unit_type=imperial&amp;map_mode=TERRAIN&amp;last_updated=2006-03-10T16:46:31-05:00&#34; height=&#34;590px&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: right; padding-right: 20px;&#34;&gt;&lt;a target=&#34;_blank&#34; href=&#34;http://mapmyrun.com/routes/create/&#34;&gt;Create Maps&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a target=&#34;_blank&#34; href=&#34;http://mapmyrun.com/routes/&#34;&gt;search&lt;/a&gt; from 80 million at &lt;a href=&#34;http://mapmyrun.com&#34;&gt;MapMyRun&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

Note the big hill at the beginning. Control of effort going up and down hills is critical, to avoid bad spikes in energy usage.

## The race

Here are the [official race results](http://www.runhigh.com/2013RESULTS/R033013AA.html).

### Start


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/just-a-short-run-2013/announcements.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Announcements&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


I started out with the 1:55:00 finish pacer (8:47 pace):


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/just-a-short-run-2013/pacer.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;My initial pacer&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


Going up the big hill, however, he totally lost me, as I slowed down to avoid prematurely feeling the burn. In fact, a slower pacer even passed me. No problem.

On the downhill, I quickly started regaining ground. I think after around three miles, I had caught up to the original 8:47 pacer, and then that was feeling too slow for me, so I passed him for good, and never saw a pacer again in the race.

### Gatorade error

I made an error at one of the aid stations when I mistaken grabbed Gatorade and threw it in my face. I got stickiness all over my face and the front of my jacket and fingers. It was really disgusting, actually. I will be more careful in the future to ask what stuff is before taking a cup.

Otherwise, I stuck well to my plan of taking water and two gels during the entire half marathon. Note that the race provided [e-Gel](http://www.cranksports.com/products/eGel/), which I had not had before. If I were seriously racing this half marathon, obviously I would have bought and tried this stuff on long runs ahead of time.

### Passing people

The thing about Just A Short Run is that people are running different races and therefore are at different paces, and also in such a huge race, there are always those who are inexperienced and go out too fast and slow down. What this means, in practice, is that if you are running evenly (or for a negative split, like I was doing), you will be needing to pass people constantly. It is very important to be a good judge of your own pace, because otherwise you might think you are doing OK, while the reality is you&#39;re following someone who is slowing down.

I like to target someone who looks faster than me and then try to keep up with him or her. I did this repeatedly in the race.

At one point I asked a guy what his pace was, and he said 8:30. I was feeling good, so eventually I passed him. I realized at that moment that I was going to be able to run considerably faster than 1:55:00, despite my very slow start.

### Last five miles

I maintained speed in the last 5 miles of the race; I might even have gone faster, but without the data, I cannot tell, since when fatigue sets in, effort does not equal actual pace. I was definitely getting tired, but I kept pushing, trying to pretend I was running a 10K race or something. I thought that I just might have a shot at finishing under 1:50:00. I didn&#39;t, but that&#39;s OK. I finished in 1:50:52.

The official [split data](http://www.runhigh.com/2013RESULTS/R033013AF.html) shows that I did the last 5 miles in 42:03, which is about 8:25 pace. Since I averaged 8:28 pace for the whole race, I clearly ran faster in the last 5 miles than in the first 8.1 miles.

If I had known what I was capable of, I could have run faster and more evenly from the start, and finished faster, but that was quite explicitly *not* the goal today. The goal was to finish strong, which I did.

## SPIbelt

This was my first time running a race wearing a SPIbelt. It did not cause me any trouble at all; I barely noticed it. I will wear it during the Pittsburgh Marathon, in order to have my phone on me in case of emergency. I did not use my phone during the race, only before and after it, but it&#39;s always nice to know that I can directly contact Abby if something goes wrong.

## Cramping

I did a little bit of a final sprint across the finish line. The moment I crossed was the moment when I felt both of my calves start to twitch. I realized that I almost crossed the line to full-on cramping, and decided to keep moving. I grabbed a banana and ate it while jogging slowly, and planning to jog off the heaviness in my calves.

Then disaster struck: I stubbed my right toes on the ground and instantly two of my toes cramped up and my lower right calf also cramped up. I ripped off my shoe and luckily, after about twenty seconds, I was OK again. I decided it was unsafe to keep moving, and I went upstairs in the North Park Boat House to just keep warm and stretch in a safe environment. I did not cramp up again.

So I have not entirely solved the cramping problem. Apparently sprinting was enough to push me over the edge. Also, closed-toe shoes are a problem because my toes inevitably get at least somewhat jammed in the course of running in closed-toe shoes. This is why I want to test out the Luna Sandals, which may completely prevent toe jamming and cramping. As for my calves, I don&#39;t know, maybe I just need to do more hard longer runs in order to get them accustomed to the lactic acid buildup or something.

## Post-race eating

My stomach was entirely OK during the race. No water sloshing, no indigestion, no gnawing hunger. I was hungry after finishing, of course.


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/just-a-short-run-2013/food.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Post-race food&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


I made some mistakes after finishing, however. I ate not only a banana, but also a bagel, a Smiley Cookie, a little bag of chips, and a little bag of cookies. I believe I should have excluded the bag of cookies and the chips, and saved the Smiley Cookie for later. I had some digestive discomfort (nothing serious though) for a while after everything I ate. I will remember next time. After a 5K or 10K, I can eat anything, but apparently, after a half marathon, digestion is trickier.

But it is hard not to gobble up a Smiley Cookie:


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/just-a-short-run-2013/smiley-cookie.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Smiley Cookie&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


At home, I ended up deciding to eat familiar leftovers rather than going out to a buffet as I had originally thought of doing with Abby.

## Feet

My feet were sore, but actually, less sore than after each of my long runs in the past month. I think I&#39;ve become more efficient. No knee pain either. After the race, just general inflammation. I think I&#39;ll be OK tomorrow.


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/just-a-short-run-2013/shoes.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Vibram FiveFingers Bikila LS&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/just-a-short-run-2013/feet.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin&amp;#39;s feet&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/just-a-short-run-2013/soles.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin&amp;#39;s soles of feet&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


I did get one small blister, on my right pinkie toe, but I didn&#39;t actually notice it until I was home and took a shower.

## What does all this mean for the marathon?

This [race time predictor](http://www.runnersworld.co.uk/general/rws-race-time-predictor/1681.html) suggests that given that I ran a half marathon in 1:50:52, I can do a full marathon in 3:51:08. I am, frankly, skeptical that I can go under 4:00:00 at all a month from now. I know I want to be conservative in the marathon, and I rather doubt I will be able to negative-split it, and I still have concerns about late-stage cramping or other physical deterioration. We shall see how my training progresses. I am going to start adding &#34;quality&#34; work in the form of interval training in order to toughen up.

## Thanks

Many thanks to my wife Abby, who dropped me off at the race and picked me up after visiting her parents in the vicinity, saving me driving and parking hassles! And thanks to all my friends who have been supportive while I&#39;ve been so nervous for weeks about this race!

I like to thank [Elite Runners and Walkers](http://eliterunners.com/) for putting on a really well-organized race. The instructions were very clear, volunteers giving out water, Gatorade, and gels were everywhere, there was plenty of post-race food, bag check was convenient, and everything seemed to go smoothly. I would like to take this opportunity to say that without Elite Runners and Walkers, I do not know where I would be as a runner. Back over a decade ago, when I started running, the Internet was not what it is now. I got information about running from books and magazines and word of mouth more than anything else. I was told about the new store Elite Runners and Walkers and I got some of my first running shoes and clothing there. I even bought my very first pair of Vibram FiveFingers KSO shoes there, in 2009, before minimalist shoes suddenly became more mainstream and available in other stores, and last year when I got some rips in those first Vibram FiveFingers shoes, I got a new pair of KSO shoes through them also. And the races they put on in the winter and spring are great: I used to run their [Spring Thaw](http://eliterunners.com/events/annual-spring-thaw/) as well as Just A Short Run. And when picking up my race packet at the store this week, Abby and I bought some more shirts and shorts in preparation for summer!

## Conclusion

This was my slowest half marathon ever, but one of the most satisfying, and one of the best-executed, given my actual fitness level, which is substantially lower than that of a decade ago. I may consider *really* racing a half marathon in the fall. Meanwhile, I definitely found the successful completion of this half marathon to be a confidence booster for the upcoming Pittsburgh Marathon. Yes, there is no real comparison between the two distances, but it&#39;s just the fact that this is a long race at all, compared to, say, a 5K or 10K.

## Race videos are out! (Update of 2013-05-09)

### From start to 1:30:00

#### Start

I couldn&#39;t find myself in the half marathon start, because it&#39;s too congested.

#### Additional loop 1

I found myself arriving under &#34;Additional loops&#34; at 27:09 on the clock to begin the first of two 5-mile loops.

(To jump immediately to the spot, click [here](http://youtu.be/BukDHKvc7rk?t=12m50s).)

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/BukDHKvc7rk&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I crossed the start line after 21 seconds, I really ran 26:48 for the first 3.1 miles (average 8:39 pace).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;additional-loop-2&#34;&gt;Additional loop 2&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, watch me cross &amp;ldquo;Additional loops&amp;rdquo; at around 1:09:09 on the clock, which means I did 5 miles in 42:00 (average 8:24 pace).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(To jump immediately to the spot, click &lt;a href=&#34;http://youtu.be/BukDHKvc7rk?t=46m11s&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;from-1-31-00-to-3-21-00&#34;&gt;From 1:31:00 to 3:21:00&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;sprint-finish&#34;&gt;Sprint finish&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Watch my sprint finish from clock time around 1:51:03 to finish at 1:51:12 (my chip time was 1:50:51, meaning I crossed the start line after 21 seconds), which means I did the last 5 miles in 42:03, almost exactly the same time as I did the first 5-mile loop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(To jump immediately to the spot, click &lt;a href=&#34;http://youtu.be/wdjy7eLUlwQ?t=15m41s&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/wdjy7eLUlwQ&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;from-3-23-00-to-4-07-00&#34;&gt;From 3:23:00 to 4:07:00&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was already done, so I am not in this video.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/t4Zwv-tSLVM&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2014-03-09&#34;&gt;(Update of 2014-03-09)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2014, I did not set a goal to run a spring half marathon, so I did not train in the winter months for one, and so I am sadly missing Just A Short Run. Maybe there&amp;rsquo;s still time for me to get back into regular running and aim to do a half marathon in the fall.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>18 miles in Vibram FiveFingers: training for the Pittsburgh Marathon through a St. Patrick&#39;s Day parade</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/03/16/18-miles-in-vibram-fivefingers-training-for-the-pittsburgh-marathon/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Mar 2013 18:22:34 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/03/16/18-miles-in-vibram-fivefingers-training-for-the-pittsburgh-marathon/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/18-miles/st-patricks-day-parade-prep.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Pittsburgh St. Patrick&amp;#39;s Day preparation&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My second &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.steelcityrrc.org/scrrcevents?eventId=619953&amp;amp;EventViewMode=2&amp;amp;CalendarViewType=1&amp;amp;SelectedDate=3/30/2013&#34;&gt;Saturday group training run with the Steel City Runners&lt;/a&gt; happened to be on St. Patrick&amp;rsquo;s Day weekend, and therefore took place just before the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pittsburghirish.org/parade/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh St. Patrick&amp;rsquo;s Day parade&lt;/a&gt;, which starts at 10 AM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;overtraining-and-knees&#34;&gt;Overtraining and knees&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/09/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings-in-one-12-mile-run/&#34;&gt;Last week I mentioned&lt;/a&gt; that I was having problems because of overtraining; I ran five days one week only to have to scale back to three the next. This week I consciously got in four days of running, with higher total mileage than either of the previous two weeks (when I did 26 and 23). This week, I got in 29. It wasn&amp;rsquo;t easy, especially given that I ran last week&amp;rsquo;s long run too hard and therefore had left knee oddness that actually lasted three days! It wasn&amp;rsquo;t so bad that I couldn&amp;rsquo;t run, but I clearly had to let it heal up, which it did in time for another long run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, both of John&amp;rsquo;s knees were in serious pain the day after last week&amp;rsquo;s training run, and a week later, he is still waiting for them to heal up, and therefore did not join me for today&amp;rsquo;s training run. Oops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;plan&#34;&gt;Plan&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For today&amp;rsquo;s run, I decided to run &lt;em&gt;only the first 16 miles&lt;/em&gt; and then walk the last 2 miles. Also, I joined the 10-minute pace group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that a lot of things went &amp;ldquo;wrong&amp;rdquo; on this run, but I got back to the start OK in the end!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;unknown-territory&#34;&gt;Unknown territory&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wore my Vibram FiveFingers Bikila LS shoes again. This is an important test, because I have &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; been on the road for 18 miles straight in these shoes before, run or walk! I need to know whether wearing these for the Pittsburgh Marathon will work out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;weather-conditions&#34;&gt;Weather conditions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had watched the forecast all week with concern that it might be pouring rain, but I was committed to do this run regardless of conditions, because if the Pittsburgh Marathon involves running in rain, I need to be ready to deal with that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that we lucked out; although it was cold, there was drizzling rain but no downpour!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/18-miles/start.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Start of run&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-route&#34;&gt;The route&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is the route of the 18-mile training run:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe id=&#34;mapmyfitness_route&#34; src=&#34;http://snippets.mapmycdn.com/routes/view/embedded/180281790?width=560&amp;height=400&amp;elevation=true&amp;info=true&amp;line_color=E60f0bdb&amp;rgbhex=DB0B0E&amp;distance_markers=1&amp;unit_type=imperial&amp;map_mode=TERRAIN&amp;last_updated=2013-03-11T10:51:41-04:00&#34; height=&#34;590px&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: right; padding-right: 20px;&#34;&gt;&lt;a target=&#34;_blank&#34; href=&#34;http://mapmyrun.com/routes/create/&#34;&gt;Create Maps&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a target=&#34;_blank&#34; href=&#34;http://mapmyrun.com/routes/&#34;&gt;search&lt;/a&gt; from 80 million at &lt;a href=&#34;http://mapmyrun.com&#34;&gt;MapMyRun&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-run&#34;&gt;The run&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started with the 10-minute pace group. I actually immediately fell back, wanting to start off running more slowly,  but was never too far from the pack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;st-patrick-s-day&#34;&gt;St. Patrick&amp;rsquo;s Day&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Immediately and throughout the run, I saw people in green who were a little loud and clearly had a bit to drink. I was amused that they were up and around already at 8 AM in the morning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We ended up running on Liberty Avenue through the setup for St. Patrick&amp;rsquo;s Day parade downtown (which begins at 10 AM). We got some cheers (many of us were wearing green) as well as some jeers. It was a strange experience, and I felt a bit embarrassed to be running through parade preparation.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/18-miles/st-patricks-day-parade-prep.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Pittsburgh St. Patrick&amp;#39;s Day preparation&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;first-water-stop&#34;&gt;First water stop&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the first water stop, I drank some water and grabbed a GU gel to go. I caught up to the 10-minute pace group at the first water stop, since a lot of people didn&amp;rsquo;t immediately keep going but waited for everyone to get water.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My new system with gels is to take one and then eat it some minutes after drinking water, rather than immediately with water. It saves time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;big-uphill-and-losing-my-map&#34;&gt;Big uphill and losing my map&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a big uphill going east on Liberty Ave during which I lost the 10-minute pace group because I prefer to go slower uphill to maintain an even &lt;em&gt;effort&lt;/em&gt; rather than &lt;em&gt;pace&lt;/em&gt;. I always make up the loss on the downhills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;second-water-stop&#34;&gt;Second water stop&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second water stop was near mile 8 in Shadyside. I caught up yet again to the 10-minute pace group at that point, and took another GU gel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, I realized that I must have lost my paper map while running up Liberty Avenue. This was bad, because although I roughly knew the route, I did not know all the details. I did have my smartphone on me, but the MapMyRun Web site did not display very well on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Worse, it appeared after the second water stop that the 10-minute pace group was either going much slower or I was all &amp;ldquo;warmed up&amp;rdquo; and going much faster, because I could not tolerate their pace, and I decided I had to forge ahead into Oakland, even though there was nobody ahead that I could follow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did find two other people who were willing to go at a faster pace along with me, so the three of us took off into Oakland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;birmingham-bridge&#34;&gt;Birmingham Bridge&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The three of us crossed the Birmingham Bridge together to the South Side. I remarked that the last time I did the Pittsburgh Marathon ten years ago, I was humbled by the uphill going &lt;em&gt;into&lt;/em&gt; Oakland (in the other direction) on the bridge.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/18-miles/birmingham-bridge.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Birmingham Bridge to South Side&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;south-side-and-falling-behind&#34;&gt;South Side and falling behind&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The South Side was a total party scene, as might be expected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Going east on Carson Street, I suddenly noticed at around mile 11 that I had lost one of my gloves. I had taken off my gloves earlier as it was getting warmer, and put them in my pockets, but just as I had lost my map because I hadn&amp;rsquo;t zipped my jacket pockets, I had now lost a glove. I apologized to my two companions and said I was turning back to find my glove if possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckily, my glove was just a block back, and a group of runners saw it and picked it up and gave it to me. But now my two companions were far away from me. I could still see them, but I didn&amp;rsquo;t want to run super fast just to catch them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;three-rivers-heritage-trail-and-getting-lost&#34;&gt;Three Rivers Heritage Trail and getting lost&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I saw my companions turn onto the Three Rivers Heritage Trail. At this point, I no longer knew exactly what the rest of the route was for the last 8 miles. I knew that there was a water/gel stop at some point in the next 7 miles before the West End Bridge, but had no idea where it was!! I really didn&amp;rsquo;t want to miss the final water/gel stop, since that would mean going 8 miles without any water or fuel. Of course, I did have some money on me, so I could stop somewhere to refuel, but I didn&amp;rsquo;t really want to stop if I didn&amp;rsquo;t have to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So now I&amp;rsquo;d run around 12 miles and my feet were definitely sore. It was a huge relief to be running on the trail, actually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then I made a mistake. I suddenly saw what seemed to be a water stop because a bunch of runners were gathering there. I approached and asked if it was the Steel City Road Runners water stop and they said no, it was Elite Runners and Walkers. They offered to give me some water anyway, but I declined, which was a mistake, because during the seconds I spent on this detour, I lost sight of my two companions!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I kept on running on the trail but they were just gone, and I never saw them again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;running-to-the-west-end-bridge&#34;&gt;Running to the West End Bridge&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I just kept on running west, figuring I would eventually get to the West End Bridge. I went through Station Square and made it across the West End Bridge. Now, I had planned ahead of time to stop running shortly after crossing the West End Bridge, because it was going to be 16 miles then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I started feeling cold, and so I did some run/walking east all the way back to the start. It was very lonely going the last 8 miles of the route alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;safe-and-warm&#34;&gt;Safe and warm&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I made it back OK. I grabbed two energy bars and went inside to get warm and stretch and devour the two energy bars. My feet were totally killing me, but I had survived 18 miles on them in Vibram FiveFingers Bikila LS shoes. I still have no idea whether I can last a whole marathon in them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;my-feet&#34;&gt;My feet&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although my feet are sore, everything seems to be OK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/18-miles/feet.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin&amp;#39;s feet&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/18-miles/shoes.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Vibram FiveFingers Bikila LS shoes&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/18-miles/soles.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin&amp;#39;s soles of feet&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;photos&#34;&gt;Photos&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/steelcityrrc&#34;&gt;Steel City Road Runners Facebook site&lt;/a&gt; is a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/media/set/?set=a.425827677512050.1073741827.391728257588659&amp;amp;type=1&#34;&gt;photo album of the St. Patrick&amp;rsquo;s Day run&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ran about 16 miles of the 18-mile route, as planned, but got lost, which I did not plan. I learned some lessons. In the future, I am zipping my jacket pockets, and I am also studying the printed map thoroughly before starting one of these runs. My super-sore feet have me worried about running the marathon in Vibram FiveFingers, so I will investigate alternatives. I&amp;rsquo;m still waiting for my order this week of &lt;a href=&#34;http://lunasandals.com/&#34;&gt;Luna Sandals&lt;/a&gt; to come in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, I&amp;rsquo;m thankful that Steel City Road Runners made it possible for me to do such a long run without feeling completely alone, and not having to haul all the water and fuel I needed during and after the run. Ten years ago when I was marathon training, I did carry along everything I needed, but it really is much nicer to simulate actual race conditions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am grateful that when I was done and called home, Abby baked a pizza for us to share when I got back. Fuel! Abby has been understanding and supportive during my training for the Pittsburgh Marathon. She thinks it&amp;rsquo;s a crazy thing to do, and it is, but I want to do it this once again while I have the opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>11 Pittsburgh bridge crossings in one 12-mile run</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/03/09/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings-in-one-12-mile-run/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Mar 2013 21:21:26 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/03/09/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings-in-one-12-mile-run/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://sphotos-b.xx.fbcdn.net/hphotos-ash3/602768_422297731198378_798317370_n.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;View from Mount Washington&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My first ever &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.steelcityrrc.org/scrrcevents?eventId=568739&amp;amp;EventViewMode=2&amp;amp;CalendarViewType=1&amp;amp;SelectedDate=3/16/2013&#34;&gt;Steel City Road Runners Saturday morning training run&lt;/a&gt; was a 12-mile run. My office mate John went with me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last time I ran as far as 12 miles &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/02/24/2013-pittsburgh-marathon-training-progress-since-signing-up-three-weeks-ago/&#34;&gt;was in February&lt;/a&gt;, so I expected to do OK. The important difference is that I have been increasing my weekly mileage. I had a monster training week last week, going up from 13 miles to 26 miles last week, the &lt;em&gt;largest&lt;/em&gt; training volume I have had in a single week in years. I&amp;rsquo;ll confess that this has taken a toll on me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result, I have backed off this week, such that including this 12-mile run (I will not run tomorrow), this week I will have 23 miles. In the long haul, &lt;em&gt;overtraining&lt;/em&gt; is a huge waste of time and energy. Unfortunately, in my attempt to &amp;ldquo;catch up&amp;rdquo; some because of the marathon coming in less than two months, I did in fact overtrain to an extent; last week I ran five out of seven days in order to reach that mileage of 26. This week, I tried to up the mileage but felt tired and wisely decided to rest when I needed to, even though that meant this week I ran only three days! Obviously, in retrospect, it would have been wiser to run four days last week and four this week, with better overall training.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I did enjoy today&amp;rsquo;s training run. It involved the most bridge crossings I have ever done in my life in a single day (by foot or otherwise): eleven!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is my report on the training run, including, of course, photos of bridge crossings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;sign-in&#34;&gt;Sign in&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;John and I signed in at 8 AM. It was going to be a beautiful, sunny day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We received printed maps of the route. I did have my smartphone with me, wearing it in my SPIbelt, so I felt pretty safe about knowing where I am or where to go in case I got lost.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings/sign-in.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Steel City Road Runners sign in&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There is indoor access to restrooms, water fountains, and warmth at these Steel City Road Runners training run meetings. Very nice for winter!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were designated pacers. I was uncertain about which pace group I should join, if any at all. I felt that probably the 10-minute pace group might be on the slow side, but definitely I did not expect to keep up with the 9-minute pace group for a long run. But we decided to start off with the 9-minute pace group and see what happens.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings/pace-groups.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Pacers&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I wore my Vibram FiveFingers Bikila LS shoes, which have been my main running shoes all winter (when there is no snow or water on the ground):&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings/vibram-fivefingers-bikila-ls.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin wearing Vibram FiveFingers Bikila LS&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-route&#34;&gt;The route&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is the route of the 12-mile training run:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe id=&#34;mapmyfitness_route&#34; src=&#34;http://snippets.mapmycdn.com/routes/view/embedded/178234904?width=560&amp;height=400&amp;elevation=true&amp;info=true&amp;line_color=E60f0bdb&amp;rgbhex=DB0B0E&amp;distance_markers=1&amp;unit_type=imperial&amp;map_mode=TERRAIN&amp;last_updated=2013-03-08T12:47:36-06:00&#34; height=&#34;590px&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: right; padding-right: 20px;&#34;&gt;&lt;a target=&#34;_blank&#34; href=&#34;http://mapmyrun.com/routes/create/&#34;&gt;Create Maps&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a target=&#34;_blank&#34; href=&#34;http://mapmyrun.com/routes/&#34;&gt;search&lt;/a&gt; from 80 million at &lt;a href=&#34;http://mapmyrun.com&#34;&gt;MapMyRun&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-bridge-crossings&#34;&gt;The bridge crossings&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 9-minute pace group was clearly going too fast for me. I hung off the back hoping to simply keep them in sight as they kept getting more ahead of me. To my surprise, John went with the group, even though he has not run in months. I was not sure it was wise of him not to have done any running before this training run, and am worried about his going too fast all of a sudden.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings/on-our-way.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;nine-minute pace group&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;rachel-carson-bridge-inbound-over-the-allegheny-river&#34;&gt;Rachel Carson Bridge, inbound over the Allegheny River&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings/rachel-carson-bridge.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;On Rachel Carson Bridge inbound&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We can see downtown Pittsburgh:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings/rachel-carson-bridge-see-downtown.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;On Rachel Carson Bridge, seeing downtown&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;7th-street-bridge-outbound&#34;&gt;7th Street Bridge, outbound&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings/7th-street-bridge.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;On 7th Street Bridge outbound&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;roberto-clemente-bridge-inbound&#34;&gt;Roberto Clemente Bridge, inbound&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings/roberto-clemente-bridge.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Approaching Roberto Clemente Bridge inbound&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;fort-duquesne-bridge-outbound&#34;&gt;Fort Duquesne Bridge, outbound&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings/fort-duquesne-bridge.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;On Fort Duquesne Bridge outbound&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;west-end-bridge-south-over-the-monongahela-river&#34;&gt;West End Bridge, south over the Monongahela River&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings/west-end-bridge.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;On West End Bridge south&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;first-water-stop-and-getting-lost&#34;&gt;First water stop and getting lost!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our first water stop was after 4 miles:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings/first-water-stop.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;First water stop&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;By the time I had reached this water stop, John and the rest of the 9-minute pace group were way ahead of me and barely visible. Unfortunately, after I drank some Gatorade, I noticed that I didn&amp;rsquo;t see them at all any more. So for almost the rest of the run, the following 8 miles, I was mostly alone! This was disconcerting because it meant that I&amp;rsquo;d have to try to follow the printed map and directions, and avoid getting lost. It would turn out that I would get lost a couple of times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;fort-pitt-bridge-inbound&#34;&gt;Fort Pitt Bridge, inbound&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings/fort-pitt-bridge.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;On Fort Pitt Bridge inbound&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;smithfield-street-bridge-outbound&#34;&gt;Smithfield Street Bridge, outbound&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings/smithfield-street-bridge.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;On Smithfield Street Bridge outbound&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Check out this view of bridges along the Monongahela River:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings/monongahela-river.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Monongahela River&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;10th-street-bridge-inbound&#34;&gt;10th Street Bridge, inbound&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leaving the South Side:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings/10th-street-bridge.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;On 10th Street Bridge inbound&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;liberty-bridge-outbound&#34;&gt;Liberty Bridge, outbound&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not having anyone to follow, I got confused about how to get onto the Liberty Bridge, missing the steps, and had to do some backtracking to find the way to get on.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings/liberty-bridge-outbound.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;On Liberty Bridge outbound&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;to-mount-washington&#34;&gt;To Mount Washington&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This training run featured a big, long uphill to Mount Washington, with a water stop at the very top!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings/to-mount-washington.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;To Mount Washington&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;After being alone for quite some time, I did encounter John and other runners coming back down Mount Washington when I was still going up. They were going really fast downhill!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings/up-to-mount-washington.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Uphill to Mount Washington&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;second-water-stop&#34;&gt;Second water stop&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My phone started acting funny when I got to the water stop at the top of Mount Washington, so I did not bother to try take any more photos after that. I was bummed that I didn&amp;rsquo;t get a photo of the view of Pittsburgh from the top, but someone did and posted it on Facebook, so here it is:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://sphotos-b.xx.fbcdn.net/hphotos-ash3/602768_422297731198378_798317370_n.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;View from Mount Washington&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At this water stop, at mile 9, I felt hungry, and saw some GU gels, and took one and ate it before continuing my run. It was &lt;a href=&#34;http://guenergy.com/products/products-roctane-gels&#34;&gt;GU Roctane&lt;/a&gt;. I didn&amp;rsquo;t look at the ingredients till after I got home and did a Web search on it. That explained a lot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While running down from Mount Washington, I felt a surge of energy and decided to run really, really fast, in hope of possibly catching sight of John at some point. In fact, I did not see any runner again for the next 3 miles until I reached the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;back-across-the-liberty-bridge-inbound&#34;&gt;Back across the Liberty Bridge, inbound&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then running through downtown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;16th-street-bridge-outbound&#34;&gt;16th Street Bridge outbound&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was kind of zoned out and missed the turn onto the bridge because I was just running fast, but luckily, I was off by just a block before I realized my mistake and backtracked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-end&#34;&gt;The end&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got back to the start in a bit less than two hours, so given my rest stops and getting lost, I definitely averaged under 10-minute pace. But I was definitely not running anywhere near 9-minute pace. I&amp;rsquo;ll keep that in my mind for the next training run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;John had finished well before me, but he himself had gotten lost near the end also.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We snacked on provided orange slices and chips:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings/after.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Steel City Road Runners snacks&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings/franklin.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Then I drove us back to our places. After both of us had showered and changed, we met up for lunch buffet at Coriander India Grill, a favorite place to eat &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/02/26/snowing-means-sambar-at-coriander-india-grill/&#34;&gt;after getting very hungry after a lot of exercise&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-next&#34;&gt;What next?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next week will be an 18-mile training run. As I have mentioned, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/02/24/2013-pittsburgh-marathon-training-progress-since-signing-up-three-weeks-ago/&#34;&gt;I do not intend to actually do such a long run&lt;/a&gt;, so I will think of a good way to run 16 miles instead: either I start walking earlier, or I walk near the end. And for sure, I will start with the 10-minute pace group rather than then 9-minute pace group. These training runs are not races. I don&amp;rsquo;t want to run too fast. In fact, I&amp;rsquo;m worried that I ran the last 3 miles today too fast, especially downhill from Mount Washington. My left knee is feeling a little funny. I hope it will recover after a day of rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve started to figure out the gel thing. I used eat gels a decade ago, but stopped because I had no reason to, but on these long runs, they do help, and I have to start planning what to use for fuel in the Pittsburgh Marathon, which will officially supply GU gel and Gatorade. I did learn, after the fact, that GU Roctane contains an insane amount of caffeine, and that&amp;rsquo;s probably what got me all hopped up to run super fast, but to my detriment today. So I need to be careful if I use Roctane in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a very instructive and tiring training run. I have a long way to go before being ready for the marathon in less than two months, but am happy to have finally joined a group training run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m very grateful for the opportunity to train with the Steel City Road Runners. Sometimes, it is much easier to commit to getting up early and going for a long run when you know that you&amp;rsquo;ll have company, that there will be support (in the form of a planned route and aid stations). Even for an introvert like me who usually prefers to run alone, the unique pains of marathon training cause me to value camaraderie for some tough runs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>