<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Treadmill on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/treadmill/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Treadmill on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/treadmill/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Why I have never considered using a treadmill desk</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/06/10/why-i-have-never-considered-using-a-treadmill-desk/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jun 2015 21:34:04 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/06/10/why-i-have-never-considered-using-a-treadmill-desk/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Ten years ago, in 2005, a friend of mine sent me an article about a
trend among some people to use a treadmill desk in order to squeeze in
some exercise while working. He seemed to think it sounded like a cool
idea that wouldn&amp;rsquo;t interfere much with work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have never considered using a treadmill desk. Because of a recent
article that seems to confirm my thoughts from a decade ago, I&amp;rsquo;m
posting my reaction here, along with a link to the article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-response-in-january-2005&#34;&gt;My response in January 2005&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At one point years ago I was thinking about stuff like that, but a few
experiments showed how pointless and soulless it is, for me.  My
enjoyment of exercise is completely ruined if extraneous stuff is
brought in, like reading or listening to music.  I learned that the
whole profound pleasure and meaning of physical activity comes from
being completely engaged in it, with nothing else on the mind.  So the
former fantasies of multitasking are now completely antithetical to my
current life values.

&lt;p&gt;
It&#39;s not the quantity [of treadmill movement] that&#39;s the issue.
That&#39;s still one foot per second of continuous movement, requiring
irrelevant constant muscular pulses.  Note that I cannot read a simple
newspaper in a car or a bus or a plane.

&lt;p&gt;
I fidget all the time, especially when playing chess, but the
movements are not arbitrary and disembodied, but are connected with
feelings of comfort or with emotional states relevant to my mental
processes.  It&#39;s not like a treadmill commanding me to go a foot every
second.  It&#39;s my personal choice when to shake my leg or shift my foot
or whatever, and for how long.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;philosophy-and-practice&#34;&gt;Philosophy and practice&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may be wondering, from how I phrased my reasons, whether I have a
primarily theoretical, ideological opposition to a treadmill desk, or
simply a pragmatic one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t really make a distinction: I take what works and doesn&amp;rsquo;t work
and make my observations a basis for a possibly more general
philosophy, rather than adopt an ideology and make my practice fit it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically, I actually have &lt;em&gt;tried&lt;/em&gt; multitasking in various ways for
the purpose of &amp;ldquo;saving time&amp;rdquo; and it just doesn&amp;rsquo;t work for
me. Furthermore, sometimes I multitask &lt;em&gt;despite knowing it doesn&amp;rsquo;t
work&lt;/em&gt;, and I pay the price. For example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I have tripped or fallen on runs or hikes when I &amp;ldquo;zoned out&amp;rdquo; and
wasn&amp;rsquo;t paying attention to the terrain but was thinking of something!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I have listened to music while reading a news article and failed to
follow the music at all.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s not saving time if I try to do two things and end up not even
doing one of them well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-research&#34;&gt;The research&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The article I just read was a news article,
&lt;a href=&#34;http://well.blogs.nytimes.com/2015/06/10/the-downside-of-treadmill-desks/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The downside of treadmill desks&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. I
was pretty shocked and amused to read, &amp;ldquo;&amp;hellip; surprisingly little
research had examined whether treadmill desks affect someone’s ability
to get work done.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The results, when the researchers compared the treadmill walkers with the people sitting at their desks, substantially favored sitting. The people who had walked during the testing performed worse on almost all aspects of thinking, including the ability to concentrate and remember, compared with those who had been seated.

&lt;p&gt;
And they were much worse at typing, being substantially slower and
more error prone than the sitting group.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The irony is that the researcher interviewed still wants to believe in
benefits:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
But even with that caveat, he said, he believes that the health
benefits of a treadmill desk should outweigh any declines in
productivity and, in fact, he plans to buy one for himself.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;alternatives&#34;&gt;Alternatives?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My alternative to sitting all day, which indeed is by now known to be
terrible for health, is simple:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get up now and then and take a break from my task and walk around.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But doesn&amp;rsquo;t this take time and stop the flow of work? Actually,
no. There&amp;rsquo;s only so much focus I can have while working on something
continuously without a break anyway. So forcing myself to take a walk
is actually a win-win situation, not even just a mere tradeoff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Treadmill desks do not appeal to me at all, and I believe I have sound
scientific reasons based on what psychology has learned about the
working of the human mind. However, I understand that different
people&amp;rsquo;s minds may work differently from mine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Have you used a treadmill desk? Why or why not? Do you believe in
your ability to multitask without a performance hit?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to enjoy treadmill running: treat it as a meditative practice</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/01/05/how-to-enjoy-treadmill-running-treat-it-as-a-meditative-practice/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jan 2012 22:42:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/01/05/how-to-enjoy-treadmill-running-treat-it-as-a-meditative-practice/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today I decided to do some treadmill &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/running/&#34;&gt;running&lt;/a&gt;, since I was going to the gym to do some strength training anyway, so I did just two miles of running as a &amp;ldquo;warmup&amp;rdquo; there, using my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/01/02/new-experiment-for-a-new-year-winter-running-in-vibram-fivefingers-shoes/&#34;&gt;Bikila LS shoes&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t much like treadmills, so why did I deliberately plan to run on one?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a blog post two months ago, I was critical of the idea of &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/04/against-just-putting-in-the-time/&#34;&gt;slogging through a treadmill workout as an unpleasant, mindless chore&lt;/a&gt; and mentioned some ways that I have tried in the past to make the most of treadmill running. I think the last time I ran on a treadmill may well have been two years ago (unfortunately, for the past decade I have kept a paper notebook exercise log, and still have not converted to a searchable digital one, which I perhaps should). So I wanted to try it again, as a &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/meditation/&#34;&gt;meditative practice&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-treadmill&#34;&gt;The treadmill&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was &amp;ldquo;surprised&amp;rdquo; to find that the treadmills in the gym are now equipped with what seems to be a TV screen attached just above the usual display (of pace, calories, incline, etc.) and a headphone jack so that you can watch and listen to TV by bringing in your own headphones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was at first rather annoyed that the addition of the display on top meant that it was no longer the case that I could look out the window that the treadmill was placed in front of. In past years when I used treadmills more often, I liked to pick the one in this particular spot precisely because it had the best view out the window. Depending on the time and season, you can see people walking outside, and running around the track, or some sports game happening. Not that I ever paid much attention, but it was &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt; going on to look at.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I realized that in fact, how is that much different from watching TV? It is different because TV programs have some kind of constructed narrative for you to attend to, while observing action outside the window is looser and not as distracting. But in a way, occasionally having my mind wander by checking out what people are doing outside goes against the &amp;ldquo;mindfulness&amp;rdquo; I have advocated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, I decided to consider the blank TV screen blocking my view a fortuitous &lt;em&gt;opportunity&lt;/em&gt; to make my treadmill running more meditative. I chuckled to myself as I thought of how I do &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/28/staring-at-the-wall-with-nowhere-to-go/&#34;&gt;meditation facing a blank wall&lt;/a&gt; anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;suggestion&#34;&gt;Suggestion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you run on a treadmill and usually distract yourself by looking at other people in the gym, or listen to music, or watch TV, or read a newspaper or book, you might want to try, for the sake of curiosity, a short meditative workout, similar to the one I describe. You only need 15-20 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;thoughts&#34;&gt;Thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To me, running on a treadmill is not much like &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zazen&#34;&gt;sitting meditation&lt;/a&gt;, but it is similar to &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kinhin&#34;&gt;walking meditation&lt;/a&gt;, which I was introduced to only less than a year ago. Because I am in a dynamic state of movement when either walking or running, my thoughts revolve around my body, my balance, my form.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My goal is to maintain good form, stay relaxed, and just experience my body in a deep way. And one thing nice about the treadmill, I have to say, is that the monotony enables me to pick up on sensations gradually, as they repeat themselves with every pair of strides. In running outside on uneven surfaces and paths, we don&amp;rsquo;t always notice what we are doing at a given moment, and then the moment passes. It is easier to notice yourself deeply when in a controlled environment such as a treadmill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;running-form&#34;&gt;Running form&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The absolute flatness of the landing surface means that I better notice asymmetries in my stride. I know my left side is weaker and tighter than my right side (and I have been gradually correcting this asymmetry over the years in various ways). So I focus on whether I&amp;rsquo;m letting my left hip release equally to my right, and where on my left foot I&amp;rsquo;m landing and where the weight transfer happens. Landing well is quite important because it is improper landing that causes knee pain, ankle pain, shin splints, the works. (From personal experience in over a decade of running, and overcoming injury, I strongly advocate a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.chirunning.com/chi-library/article/running-with-a-midfoot-strike-vs-running-on-the-balls-of-your-feet/&#34;&gt;midfoot strike&lt;/a&gt; and avoiding a heel strike.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The monotony and consistency of running on a treadmill makes it easy and even pleasant to spend some time paying attention to some particular aspect of the body movement, then moving on to another, and then maybe attempting to gain an integrated awareness. Here are some areas I focus on:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;foot strike&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;foot placement relative to hips&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;foot distance from center line bisecting left and right&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;hip tightness and release&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;rolling of ankles&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;feeling of impact: knees bad, glutes good&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;calves, hamstrings, quads: what&amp;rsquo;s being worked when?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;core trunk engaged and flexible&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;chest open and free&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;shoulders down&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;arm swings symmetric&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;breathing in regular pattern&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;feel of breath at nostrils, lips&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;head up, balanced&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;efficient stride rate&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t beat yourself up with some visualization of what the &amp;ldquo;perfect&amp;rdquo; form is (whether something you learned from a book). I find it more useful and meditative to observe, and then slowly &amp;ldquo;correct&amp;rdquo; if desired, basically experimenting with adjustments and really feeling what the results are. Our bodies are all different, and frankly, we all have some fundamental asymmetries that we need to work around and accept rather than try to eradicate by force.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Attending to all these body areas and motions briefly, bit by bit, the time does not pass quite as slowly for me as when just letting my thoughts roam about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;speed&#34;&gt;Speed&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like to start out on a treadmill by walking slowly, to warm up, and gradually increasing the pace until I am jogging. Then I continue gradually increasing the pace until I get into an easy aerobic zone. Depending on my goals and length of the workout, I may just stay there or crank things up more and more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I happen not to like going very fast (say, mile race pace or faster) on a treadmill. The unnaturalness of the environment seems to cause me to feel awkward and in danger of injury. I don&amp;rsquo;t have these problems when running comparably fast on the track outside. I think the forces generated are very different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel mostly OK going steadily at my &lt;a href=&#34;http://runningtimes.com/Article.aspx?ArticleID=7479&#34;&gt;lactate threshold pace&lt;/a&gt; on a treadmill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aside from the body mechanics of going faster, I find that my thoughts get more frantic, as I start worrying about things that never occur to me when I&amp;rsquo;m running somewhere rather than going nowhere. For example, I happen to worry about slipping further back on the belt and maybe tripping off the end. This has happened to me in the past on longer treadmill runs where I have zoned out; zoning out is definitely not &amp;ldquo;mindful&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t enjoy the coercive sensation of being forced physically to keep exactly a certain pace &amp;ldquo;or else&amp;rdquo;. That plus the fragmentation of my attention toward my body results in a challenge to my meditative state. Obviously, the challenge can be considered an &lt;em&gt;opportunity&lt;/em&gt; as well, but it&amp;rsquo;s not one I&amp;rsquo;m taking up right now anyway while I&amp;rsquo;m just doing some easy running.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;distractions&#34;&gt;Distractions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the gym, people are always coming and going. Sometimes they grunt or drop weights. Sometimes there are lines for the treadmills. There are often people on neighboring treadmills. It is easy to be self-conscious in a gym and think silly thoughts such as, do I look like a loser with my bad form or slow speed setting or wimpy set of weights. These distractions are also an &lt;em&gt;opportunity&lt;/em&gt;, to find acceptance of self and others, and realize that we&amp;rsquo;re all here together, with our own shapes and sizes, taking a break from the computer and the couch, using our bodies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The muzak is constant. Luckily, it&amp;rsquo;s not too loud. Still, it&amp;rsquo;s distracting when the muzak at some point is going at a steady beat that is different from my stride rate. Should I match it? Sometimes I do for a while, if I feel I&amp;rsquo;m plodding and the muzak is faster. But that&amp;rsquo;s a kind of distraction. Generally I do not let the muzak get to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My brief treadmill run today, facing a blank TV screen, went OK. I will probably be doing more and perhaps longer treadmill runs once every couple of days this winter, although I plan to try an extended outdoors run this weekend. And I will continue to stare at the blank screen and try to make the most of my runs as meditative experiences.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>