<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Cavaquinho on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/cavaquinho/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Cavaquinho on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/cavaquinho/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Was that a ukulele I heard in Frick Park? No, a cavaquinho</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/06/was-that-a-ukulele-i-heard-in-frick-park-no-a-cavaquinho/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Oct 2013 14:19:09 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/06/was-that-a-ukulele-i-heard-in-frick-park-no-a-cavaquinho/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I had just run into Frick Park past the blue slide playground entrance when I thought I heard someone playing a ukulele! I looked around and saw a guy sitting on a park bench. I thought of approaching him, but decided not to interrupt my run, and kept going.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s what Frick Park looked today on a trail, with some fallen leaves. Bizarre that it&amp;rsquo;s still summer temperatures right now though.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/frick-park-2013-10-06.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Frick Park trail with fallen leaves&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When I came back around out of the trails, I saw the guy again and he was packing up to leave, so I approached him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out to be Ben, to whom &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/01/run-shadyside-5k-outrunning-mickey-mouse-and-lending-a-trumpet/&#34;&gt;I had lent a trumpet two years ago&lt;/a&gt; (since returned)! I asked him if the instrument in his case was a ukulele. He said no. I asked if it was a guitar. He said no. It was a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cavaquinho&#34;&gt;cavaquinho&lt;/a&gt;, the Portuguese ancestor of the Hawaiian ukulele! He pulled it out of the case and let me check it out. It&amp;rsquo;s tuned differently from the ukulele:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/cavaquinho.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Ben&amp;#39;s cavaquinho&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I had heard of this instrument, from reading something about the history of the ukulele (in particular, I had looked at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.coolhanduke.com/worldukehistory.html&#34;&gt;Cool Hand Uke&amp;rsquo;s booklet on ukulele history&lt;/a&gt; recently). Also, Handerson (who is from Brazil) had asked me if I knew where to buy a cavaquinho. Ben said he was looking for other cavaquinho players in Pittsburgh, so I sent him Handerson&amp;rsquo;s contact information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So no, I was not just hallucinating &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/10/05/performing-with-the-steel-city-ukuleles-at-the-wilkins-school-community-center-ecofest-2013-with-videos/&#34;&gt;post-ukulele-gig&lt;/a&gt; when I thought I heard a ukulele in Frick Park.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You never know what or who you might encounter in the park on a nice day.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>