<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Squirrel Hill on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/squirrel-hill/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Squirrel Hill on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/squirrel-hill/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>The growth of loyalty after seventeen years</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/07/22/the-growth-of-loyalty-after-seventeen-years/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2014 21:44:11 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/07/22/the-growth-of-loyalty-after-seventeen-years/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Tonight I finally got a haircut.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For two weeks I&amp;rsquo;d been looking for my &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/barber/&#34;&gt;barber&lt;/a&gt; Joe, of Harry&amp;rsquo;s Barber Shoppe in Squirrel Hill; I was due for my haircut. I&amp;rsquo;d called Joe&amp;rsquo;s phone number from work in the afternoon. I&amp;rsquo;d driven by on the way home (the shop is just a block away from home). I&amp;rsquo;d taken a walk on Saturday to see if he was open. No sign of him. I was worried. I began imagining the worst.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not kidding when I tell people that I don&amp;rsquo;t know what I&amp;rsquo;d do without Joe to cut my hair. He&amp;rsquo;s been the only one to cut my hair in the past seventeen years, apart from that one time he broke his hand and was out of commission for a while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first thought when I wondered whether Joe was OK was, if he was gone, I would miss not only a great cut (after the first couple of times in 1997, he figured out how to do things just the way I like), but also some kind of relationship. Since Joe is a lot older than me, I know that one day I will have to find a new barber; I was just thinking that when that day comes, I don&amp;rsquo;t want just a haircut, but I want some kind of relationship. Joe doesn&amp;rsquo;t just cut my hair. He asks me how my life is going; he was there before I was married, and now he inquires about Abby, whom he&amp;rsquo;s met, that time when I was waiting so long for my turn that she walked over and brought me dinner. He knows the structure of my head and the properties of my hair more than I do. We take turns guessing who&amp;rsquo;s singing the songs on his favorite radio station; I&amp;rsquo;ve absorbed some of his oldies into my consciousness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;lucky&#34;&gt;Lucky&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The whole haircut experience is about much more than my walking out with less hair. That&amp;rsquo;s why I was relieved to find him accidentally after an evening run in Frick Park that ended with my spotting in the distance the light in Joe&amp;rsquo;s shop and stopping by and seeing him there. It was already late in the evening, nearly 8:00 PM already, but he said he would take me (he was finishing up one guy in the chair), so I ran back home to change out of my running gear and get my wallet and return to the shop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joe said he was OK. He&amp;rsquo;s continued to have back trouble and reduced his work, but he&amp;rsquo;s still around. It does not even occur to me to get angry with him for causing me to look for him for two weeks. I&amp;rsquo;m simply grateful he&amp;rsquo;s OK and able to work and cheerful. He thanks me for being patient and returning to him again and again. That is all. The rest is philosophical banter about what is important in life, and chuckling to myself as I easily identify &amp;ldquo;drunky&amp;rdquo; Dean Martin on the radio singing &amp;ldquo;Ain&amp;rsquo;t That a Kick in the Head?&amp;rdquo; Such a dated song, I think, but it has a certain charm and who else could sing it in perfect character besides Dean Martin?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/2zBszbgkH8g&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;questions&#34;&gt;Questions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Are you loyal to someone who cuts your hair? What would you do (or have done) if that person is no longer present in your life?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A haircut leading to my playing &#34;I&#39;ll Always Love You&#34; on flute</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/08/08/a-haircut-leading-to-my-playing-ill-always-love-you-on-flute/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Aug 2013 22:17:12 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/08/08/a-haircut-leading-to-my-playing-ill-always-love-you-on-flute/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/haircut-2013-08-08/floor.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;New floor&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/haircut-2013-08-08/wall.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Celebrity wall&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I got a haircut from my barber Joe, whom I have been seeing &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/29/my-favorite-barber/&#34;&gt;for sixteen years now&lt;/a&gt; since moving to Pittsburgh. Unexpectedly, this led me to &amp;ldquo;discovering&amp;rdquo; a piece of music and going home to play it on flute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was happy to arrive with only one other person in line, just getting into the chair, because Joe has a policy of not taking reservations, and &amp;ldquo;if you leave, you lose your turn&amp;rdquo;:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/haircut-2013-08-08/lose-your-turn.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Lose your turn&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In practice, Joe usually takes 20-25 minutes per person, I figured on being out within 50 minutes. Since I was pretty exhausted because of a tough week, I took the opportunity to do some napping. In practice, I don&amp;rsquo;t really sleep, but do get rest. Since Joe always has his oldies radio station on, I try to enjoy the music (which is not the kind of music I ordinarily listen to these days) and identify songs and singers I recognize.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;music&#34;&gt;Music&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I heard someone sing a song that I recognized but had never truly known. I think it&amp;rsquo;s a beautiful song, actually (from a melodic and harmonic point of view), although horribly cheesy if you pay attention to the lyrics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recognized the song as being in &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/17/st-patricks-day-party-playing-tin-whistle-and-flute/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;I Used to Play Flute&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, although I did not remember the title. I did remember really enjoying playing it on flute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this evening, after dinner, I found the song in the book. It&amp;rsquo;s called &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/I%27ll_Always_Love_You_%28Taylor_Dayne_song%29&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;ll Always Love You&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. I played through the song with the CD track accompaniment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also looked for a sung performance on YouTube, and found one, by the musician who actually created it in 1987, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.taylordayne.com/&#34;&gt;Taylor Dayne&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/0bGdnMnq40s&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t think this this is who I heard on Joe&amp;rsquo;s radio station. Taylor Dayne sings more wildly than whoever was on the radio (or maybe in my half-asleep state, I wasn&amp;rsquo;t paying enough attention). This is not the kind of music I was listening to in 1988, and I have to confess I cringed when watching this video, because although the performance is quite good, her style of singing is just not really to my taste! I prefer the song as an instrumental.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;tito-nieves&#34;&gt;Tito Nieves&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was very amused to find a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jukebo.com/tito-nieves/music-clip,i-ll-always-love-you,u8quz.html&#34;&gt;salsa cover of this song&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tito_Nieves&#34;&gt;Tito Nieves&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s pretty good, actually:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;width:480px;&#34;&gt;&lt;iframe src=&#34;http://www.ultimedia.com/swf/iframe_pub.php?width=480&amp;height=385&amp;id=u8quz&amp;url_artist=http://www.jukebo.com/tito-nieves/music-clip,i-ll-always-love-you,u8quz.html&amp;autoplay=0&amp;mdtk=04516441&amp;site=.fr&#34; width=&#34;480&#34; height=&#34;385&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; scrolling=&#34;no&#34; marginwidth=&#34;0&#34; marginheight=&#34;0&#34; hspace=&#34;0&#34; vspace=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;SPAN style=&#34;color:#000000; font:bold 11px verdana;&#34;&gt;See all &lt;/SPAN&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jukebo.com/tito-nieves/music-clip,i-ll-always-love-you,u8quz.html&#34; style=&#34;color:#000000;text-decoration:underline;  font:bold 11px verdana;&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;music videos Tito Nieves&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;haircut-photos&#34;&gt;Haircut photos&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, I was delighted not only to have gotten a haircut, but also learned something about a piece of music that had up till now only been a CD track and a flute part that I had played through months ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/haircut-2013-08-08/before.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin before haircut&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;After:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/haircut-2013-08-08/after.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin after haircut&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Attending J-Jam in Squirrel Hill but not playing music in it</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/02/10/attending-j-jam-in-squirrel-hill-but-not-playing-music-in-it/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Feb 2013 23:23:13 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/02/10/attending-j-jam-in-squirrel-hill-but-not-playing-music-in-it/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://d2bm3ljpacyxu8.cloudfront.net/width/496/crop/0,0,496x661/jjampgh.webs.com/jjam%20feb%202013.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;February 10 2013 J-Jam flyer&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Today in Dunkin&amp;rsquo; Donuts in Squirrel Hill was another &lt;a href=&#34;http://jjampgh.webs.com/&#34;&gt;J-Jam&lt;/a&gt; of music. I&amp;rsquo;d performed in a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/10/28/singing-and-playing-bossa-nova-favorite-chega-de-saudade-at-dunkin-donuts-for-j-jam/&#34;&gt;J-Jam in October over three months ago&lt;/a&gt;, but did not perform or attend the J-Jam in December. This time, I again did not perform, but did attend with Abby to watch and listen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason I did not perform is that I came back from a &lt;a href=&#34;http://nescala.org/&#34;&gt;Scala conference&lt;/a&gt; just &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/02/10/ne-scala-2013-my-first-scala-conference/&#34;&gt;late yesterday night&lt;/a&gt;, so I was yet again too busy to meet up with Ben to prepare something to perform, and also even if we had something, I was not confident I would be up to performing just after coming home. I was right: I came home exhausted and slept in today before making it to J-Jam at all.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/j-jam-2013-02-10/j-jam.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;J-Jam&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I was glad we did attend, however, because it&amp;rsquo;s so wonderful to see local musicians come together and have fun. As a reminder, this community event also serves as a fundraiser for the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sqfoodpantry.org/&#34;&gt;Squirrel Hill Food Pantry&lt;/a&gt;: donations are accepted at J-Jam.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby had to leave early, and I myself did not stay until the very end, but saw most of the performances, and left very happy. I hope that later this year I&amp;rsquo;ll perform in it again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you, &lt;a href=&#34;http://cantorben.com/&#34;&gt;Ben&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.boulevardoftheallies.com/&#34;&gt;Joel&lt;/a&gt;, for putting this together again!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2013-03-03&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-03-03)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out a recent article in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.thejewishchronicle.net/view/full_story/21685320/article-Performing-for-tzedaka&#34;&gt;The Jewish Chronicle&lt;/a&gt; about the event, without a video clip.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My favorite Uncle Sam&#39;s sub</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/12/08/my-favorite-uncle-sams-sub/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Dec 2012 21:24:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/12/08/my-favorite-uncle-sams-sub/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Last Sunday, after a long first rehearsal for the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/11/24/preparing-to-play-irish-flute-in-the-holiday-ball/&#34;&gt;Holiday Ball Orchestra&lt;/a&gt;, I was starving, and since Abby was off in Weirton performing in a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pittsburghmandolinsociety.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Mandolin Orchestra&lt;/a&gt;, I decided to indulge in a dinner alone at the local &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.unclesamssubs.com/&#34;&gt;Uncle Sam&amp;rsquo;s Subs&lt;/a&gt; in Squirrel Hill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been eating at Uncle Sam&amp;rsquo;s Subs periodically since moving to Pittsburgh 15 years ago. I&amp;rsquo;ve tried all the options (I ate out a lot more during my early grad school days in Pittsburgh), including, during my vegetarian phase, the really tasty Mediterranean, Vegetarian Combo, Roma Vegetable, Vegetable Florentine, and Grilled Portabella subs (see the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.unclesamssubs.com/menu&#34;&gt;menu&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nowadays I indulge in an Uncle Sam&amp;rsquo;s sub only maybe two or three times a year, as a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/06/16/the-joy-of-eating-ice-cream-for-breakfast/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;cheat&amp;rdquo; meal&lt;/a&gt; when I&amp;rsquo;m feeling the big craving for one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; eat in, because they give you a whole bunch of fries for free when you eat in rather than take out. For me, it&amp;rsquo;s all about the fries!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve settled on the Uncle Sam&amp;rsquo;s Special Steak as my usual selection these days, because it strikes a good balance of cheese steak, mushrooms, peppers, and cheese.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;before-and-after-photos&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Before&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;after&amp;rdquo; photos&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Uncle Sam&amp;rsquo;s Special steak:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/uncle-sams-subs/uneaten.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Uncle Sam&amp;#39;s Special Steak&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I ate the whole thing! It took me some time:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/uncle-sams-subs/eaten.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Finished eating&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I was very satisfied afterwards.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/uncle-sams-subs/franklin.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Full Franklin&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I totally recommend Uncle Sam&amp;rsquo;s Subs if you&amp;rsquo;re very hungry and need to refuel. Whether you&amp;rsquo;re an omnivore or a vegetarian, check it out! Eat in for the fries. And make sure to get your metabolism up by exercising or something beforehand, because else you&amp;rsquo;ll get carb coma.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Singing and playing bossa nova favorite &#34;Chega de Saudade&#34; at Dunkin&#39; Donuts for J-Jam</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/10/28/singing-and-playing-bossa-nova-favorite-chega-de-saudade-at-dunkin-donuts-for-j-jam/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Oct 2012 00:54:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/10/28/singing-and-playing-bossa-nova-favorite-chega-de-saudade-at-dunkin-donuts-for-j-jam/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/j-jam-2012-10-28/5.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;CMU Klezmer Band performing&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Yesterday evening, I ended up unexpectedly &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/10/27/singing-an-irish-ballad-as-an-asian-pirate-at-a-halloween-belly-dance-hafla/&#34;&gt;singing alone in public for the first time in my life&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This evening, I ended up unexpectedly singing again, with guitarist &lt;a href=&#34;http://cantorben.com/&#34;&gt;Cantor Ben Rosner&lt;/a&gt; accompanying me: the first time in my life singing with an accompanist for the general public, and the first time I&amp;rsquo;ve worked with a guitarist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had just met for the first time this evening, and had only a minute ahead of time to agree on a suitable tempo and have him quickly sight read chords before we just launched into the music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had not come to the local Dunkin&amp;rsquo; Donuts in Squirrel Hill expecting to &lt;em&gt;sing&lt;/em&gt; at all, actually! What happened?!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-story-behind-the-jam-session-at-dunkin-donuts&#34;&gt;The story behind the jam session at Dunkin&amp;rsquo; Donuts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby had recently just met a new guy playing in the [Pittsburgh Mandolin Orchestra], &lt;a href=&#34;http://cantorben.wix.com/cantor-benjamin-rosner&#34;&gt;Cantor Ben Rosner&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bethshalompgh.org/&#34;&gt;Congregation Beth Shalom&lt;/a&gt; in Squirrel Hill. He was passing out flyers advertising a music jam session he was organizing, &amp;ldquo;J-Jam&amp;rdquo;, to be held tonight in the local Dunkin&amp;rsquo; Donuts, which happens to be &lt;a href=&#34;http://triblive.com/home/1926901-74/hill-squirrel-dunkin-donuts-kosher-pittsburgh-says-area-jewish-restaurant&#34;&gt;the only Dunkin&amp;rsquo; Donuts in the area that is certified kosher&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apparently this was not the first &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.thejewishchronicle.net/view/full_story/19127215/article-Open-mic-night-draws-Jewish-performers-to-Dunkin%E2%80%99-Donuts?instance=news_special_coverage_right_column&#34;&gt;Jewish community oriented music jam held at Dunkin&amp;rsquo; Donuts&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-01-16&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-01-16)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;J-Jam now has its own &lt;a href=&#34;http://jjampgh.webs.com/&#34;&gt;official Web site&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.facebook.com/jjamPGH&#34;&gt;Facebook page&lt;/a&gt;. Check them out!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;deciding-to-participate&#34;&gt;Deciding to participate&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I hear about music jams, I get excited as well as nervous. I always feel that I wish I were a much better musician than I am now, so that I don&amp;rsquo;t always feel that I&amp;rsquo;m the &lt;em&gt;worst&lt;/em&gt; one at these events, but at the same time, I learn so much from just being out there, both to enjoy hearing other musicians, and to study how they do what they do, and in turn try to provide something of my own soul to other musicians and the audience as well. It&amp;rsquo;s like being naked; it&amp;rsquo;s still really tough for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I was intrigued because, well, Dunkin&amp;rsquo; Donuts should be pretty low key, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had spread the word to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.andrew.cmu.edu/user/lukas/pcars/Welcome.html&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Recorder Society&lt;/a&gt; mailing list, but nobody seemed up for participating, except Chuck said he was interested in coming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;preparation&#34;&gt;Preparation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had no time whatsoever to &amp;ldquo;prepare&amp;rdquo; for this music jam. We exchanged some emails only earlier today, in which I mentioned some music I might play, if a suitable accompanist were available. These emails were exchanged as Abby and I were at the second day of &lt;a href=&#34;http://podcamppittsburgh.com/pcpgh-7-sessions-sunday/&#34;&gt;PodCamp Pittsburgh 7&lt;/a&gt; all day. When we came home from PodCamp Pittsburgh, all we could do was crash with a long nap, eat dinner, and frantically pack up our instruments. I brought along a little binder of stuff I might play. I had told Ben that I could play stuff like Baroque flute sonata movements or bossa nova or tango or Cuban bolero.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby has been performing in music groups longer than I have, so she has her own selections at hand for her tamburas whenever desired.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;at-j-jam&#34;&gt;At J-Jam&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dunkin&amp;rsquo; Donuts was amazingly crowded. There were people of all ages, from toddlers to the elderly, sitting around listening to the live music and enjoying kosher food. It was pretty loud in there. I immediately decided that I would not play Baroque flute here. (I had brought it along with my Irish flute, modern flute, and soprano and alto recorders.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since we had arrived an hour and a half past the begin time of the music jam, we had missed no shortage of performances already, I was sure. There were musicians singing and playing guitar and cello; I saw who I presumed to be Ben Rosner accompanying on mandolin at the time:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/j-jam-2012-10-28/1.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Musicians in the middle of performing&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;meeting-ben-and-deciding-what-to-do&#34;&gt;Meeting Ben and deciding what to do&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/j-jam-2012-10-28/2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Patrons in Dunkin&amp;#39; Donuts&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;After the current musicians&amp;rsquo; set, Ben came up to Abby and me, and said we could play after a couple more groups had their turn. He asked what I wanted to play. We took a few seconds to flip through that stuff I had brought, and decided to play one of the bossa nova songs I had brought, &amp;ldquo;Chega de Saudade&amp;rdquo;: he would sight read the chords and accompany me. I chose &amp;ldquo;Chega de Saudade&amp;rdquo; because I had given a shot at it spontaneously &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/21/my-first-time-singing-bossa-nova-also-a-temporary-farewell-to-baroque-flute/&#34;&gt;at a party a month ago&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I immediately made an interesting decision: although I had originally intended to play the melody on flute, and then launch into a jazzy improvisation before concluding, I decided, based on having just &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/10/27/singing-an-irish-ballad-as-an-asian-pirate-at-a-halloween-belly-dance-hafla/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;sung&lt;/em&gt; yesterday as a pirate&lt;/a&gt;, that I was in the mood to sing, and a lot of people had been singing all evening, so I wanted to do that too. And it seemed that a voice would carry well over the conversations of the Dunkin&amp;rsquo; Donuts patrons. So I would sing the song, in Portuguese of course, and then switch into flute improvisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;a-lot-of-good-music-i-heard&#34;&gt;A lot of good music I heard&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was really impressed by the soulful performances of everyone who showed up to sing and play instruments. Really high quality stuff.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/j-jam-2012-10-28/3.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;I-forgot-her-name&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So I heard a lot of traditional songs and Klezmer (in fact, the &lt;a href=&#34;http://cmuklezmer.weebly.com/index.html&#34;&gt;CMU Klezmer Band&lt;/a&gt; was there). Not what I usually listen to or encounter, but it was really great soaking in the different kinds of music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When one of the CMU Klezmer Band guys, the clarinetist, passed out lyrics to a particularly popular song, I even sang along, stumbling through Yiddish for the first time in my life!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/j-jam-2012-10-28/4.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;CMU Klezmer Band waiting for turn&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.boulevardoftheallies.com/&#34;&gt;Joel&lt;/a&gt;, the J-Jam co-organizer who was handling the sound system throughout, performed one of his own compositions, and then one of his young guitar students performed along with him.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/j-jam-2012-10-28/7.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Joel and student&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;familiar-faces&#34;&gt;Familiar faces&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I saw a number of familiar people. In Pittsburgh, if you meet someone for the first time, it seems that there are already a lot of connections through other people you already know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Roz, whom &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/24/roaring-like-a-lion-on-a-saturday-morning/&#34;&gt;I last saw over a year ago when she was trying to sell accordions&lt;/a&gt; did some singing with the CMU Klezmer Band.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://betterfly.com/75586018&#34;&gt;Cindy Harris&lt;/a&gt;, who played autoharp so beautifully at &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/28/another-french-music-jam-also-announcing-cats-dance/&#34;&gt;one of the French music jams I&amp;rsquo;ve gone to&lt;/a&gt; did some solo pieces on autoharp:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/j-jam-2012-10-28/8.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Cindy Harris on autoharp&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At some point, Chuck from Pittsburgh recorder showed up. He wasn&amp;rsquo;t here to play, but came to watch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;abby-played-while-ben-and-i-figured-stuff-out&#34;&gt;Abby played while Ben and I figured stuff out&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Abby took her turn playing some pieces solo on tambura, Ben and I ducked to the back of the store for a minute so that we could agree on a tempo as well as have him sight read the chord progressions of &amp;ldquo;Chega de Saudade&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;ben-and-me&#34;&gt;Ben and me&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ben and I returned, and set up quickly (we were the last set for the night other than a guy who was going to play some solo violin to close).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I felt pretty awkward trying to sing &amp;ldquo;Chega de Saudade&amp;rdquo; for the first time in public, and in front of a microphone, while trying to read the Portuguese lyrics off a printout I had. (Note to self: I need to memorize these lyrics once and for all.) Ben and I had a go at it, and of course we made some mistakes, but that was expected. Then came time for me to grab my flute and improvise. Under pressure, I was less creative and accurate than I am when just improvising at home, unfortunately, but I&amp;rsquo;ll learn in time to deal with the difference in setting. Also, I botched up a place to return to, so there was confusion for a moment as Ben and I found a way to gracefully end somewhere!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;just-me&#34;&gt;Just me&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided to play one more piece, solo, that I thought I would do a lot better than the bossa nova experiment, so I got my Irish flute and chose spontaneously, while flipping through my binder, to play &amp;ldquo;Waltz in the House&amp;rdquo; by Emile Benoit. I love this beautiful song, and learned it half a year ago at my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/04/21/my-first-time-in-a-public-music-jam-intense-fun-with-chris-norman-and-david-greenberg/&#34;&gt;first public jam session&lt;/a&gt;, when I was playing on Baroque flute at the time. But of course, tonight I chose to play it on Irish flute, and I played it with the best feeling and sonority I had in me, having played it for my own pleasure and for my baby nephew many times, always with the inflections and ornamentations I feel at the moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People seemed to like this last piece I played. I also got a lot of comments afterwards on the beauty of the tone of my &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.caseyburnsflutes.com/&#34;&gt;wooden Irish flute&lt;/a&gt;; yes, it is a lovely instrument.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-next-j-jam&#34;&gt;The next J-Jam&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next J-Jam is already scheduled for Sunday, December 16. I hope Ben and I can come up with good stuff to play together, and with more preparation!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you love music and can make it to J-Jam, please come on over to Dunkin&amp;rsquo; Donuts in Squirrel Hill then! And if you would like to perform something, email Cantor Ben Rosner at the email address in the flyer below:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/j-jam-2012-10-28/flyer-for-2012-12-16.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Flyer for J-Jam 2012-12-16&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;next&#34;&gt;Next?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m still rather unsatisfied with my singing. I&amp;rsquo;m going to work hard on getting my singing into better shape. The next music jam I&amp;rsquo;m in, I absolutely plan to be ready to sing much better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for the jazz improvisation, that&amp;rsquo;s going to take me even longer to get to where I want it. That&amp;rsquo;s going to be a major project, since I have been living mostly in the classical music world lately. But I know for sure that jazz is one place I want to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I had a great time at our first J-Jam, both listening and performing! It&amp;rsquo;s a fantastic Squirrel Hill community event that I hope will continue regularly, and I&amp;rsquo;m grateful to Joel and Ben for organizing it and spreading the word to have people come over to listen and perform, and I was inspired by the wonderful performances by everyone who came to share their love of music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I look forward to participating again!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2012-12-16&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-12-16)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did not perform in or even attend &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.facebook.com/events/347798348651757/&#34;&gt;J-Jam on December 16&lt;/a&gt; after all! It quickly became clear in early December, after I met up with Ben to play together, that I was getting way too busy with many other things, and even if I hadn&amp;rsquo;t been, Ben himself was busy too, such that we had no opportunity to get together again anyway to work on something to play. Furthermore, the time conflicted with the monthly meeting of the Pittsburgh Recorder Society, which I hate to miss, so I did not even show up at J-Jam in December just to watch and listen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-02-10&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-02-10)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did not perform in the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/02/10/attending-j-jam-in-squirrel-hill-but-not-playing-music-in-it/&#34;&gt;February 2013 J-Jam&lt;/a&gt; either, but did attend.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Your Day Without Shoes and my very first day out completely without shoes</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/06/07/your-day-without-shoes-and-my-very-first-day-out-completely-without-shoes/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Jun 2012 21:02:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/06/07/your-day-without-shoes-and-my-very-first-day-out-completely-without-shoes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/your-day-without-shoes-abby-franklin.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby and Franklin without shoes in DC&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/your-day-without-shoes-musicians.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby and Franklin without shoes in DC&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;

May 26, 2012 was &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.primalfootalliance.org/ydws/&#34;&gt;Your Day Without Shoes&lt;/a&gt;, which Abby and I tried to observe, even though we were in DC at my sister&amp;rsquo;s at the time, visiting our new &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/nephew/&#34;&gt;nephew&lt;/a&gt;, and therefore we were in an unfamiliar environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that although Abby did spend the day without shoes, I wore shoes once in the morning and then not again the rest of the day. I&amp;rsquo;ll explain why, and also describe my actual very first day without shoes (while being out and about), which was today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;ok-so-why-barefoot&#34;&gt;OK, so why barefoot??&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some reasons I&amp;rsquo;ve been experimenting with walking or running barefoot in the past year or two:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;my long history of problems with shoes of all kinds, because they mostly don&amp;rsquo;t fit me well or rub me or cause me knee and other problems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;curiosity, novelty&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a varied and heightened sensory life experience&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;working out kinks in my body balance and movement form&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;moving well barefoot is good training for moving well in shoes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t have an ideological reason for going barefoot. I am sympathetic to the idea that our feet work pretty well because of our evolutionary history, but I am not a primitivist. I am typing this at a computer, illuminated by light that is not coming from the sun or moon. I am a pragmatist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;your-day-without-shoes&#34;&gt;Your Day Without Shoes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;how-i-failed&#34;&gt;How I failed&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the official &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.primalfootalliance.org/ydws/&#34;&gt;Your Day Without Shoes&lt;/a&gt;, I had hoped to do entirely without shoes, but in the end, I chickened out and wore my trusty Vibram FiveFingers KSO shoes in a morning errand driving my brother-in-law to a grocery store, Harris Teeter, to buy food for a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/05/31/some-pretty-attacking-chess-at-a-party-last-weekend/&#34;&gt;barbecue we were going to have&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I have never been barefoot in a grocery store before, and certainly not in some unknown store I&amp;rsquo;ve never scoped out in advance, I felt it was too risky to cause possible &amp;ldquo;trouble&amp;rdquo; on a simple errand that we had to run. If there had been no time pressure and I had been alone (not inconveniencing my brother-in-law and indirectly, our party guests for the afternoon), maybe I would have given it a shot. Or maybe not, given that I have not gone barefoot in a grocery store at home in Pittsburgh yet!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have repeatedly gotten in some trouble when attempting to be barefoot in public. I am not the kind of person who likes to deliberately cause confrontations; I realize, of course, that this makes me part of the problem, not speaking up. But I get not only words and looks of disapproval, but &amp;ldquo;official&amp;rdquo;-looking people who make up painfully obvious made-up sermons about &amp;ldquo;laws&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;rules&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;health codes&amp;rdquo;. In principle, I could go out of my way to contact appropriate authorities in order to defend myself, but right now, not being a barefoot zealot but a novice experimenting, I have settled for experimenting where it is &amp;ldquo;safe&amp;rdquo; while building up my barefooting experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Safe&amp;rdquo; for me right now is roughly:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;anywhere outside a public building, such as on the streets, sidewalks, grass, parks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;at home&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;at work (while not being in a gym or library or other such place where &amp;ldquo;official&amp;rdquo; looking people go around telling people how to behave)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;in my car&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;at other people&amp;rsquo;s homes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a place I frequent where I basically know the people in charge and have inferred they&amp;rsquo;re OK with my being barefoot&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;abby-and-i-experimented-with-going-barefoot-the-rest-of-the-day&#34;&gt;Abby and I experimented with going barefoot the rest of the day&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;eastern-market&#34;&gt;Eastern Market&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I did go barefoot later in the morning, after my grocery shopping errand, when we went to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.easternmarket-dc.org/&#34;&gt;Eastern Market&lt;/a&gt;, which was hustling and bustling on a Saturday. We were there to check out the outside action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, it was very sunny and hot that day (I think the temperature was up to 90F!), and some of the outside brick and asphalt surfaces were burning hot, too hot to really walk on. We ended up looking for surfaces under shade, or painted white, to step on, but there were not many such surfaces. So we had to basically &amp;ldquo;run&amp;rdquo; in order to minimize foot contact with the ground. We didn&amp;rsquo;t last very long out there and headed back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That was a rookie mistake to have made. Well, we learn by failing small. We&amp;rsquo;re no purists about barefooting, just curious and pragmatic experimenters. No more going barefoot again in such conditions!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;evening-walk&#34;&gt;Evening walk&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a long day, cleaning up from the party, it was starting to get dark outside, and cooler, and Abby and I went out for a little walk in the neighborhood. So we went out barefoot, in keeping with the theme for the day. The walk was nice. Without the burning sun, the sidewalks and roads were just fine for walking on barefoot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby came up with the idea that when we went home, we should start doing some barefoot walking together after dinner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-very-first-day-out-without-shoes&#34;&gt;My very first day out without shoes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today was my very first day out without shoes. I hadn&amp;rsquo;t intended on that, here&amp;rsquo;s what happened:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;yesterday&#34;&gt;Yesterday&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday I went for a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/06/06/i-celebrated-national-running-day-in-schenley-park-remembering-how-i-began-to-run-13-year-ago/&#34;&gt;nice run for National Running Day&lt;/a&gt;. Usually when I run in the trails, I wear my Vibram FiveFingers KSO Trek shoes, because they give me more protection and never blister me. But yesterday I wanted to experiment (yet again) with wearing the more truly minimalist KSO shoes, which, unfortunately, have had a history of blistering me badly because of the design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The run was great, and over the months I have adapted (thanks to periodic barefooting) to landing even more subtly and efficiently so that even with the KSO shoes, I do not find the rocks or tree roots out on the trail to be too uncomfortable to deal with. Unfortunately, I still got a blister at my usual rubbing spot at the side of my big toe joint. (You may be able to spot it in the photos below.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/national-running-day-vibram-fivefingers-kso.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin&amp;#39;s Vibram FiveFingers KSO shoes&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/national-running-day-barefoot.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin&amp;#39;s Vibram FiveFingers KSO shoes&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out yesterday that because of the blister, I just didn&amp;rsquo;t want to wear any shoes for the rest of the day, and in fact I didn&amp;rsquo;t. I went barefoot from the time I finished my run to the time I left work and drove home, and I was barefoot the rest of the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;today&#34;&gt;Today&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today my blister had subsided (it will probably be &amp;ldquo;OK&amp;rdquo; tomorrow), but I still did not feel like wearing shoes. So I went to work barefoot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, it was sunny and the asphalt in the parking lot was very hot. I did what I could to ease my walk out of the parking lot to my office (basically, &amp;ldquo;run&amp;rdquo; when on hot surfaces), but frankly, it was not pleasant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went home from work barefoot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then after dinner, I ran barefoot in Squirrel Hill from home to the monthly meeting of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://pghrb.heroku.com/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Ruby&lt;/a&gt; group. Afterwards, I ran back home. So that was my day without shoes!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Little by little, I have expanded my barefooting experience, and plan to continue exploring. I find it very enjoyable and surprising that after more than a year, I am no longer very uncomfortable walking on typical city sidewalks and roads (unless there is hot direct sun involved with darker surfaces).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Snowing means sambar at Coriander India Grill</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/02/26/snowing-means-sambar-at-coriander-india-grill/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Feb 2012 12:10:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/02/26/snowing-means-sambar-at-coriander-india-grill/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/coriander-grill/store-front.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Coriander Grill&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, there was snow in Pittsburgh (almost all melted today, of course).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I had originally planned to be going on a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/pittsburghhikers/events/50162262/&#34;&gt;Meetup hike at Ohiopyle&lt;/a&gt;, carpooling with John, but on Friday we bailed out because of the weather forecast. We&amp;rsquo;ve done that hike a couple of times before, and will certainly do it again when it&amp;rsquo;s repeated in warmer weather anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Snow, however little there is of it, always makes me want to eat &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sambar_(dish)&#34;&gt;sambar&lt;/a&gt;. I love Indian food, and for some reason, I especially like sambar. Once every month or two, I crave going to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.coriandergrill.com/&#34;&gt;Coriander India Grill&lt;/a&gt; in Squirrel Hill, just a couple of blocks from where we live, to eat sambar and other good stuff. We&amp;rsquo;ve been to Coriander Grill several times, on different days and for lunch and dinner. There has been inconsistency, but I have reason to believe that lunch buffet on Saturday is a good time to go to Coriander.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/coriander-grill/sambar.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Sambar&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So the three of us went to Coriander for lunch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2014-01-13&#34;&gt;(Update of 2014-01-13)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I went to Coriander Grill for a Sunday dinner buffet yesterday, because we were hungry after a long hike, and I thought it would be a good idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We hadn&amp;rsquo;t been to Coriander for a while. They restricted their buffet days and increased the price. What we didn&amp;rsquo;t realize was that they also restricted the selection severely. Also, they kept on running out of food and not refilling frequently enough. Finally, we didn&amp;rsquo;t feel too well afterwards. I had a sleepless night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was very, very disappointed, and can no longer recommend Coriander Grill for their buffet. It is, of course, possible that their regular menu is still fine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;more-on-coriander-grill&#34;&gt;More on Coriander Grill&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The non-buffet menu at Coriander Grill is substantial. Abby and I have been there for dinner and sampled their &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Goa&#34;&gt;Goa&lt;/a&gt; Portuguese meat-based selections, for example. They also have Indian-Chinese dishes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lunch buffet is varied enough, and rotates, such that there is always something different there when we go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;preparation-for-lunch&#34;&gt;Preparation for lunch&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might be thinking, &amp;ldquo;Preparation for eating at a lunch buffet?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You bet. Eating at a buffet is &lt;em&gt;serious business&lt;/em&gt;, not to be undertaken lightly. It requires preparation of &lt;em&gt;mind, body, and spirit&lt;/em&gt;. (For amusement, check out this blog post on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://milkmiracle.net/2010/09/25/buffet/&#34;&gt;proper way to eat an an Indian buffet&lt;/a&gt;; please note that I am nowhere as &amp;ldquo;serious&amp;rdquo; as this guy, however.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;fasting&#34;&gt;Fasting&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The number one rule of eating at a buffet is, I plan to eat &lt;em&gt;a lot&lt;/em&gt;. A lot of &lt;em&gt;variety&lt;/em&gt;, and also a lot of volume. To do this effectively, fasting is necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe that &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.marksdailyapple.com/fasting/&#34;&gt;intermittent fasting&lt;/a&gt; is a good thing. I even believe that intermittent bingeing is a good thing. We are evolved to adapt to changes in food availability. Our bodies and minds are not designed to do the same thing over and over again, because then adaptation kicks in and we lose our physical and mental sharpness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that I didn&amp;rsquo;t eat very much on Friday (and had lost some weight during the week that I needed to make up), so on Saturday morning, when we decided to eat at Coriander, I was already partially prepared. Skipping breakfast was of course mandatory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;exercise&#34;&gt;Exercise&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did half an hour of intense exercise before lunch. I have learned from experience that exercise right before eating (whether for a buffet or just an ordinary meal) is effective in reducing gain of fat, redirecting toward muscle gain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, &lt;a href=&#34;http://ezinearticles.com/?Fasted-Cardio---Exercise-on-an-Empty-Stomach&amp;amp;id=4979785&#34;&gt;exercising on an empty stomach&lt;/a&gt; has additional benefits. Again, think about evolution. Our hunter-gatherer ancestors did not have &lt;sup&gt;24&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;7&lt;/sub&gt; access to junk food at all times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: usually, I do &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; exercise on a fully empty stomach, because there are drawbacks as well, as I learned from experience. Generally, I have found that eating a handful of nuts and possibly some dried fruit before exercising is optimal for me, in giving me some energy flow while keeping my head clear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;knowing-what-not-to-eat&#34;&gt;Knowing what not to eat&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no avoiding fatty, salty, starchy, sugary foods at a buffet. That&amp;rsquo;s part of the full experience. And that&amp;rsquo;s why I don&amp;rsquo;t eat at a buffet often, even a nice one like Coriander&amp;rsquo;s just blocks away from home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there are some guidelines that are very useful. The main thing is, I &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; eat rice or bread at a buffet. You don&amp;rsquo;t have to be &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/paleo/&#34;&gt;paleo&lt;/a&gt; or on some official low-carb diet to know that this is not worth the money, the bloat in your stomach, the wrecked blood sugar, and the fat gain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At an Indian buffet, I&amp;rsquo;m not really going to eat paleo-style. However, I&amp;rsquo;ll try to take it easy on breaded foods and especially the potatoes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;lunch-buffet&#34;&gt;Lunch buffet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lunch buffet offers two soups, a good selection of hot foods (including both meat/poultry/fish and vegetarian selections), and a cold section of salad, fruit, dessert.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/coriander-grill/two-soups.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Two soups provided&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/coriander-grill/buffet-left.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Left side of warm buffet&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/coriander-grill/buffet-right.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Right side of warm buffet&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/coriander-grill/buffet-cold.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Cold buffet&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-i-ate&#34;&gt;What I ate&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ate five rounds of food for lunch. (Yes, this was basically my meal for the entire day. In the evening yesterday, I did eat an apple and a snack, but no more than that.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first round (which I forgot to take a photo of), I ate a plate of hot food (Indian-Chinese chicken, fried veggie fritters, spinach, cauliflower/potatoes) and a full cup of sambar. I know the fried, breaded veggie fritters are not the healthiest food or buffet-optimal, but I enjoy having some.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For round 2, I had a bit of creamy chicken, vegetable korma, chickpeas, lentil dal, and more of the cauliflower/potatoes (I love that stuff). I am not a fan of creamy chicken or korma, but I always try a little bit of it because it&amp;rsquo;s there. I do very much like chickpeas and dal.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/coriander-grill/round-2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Round 2&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For round 3, I got more chickpeas, more dal, more spinach, more cauliflower/potatoes, my last veggie fritter, and a Tandoori-style chicken leg.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/coriander-grill/round-3.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Round 3&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For round 4, I got more Indian-Chinese chicken, more spinach, more chickpeas, more cauliflower/potatoes, and another cup of sambar! Halfway through this plate, I knew I was basically done eating.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/coriander-grill/round-4.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Round 4&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For my final round, I got a bit of salad (tomato, cucumber, lettuce, pickle, with some chutney), and a bit of cantaloupe and honeydew, and a wedge of lime. I like sucking lemon or lime at the end of a meal.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/coriander-grill/round-5.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Round 5&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;That was a lot of food! That was even more food than I normally eat at a buffet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and John ate some sugary desserts, but I had no room and no desire to have some myself. As I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/02/20/enjoying-more-french-dancing-in-pittsburgh/&#34;&gt;remembered recently&lt;/a&gt; at Gullifty&amp;rsquo;s, eating sugary desserts does not work well for me. I&amp;rsquo;ve resolved to do it only if something seems like it will be particularly tasty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;consequences&#34;&gt;Consequences&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I weighed myself when I got home. I had gained four pounds from the moment I left home to the point of return.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did end up getting sleepy in the afternoon and took a nap. I needed it anyway though, and I felt great the rest of the day, like I&amp;rsquo;d rebooted my body and satisfied some cravings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did gain quite a bit of extra weight, and pushed my fat percentage by one percent, but I know from experience this is temporary. My appetite today has been low, so I have naturally been eating less, and in a day or two I will have returned to my &amp;ldquo;normal&amp;rdquo; weight and fat percentage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like eating at buffets once every month or two. Having variety and knowing that I am giving my permission to eat all I want, rather than my usual policy of being much more moderate, adds a bit of excitement to my life, while probably also giving physical health benefits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-11-08&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-11-08)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year a new Indian restaurant opened in Pittsburgh, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.allindiapgh.com/&#34;&gt;All India&lt;/a&gt;. It is by far my favorite Indian restaurant in town now.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Roaring Like a Lion on a Saturday Morning</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/09/24/roaring-like-a-lion-on-a-saturday-morning/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Sep 2011 08:31:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/09/24/roaring-like-a-lion-on-a-saturday-morning/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I woke up today eager to roar like a lion again on a Saturday morning. I hadn&amp;rsquo;t done that in a couple of months now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/3326415463_f9ea763180_m.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;[Lion&amp;#39;s roar]&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;

(&lt;a href=&#34;http://picturesandbox.com/browse/free-stock-photos/3326415463/-.html&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am, of course, referring to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.yogajournal.com/poses/1705&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;lion&amp;rsquo;s breath&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; performed in yoga.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.yogajournal.com/media/originals/lion_248.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;[Lion&amp;#39;s breath]&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Abby and I had not gone to the free Saturday morning &amp;ldquo;Yoga with Phyllis&amp;rdquo; sessions at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.clpgh.org/locations/squirrelhill/&#34;&gt;Squirrel Hill Library&lt;/a&gt; for a couple of months now, but we had scheduled it in for this morning, so we arrived at the library early enough to get our favorite spots and set up our mats (we learned the hard way the first time that space gets crowded quickly).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/saturday-yoga.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;[Yoga mats in place]&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The instructor, Phyllis Berkovitz, is great. She has a deep, soothing voice, a perpetual smile, and a twinkle in her eye. She is relaxed and funny, making everyone feel comfortable and happy. Phyllis has been teaching yoga here for three decades, and is a truly valuable contributor to the Squirrel Hill Library&amp;rsquo;s community programs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are curious about yoga and don&amp;rsquo;t yet have a practice, check out her weekly Saturday morning class (or Tuesday evening class)!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;pittsburgh-as-small-town&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh as small town&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When attending this yoga class, we often unexpectedly run into people we know (from other contexts) . Today, for example, we ran into a woman from West Virginia (whose sister is here, and was also at class) whom Abby had borrowed an accordion (named &amp;ldquo;Bob&amp;rdquo;) for us to try out in case we wanted to buy it. (I have only begun playing the accordion and have logged maybe two or three hours of practice on &amp;ldquo;Bob&amp;rdquo; so far. More on my new musical hobby later.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;addendum&#34;&gt;Addendum&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By chance, today I saw this feel-good story about how &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.csmonitor.com/World/Making-a-difference/Change-Agent/2011/0923/Ex-convict-teaches-yoga-to-help-calm-violence-in-Mexico-s-prisons&#34;&gt;an ex-convict is teaching yoga to help calm violence in Mexico&amp;rsquo;s prisons&lt;/a&gt; so I felt I should share it here.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/0923FreddieDiazblogpost_full_380.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;[Fredi Daz]&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>