<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/post/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 29 Jul 2016 07:50:37 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/post/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>The powerful e5 Pawn break against the Benoni: using it as White, neutralizing it as Black</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2016/07/29/the-powerful-e5-pawn-break-against-the-benoni-using-it-as-white-neutralizing-it-as-black/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Jul 2016 07:50:37 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2016/07/29/the-powerful-e5-pawn-break-against-the-benoni-using-it-as-white-neutralizing-it-as-black/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been very busy coaching chess and therefore haven&amp;rsquo;t published any chess writing lately, but I was inspired by a discussion about a chess position with Isaac, the creator of &lt;a href=&#34;https://chesssummit.com/&#34;&gt;Chess Summit&lt;/a&gt;, to write a guest &lt;a href=&#34;https://chesssummit.com/2016/07/28/the-powerful-e5-pawn-break-against-the-benoni-using-it-as-white-neutralizing-it-as-black/&#34;&gt;blog post there&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you love chess and want to follow the journeys of chess players who are working hard to improve their game and share their stories along the way, check out the Chess Summit site!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On finally achieving the US National Master chess title at age 45: part 1</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2016/01/22/on-finally-achieving-the-us-national-master-chess-title-at-age-45-part-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Jan 2016 20:49:11 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2016/01/22/on-finally-achieving-the-us-national-master-chess-title-at-age-45-part-1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&#34;true&#34;  href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/franklinmingchen/24441379882/in/album-72157661509446593/&#34; title=&#34;National Master certificate&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://c3.staticflickr.com/2/1560/24441379882_36a8f817c7.jpg&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; height=&#34;375&#34; alt=&#34;National Master certificate&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async src=&#34;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On December 18, 2015, I finally achieved the
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chess_title#Master&#34;&gt;United States National Master&lt;/a&gt;
chess title, at the relatively late age of 45 (I don&amp;rsquo;t have
statistics, but I suspect the vast majority of chess players who reach
National Master do so in their teens and twenties). I plan to
eventually write about how I significantly improved my chess when I
returned after a twenty-year break to start playing again ten years
ago at age 35, and how I now teach and coach chess based on my
experience in self-improvement. I will also write more about how I
continue to work on self-improvement outside of chess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For now, below is an interview that was published in the June 2016
issue of the
&lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburghcc.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Chess Club&lt;/a&gt; publication, &amp;ldquo;En
Passant&amp;rdquo;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&#34;true&#34;  href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/franklinmingchen/28474055921&#34; title=&#34;Untitled&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://c2.staticflickr.com/9/8194/28474055921_0e62aa5380.jpg&#34; width=&#34;375&#34; height=&#34;500&#34; alt=&#34;Untitled&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async src=&#34;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;when-did-you-learn-chess-how-old-were-you-who-taught-you-what-did-you-think-or-feel-during-that-first-experience&#34;&gt;When did you learn chess? How old were you? Who taught you? What did you think or feel during that first experience?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t actually remember a moment in my life when I didn&amp;rsquo;t know the
basic rules of chess!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s what I mean: my first life memories are from shortly before I
was 3 years old (I remember celebrating my 3rd birthday), when I was
already playing chess with my father. The story is that when I was 2
years old, the 1972 Fischer-Spassky match was happening and the result
was that during the summer of 1972, my father and his grad school
classmates decided to teach themselves chess. According to him, at
some point I watched and deduced some of the movements, and he noticed
my interest. I don&amp;rsquo;t remember any of that, but I remember that at some
point he bought &amp;ldquo;Bobby Fischer Teaches Chess&amp;rdquo; (he may still have this
in his library) and he led me through it after he had finished it
himself. So that was my first chess book, and we did it before I was 4
years old, because life changed for me after my sister was born before
I turned 4, and my father no longer had much attention for me for a
while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I remember is simply the joy of seeing the geometry of the
different piece movements fitting together. I was also extremely
particular about setting up the board: I always wanted my Knights to
face each other, and I still am, and at the beginning of every game,
you will note that I always adjust my Knights accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-was-the-next-big-step-in-your-chess-life-as-a-child&#34;&gt;What was the next big step in your chess life as a child?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After my father finished graduate school, he was very busy finding
jobs, etc., and chess was put aside for a while, but finding chess
sets lying around in school led me to find in the libraries some chess
books written for children, and I enjoyed them very much. When I was
7, he found his first stable job in Morristown, New Jersey, so we
moved yet again. We discovered that the Morris County Free Library had
a huge chess book collection, and we started reading through it
together. In the process, we finally realized that we had gotten some
of the rules wrong when playing with each other at home!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I must have read through 30 or 40 chess books from that library
between age 7 and 9 before we moved again. During that time, I had
nobody to play with, because the one time in school recess I tried to
play with a classmate who claimed he knew how to play, he captured my
King after I overlooked a pin, and claimed victory, and would not
listen to me when I said I could not make an illegal make and Kings
cannot be captured! I did have one &lt;a href=&#34;http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/05/30/life-lessons-i-learned-from-a-lunch-recess-chess-game-at-age-seven/&#34;&gt;interesting experience with a chess
computer&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also started teaching my younger sister chess during this time
period (at around age 4), because I had no one else to play with other
than my father. And I lost every single game I played with my father,
because he would not let me win; he would give me chances when I was
losing, but &lt;a href=&#34;http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/06/03/why-i-am-grateful-that-my-father-never-let-me-win-a-chess-game-against-him/&#34;&gt;never let me actually win&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-did-you-get-into-playing-in-chess-tournaments&#34;&gt;How did you get into playing in chess tournaments?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, my father had to learn that there was such a thing as chess
tournaments for amateurs. This happened when he accidentally
discovered a chess club.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shortly before I turned 10, my parents and my sister and I were at the
local community center (for a new job, my father had moved the family
again, to Madison Heights, Michigan) when my father heard strange
noises in the basement and wondered what was going on. He went down
and came back up all excited. My sister and I went back down with him,
and I still remember the thick cigar smoke and the men loudly banging
on ticking chess clocks while swearing and trash-talking during
blitz. My father and I joined the club and began playing in casual
blitz as well as in unrated club tournaments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone said we should also join the Michigan Chess Association and
the US Chess Federation and play in official rated tournaments. My
father said &amp;ldquo;wait, we just paid for one membership and you want us to
pay for two others already?&amp;ldquo;, but signed us up for MCA membership,
so that we could get the newsletter and stay informed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;when-was-your-first-tournament-do-you-remember-what-you-felt-when-you-won-your-first-official-game&#34;&gt;When was your first tournament? Do you remember what you felt when you won your first official game?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By summer, everyone was excited about the upcoming annual Michigan
Open over Labor Day weekend, so we went, signed up with USCF, and
played in our first USCF rated tournament, the under-1800 Reserve
Section of the 1980 Michigan Open. I lost my first round game, but
in the second round, I won a very long, 88-move game as White (I
still have the original scoresheet and just looked over the game
again) against a 1400-rated opponent. My opponent made the final
blunder in an endgame, allowing me to trade into a King and Pawn
ending I knew was a win. I took the opposition, won the Pawn Queening
race, and knew how to win with a Queen against Knight Pawn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It felt great to bounce back so quickly from a first round loss to
winning my first tournament game. I ended up scoring 3.&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;7&lt;/sub&gt;.0 and
winning a 2nd place Unrated trophy, while my father won the 1st
place Unrated trophy. I achieved my first provisional rating of
1591, while his was 1574, lower than mine despite his higher score.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My father was so excited by our success that we continued playing
in tournaments for a while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-happened-after-your-first-tournament&#34;&gt;What happened after your first tournament?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After our first tournament, my father and I were excited to continue
playing. He decided to continue playing in the Reserve Section while I
never played in the Reserve Section again after the first tournament,
because unlike him, I was not in it for the prizes but for the
challenge of playing against stronger opponents and getting better
myself. I did well in the Open Section of my second tournament three
months after my first, and my rating went up from 1591 to 1659, so
that was exciting. I won no prize, while my father got what he wanted
and won prizes for a fine performance in the Reserve Section. After
this second tournament, everyone was taking note of my progress, and
said I had talent. I didn&amp;rsquo;t think so highly of myself, because by
then, I had met Ben Finegold, who was a year younger than me, but
already much better than me in the tournament scene.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In January 1981, my father applied for a chess scholarship from the
American Chess Foundation in order for fund some chess instruction for
me, and we got funding for ten lessons in May from the winner of
the 1980 Michigan Open, Master David Whitehouse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before the lessons even began, I had continued to do well in
tournaments, beat my first Expert, and gotten my rating up to 1741.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I very much enjoyed the lessons, and still remember a great deal from
them in retrospect. Mr. Whitehouse showed me some endgames, openings,
and illustrative games of his, but most of all, gave me a tremendously
useful book list, and I would even today recommend the study of many
of the classics that he listed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-was-your-first-setback&#34;&gt;What was your first setback?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, despite the ten weeks of instruction, it turned out
that I was stuck at a plateau for an entire year of tournament play,
not having gone higher than 1765. In fact, during my second year of
tournament play (age 11), I had my first loss against a lower-rated
opponent, my first draw against a lower-rated opponent, and my first
loss to an unrated opponent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, my father himself had topped out at a rating of around
1774, I had finally beaten him at home (after which he never played a
game of chess again for another 20 years), family life was in disarray
as he looked for another job, and I was becoming a teenager and not
getting along with my parents or my teachers in school. So my father
let our USCF memberships expire, in July 1982, and my parents worried
that I was too obsessed with chess (my mother never approved of it in
the first place) and took away my chess set. I didn&amp;rsquo;t protest too
much, because I had my own life problems at the time, plus had no idea
how to continue to improve in chess. So that&amp;rsquo;s how I retired from
chess at age 12. Life was in disarray for everyone, and I almost
failed my classes in the fall during the 7th grade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;when-did-you-return-to-chess-after-this-setback&#34;&gt;When did you return to chess after this setback?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within the following year, some things had improved: my father had a
new job lined up, and he renewed my lapsed USCF membership and gave me
my chess set back. It was clear, though, that chess was only to be a
hobby and he would not be supporting me in any substantial way. In
1983-1985, I concluded my chess career of my youth by playing two
tournaments each of those years (during which my father had one more
job change, the final one of his career, and we had moved a couple
more times).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through introspection, I did make a conscious effort to improve my
play and broke through my 1700 plateau quickly during my return to
chess at age 13, having missed age 12. I got up to 2050 when I was
15. All the while, though, I felt more and more that I still didn&amp;rsquo;t
really understand chess, and Ben Finegold had long since made Master,
and would drop out of high school to move to Europe for a professional
chess career. I did still think enough about chess that I wrote my
college application on how chess is simultaneously an art, sport, and
science, and informed how I think about human endeavors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then chess ended for me for 20 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;as-your-rating-was-rising-say-after-it-past-1200-1500-1800-what-types-of-thoughts-did-you-have-did-you-think-you-would-one-day-become-a-chess-master-or-grandmaster-can-you-share-the-emotions-of-reaching-higher-ratings&#34;&gt;As your rating was rising, say after it past 1200, 1500, 1800, what types of thoughts did you have? Did you think you would one day become a Chess Master or Grandmaster? Can you share the emotions of reaching higher ratings?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my youth, I never believed I was going to become a Master, and I
never acted as though I wanted to give it a try.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I liked to play, hoped I was improving, but didn&amp;rsquo;t have the internal
drive or family support to do anything really serious with chess. I
didn&amp;rsquo;t really play that much chess as a youth: in 1980-1985, I played
16 rated tournaments, for a total of 83 rated games that took me from
unrated to an initial rating of 1591 to a peak rating of 2050. Compare
with my adult tournament career so far from 2005-2015, which consisted
of 436 rated games: the vast majority of my chess playing has occurred
in my adulthood, with rating range from 2057 up finally to 2201.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My plateau at age 11, during which I received no encouragement or
support from anyone, made me pessimistic even when I recovered from
it. To be honest, during the entire time I played from 1983-1985, I
was afraid to have any serious expectations or goals. My own lack of
confidence combined with my fear of family disapproval caused me to
actually be relieved when I no longer had time for chess. In fact, I
considered myself rather lucky to have made it to past 2000 and had a
lingering fear that if I continued, I would just lose that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-made-you-return-to-chess-after-a-20-year-absence&#34;&gt;What made you return to chess after a 20 year absence?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did play a little bit of casual chess in my freshman year in
college, but then never played a game again for 17 years, nor did I
follow any chess world news during that time. Chess was dead to me
during those years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in the early 2000s, a friend mentioned that there were strong free
chess engines that were worth trying out. I was skeptical at first,
because in my youth I could beat chess computers. But I started
playing with some engines to see how much they had improved since my
childhood. They were still not so strong, but were definitely much
stronger!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I became very interested in whether the engines were strong enough to
resolve some analytical questions I had about complicated games in my
childhood in which I didn&amp;rsquo;t know if I played something correctly (in
particular, some sacrifices). So my renewed interest in chess was not
as a competitor but as an analyst. I started reading chess books
again, and rejoining USCF, although not yet playing. In particular,
around 2003, my life was changed when a chess book showed up in the
public library, John Watson&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Chess Strategy in Action&amp;rdquo;. I checked it
out and it completely altered my perception of and understanding of
chess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, at this point in my life in my mid-30s, I was noticing
small but clear signs of physical and mental decline (I had peaked in
my 5K race speed) and thought to myself that I had unfinished business
in my life, dreams I gave up or did not allow myself in childhood,
that I should return to soon if I wanted to accomplish them at all
before it was too late. One of those dreams was to actually see how
well I can play chess if I committed to improvement, since I believed
deep in my heart that I had stopped before reaching my full potential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I discovered the existence of the Pittsburgh Chess Club in 2004,
played a game of chess with my father while visiting him for
Christmas, our first game in over 20 years, and in 2005, started
playing in tournaments again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-did-you-do-to-move-your-rating-up-did-you-study-a-lot-play-a-lot-what-types-of-exercises-did-you-do-did-you-have-chess-boards-set-up-at-places-in-the-house-was-there-anything-unique-you-could-share-that-readers-will-enjoy-knowing-or-reading&#34;&gt;What did you do to move your rating up? Did you study a lot? play a lot? What types of exercises did you do? Did you have chess boards set up at places in the house? Was there anything unique you could share that readers will enjoy knowing or reading?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my youth, there were no chess engines or computers really worth
using, so progress was much harder for someone like me who was on his
own and did not have access to strong coaches (other than the ten free
lessons I received at age 11). So, I initially just learned from
playing blitz often at the club, playing in tournaments and reading
books and magazines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To break my 1700 plateau, I studied specific opening systems that had
clear strategic goals for the middlegame. That made a huge difference
moving forward because I was no longer playing just randomly, but with
purpose. That worked to get me up to 2000+, but it was at that point
when I realized that I was holding myself back by playing only these
weird offbeat openings that I had studied. I had to go back to the
classics in order to rebuild myself to go beyond 2000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had another plateau during my entire first year back to chess in
adulthood, I was stuck at a plateau of the low 2000s and despaired of
ever improving beyond my childhood level. I realized that I had to
rebuild my chess understanding from scratch. I had never studied chess
systematically before, had a really spotty understanding of every
aspect of the game, from openings to middlegames to endgames. So in my
second year back, in 2006, I started rebuilding myself, gradually
transforming how I play. That paid off as I finally cracked 2100 and
then 2150, during 2006 and 2007. It was not until I passed 2100 that
for the first time in my life, I decided to set myself a goal of
making Master!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The single most helpful tool to me in recent years has been analyzing
my own games in detail with use of strong chess engines. I would say
this is more important than anything else. Being confronted with
reliable evidence of ideas or tactics that you missed (or your
opponent missed) must be the single most useful tool for improvement
available today that wasn&amp;rsquo;t available in the pre-computer era. In
particular, computers make it easy to try &amp;ldquo;what if&amp;rdquo; by experimenting
with different continuations, setups, and see how they measure up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;were-there-times-you-were-disappointed-with-yourself-and-thought-about-quitting-were-there-other-factors-like-friend-family-girlfriend-who-led-you-or-tried-to-dissuade-you-to-continue-playing-chess-is-there-any-story-you-would-like-to-share-on-this-topic&#34;&gt;Were there times you were disappointed with yourself and thought about quitting? Were there other factors like friend, family, girlfriend who led you or tried to dissuade you to continue playing chess? Is there any story you would like to share on this topic?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have often been disappointed in my chess play, but interestingly,
never seriously thought about quitting except in one situation: I only
thought about quitting once I came close to reaching Master and kept
failing, which coincided chronologically with my meeting a young
woman.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every loss or draw that set me back as I approached 2200 had a
tendency of making me feel like I didn&amp;rsquo;t have what it takes. And
starting to date again in 2007 definitely began to take a toll on my
chess, both because Abby actively opposed my chess activities at the
time and because of my whole schedule and routine was disrupted,
making tournament play difficult logistically. By the time we got
married in 2009, I had basically quit chess, and I thought for good,
and not willingly but as a concession. I periodically tried to come
back and play, but always less well than I was capable, because of
being rusty, unsupported, and tired. It wasn&amp;rsquo;t until the second half
of 2015 that I was ready to try again to play the best I could, this
time finally with complete emotional support from Abby, who had
finally come to understand how much chess meant to me. I also canceled
a lot of my usual activities in the second half of 2015 in order to
focus my energy outside of work on chess, and all this paid off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-is-the-single-most-important-factor-a-chess-player-must-consider-to-move-up-his-her-rating&#34;&gt;What is the single, most important factor a chess player must consider to move up his/her rating?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We all hit a plateau at some point, at which we are apparently making
the same kinds of errors that stronger players are not making, so
somehow we have to change the kinds of errors that we make.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the most powerful tool available is analysis of your own
games. Each game you play has the fingerprints of your personal
weaknesses all over it. Using a chess engine, and ideally a strong
human guide who can explain concepts and variations that lie behind
the engine&amp;rsquo;s numerical evaluations, you can learn to gradually remove
errors. For example, if you lost an otherwise good game only because
of one misconception during an endgame, avoiding that single error in
the future could pay off in any number of similar situations. Or if
you misplayed an opening, rebuilding your thought process that led to
a strategic misunderstanding can help in all future games using that
opening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;have-you-been-close-to-2200-several-times-and-then-fell-therefore-postponing-the-master-level-can-you-give-details-of-how-you-felt&#34;&gt;Have you been close to 2200 several times and then fell? (therefore postponing the Master level)? Can you give details of how you felt?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, I have been close several times! In fact, a couple of times I had
2200 locked up, in the sense that if I had withdrawn from a tournament
in progress, I would have guaranteed going over 2200 based on the wins
I had already racked up in the tournament.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first time was in the 2007 PA State Action Championship. I went in
at 2171 and had won the first three rounds. In the fourth round, I had
a totally won game against a Master and nerves got to me and I fell
apart and lost. In the final round, I had a totally won game against
an 1800 and fell apart and lost. This was my first experience of
completely choking under the pressure of knowing I was very close to
2200.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then in January 2008, I had a rating of 2197 from a Pittsburgh Chess
League round. The thing you have to understand is that in
January-February, I was simultaneously playing in the PCC Championship
held on Tuesday nights, and had won my first three rounds by February,
which meant that if I had withdrawn, I would have secured far more
than the 3 rating points necessary to go over 2200. But I had never
withdrawn from a tournament in my life, and didn&amp;rsquo;t want to achieve
Master through calculated cowardice. So I played on. But I choked, and
proceeded to draw the fourth game and lose the fifth. I continued to
play worse as I got engaged to be married, and quit chess the year of
my marriage in 2009.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I periodically came back in 2010-2012 but just played worse and worse,
unforced errors. In 2013, I started recovering, and in 2014, I again
almost made Master. At 2195, I choked, losing a won game against a
much lower-rated player while a Rook up! All I needed was to win that
game to make Master. And I kept on choking in tournaments after that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fall of 2015, I more or less stopped choking. I still played badly
sometimes, but I distinguish between poor quality of play and just
plain choking. How did I stop choking? I stopped paying attention to
my rating. In fact, in my final tournament games of 2015 that led me
to go over 2200, I did not do any calculations to determine whether I
would or would not go over. I knew it could be close, but did not want
to calculate. I tried to focus on my games and nothing else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m still proud that I made Master without the trick of withdrawing
from any tournaments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;can-you-discuss-which-is-more-important-for-chess-improvement-studying-the-opening-middlegame-or-endgame-explain-why&#34;&gt;Can you discuss which is more important for chess improvement: studying the opening, middlegame, or endgame? Explain why.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The short answer is that everything is actually interconnected, and I
wish I had known this earlier. A quality game will have a story behind
it that connects all phases of chess. Because of this, I think the
study of complete, annotated games (including annotating your own
games) is the single most useful technique for improvement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, opening study is popular, but studying the opening in
isolation, apart from understanding fundamental principles and knowing
not to fall into tricky traps, is almost irrelevant at under-2000
level, where games will mostly be decided not by opening subtleties,
but by later parts of the game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My main improvements have come from understanding the middlegame
better, learning how to assess positions and create plans based on
features of the positions, especially through considering Pawn
structure. If you think of an opening as a way to try to get to a
certain kind of middlegame, and think of the middlegame as a way to
get to a certain kind of endgame, then everything starts to fit
together. The middlegame is the core.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Improving in the endgame is important at all levels.  When I look at
my first tournament games at a 1500-1600 level, I see that the vast
majority of them went into endgames where anything could happen
because none of us really knew what we were doing, but I managed draws
and wins because I was a bit better there than opponents who otherwise
matched me in the opening and middlegame.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With my young students, I go over the opening phase with them only
enough for them to survive it (by playing classically and avoiding
needlessly complex and subtle variations), but focus my instruction
primarily on how to get to a desired middlegame by means of opening
choice. I also add endgame instruction incrementally as it becomes a
bottleneck in overall performance: when they get good enough to get a
dominating middlegame and then fail to win in the endgame, that&amp;rsquo;s when
we work on the endgame. But I feel like spending a lot of time on the
endgame up front is not realistic if one is not even surviving the
middlegame.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;were-there-any-special-small-or-large-celebration-when-you-became-a-master&#34;&gt;Were there any special, small or large celebration when you became a Master?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No, there was no celebration. I have to confess I&amp;rsquo;m not really a
celebration kind of person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-are-your-plans-now&#34;&gt;What are your plans now?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will continue what I&amp;rsquo;ve already been doing in chess since 2012:
writing and teaching.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started writing about chess on my personal blog around 2012. I
really enjoy sharing my analysis and thoughts with others, and this
eventually led to my writing for GM Nigel Davies&amp;rsquo; &lt;a href=&#34;http://ChessImprover.com/author/FranklinC/&#34;&gt;The Chess Improver&lt;/a&gt;
site and giving private chess lessons since 2013. I am still teaching
now and very much enjoy helping others improve their chess. So
teaching has been my main focus in chess for a while now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will continue to play in local tournaments as time permits. I am not
done improving yet! Also, I enjoy being a role model for my students,
to walk the walk as I give them advice about how to study, improve,
and compete. I have even been inspired to try to play model games to
illustrate specific themes I teach. For example, last year when the
subject was isolated Pawns, I played a game in which I chose an
opening aimed specifically against an isolated Pawn structure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2016-06-25&#34;&gt;(Update of 2016-06-25)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still play chess with my father whenever I see him. He&amp;rsquo;s still
playing pretty well at age 78. I feel he is possibly even better than
when he was in his 40s, probably because he has all the time in the
world to play casual games regularly at his local community center
since retirement. It&amp;rsquo;s actually harder for me to beat him now than
when I was a kid. Here&amp;rsquo;s a photo from the last visit to my parents&amp;rsquo; in
May 2016; I barely managed to win this game, where I took advantage of
the weakness of his isolated Pawn in the endgame:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&#34;true&#34;  href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/franklinmingchen/27597310106/in/album-72157671558553835/&#34; title=&#34;Untitled&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://c3.staticflickr.com/8/7317/27597310106_994a1df764.jpg&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; height=&#34;375&#34; alt=&#34;Untitled&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async src=&#34;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How the X-Files reminded me of the meaning of Martin Luther King Jr.</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2016/01/18/how-the-x-files-reminded-me-of-the-meaning-of-martin-luther-king-jr./</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Jan 2016 22:07:06 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2016/01/18/how-the-x-files-reminded-me-of-the-meaning-of-martin-luther-king-jr./</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today was my second official celebration (with a day off from work as
a holiday) of
&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Martin_Luther_King,_Jr._Day&#34;&gt;Martin Luther King, Jr. Day&lt;/a&gt;. (I
wrote last year on
&lt;a href=&#34;../blog/2015/01/19/for-martin-luther-king-jr-day-some-black-american-voices-that-spoke-to-me-recently/&#34;&gt;my first official celebration&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For today, I not only reread MLK&amp;rsquo;s 1963
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.africa.upenn.edu/Articles_Gen/Letter_Birmingham.html&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Letter from a Birmingham jail&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;
as I do annually, but also rewatched my single favorite X-Files
episode,
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Musings_of_a_Cigarette_Smoking_Man&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Musings of a Cigarette Smoking Man&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;
from 1997.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quite unexpectedly, this hilariously entertaining yet dark and sad
episode of the TV series made a deep impression on my mind when I saw
it almost twenty years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;mlk-in-the-x-files-episode-warning-spoilers&#34;&gt;MLK in the X-files episode (warning: spoilers!!)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you haven&amp;rsquo;t watched this old 1997 episode of the X-files before
you might want to go and watch it before reading any further. If you
already have watched it or don&amp;rsquo;t care, here&amp;rsquo;s an unofficial
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.insidethex.co.uk/transcrp/scrp407.htm&#34;&gt;transcript&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically, this episode is a Forrest Gump inspired look back at
history, in which the infamous
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Smoking_Man&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;smoking man&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;
character is revealed (or is he?) to have had a history involving
having a father who was an executed communist spy, but he himself
grows up into a young man devoted to working covertly to defeat
perceived threats to America. According to the story as it unfolds in
this episode, the smoking man personally assassinated both John
F. Kennedy and Martin Luther King, Jr.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What made the part about assassinating MLK poignant was that he
respected MLK, and decided to eliminate him because of a speech by MLK
he heard on his radio against the Vietnam War.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The smoking man says:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;If this were only a civil rights issue, I&amp;rsquo;d vote for a King/Benjamin
Spock presidential ticket. But after last night, it&amp;rsquo;s not&amp;hellip;  I
respect King. He&amp;rsquo;s an extraordinary man. But now he&amp;rsquo;s talking like a
Maoist&amp;hellip; And if he convinces Negroes not to fight in Vietnam, we&amp;rsquo;ll
lose&amp;hellip; and the first domino will have fallen.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;mlk-s-1967-speech-beyond-vietnam-a-time-to-break-silence-https-en-wikipedia-org-wiki-beyond-vietnam-a-time-to-break-silence&#34;&gt;MLK&amp;rsquo;s 1967 speech, &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beyond_Vietnam:_A_Time_to_Break_Silence&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Beyond Vietnam: A Time to Break Silence&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.americanrhetoric.com/speeches/mlkatimetobreaksilence.htm&#34;&gt;transcript&lt;/a&gt;
of the actual speech that so angered and saddened the X-Files smoking
man (and in real history, a whole lot of people).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An excerpt used in the X-Files episode: &amp;ldquo;It is a sad fact that because
of comfort, complacency, a morbid fear of communism, our proneness to
adjust to injustice, the Western nations that initiated so much of the
revolutionary spirit of the modern world have now become the arch
anti-revolutionaries. This has driven many to feel that only Marxism
has a revolutionary spirit. Therefore, communism is a judgment against
our failure to make democracy real and follow through on the
revolutions that we initiated. Our only hope today lies in our ability
to recapture the revolutionary spirit and go out into a sometimes
hostile world declaring eternal hostility to poverty, racism, and
militarism.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s audio of MLK himself speaking:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/zyE4eo_leX8&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-the-us-and-world-were-like-in-1997&#34;&gt;What the US and world were like in 1997&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was watching this episode in 1997, I had been in a state of
apathy and disappointment in the legacy of MLK for a number of years,
partially thanks to having watched Spike Lee&amp;rsquo;s 1992 film
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Malcolm_X_%281992_film%29&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Malcolm X&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;
and then gone on to read the 1965
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Autobiography_of_Malcolm_X&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Autobiography of Malcolm X&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. I
had come to get the impression that MLK had failed, because he was too
&amp;ldquo;soft&amp;rdquo;, and Malcolm X was &amp;ldquo;tougher&amp;rdquo;. Note that the 1990s was a dark
time, as the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rodney_King&#34;&gt;Rodney King&lt;/a&gt;
beating was in 1991 and the LA riots were in 1992. And the
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bosnian_War&#34;&gt;Bosnian War&lt;/a&gt; 1992-1995 was
fresh in my memory, illustrating that the end of the Cold War in 1991
was just the beginning of a falling apart of the former Eastern Bloc.
So the 1990s were a time when I wondered what had gone wrong, not only
in America, but in the whole world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Somehow, revisiting MLK by accident through this X-Files episode, I
returned to thinking that I wished MLK had lived much longer. It felt
to me that he was only starting his global work when he was shut
down. Yet, as long as his words remain, and are not forgotten, there
may be hope. Not so much the overexposed 1963 words like
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/I_Have_a_Dream&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;I have a dream&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, but
the 1967 words against the American war on Vietnam.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;history&#34;&gt;History&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s why, when 2003 came around, with the beginning of the
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iraq_War&#34;&gt;Iraq War&lt;/a&gt;, I felt angry and
sad, and remembered that X-Files episode. I knew that MLK would have
warned against the Iraq War as well. Was there any way he could have
stopped it? Or would he have been eliminated, again?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every year, I will continue to renew my memory of and my understanding
of what MLK did in his life and what he was in the middle of doing
when he was murdered.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>If you were this old man playing chess against a young boy, what would you have done?</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2016/01/09/if-you-were-this-old-man-playing-chess-against-a-young-boy-what-would-you-have-done/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Jan 2016 12:08:32 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2016/01/09/if-you-were-this-old-man-playing-chess-against-a-young-boy-what-would-you-have-done/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m going to tell you a true story about an old man and a young boy
(age under 10) who played a game of chess in a competitive tournament
where prize money was at stake. I&amp;rsquo;d like you to think about the odd
situation that occurred, while looking at it, with &lt;em&gt;empathy&lt;/em&gt;, from
different points of view:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the old man&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the young boy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the boy&amp;rsquo;s parent&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the tournament director, whose job is to enforce the official
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.uschess.org/content/view/7864/221/&#34;&gt;US Chess Federation rules of tournament chess&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the bigger picture of the chess community&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the biggest picture of life lessons&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the whole story, do you think that what happened was right?
Is there something you would have done differently if you had been one
of the actors in the story? In particular, what would you have done as
the old man?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;prelude&#34;&gt;Prelude&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s call the old man Mr. M, the boy B, the tournament director T.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the beginning of the second half of a long tournament, Mr. M and B
were paired against each other. Neither had been doing too well in the
tournament up till that point, but there was the rest of the
tournament to go, and anything can happen in a long tournament. Mr. M
on paper had the highest US chess rating of their shared class
division going into the tournament and so was the favorite to win. B
was a young newcomer to chess who had only been playing for half a
year but was improving rapidly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out during the game that B played extremely well, outplaying
Mr. M. The position was complicated but B had an advantage. B thought
he spotted a winning move, and carelessly (still being young and
impulsive, unfortunately) &lt;em&gt;picked up one of his pieces&lt;/em&gt; in order to
make the winning move, but in mid-air realized it was not going to
win.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;touch-move&#34;&gt;Touch-move&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Touch-move_rule&#34;&gt;touch-move&lt;/a&gt; rule
in chess is one of the most important rules that exists in serious
tournament chess. If you touch your own piece with &lt;em&gt;intent&lt;/em&gt; to move
it, or touch an opponent&amp;rsquo;s piece with &lt;em&gt;intent&lt;/em&gt; to capture it, then you
have to complete your move using the touched piece one way or another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Violating touch-move is very common among young chess players in a
casual setting, and therefore a critical bad habit to break, as B
learned the hard way in this game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;where-to-move-it&#34;&gt;Where to move it?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, since B was still in mid-air, he did not have to complete the
move he was going to play. He did have to complete some legal move
using his touched piece, which he still held. At this point, he
&lt;em&gt;intended&lt;/em&gt; to put the piece back on its &lt;em&gt;original&lt;/em&gt; square, as is legal
to do so, to think of what move to make with the piece.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, in confusion, B accidentally released the piece on a
random other square rather than the original square. This was really
bad luck because the move that was thereby &lt;em&gt;determined&lt;/em&gt; by the
release.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-old-man-s-decision&#34;&gt;The old man&amp;rsquo;s decision&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since Mr. M knew as well as B did that B did not intend to release the
piece on the absurd square it was released at, he decided to allow B
to return the piece to the original square in order to make a
different legal move. Very charitable!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then Mr. M suddenly changed his mind and said the accidentally
determined move had to stand. The tournament director was called and
ruled that according to the rules, indeed the move had to stand: the
piece was released on a legal square.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;B&amp;rsquo;s parent did not contest the ruling, because it was by the book, and
the result was that Mr. M captured B&amp;rsquo;s piece and quickly won the game,
because the rest of the game was nonsensical given the nonsensical
move B was forced to play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;your-reaction&#34;&gt;Your reaction?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Given this information, how do you feel about what happened? Rules
  are rules, but Mr. M had the power to insist on strict enforcement
  or to overlook the unintended violation, and originally intended to
  let it go.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first reaction when learning about this story was anger that Mr. M
had changed his mind like that. If Mr. M had taken one course of
action or the other, &lt;em&gt;without suddenly changing his mind&lt;/em&gt;, I would
have been OK with that. Either be forgiving or play by the book, but
be consistent!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My second reaction, was from the point of view of what this
incident meant for B in the long run. I had some conflicting feelings:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I felt bad about B being forced to lose an important game in which
he was playing some of the best chess he had ever played in his
life.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I was annoyed that B still hadn&amp;rsquo;t mastered &amp;ldquo;touch-move&amp;rdquo;, and felt
that he needed to &lt;em&gt;learn a lesson&lt;/em&gt; that would help him avoid such
carelessness in his future chess tournaments, and this was a
legitimate case of his learning an important lesson.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I worried about how B would feel about this loss, given that he had
started off the tournament pretty badly and was just getting his
momentum back by the second half.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;complications&#34;&gt;Complications&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this wasn&amp;rsquo;t the whole story. The other thing Mr. M did when
explaining why he changed his mind was that he wanted to win the game
and the tournament (recall that he was in a worse position against B,
and hadn&amp;rsquo;t been doing so well in the tournament despite being the
highest rated player in the section). So his concern wasn&amp;rsquo;t about
strictly enforcing the rules; presumably if he already had a
tournament win locked up and this game didn&amp;rsquo;t &amp;ldquo;matter&amp;rdquo;, he would have
been &amp;ldquo;charitable&amp;rdquo; and allowed B to continue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Does this change how you feel about what happened?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, Mr. M&amp;rsquo;s justification made me actively dislike him. At the
same time, maybe B learned an additional life lesson in this
tournament, that adults will do whatever is in their own interest and
any generosity offered may be contingent on whether it impacts their
own interest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-end-result&#34;&gt;The end result&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some rounds later, the tournament was complete. It turned out that
Mr. M won all subsequent games he played in the tournament, and
therefore won the tournament, along with the prize money for first
place, $500. He achieved his goal, fulfilling his justification for
being firm in his game against B. So from his point of view, he made
the right decision and got his moment of glory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;B bounced back from his disaster and also won his remaining games, and
ended up with a pretty successful tournament overall. You could say
that although it was unfortunate that his touch-move slip might have
cost him first place, he learned a lot about taking touch-move
seriously and about recovering from unfortunate incidents during a
chess tournament. So from B&amp;rsquo;s point of view, he probably learned a lot
more from Mr. M&amp;rsquo;s adherence to the rules than if Mr. M had been too
nice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although I don&amp;rsquo;t like how Mr. M went about what he did, the end result
seems actually optimal for everyone involved. Or was it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;appendix&#34;&gt;Appendix&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve written in the past about some life lessons I learned from chess
as a child. I&amp;rsquo;m curious how B will look back at his incident later in
life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../blog/2012/05/30/life-lessons-i-learned-from-a-lunch-recess-chess-game-at-age-seven&#34;&gt;Life lessons I learned from a lunch recess chess game at age seven&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../blog/2012/06/03/why-i-am-grateful-that-my-father-never-let-me-win-a-chess-game-against-him&#34;&gt;Why I am grateful that my father never let me win a chess game against him&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Accidentally discovering and performing some music by Brazilian composer Ernesto Nazareth: Coração que Sente</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/12/29/accidentally-discovering-and-performing-some-music-by-brazilian-composer-ernesto-nazareth-cora%C3%A7%C3%A3o-que-sente/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Dec 2015 23:05:10 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/12/29/accidentally-discovering-and-performing-some-music-by-brazilian-composer-ernesto-nazareth-cora%C3%A7%C3%A3o-que-sente/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In November, I fell in love with some music I accidentally discovered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What happened was that I was looking for some music for &lt;em&gt;flute&lt;/em&gt; and
&lt;em&gt;guitar&lt;/em&gt; to play, with me on flute and one of my friends on guitar, and
I did a simple search in the
&lt;a href=&#34;../blog/2011/09/30/free-to-the-people-since-1895/&#34;&gt;local library&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://librarycatalog.einetwork.net/&#34;&gt;online catalog&lt;/a&gt;, and at the top
sorted by date was
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.halleonard.com/product/viewproduct.action?itemid=49044167&amp;amp;&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Brazilian folk tunes for flute and guitar&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;,
which came with a CD of sample performance tracks,
so I picked it up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What followed was a series of explorations that resulted in unexpected
changes in my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;exploring-the-brazilian-music-in-the-score-book&#34;&gt;Exploring the Brazilian music in the score book&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I listened to some tracks on the CD of this book of arrangements and
found the music (Brazilian polkas, tangos, waltzes) really
enchanting. Most of the music was by a composer
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ernesto_Nazareth&#34;&gt;Ernesto Nazareth&lt;/a&gt;,
who lived 1863-1934. I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t call this music &amp;ldquo;folk tunes&amp;rdquo;: it&amp;rsquo;s
a sophisticated combination of popular and classical styles using
catchy dance rhythms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m a real sucker for waltzes, so at first I thought I would pick one
of the beautiful waltzes to choose to suggest to play with a partner
on guitar. It came down to &amp;ldquo;Confidências&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;Coração que Sente&amp;rdquo;
(English translation: &amp;ldquo;Heart that Feels&amp;rdquo;). The
latter was much easier and shorter, as I learned while sight reading
through it with the CD track, so I thought I was done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;finding-astounding-performances-of-coração-que-sente-on-youtube&#34;&gt;Finding astounding performances of &amp;ldquo;Coração que Sente&amp;rdquo; on YouTube&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking for performances of the piece on YouTube to get an idea of
how people play it, I immediately entered a strange new world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, I learned that the original music was for
&lt;em&gt;piano&lt;/em&gt;. OK. Then, while listening to and/or watching a dozen or so
videos of performances of this piece (OK, I was obsessed), I found a
huge variety of interpretations, and some of them spoke to me more
than others. Some I found light and boring. The ones that interested
me were the ones that were extremely intense and probing. You might
think this music was just fluff, but I found a dark undercurrent
behind it that spoke to me, in that its different sections (the piece
is roughly in rondo form) present clear emotional contrasts, with
longing, melancholy, and manic excitement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;arthur-moreira-lima&#34;&gt;Arthur Moreira Lima&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A very intense performance I found was by a pianist named
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arthur_Moreira_Lima&#34;&gt;Arthur Moreira Lima&lt;/a&gt;
in 1975, used after the fact as soundtrack on YouTube for a silent
film using footage from 1929. What an odd pairing!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lima goes all out in Romantic expressiveness, with extensive rubato
and dynamic and rhythmic flexibility. It was completely different from
the relatively straight, danceable version on the flute/guitar CD
demo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have to listen to his performance (ignore the film or watch it, as
you wish):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Mmjt8RrfXtA&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;joão-carlos-assis-brasil&#34;&gt;João Carlos Assis Brasil&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even more extreme than Lima was this weird guy João Carlos Assis
Brasil, who is apparently so unknown in the English-speaking world
that Wikipedia doesn&amp;rsquo;t have an entry on him, although I found this
random
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bach-cantatas.com/Bio/Assis-Brasil-Joao-Carlos.htm&#34;&gt;pieced-together bio&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His live performance here from 2013 is the single most extreme, yet
deepest, interpretation of this waltz I found (he adds his own
ornamentation). I was deeply moved by it. (Warning, bad sound
quality.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/iG_o94sU1tE&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;other-good-performances&#34;&gt;Other good performances&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://pt.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fernanda_Chaves_Canaud&#34;&gt;Fernanda Canaud&lt;/a&gt;,
with a very expressive performance (including her own extensive
embellishments), uses drastic changes in articulation and tempo for
contrast. I particularly liked how naturally she seemed to express her
personality through the piece:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/-DfOYvNCaqk&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://pt.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maria_Teresa_Madeira&#34;&gt;Maria Theresa Madeira&lt;/a&gt;
captures well the moods of the different sections of the piece; I
really like the rhythmic alertness and drive throughout:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/eeztzLsF6Cc&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some random YouTube guy named Ilton, playing a really crappy upright
piano, but with amazing rhythmic expression that I totally love (if he
played this on a good piano, I would consider his interpretation one
of my favorites, period):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/b-gYk_YUoIM&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://lucianoalves.com.br/&#34;&gt;Luciano Alves&lt;/a&gt;, 2013, in an elegant
performance:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/y8LchR8Mi5Y&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://pt.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marcelo_Bratke&#34;&gt;Marcelo Bratke&lt;/a&gt; in a
relaxed, easygoing, dream interpretation with a lilt (but after all
the intense interpretations, I find this tame, I confess):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Pn5vYhfQYHs&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-performance-that-made-me-decide-to-learn-and-play-the-piece&#34;&gt;The performance that made me decide to learn and play the piece&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I spent a lot of time listening to and watching performances of the
piece, but one performance was the one that made me decide to go learn
and play the piece! It was this one by some random guy Marcelo Chiarella:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/QaQL9VlJy8s&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why? Because I could &lt;em&gt;relate to&lt;/em&gt; his playing:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;He wasn&amp;rsquo;t some famous pro pianist, as far as I could tell.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The sound quality was good and the recording was as though I were
standing right there, made me feel like I was in his home, and
nobody else there.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I could see his hands up close.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I liked various things he did with expression (especially when he
&lt;em&gt;wasn&amp;rsquo;t&lt;/em&gt; pedaling).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I knew that I could be much more expressive and personal
(remember, the title in English translation is &amp;ldquo;Heart that feels&amp;rdquo;)
while playing this piece &lt;em&gt;solo&lt;/em&gt;, on piano, than in a flute/guitar
duet. So I decided to go for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;finding-an-official-free-score&#34;&gt;Finding an official free score&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had to find a score. Luckily, it turned out that there was some
big
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ernestonazareth150anos.com.br/&#34;&gt;150-year anniversary celebration for Ernesto Nazareth&lt;/a&gt;
in 2013, and I found an official &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ernestonazareth150anos.com.br/files/uploads/work_elements/work_43/coracao_que_sente_piano.pdf&#34;&gt;free PDF score&lt;/a&gt; on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ernestonazareth150anos.com.br/works/view/43&#34;&gt;page for the piece&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That page also had a story about the title of the piece and why it was
composed. It was in Portuguese, so I tried with the help of Google
Translate to translate it (I only studied Portuguese for several weeks
many years ago), and pieced together (I hope I didn&amp;rsquo;t get this too
wrong) that Nazareth dedicated it to a student of his, Gabriella
Crauz, who had showed great emotion as Nazareth described the last
days of a dying nephew, as though she had been there herself
experiencing what he experienced as he saw the sights in the city one
last time. (If you know Portuguese, please correct me if I got the
story wrong.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This story only added to the sense I already had that this seemingly
simple piece hid a depth of emotion that some performers already
revealed for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-performance-of-coração-que-sente&#34;&gt;My performance of &amp;ldquo;Coração que Sente&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I started working on the piece, I had to decide where and when to
perform it. It turned out that I learned that friends who mean a lot
to me decided to move. This was really tough news to me, and they have
always invited me and Abby to their December holiday party, where I
play music, so I decided that I was going to perform the piece at
their (now farewell) party and openly dedicate my performance to them,
because they are human beings of deep feeling, hence &amp;ldquo;Heart that
feels&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I performed the piece at the party the day after Christmas. In my
nervousness, I completely lost my train of thought a couple of times
and botched things up inexplicably (I had gone through the piece with
no errors so many times at home), but I made it through, and my
gesture was appreciated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I then decided to quickly record myself at home soon after (and still
botched some things up), so here I am. This is for Henry and Gina:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34;
src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/VBOS9btMUPI&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;
allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;other-music-by-ernesto-nazareth&#34;&gt;Other music by Ernesto Nazareth&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spent all this time talking about just one piece by Nazareth, but he
wrote much more, and more substantial pieces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I totally love Fernanda Canaud&amp;rsquo;s performance of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ernestonazareth150anos.com.br/works/view/133&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Batuque&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, &amp;ldquo;Coração
que Sente&amp;rdquo;, and
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ernestonazareth150anos.com.br/works/view/136&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Odeon&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;
(the performance of &amp;ldquo;Coração que Sente&amp;rdquo; is very different from the one
I posted above: more inward, refined, beautiful rather than super-dramatic):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/U6WaAgRWqaw&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is Nazareth playing his own pieces in recordings from 1912-1930:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/eZS3bDNJEUY&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a one-hour special documentary video &amp;ldquo;Nazareth Revisitado&amp;rdquo;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/TJAT3pJJR6M&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-note-on-the-english-language-oriented-web&#34;&gt;A note on the English-language-oriented Web&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found a whole world of music and musicians that barely register in
the English-language-oriented part of the Web. Most of what I found
when trying to look up Nazareth or various Brazilian pianists was in
Portuguese. So it&amp;rsquo;s been really humbling to remember that many in the
English-speaking world might not even know about all these Brazilian
composers and musicians who are not big enough stars to warrant
international fame.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am grateful for accidentally discovering an entire world of
Brazilian music and performers of it through my search in the local
library catalog for music to play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am grateful for friends who inspire me by their examples as human
beings of genuine and great feeling.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Clever chess tactics that were not what they seemed</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/11/30/clever-chess-tactics-that-were-not-what-they-seemed/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Nov 2015 02:25:52 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/11/30/clever-chess-tactics-that-were-not-what-they-seemed/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In round 3 of the current 6-round Pittsburgh Chess Club Tuesday night
tournament, I played a very tense game that led to an unusual position
with beautiful tactical possibilities. My opponent, Melih, is a strong
player who is a winner of the 2015 Pittsburgh Chess Club Championship earlier
this year, and had won the last two tournament games we have played,
so I came into this game anxious and also thirsty for revenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The game proved to be very challenging for both of us. I achieved a
better position out of the opening as Black but was too cautious to
press more aggressively. After more than 3 hours (!) of play, we ended
up in a simplified late middlegame in which I had only a small but
clear advantage. We were both clearly physically and mentally
exhausted, and starting to run out of time (these tournament games
have a time control of 2 hours per person with a 5-second delay per
move). It was up to me to try to find a way to win by inducing errors
in his play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;get-ready-to-be-quizzed&#34;&gt;Get ready to be quizzed!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What ended up happening was in retrospect both remarkable and
comic. To maximize your entertainment as well as challenge your
tactical skills, I recommend pausing at each diagrammed position below
in order to ask yourself what move you would play, and why, before
gradually uncovering the whole story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: an interactive chess board with all variations is provided at
the end of this article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;first-assess-a-quiet-looking-starting-position&#34;&gt;First, assess a quiet-looking starting position&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For context, here is the position after 21 moves, after Black played
21&amp;hellip;Qc6.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../chess/ozbek-chen-2015-11-17/22w.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;21...Qc6; White to move&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;questions&#34;&gt;Questions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What opening do you think this middlegame came from?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Who stands better and why?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is White&amp;rsquo;s best plan, and what is Black&amp;rsquo;s best plan?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;answers&#34;&gt;Answers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Congratulations if you guessed this was a
  &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/French_Defence#Advance_Variation:_3.e5&#34;&gt;French Defense, Advance Variation&lt;/a&gt;,
  gone totally wrong for White!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Black stands better and has a simple plan:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;attack White&amp;rsquo;s backward Pawn on c3 on the half-open file, and
perhaps also the e5 Pawn as well; and the a2 Pawn and b4 Pawn are
also potential targets&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;use the half-open c-file for the Rooks, and the dark-squared Bishop
against White&amp;rsquo;s Pawns, and get the Queen involved as well&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;using these attacks, overload White&amp;rsquo;s defenses somehow in order to
win at least one of those Pawns to enter a probably winning endgame&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;White&amp;rsquo;s only possible counter-plan:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;defend the weak Queen side Pawns&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;maybe plant the Knight on a good outpost such as d4&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;defend the Pawn on e5 with maybe an f4 advance, and hope to attack
Black&amp;rsquo;s King side with perhaps an f5 break&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;progress-after-seven-moves&#34;&gt;Progress after seven moves?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Black has just played 28&amp;hellip;Rc4.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../chess/ozbek-chen-2015-11-17/29w.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;28...Rc4; White to move&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;questions-1&#34;&gt;Questions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Who has made more progress in the last seven moves: White or Black?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is the nature of the progress made?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;answers-1&#34;&gt;Answers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;White has played to wait to see what Black is up to; meanwhile, Black
has made some progress on the Queen side by:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;doubling Rooks on the half-open c-file&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;using the Queen to bear down on White&amp;rsquo;s a-Pawn, which White has
(mistakenly) advanced to a3.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;white-played-a-surprising-move&#34;&gt;White played a surprising move&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;White has just played 29 Rac2.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../chess/ozbek-chen-2015-11-17/29b.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;29 Rac2; Black to move&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;questions-2&#34;&gt;Questions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the 29th move, White moved the Rook from a2 to c2, leaving the
defense of the a3 Pawn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is the meaning of this strange move?!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can Black just take the Pawn with the Queen?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;answers-2&#34;&gt;Answers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may be thinking &amp;ldquo;White is provocatively setting a trap for Black
to fall into&amp;rdquo;. You get credit if you can see the trap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;black-fell-into-a-trap&#34;&gt;Black fell into a trap?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I played 29&amp;hellip;Qxa3.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../chess/ozbek-chen-2015-11-17/30w.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;29...Qxa3; White to move&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But wait, I took the Pawn! Did I fall into a trap?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;questions-3&#34;&gt;Questions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is the trap you saw earlier, if you saw it?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is it really a trap?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;white-closed-the-trap&#34;&gt;White closed the trap?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;White has played 30 Ra2.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../chess/ozbek-chen-2015-11-17/30b.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;30 Ra2; Black to move&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;answers-3&#34;&gt;Answers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the Rook moved back to a2, apparently trapping Black&amp;rsquo;s Queen. But
again, was it really a trap?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;black-refuted-the-trap&#34;&gt;Black refuted the trap?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Black played 30&amp;hellip;Rxd4.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../chess/ozbek-chen-2015-11-17/31w.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;30...Rxd4; White to move&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You get credit if you saw this move taking White&amp;rsquo;s Knight on d4, and
saw that White&amp;rsquo;s Queen is overloaded such that retaking the Rook in
either one of two ways leads to losing back the Rook on c1 and
therefore losing a piece overall and the game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was very proud of seeing this tactic. (If you saw a different move
for Black, we&amp;rsquo;ll discuss that further down below.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;white-refuted-the-refutation&#34;&gt;White refuted the refutation?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;White played 31 Qc2.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../chess/ozbek-chen-2015-11-17/31b.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;31 Qc2; Black to move&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When Melih moved his Queen to c2, I was in shock and disgust at
myself: in my fatigue near the end of this game, and overexcitement at
believing I had &amp;ldquo;refuted&amp;rdquo; a &amp;ldquo;trap&amp;rdquo;, I had completely failed to take
into account that White was not actually required to take my Rook on d4!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amusingly, it turns out that Melih, after playing 29 Rac2 setting the
&amp;ldquo;trap&amp;rdquo;, saw to his horror the resource 30&amp;hellip;Rxd4, and thought he was
lost, but then saw 31 Qc2. So neither of us had originally seen this
saving resource for White.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;questions-4&#34;&gt;Questions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is Black&amp;rsquo;s Queen trapped for real now?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What should Black do? Is Black lost? Or is Black still winning? Or
should Black start looking for a draw?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;black-panicked-trying-to-draw&#34;&gt;Black panicked, trying to draw&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, Black&amp;rsquo;s Queen is trapped for real. You get credit if you saw
that Black&amp;rsquo;s flashy 30&amp;hellip;Rxd4 had this flaw.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only question for me was how best to give up my Queen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I chose poorly. In a daze, I could not think straight. I chose to give
back a Rook with 31&amp;hellip;Qxc3, in order to force a trade Queens on c3 and
go into an endgame an exchange down for two Pawns, and hope for a draw.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../chess/ozbek-chen-2015-11-17/36w.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;31...Qxc3; White to move&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I was correct that the resulting position was objectively equal and
drawable, but in a time scramble, it&amp;rsquo;s obviously easier to play White,
and for the rest of the game, both sides made major errors (with White
botching up winning positions and Black botching up drawn positions)
until a simplified position was reached (Rook and two Pawns for each
side) with only seconds left on the clock, and a draw agreed. I
consider myself lucky to have drawn. The final position was:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../chess/ozbek-chen-2015-11-17/draw.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Agreed drawn&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;but-black-could-have-played-to-win&#34;&gt;But Black could have played to win&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You get credit if you chose instead to sacrifice the Queen with
31&amp;hellip;Qxc1+ to get the Rook and Bishop and Pawns against White&amp;rsquo;s Queen,
with advantage and a good chance of winning. After 32 Qxc1 Bxb4, Black
is about to win White&amp;rsquo;s c3 Pawn:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../chess/ozbek-chen-2015-11-17/33rooksw.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;32...Bxb4; White to move&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In fact, if you saw all this when thinking about whether to take the
Pawn on a3 in the first place, then you get bonus points for seeing a
way to an advantage through the sequence of tactical blows. Neither
Melih nor I saw any of this up front, unfortunately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I chickened out and did not take this continuation because after being
shocked that my Queen was disappearing, I experienced a visceral fear
that I needed to bring down White&amp;rsquo;s Queen also, else it with White&amp;rsquo;s
Rook might be dangerous to my King.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that my fear was objectively unwarranted, as Black&amp;rsquo;s
defenses are sufficient because of the power of the dark-squared
Bishop to hit White&amp;rsquo;s e5 Pawn and even the f2 Pawn, but I was not
thinking straight any more as time was running out for the four-hour
game and it was already around 11 PM at night on a weekday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;one-possible-position&#34;&gt;One possible position&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a position that might have arisen if I had gone into this
variation:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../chess/ozbek-chen-2015-11-17/35rooksw.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;White to move&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The thing is, even though the computer says Black has an advantage, it
could be scary playing against White&amp;rsquo;s Queen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;another-possible-position&#34;&gt;Another possible position&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But analysis also shows that White has to be very careful. For
example, if White is greedy and wastes time taking Black&amp;rsquo;s a7 Pawn
above, Black quickly gets a winning attack:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../chess/ozbek-chen-2015-11-17/37rooksw.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;White to move&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In time pressure, anything can happen, and I think it would have been
very likely that White would have grabbed the a7 Pawn, after which
Black&amp;rsquo;s position play itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;finally-black-s-real-refutation&#34;&gt;Finally: Black&amp;rsquo;s real refutation!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I said you get extra credit for seeing everything to the point of
sacrificing Black&amp;rsquo;s Queen for an advantage. But you only get full
credit if you saw the real refutation of White&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;trap&amp;rdquo; earlier in the
game! I kicked myself for not having seen it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;questions-5&#34;&gt;Questions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Was there a point at which Black could have deviated and won the
game outright?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hint: which of Black&amp;rsquo;s pieces have we not focused on in the
variations covered so far?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;answers-4&#34;&gt;Answers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Black could, after White &amp;ldquo;trapped&amp;rdquo; the Queen with 30 Ra2, used a
different and better deflection of White&amp;rsquo;s overloaded Queen than
30&amp;hellip;Rxd4, which was OK but not best.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We haven&amp;rsquo;t looked at Black&amp;rsquo;s Bishop enough. I only saw this upon
recovering from the draw and analyzing the game later at home: the
winning shot is 30&amp;hellip;Bg5!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../chess/ozbek-chen-2015-11-17/31varw.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;White to move&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If White blocks the threat to the Queen with 31 f4,
then Black just lops off the Pawn with 31&amp;hellip;Bxf4 and now:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;if White takes the Bishop or otherwise moves the Queen, Black will
win either the Rook on a2 or the Rook on c1&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;if White takes Black&amp;rsquo;s Queen, then Black takes White&amp;rsquo;s Queen on d2
with tempo and will eventually win all three of White&amp;rsquo;s weak
Pawns on dark squares (c3 followed by e5 and b4)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Either way, the endgame is an easy win for Black.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neither Melih nor I saw this winning resource for Black during the
game. We just weren&amp;rsquo;t looking at that quiet Bishop because it hadn&amp;rsquo;t
participated in anything up till that point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chess never ceases to surprise me. Tactical possibilities are
everywhere, and in this game, both Melih and I missed various
possible continuations, playing moves thinking we knew what had to
follow. I hope you enjoyed this story of missed opportunities and
incomplete calculations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My thanks to Melih for a challenging and fascinating game, and sharing
his thoughts with me afterwards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&#34;true&#34;  href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/franklinmingchen/23445261516/in/datetaken/&#34; title=&#34;Melih and Franklin at the Pittsburgh Chess Club&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm1.staticflickr.com/589/23445261516_25ee07e170_z.jpg&#34; width=&#34;640&#34; height=&#34;480&#34; alt=&#34;Franklin and Melih at the Pittsburgh Chess Club&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async src=&#34;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;appendix-interactive-playable-board&#34;&gt;Appendix: interactive playable board&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;
        src=&#34;http://chesstempo.com/js/pgnyui.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;
        src=&#34;http://chesstempo.com/js/pgnviewer.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;link
     type=&#34;text/css&#34;
     rel=&#34;stylesheet&#34;
     href=&#34;http://chesstempo.com/css/board-min.css&#34;&gt;
&lt;/link&gt;

&lt;script&gt;
    new PgnViewer(
      { boardName: &#34;demo&#34;,
        pgnFile: &#39;/chess/ozbek-chen-2015-11-17/ozbek-chen.pgn&#39;,
        pieceSet: &#39;merida&#39;,
        pieceSize: 46
      }
    );
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;style&gt;
#demo-stuff {
    display: flex;
}

#demo-moves {
    overflow-y: auto;
}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;div id=&#34;demo-stuff&#34;&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;demo-container&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;demo-moves&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thoughts on learning that I have eaten English muffins wrong all my life</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/06/28/thoughts-on-learning-that-i-have-eaten-english-muffins-wrong-all-my-life/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Jun 2015 18:25:34 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/06/28/thoughts-on-learning-that-i-have-eaten-english-muffins-wrong-all-my-life/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today, I found out I had been eating
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/English_muffin&#34;&gt;English muffins&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;em&gt;wrong&lt;/em&gt; my whole life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-story&#34;&gt;The story&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This morning, while at breakfast in a hotel before Abby and I were
checking out before returning home, I suddenly decided I might as well
change things up and eat my egg and sausage patties inside the halves
of an English muffin (yesterday I had eaten them alone, and an
uninspiring crappy plain bagel on the side).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I was about to bite into my sandwich, Abby interrupted me and said,
&amp;ldquo;You need to toast the English muffin.&amp;rdquo; I said, &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;ve never toasted an
English muffin.&amp;rdquo; She made a face of disgust and said, &amp;ldquo;Eww, that&amp;rsquo;s
&lt;em&gt;wrong&lt;/em&gt;, English muffins are designed to be eaten toasted! They are
disgusting raw.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I disputed that there was a &amp;ldquo;right&amp;rdquo; way to eat English muffins, but
allowed her to toast the muffin halves for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The resulting sandwich tasted pretty good. I then realized that I had
been eating English muffins wrong my entire life. How could this be?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-breakfast-growing-up-in-america&#34;&gt;My breakfast growing up in America&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have to understand that I spent the first couple of years of my
remembered childhood, as the first child of immigrant parents to
America, eating a breakfast that often consisted of
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Congee&#34;&gt;congee&lt;/a&gt; (rice porridge) with
toppings (I particularly liked pickled cucumbers and
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rousong&#34;&gt;rousong&lt;/a&gt;, a dried pork product).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bread was not part of my usual diet until I went to Kindergarten in
New York City, where I ate free lunches and was introduced to such
bizarre concepts as the grilled
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cheese_sandwich&#34;&gt;cheese sandwich&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did increasingly eat &amp;ldquo;American&amp;rdquo; foods as I grew up, but still, I was
never introduced to the full variety of breakfast foods for a long
time. It wasn&amp;rsquo;t until I was over ten years old, for example, that I
took the initiative and convinced my mother that we should try out
pancakes and waffles and cinnamon toast. Jellies, jams, syrup, butter
really came into my life then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But English muffins were somehow left out. My mother bought them but
apparently &lt;em&gt;we ate them wrong&lt;/em&gt;. We didn&amp;rsquo;t toast them. And because &lt;em&gt;they
didn&amp;rsquo;t taste so good&lt;/em&gt; to me, I never really ate them again. For the
next decades of my life, given a choice, I never took an English
muffin if I could instead eat a donut, cupcake, bagel, or ordinary
sliced bread. I had come to associate English muffins with &amp;ldquo;not
tasty&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;lessons-learned-from-my-conversion-today&#34;&gt;Lessons learned from my conversion today&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, this morning I learned that toasted English muffins are actually
pretty good. They have a particular texture, form factor, aroma,
crispness when toasted. Although I currently try to limit my intake of
bread in general, in the future if I am confronted with the usual free
hotel breakfast, I will definitely choose English muffins!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After we returned home, I actually looked online to find out the
&amp;ldquo;truth&amp;rdquo; about English muffins. Well, it turns out that a lot of people
online do note that raw English muffins don&amp;rsquo;t taste so good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What broader lessons have I learned?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is possible for an immigrant to live in a country for decades and
yet not fully understand what a native does, simply because of early
choices or misleading experiences in some aspect of life.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Just because something tastes bad in one form doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean it has to
taste bad in &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; its possible forms (I am always learning this; I only
recently learned to &lt;a href=&#34;../blog/2014/03/21/time-to-taste-the-world-thoughts-on-expanding-my-food-tastes-as-an-adult&#34;&gt;enjoy Brussels sprouts&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Although there is no such thing, objectively, as preparing or eating
something the &amp;ldquo;wrong&amp;rdquo; way, you might find some ways (including
generally accepted traditional practices) to have merit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;People don&amp;rsquo;t always tell you when you&amp;rsquo;re doing something
&amp;ldquo;wrong&amp;rdquo;. Some might just be polite and remain silent. Others might
let the oddity slip because they think you are just being weird and
truly enjoy raw English muffins. Don&amp;rsquo;t make the assumption that
people are doing what they really like; they could just be operating
out of habit and not knowing or having explored an alternative.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed learning that English muffins are actually edible after
all. I don&amp;rsquo;t really expect to ever eat a raw English muffin again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Has anyone ever pointed out something to you that you weren&amp;rsquo;t aware
  of even though maybe you &amp;ldquo;should&amp;rdquo; have known? Did you feel
  embarrassed or argue, or did you try out the new suggestion? When
  you see someone doing something weird, do you ever step in and offer
  a suggestion, or do you prefer to be polite and not be nosy?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;postscript&#34;&gt;Postscript&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This evening when discussing the breakfast incident with Abby, somehow
the subject of bagels came up and she said something about toasting
bagels, and I recoiled in horror, because I was pretty sure that
&lt;em&gt;bagels are not supposed to be toasted&lt;/em&gt;. Again, I had to consult the
Internet to find out the &amp;ldquo;truth&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you might expect, the truth is that I grew up with bagels living in
New York City and the East Coast in general, before moving to the
Midwest. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.thedailymeal.com/real-new-yorkers-dont-toast-their-bagels&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Real New Yorkers don&amp;rsquo;t toast their bagels&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;.
If you have access to a fresh, good bagel, it&amp;rsquo;s pretty wrong to toast
it, right? Well, as the article points out, there are differing
opinions, admittedly, and nobody argues that a crappy stale bagel or a
frozen one shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be toasted. Still, out of sheer habit, I have
never toasted a bagel, even if it might deserve toasting. Interesting,
huh? It&amp;rsquo;s just a habit. I see the logic of reviving a bagel as
needed. So I will consider toasting crappy bagels in the future if
they need that treatment.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The importance of stalemate in chess: how chess is completely different from life</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/06/16/the-importance-of-stalemate-in-chess-how-chess-is-completely-different-from-life/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Jun 2015 22:16:19 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/06/16/the-importance-of-stalemate-in-chess-how-chess-is-completely-different-from-life/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I just saw a cute end to a top-level chess game that ended in a forced
draw because the would-be losing side &lt;a href=&#34;http://dejanbojkov.blogspot.com/2015/06/jakovenko-and-stalemate.html&#34;&gt;managed a swindle&lt;/a&gt; by giving away
all his pieces by force in order to create a
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stalemate&#34;&gt;stalemate&lt;/a&gt;. If you don&amp;rsquo;t
play chess, a stalemate is what happens when it&amp;rsquo;s your turn to move
and you have no legal moves. You can claim a draw when you are &lt;em&gt;totally
trapped&lt;/em&gt; in this way. So one way of saving an otherwise losing game,
when you are outnumbered and about to be checkmated (losing when your
King comes under attack and it&amp;rsquo;s your move and you cannot stop the
check), is to find a brilliant way to be &lt;em&gt;unable to move&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../images/stalemate.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Black forced a draw through being stalemated!&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Is this a totally bizarre concept or what? Why was this rule of chess
invented anyway? Wouldn&amp;rsquo;t it make more sense if being trapped meant
&lt;em&gt;losing&lt;/em&gt;, like it does in real life conflicts?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;history-of-stalemate&#34;&gt;History of stalemate&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stalemate was apparently
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stalemate#History_of_the_stalemate_rule&#34;&gt;standardized to be a draw in the 19th century&lt;/a&gt;. Before
that, conventions differed on what the outcome of the game was
supposed to be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now and then, notable chess players have called for the abolishment of
his rule, to replace the stalemate with a win for the side that
trapped the other side, because this is &amp;ldquo;logical&amp;rdquo; and corresponds to
what you would expect in war or in some other &amp;ldquo;real life&amp;rdquo; situation in
which you have pressed hard for a long time, accumulated a lot of
force, and can cause your opponent to not be able to move at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;i-like-that-stalemate-is-illogical&#34;&gt;I like that stalemate is illogical&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m going to be blunt: I like that stalemate is &amp;ldquo;illogical&amp;rdquo;! It
creates tremendous difficulty for the side with more material to win
in endgames. I like that it gives the underdog a chance to avoid
losing by being clever. If stalemate were not a draw, then it would be
trivial to win many games in which one side has made a mistake and
lost a Pawn, because then all that has to be done is trade everything
off until all that remains is a King and Pawn versus King, and declare
victory. Stalemate means that the side with the extra Pawn has to work
super hard to avoid trading everything off, to avoid just mechanically
fighting battles with equal losses on both sides until one Pawn is
left.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like stalemate because in real life, often it is too easy for one
side to win just because of an early error by the loser. &lt;em&gt;Chess is not
real life&lt;/em&gt;, and I like it that way. Stalemate and other rules of chess
add bizarre whimsy and creativity to the game, just as the rule of
checkmate at all is counter to real life. In real life, you can kill
the general of an army and still lose the war. In chess, it&amp;rsquo;s always
like in the movies, on the other hand: you can have a lone hero defy
all odds to get at the enemy King and sacrifice everything else for
this objective, and have a happy ending. There is something &lt;em&gt;romantic&lt;/em&gt;
about chess that is part of its appeal to me. Chess is a game of logic
but according to weird heroic rules, where sheer &lt;em&gt;material wealth&lt;/em&gt; is
not enough to guarantee a win.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is unfortunate that many top-level chess games end in a draw, but
to abolish stalemate would change the capricious character of the
game in a way that ruins its appeal to me (on a lower level of play).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you are not a chess player, what do you think of the stalemate
  rule? If you are a chess player, what do you think of it?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How learning about the Magna Carta in high school changed my life</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/06/13/how-learning-about-the-magna-carta-in-high-school-changed-my-life/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Jun 2015 15:35:30 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/06/13/how-learning-about-the-magna-carta-in-high-school-changed-my-life/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I couldn&amp;rsquo;t help noticing the headlines in the news lately about the
800th anniversary of the
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Magna_Carta&#34;&gt;Magna Carta&lt;/a&gt;, that
historical document from 1215 in England. As I write, apparently there
is a
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bbc.com/news/uk-england-33116579&#34;&gt;celebration being held on the River Thames&lt;/a&gt;,
even. And I just found a Web site devoted entirely to this
&lt;a href=&#34;http://magnacarta800th.com/&#34;&gt;800th anniversary&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Magna Carta has not been on my mind for over thirty years since I
first learned about it in a social studies class in the ninth grade high
school in the early 1980s. But when I think about it, the surprising
truth is that learning about the Magna Carta was a &lt;em&gt;turning point&lt;/em&gt; in
my life as a new teenager (age twelve or thirteen), and the lessons I
learned have informed me throughout my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-is-the-magna-carta-associated-with&#34;&gt;What is the Magna Carta associated with?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Magna Carta in popular imagination is associated with &amp;ldquo;liberty&amp;rdquo;,
with &amp;ldquo;the people&amp;rdquo; rising up in revolt against arbitrary monarchy and
making King John sign a document guaranteeing basic rights, such as
the right to a fair trail and no taxation without representation; and
&amp;ldquo;equality&amp;rdquo;, putting the king himself under the scope of law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Magna Carta is thought of as an inspiration for
subsequent milestones in history such as the United States Declaration
of Independence and the &lt;a href=&#34;../categories/constitution/&#34;&gt;Constitution&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-truth-as-i-learned-it&#34;&gt;The truth as I learned it&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I took a required &amp;ldquo;social studies&amp;rdquo; class in the ninth grade in high
school. It was one of the most interesting and life-changing classes I
ever took. I remember more from that class than probably any other in
all of high school. I loved the class because it was a small honors
class, didn&amp;rsquo;t follow a standard textbook, the teacher had us engage in
discussions, and we did many interesting activities such as watch
films and play games and do simulations. She used a kind of &amp;ldquo;Socratic
method&amp;rdquo; to direct us and get us thinking and offering our opinions
with reasons. &lt;em&gt;This was the one of the first (and few) times in school
in which I felt I was being treated as an independent adult-to-be, not
as a child.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is what I learned in ninth grade social studies class from the
coverage of the Magna Carta:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John,_King_of_England&#34;&gt;King John&lt;/a&gt; was
just one of a line of random kings in history who gained their power
from accident of birth rather than anything else.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Our teacher made fun of an artist&amp;rsquo;s fictional depiction of King
John&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;signing&amp;rdquo; the Magna Carta, arguing that since King John was
illiterate, he could not have signed it, and usual practice was to
press his seal on documents. (Amusingly, there is still
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bbc.com/news/blogs-magazine-monitor-30879124&#34;&gt;online discussion of this detail&lt;/a&gt;
decades after my class.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The whole Magna Carta thing came out of a civil war. It wasn&amp;rsquo;t like
one side was really right and the king was particularly evil as far
as kings went back in the day.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A bunch of &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Landed_gentry&#34;&gt;landed nobility&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Collusion&#34;&gt;colluded&lt;/a&gt; to protect their
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Collective_bargaining&#34;&gt;collective interests&lt;/a&gt;.
Basically, they tried to form the first &amp;ldquo;union&amp;rdquo; against royal
interests.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This document did not have anything to do with &amp;ldquo;the people&amp;rdquo; as such
(who in those days lived in abject misery whether under the nobility
or the king). The Magna Carta was not for the &amp;ldquo;little people&amp;rdquo;. Its
clauses were specific about whom they applied to, i.e., &amp;ldquo;free men&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Magna Carta was the product of a power struggle among those who
already had power. It was about power and money. A bunch of
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rent-seeking&#34;&gt;rent-seeking&lt;/a&gt; nobility
didn&amp;rsquo;t like that the king was arbitrarily cutting in on them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Magna Carta was originally a flop: civil war continued, King
John ignored its rules. But it proved useful later symbolically when
conditions changed, proved to be something to rally around and
reinterpret for a new age.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;no-untarnished-heroes&#34;&gt;No untarnished heroes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest question that arose in discussion was, should we be
cynical about the Magna Carta because of what it was originally for,
as opposed to what it later became to stand for or how it inspired
more far-reaching change? I think we can ask that of anything,
especially, for those of us in the United States, of our own
perception of our Founding Fathers and the nature of the American
Revolution, which all occurred five hundred years after the Magna
Carta.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I learned from the study of history (which I enjoyed so much I
took two non-required world history courses in the tenth grade before
the required American history sequence in the eleventh grade) that
there are no easy answers, and that it is important to be skeptical of
mythologizing the past. I have remembered these lessons long after not
thinking about the Magna Carta again after that class in the ninth
grade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The noblemen who came up with the Magna Carta may have been thinking
only of themselves, but might have unwittingly paved the way for
others. Intention is one thing, but the final result is another
thing. (And history shows that there never is a final result either.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;some-interesting-resources-on-the-magna-carta&#34;&gt;Some interesting resources on the Magna Carta&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a &lt;a href=&#34;http://the-orb.net/textbooks/muhlberger/magna_carta.html&#34;&gt;medieval studies textbook section on the Magna Carta&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did not touch upon the religion aspect of the power struggles in the
medieval era (such as King John&amp;rsquo;s fights with the Pope; three hundred
years after King John, the whole
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Church_of_England&#34;&gt;Church of England&lt;/a&gt;
finally split off from Catholicism when King Henry VIII wanted to
annul a marriage but the Pope wouldn&amp;rsquo;t let him), but here is a
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/09531a.htm&#34;&gt;Catholic encyclopedia article about the Magna Carta&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s an article about a Magna Carta skeptic, a British judge who
calls it an insignificant, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/uknews/law-and-order/11670716/Magna-Carta-Turgid-document-was-eclipsed-by-the-French-says-top-judge.html&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;turgid document&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can search online for a whole lot more commentary, given the
hugeness of this 800th anniversary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;here-s-that-fictional-depiction&#34;&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s that fictional depiction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:A_Chronicle_of_England_-_Page_226_-_John_Signs_the_Great_Charter.jpg#/media/File:A_Chronicle_of_England_-_Page_226_-_John_Signs_the_Great_Charter.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;A Chronicle of England - Page 226 - John Signs the Great Charter.jpg&#34; src=&#34;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/d/d6/A_Chronicle_of_England_-_Page_226_-_John_Signs_the_Great_Charter.jpg&#34; height=&#34;480&#34; width=&#34;598&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#34;&lt;a href=&#34;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:A_Chronicle_of_England_-_Page_226_-_John_Signs_the_Great_Charter.jpg#/media/File:A_Chronicle_of_England_-_Page_226_-_John_Signs_the_Great_Charter.jpg&#34;&gt;A Chronicle of England - Page 226 - John Signs the Great Charter&lt;/a&gt;&#34; by &lt;a href=&#34;//en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_William_Edmund_Doyle&#34; class=&#34;extiw&#34; title=&#34;en:James William Edmund Doyle&#34;&gt;James William Edmund Doyle&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;a href=&#34;//en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_William_Edmund_Doyle&#34; class=&#34;extiw&#34; title=&#34;w:James William Edmund Doyle&#34;&gt;Doyle, James William Edmund&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;span style=&#34;white-space:nowrap&#34;&gt;1864&lt;/span&gt;) &#34;&lt;a rel=&#34;nofollow&#34; class=&#34;external text&#34; href=&#34;http://books.google.com.sg/books?id=YcM_AAAAYAAJ&amp;amp;pg=PA226&#34;&gt;John&lt;/a&gt;&#34; in &lt;a rel=&#34;nofollow&#34; class=&#34;external text&#34; href=&#34;http://books.google.com.sg/books?id=YcM_AAAAYAAJ&#34;&gt;A Chronicle of England: B.C. 55 – A.D. 1485&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;//en.wikipedia.org/wiki/London&#34; class=&#34;extiw&#34; title=&#34;en:London&#34;&gt;London&lt;/a&gt;: Longman, Green, Longman, Roberts &amp;amp; Green, pp.&amp;nbsp;p. 226 Retrieved on &lt;span style=&#34;white-space:nowrap&#34;&gt;12 November 2010&lt;/span&gt;.. Licensed under Public Domain via &lt;a href=&#34;//commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/&#34;&gt;Wikimedia Commons&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;extrapolations&#34;&gt;Extrapolations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, all around us we see fights that are supposedly about principle
but are really power struggles. Instead of landed nobility, we have
powerful lobbying groups, multinational corporations, you name
it. When any of these interests collude to win a battle over some
other one, they might not be in the game for you and me, but for
themselves. The purported idea of &amp;ldquo;democracy&amp;rdquo; is in fact under siege
today on many fronts. In future blog posts, I will begin exploring
what some of these are; they mostly involve technology-based power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2015-06-14&#34;&gt;(Update of 2015-06-14)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the local paper, I just read this really interesting article by
University of Pittsburgh law professor Bernard Hibbits on the
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.post-gazette.com/news/world/2015/06/14/How-Magna-Carta-helped-make-America/stories/201506150001&#34;&gt;opportunistic use of the Magna Carta by Americans&lt;/a&gt; throughout history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2015-06-16&#34;&gt;(Update of 2015-06-16)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A random
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bbc.com/news/uk-33126723&#34;&gt;news article about the celebrations&lt;/a&gt;
feature nothing but photos or descriptions of an Archbishop, the
Queen, various Dukes, a Prince, a Princess, a Lord, a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.therichest.com/celebnetworth/politician/minister/david-cameron-net-worth/&#34;&gt;Prime Minister&lt;/a&gt;
who
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_Cameron#Inheritance_and_family_wealth&#34;&gt;inherited much wealth (a lot hidden in tax shelters)&lt;/a&gt;,
and had no photos of &amp;ldquo;regular people&amp;rdquo;, or quotes from them asking what
they thought of the lavish occasion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yeah, same old, same old, 800 years later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Learning about the Magna Carta as a twelve-year-old was an important
part of my growing up in life. I learned that people are human and
selfish and have different motivations, but sometimes can work toward
agreements at least among themselves as equals, and some other party
as well. But I also learned the lesson that there are always those
who are left out at the bargaining table, and that the nobility are
always looking out for themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When did you learn about the Magna Carta in school? Did you learn it
  in the same gritty way that I did, or in a more romanticized way?
  Are there things you learned in history classes in school that
  changed your life, changed what you believe and how you act (as a
  voter or activist)?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How Ornette Coleman changed my life</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/06/12/how-ornette-coleman-changed-my-life/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jun 2015 23:59:40 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/06/12/how-ornette-coleman-changed-my-life/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The legendary jazz musician
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ornette_Coleman&#34;&gt;Ornette Coleman&lt;/a&gt;
recently died at age 85. He had not been on my radar for a long
time. In fact, I never actually listened to much of his music at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, my immediate first thought on hearing this news was, &lt;strong&gt;Ornette
Coleman permanently changed the course of my life&lt;/strong&gt;. How can this be?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;first-reactions-to-ornette-coleman-s-music&#34;&gt;First reactions to Ornette Coleman&amp;rsquo;s music&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2000, during a huge transition in my life that turned everything
upside down, I began experimenting with listening to a lot of kinds of
music I had never experienced before. I was exploring Cuban,
Brazilian, Argentinian music. I was exploring Western classical music
of the 20th century (I had a fairly narrow taste up till then focused
primarily on the Classical 18th century and Romantic 19th century,
with little before or after this range). In jazz, I was expanding
beyond the swing, bebop, hard bop eras of jazz. I frequently reached
areas that made me confused or disgusted. For example, in jazz I got
&lt;a href=&#34;../blog/2012/09/23/celebrating-the-birthday-of-john-coltrane/&#34;&gt;as far as I could with John Coltrane&lt;/a&gt;
as Coltrane ventured into &amp;ldquo;free jazz&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided to try out Ornette Coleman for another approach to &amp;ldquo;free
jazz&amp;rdquo;, and checked out the album
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Shape_of_Jazz_to_Come&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Shape of Jazz to Come&amp;rdquo; (1959)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;lonely-woman&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Lonely Woman&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Immediately, I was struck by the track
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lonely_Woman_%28composition%29&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Lonely Woman&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. Conventional
concerns such as being strictly &amp;ldquo;in tune&amp;rdquo; were out the window, in
favor of extremely flexibility of pitch and raw, wailing emotional
expression. It showcased Coleman&amp;rsquo;s lyrical side and was easy to
love. OK, not too weird.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/DNbD1JIH344&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;other-tracks&#34;&gt;Other tracks&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But bam, that was just a warmup. For example, check out
&amp;ldquo;Eventually&amp;rdquo;. It&amp;rsquo;s very free indeed, a lot of notes, an expression of
hyperactive motion, conventional tonality unimportant. Still, not too
harsh, and not totally random.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/WoC69lxnS_Y&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, what I really understood from his music was that he was doing
what came naturally to him. It did not feel forced, it was not to
prove a point. He was enjoying what he was doing. This sense of
&lt;em&gt;freedom&lt;/em&gt; really impressed me. It wasn&amp;rsquo;t reaction, it wasn&amp;rsquo;t
rebellion. I respected that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;free-jazz-a-collective-improvisation&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Free Jazz: A Collective Improvisation&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next album I checked out was
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Free_Jazz:_A_Collective_Improvisation&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Free Jazz: A Collective Improvisation&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was a step beyond, and confusing to me because of the
simultaneous playing that often seemed chaotic. I confess to taking no
huge pleasure in attempting to listen to it all at once (note that
apart from lack of conventional structure, it also keeps going on and
on at length). I found it more enjoyable to listen to only a couple of
random minutes, trying to absorb some stretch of order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, although this was not really my thing, it opened up my mind
to &amp;ldquo;why not?&amp;rdquo; Maybe this particular experiment didn&amp;rsquo;t work, but I
could imagine a simpler setting, say, with fewer instruments, in which
collective improvisation could work out better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check it out yourself:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/xbZIiom9rDA&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;something-else&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Something Else!!!!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I checked out
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Something_Else!!!!&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Something Else!!!!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;,
which actually was his first album and closer to bebop and so forth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t have much to say about it, but it&amp;rsquo;s not too confusing to
enjoy, because of still audible ties to some traditional forms and
styles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;freedom&#34;&gt;Freedom&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, I didn&amp;rsquo;t continue exploring Coleman&amp;rsquo;s music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the sense of &lt;em&gt;freedom&lt;/em&gt;, of &lt;em&gt;permission&lt;/em&gt; to ignore boundaries and
go wherever, musically, really affected me. Was what he was doing
&amp;ldquo;jazz&amp;rdquo;? Listening to him, I made up my mind that I was never again
going to get involved in debates about what jazz &amp;ldquo;really is&amp;rdquo; or what
classical music &amp;ldquo;really is&amp;rdquo; or even what music &amp;ldquo;really is&amp;rdquo;. These
labels stopped being meaningful to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That was what I really learned from him and his life. By coincidence,
I just read this Rolling Stone article,
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rollingstone.com/music/news/vernon-reid-on-ornette-coleman-he-set-a-lot-of-people-free-20150612&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Vernon Reid on Ornette Coleman: &amp;lsquo;He set a lot of people free&amp;rsquo;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;,
that echoes exactly what I felt I learned fifteen years ago from my
brief exposure to him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past year or so, there have been times when, alone and not
likely to bother anyone, I pull out my bass recorder (ha, my lowest
instrument) and just go wild, play some melodic shapes, make up
rhythms, go multiphonic, whatever, for the sheer joy of it. And I&amp;rsquo;m
not embarrassed, because I remember Ornette Coleman and he gave us all
permission to express our unconscious in whatever honest way it comes
out. And he gave us permission to accept and encourage each other to
do that, whether or not we personally like or understand everything
that comes out of tapping the unconscious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hadn&amp;rsquo;t expected to think so much upon hearing of Ornette Coleman&amp;rsquo;s
death. But he set an example that I respected deeply, forever changing
not only my perceptions of music but of what musicians can and should
be allowed to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Are you an Ornette Coleman fan or detractor? Did he change your
  life? If so, how exactly?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What unexpected life lessons have you learned from your father?</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/06/11/what-unexpected-life-lessons-have-you-learned-from-your-father/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Jun 2015 22:15:56 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/06/11/what-unexpected-life-lessons-have-you-learned-from-your-father/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I came across a great story by a guy who wrote an article,
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bbc.com/news/magazine-32961309&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;How my father gave me a terrifying lesson at 10&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please read the whole thing before reading further below, where I&amp;rsquo;ll
share some stories about my own father.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-misunderstood-lesson&#34;&gt;The misunderstood lesson&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Warning: this is a spoiler if you haven&amp;rsquo;t already read
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bbc.com/news/magazine-32961309&#34;&gt;the story&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Did you guess what the lesson was going to be before reaching the
  end of the story? At what point did you get the idea that the author
  of the story did not grasp for twenty years?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I saw it coming as soon as terrifying accidents started happening down
in the coal mine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically, the father was trying to terrify his son out of becoming a
coal miner like him. It was an act of manipulation but also of
compassion. And it worked, but not without his son bearing resentment
for the apparently mean and senseless prank for twenty years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-stories&#34;&gt;My stories&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was reminded of some less drastic manipulation that I faced in my
childhood that had unexpected benefits that I didn&amp;rsquo;t understand at the
time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like the author, I was about ten years old when these incidents
occurred: old enough to feel embarrassment, shame, self-consciousness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-cigar&#34;&gt;The cigar&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One day my father came home from work with a box of cigars. I guess it
was some kind of present. Neither he nor my mother smoked at all, so I
was surprised that he lit one up and handed it to me to try out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that this was around 1980, when I had lived ten years in the
1970s when I still saw a lot of smoking in old TV show and movies, and
I saw the Marlboro Man everywhere in print (he just
&lt;a href=&#34;http://thinkprogress.org/health/2014/01/27/3207091/marlboro-man-dies-smoking/&#34;&gt;died last year from chronic obstructive pulmonary disease &lt;/a&gt;. Today&amp;rsquo;s
anti-smoking culture in America did not exist yet then. I knew lots of
people who smoked: my relatives, doctors, you name it. In fact, in the
blue-collar neighborhood where we lived, half the teachers smoked,
probably half my schoolmates smoked by the time they got to around age
12, our next door neighbors and their children all smoked. The local
chess club my father took me to, located in the basement of the
community center, was always filled with smoke.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I had not yet reached an age when I might have started running
around with a smoking crowd and gotten into it myself. I had a little
bit of curiosity, but not much. Still, enough that I was excited that
my father was going to share something &amp;ldquo;grownup&amp;rdquo; with me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had no idea what I was doing, took a puff, and coughed with total
disgust. I didn&amp;rsquo;t know at the time that there were proper ways to
handle a cigar; I guess it was a good thing I didn&amp;rsquo;t know that. All I
knew was that I was in agony, the special treat from my father was
bullshit, that I never wanted anything to do with a cigar, or by
extension a cigarette, again in my life. I was &lt;em&gt;angry&lt;/em&gt; that he did
this thing to me. We never talked about this incident again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And therefore, I have never smoked in my life. The memory of that
experience was just too painful, and also by middle school, I started
hearing preaching by some other adults (and some crusading classmates
as well) about the health dangers of smoking. I was so traumatized
that this information alone put me off permanently, overriding any
natural curiosity I had about how pleasurable smoking had to be that
people would take risks and pay money to engage in it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-beer&#34;&gt;The beer&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Something similar happened with alcohol. One day my father had some
cans of beer around, probably left over after some office party. We
never had alcohol around. My parents did not drink. At least, so I
thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, to my surprise, he opened a can and said to take a sip and try
it out. I knew this was a &amp;ldquo;grownup&amp;rdquo; thing to do that I wasn&amp;rsquo;t supposed
to, so I eagerly tried it out. The taste was revolting. Meanwhile, he
drank the whole thing. Then he quickly got very red and acted funny. I
learned a couple of lessons immediately from this: he shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be
drinking, I hate beer, and I don&amp;rsquo;t want to get all red and funny.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, I was completely immune, all the way through high school,
to any peer pressure to drink. Never mind that eventually I learned
that you may have to get used to the taste, or that there were entire
other worlds of alcohol, such as wine, that tasted different. For a
long time, I just didn&amp;rsquo;t feel like experimenting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first time I drank alcohol again was right before college, some
champagne at an awards ceremony for a science competition that took
place the summer after I graduated from high school. I don&amp;rsquo;t know if I
got red, but I was told that I was acting funny, and so I went to my
room and fell asleep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went to a party the first week of college and there was beer, and
now under the influence of many new friends, I drank some. But I still
didn&amp;rsquo;t like it, didn&amp;rsquo;t like how everyone ended up behaving funny,
wasn&amp;rsquo;t too happy that we were all underage, and so I never drank again
in college.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since college, I have now and then partaken of beer and wine, and
acquired more of an appreciation, but because I get very dizzy and
sleepy quickly, currently I almost completely avoid drinking. It&amp;rsquo;s
just for the best.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lecturing one&amp;rsquo;s children not to do something doesn&amp;rsquo;t always work, but
sometimes trickery apparently works. I&amp;rsquo;m not praising it or condemning
it, because I&amp;rsquo;ve endured other forms of trickery from my parents that
backfired. I&amp;rsquo;m just surprised by how strongly I reacted and how
susceptible I was to first negative experiences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Do you have happy or sad examples of this kind of parental
  manipulation? Did they work on you or not, and was this to your
  long-term benefit or not? If you are a parent, are you above this
  trickery, or do you deliberately and cleverly use it?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Revisiting Bach&#39;s Air on G String, from a singing and dancing viewpoint</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/06/10/revisiting-bachs-air-on-g-string-from-a-singing-and-dancing-viewpoint/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jun 2015 23:46:26 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/06/10/revisiting-bachs-air-on-g-string-from-a-singing-and-dancing-viewpoint/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Three years ago, &lt;a href=&#34;../blog/2012/09/14/passion-of-bachs-air-on-the-g-string-three-different-interpretations/&#34;&gt;I wrote a post comparing three very different
performance styles&lt;/a&gt;
for Johann Sebastian Bach&amp;rsquo;s famous music,
&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Air_on_the_G_String&#34;&gt;Air on G String&lt;/a&gt;
and indicating which I preferred.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have received an unexpected number comments over the years, and
thought it was time to write an update of my thoughts in response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Primarily, I am responding to those who (correctly) criticized the
unfortunately chosen exemplar of the style that I preferred. I tried
to find better versions that might illustrate my perceptions. I also
integrated some thoughts based on how I perceive music as a singer and
as a dancer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;better-than-the-rushed-croatian-baroque-ensemble-s-performance&#34;&gt;Better than the rushed Croatian Baroque Ensemble&amp;rsquo;s performance?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I agreed quickly with the first commenters that the Croatian
ensemble&amp;rsquo;s performance was too perfunctory, even downright brutal and
unpleasant in various ways. I wish I had
chosen a better example of what I actually &lt;em&gt;like&lt;/em&gt; rather than &lt;em&gt;prefer
to the other two versions&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I searched YouTube for period-style performances that are
closer to what I envision than either the Croatian ensemble&amp;rsquo;s or
Koopman&amp;rsquo;s. It proved impossible for me to find a perfect performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-period-performance-i-like-more-christopher-hogwood&#34;&gt;A period performance I like more: Christopher Hogwood&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like this version by the late &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christopher_Hogwood&#34;&gt;Christopher Hogwood&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s Academy of
Ancient Music:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/nrtdhH8_47k&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a sweetness and &lt;em&gt;bouncy lightness&lt;/em&gt; to this version that I
like, but it is also somewhat anemic. Personally, I would play up more
contrast and fullness of sound and passion, but the overall tempo and
breathing to this version seems right to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;voices-of-music-richer-sound&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Voices of Music&amp;rdquo;: richer sound&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Voices of Music&amp;rdquo; here in a good performance:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/pzlw6fUux4o&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like the richness of sound in this performance. I miss the lighter,
more bouncy feeling that Hogwood brought out though. This performance
is a bit too legato for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;i-care-about-singing&#34;&gt;I care about singing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I approach this music from the viewpoint of singing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bouncy lightness is very important to me, along with the rhythmic
characterization. I feel this music as a song (it is an &amp;ldquo;air&amp;rdquo;, after
all), and I cannot help singing along when I hear it. Therefore, when
it&amp;rsquo;s taken too slow for me to sing and make it to natural breathing
points in phrases, that considerably lessens my pleasure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;yehudi-menuhin-solo-violin&#34;&gt;Yehudi Menuhin, solo violin&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s an interesting old black and white video of a performance by a young Yehudi Menuhin on violin with
accompaniment. It&amp;rsquo;s not a period performance, but moves along at a
decent &amp;ldquo;singing&amp;rdquo; tempo, as befits violin, that singing instrument.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34;
src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/08bDiKXW0gg&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;
allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I confess that I rather like this performance for its virtues,
although it distorts Bach&amp;rsquo;s music by so emphasizing just the musical
line, at the expense of the balance of the other voices and the
essential character of the dissonances among the voices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;more-menuhin-but-as-conductor&#34;&gt;More Menuhin, but as conductor&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s Yehudi Menuhin not as violin soloist but as conductor of the
Bath Festival Orchestra in 1960. Again, not a period performance, but
he takes the music briskly, and has the violins create sufficient
phrase delineations that I feel the music alertly as though it sings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s direct and clear, maybe not the most subtle and warm,
but I like it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/kaBAE4stNIo&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;dancing-is-possible-too&#34;&gt;Dancing is possible too&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also like to dance to expressive music. A pioneer of modern dance,
Doris Humphrey, famously choreographed a dance to a slowish
performance of this music:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/NjwJyaSIRqY&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not how I would dance to it, because I feel the music
differently. Surprisingly, I could find few examples on YouTube of
dancing to this music. I may consider choreographing a dance myself as
a project to express my own personal vision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing I would like to mention is that I feel that the &lt;em&gt;walking bass&lt;/em&gt;
is very important in this music and gives it the impetus. When played
too slow, the walking bass no longer feels like it&amp;rsquo;s walking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel this music in my legs, not just in my lungs. Yes, I have
actually hummed it to myself while walking in time to the bass
leisurely in the local park. There is a limit to how &amp;ldquo;leisurely&amp;rdquo; I can
walk without feeling frustrated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;ice-dancing&#34;&gt;Ice dancing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found this somewhat frenetic but nevertheless beautiful ice dancing
performance from the 1992 World Figure Skating Championships:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/1JjbwtM_E3g&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;recorder-quartet&#34;&gt;Recorder quartet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A final performance to enjoy: the Japanese &amp;ldquo;Sekishi Recorder Quartet&amp;rdquo;
playing their hearts out in 2009. I think it&amp;rsquo;s lovely: impeccable
phrasing, transparency,
and rich ensemble balance and tone. (As a twist, the melody line performer adds
his own ornamentations.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/pRRRK0UClNs&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was inspired by the accumulated comments on my previous post on
Bach&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Air on G String&amp;rdquo; that I decided to flesh out my thoughts by
using more example performances, as well as relate the orchestral
music to singing and dancing. I hope you have enjoyed these
explorations. There is no single &amp;ldquo;right&amp;rdquo; way to experience music, but
I wanted to share how I experience it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;ve read my previous post, does this one help clarify where
  I&amp;rsquo;m coming from with my musical values? Do you dance
  or sing? Does this affect how you perceive this piece of music and
  like to perform it or hear it performed?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why I have never considered using a treadmill desk</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/06/10/why-i-have-never-considered-using-a-treadmill-desk/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jun 2015 21:34:04 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/06/10/why-i-have-never-considered-using-a-treadmill-desk/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Ten years ago, in 2005, a friend of mine sent me an article about a
trend among some people to use a treadmill desk in order to squeeze in
some exercise while working. He seemed to think it sounded like a cool
idea that wouldn&amp;rsquo;t interfere much with work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have never considered using a treadmill desk. Because of a recent
article that seems to confirm my thoughts from a decade ago, I&amp;rsquo;m
posting my reaction here, along with a link to the article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-response-in-january-2005&#34;&gt;My response in January 2005&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At one point years ago I was thinking about stuff like that, but a few
experiments showed how pointless and soulless it is, for me.  My
enjoyment of exercise is completely ruined if extraneous stuff is
brought in, like reading or listening to music.  I learned that the
whole profound pleasure and meaning of physical activity comes from
being completely engaged in it, with nothing else on the mind.  So the
former fantasies of multitasking are now completely antithetical to my
current life values.

&lt;p&gt;
It&#39;s not the quantity [of treadmill movement] that&#39;s the issue.
That&#39;s still one foot per second of continuous movement, requiring
irrelevant constant muscular pulses.  Note that I cannot read a simple
newspaper in a car or a bus or a plane.

&lt;p&gt;
I fidget all the time, especially when playing chess, but the
movements are not arbitrary and disembodied, but are connected with
feelings of comfort or with emotional states relevant to my mental
processes.  It&#39;s not like a treadmill commanding me to go a foot every
second.  It&#39;s my personal choice when to shake my leg or shift my foot
or whatever, and for how long.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;philosophy-and-practice&#34;&gt;Philosophy and practice&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may be wondering, from how I phrased my reasons, whether I have a
primarily theoretical, ideological opposition to a treadmill desk, or
simply a pragmatic one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t really make a distinction: I take what works and doesn&amp;rsquo;t work
and make my observations a basis for a possibly more general
philosophy, rather than adopt an ideology and make my practice fit it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically, I actually have &lt;em&gt;tried&lt;/em&gt; multitasking in various ways for
the purpose of &amp;ldquo;saving time&amp;rdquo; and it just doesn&amp;rsquo;t work for
me. Furthermore, sometimes I multitask &lt;em&gt;despite knowing it doesn&amp;rsquo;t
work&lt;/em&gt;, and I pay the price. For example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I have tripped or fallen on runs or hikes when I &amp;ldquo;zoned out&amp;rdquo; and
wasn&amp;rsquo;t paying attention to the terrain but was thinking of something!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I have listened to music while reading a news article and failed to
follow the music at all.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s not saving time if I try to do two things and end up not even
doing one of them well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-research&#34;&gt;The research&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The article I just read was a news article,
&lt;a href=&#34;http://well.blogs.nytimes.com/2015/06/10/the-downside-of-treadmill-desks/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The downside of treadmill desks&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. I
was pretty shocked and amused to read, &amp;ldquo;&amp;hellip; surprisingly little
research had examined whether treadmill desks affect someone’s ability
to get work done.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The results, when the researchers compared the treadmill walkers with the people sitting at their desks, substantially favored sitting. The people who had walked during the testing performed worse on almost all aspects of thinking, including the ability to concentrate and remember, compared with those who had been seated.

&lt;p&gt;
And they were much worse at typing, being substantially slower and
more error prone than the sitting group.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The irony is that the researcher interviewed still wants to believe in
benefits:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
But even with that caveat, he said, he believes that the health
benefits of a treadmill desk should outweigh any declines in
productivity and, in fact, he plans to buy one for himself.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;alternatives&#34;&gt;Alternatives?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My alternative to sitting all day, which indeed is by now known to be
terrible for health, is simple:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get up now and then and take a break from my task and walk around.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But doesn&amp;rsquo;t this take time and stop the flow of work? Actually,
no. There&amp;rsquo;s only so much focus I can have while working on something
continuously without a break anyway. So forcing myself to take a walk
is actually a win-win situation, not even just a mere tradeoff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Treadmill desks do not appeal to me at all, and I believe I have sound
scientific reasons based on what psychology has learned about the
working of the human mind. However, I understand that different
people&amp;rsquo;s minds may work differently from mine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Have you used a treadmill desk? Why or why not? Do you believe in
your ability to multitask without a performance hit?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The many faces of &#34;Stella by Starlight&#34;</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/06/01/the-many-faces-of-stella-by-starlight/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jun 2015 01:08:23 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/06/01/the-many-faces-of-stella-by-starlight/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently I got obsessed with the classic 1944 jazz standard
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stella_by_Starlight&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Stella by Starlight&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought I&amp;rsquo;d share some very different interpretations of this music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;harry-james-1947&#34;&gt;Harry James, 1947&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the original version, not jazz, but slow, sentimental, lush: a
sentimental serenade perfect for dancing foxtrot to. Pretty good, if
you like &amp;ldquo;oldies&amp;rdquo;. And if you don&amp;rsquo;t like oldies, you need to hear this
anyway, to understand why the piece was so interesting: there is
inherently beautiful harmonic movement and color that would attract
jazz musicians to adopt this tune and transform it, and they still
continue to do that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/TjRMLqb6Sgs&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;miles-davis-quintet-1964&#34;&gt;Miles Davis quintet, 1964&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A really quirky version that starts with a slow intro before everyone
starts swinging, and then it goes fragmented again, and then the cycle
continues with all kinds of different ideas. Ten minutes long.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Riok08Y_ri4&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;tito-puente-around-1983&#34;&gt;Tito Puente, around 1983?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tito Puente and his Latin jazz band,
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michel_Camilo&#34;&gt;Michel Camilo&lt;/a&gt; on
piano. Puente himself starts off soloing on vibraphone: beautiful,
haunting rhythmic playing. Later, there is an electric guitar
solo. But mostly, this whole performance is melodic, and with its
steady and standard Afro-Cuban rhythmic drive, utterly danceable for
salsa. Something different!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the performance that inspired me to write this blog post,
because I&amp;rsquo;d never encountered this version before, but it was so
enchanting. From foxtrot original to salsa&amp;hellip; who would have thought?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34;
src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/xJF5BRuRtVo&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;
allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;chet-baker-quartet-1987&#34;&gt;Chet Baker quartet, 1987&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Live video footage from Tokyo. Baker is near the end of his tragic
life. He starts off with a fragmentary approach, and makes use of
long-held but gently played notes that creates soft but extended
dissonances against what&amp;rsquo;s going on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34;
src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/qq8oHYWHji8&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;
allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;learn-jazz-standards&#34;&gt;Learn Jazz Standards&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A wonderful backing track from &amp;ldquo;Learn Jazz Standards&amp;rdquo;, not for
listening to but playing against:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34;
src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/XR6KDWrn2ew&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;
allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One day I&amp;rsquo;ll take up the challenge of improvising an own performance
of &amp;ldquo;Stella by Starlight&amp;rdquo;, but I have to confess that right now it
seems too hard for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love &amp;ldquo;Stella by Starlight&amp;rdquo;. It will endure forever as a jazz
standard, I&amp;rsquo;m sure. I hope you like it too.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Yes, I want my writing to be dated!</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/05/31/yes-i-want-my-writing-to-be-dated/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 May 2015 22:55:05 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/05/31/yes-i-want-my-writing-to-be-dated/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I just finished
&lt;a href=&#34;http://conscientiousprogrammer.com/blog/2015/05/31/why-i-switched-from-octopress-2-to-hugo/&#34;&gt;migrating both this blog and my programming blog from Octopress 2 to Hugo&lt;/a&gt;. During
this process, I made sure to preserve my old URLs as well as Disqus,
because nothing is as distressing to me, as a reader, as moved or
broken links when I&amp;rsquo;m looking for old blog posts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, there&amp;rsquo;s always the possibility of changing the &amp;ldquo;real&amp;rdquo; URLs and
just using an alias with a URL redirect for the sake of old URL
schemes. One possibility was to remove dates from my URLs, e.g.,
change something like
&lt;code&gt;http://conscientiousprogrammer.com/blog/2015/05/31/why-i-switched-from-octopress-2-to-hugo/&lt;/code&gt;
to
&lt;code&gt;http://conscientiousprogrammer.com/blog/why-i-switched-from-octopress-2-to-hugo/&lt;/code&gt;. Matt
Gemmell, among many others, has argued for &lt;a href=&#34;http://mattgemmell.com/permalinks/&#34;&gt;permalinks that do not
include the clutter of embedded dates&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I made the decision years ago, when I had the choice, to keep
the embedded dates, and I still stand by my decision today. Here&amp;rsquo;s why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;are-embedded-dates-actually-bad-user-interface-design&#34;&gt;Are embedded dates actually bad user-interface design?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not sure long date-embedded permalinks are really so bad
visually:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nobody goes around having to manually type in these links anyway.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I believe that in the long run, people actually do care about the
date, and having it in the URL makes it that much easier to know the
date.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Redundancy can be a good thing, if it exposes useful information
that in theory one could determine more indirectly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-bigger-philosophical-issues&#34;&gt;The bigger philosophical issues&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the main reason I deliberately choose to expose the date of a
post is that I disagree with Matt Gemmell&amp;rsquo;s statement that one should
prefer to boost one&amp;rsquo;s article&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;standing&amp;rdquo; by giving the impression
that one is making a &amp;ldquo;definitive goddamned opinion&amp;rdquo; on a topic, some
kind of timeless statement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;relevance&#34;&gt;Relevance?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I understand that there are people who would be swayed by this
psychological trick, and I totally confess that sometimes when I do a
Web search and up pops a link to a four-year-old post, I wonder
whether to read something else instead that might be more &amp;ldquo;relevant&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But as a reader who seeks genuinely useful information, no matter how
recent or old, I overcome my initial twinge at encountering an &amp;ldquo;old&amp;rdquo;
article, and check it out for its own merits. And often, I find that
it is just fine. For example, there are some fantastic Haskell blogs
filled with information still useful today. For example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Any of Dan Piponi&amp;rsquo;s articles are great, e.g., a random 2009 article
on
&lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.sigfpe.com/2009/01/haskell-monoids-and-their-uses.html&#34;&gt;monoids and their uses&lt;/a&gt;,
with an ungainly URL of
&lt;code&gt;http://blog.sigfpe.com/2009/01/haskell-monoids-and-their-uses.html&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Any of Gabriel Gonzalez&amp;rsquo;s articles are great, e.g., a 2012 article
on
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.haskellforall.com/2012/06/you-could-have-invented-free-monads.html&#34;&gt;free monads&lt;/a&gt;
with the URL
&lt;code&gt;http://www.haskellforall.com/2012/06/you-could-have-invented-free-monads.html&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, the dating is actually useful because once you see
another article by the same author with a different date, you know
which one came first and can retrace the &lt;em&gt;history&lt;/em&gt; of the author&amp;rsquo;s
thinking just throw the URL. In fact, I track my own history through
the fact that on my file system, my posts are in alphabetical order
according to date.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-reality-and-humanity-of-transience&#34;&gt;The reality and humanity of transience&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, the main fact I want to emphasize when I write is precisely
that I am not giving my definitive opinion about anything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I have no &amp;ldquo;forever&amp;rdquo; opinions about any topic!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I change my mind as I continue to grow and learn, and I want my
writing to reflect that, and in a way such that a reader can easily
track what changed and when. I do not write to give an illusion that I
am writing eternal truths. I do not write in order to be an authority
on a topic, but to share a snapshot of what I understand at a
particular moment in my life. When I change my mind, I do often go
back and add a dated update section linking to a new article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have retained dated permalinks for my migrated blogs, despite some
voices that argue otherwise, because of the extra information they
provide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Do you agree that dated permalinks are worth the ugliness or not? Is
  this your opinion as an author, a reader, a critic, or a search
  engine user?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>