<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Childhood on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/childhood/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Childhood on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/childhood/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>The special bond between children and their fathers, through chess</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/01/13/the-special-bond-between-children-and-their-fathers-through-chess/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Jan 2013 18:25:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/01/13/the-special-bond-between-children-and-their-fathers-through-chess/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I was reading the January 2013 issue of &amp;ldquo;Chess Life&amp;rdquo; magazine (which you can read &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.uschess.org/content/view/12035/365/&#34;&gt;online as PDF if you are a USCF member&lt;/a&gt;) and couldn&amp;rsquo;t help notice that by sheer coincidence, two different articles happened to mention how the article&amp;rsquo;s subject was shaped through their experiences playing chess in their childhood with their fathers. I was very moved because I always get emotional when &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/06/03/why-i-am-grateful-that-my-father-never-let-me-win-a-chess-game-against-him/&#34;&gt;reflecting on how chess gave me a special bond to my father&lt;/a&gt; as well. Similar stories are often true for children and their parents, through any shared activity at all, whether music, hunting, cooking, baseball, sewing, auto repair, stargazing, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are two excerpts from the articles:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;chess-life-article-excerpts&#34;&gt;Chess Life article excerpts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;corbin-seavers-of-the-potter-s-house-scholastic-chess-club&#34;&gt;Corbin Seavers of The Potter&amp;rsquo;s House Scholastic Chess Club&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seavers, who was an anti-apartheid activist, formed The Potter&amp;rsquo;s House Scholastic Chess Club to reach out to children, especially low income and minority youth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
I only cared about chess because my father cared about chess. I only learned the game because my father taught it to me. That is why today I tell fathers chess is one way you can build a common interest and hobby with your child. It brought my father and me closer together, and I can say that it has definitely helped me in building a closer relationship with my daughter.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;alejandro-ramirez-young-grandmaster&#34;&gt;Alejandro Ramirez, young Grandmaster&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GM Ramirez achieved the GM title at age 15. In the article about him, he said quite a bit about the role of his father in his life and chess career. An excerpt:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
My dad was instrumental in my development as a person and as a chess player. Despite the fact that he can&#39;t really see tactics or see more than a few moves ahead, he has a deep understanding of psychology and can sense positions quite well. If I explain a game to him, he can infer things I can&#39;t see, such as the mood of the player, the causes for blunders and many others.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-father-and-chess-today&#34;&gt;My father and chess today&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heck, when I called home to my parents today, I asked my father whether he might start playing in chess tournaments again. It&amp;rsquo;s been a long time (about thirty years) since we used to play in tournaments together. If he were living near me, I&amp;rsquo;d be dragging him to the local tournaments that I have been playing in again. I think it&amp;rsquo;s great that he has been playing regularly for fun again after retiring, but there&amp;rsquo;s nothing like playing in an actual tournament, ha!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next time I see him, I&amp;rsquo;ll be sure to show some of my recent games to him, so we can laugh and talk s-t about the dumb moves I made or my opponent made. He likes seeing games. Every time we see each other, I give him all the issues of &amp;ldquo;Chess Life&amp;rdquo; that I&amp;rsquo;ve accumulated since the last visit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-sister-and-chess&#34;&gt;My sister and chess&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My younger sister also played chess, but retired at the age of six, after her very first tournament, the Michigan Youth Championship, in which she played well and won a trophy. This is a sad story that was very instrumental in the development of her life, but since it is her story, I need to ask her whether I can tell it someday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you think about your childhood, what do you remember as being special and formative between you and your father or mother? Have you ever thanked them for what they gave you? Very often they might not even realize how important something was to you. Don&amp;rsquo;t wait until it is too late to show them your gratitude.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And if you are a parent, what do you think your children really appreciate about their relationship with you? You might be surprised. It might even be something that you think is trivial that they never talk about but is actually the most important thing to them.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why I do not play chess online: chess as a human activity</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/08/30/why-i-do-not-play-chess-online-chess-as-a-human-activity/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Aug 2012 01:19:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/08/30/why-i-do-not-play-chess-online-chess-as-a-human-activity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I found out, while reading the magazine &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chess_Life&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Chess Life&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, to which I am subscribed to as a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/08/21/returning-to-chess/&#34;&gt;member of the United States Chess Federation&lt;/a&gt; (USCF), that there are apparently plans to offer &lt;a href=&#34;http://uschess.org/onlineplay/&#34;&gt;online chess play&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have to confess that I have &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; been interested in playing chess online. I also do not like to play chess against computers, and not just because &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/05/30/life-lessons-i-learned-from-a-lunch-recess-chess-game-at-age-seven/&#34;&gt;my first experience playing chess against a computer was bizarrely negative&lt;/a&gt;. I understand that many people take great pleasure in both of these activities, but I still restrict myself to playing chess only against humans, and face to face. Here&amp;rsquo;s why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;growing-up-with-chess-with-my-father&#34;&gt;Growing up with chess with my father&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve written about some &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/06/03/why-i-am-grateful-that-my-father-never-let-me-win-a-chess-game-against-him/&#34;&gt;life lessons I learned from playing chess with my father&lt;/a&gt;, but not actually told the story of how we ended up joining the USCF and playing in rated tournaments. Here&amp;rsquo;s the story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;taking-chess-more-seriously-in-the-3rd-grade-because-of-china&#34;&gt;Taking chess more seriously in the 3rd grade because of China&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve mentioned &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/06/01/life-lessons-i-learned-from-a-lunch-recess-chess-game-with-a-classmate-at-age-seven/&#34;&gt;getting into chess more seriously in the 2nd grade because of a strange incident at school&lt;/a&gt;. My story picks up from there in the 3rd grade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One day in 1978, my father excitedly clipped out a chess game annotated in the regular chess column in the Sunday New York Times, and showed it to me playing it out. He might still have this clipping saved somewhere in a folder. It was a famous (notorious) game in which a relatively weak chess master from China, &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Liu_Wenzhe&#34;&gt;Liu Wenzhe&lt;/a&gt;, won against a Dutchman, &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jan_Hein_Donner&#34;&gt;Jan Hein Donner&lt;/a&gt;, a strong grandmaster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have to understand that in the 1970s, China was not taken seriously in the West. This was the first time in which a chess player of Chinese descent had scored a major upset against a Westerner. For my father, this was a big deal: he had always played a good game of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Xiangqi&#34;&gt;Chinese chess&lt;/a&gt;, but never invested any time in improving at &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chess&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Western&amp;rdquo; chess&lt;/a&gt;. Just seeing that someone of Chinese descent could play well caused him to become truly enthusiastic about Western chess. (For the curious, here is a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.huffingtonpost.com/lubomir-kavalek/chess-in-clouds-of-smoke_b_1270659.html&#34;&gt;record of the famous Donner-Liu game&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From that day on, every time I walked off to the local store on Sunday morning to buy the New York Times to bring back home, my father and I would immediately clip out the chess column and study it together. We both got more serious about studying chess books we got from the public library.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-04-15&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-04-15)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The author of the New York Times chess column, Robert Byrne, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/04/15/rip-robert-byrne/&#34;&gt;just died&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;fourth-grade-joining-the-local-chess-club&#34;&gt;Fourth grade: joining the local chess club&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After we moved after my third grade, my father found out that there was a chess club that met in the basement of the local community center, and he brought me there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;cigar-smoke-and-chess-with-the-guys&#34;&gt;Cigar smoke and chess with the guys&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was quite an experience entering the chess club. The place was filled with cigar smoke and loud men slamming chess pieces around, wisecracking and swearing. Many of the guys were old, but there were younger guys also, although the youngest one was about twenty years old; I was just ten.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Somehow, in the midst of this chaos, I was welcomed to the club and enjoyed playing. Sometimes my six-year-old sister came along too, but it was clear that she didn&amp;rsquo;t really belong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;tournaments&#34;&gt;Tournaments&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It wasn&amp;rsquo;t long before the guys told us about USCF and ratings and tournaments and encouraged us to join USCF and play in rated tournaments. So my father and I signed up and played in the Michigan Open. We both won trophies in our first tournament, and continued to play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;social&#34;&gt;Social&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, a very shy boy who had relatively little interaction with his schoolmates outside of school, playing chess became the closest thing I had to a &lt;em&gt;social life&lt;/em&gt;. So I have always associated chess with being social, with seeing people smile and frown, with sitting across from someone and noticing his (or very occasionally, her) changes in emotion, concentration, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;playing-chess-against-computers-or-by-means-of-a-computer&#34;&gt;Playing chess against computers or by means of a computer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I never even touched a chess computer again (after my mentioned initial experience in the 2nd grade) until well into high school, when I bought a &lt;a href=&#34;http://tluif.home.xs4all.nl/chescom/EngFidExc.html&#34;&gt;Fidelity Excellence&lt;/a&gt; in the 11th grade. Playing against this computer was frustrating. In the mid-1980s, an affordable chess computer or program was still rather weak. I had no real fun playing with the computer. My enjoyment of chess was tied to the human aspects of the game rather than the purely calculational aspects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t really touch chess again after high school until twenty years later. I was surprised by how much better computers had gotten but again took no pleasure in playing against a program running on my computer. And I saw that online chess had become popular, but had no interest in participating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;back-to-humanity&#34;&gt;Back to humanity&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2004, I became a member again of the USCF and started receiving &amp;ldquo;Chess Life&amp;rdquo; in the mail. I opened up the first issue I received, and noticed that it had an article mentioning my old chess buddy &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ben_Finegold&#34;&gt;Ben Finegold&lt;/a&gt; whom I first met back in the cigar-smoke chess club days in Michigan when I was ten and he was eleven. We&amp;rsquo;d played a good amount of blitz chess together as well as three rated tournament games. Unlike me, he went off to become a chess professional and one of the top chess players in the US, while my chess skill stagnated and I went to college, etc. I wondered whether to take up chess again, to see if I could continue my improvement where I left off as a kid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While visiting my parents for Christmas in 2004, I challenged my father to a chess game for the first time in over twenty years. We played, I did well, and when I returned to Pittsburgh, I searched online and found the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pittsburghcc.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Chess Club&lt;/a&gt; and stopped by for a visit. The guys were really friendly, I started playing blitz chess, like the old days, and in early January 2005, I joined the club and registered for my first tournaments in twenty years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was good to be back. To humanity, really, more so than to chess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It makes me feel old-fashioned, but I have no interest in playing chess online. To me, the game simply has a deeper significance to me than some kind of intellectual puzzle, a significance rooted in its role in my life.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why I am grateful that my father never let me win a chess game against him</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/06/03/why-i-am-grateful-that-my-father-never-let-me-win-a-chess-game-against-him/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Jun 2012 20:59:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/06/03/why-i-am-grateful-that-my-father-never-let-me-win-a-chess-game-against-him/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been writing a lot recent about life lessons learned from playing chess as a kid. Here are some life lessons I learned as a result of the fact that &lt;strong&gt;my father never let me win a chess game against him&lt;/strong&gt;. Based on what I have seen adults doing with children, I somewhat suspect this is unusual. I get the impression that parents like to let their children &amp;ldquo;win&amp;rdquo; at something, presumably for the purpose of giving them a &amp;ldquo;self-esteem&amp;rdquo; boost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it&amp;rsquo;s important to demonstrate compassion and judgment in encouraging children in their pursuits, but based on my own experience, I am not sure it is necessary to let a kid &amp;ldquo;win&amp;rdquo; when the win is nowhere near deserved objectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My father &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; let me win a chess game against him. I played many games with him starting from around age 3, and I did not win a single chess game against him until age eleven, on my own merits alone, when I had overtaken him in my strength. I don&amp;rsquo;t know what his rationale was, but I do know what his behavior taught me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-life-lessons&#34;&gt;The life lessons&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reason and logic have a force of their own, that lies beyond nepotism and other external factors, and must be respected and cultivated.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sometimes one deserves to lose, based on reality, and a child should learn to be a loser and not let losing be correlated with self-esteem or love.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Children at some point can detect lying, and my father showed me respect by not pretending to lose.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Children also appreciate compassion, and I knew my father was not always playing at full strength (he magically got better as I got better), but also knew that by not playing at full strength he made the game challenging yet fun for me, rather than demoralizing and impossible to learn level-appropriate lessons from.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When I actually finally won, it was a big deal, not something that just randomly happened for no reason; I knew that I had reached a true milestone in my life, in which I had through hard work actually surpassed my father at something.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;postscript&#34;&gt;Postscript&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, it turned out that when I won my first game with my father, that was the last game we ever played again for two decades. We never talked about why we stopped playing. After that game, simultaneously neither of us asked again to play the other. There was some kind of unspoken awkwardness. I was heading toward puberty and had begun acting up and resisting authority by that time, and he had been discouraged in his own quest for chess improvement, so he basically quit playing chess after I beat him for the first time. It was an awkward time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We played our first game in decades only when I was into my thirties and I was visiting one Christmas and invited him to play. We played, and I showed no mercy, and I won, but it was an honest game. Like old days. We still play now and then when visiting each other. He knows my level, I know his level, and we know I am basically always going to win, but what can we do other than play some honest games and enjoy the artistry we create together, no matter who wins?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Outside of official competitions, winning is not the only thing. It wasn&amp;rsquo;t when I was a child, and it isn&amp;rsquo;t now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;photo-of-me-playing-chess-with-my-father-in-summer-2010&#34;&gt;Photo of me playing chess with my father in summer 2010&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found a photo of my father and me playing a game of chess at my parents&amp;rsquo; home when Abby and I were visiting in summer 2010. (My actual first chess game with my father in two decades was when I was visiting over Christmas 2004.)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/chess-nelson-franklin-2010.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Nelson versus Franklin in chess in summer 2010&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2013-02-27&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-02-27)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The renowned chess instructor Bruce Pandolfini gave a nuanced, thoughtful answer to a parent&amp;rsquo;s question about whether to let a child win. (&lt;strong&gt;Update of 2013-12-22&lt;/strong&gt;: Unfortunately, the link I originally provided to his article no longer works, as Chess Cafe has begun removing archives of its content).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still think that how my father operated worked out well for me. I learned to value getting better, rather than winning. I trusted that getting better would eventually lead to winning, and it did. Even as an adult who has limited time and ambition, I still value getting better over winning. And &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/02/20/pittsburgh-chess-club-championship-2013-round-6-winning-as-black-like-a-madman/&#34;&gt;I just won the 2013 Pittsburgh Chess Club Championship&lt;/a&gt;. I am in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pscfchess.org/ratings/regtoppa.htm&#34;&gt;top 40 of the active rated chess players in Pennsylvania&lt;/a&gt;. I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be here if my father had not instilled in me a love of excellence and an honest self-evaluation. I don&amp;rsquo;t even feel good when I win. I only feel good when I judge that I &lt;em&gt;deserved&lt;/em&gt; to win.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2013-12-22&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-12-22)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hugh Patterson at The Chess Improver posted a great article &lt;a href=&#34;http://chessimprover.com/some-thoughts-for-parents/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Some Thoughts for Parents&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, although I am not a parent yet, I am teaching chess now, so I&amp;rsquo;m personally facing practical decision-making in how I try to simultaneously install love for chess, sheer fun, and a healthy drive for excellence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2015-12-21&#34;&gt;(Update of 2015-12-21)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two years later, I made a focused push, temporarily putting many
things aside in my life, in the fall of 2015 to &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2016/01/22/on-finally-achieving-the-us-national-master-chess-title-at-age-45-part-1&#34;&gt;achieve my US Chess
National Master&lt;/a&gt; title, and finally made it, a dream come true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it wasn&amp;rsquo;t winning that matters to me in this achievement: it is
that I have actually been playing pretty well and feel I finally
deserved the title. When I was not playing well, I did not feel I
deserved.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why I am grateful that my father never let me win a chess game against him</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/06/03/why-i-am-grateful-that-my-father-never-let-me-win-a-chess-game-against-him/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Jun 2012 20:59:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/06/03/why-i-am-grateful-that-my-father-never-let-me-win-a-chess-game-against-him/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been writing a lot recent about life lessons learned from playing chess as a kid. Here are some life lessons I learned as a result of the fact that &lt;strong&gt;my father never let me win a chess game against him&lt;/strong&gt;. Based on what I have seen adults doing with children, I somewhat suspect this is unusual. I get the impression that parents like to let their children &amp;ldquo;win&amp;rdquo; at something, presumably for the purpose of giving them a &amp;ldquo;self-esteem&amp;rdquo; boost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it&amp;rsquo;s important to demonstrate compassion and judgment in encouraging children in their pursuits, but based on my own experience, I am not sure it is necessary to let a kid &amp;ldquo;win&amp;rdquo; when the win is nowhere near deserved objectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My father &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; let me win a chess game against him. I played many games with him starting from around age 3, and I did not win a single chess game against him until age eleven, on my own merits alone, when I had overtaken him in my strength. I don&amp;rsquo;t know what his rationale was, but I do know what his behavior taught me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-life-lessons&#34;&gt;The life lessons&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reason and logic have a force of their own, that lies beyond nepotism and other external factors, and must be respected and cultivated.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sometimes one deserves to lose, based on reality, and a child should learn to be a loser and not let losing be correlated with self-esteem or love.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Children at some point can detect lying, and my father showed me respect by not pretending to lose.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Children also appreciate compassion, and I knew my father was not always playing at full strength (he magically got better as I got better), but also knew that by not playing at full strength he made the game challenging yet fun for me, rather than demoralizing and impossible to learn level-appropriate lessons from.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When I actually finally won, it was a big deal, not something that just randomly happened for no reason; I knew that I had reached a true milestone in my life, in which I had through hard work actually surpassed my father at something.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;postscript&#34;&gt;Postscript&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, it turned out that when I won my first game with my father, that was the last game we ever played again for two decades. We never talked about why we stopped playing. After that game, simultaneously neither of us asked again to play the other. There was some kind of unspoken awkwardness. I was heading toward puberty and had begun acting up and resisting authority by that time, and he had been discouraged in his own quest for chess improvement, so he basically quit playing chess after I beat him for the first time. It was an awkward time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We played our first game in decades only when I was into my thirties and I was visiting one Christmas and invited him to play. We played, and I showed no mercy, and I won, but it was an honest game. Like old days. We still play now and then when visiting each other. He knows my level, I know his level, and we know I am basically always going to win, but what can we do other than play some honest games and enjoy the artistry we create together, no matter who wins?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Outside of official competitions, winning is not the only thing. It wasn&amp;rsquo;t when I was a child, and it isn&amp;rsquo;t now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;photo-of-me-playing-chess-with-my-father-in-summer-2010&#34;&gt;Photo of me playing chess with my father in summer 2010&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found a photo of my father and me playing a game of chess at my parents&amp;rsquo; home when Abby and I were visiting in summer 2010. (My actual first chess game with my father in two decades was when I was visiting over Christmas 2004.)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/chess-nelson-franklin-2010.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Nelson versus Franklin in chess in summer 2010&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2013-02-27&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-02-27)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The renowned chess instructor Bruce Pandolfini gave a nuanced, thoughtful answer to a parent&amp;rsquo;s question about whether to let a child win. (&lt;strong&gt;Update of 2013-12-22&lt;/strong&gt;: Unfortunately, the link I originally provided to his article no longer works, as Chess Cafe has begun removing archives of its content).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still think that how my father operated worked out well for me. I learned to value getting better, rather than winning. I trusted that getting better would eventually lead to winning, and it did. Even as an adult who has limited time and ambition, I still value getting better over winning. And &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/02/20/pittsburgh-chess-club-championship-2013-round-6-winning-as-black-like-a-madman/&#34;&gt;I just won the 2013 Pittsburgh Chess Club Championship&lt;/a&gt;. I am in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pscfchess.org/ratings/regtoppa.htm&#34;&gt;top 40 of the active rated chess players in Pennsylvania&lt;/a&gt;. I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be here if my father had not instilled in me a love of excellence and an honest self-evaluation. I don&amp;rsquo;t even feel good when I win. I only feel good when I judge that I &lt;em&gt;deserved&lt;/em&gt; to win.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2013-12-22&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-12-22)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hugh Patterson at The Chess Improver posted a great article &lt;a href=&#34;http://chessimprover.com/some-thoughts-for-parents/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Some Thoughts for Parents&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, although I am not a parent yet, I am teaching chess now, so I&amp;rsquo;m personally facing practical decision-making in how I try to simultaneously install love for chess, sheer fun, and a healthy drive for excellence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2015-12-21&#34;&gt;(Update of 2015-12-21)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two years later, I made a focused push, temporarily putting many
things aside in my life, in the fall of 2015 to &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2016/01/22/on-finally-achieving-the-us-national-master-chess-title-at-age-45-part-1&#34;&gt;achieve my US Chess
National Master&lt;/a&gt; title, and finally made it, a dream come true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it wasn&amp;rsquo;t winning that matters to me in this achievement: it is
that I have actually been playing pretty well and feel I finally
deserved the title. When I was not playing well, I did not feel I
deserved.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Life lessons I learned from a lunch recess chess game at age seven: the prequel with a classmate</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/06/01/life-lessons-i-learned-from-a-lunch-recess-chess-game-with-a-classmate-at-age-seven/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jun 2012 13:43:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/06/01/life-lessons-i-learned-from-a-lunch-recess-chess-game-with-a-classmate-at-age-seven/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Two days ago, I wrote about &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/05/30/life-lessons-i-learned-from-a-lunch-recess-chess-game-at-age-seven/&#34;&gt;life lessons I learned from playing a chess game against a computer in the 2nd grade during lunch recess&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, I&amp;rsquo;m writing about what I learned from the only other chess game I played on site in elementary school. I played this game much earlier than the computer game; I played it with a classmate who had seen me looking at chess books in the classroom library and challenged me to a game. Let&amp;rsquo;s call him X. Here are our school photos:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/franklin-second-grade.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin Chen 2nd grade school photo&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/second-grade-chess-opponent.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Classmate in 2nd grade I played one chess game with&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-game-with-x&#34;&gt;My game with X&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was nervous when we sat down to play, because I had up till this point never played chess with anyone but my father.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nobody was watching us. It was just the two of us sitting on the floor in a corner where books and games were stored.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The game lasted no more than two minutes; it lasted four moves before ending!!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;X was playing very quickly, spending no more than a split second per move. Furthermore, he played completely unlike my father and unlike any of the sample instructive games I had seen in chess books. His first move, h4, totally confused and unnerved me. I tried to play according to vague principles I recalled about how one should play, moving my center Pawns, even as he did a strange Rook lift maneuver I had never seen in my entire life. On his third move, he attacked my e Pawn with this rogue Rook and I protected it. On his fourth move, he attacked my Pawn with his d Pawn. We had reached this position:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/second-grade-chess-game.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;My only chess game with another kid in elementary school&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I got excited because it looked like he had made a mistake. His Pawn on d4 is protected only once, by his Queen, while I was attacking it with both my Knight and my Pawn at e5. Therefore, his Pawn was &amp;ldquo;free&amp;rdquo; for me to take!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, I momentarily overlooked that my e Pawn was pinned and took his d Pawn with my e Pawn. (Note: taking the Pawn with the Knight would have lost it; X was definitely no dummy and may even have been a far better chess player than me at the time.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-argument&#34;&gt;The argument&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;X, who had something of a stern, morose temperament, suddenly broke out into a big smile of victory, grabbed his Rook and took my King, jumped up from the ground, and said he won the game!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I protested that I had overlooked that I had made an illegal move, and asked him to give my King back so that I could put all the pieces back to where they were before I made the illegal move, saying that we can&amp;rsquo;t make illegal moves, and Kings cannot be captured in chess, so not only could I not take the Pawn, but he also could not take my King. (I was correct, of course; illegal moves cannot be allowed to stand, and the King can never be taken during a chess turn.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;X refused to listen to me and just gloated. As I had no desire to create a scene and ask for a teacher to adjudicate our dispute, I just walked away. I never played a chess game with him again, and I never told anyone in my life about this incident, until today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;life-lessons-i-learned&#34;&gt;Life lessons I learned&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the things I learned from this incident:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;X may have gotten away with claiming to have won against me, but lost a potential playmate.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some people are uninformed but very sure they are right, and there is no use arguing with them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Even when playing a game by the rules, the ultimate outcome in the real world may depend on whether others are playing by the rules.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I needed more experience in facing unexpected, strange openings and strategies, in order to avoid getting mentally flustered and inattentive.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I needed more experience in staying calm against someone who behaved aggressively and intimidated me.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I needed to look at the larger context when it seemed that something was free for the taking.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I needed to pay more attention to threats directed toward my King from afar.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I needed to be &amp;ldquo;defensive&amp;rdquo; against illegal game endings by not making illegal moves myself.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-i-did-with-what-i-learned&#34;&gt;What I did with what I learned&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;X did me a little favor by teaching me all these lessons. I went home and actually studied his Rook strategy and came up with ways to deal with it if anyone ever played it against me again. I also never played an illegal move again in my life. (Note: up till this point, I was still having some problems &amp;ldquo;seeing&amp;rdquo; that pieces or Pawns of mine were pinned, and would sometimes play illegal moves against my father too.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also decided it was time to go beyond kids&amp;rsquo; chess books and learn more about strategy, going beyond just the basic rules and counting piece points. Luckily for me, the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.gti.net/mocolib1/&#34;&gt;Morris County Library&lt;/a&gt; had a great chess collection, and I got my father to drive us there regularly, where we took out lots of chess books (as well as books on all the other subjects that interested me). My father never asked me why I was getting so excited about chess, but was happy to get into it more himself. We went over serious game collections and opening books, for the first time in our lives, and in months I felt I was much more informed and stronger as a chess player. That set the stage for my proud accomplishment of obtaining a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/05/30/life-lessons-i-learned-from-a-lunch-recess-chess-game-at-age-seven/&#34;&gt;winning position against a chess computer later in the 2nd grade&lt;/a&gt;, which also taught me more life lessons already discussed.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Remembering my Uncle Steve</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/03/16/remembering-my-uncle-steve/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Mar 2012 18:19:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/03/16/remembering-my-uncle-steve/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today I got a call from my mother informing me that my Uncle Steve, husband of my mother&amp;rsquo;s sister Aunt Soo-kin, died yesterday. He had been sick for quite some time, and last year, in the hospital for something else, they found cancer in addition, so it was a very tough battle for him, and he was always a fighter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was very grateful for the opportunity in July 2010 to visit Aunt and Uncle in East Lansing when he was still very much active. I had not seen either of them in possibly twenty years; my parents and Abby and I went up to their home, and they got to meet Abby for the very first time (he was not well when we married in 2009).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below is the only photo I currently have of him (my parents have the family photo album that must have a lot more photos from the past forty years since we&amp;rsquo;ve all been in the United States). (From left to right: Abby, my mother, Aunt Soo-kin, my father, and Uncle Steve.)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/aunt-uncle/abby-mother-aunt-father-uncle.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby, Franklin&amp;#39;s mother, Aunt Soo-kin, Franklin&amp;#39;s father, Uncle Steve&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(Update: my brother-in-law André just sent me some more photos, from the wedding of my sister Linda and him in 2010 that he did manage to attend.)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/aunt-uncle/aunt-uncle.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Aunt and Uncle at Linda and André&amp;#39;s wedding&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What do I remember most about Uncle Steve, and how did he impact my life?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-visit-in-july-2010&#34;&gt;The visit in July 2010&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Uncle Steve was full of energy and insisted on taking us around Lansing, giving all of us a tour of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michigan_State_Capitol&#34;&gt;Michigan State Capitol&lt;/a&gt; as well as the Michigan State University campus, especially the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cpa.msu.edu/beal/&#34;&gt;botanical garden&lt;/a&gt;. He also took us to his favorite Chinese buffet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, typical of him, he had originally planned to get us on a cruise on the river. We had gone down to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lansingcitymarket.com/&#34;&gt;Lansing City Market&lt;/a&gt;, where he bought tickets, but then it turned out that the timing was bad and nothing was available that day, so we had to cancel on the plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;uncle-steve-s-traits&#34;&gt;Uncle Steve&amp;rsquo;s traits&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main thing I will always remember about Uncle Steve is how different he was from other relatives. He was very energetic and aggressive, outspoken, adventurous compared to the rest of us. The way he talked, drove, and ate was quite different from how my father behaved, so in my childhood, the contrast between my two main adult male role models was striking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I saw him (and aunt and their two children, my cousins) more often when I was in elementary school, middle school, high school in Michigan. Then when I went off to college, I saw them much less often.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-number-one-memory-how-to-take-risks-and-win&#34;&gt;My number one memory: how to take risks and win&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a child, sometimes I had the opportunity to play ping pong. I didn&amp;rsquo;t do it often, because we didn&amp;rsquo;t have the space, but every time we went up to East Lansing to visit Uncle and Aunt and my cousins, I looked forward to using their ping pong table. I got to play with my father, and then Uncle would step in and totally destroy both of us with his ultra-aggressive style. He was pretty serious about anything competitive (he played tennis also), and he had high-quality ping pong bats such that he could create a lot of spin, for example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main thing is that Uncle Steve moved fast and went for hard, fast killer shots whenever possible (while using the backhand spin defensively as appropriate). He didn&amp;rsquo;t always make it, but he went for it. I really admired his style of play. He used a &lt;a href=&#34;http://tabletennis.about.com/od/griptypes/a/jkpenholdgrip.htm&#34;&gt;Japanese-style penhold grip&lt;/a&gt; to maximize his forehand attacking style.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used the Chinese-style penhold grip (learned from my father) for a long time whenever I played ping pong. The Japanese-style grip seemed too extreme for me. In any case, from Uncle Steve I learned to &lt;em&gt;stay on the attack&lt;/em&gt; in ping pong. Even though for much of my life I used to be shy and anxious, there were a couple of areas in my life in which I adopted a relentlessly aggressive persona. I have Uncle Steve to thank for showing me how it&amp;rsquo;s done. To this day, if I play ping pong, I will play in an attacking style, not a defensive style. I will err on the side of hitting the ball out of control and out of play losing points rather than playing &amp;ldquo;safe&amp;rdquo; and missing an opportunity to hit a winner. I don&amp;rsquo;t really know why, but I somehow absorbed this huge &lt;em&gt;life lesson&lt;/em&gt; from Uncle Steve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point, I did start switching around between the penhold grip and the shake-hand grip, because of comfort. I don&amp;rsquo;t play ping pong much these days; I think the last time was a year ago when I was back at my parents&amp;rsquo; home, where they have had a ping pong table for twenty years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a photo of my father and me playing ping pong twenty years ago:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/franklin-father-ping-pong-air.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin playing ping pong with father at home around 1993?&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;in-closing&#34;&gt;In closing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Uncle Steve leaves behind his wife, two children, and their children.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, Uncle Steve never got to see my new nephew Jack, born last month. But the cycle of life continues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will miss Uncle Steve&amp;rsquo;s energy and fighting spirit.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/andre-linda-jack-mother-father.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;André, Linda, Jack, mother, father&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(Photo: brother-in-law André, sister Linda, nephew Jack, mother, father.)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How school made me hate computer science and programming</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/01/16/how-school-made-me-hate-computer-science-and-programming/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Jan 2012 19:57:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/01/16/how-school-made-me-hate-computer-science-and-programming/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Some months ago, when the legendary computer scientist &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_McCarthy_(computer_scientist)&#34;&gt;John McCarthy&lt;/a&gt; died, I wrote a blog post in which I briefly reminisced about the way &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/25/rip-john-mccarthy-but-lisp-will-never-die/&#34;&gt;I hated computer programming before I came to love it&lt;/a&gt;. Today I am filling in some more details about how school (elementary school through college) made me fear, misunderstand, and hate computer science and programming. I am inspired to do this because&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Just a few weeks ago, I came across an old article from 1992 by someone who had a similar experience, and I wanted to complete my story. Although my story also goes back more than two decades, I feel that the same fundamental stumbling blocks exist to &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/09/why-everyone-should-learn-computer-science/&#34;&gt;the universal computational competence that I now advocate&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The topic of learning &amp;ldquo;coding&amp;rdquo; has exploded into the popular media, with hundreds of thousands of people having signed up for &lt;a href=&#34;http://codeyear.com/&#34;&gt;Code Year&lt;/a&gt; and even New York Mayor Bloomberg stating that &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.businessinsider.com/mike-bloomberg-pledges-to-learn-to-code-on-codecademy-this-year-2012-1&#34;&gt;he has signed up&lt;/a&gt; for the free &lt;a href=&#34;http://codecademy.com/&#34;&gt;Codecademy&lt;/a&gt; online tutorial courses.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My goals in telling my story:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I want to raise awareness among those who might this year be jumping into &amp;ldquo;coding&amp;rdquo; that they might encounter the same kinds of stumbling blocks that discouraged me at first, so that they don&amp;rsquo;t prematurely jump to such conclusions as &amp;ldquo;programming is boring and confusing&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;programming requires special talent I don&amp;rsquo;t have&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I want for educators to take note of the barriers facing students who may not be &amp;ldquo;naturals&amp;rdquo; to understanding computation or writing computer programs in the context of currently common programming environments.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a forthcoming article, I will engage in a severe critique of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://codecademy.com/&#34;&gt;Codeacademy&lt;/a&gt; lessons I have so far examined and gone through, while helping my wife learn programming from scratch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;6th-grade-and-basic-in-the-early-1980s&#34;&gt;6th grade and BASIC in the early 1980s&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was in middle school in the 6th grade, my math teacher was crazy about computers. He was convinced that his best math students, including me, should learn computer programming. I was basically coerced into staying after school for sessions in which he taught us to program in BASIC for the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/TRS-80&#34;&gt;TRS-80 microcomputer&lt;/a&gt;. The BASIC language was very primitive. We used line numbers and &lt;code&gt;GOTO&lt;/code&gt;. Some boys got totally into programming, and tried writing video games. I was not one of them. I was not a natural at programming. I will admit it: I never really understood &lt;code&gt;GOSUB&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;PEEK&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;POKE&lt;/code&gt; at the time. In fact, one beautiful spring day, since it was nice outside, I decided to simply walk home from school instead of staying around for his class. After missing a couple of sessions, I was shocked that he contacted my parents and basically made me continue on. I finished out the year, then never wrote a BASIC program again (until college).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did like playing computer games, however. I just had no interest in making them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;7th-grade-and-pac-man&#34;&gt;7th grade and Pac-Man&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the 7th grade, I was crazy about video games and my sister and I managed to save enough allowance money to buy an &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Atari_2600&#34;&gt;Atari 2600&lt;/a&gt; video game console. I had encountered an IBM PC by then, but had no interest in it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;9th-grade-and-my-first-programming-class&#34;&gt;9th grade and my first programming class&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I started high school in the 9th grade, there was a requirement that all students take a semester of &amp;ldquo;computer literacy&amp;rdquo;. After several meetings of that class, I wanted out. We were shown slides of tape drives, told about bits and bytes, and I had no interest whatsoever in any of that. I heard that there was a way out of the requirement, which was to take an actual computer programming class. Since my father was working as a mainframe programmer (his degree in information sciences being from the 1970s), he suggested I take &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/COBOL&#34;&gt;COBOL&lt;/a&gt;, which were offered by my high school (in addition to &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fortran&#34;&gt;Fortran&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IBM_RPG&#34;&gt;RPG&lt;/a&gt; and probably others I don&amp;rsquo;t remember).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I switched to the COBOL class. Here we learned about pseudocode, used &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.retroist.com/2009/01/11/ibm-flowcharting-template/&#34;&gt;flowchart templates&lt;/a&gt; to draw symbols on paper, wrote our programs out in pencil, and used the big keypunch machine to punch out our programs. Every day we had the opportunity to submit a punch card deck to the teacher (with the appropriate job control and compiler cards) to drop off for overnight processing at some mainframe somewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hated the class. The whole rigid process we were supposed to go through, the verbosity of the COBOL language, and the nature of the programs we wrote, made computing seem very boring. I started not doing any homework, and after several weeks, I was failing the class, and the teacher called my parents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I dutifully caught up on all the missing programming projects, got my A in the class, and then never touched COBOL again, and forgot any COBOL I &lt;em&gt;pretended&lt;/em&gt; to learn while basically copying and pasting from example programs in the textbook and modifying stuff until it &amp;ldquo;worked&amp;rdquo;. I have a confession to make: despite my A in the class, I never really understood COBOL or programming. I was just going through the motions. It was truly &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cargo_cult_programming&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;cargo-cult programming&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;This is a warning to all educators to actually verify whether someone has learned something, as opposed to cleverly faked it!&lt;/strong&gt; (I will come to this subject again.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;10th-grade-and-pascal&#34;&gt;10th grade and Pascal&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the 10th grade (in a new high school), my math teacher made it mandatory to write some rudimentary programs in Pascal to illustrate the trigonometry and other stuff we were learning. We used the MacPascal interpreter on the Macintosh for this purpose: there was a computer lab where we did our work and printed out our programs and results. I have almost no memory of any of this except that I was intrigued by the automatic formatting and the proportional fonts in MacPascal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I should note that at this time in my life, I had no interest in computers. We still did not have one at home, and I had long since outgrown the Atari video game console.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;11th-grade-and-advanced-placement-computer-science&#34;&gt;11th grade and Advanced Placement computer science&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the 11th grade, I had the opportunity to take an Advanced Placement course in computer science, taught using the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pascal_(programming_language)&#34;&gt;Pascal&lt;/a&gt; programming language. (I mentioned this in &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/25/rip-john-mccarthy-but-lisp-will-never-die/&#34;&gt;my previous article&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I signed up for the class. You might wonder why, given that I had no interest in computers or programming (in Pascal or any other language). I had a perverse incentive. Advanced Placement courses were advertised as a way to get out of equivalent courses in college. I figured that if I ended up in college with a computing course requirement, I wanted to place out of it! So I signed up for Advanced Placement computer science because I &lt;em&gt;hated&lt;/em&gt; computers and wanted to get the pain over with earlier rather than later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The course was taught by a math teacher who made us use as a textbook a book that I found totally over my head, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Solve-Computer-Prentice-Hall-International-Science/dp/0134340019&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;How to Solve It by Computer&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;m betting that if I had a copy of this book now to look at, I might actually enjoy it, but at the time, it was forbidding. It was all about &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Loop_invariant&#34;&gt;loop invariants&lt;/a&gt;, proving your algorithms to be correct, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One side effect of the course was that pretty soon it became clear that it was the most time-consuming course. I simply did not have enough time in the computer lab to get my programs running correctly. I had my father buy me an Apple IIe computer so that I could do my coding and debugging at home into the wee hours of the night as necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found it annoyingly difficult to get out of the BASIC and COBOL mindset into the &amp;ldquo;structured programming&amp;rdquo; enforced by Pascal. As a result, I am sensitive to the idea that &amp;ldquo;learning&amp;rdquo; inferior programming languages can genuinely get in the way of further progress as a programmer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did not enjoy the class at all, but did enjoy the side effect of having a computer at home, which I used for playing some games as well as for word processing, so that I no longer needed to use a typewriter and scissors to work on drafts of papers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, I will admit that for much of the class, I was proceeding with no real understanding of what I was doing. I was copying and pasting and cargo-culting my way through the class, and through my receiving a 5 on the Advanced Placement exam. After this class, I thought I was done with programming for the rest of my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem was that we never wrote any programs to do anything I found interesting, and was never exposed to the general possibilities of what we could do through programming. Writing a recursive program to generate fractals was not very interesting to me. My biggest project in the class was writing a program to maintain a library of books and be able to sort and search it and write it out to floppy disk and read it back in. That was also not very interesting to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;motivations&#34;&gt;Motivations&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My hobbies at the time included playing chess, learning languages (I was enthusiastic about French and had taught myself Latin), reading lots of books. If the world had been different then, and someone had told me what I could do by knowing how to program, I could have been very interested. For example, suppose that the Web existed then. Suppose someone told me that by knowing how to program, I could write code to create my own flashcard system for learning languages. Then there would be a question of whether an application already exists for purchase that can do that. (It turns out that I have never been satisfied with any flashcard program I have used.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think that to attract interest in computer programming, it is vital to give people reasons that they can relate to. And it is not helpful to &lt;em&gt;discourage&lt;/em&gt; potential programmers by telling them that they should be doing something else, like, just focusing on being a doctor or salesman, giving the argument that the &amp;ldquo;good&amp;rdquo; programmers are already doing their job creating applications ready to use, and that therefore &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Comparative_advantage&#34;&gt;comparative advantage&lt;/a&gt; says that only professional programmers should learn how to program. This is like telling someone centuries ago that it is no use learning to read or write because others can already do it and probably do it much better. I think the proliferation of information means that more and more people need to be able to analyze it. Whether you call it &amp;ldquo;scripting&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;macros&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;customization&amp;rdquo;, the truth is that at some point, real programming is necessary in order to truly understand and control one&amp;rsquo;s data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;after-11th-grade&#34;&gt;After 11th grade&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rest of the story, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/25/rip-john-mccarthy-but-lisp-will-never-die/&#34;&gt;I already told earlier&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My K-12 schooling did nothing to encourage me to actually understand and apply computer science and programming. I wonder to what extent the kind of experience I had still applies today in K-12.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;postscript&#34;&gt;Postscript&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Upcoming topics I will write about:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My eye-opening experience as a teaching assistant for an undergraduate computer science course.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My current monitoring of Codecademy&amp;rsquo;s offerings and my ongoing efforts to teach my wife computer programming.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Finding and using my childhood flute books</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/01/08/finding-and-using-my-childhood-flute-books/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Jan 2012 11:40:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/01/08/finding-and-using-my-childhood-flute-books/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/belwin-home-practice-record.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;My 5th grade flute book practice record&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I was in my basement looking for stuff and happened to find three of my childhood &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/flute/&#34;&gt;flute&lt;/a&gt; books:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Belwin-Band-Builder-Part-Flute/dp/B000M0CLSW&#34;&gt;Belwin Band Builder part 1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Rubank-Intermediate-Method-Piccolo-Educational/dp/1423444221&#34;&gt;Rubank Intermediate Method: Flute or Piccolo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Marcel-Franks-Classical-Tunes-Flute/dp/B002JVQCWI&#34;&gt;Marcel Frank&amp;rsquo;s 95 Classical Tunes For The Flute&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are my memories of my usage of these books and how I might use them now, three decades later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;belwin-band-builder&#34;&gt;Belwin Band Builder&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Belwin Band Builder is a completely trivial and boring beginning band method that I used when learning flute in the 5th grade under Mr. Peters. The amusing thing is the &amp;ldquo;home practice record&amp;rdquo; at the back of the book, which still has my father&amp;rsquo;s signatures, as you can see from the photo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see, my memory in my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/09/taking-up-flute-again-after-decades/&#34;&gt;blog post about starting flute up again&lt;/a&gt; of being delinquent with practice has been completely validated! There are a lot of &amp;ldquo;0 minutes&amp;rdquo; written down, on days when I didn&amp;rsquo;t even touch the flute and couldn&amp;rsquo;t even get myself to write down an exaggerated number of minutes of practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notice that only the first six weeks were graded by Mr. Peters, and in the first week, I had gotten a B- that I had tried to erase. At some point, Mr. Peters&amp;rsquo; health problems got bad, I think, and he stopped paying attention to our practice record. My father did keep on signing, for sixteen weeks, and I put down three final weeks that I didn&amp;rsquo;t even have him sign, because Mr. Peters wasn&amp;rsquo;t checking anything any more anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;rubank-intermediate-method&#34;&gt;Rubank Intermediate Method&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I recall correctly, Mr. Peters started teaching 6th grade band when he suddenly got so ill he had to retire, and our subsitute Mr. McLaughlin became permanent band director (I had him for the rest of 6th grade band and in intermediate band after that).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before Mr. Peters left, he gave me a list of two flute method books he recommended, and I dutifully gave the list to my father, who ordered them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that I never used them. I may have glanced at them, and fooled around a few minutes with them, but I never used them!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Rubank Intermediate Method was one of these books. Despite the physical age of my copy, the only evidence that I ever touched it is my name crudely written in marker on the front cover. I just started using the method and had to bend back on stapled binding so that the book would open flat for my music stand! The method looks useful to me now, with lots of technical exercises for all keys, interspersed with some musical excerpts such as gavottes and minuets, but back when I was eleven years old and not a classical music fan, this book must have seemed to me&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;foreign&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;boring&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;hard&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;pointless&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At that age, I was mostly interested in playing&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;marches&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;syncopated rock&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;big band swing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;marcel-frank-s-95-classical-tunes-for-the-flute&#34;&gt;Marcel Frank&amp;rsquo;s 95 Classical Tunes For The Flute&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is all classical stuff. Enough said: my eleven-year-old self did not find much of this music interesting. There are exceptions, however! Flipping through this book, I recognize some excerpts as music I definitely tried playing at the time. Some examples:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A Song of India&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sleeping Beauty&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Roses from the South&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Radetzky March&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My explanation is quite simple:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I loved &lt;em&gt;marches&lt;/em&gt; of any kind (hence my later joining marching band).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I loved fast &lt;em&gt;waltzes&lt;/em&gt;, through exposure to them from TV cartoons such as &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tom_and_Jerry&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Tom and Jerry&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There were pieces I &lt;em&gt;recognized&lt;/em&gt; as having heard (such as &amp;ldquo;A Song of India&amp;rdquo;) because of random &amp;ldquo;Greatest Classical Masterpieces&amp;rdquo; types of LP records (and there were many varieties of this kind of material) that my mother sometimes bought at garage sales and flea markets and brought home. Being familiar with a tune (and liking it) definitely was a motivation to at least try playing it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, I do not particularly like the selections or length (each just a single page) in this compilation. So I don&amp;rsquo;t expect to use this book much. I have other flute music already I have been enjoying practicing, especially the music that comes with a good accompaniment CD (this makes such a big difference).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-reflections&#34;&gt;My reflections&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s funny to me that even now, thirty years later, my mind still operates in a similar way. I still like marches. I still like fast waltzes (and even originally took up &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/ballroom-dance/&#34;&gt;ballroom dance&lt;/a&gt; specifically because I wanted to eventually dance the Viennese waltz. I still am more motivated to play something new if I&amp;rsquo;ve heard it before and like it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I&amp;rsquo;m also more mature now, more open. I&amp;rsquo;ve listened to a whole lot more and whole lot more variety of music since I was a child. And I&amp;rsquo;m willing to try listening to or playing any kind of music now. In fact, just last year, most of the music I&amp;rsquo;ve played on any instrument has been completely new to me, as a listener or performer. And that&amp;rsquo;s great. It&amp;rsquo;s part of the whole fun of living, experiencing more and different music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was amusing rediscovering my old flute books. The intermediate method looks like a good one to use for practice. It&amp;rsquo;s never too late to continue where I left off as a child, with a different mindset and more mature self-discipline!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Taking up flute again after decades?!</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/11/09/taking-up-flute-again-after-decades/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Nov 2011 20:08:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/11/09/taking-up-flute-again-after-decades/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/franklins-flute.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin&amp;#39;s flute&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Tonight, on a whim, I decided to try out my flute yet again.  Every couple of months for several years now I have pulled it out to see if I might want to start playing it again.  Each time, I encountered serious problems with producing a decent sound at all, and thought that maybe I wasn&amp;rsquo;t meant to play the flute, because the embouchure is such a problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, for the first time in several years, I found that maybe I can get back into playing flute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This possibility pleases me, because the story of me and flutes goes back decades, and is actually rather sad but perhaps instructive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;elementary-school&#34;&gt;Elementary school&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story starts in the last year of elementary school, 5th grade, when a bunch of us students were given the opportunity to choose and start playing a musical instrument. I can still remember Mr. Peters, the music teacher, asking each of us individually what we wanted to play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this time in my life (ten years old), I had received minimal musical instruction so far. I did not grow up in a sufficiently privileged family to receive formal musical lessons, and in fact had never even touched or seen in real life any other musical instrument than the upright piano we just got at home because my mother and younger sister wanted one. I did not listen to any music, had never gone to any kind of musical concert or event before, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d asked my mother earlier what I should ask Mr. Peters to play, so I was ready to answer him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I timidly asked, &amp;ldquo;Piano?&amp;rdquo; Mr. Peters smiled and said, no, that&amp;rsquo;s not something available in the music program. I then asked, &amp;ldquo;Violin?&amp;rdquo; Again, no. I was getting really embarrassed now, because I didn&amp;rsquo;t even know what a violin was: I&amp;rsquo;d never heard one or seen one, but it was a word planted in my head by my mother! (Only many years later did I find out that all Asian kids are supposed to play piano or violin.) Finally, I said, &amp;ldquo;Flute?&amp;rdquo; Yes, flute was an option.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So that&amp;rsquo;s how I started out on flute. I had never encountered a flute before. It was just a word to me. To this day I don&amp;rsquo;t know why my mother had this instrument in her mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;renting-an-instrument&#34;&gt;Renting an instrument&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of my classmates and I ended up renting instruments through the school. My father was not at all interested in my playing music and only because my mother thought I should learn a musical instrument did he cough up the cash to rent a flute for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t particularly like the flute, but I did enjoy getting started playing it. Mostly, I enjoyed the new social group I had: those of use who started on an instrument would gather and learn to play together. That was new to me, and fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;practice&#34;&gt;Practice&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I did not like practicing. I &lt;em&gt;hated&lt;/em&gt; it. Worse, we were given time sheets to fill out indicating how much time we spent practicing at home every day, and have that signed by our parents as witnesses. Well, I wasn&amp;rsquo;t practicing enough, and got scolded by Mr. Peters. I started lying or padding my estimate of how much time I practiced (I still remember writing in &amp;ldquo;30&amp;rdquo; for minutes practiced inside little boxes). What did my father know anyway about what happened when I supposed got started practicing at home and then ended half an hour later?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;middle-school&#34;&gt;Middle school&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When middle school began, I took 6th grade band. Band ended up being the basis of my social life as it was. I still wasn&amp;rsquo;t really practicing flute. Furthermore, I had come to &lt;em&gt;hate&lt;/em&gt; flute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;bad-instrument&#34;&gt;Bad instrument&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing that happened was that flute rental was over, and I had my father buy me a flute. Of course, he bought a totally beat up piece of crap from some garage sale or something somewhere. It was a horrible instrument. The pads got sticky, the mouthpiece was bent, and it was just no fun to play, it was hard to make a good sound out of it, and I knew it was a lot worse than my elementary school rental.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used that flute for another two years before I stopped playing it, forever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;girly-instrument&#34;&gt;Girly instrument&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another thing that happened was that most of the other kids playing flute was girls. Oops, I had ended up with a girly instrument! This was not a trivial matter, given that puberty was starting to kick in, along with a lot of social awareness and anxiety that I never had in elementary school.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-instrument-i-really-wanted-to-play&#34;&gt;The instrument I really wanted to play&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, finally being exposed to a whole bunch of different instruments, hearing them, especially hearing the really good kids, I realized that I really wanted to play the cornet (from which there was a clear path to trumpet).  I liked that the cornet/trumpet was prominent, loud, got the main melodies, everyone could hear it (not always the case with the flute parts!), and of course, it was &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; girly (although, interestingly, a number of girls did play it and were really good at it, and I had a crush on all of them).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, I knew there was no chance my parents would allow me to switch to trumpet. So all I did was dream about playing trumpet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I played flute in the 6th grade, and then in the 7th grade.  I played without &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; enjoyment of the flute during those two years. I did enjoy the social bonding from band, but that was basically it. Also, playing in band allowed one to place out of physical education (don&amp;rsquo;t ask me why), and I dreaded gym class, so I stuck to music to get out of gym (a big mistake, in retrospect).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;high-school&#34;&gt;High school&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;9th-grade&#34;&gt;9th grade&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I skipped the 8th grade of middle school (for reasons beyond the scope of this blog post), and started the 9th grade of high school. Again, I took band in order to avoid gym. It was a miserable experience. Not only did I have to wake up super early to have my mother drive me to marching band practice at 5 AM before school classes started at 7 AM, but also, as a young 9th grader I felt particularly out of place among students who were as much as four years older than me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall the 9th grade was a miserable part of my life, and band was just one part of that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;10th-grade-through-12th-grade&#34;&gt;10th grade through 12th grade&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the 9th grade, because I threatened to drop out of school, the family moved to a different city and a different school after that, and I started 10th grade in a 10-12 high school.  Because of my miserable experiences with flute and with band, and the fact that there was no longer a gym exception for being in band, it never even occurred to me to look into joining a band at the new high school. Of course, that was perfectly OK with my father, who never liked my wasting my time on music anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This high school also had an orchestra, which I knew nothing about other than that it existed (remember, I had still never seen a violin in real life, upon reaching high school).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rest of high school was another miserable part of my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;college&#34;&gt;College&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I fell in love with music all over again in college, because of a kind of accident. There was a requirement to take courses from a &amp;ldquo;core curriculum&amp;rdquo;, and first semester of freshman year, I randomly signed up for &amp;ldquo;Piano Music of the 19th Century&amp;rdquo;. It was a great class. Combined with making new friends who listened to classical music, I started listening to a lot of music. I also started trying to teach myself piano. In retrospect, I should have tried to get real instruction, but I knew that there was no parental support for my &amp;ldquo;wasting my life&amp;rdquo; on a new musical hobby.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;buying-a-new-flute&#34;&gt;Buying a new flute&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another decade or so after college, I got the idea that maybe I should try out flute again! After all, the adolescent days of thinking it was &amp;ldquo;girly&amp;rdquo; were over. The flute has still never been my favorite instrument to listen to, but I already had a head start on it, and various other instruments are more expensive to play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I bought a brand new flute (the one pictured in this blog post). Unfortunately, I kept on having a hard time making decent sounds on it, until tonight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;trumpet&#34;&gt;Trumpet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I had the wild idea of finally realizing my childhood dream and learning trumpet. I bought a trumpet. I started practicing, but realized a couple of things.  One was that it is a &lt;em&gt;very loud&lt;/em&gt; instrument. I have neighbors and stuff. I got a mute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More seriously, I found the pressure on my lips unpleasant, and the pressure in general gave me a headache. Reluctantly, I concluded that it was not healthy for me to really play the trumpet, and put it aside. Recently, I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/01/run-shadyside-5k-outrunning-mickey-mouse-and-lending-a-trumpet/&#34;&gt;lent&lt;/a&gt; it to someone who is hopefully making more use of the instrument than I was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-future&#34;&gt;The future&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regarding taking up the flute again as a result of tonight: I already started playing a new musical instrument this year, the &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/recorder/&#34;&gt;recorder&lt;/a&gt;, and I already spend an average of an hour a day practicing it.  (I also got started on &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/accordion/&#34;&gt;accordion&lt;/a&gt;, but have not had time so far to continue with it.) So it&amp;rsquo;s unclear to me how much I can devote to restarting the flute. I&amp;rsquo;d like to spend some time at least messing around in order to evaluate whether it&amp;rsquo;s worth restarting. One nice thing about the flute is that it is very versatile and if I were to get competent at playing it, I could play it in more contexts than I can currently play the recorder in. I enjoy the recorder, but it has various limitations as an instrument (which is why in Bach&amp;rsquo;s time the Baroque flute came to replace the use of the recorder, and then the modern flute was invented).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Taking up flute again after decades?!</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/11/09/taking-up-flute-again-after-decades/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Nov 2011 20:08:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/11/09/taking-up-flute-again-after-decades/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/franklins-flute.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin&amp;#39;s flute&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Tonight, on a whim, I decided to try out my flute yet again.  Every couple of months for several years now I have pulled it out to see if I might want to start playing it again.  Each time, I encountered serious problems with producing a decent sound at all, and thought that maybe I wasn&amp;rsquo;t meant to play the flute, because the embouchure is such a problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, for the first time in several years, I found that maybe I can get back into playing flute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This possibility pleases me, because the story of me and flutes goes back decades, and is actually rather sad but perhaps instructive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;elementary-school&#34;&gt;Elementary school&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story starts in the last year of elementary school, 5th grade, when a bunch of us students were given the opportunity to choose and start playing a musical instrument. I can still remember Mr. Peters, the music teacher, asking each of us individually what we wanted to play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this time in my life (ten years old), I had received minimal musical instruction so far. I did not grow up in a sufficiently privileged family to receive formal musical lessons, and in fact had never even touched or seen in real life any other musical instrument than the upright piano we just got at home because my mother and younger sister wanted one. I did not listen to any music, had never gone to any kind of musical concert or event before, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d asked my mother earlier what I should ask Mr. Peters to play, so I was ready to answer him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I timidly asked, &amp;ldquo;Piano?&amp;rdquo; Mr. Peters smiled and said, no, that&amp;rsquo;s not something available in the music program. I then asked, &amp;ldquo;Violin?&amp;rdquo; Again, no. I was getting really embarrassed now, because I didn&amp;rsquo;t even know what a violin was: I&amp;rsquo;d never heard one or seen one, but it was a word planted in my head by my mother! (Only many years later did I find out that all Asian kids are supposed to play piano or violin.) Finally, I said, &amp;ldquo;Flute?&amp;rdquo; Yes, flute was an option.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So that&amp;rsquo;s how I started out on flute. I had never encountered a flute before. It was just a word to me. To this day I don&amp;rsquo;t know why my mother had this instrument in her mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;renting-an-instrument&#34;&gt;Renting an instrument&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of my classmates and I ended up renting instruments through the school. My father was not at all interested in my playing music and only because my mother thought I should learn a musical instrument did he cough up the cash to rent a flute for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t particularly like the flute, but I did enjoy getting started playing it. Mostly, I enjoyed the new social group I had: those of use who started on an instrument would gather and learn to play together. That was new to me, and fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;practice&#34;&gt;Practice&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I did not like practicing. I &lt;em&gt;hated&lt;/em&gt; it. Worse, we were given time sheets to fill out indicating how much time we spent practicing at home every day, and have that signed by our parents as witnesses. Well, I wasn&amp;rsquo;t practicing enough, and got scolded by Mr. Peters. I started lying or padding my estimate of how much time I practiced (I still remember writing in &amp;ldquo;30&amp;rdquo; for minutes practiced inside little boxes). What did my father know anyway about what happened when I supposed got started practicing at home and then ended half an hour later?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;middle-school&#34;&gt;Middle school&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When middle school began, I took 6th grade band. Band ended up being the basis of my social life as it was. I still wasn&amp;rsquo;t really practicing flute. Furthermore, I had come to &lt;em&gt;hate&lt;/em&gt; flute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;bad-instrument&#34;&gt;Bad instrument&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing that happened was that flute rental was over, and I had my father buy me a flute. Of course, he bought a totally beat up piece of crap from some garage sale or something somewhere. It was a horrible instrument. The pads got sticky, the mouthpiece was bent, and it was just no fun to play, it was hard to make a good sound out of it, and I knew it was a lot worse than my elementary school rental.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used that flute for another two years before I stopped playing it, forever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;girly-instrument&#34;&gt;Girly instrument&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another thing that happened was that most of the other kids playing flute was girls. Oops, I had ended up with a girly instrument! This was not a trivial matter, given that puberty was starting to kick in, along with a lot of social awareness and anxiety that I never had in elementary school.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-instrument-i-really-wanted-to-play&#34;&gt;The instrument I really wanted to play&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, finally being exposed to a whole bunch of different instruments, hearing them, especially hearing the really good kids, I realized that I really wanted to play the cornet (from which there was a clear path to trumpet).  I liked that the cornet/trumpet was prominent, loud, got the main melodies, everyone could hear it (not always the case with the flute parts!), and of course, it was &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; girly (although, interestingly, a number of girls did play it and were really good at it, and I had a crush on all of them).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, I knew there was no chance my parents would allow me to switch to trumpet. So all I did was dream about playing trumpet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I played flute in the 6th grade, and then in the 7th grade.  I played without &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; enjoyment of the flute during those two years. I did enjoy the social bonding from band, but that was basically it. Also, playing in band allowed one to place out of physical education (don&amp;rsquo;t ask me why), and I dreaded gym class, so I stuck to music to get out of gym (a big mistake, in retrospect).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;high-school&#34;&gt;High school&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;9th-grade&#34;&gt;9th grade&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I skipped the 8th grade of middle school (for reasons beyond the scope of this blog post), and started the 9th grade of high school. Again, I took band in order to avoid gym. It was a miserable experience. Not only did I have to wake up super early to have my mother drive me to marching band practice at 5 AM before school classes started at 7 AM, but also, as a young 9th grader I felt particularly out of place among students who were as much as four years older than me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall the 9th grade was a miserable part of my life, and band was just one part of that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;10th-grade-through-12th-grade&#34;&gt;10th grade through 12th grade&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the 9th grade, because I threatened to drop out of school, the family moved to a different city and a different school after that, and I started 10th grade in a 10-12 high school.  Because of my miserable experiences with flute and with band, and the fact that there was no longer a gym exception for being in band, it never even occurred to me to look into joining a band at the new high school. Of course, that was perfectly OK with my father, who never liked my wasting my time on music anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This high school also had an orchestra, which I knew nothing about other than that it existed (remember, I had still never seen a violin in real life, upon reaching high school).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rest of high school was another miserable part of my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;college&#34;&gt;College&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I fell in love with music all over again in college, because of a kind of accident. There was a requirement to take courses from a &amp;ldquo;core curriculum&amp;rdquo;, and first semester of freshman year, I randomly signed up for &amp;ldquo;Piano Music of the 19th Century&amp;rdquo;. It was a great class. Combined with making new friends who listened to classical music, I started listening to a lot of music. I also started trying to teach myself piano. In retrospect, I should have tried to get real instruction, but I knew that there was no parental support for my &amp;ldquo;wasting my life&amp;rdquo; on a new musical hobby.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;buying-a-new-flute&#34;&gt;Buying a new flute&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another decade or so after college, I got the idea that maybe I should try out flute again! After all, the adolescent days of thinking it was &amp;ldquo;girly&amp;rdquo; were over. The flute has still never been my favorite instrument to listen to, but I already had a head start on it, and various other instruments are more expensive to play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I bought a brand new flute (the one pictured in this blog post). Unfortunately, I kept on having a hard time making decent sounds on it, until tonight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;trumpet&#34;&gt;Trumpet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I had the wild idea of finally realizing my childhood dream and learning trumpet. I bought a trumpet. I started practicing, but realized a couple of things.  One was that it is a &lt;em&gt;very loud&lt;/em&gt; instrument. I have neighbors and stuff. I got a mute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More seriously, I found the pressure on my lips unpleasant, and the pressure in general gave me a headache. Reluctantly, I concluded that it was not healthy for me to really play the trumpet, and put it aside. Recently, I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/01/run-shadyside-5k-outrunning-mickey-mouse-and-lending-a-trumpet/&#34;&gt;lent&lt;/a&gt; it to someone who is hopefully making more use of the instrument than I was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-future&#34;&gt;The future&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regarding taking up the flute again as a result of tonight: I already started playing a new musical instrument this year, the &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/recorder/&#34;&gt;recorder&lt;/a&gt;, and I already spend an average of an hour a day practicing it.  (I also got started on &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/accordion/&#34;&gt;accordion&lt;/a&gt;, but have not had time so far to continue with it.) So it&amp;rsquo;s unclear to me how much I can devote to restarting the flute. I&amp;rsquo;d like to spend some time at least messing around in order to evaluate whether it&amp;rsquo;s worth restarting. One nice thing about the flute is that it is very versatile and if I were to get competent at playing it, I could play it in more contexts than I can currently play the recorder in. I enjoy the recorder, but it has various limitations as an instrument (which is why in Bach&amp;rsquo;s time the Baroque flute came to replace the use of the recorder, and then the modern flute was invented).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>