<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>School on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/school/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in School on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/school/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Life lessons I learned from a lunch recess chess game at age seven: the prequel with a classmate</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/06/01/life-lessons-i-learned-from-a-lunch-recess-chess-game-with-a-classmate-at-age-seven/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jun 2012 13:43:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/06/01/life-lessons-i-learned-from-a-lunch-recess-chess-game-with-a-classmate-at-age-seven/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Two days ago, I wrote about &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/05/30/life-lessons-i-learned-from-a-lunch-recess-chess-game-at-age-seven/&#34;&gt;life lessons I learned from playing a chess game against a computer in the 2nd grade during lunch recess&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, I&amp;rsquo;m writing about what I learned from the only other chess game I played on site in elementary school. I played this game much earlier than the computer game; I played it with a classmate who had seen me looking at chess books in the classroom library and challenged me to a game. Let&amp;rsquo;s call him X. Here are our school photos:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/franklin-second-grade.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin Chen 2nd grade school photo&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/second-grade-chess-opponent.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Classmate in 2nd grade I played one chess game with&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-game-with-x&#34;&gt;My game with X&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was nervous when we sat down to play, because I had up till this point never played chess with anyone but my father.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nobody was watching us. It was just the two of us sitting on the floor in a corner where books and games were stored.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The game lasted no more than two minutes; it lasted four moves before ending!!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;X was playing very quickly, spending no more than a split second per move. Furthermore, he played completely unlike my father and unlike any of the sample instructive games I had seen in chess books. His first move, h4, totally confused and unnerved me. I tried to play according to vague principles I recalled about how one should play, moving my center Pawns, even as he did a strange Rook lift maneuver I had never seen in my entire life. On his third move, he attacked my e Pawn with this rogue Rook and I protected it. On his fourth move, he attacked my Pawn with his d Pawn. We had reached this position:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/second-grade-chess-game.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;My only chess game with another kid in elementary school&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I got excited because it looked like he had made a mistake. His Pawn on d4 is protected only once, by his Queen, while I was attacking it with both my Knight and my Pawn at e5. Therefore, his Pawn was &amp;ldquo;free&amp;rdquo; for me to take!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, I momentarily overlooked that my e Pawn was pinned and took his d Pawn with my e Pawn. (Note: taking the Pawn with the Knight would have lost it; X was definitely no dummy and may even have been a far better chess player than me at the time.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-argument&#34;&gt;The argument&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;X, who had something of a stern, morose temperament, suddenly broke out into a big smile of victory, grabbed his Rook and took my King, jumped up from the ground, and said he won the game!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I protested that I had overlooked that I had made an illegal move, and asked him to give my King back so that I could put all the pieces back to where they were before I made the illegal move, saying that we can&amp;rsquo;t make illegal moves, and Kings cannot be captured in chess, so not only could I not take the Pawn, but he also could not take my King. (I was correct, of course; illegal moves cannot be allowed to stand, and the King can never be taken during a chess turn.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;X refused to listen to me and just gloated. As I had no desire to create a scene and ask for a teacher to adjudicate our dispute, I just walked away. I never played a chess game with him again, and I never told anyone in my life about this incident, until today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;life-lessons-i-learned&#34;&gt;Life lessons I learned&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the things I learned from this incident:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;X may have gotten away with claiming to have won against me, but lost a potential playmate.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some people are uninformed but very sure they are right, and there is no use arguing with them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Even when playing a game by the rules, the ultimate outcome in the real world may depend on whether others are playing by the rules.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I needed more experience in facing unexpected, strange openings and strategies, in order to avoid getting mentally flustered and inattentive.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I needed more experience in staying calm against someone who behaved aggressively and intimidated me.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I needed to look at the larger context when it seemed that something was free for the taking.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I needed to pay more attention to threats directed toward my King from afar.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I needed to be &amp;ldquo;defensive&amp;rdquo; against illegal game endings by not making illegal moves myself.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-i-did-with-what-i-learned&#34;&gt;What I did with what I learned&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;X did me a little favor by teaching me all these lessons. I went home and actually studied his Rook strategy and came up with ways to deal with it if anyone ever played it against me again. I also never played an illegal move again in my life. (Note: up till this point, I was still having some problems &amp;ldquo;seeing&amp;rdquo; that pieces or Pawns of mine were pinned, and would sometimes play illegal moves against my father too.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also decided it was time to go beyond kids&amp;rsquo; chess books and learn more about strategy, going beyond just the basic rules and counting piece points. Luckily for me, the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.gti.net/mocolib1/&#34;&gt;Morris County Library&lt;/a&gt; had a great chess collection, and I got my father to drive us there regularly, where we took out lots of chess books (as well as books on all the other subjects that interested me). My father never asked me why I was getting so excited about chess, but was happy to get into it more himself. We went over serious game collections and opening books, for the first time in our lives, and in months I felt I was much more informed and stronger as a chess player. That set the stage for my proud accomplishment of obtaining a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/05/30/life-lessons-i-learned-from-a-lunch-recess-chess-game-at-age-seven/&#34;&gt;winning position against a chess computer later in the 2nd grade&lt;/a&gt;, which also taught me more life lessons already discussed.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Life lessons I learned from a lunch recess chess game at age seven</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/05/30/life-lessons-i-learned-from-a-lunch-recess-chess-game-at-age-seven/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 May 2012 07:38:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/05/30/life-lessons-i-learned-from-a-lunch-recess-chess-game-at-age-seven/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/franklin-second-grade.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin Chen 2nd grade school photo&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Recently, I have had the opportunity to play chess casually with kids at parties. I could not help reflecting on my own childhood memories of playing chess. I feel that there was much I learned about life from the chess activities of my youth, whether casual or serious. This is the first of a planned series of posts about chess.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://tluif.home.xs4all.nl/chescom/CC3.JPG&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Chess Challenger III from 1977&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This post is about the first time I played with a chess computer and was surprised to find myself winning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-little-bit-of-my-chess-history&#34;&gt;A little bit of my chess history&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Supposedly I first learned chess at some time between the ages of two and three, accidentally picking it up while my father was learning the game along with grad student classmates of his. At the time chess was becoming extremely popular in the United States because of the &amp;ldquo;Fischer boom&amp;rdquo; resulting from &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bobby_Fischer&#34;&gt;Bobby Fischer&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s world championship match and victory against Boris Spassky. Since I don&amp;rsquo;t remember anything from before age two and a half (I remember the months leading up to my celebrating my third birthday), I don&amp;rsquo;t remember a time when I didn&amp;rsquo;t know at least the basic rules of chess!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;kindergarten&#34;&gt;Kindergarten&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was in Kindergarten, I came across some chess books targeted toward children and filled in some gaps (since my father actually had been confused about some of the rules, involving the details of castling and capturing &lt;em&gt;en passant&lt;/em&gt;). I played casually with my father, but nobody else, getting beaten every time (although in retrospect, I have doubts about whether we were playing completely legal games).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;second-grade&#34;&gt;Second grade&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the second grade in elementary school, I was much improved because I had started going through chess books geared toward adults, checked out from the local public library. I had earlier spent some time in the school library going through all the basic chess books there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;chess-challenger-iii&#34;&gt;Chess Challenger III&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://tluif.home.xs4all.nl/chescom/CC3.JPG&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Chess Challenger III from 1977&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One day at lunch recess, a lunch proctor who had heard that I played chess brought me her new &lt;a href=&#34;http://tluif.home.xs4all.nl/chescom/EngCc3.html&#34;&gt;Chess Challenger III&lt;/a&gt; computer. I started playing a game with it (with me as White and the computer as Black). To my surprise, I was winning against this computer, which had fallen into a trap I had set! (Up until this point, I had only ever played chess with my father, and he had always won.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;White to play and win:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/chess-challenger-iii_files/diag3FE05522BFCEDF4D.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Critical position in game&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the bell rang shortly after I had trapped Chess Challenger III&amp;rsquo;s Queen and I excitedly told everyone I was beating the computer. The proctor just sniffed and dismissed my claim, practically calling me a liar. I never talked to her again in my life and never asked to play the computer again for a rematch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I learned:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chess computers are not perfect, and even a child might play better.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Adults in school often misunderstand or disrespect students who do something unexpected.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;my-game-against-chess-challenger-iii&#34;&gt;My game against Chess Challenger III&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have fully annotated my one and only &lt;a href=&#34;../../chess/chess-challenger-iii.htm&#34;&gt;game against Chess Challenger III&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am guessing the computer was set at a default &amp;ldquo;easy&amp;rdquo; level; I am guessing that at its highest level (which unfortunately would have led to its playing too slowly in a recess setting), I may not have been able to beat it. I had never played with anyone other than my father by this age (I started playing with other people only at age ten, with some exceptions I&amp;rsquo;ll discuss later), but I&amp;rsquo;m guessing my ELO rating strength at age seven was probably no higher than 1200.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>