<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Cooking on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/cooking/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Cooking on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/cooking/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Why we decided to compile our own family cookbook</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/12/07/why-we-decided-to-compile-our-own-family-cookbook/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Dec 2014 19:46:48 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/12/07/why-we-decided-to-compile-our-own-family-cookbook/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Cooking has been a significant part of my life since 1999 when, shortly before reaching age 30, my bachelor self decided to completely change his unhealthy diet and lifestyle, and that meant &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/03/21/time-to-taste-the-world-thoughts-on-expanding-my-food-tastes-as-an-adult/&#34;&gt;finally getting down and dirty with seriously cooking for myself&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After getting married to Abby ten years later, cooking responsibilities have rotated between us based on the situation; there have been long stretches of time during which I did all the cooking every day, and there have been long periods during which she did all the cooking. Currently, we roughly split the cooking between us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-compile-our-own-cookbook&#34;&gt;Why compile our own cookbook?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve occasionally posted on this blog a recipe and/or photos of some food I&amp;rsquo;ve cooked, but for the most part, cooking is just a mundane everyday activity that I don&amp;rsquo;t keep track of, since the task of cooking is primarily utilitarian for us, not innovative or artistic. We simply need to eat every day, and prefer not to eat out often, for various reasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently I decided that we should start compiling our own family cookbook, noting details of what we prepare and how, in order to better replicate good results and improve on bad results, and make planning and impromptu cooking more efficient. Without our own cookbook, we have to rely on our faulty memories, and things sometimes don&amp;rsquo;t come out right (especially where the oven is concerned).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below is an example of the kind of cooking we do. This is not a cooking blog, so I don&amp;rsquo;t expect to write much or often about our cooking, but I just felt like it tonight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-i-prepared-tonight&#34;&gt;What I prepared tonight&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;raw-veggie-sticks&#34;&gt;Raw veggie sticks&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/franklinmingchen/15945039966&#34; title=&#34;IMG_20141207_174932 by Franklin Chen, on Flickr&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7535/15945039966_f2273fbf1d.jpg&#34; width=&#34;375&#34; height=&#34;500&#34; alt=&#34;IMG_20141207_174932&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We like to regularly cut up raw veggie sticks to eat as daytime snacks at work, or sometimes also as crunchy variety during regular meals as part of salads. I chopped up some carrots and celery for this purpose tonight. We often use other ingredients also, but tonight I just stuck to the basics. A list of some random options we&amp;rsquo;ve used (depending on season, availability in our &lt;a href=&#34;http://kretschmannfarm.com/&#34;&gt;Kretschmann Farm&lt;/a&gt; box subscription, and whim while out grocery shopping):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;carrots&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;celery&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;cucumbers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;peppers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;radishes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;parsnips&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;beets&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;turnips&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trick is simply to slice stuff lengthwise into reasonable widths, then chop them across to create reasonable lengths. No need to be exact. Also, &lt;a href=&#34;http://groovygreenlivin.com/5-vegetables-that-you-don%E2%80%99t-need-to-peel/&#34;&gt;we don&amp;rsquo;t bother to peel carrots&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;kale-boiled&#34;&gt;Kale, boiled&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/franklinmingchen/15970795205&#34; title=&#34;IMG_20141207_174941 by Franklin Chen, on Flickr&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7560/15970795205_3e6492769a.jpg&#34; width=&#34;375&#34; height=&#34;500&#34; alt=&#34;IMG_20141207_174941&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We like kale. There are actually many different varieties with different colors and textures. Here&amp;rsquo;s some ordinary kale. I find it easiest to just boil it while preparing other foods. I test it periodically to make sure it is no longer tough to eat but still has some bite also and is not soggy. We boil the kale either in water or in our own homemade chicken broth that we make with the bones and other parts of whole chickens after eating the muscle meat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;turnips-sauteed&#34;&gt;Turnips, sauteed&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/franklinmingchen/15970797965&#34; title=&#34;IMG_20141207_174949 by Franklin Chen, on Flickr&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8671/15970797965_64a385e5dd.jpg&#34; width=&#34;375&#34; height=&#34;500&#34; alt=&#34;IMG_20141207_174949&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OK, this is an example of something of an experiment that is going into the family cookbook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have cooked turnips in many ways (including, of course, as raw veggie sticks). Possibly the most common way we cook them is in the oven along with beets, potatoes, or the like, either as chunks or in &amp;ldquo;home fries&amp;rdquo; shapes. I&amp;rsquo;ve also prepared them as part of beef casserole dishes in the oven. Or as chicken stir fry with turnips. The possibilities are endless. You just have to be aware of how long they take to cook, and how thinly to slice for the purpose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tonight, I decided to slice the turnips very thin, for the purpose of creating a nice topping for the main dish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;extra virgin olive oil&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;turnips, sliced very thin&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;some onion bits&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;fresh rosemary&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;salt and pepper&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;garlic, generous amount&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My habit these days when cooking in the skillet is to delay the introduction of the garlic, in order to give the result more kick.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;baked-salmon&#34;&gt;Baked salmon&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/franklinmingchen/15968891841&#34; title=&#34;IMG_20141207_180014 by Franklin Chen, on Flickr&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7570/15968891841_7e3aa84a19.jpg&#34; width=&#34;375&#34; height=&#34;500&#34; alt=&#34;IMG_20141207_180014&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, some fish (salmon). I have to confess that I&amp;rsquo;m not yet very happy about the results when I cook fish. Abby does a better job than me overall, so I usually let her cook fish. Still, both of us find it tricky to get fish just so: what&amp;rsquo;s the perfect balance between undercooked and overcooked?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I slightly overcooked the salmon tonight, for a couple of reasons: I forgot to get it out of the fridge earlier in the day to warm it up more before preparation, and I baked a bit too long as an attempt to make up for that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using the oven is always tricky for me. Higher temperature means cooking faster, but also means drying things out. For this dish, I decided on a temperature of 400 F for 30 minutes. Next time, if I have the salmon fully defrosted, I believe 20 should do the trick.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;extra virgin olive oil&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;lemon slices&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;salmon fillets, skin side down on top of the lemon slices&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;salt and pepper&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;fresh rosemary&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;garlic, generous amount&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;some onion bits&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result came out a bit dry, but other than that tasted great to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re wondering &amp;ldquo;why rosemary in particular&amp;rdquo;, the answer is &amp;ldquo;our farm box from last week gave us a bunch and we need to use it&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cooking is a necessity but can be a pleasure or a frustration as well. There are times when I feel &amp;ldquo;lazy&amp;rdquo; and don&amp;rsquo;t want to cook and feel it&amp;rsquo;s a chore, but there are times when I feel slightly creative or experimental and want to make something I will find enjoyable to eat (and hopefully Abby will find enjoyable to eat also). Hopefully collecting our efforts into a cookbook will make it easier to whip up more variety when we are feeling &amp;ldquo;lazy&amp;rdquo; and don&amp;rsquo;t want to think too much.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Report on my first day of Stoic Week 2014</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/24/report-on-my-first-day-of-stoic-week-2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2014 22:30:51 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/24/report-on-my-first-day-of-stoic-week-2014/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Last year, I heard about the first Stoic Week, &lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.exeter.ac.uk/stoicismtoday/stoic-week-2013/&#34;&gt;Stoic Week 2013&lt;/a&gt;, but did not participate because I was distracted at the time and did not feel like focusing. This week, I decided it was time to sign up for &lt;a href=&#34;http://modernstoicism.com/course/view.php?id=5&#34;&gt;Stoic Week 2014&lt;/a&gt;, and I did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-my-interest-in-stoicism&#34;&gt;Why my interest in Stoicism?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve mentioned Stoicism only briefly in my blog: once in 2012 when &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/11/22/thanking-the-best-of-all-possible-worlds/&#34;&gt;thinking about Thanksgiving&lt;/a&gt; and once earlier this year after &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/01/17/hiroo-onoda-and-the-six-million-dollar-man/&#34;&gt;rewatching an old TV episode&lt;/a&gt;. As I mentioned, it was in 2011, upon reading a book on Stoicism, that I made some major changes in my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that a couple of weeks ago, I decided to make major changes in my life again, but not while thinking about Stoicism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over a year ago, my meditation practice fell apart, and I never really regained it. As a result, my thoughts and habits have become disordered, I have felt. For example, I stopped writing regularly for my blog. I spent too much time on Facebook and Twitter instead, being distracted, annoyed, and worse, behaving in ways that I later came to feel counterproductive. I did &amp;ldquo;quit&amp;rdquo; Facebook in July, and also &amp;ldquo;quit&amp;rdquo; Twitter some weeks ago (part of the big life changes I set in motion), but still, I have felt ungrounded. I decided Stoic Week 2014 would be a good opportunity for me to return to the contemplative life that Buddhism and Stoicism in their different ways aspire to and that I had forgotten.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-i-did-the-first-day-of-stoic-week-2014&#34;&gt;What I did the first day of Stoic Week 2014&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, as I started the first day of Stoic Week 2014, I began by meditating ten minutes, Zen style. &lt;em&gt;This was my first meditation session in weeks&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I read the assigned text for today in the Stoic Week handbook, on &amp;ldquo;What is in our power?&amp;rdquo; A basic principle of Stoicism is that we should know what is under our control and what is not, and summarily refuse to dwell on or resent what is not under our control, and focus on making good decisions about what is under our control. A very simple but powerful concept, especially in a world in which it is easy to get annoyed or angry about many things we hear about in the news or encounter in our daily lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My exercise habit has been very spotty for months now. Well, today I reflected that, what the hell, it is completely under my control whether I choose to exercise or not, so why am I wasting this precious freedom? Some people don&amp;rsquo;t have this freedom. Others, including prisoners in jail, have little freedom but make use of what they have, and &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/17/the-joys-of-convict-conditioning-bodyweight-exercising/&#34;&gt;they exercise&lt;/a&gt;! It happened to be warm outside today, so I really had no excuse. I went for a run in Frick Park. It was short, less than three miles long, but I went. &lt;em&gt;This was my first run in weeks&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was my turn to cook today at home, so I made a substantial beef casserole dish. Abby has (rightfully) complained in the past when I didn&amp;rsquo;t completely clean up after cooking. Well, today I thought to myself that it is completely within my control whether I choose to attend to the details of cleanup as much as I attend to the details of using our skillets and baking pans. So I cleaned up as well as I could.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have not been feeling very well physically for weeks now since an incident involving emergency dental work that somehow resulted in complications. I am still in recovery. OK, so it is not under my control that I am not in good health right now. But what is under my control? After lunch I took a nap, because I felt like I needed it. I have been skimping on naps, but this is stupid, because I know that sleep is the best restorative practice when ill. It is under my control whether I choose to set aside time to sleep as needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At work, a colleague just came back from his first trip in Asia. He gave me samples of some odd snacks: chips, cookies, and candy. In recent months, I would have opened them up and eaten them on the spot. Indeed, I have been having problems with eating too many snacks for no rational reason. Today, I decided that it is up to me whether I choose to give in to random cravings or temptations, and so I chose to put the snacks aside for later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After work, I went to a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/Pittsburgh-Code-Supply/events/210396972/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Code and Supply Build Night&lt;/a&gt;, where food was served. Apart from a Thanksgiving dinner (!), some kind of cake lurked around. I took one glance, and chose not to even look at it again until leaving (when it was already all eaten).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leaving Build Night, I found myself annoyed that it was taking forever for the pedestrian light to change, but caught myself and observed that, first of all, the cycle is as it is, beyond my control; and second, I had mistakenly assumed that someone had pressed the button, so it was my fault I had to wait so long. I pressed the button and eventually got to cross. Next, while driving home, I made the mistake of driving behind a bus, which kept stopping. I got annoyed, not by the bus, but by myself, for mistakenly driving on the wrong street rather than the other one that does not have this problem; I got annoyed that I was too lazy to make a U-turn on the street I was parked on in order to get to that other street. But I stopped myself when I realized that what was done was done, and I simply had to endure the rest of the drive home behind the bus because it was not going to save any more time if I detoured around it late in the game: the best I can do is to be more careful in the future when making choices while driving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I felt I improved my life today by keeping in mind the fundamental Stoic principle of observing what is not under my control and what is under my control. I look forward to continuing to adopt this outlook for the rest of the week, and beyond that.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Finally making rhubarb tasty to myself: flour-less rhubarb crisp</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/06/09/finally-making-rhubarb-tasty-to-myself/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Jun 2014 18:15:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/06/09/finally-making-rhubarb-tasty-to-myself/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;For the first forty years of my life, I believe I never ate any rhubarb. At least, I don&amp;rsquo;t ever recall anything identified as rhubarb that I ate. It was just something I heard about, in the context of pie, and I rarely eat pies, and am rather particular about pie when I do eat it (for example, I have sometimes eaten pumpkin pie, because my father likes it, but I never once really enjoyed it).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My Krestschmann Farm box subscription has always recognized that some people don&amp;rsquo;t like rhubarb, and allows opting out of receiving it. Since I never ate it, I didn&amp;rsquo;t know whether I liked it, but looking up its description online, I felt no need to try it, so I always indicated that I did not want it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today was the first time I cooked rhubarb and made something that I actually enjoyed eating. Here&amp;rsquo;s the story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-first-time-cooking-rhubarb-was-a-disaster&#34;&gt;My first time cooking rhubarb was a disaster&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost exactly a year ago, Abby and I accidentally did not specify rhubarb exclusion from our farm box (upon renewing our subscription). So we received rhubarb.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t know what the heck to do with it. I decided to make an Indian-style lentil dish and &amp;ldquo;hide&amp;rdquo; rhubarb in it. At first I thought it was OK, but then I decided it was weird. Unfortunately, I had to finish the whole batch. Abby didn&amp;rsquo;t help me finish it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rhubarb-lentils-2013-06-10.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Rhubarb lentils&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;abby-s-experiment-didn-t-work-for-me&#34;&gt;Abby&amp;rsquo;s experiment didn&amp;rsquo;t work for me&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby also tried an experiment, cooking rhubarb with banana on the stove. The resulting concoction caused an argument, because after trying it, I refused to eat any more of it, but she had made a huge batch and so she was stuck with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-experiment-today&#34;&gt;My experiment today&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I decided that instead of randomly making crap up, I would look for some kind of &amp;ldquo;recipe&amp;rdquo;, and also incorporate the advice of friends from last year. The following is what I made. I found it surprisingly edible, and even had to stop myself from eating too much after dinner:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rhubarb-2014-06-09.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Rhubarb crisp&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My ingredients:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Coconut oil&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rhubarb, chopped up&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Honey (I tried to go easy with this!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cinnamon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cloves&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Orange zest&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lemon juice&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Salt&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cocoa powder (a tiny sprinkle, just an improvisation)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Raw walnuts and pecans, chopped&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Preheat oven to 350 degrees F, layer the nuts on top of the remainder of the mixture, and bake for 40 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to everyone who offered suggestions to me last year!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result was fairly tart, which is fine, but I didn&amp;rsquo;t want to put too much sugar into this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-next&#34;&gt;What next?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was planning to notify Kretschmann Farm that we don&amp;rsquo;t want to receive rhubarb, but I have second thoughts now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, we will probably go ahead as planned and put rhubarb on our &amp;ldquo;do not want&amp;rdquo; list, simply because we&amp;rsquo;d rather get other stuff instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;lessons-learned&#34;&gt;Lessons learned&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I learned some lessons from this whole rhubarb incident:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I can learn to &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/03/21/time-to-taste-the-world-thoughts-on-expanding-my-food-tastes-as-an-adult/&#34;&gt;like stuff I never ate for decades&lt;/a&gt;, if I prepare it just so. (More generally, I try to continuously find opportunities to &lt;a href=&#34;http://sivers.org/hate&#34;&gt;love what I used to hate&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is wise to listen to accumulated wisdom, especially from my friends (whose taste might be correlated a bit with mine).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Accidentally &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; choosing to opt out of my &amp;ldquo;default&amp;rdquo; preference led to some interesting experiences.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s the latest food you feared or hated or didn&amp;rsquo;t know about that you recently tried? How did it go? If it went poorly, will you try again, or just write it off?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Broccoli and friends</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/11/01/broccoli-and-friends/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2013 18:26:40 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/11/01/broccoli-and-friends/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Today I saw an article about &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2013/11/03/magazine/broccolis-extreme-makeover.html&#34;&gt;marketing broccoli and other vegetables&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By coincidence, I had this morning whipped up a vegetable dish in the kitchen that included some broccoli.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-my-father-got-me-to-eat-broccoli&#34;&gt;How my father got me to eat broccoli&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the basic story of why I ate broccoli as a child and through adulthood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I distinctly remember not really liking broccoli as a toddler of around two and a half to three years old (my childhood memories do not go earlier than age two and a half). I also remember a major turning point, after which I &amp;ldquo;happily&amp;rdquo; ate it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My mother was unsuccessful in nagging me to eat my brocolli. It was when my father called broccoli florets &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;baby trees&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo;. All of a sudden it seemed cool to eat them, as though I were a large beast swooping down from the sky (I liked trees and all my youthful drawings and watercolors included them; I have fond memories of sitting outside under a tree).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;simple-vegetable-medley&#34;&gt;Simple vegetable medley&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/broccoli-medley.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Broccoli and other vegetables&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I used a wok, but for the volume, not at high heat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Time: 25 minutes&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;olive oil&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;onion, sliced&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;carrots, sliced&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;celery stalks, sliced&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;broccoli florets and thinly sliced stems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;assorted peppers, sliced&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;garlic&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;seasoning mix&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically, I used what was at hand from our farm box subscription.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still love to eat those florets as though I were a giant beast feasting on trees.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An erhu player and a tuba player at a party said &#34;Let&#39;s jam&#34;</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/09/28/an-erhu-player-and-a-tuba-player-at-a-party-said-lets-jam/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Sep 2013 22:02:19 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/09/28/an-erhu-player-and-a-tuba-player-at-a-party-said-lets-jam/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I attended a music potluck party tonight. We had been unsure about whether to attend, since I do have the Great Race 10K to run tomorrow and need to avoid staying up too late. So we went with the understanding that we would leave early as needed, in order for me to wind down at home and go to bed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;food&#34;&gt;Food&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I whipped up a large batch of roasted vegetables to bring to the potluck:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/vegetables-2013-09-28.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Roasted vegetables&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;music&#34;&gt;Music&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a lot of eating and chatting, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.appalasia.com/Mimi.htm&#34;&gt;Mimi&lt;/a&gt; was ready to start jamming, and got out her &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Erhu&#34;&gt;erhu&lt;/a&gt;. A guy who had brought a tuba was ready to play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OK, who else was in?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I pulled out my flute. Abby took out her mandolin. It seemed like nobody else (yet) was interested in joining in. (But as we know, the party usually really gets going later in the evening when musicians are involved.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tuba player seemed really into jazz. He asked for requests and started his own rhythmic bass sometimes. I tried to join in with him and Mimi as they led the way. It was pretty hard for me, and frightening, but I did what I could to contribute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At one point, I volunteered to sing and play &amp;ldquo;Has Anybody Seen My Gal?&amp;rdquo; on ukulele, which I did (for the first time by myself outside home), and they followed along. I don&amp;rsquo;t know if that was the first time an erhu, tuba, and ukulele were in action simultaneously!?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;lending-my-flute-out&#34;&gt;Lending my flute out&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point, a guy arrived at the party who wanted to jam. He hadn&amp;rsquo;t yet brought in his trombone, but asked if he could borrow my flute. I recognized him from previous parties, and I had seen him play flute in at least one of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So he borrowed my flute and I sat back and watched and listened. He was a really good improviser. Actually, at the suggestion of the tuba player, who really liked totally free improvisation, the three of them did something I found amazing and beautiful. Starting with some long tones, they created an eerie sonic soundscape together, listening to one another while blending the erhu, tuba, and flute. I was really moved by this display of musicality and feeling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;leaving-early&#34;&gt;Leaving early&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby noted that it was getting &amp;ldquo;late&amp;rdquo; for us, and so we regrettably had to leave. Guests were still coming in and bringing food, even though those of us who had arrived early had filled our stomachs long ago. I got my flute back and packed up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is always a special treat for me when I get to hang around creative, accomplished musicians and get to see them make music spontaneously. I&amp;rsquo;m usually too intimidated in these kinds of situations to join in, but I did briefly tonight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-11-06&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-11-06)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was surprised and saddened to learn from Mimi that just a couple of days ago, the man who had borrowed my flute and played so beautifully, David Olson, &lt;a href=&#34;http://obituaries.triblive.com/listing/231895/David-E-Olson/&#34;&gt;died&lt;/a&gt;. Even in the brief time that I interacted with him at all, just in a handful of music parties, I was struck by his enthusiasm, humor, and graciousness. It is hard to believe that he is gone now, just a month since he was playing my flute. RIP, David.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cooking the huge batch of food: sweet potatoes, peppers, butternut squash</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/01/12/cooking-the-huge-batch-of-food-sweet-potatoes/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Jan 2013 19:42:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/01/12/cooking-the-huge-batch-of-food-sweet-potatoes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s Saturday, so I did a huge batch of cooking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were a lot of sweet potatoes that needed to be used. I sauteed some of them and roasted the others. Same with the assorted peppers. The butternut squash I kept simple, just slicing in half, putting them face down in a pan with some water, and baking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sweet potatoes in progress already in skillet:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/cooking-2013-01-12/sauteed-sweet-potatoes.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Preparing onions (and garlic to be added later):&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/cooking-2013-01-12/onions.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/cooking-2013-01-12/garlic.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A separate batch of sweet potatoes, in the oven:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/cooking-2013-01-12/oven-sweet-potatoes.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Peppers in skillet:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/cooking-2013-01-12/sauteed-peppers.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Sweet potatoes and peppers cut into &amp;ldquo;fries&amp;rdquo; from the oven, a favorite of mine:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/cooking-2013-01-12/sweet-potato-pepper-fries.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Butternut squash from the oven, to be scooped out and seasoned:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/cooking-2013-01-12/butternut-squash.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cooking the whole cauliflower including the leaves again</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/01/06/cooking-the-whole-cauliflower-including-the-leaves-again/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Jan 2013 19:40:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/01/06/cooking-the-whole-cauliflower-including-the-leaves-again/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;We often get cauliflower with leaves intact. So I end up doing something with both the florets and the leaves, cooking them separately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;sauteed-cauliflower-florets&#34;&gt;Sauteed cauliflower florets&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/cauliflower-2013-01-06.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Sauteed cauliflower florets&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Sauteed with olive oil, garlic, and random other bits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;cauliflower-leaf-soup&#34;&gt;Cauliflower leaf soup&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/cauliflower-leaf-soup-2013-01-06.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Cauliflower leaf soup&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Winter means soup.  Toss in a base of chopped up onion, carrot, celery, and spices, and make cauliflower leaf soup!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A winter red cabbage slaw for the New Year</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/01/01/a-winter-red-cabbage-slaw-for-the-new-year/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2013 21:34:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/01/01/a-winter-red-cabbage-slaw-for-the-new-year/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Happy New Year!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/red-cabbage-slaw.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Red cabbage slaw&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For a party, I used what was at hand at home to make something to share. I decided on a red cabbage slaw, after doing a Google search for ingredients and seeing some recipes. I didn&amp;rsquo;t follow any one recipe, but merged a couple of ideas. Since people seemed to eat up the cabbage slaw, and several complimented me on it and asked for the recipe, here it is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;recipe-for-red-cabbage-slaw&#34;&gt;Recipe for red cabbage slaw&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; red cabbage, sliced thin&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2 &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.orangepippin.com/apples/goldrush&#34;&gt;Gold Rush&lt;/a&gt; apples, peeled and sliced thin&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;4 carrots, grated&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.organicgardeninfo.com/growing-cylindra-beets.html&#34;&gt;long beet&lt;/a&gt;, grated&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; red onion, sliced thin&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dressing:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;6 tablespoons extra virgin olive oil&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;6 tablespoons raw apple cider vinegar&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;4 tablespoons honey mustard&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2 cloves of garlic, minced&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Toppings:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;pecans&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;walnuts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;raisins&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Put all the prepared ingredients into a large bowl.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mix the dressing into the bowl.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover and leave in the refrigerator for 24 hours. Stir again once or twice during that period to make sure everything is even.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;notes&#34;&gt;Notes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some recipes for cabbage slaw that I saw called for added sugar, but given the specific ingredients I chose, there was no need at all for extra sugar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I chose some nuts that seemed to make sense. Other nuts could be used also, or left out if someone is allergic to nuts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I could see dried cranberries being used instead of raisins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other substitutions are easy to imagine also; in fact, my recipe involved substitutions for ingredients in recipes I found online.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;thanks&#34;&gt;Thanks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The red cabbage, Gold Rush apples, carrots, long beet happen to have come from our &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.kretschmannfarm.com/Winter%20Boxes/Winter%20boxes.htm&#34;&gt;winter box subscription from Kretschmann Farm&lt;/a&gt;. Abby and I are really happy that they offer a winter box subscription as well as the regular season subscription, so that we can continue to get quality organic, local produce all year long.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having a subscription not only allows us to eat seasonally, but also explore foods we may not necessarily have eaten much of or even seen before. For example, I like these long beets and Gold Rush apples.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reflections on Food Day</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/10/24/reflections-on-food-day/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Oct 2012 22:38:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/10/24/reflections-on-food-day/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/food-day-2012-breakfast-1.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Soup and veggies&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A year ago I celebrated &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.foodday.org/&#34;&gt;Food Day&lt;/a&gt; for the first time, by sharing &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/24/every-day-is-food-day/&#34;&gt;some reflections on what food means to me&lt;/a&gt;. Today I review my reflections and some more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;buying-food&#34;&gt;Buying food&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I still take care to shop carefully for groceries and make our own tasty meals to eat. Some of our sources:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://kretschmannfarm.com/&#34;&gt;Kretschmann Farm&lt;/a&gt; CSA subscription for local produce&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.localharvest.org/miseras-organic-farm-M14896&#34;&gt;Misera&amp;rsquo;s Organic Farm&lt;/a&gt; for local &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/24/whats-a-nice-acorn-squash-like-you-doing-in-a-pot-of-spicy-lentils/&#34;&gt;chickens&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lewisfamilyfarms.com/&#34;&gt;Lewis Family Farms&lt;/a&gt; for local beef&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://pine-richland.patch.com/articles/stoney-lane-farm-a-little-bit-country-in-suburbia&#34;&gt;Stoney Lane Farm&lt;/a&gt; for local &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/28/thankful-for-the-free-range-orange-yolked-eggs/&#34;&gt;eggs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.traderjoes.com/&#34;&gt;Trader Joe&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.eastendfood.coop/&#34;&gt;East End Food Co-op&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our food choices are based on our concerns for both &lt;em&gt;health&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;sustainability&lt;/em&gt;. Our choices may have an impact on one or the other or both.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;cooking&#34;&gt;Cooking&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I started my blog over a year ago, I had thought I would be posting more about cooking, since I was doing a good amount of it, but as it turned out, during this year (2012), Abby took over almost all of the cooking for us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;diet&#34;&gt;Diet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both Abby and I have experimented in paleo directions in the past year. As a reminder, this doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean that we&amp;rsquo;re just going around chowing down on all the meat we can eat. It does mean that we have&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;considerably increased our consumption of vegetables&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;increased our consumption of various fats and oils&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;reduced our consumption of carbs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-question-of-carbs&#34;&gt;The question of carbs&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What we seemed to discover was that we needed some base level of carbs in order to maintain energy and weight levels. Through experimentation, Abby has focused on getting carbs through potatoes and sweet potatoes primarily, going almost completely off wheat. I, on the other hand, am still hooked on rice; I also still eat some wheat, but frankly, I can tell from the effects that I would probably do best to eliminate it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;rice-disaster&#34;&gt;Rice disaster?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, I wondered about brown rice, and even briefly experimented with &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/07/is-brown-rice-healthy-or-not/&#34;&gt;switching to white rice&lt;/a&gt;. The white rice experiment was a fast failure: the high glycemic index and lack of fiber didn&amp;rsquo;t help me at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More recently, there have been reports of &lt;em&gt;brown rice&lt;/em&gt; in particular having &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.consumerreports.org/cro/magazine/2012/11/arsenic-in-your-food/index.htm&#34;&gt;high levels of arsenic&lt;/a&gt;. This is rather disturbing, and Abby and I have agreed that I need to quickly re-evaluate my consumption of brown rice. I&amp;rsquo;ve committed to trying out some alternative source of calories/fiber.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-breakfast&#34;&gt;My breakfast&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My breakfast has remained fairly &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/01/26/improving-my-breakfast-and-other-meals/&#34;&gt;stable&lt;/a&gt; since &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/23/paleo-diet-experimentation/&#34;&gt;I quit oatmeal&lt;/a&gt;. Basically, I eat&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;veggies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;eggs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;nuts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a prune&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Depending on how I feel and what&amp;rsquo;s available, occasionally I&amp;rsquo;ll eat some bacon or fish, and sometimes I&amp;rsquo;ll add some sweet potatoes or other carbs, but typically that&amp;rsquo;s it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(I stopped the flax seeds, largely out of inconvenience of grinding them!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s what I happened to eat today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/food-day-2012-breakfast-1.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Soup and veggies&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/food-day-2012-breakfast-2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Eggs&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The soup and veggies were leftovers from big batches Abby or I had made earlier:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;my cauliflower leaf soup with garlic, carrots, sweet potatoes, curry powder, extra virgin olive oil&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;my stir-fried cauliflower florets with garlic, green peppers, coconut oil&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Abby&amp;rsquo;s spaghetti squash with onion and other stuff&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And on top of that I also ate two fried eggs with walnuts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-lunch-and-dinner&#34;&gt;My lunch and dinner&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lunch and dinner were combinations of various leftovers, all originally made by Abby (hence my not knowing the exact ingredients):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ground beef stew with green peppers, jalapeno, onion, various seasoning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;slow-cooked chicken with veggies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;leftover kale and onion&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;dinner included sauteed zucchini and other veggies Abby cooked tonight&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;brown rice&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;fasting&#34;&gt;Fasting&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes I deliberately fast for a meal or two. This happens when I just don&amp;rsquo;t feel all that hungry. I treat that as a signal from my body that I don&amp;rsquo;t really need to eat. My experiments have convinced me that &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Intermittent_fasting&#34;&gt;intermittent fasting&lt;/a&gt; helps with fat loss and mental clarity. It also helps me remember to be grateful, when I do eat again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are human beings, not robots. We need food. And food isn&amp;rsquo;t just &amp;ldquo;fuel&amp;rdquo;. It lives or has lived. It is complex. I am grateful to be living in a land of plenty, and that Abby has taken so much care to make varied and tasty dishes for us. But as the recent reports on arsenic reminds me, there is much we must continue to do to prevent the degradation of what we eat.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My end-of-summer vegetable medley recipe</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/09/17/end-of-summer-vegetable-medley-recipe/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Sep 2012 08:41:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/09/17/end-of-summer-vegetable-medley-recipe/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/end-of-summer-vegetable-medley.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin&amp;#39;s end-of-summer vegetable medley&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I whipped up what I&amp;rsquo;ll call my &amp;ldquo;end-of-summer vegetable medley&amp;rdquo; (since summer is basically over now), using ingredients we happened to have on hand, from &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/kretschmann-farm/&#34;&gt;Kretschmann Farm&lt;/a&gt; as well as from Abby&amp;rsquo;s parents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;recipe&#34;&gt;Recipe&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;equipment&#34;&gt;Equipment&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Large skillet (I happened to use a wok)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;ingredients&#34;&gt;Ingredients&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Oil for high heat (I used coconut oil)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One green pepper&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One green zucchini&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One yellow zucchini&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One tomato&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Garlic, one large clove&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Seasoning mix (I used sea salt and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.traderjoes.com/fearless-flyer/article.asp?article_id=539&#34;&gt;Trader Joe&amp;rsquo;s 21 Seasoning Salute&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fresh cilantro&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Extra virgin olive oil&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;preparation&#34;&gt;Preparation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Green pepper: slice into strips.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Green zucchini: slice into thin coins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yellow zucchini: slice into thin coins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tomato: slice thinly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Garlic: crush and mince a large clove (or more if you prefer).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cilantro: chop up a bunch of fresh cilantro.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;cooking&#34;&gt;Cooking&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the ingredients are ready, the rest only takes a few minutes at high heat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heat the oil in the skillet to high heat. When the skillet is ready, put the green pepper and zucchinis into the skillet and toss/stir to coat with oil. Then add the seasoning mix and continue to toss/stir for a while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the vegetables look to be half done (to your liking; I prefer them to retain some bite rather than be soggy), add the tomato and garlic and continue to toss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When everything is almost done, add the cilantro and toss/stir briefly, then turn off the heat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Add extra virgin olive oil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Improving my breakfast and other meals: a paleo progress report</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/01/26/improving-my-breakfast-and-other-meals/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jan 2012 09:40:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/01/26/improving-my-breakfast-and-other-meals/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the past couple of months, I&amp;rsquo;ve made some large changes in my diet. Fundamentally, I&amp;rsquo;ve moved in a &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/paleo/&#34;&gt;paleo&lt;/a&gt; direction. The largest change was breakfast, where I completely gave up my old breakfast and &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/03/one-of-these-breakfasts-is-not-paleo/&#34;&gt;replaced it&lt;/a&gt;. After some experimentation, I&amp;rsquo;ve finally arrived at a breakfast template that seems optimal for me (as gauged by my morning energy level and other criteria I discuss below).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an example, here is what I ate this morning:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/breakfast-with-prune.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Breakfast with flax seeds and prune&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The ingredients, and what has changed, and why:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;recipe&#34;&gt;Recipe&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; tsp &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.organicfacts.net/organic-oils/organic-coconut-oil/health-benefits-of-coconut-oil.html&#34;&gt;coconut oil&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2 &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/28/thankful-for-the-free-range-orange-yolked-eggs/&#34;&gt;eggs&lt;/a&gt;, fried&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; clove of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.garlic-central.com/garlic-health.html&#34;&gt;garlic&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;some shakes of seasoning mix (salt, pepper, etc.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a dash of turmeric&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;some red pepper flakes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;butternut squash&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;spinach&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;uncooked &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.traderjoes.com/how-to/olive-oil.asp&#34;&gt;extra virgin olive oil&lt;/a&gt; on top of the veggies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;about 7 walnuts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 tsp &lt;a href=&#34;http://lowcarbdiets.about.com/od/whattoeat/a/flaxinfo.htm&#34;&gt;flax seeds&lt;/a&gt;, sprinkled on top of everything at the end&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 prune on the side&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;changes-and-rationale&#34;&gt;Changes and rationale&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;carbs&#34;&gt;Carbs&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I stopped my short experiment of eating potatoes or rice with breakfast because I found that my morning energy level was simply better without those high-glycemic carbs. I think there is a legitimate place for such carbs, but not in my current schedule, which does not (yet) include intensive exercise before breakfast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;additions&#34;&gt;Additions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I now always eat two eggs, instead of one. One wasn&amp;rsquo;t really enough to make me feel satisfied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recently added coconut oil, which I had not been using because some past experiments did not work out well. I think that was because of using too much. So I&amp;rsquo;m not using much now. Amusingly, my main use of coconut oil up till now has been to rub onto my skin during this dry winter season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve added more spices such as turmeric and hot red pepper to my breakfast because I like them and because they seem to give me a little wake-up boost and stimulate alertness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The flax seeds are new, as well as the prune. The prune is probably not &amp;ldquo;paleo&amp;rdquo;, according to someone or other, but as I&amp;rsquo;ve mentioned before, I get confused by the different paleo schools of thought, and I don&amp;rsquo;t follow any of them, but just use them as practical sources of ideas for self-experimentation. I have a very specific rationale for the use of flax seeds and prunes: I have to confess that I dealt with constipation issues when initially moving away from my big oatmeal breakfast to my paleo-style breakfast. I tried various solutions, but one that seems to have worked is the addition of flax seeds (which I typically only add for breakfast, but sometimes will also do for another meal too) and the prune. I have had no constipation issues since adding these to my breakfast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;other-meals&#34;&gt;Other meals&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been trying to kick my &amp;ldquo;addiction&amp;rdquo; to rice. I have gradually decreased my consumption of rice (white or brown). Almost imperceptibly, my craving for it has decreased continually. It&amp;rsquo;s now been a couple of days since I have been doing without rice for lunch, but I am still eating it for dinner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still love pizza, and have not yet eliminated it. It&amp;rsquo;s very hard to avoid both convenience and temptation when it&amp;rsquo;s provided at talks and meetings. However, on days when I plan to eat pizza, I have tried to get my metabolism up before eating it. That seems to help. I&amp;rsquo;ll still keep in my mind the idea of giving up pizza.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My experimentation with diet have continued over the months, and will continue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope my report may be of use to you if you are considering changing up your breakfast patterns away from the &amp;ldquo;standard&amp;rdquo; American sugary breakfasts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do you eat for breakfast that works for you? What do you similarly or differently from me?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is brown rice healthy or not?</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/12/07/is-brown-rice-healthy-or-not/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Dec 2011 23:48:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/12/07/is-brown-rice-healthy-or-not/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been thinking for a year or two now about my relationship with rice, in conjunction with reading about &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/23/paleo-diet-experimentation/&#34;&gt;paleo diets&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;ve been eating rice, white or brown, for most of my life, and am now considering make some further changes to my diet (beyond &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/03/one-of-these-breakfasts-is-not-paleo/&#34;&gt;giving up oatmeal&lt;/a&gt; for an entire month now).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what now with rice?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;white-rice&#34;&gt;White rice&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was a kid, I ate white rice often, because it was something my mother provided for most meals. Actually, it was present for me at almost all meals, until I decided I wanted to eat, all the time, the sweet breakfast cereals I saw on TV.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I went off to college, I drastically changed my diet, being dependent on cafeteria food and also being tempted by opportunities to eat pizza and chicken wings and the like outside of the provided meals. I ate much less rice then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While in grad school at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cmu.edu/&#34;&gt;CMU&lt;/a&gt;, I got back into eating white rice, as a result of developing the habit of eating Indian food for lunch: I would buy lunch from either the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.tasteofindiapittsburgh.com/&#34;&gt;Taste of India&lt;/a&gt; present on campus or from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.srees.com/&#34;&gt;Sree&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/a&gt; food truck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;brown-rice-for-five-years&#34;&gt;Brown rice for five years&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For many years, I kept hearing that brown rice was healthier than white rice, and this advice was based on the idea that white rice has lost many of its nutrients and fiber during the refinement process. But I never ate brown rice because every time I tried making it, it came out unpalatable. Eventually I learned that I was making it wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2006, after hearing too often from a friend that white rice was &amp;ldquo;white death&amp;rdquo;, I took the plunge and bought a fancy Zojirushi Neuro Fuzzy rice cooker, to be able to make good brown rice as well as start eating steel cut oatmeal (which my friend also advocated eating). So it&amp;rsquo;s been over five years since I have been eating a lot of oatmeal (recently stopped) and brown rice (still going). And I have to confess that if one is going to eat steel cut oatmeal or brown rice, the Neuro Fuzzy cooker is the way to go, with its timer functions that make it trivial to generate really good results!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;paleo&#34;&gt;Paleo&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enter the paleo movement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started reading that maybe brown rice isn&amp;rsquo;t so healthy after all.  Sources such as &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.marksdailyapple.com/is-rice-unhealthy/&#34;&gt;Mark Sisson&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&#34;http://perfecthealthdiet.com/&#34;&gt;Jaminets&lt;/a&gt; argue that brown rice is harmful because of phytic acid that binds to nutrients and makes them inaccessible to us. I don&amp;rsquo;t know how true this is. But if it is true, it is worrying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sisson suggests soaking and fermenting brown rice. Having sort of tried this, I was disgusted by the results. Stephan Guyenet suggested a whole complicated-sounding protocol for &lt;a href=&#34;http://wholehealthsource.blogspot.com/2009/04/new-way-to-soak-brown-rice.html&#34;&gt;soaking brown rice&lt;/a&gt;. Looking at the comments gave me a headache.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-now&#34;&gt;What now?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what am I to do?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I eat brown rice in part to get fiber and in part to get (carb) calories. I have experimented with eating less brown rice lately, but am now considering doing an experiment in which I actually give it up for two weeks or so, to see how I feel. Giving up oatmeal has largely been a good thing for me; I rather enjoy eating a lot of veggies and more protein for breakfast. But getting rid of brown rice is much more radical.  Should I really go back to white rice?  I don&amp;rsquo;t know right now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2012-10-24&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-10-24)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Food Day in 2012, I wrote more about some &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/10/24/reflections-on-food-day/&#34;&gt;dilemmas with rice&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>One of these breakfasts is not paleo</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/11/03/one-of-these-breakfasts-is-not-paleo/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Nov 2011 22:33:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/11/03/one-of-these-breakfasts-is-not-paleo/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Over a week ago, I briefly discussed my plans to experiment more with a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/23/paleo-diet-experimentation/&#34;&gt;paleo-style diet&lt;/a&gt;. I decided to quit eating oatmeal for breakfast, cold turkey (no pun intended). I was going to stay off oatmeal for at least two weeks. Well, fourteen days of no oatmeal have gone by.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some photos of actual breakfasts I&amp;rsquo;ve had during these two weeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warning to the purists: one of these breakfasts is not paleo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/breakfast/2011-11-01-eggs-broccoli-walnuts.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Eggs, broccoli, walnuts&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/breakfast/2011-11-02-egg-lentil-soup.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Egg, lentil soup&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/breakfast/2011-11-03-eggs-broccoli-soup.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Eggs, broccoli, soup&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-three-breakfasts-depicted&#34;&gt;The three breakfasts depicted&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Two eggs, broccoli, walnuts, olive oil, spicy seasonings&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One egg, leftover &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/24/whats-a-nice-acorn-squash-like-you-doing-in-a-pot-of-spicy-lentils/&#34;&gt;lentil vegetable soup&lt;/a&gt; from freezer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Two eggs, broccoli, other leftover vegetable soup (exact contents unknown, since Abby made it)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also often use spinach in place of broccoli, and typically also eat a handful of nuts before anything else for breakfast, and take fish oil and vitamin D (the only supplements I take regularly).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;which-is-not-paleo&#34;&gt;Which is not paleo?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, the lentils are not paleo. However, Tim Ferriss &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.fourhourworkweek.com/blog/2010/09/19/paleo-diet-solution/&#34;&gt;eats them&lt;/a&gt;, and I like them and find them filling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;observations&#34;&gt;Observations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At first, I was having a lot of trouble maintaining my weight, because of a calorie deficit from skipping the carb and sugar heavy breakfast, and eating less pizza. I piled on more veggies through the day (mainly, eating more for breakfast and lunch) and have been eating more chicken and beef. I am still dependent on brown rice for lunch and dinner. I will try to formulate an experiment to reduce or eliminate that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My diet is still nowhere near paleo, because of the rice, some pizza cheating, and still eating a snack of a slice of rye bread with almond butter on most days. But the oatmeal is gone, and I don&amp;rsquo;t feel like going back. The protein/fat/veggie loaded breakfast makes me feel so much better. I am more alert from it, and when I exercise before lunch, I believe that I am more effective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m considering swapping out some of the rice in favor of lentils, for the fiber and protein. Of the legumes, I find lentils most filling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;controversy-over-paleo-and-the-nature-of-belief&#34;&gt;Controversy over paleo, and the nature of belief&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, a criticism of the paleo diet has been going around on the Web. It was offered by the anthropologist &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.npr.org/blogs/13.7/2011/10/27/141666659/the-paleo-diet-not-the-way-to-a-healthy-future&#34;&gt;Barbara J. King&lt;/a&gt;. She loves animals, is mostly vegetarian, and is concerned about factory farming and the environment. As an ex-vegetarian, certainly I share many of her concerns, and Abby and I go organic and local with our food choices (whether meat or anything else).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I think King weakens her voice by combining completely independent issues within one critique: one issue is purely scientific (what kind of diet is best for human health, and for which humans), and the others are ethical or philosophical or political. I think all the different issues should be analyzed and debated separately, then the interactions addressed. For example, what if a paleo-style diet is better for health for a substantial part of the population, and yet the demand for it creates pressure on food production? Then some kind of trade-off would need to be discussed. Or what if people moving to paleo results in fewer people eating processed food, sugar, and other products of entire industries that are arguably not beneficial to either people&amp;rsquo;s health or the environment?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a lot of &amp;ldquo;what ifs&amp;rdquo;. I believe King basically loves animals and would prefer to eliminate their use as food, globally. And that&amp;rsquo;s fine: I respect the views of ethical vegetarians, the way I respect Christians and Hindus and others who have some fundamental beliefs not to be questioned. But I think that if one starts with a fixed assumption that colors everything else in one&amp;rsquo;s life, one has to realize that one has weakened one&amp;rsquo;s ability to ask unpleasant questions that might have an undesirable answer. For example, someone who believes an embryo is a sacred life form has any moral choice other than to find every possible bit of argumentation against abortion, regardless of many questions surrounding it that lie outside the scope of the fetus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, I&amp;rsquo;m sure a lot of paleo fans simply love eating meat, and now have a  ideology suitable for rationalizing what they want to hear. From what I can tell, there&amp;rsquo;s also some intersection between paleo and certain political orientations as well. All this is very interesting to me as an observer of humanity, but for myself, I just want to know what&amp;rsquo;s true, what works (for many definitions of &amp;ldquo;works&amp;rdquo;), and have little patience for ideology. I want to know the answers, even if they call into question things I currently believe. In fact, I get excited when I&amp;rsquo;m wrong, because that means I&amp;rsquo;m alive and learning; since I don&amp;rsquo;t accept that by age 30, I&amp;rsquo;d already learned all the answers, I&amp;rsquo;d be pretty disappointed if every year since then I didn&amp;rsquo;t find something that I was wrong about and needed to correct!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Every day is Food Day</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/10/24/every-day-is-food-day/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Oct 2011 21:26:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/10/24/every-day-is-food-day/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I found out only yesterday that today is &lt;a href=&#34;http://foodday.org/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Food Day&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I &lt;a href=&#34;http://foodday.org/about-food-day/&#34;&gt;looked up&lt;/a&gt; what it&amp;rsquo;s all about and it seems that October 24 has been designated &lt;em&gt;Food Day&lt;/em&gt;, sponsored by the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cspinet.org/&#34;&gt;Center for Science in the Public Interest&lt;/a&gt;, a nonprofit watchdog group. I looked further, and saw that the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Center_for_Science_in_the_Public_Interest&#34;&gt;Wikipedia entry&lt;/a&gt; is informative, noting controversies concerning the group, especially the vocal opposition from the restaurant, food, and tobacco industries, but from other sources also, including former CSPI members.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anything concerning food policy in this country is, well, political.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not here today to talk about the politics of food (I recommend &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.foodpolitics.com/&#34;&gt;Marion Nestle&lt;/a&gt; as one sober source about it), but about my personal relationship with food. Once upon a time, I knew very little about food, cared little about it, and rarely prepared it myself. But then things changed, and every day became Food Day for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;before-awareness&#34;&gt;Before awareness&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As late as graduate school, I was still eating random junk, and not really cooking for myself. White bread, processed lunch meats. Frozen dinners. Commercial cereal for breakfast, pizza, Chinese take-out. Potato chips, cookies, candy bars. Canned soups. Frozen chicken wings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not much variety, and not very good for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had never once thought about where my food came from, what was in it, and whether it was any good. I just assumed that name-brand tasty goodies at the grocery store must be OK. Food was an impersonal &amp;ldquo;fuel&amp;rdquo; and a source of instant gratification.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-vegetarian-phase&#34;&gt;My vegetarian phase&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Around 1999, I don&amp;rsquo;t remember exactly how it happened (although being around some female grad students who were vegetarian probably had something to do with it), I started learning about food production. In particular, I came across polemical books about the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Prisoned-Chickens-Poisoned-Eggs-Industry/dp/1570670323&#34;&gt;poultry industry&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/MAD-COWBOY-Plain-Cattle-Rancher/dp/0684854465&#34;&gt;meat industry&lt;/a&gt;. These and similar sources of information exposing the conditions of factory farming, the health hazards of the system, and the environmental impact, led me to actually become a vegetarian.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I became a zealous convert to vegetarianism, went to a local &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.vegetariansummerfest.org/&#34;&gt;vegetarian conference&lt;/a&gt;, and even returned a vegan! That lasted only three months. In the end, my vegetarianism lasted only a year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Why I ended vegetarianism, and how I feel about vegetarianism as an idealized diet or societal arrangement, may be the topic for a future blog post.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;lasting-changes&#34;&gt;Lasting changes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, regardless of how my thinking has evolved since my vegetarian days, many side effects still remain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did learn a lot of facts about food production and health (amid stronger vegetarian claims that I do not accept today). This was stuff that surely everyone should learn as a child in school.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was forced to really cook for myself, especially during my vegan phase, which made it much, much harder to eat out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result, my relationship with food was radically transformed. It became one of the centers of my life, rather than something peripheral. After all, I was cooking something almost every other day. And much of it was from the bulk section of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.eastendfood.coop/&#34;&gt;East End Food Co-op&lt;/a&gt;: various rices, chickpeas, lentils, red kidney beans, black beans, you name it. A whole lot of variety to choose from. I got a pressure cooker, a rice cooker, a slower cooker, an immersion blender, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I had spent most of my life up till then in purely intellectual, theoretical pursuits, it was really new to be getting down and dirty physically with raw ingredients and turning them into something. I felt more in touch with my body, and grateful for living in a land of plenty, never needing to go hungry. I enjoyed exploring many new flavors, ethnic cuisines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This all happened in conjunction with other life changes, such as taking up &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/running/&#34;&gt;running&lt;/a&gt; and dancing and losing thirty pounds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once upon a time, food really was the center of human life: you spent much of the day doing what you could to eat something so you could stay alive! In the developed world, we&amp;rsquo;ve removed a lot of the drudgery and uncertainty of finding something to eat (even half a century ago, women had to spend huge amounts of time on feeding their families), and that can&amp;rsquo;t be a bad thing, but we&amp;rsquo;ve also lost touch with our biological, animal natures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not advocating that everyone should spend huge amounts of time on food preparation, but I think that if everyone were simply more aware of the chain of what happens to feed us, and were mindful and grateful when eating anything, the world would be a better place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether Abby is doing the cooking or I am doing the cooking, I remember my mortality and the impermanence of all living things that gave rise to my meal, and consider each day of my life a gift.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, every day is Food Day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;postscript&#34;&gt;Postscript&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A blog post about Food Day is probably not complete with at least some photo and recipe of something recently prepared or eaten, so here is my &lt;em&gt;chicken curry with cauliflower&lt;/em&gt;, based on the recipe in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.notyourmotherscookbook.com/not-your-mothers-slow-cooker-cookbook/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Not Your Mother&amp;rsquo;s Slow Cooker Cookbook&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The photo is not glamorous, but it is a real photo of real food, simple and tasty.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/chicken-curry-cauliflower.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Chicken curry with cauliflower&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Prep time:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;15 minutes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Equipment:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;medium-sized Crock Pot&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;set it on high for 3 hours (original recipe called for low for longer)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ingredients:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2 pounds boneless, skinless chicken thighs (I find thighs are better than breasts, which tend to dry out)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3 tablespoons extra virgin olive oil&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2 medium onions, chopped coarsely&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2 gloves garlic, minced&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1.5 teaspoons ground coriander&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 teaspoon turmeric&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 teaspoon ground cumin (I also tossed in cumin seeds)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 tablespoon ground ginger (was in a hurry, didn&amp;rsquo;t use fresh)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2 teaspoons paprika&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;0.5 teaspoon red chile pepper flakes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;0.5 teaspoon mustard seeds&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;one can of diced tomatoes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;juice of half lemon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 head cauliflower (florets and stems)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;salt&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Procedure:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some olive oil into slow cooker to coat the bottom.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chop up the chicken thighs, not too finely, and brown in skillet with olive oil for a few minutes, remove.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Into the same skillet, cook onions for a few minutes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add the rest of the dry ingredients to the skillet, continue cooking the mixture for a couple of minutes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add the wet ingredients (tomatoes, lemon juice) to the skillet, mix everything up.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Put the chicken into the slow cooker.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scrape the skillet&amp;rsquo;s contents into the slow cooker.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mix stuff up in the slow cooker.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cook for 3 hours.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When done, add salt to taste.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2012-10-24&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-10-24)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Food Day, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/10/24/reflections-on-food-day/&#34;&gt;a year later&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Paleo diet experimentation</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/10/23/paleo-diet-experimentation/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Oct 2011 23:59:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/10/23/paleo-diet-experimentation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Three days ago, I stopped eating my usual breakfast: &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steel-cut_oats&#34;&gt;steel-cut oatmeal&lt;/a&gt; topped with fruit and nuts and maple syrup. I&amp;rsquo;d been eating oatmeal almost every day for breakfast for about 15 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the beginning of a gradual experiment toward more of a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paleolithic_diet&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Paleo diet&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is this &amp;ldquo;Paleo diet&amp;rdquo;, and why am I doing it, and why now, and how?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-s-a-paleo-diet&#34;&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s a Paleo diet?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I first heard of the &amp;ldquo;Paleo diet&amp;rdquo; an entire decade ago, back in 2002, from the &lt;a href=&#34;http://thepaleodiet.com/&#34;&gt;book&lt;/a&gt; of that name by Loren Cordain. The concept is much more popular now, with very passionate communities revolving around it, than it was then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The basic idea is simple: that our hunter-gatherer ancestors were healthy and that the Neolithic era, in which agriculture altered our diet (and our lifestyle) was the end of true human health. OK, I&amp;rsquo;m exaggerating, but that&amp;rsquo;s the idea in a nutshell: that we suffer from &amp;ldquo;diseases of civilization&amp;rdquo; because of eating stuff that we are not really evolutionarily adapted to, such as grains, beans, sugar, dairy, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not going to enter the debates over the evidence or the ideological tinges, because I&amp;rsquo;m never a &amp;ldquo;true believer&amp;rdquo; in anything anyway, and am an opportunist: I like to use interesting ideas and test whether they work for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-did-i-do-in-2002&#34;&gt;What did I do in 2002?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2002, I was still not very far removed from my one-year vegetarian experiment in 1999 (which included a couple of months of veganism). I was in drastically better health and fitness than prior to 1999, having lost 30 pounds, but knew that I could not simply chalk it up to my mostly-vegetarian diet. The fact that I was not eating junk food and processed food and crappy take-out, and had finally learned to really cook most meals for myself, clearly made a difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I was still having blood sugar issues, which I attributed to heavy consumption of refined carbs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found it hard to buy Cordain&amp;rsquo;s ideas completely. Speculation based on evolutionary &amp;ldquo;just so&amp;rdquo; stories has a long history, after all. Still, they were interesting ideas. I did find some better carbs for myself, e.g., losing the white rice and bread, going to brown rice, going to whole wheat bread, and eventually even getting away from whole wheat bread to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.foodforlife.com/&#34;&gt;Ezekiel sprouted grain bread&lt;/a&gt;. This was all based on self-experimentation, of course, not ideology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also eventually switched from old-fashioned oats to steel-cut oats, once I got a rice cooker with a timer and multiple settings that could make my steel-cut oatmeal for me every morning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Around 2007, finding out that I was definitely allergic to soy changed aspects of my diet also, since I had depended a lot on &amp;ldquo;vegetarian&amp;rdquo; type food that involved soy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In no way was I eating paleo yet, however. It just seemed too radical a change from my routine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-am-i-trying-this-now&#34;&gt;Why am I trying this now?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A year ago, the paleo diet came to my attention again in a big way, thanks to Tim Ferriss&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.fourhourworkweek.com/blog/2010/09/19/paleo-diet-solution/&#34;&gt;blog post about it&lt;/a&gt;. So I started thinking about it again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, I&amp;rsquo;d come across books such as &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.newtrendspublishing.com/SallyFallon/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nourishing Traditions&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; by Sally Fallon from the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.westonaprice.org/&#34;&gt;Weston A. Price Foundation&lt;/a&gt; that had their own take on &amp;ldquo;traditional&amp;rdquo; diets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in March 2011, Abby and I attended &lt;a href=&#34;http://farmtotablepa.com/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Farm to Table&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, a local conference that happened to be dominated by Weston A. Price people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby experimented with reducing her own consumption of cereals and breads and noticed some real benefits for herself. She actually has gone more paleo and more quickly than I have, so I have to confess that this makes it easier for me to also do my experiments, such that we&amp;rsquo;re not having major food incompatibilities eating together! For example, she gave up oatmeal almost entirely months ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;oatmeal&#34;&gt;Oatmeal&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I&amp;rsquo;ve been eating oatmeal so long, phasing it out for at least two weeks (my plan) will surely tell me something interesting about what it does to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still remember when I was having health problems in college and it took months to figure out, only by accident, that all that had happened was that I had become lactose intolerant, and so my eating Cheerios with milk every morning was causing me problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So self-experimentation is a great way to figure oneself out. Books and experts can&amp;rsquo;t do that for you. They can only give hints and possibilities. We are all different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;changes-so-far&#34;&gt;Changes so far&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, I&amp;rsquo;m not going all-out paleo (according to whatever school of thought on paleo: there are quite a lot of different interpretations of what is permitted or forbidden, as with any other &amp;ldquo;movement&amp;rdquo;). I still find it hard to believe that I should really be banning a whole lot of food I am used to eating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m starting with small but real experiments, to see what happens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, it is easy to get rid of oatmeal. I&amp;rsquo;ve already gone three days just fine. Instead, I eat an egg or two with a bowl of veggies (I especially like broccoli) and some nuts and olive oil and spices. I believe I already detect a much more stable morning energy level as a result.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a habit of eating too much pizza, as a result of going to seminars where pizza is inevitably served. Maybe I&amp;rsquo;ll pick off toppings and skip the bread, but I admit that sounds kind of unappetizing and weird.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, I have been eating brown rice for years, so it&amp;rsquo;s kind of hard for me to just give it up entirely. I&amp;rsquo;ll plan to reduce it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make up for the lost carbs, I expect to eat more vegetables and meat than in the past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;side-effects-so-far&#34;&gt;Side effects so far&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rapid loss of weight. I &lt;em&gt;do not&lt;/em&gt; want this! I am already light. I want to gain strength and vitality, not lose weight. I&amp;rsquo;m near the height and weight of Bruce Lee. What I&amp;rsquo;d like is more muscle, not lost weight. So I need to eat more fat to make up the caloric deficit of losing oatmeal.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>