<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Mandolin on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/mandolin/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Mandolin on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/mandolin/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>An erhu player and a tuba player at a party said &#34;Let&#39;s jam&#34;</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/09/28/an-erhu-player-and-a-tuba-player-at-a-party-said-lets-jam/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Sep 2013 22:02:19 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/09/28/an-erhu-player-and-a-tuba-player-at-a-party-said-lets-jam/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I attended a music potluck party tonight. We had been unsure about whether to attend, since I do have the Great Race 10K to run tomorrow and need to avoid staying up too late. So we went with the understanding that we would leave early as needed, in order for me to wind down at home and go to bed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;food&#34;&gt;Food&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I whipped up a large batch of roasted vegetables to bring to the potluck:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/vegetables-2013-09-28.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Roasted vegetables&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;music&#34;&gt;Music&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a lot of eating and chatting, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.appalasia.com/Mimi.htm&#34;&gt;Mimi&lt;/a&gt; was ready to start jamming, and got out her &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Erhu&#34;&gt;erhu&lt;/a&gt;. A guy who had brought a tuba was ready to play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OK, who else was in?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I pulled out my flute. Abby took out her mandolin. It seemed like nobody else (yet) was interested in joining in. (But as we know, the party usually really gets going later in the evening when musicians are involved.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tuba player seemed really into jazz. He asked for requests and started his own rhythmic bass sometimes. I tried to join in with him and Mimi as they led the way. It was pretty hard for me, and frightening, but I did what I could to contribute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At one point, I volunteered to sing and play &amp;ldquo;Has Anybody Seen My Gal?&amp;rdquo; on ukulele, which I did (for the first time by myself outside home), and they followed along. I don&amp;rsquo;t know if that was the first time an erhu, tuba, and ukulele were in action simultaneously!?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;lending-my-flute-out&#34;&gt;Lending my flute out&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point, a guy arrived at the party who wanted to jam. He hadn&amp;rsquo;t yet brought in his trombone, but asked if he could borrow my flute. I recognized him from previous parties, and I had seen him play flute in at least one of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So he borrowed my flute and I sat back and watched and listened. He was a really good improviser. Actually, at the suggestion of the tuba player, who really liked totally free improvisation, the three of them did something I found amazing and beautiful. Starting with some long tones, they created an eerie sonic soundscape together, listening to one another while blending the erhu, tuba, and flute. I was really moved by this display of musicality and feeling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;leaving-early&#34;&gt;Leaving early&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby noted that it was getting &amp;ldquo;late&amp;rdquo; for us, and so we regrettably had to leave. Guests were still coming in and bringing food, even though those of us who had arrived early had filled our stomachs long ago. I got my flute back and packed up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is always a special treat for me when I get to hang around creative, accomplished musicians and get to see them make music spontaneously. I&amp;rsquo;m usually too intimidated in these kinds of situations to join in, but I did briefly tonight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-11-06&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-11-06)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was surprised and saddened to learn from Mimi that just a couple of days ago, the man who had borrowed my flute and played so beautifully, David Olson, &lt;a href=&#34;http://obituaries.triblive.com/listing/231895/David-E-Olson/&#34;&gt;died&lt;/a&gt;. Even in the brief time that I interacted with him at all, just in a handful of music parties, I was struck by his enthusiasm, humor, and graciousness. It is hard to believe that he is gone now, just a month since he was playing my flute. RIP, David.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pittsburgh Contras and Squares Holiday Ball 2012</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/12/14/pittsburgh-contras-and-squares-holiday-ball-2012/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Dec 2012 23:50:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/12/14/pittsburgh-contras-and-squares-holiday-ball-2012/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/holiday-ball-2012/grand-march.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Grand March&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So this year I joined Abby again to play in the &amp;ldquo;Holiday Ball Orchestra&amp;rdquo; as I had &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/16/playing-recorder-and-flute-at-the-holiday-ball/&#34;&gt;done for the first time last year&lt;/a&gt;, for the annual &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/pages/Pittsburgh-Holiday-Ball/283731778337030&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Contras and Squares Holiday Ball&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My experience at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/events/383908395031216/&#34;&gt;this year&amp;rsquo;s event&lt;/a&gt; compared to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/events/308706299154491/&#34;&gt;last year&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/a&gt;, and thoughts about the future:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;preparation&#34;&gt;Preparation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, I was much more &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/11/24/preparing-to-play-irish-flute-in-the-holiday-ball/&#34;&gt;prepared&lt;/a&gt; this second time than the first time. Not only have I been playing any music at all for an entire extra year, but also, I had prior knowledge of and access to most of the music that is played every year, so I could start my practice well before the event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;costumes&#34;&gt;Costumes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby wanted me to dress up again. Since people enjoyed my wearing red pants last year, I wore them again this year. I was tired of the whole green thing, however, and so I wore a pink shirt and red vest to go all out on the red theme. I added a sport jacket also, one that had been too big for me my whole life till now; it turns out that my blazer that I wore last year is too small now, as my chest has noticeably expanded in the past year (probably because of weight lifting, posture changes, and playing wind instruments). I added a beret that I&amp;rsquo;d never worn before.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/holiday-ball-2012/franklin.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Abby came up with her own colorful outfit.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/holiday-ball-2012/abby-octave-mandolin.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;venue&#34;&gt;Venue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was afraid that Swisshelm Park Community Center would be super cold again like last year, but I did bring my Handeze fingerless gloves just in case. It turned out that the place was warm (it&amp;rsquo;s been a very warm &amp;ldquo;winter&amp;rdquo;), and so I did not have any problems feeling cold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;on-stage&#34;&gt;On stage&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year I think there were somewhat fewer musicians in the Holiday Ball Orchestra than last year. I thought this was actually a good thing. Last year there were some real problems with space and also with ensemble balance (there were a whole lot of violins last year, for example).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;instruments&#34;&gt;Instruments&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I brought my modern flute, wooden keyless Irish flute, and tin whistle. Last year I had played primarily recorder, but this year I chose not to play recorder at all: the Irish flute was what I wanted to use as much as possible for this music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also brought my melodica! I had practiced playing the Hallelujah Chorus part of the Grand March using it and was excited to make my melodica debut. I also planned to use it in some of the Christmas songs, such as &amp;ldquo;Frosty the Snowman&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby brought an &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Octave_mandolin&#34;&gt;octave mandolin&lt;/a&gt; she had been borrowing. She started playing mandolin just this year, and octave mandolin just in the past couple of weeks, I think. This instrument is so much better suited to the music, she says, than her tamburitza she played last year.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/holiday-ball-2012/instruments.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Our instruments&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Several &amp;ldquo;kazumpets&amp;rdquo; (kazoo trumpets) were also provided by Lynette and Jim, and passed out to whoever wanted to play them during certain songs. Abby took one.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/holiday-ball-2012/abby-kazumpet.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby with kazumpet&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;dancing&#34;&gt;Dancing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since Abby and I have now actually done some &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/10/07/my-first-contra-dance-workshop-unexpected-fun/&#34;&gt;contra dancing together&lt;/a&gt;, there was a question of whether we would do any dancing. Abby and I discussed this before the event; Abby was very excited to play music on octave mandolin, and so she did not want to dance, so we did no dancing. Like I said last year: &amp;ldquo;We can always dance some other time.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the other musicians were very excited about dancing and pre-arranged to spend one half or the other of the time dancing instead of playing music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I saw a lot of familiar faces among the dancers, thanks to having met some of them when doing French and contra dances at CMU, and others I met from non-dance contexts elsewhere in the past year in Pittsburgh. It was nice to see my friend Henry and his girlfriend Gina at the dance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;off-and-running&#34;&gt;Off and running&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marlin was the caller again as usual and the evening proceeded with the Grand March and then the whole big assortment of jigs, reels, waltzes, Christmas songs, and a couple of interesting new pieces for this year.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/holiday-ball-2012/grand-march.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Grand March&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t have additional interesting photos or videos to share from during the event, because I took none: after the initial Grand March, I was entirely focused just on playing music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;overall-experience&#34;&gt;Overall experience&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was far less nervous than I was last year. Also, I positioned myself near, rather than deliberately far away from, a microphone, in order to be more audible. I don&amp;rsquo;t actually know what I sounded like, but some dancers during intermission commented that they liked the sound of the wooden Irish flute, so I guess it must have been audible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Playing music for hours is tiring, especially when it is so fast and there are so many notes. Of course, nobody is required to play all the notes all the time. I picked and chose when to take breaks, typically alternating repeats or entire sections. And there is definitely a limit to how long I can play flutes before my mouth gives up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the second half, a guy who had danced during the first half played a keyed Irish flute and tin whistle with us. I hadn&amp;rsquo;t seen him at the two of three rehearsals I had attended, so I hadn&amp;rsquo;t known someone else would be playing those instruments. As a result, I changed some things up in the second half, by playing the tin whistle sometimes when he was playing the flute, and vice versa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did play the melodica as planned, but noticed that the intonation was poor in the lower notes, so I backed off. I&amp;rsquo;ll have to fix this problem before I do more melodica playing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I chose not to force myself to &amp;ldquo;achieve&amp;rdquo; some of the &amp;ldquo;goals&amp;rdquo; I set last year, which were to do some solos and nontrivial ornamentation/improvisation. I felt that because of the natural of my musical focus all this year, I hadn&amp;rsquo;t had time to devote to getting good enough to really justify taking the spotlight for some tunes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The music is still crazy fast: I am still not able to play everything quite properly at the appropriate tempo. Frustrating, but that&amp;rsquo;s OK. I expect to continue to improve my technique; I&amp;rsquo;m already so much better than I was last year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I very much enjoyed performing for the Holiday Ball this year. And I feel like the Holiday Ball Orchestra sounded better this year than we did last year, and some dancers remarked on this also. I think there are several reasons for this. One is that we had some people coming back for the second time (like me), much improved. Another is that there were slightly fewer people, which I think creates a tighter ensemble.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;goals-for-the-future&#34;&gt;Goals for the future&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right now, I&amp;rsquo;m just totally exhausted and happy to be done with music performance of any kind this year. It&amp;rsquo;s been a very tough week, a very tough month, and a very tough two months in my life, with all the things that piled up on me since the end of October.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because December always ends up being so frantic for me, for next year I need to better plan what activities I pursue during this time of year. Last year, I was totally set on playing again this year in the Holiday Ball. Now, I am not sure whether I will continue for next year. It&amp;rsquo;s a question of priorities, and I need to plan what I will be doing next year in December. If I do it again next year, then clearly I want to be doing some solos!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;thank-yous&#34;&gt;Thank yous&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, I have to thank Lynette for organizing the music scores and putting it into booklets for everyone. Jim made the kazumpets. Donna, Allison, and Maro led the rehearsals as well as conducted and played their instruments with enthusiasm; I&amp;rsquo;ve been really happy to have met them a year ago, because I&amp;rsquo;ve been encountering them in other musical contexts in Pittsburgh in the past year too!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We play for the dancers, and so I really appreciate it when they take note of our playing and respond to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And none of this would happened without Abby, who got me into the whole scene in the first place. I&amp;rsquo;ve met so many musicians and dancers, and tried out different instruments and musical styles and dances in the past year, thanks to Abby!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Singing and playing bossa nova favorite &#34;Chega de Saudade&#34; at Dunkin&#39; Donuts for J-Jam</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/10/28/singing-and-playing-bossa-nova-favorite-chega-de-saudade-at-dunkin-donuts-for-j-jam/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Oct 2012 00:54:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/10/28/singing-and-playing-bossa-nova-favorite-chega-de-saudade-at-dunkin-donuts-for-j-jam/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/j-jam-2012-10-28/5.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;CMU Klezmer Band performing&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Yesterday evening, I ended up unexpectedly &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/10/27/singing-an-irish-ballad-as-an-asian-pirate-at-a-halloween-belly-dance-hafla/&#34;&gt;singing alone in public for the first time in my life&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This evening, I ended up unexpectedly singing again, with guitarist &lt;a href=&#34;http://cantorben.com/&#34;&gt;Cantor Ben Rosner&lt;/a&gt; accompanying me: the first time in my life singing with an accompanist for the general public, and the first time I&amp;rsquo;ve worked with a guitarist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had just met for the first time this evening, and had only a minute ahead of time to agree on a suitable tempo and have him quickly sight read chords before we just launched into the music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had not come to the local Dunkin&amp;rsquo; Donuts in Squirrel Hill expecting to &lt;em&gt;sing&lt;/em&gt; at all, actually! What happened?!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-story-behind-the-jam-session-at-dunkin-donuts&#34;&gt;The story behind the jam session at Dunkin&amp;rsquo; Donuts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby had recently just met a new guy playing in the [Pittsburgh Mandolin Orchestra], &lt;a href=&#34;http://cantorben.wix.com/cantor-benjamin-rosner&#34;&gt;Cantor Ben Rosner&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bethshalompgh.org/&#34;&gt;Congregation Beth Shalom&lt;/a&gt; in Squirrel Hill. He was passing out flyers advertising a music jam session he was organizing, &amp;ldquo;J-Jam&amp;rdquo;, to be held tonight in the local Dunkin&amp;rsquo; Donuts, which happens to be &lt;a href=&#34;http://triblive.com/home/1926901-74/hill-squirrel-dunkin-donuts-kosher-pittsburgh-says-area-jewish-restaurant&#34;&gt;the only Dunkin&amp;rsquo; Donuts in the area that is certified kosher&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apparently this was not the first &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.thejewishchronicle.net/view/full_story/19127215/article-Open-mic-night-draws-Jewish-performers-to-Dunkin%E2%80%99-Donuts?instance=news_special_coverage_right_column&#34;&gt;Jewish community oriented music jam held at Dunkin&amp;rsquo; Donuts&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-01-16&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-01-16)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;J-Jam now has its own &lt;a href=&#34;http://jjampgh.webs.com/&#34;&gt;official Web site&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.facebook.com/jjamPGH&#34;&gt;Facebook page&lt;/a&gt;. Check them out!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;deciding-to-participate&#34;&gt;Deciding to participate&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I hear about music jams, I get excited as well as nervous. I always feel that I wish I were a much better musician than I am now, so that I don&amp;rsquo;t always feel that I&amp;rsquo;m the &lt;em&gt;worst&lt;/em&gt; one at these events, but at the same time, I learn so much from just being out there, both to enjoy hearing other musicians, and to study how they do what they do, and in turn try to provide something of my own soul to other musicians and the audience as well. It&amp;rsquo;s like being naked; it&amp;rsquo;s still really tough for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I was intrigued because, well, Dunkin&amp;rsquo; Donuts should be pretty low key, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had spread the word to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.andrew.cmu.edu/user/lukas/pcars/Welcome.html&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Recorder Society&lt;/a&gt; mailing list, but nobody seemed up for participating, except Chuck said he was interested in coming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;preparation&#34;&gt;Preparation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had no time whatsoever to &amp;ldquo;prepare&amp;rdquo; for this music jam. We exchanged some emails only earlier today, in which I mentioned some music I might play, if a suitable accompanist were available. These emails were exchanged as Abby and I were at the second day of &lt;a href=&#34;http://podcamppittsburgh.com/pcpgh-7-sessions-sunday/&#34;&gt;PodCamp Pittsburgh 7&lt;/a&gt; all day. When we came home from PodCamp Pittsburgh, all we could do was crash with a long nap, eat dinner, and frantically pack up our instruments. I brought along a little binder of stuff I might play. I had told Ben that I could play stuff like Baroque flute sonata movements or bossa nova or tango or Cuban bolero.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby has been performing in music groups longer than I have, so she has her own selections at hand for her tamburas whenever desired.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;at-j-jam&#34;&gt;At J-Jam&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dunkin&amp;rsquo; Donuts was amazingly crowded. There were people of all ages, from toddlers to the elderly, sitting around listening to the live music and enjoying kosher food. It was pretty loud in there. I immediately decided that I would not play Baroque flute here. (I had brought it along with my Irish flute, modern flute, and soprano and alto recorders.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since we had arrived an hour and a half past the begin time of the music jam, we had missed no shortage of performances already, I was sure. There were musicians singing and playing guitar and cello; I saw who I presumed to be Ben Rosner accompanying on mandolin at the time:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/j-jam-2012-10-28/1.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Musicians in the middle of performing&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;meeting-ben-and-deciding-what-to-do&#34;&gt;Meeting Ben and deciding what to do&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/j-jam-2012-10-28/2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Patrons in Dunkin&amp;#39; Donuts&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;After the current musicians&amp;rsquo; set, Ben came up to Abby and me, and said we could play after a couple more groups had their turn. He asked what I wanted to play. We took a few seconds to flip through that stuff I had brought, and decided to play one of the bossa nova songs I had brought, &amp;ldquo;Chega de Saudade&amp;rdquo;: he would sight read the chords and accompany me. I chose &amp;ldquo;Chega de Saudade&amp;rdquo; because I had given a shot at it spontaneously &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/21/my-first-time-singing-bossa-nova-also-a-temporary-farewell-to-baroque-flute/&#34;&gt;at a party a month ago&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I immediately made an interesting decision: although I had originally intended to play the melody on flute, and then launch into a jazzy improvisation before concluding, I decided, based on having just &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/10/27/singing-an-irish-ballad-as-an-asian-pirate-at-a-halloween-belly-dance-hafla/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;sung&lt;/em&gt; yesterday as a pirate&lt;/a&gt;, that I was in the mood to sing, and a lot of people had been singing all evening, so I wanted to do that too. And it seemed that a voice would carry well over the conversations of the Dunkin&amp;rsquo; Donuts patrons. So I would sing the song, in Portuguese of course, and then switch into flute improvisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;a-lot-of-good-music-i-heard&#34;&gt;A lot of good music I heard&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was really impressed by the soulful performances of everyone who showed up to sing and play instruments. Really high quality stuff.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/j-jam-2012-10-28/3.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;I-forgot-her-name&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So I heard a lot of traditional songs and Klezmer (in fact, the &lt;a href=&#34;http://cmuklezmer.weebly.com/index.html&#34;&gt;CMU Klezmer Band&lt;/a&gt; was there). Not what I usually listen to or encounter, but it was really great soaking in the different kinds of music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When one of the CMU Klezmer Band guys, the clarinetist, passed out lyrics to a particularly popular song, I even sang along, stumbling through Yiddish for the first time in my life!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/j-jam-2012-10-28/4.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;CMU Klezmer Band waiting for turn&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.boulevardoftheallies.com/&#34;&gt;Joel&lt;/a&gt;, the J-Jam co-organizer who was handling the sound system throughout, performed one of his own compositions, and then one of his young guitar students performed along with him.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/j-jam-2012-10-28/7.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Joel and student&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;familiar-faces&#34;&gt;Familiar faces&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I saw a number of familiar people. In Pittsburgh, if you meet someone for the first time, it seems that there are already a lot of connections through other people you already know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Roz, whom &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/24/roaring-like-a-lion-on-a-saturday-morning/&#34;&gt;I last saw over a year ago when she was trying to sell accordions&lt;/a&gt; did some singing with the CMU Klezmer Band.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://betterfly.com/75586018&#34;&gt;Cindy Harris&lt;/a&gt;, who played autoharp so beautifully at &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/28/another-french-music-jam-also-announcing-cats-dance/&#34;&gt;one of the French music jams I&amp;rsquo;ve gone to&lt;/a&gt; did some solo pieces on autoharp:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/j-jam-2012-10-28/8.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Cindy Harris on autoharp&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At some point, Chuck from Pittsburgh recorder showed up. He wasn&amp;rsquo;t here to play, but came to watch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;abby-played-while-ben-and-i-figured-stuff-out&#34;&gt;Abby played while Ben and I figured stuff out&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Abby took her turn playing some pieces solo on tambura, Ben and I ducked to the back of the store for a minute so that we could agree on a tempo as well as have him sight read the chord progressions of &amp;ldquo;Chega de Saudade&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;ben-and-me&#34;&gt;Ben and me&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ben and I returned, and set up quickly (we were the last set for the night other than a guy who was going to play some solo violin to close).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I felt pretty awkward trying to sing &amp;ldquo;Chega de Saudade&amp;rdquo; for the first time in public, and in front of a microphone, while trying to read the Portuguese lyrics off a printout I had. (Note to self: I need to memorize these lyrics once and for all.) Ben and I had a go at it, and of course we made some mistakes, but that was expected. Then came time for me to grab my flute and improvise. Under pressure, I was less creative and accurate than I am when just improvising at home, unfortunately, but I&amp;rsquo;ll learn in time to deal with the difference in setting. Also, I botched up a place to return to, so there was confusion for a moment as Ben and I found a way to gracefully end somewhere!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;just-me&#34;&gt;Just me&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided to play one more piece, solo, that I thought I would do a lot better than the bossa nova experiment, so I got my Irish flute and chose spontaneously, while flipping through my binder, to play &amp;ldquo;Waltz in the House&amp;rdquo; by Emile Benoit. I love this beautiful song, and learned it half a year ago at my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/04/21/my-first-time-in-a-public-music-jam-intense-fun-with-chris-norman-and-david-greenberg/&#34;&gt;first public jam session&lt;/a&gt;, when I was playing on Baroque flute at the time. But of course, tonight I chose to play it on Irish flute, and I played it with the best feeling and sonority I had in me, having played it for my own pleasure and for my baby nephew many times, always with the inflections and ornamentations I feel at the moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People seemed to like this last piece I played. I also got a lot of comments afterwards on the beauty of the tone of my &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.caseyburnsflutes.com/&#34;&gt;wooden Irish flute&lt;/a&gt;; yes, it is a lovely instrument.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-next-j-jam&#34;&gt;The next J-Jam&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next J-Jam is already scheduled for Sunday, December 16. I hope Ben and I can come up with good stuff to play together, and with more preparation!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you love music and can make it to J-Jam, please come on over to Dunkin&amp;rsquo; Donuts in Squirrel Hill then! And if you would like to perform something, email Cantor Ben Rosner at the email address in the flyer below:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/j-jam-2012-10-28/flyer-for-2012-12-16.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Flyer for J-Jam 2012-12-16&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;next&#34;&gt;Next?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m still rather unsatisfied with my singing. I&amp;rsquo;m going to work hard on getting my singing into better shape. The next music jam I&amp;rsquo;m in, I absolutely plan to be ready to sing much better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for the jazz improvisation, that&amp;rsquo;s going to take me even longer to get to where I want it. That&amp;rsquo;s going to be a major project, since I have been living mostly in the classical music world lately. But I know for sure that jazz is one place I want to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I had a great time at our first J-Jam, both listening and performing! It&amp;rsquo;s a fantastic Squirrel Hill community event that I hope will continue regularly, and I&amp;rsquo;m grateful to Joel and Ben for organizing it and spreading the word to have people come over to listen and perform, and I was inspired by the wonderful performances by everyone who came to share their love of music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I look forward to participating again!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2012-12-16&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-12-16)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did not perform in or even attend &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.facebook.com/events/347798348651757/&#34;&gt;J-Jam on December 16&lt;/a&gt; after all! It quickly became clear in early December, after I met up with Ben to play together, that I was getting way too busy with many other things, and even if I hadn&amp;rsquo;t been, Ben himself was busy too, such that we had no opportunity to get together again anyway to work on something to play. Furthermore, the time conflicted with the monthly meeting of the Pittsburgh Recorder Society, which I hate to miss, so I did not even show up at J-Jam in December just to watch and listen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-02-10&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-02-10)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did not perform in the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/02/10/attending-j-jam-in-squirrel-hill-but-not-playing-music-in-it/&#34;&gt;February 2013 J-Jam&lt;/a&gt; either, but did attend.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Celebrating this blog&#39;s one-year anniversary</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/09/22/celebrating-this-blogs-one-year-anniversary/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Sep 2012 18:11:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/09/22/celebrating-this-blogs-one-year-anniversary/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;One year ago, I started this blog, inspired by my attending &lt;a href=&#34;http://podcamppittsburgh.com/&#34;&gt;PodCamp Pittsburgh&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not going to write up a lengthy retrospective today, because I have to go soon to a concert Abby will be in tonight, as part of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pittsburghmandolinsociety.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Mandolin Society orchestra&lt;/a&gt; in Synod Hall. It was interesting rereading my own &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/21/one-month-anniversary-of-my-blog/&#34;&gt;one-month retrospective from last year&lt;/a&gt;: I&amp;rsquo;ve learned so much about myself, and other people, and changed so much, during the past year of writing here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All I will say for now is: &lt;em&gt;I will continue to write for an online audience, and I expect to do this for the rest of my life&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;podcamp-pittsburgh-reminder&#34;&gt;PodCamp Pittsburgh reminder!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PodCamp Pittsburgh 7 is happening later this year than it did last year; it is coming October 27-28. There is still a &lt;a href=&#34;http://podcamppittsburgh.com/pcpgh7-speaker-submission/&#34;&gt;call for speakers&lt;/a&gt;. I remember last year some of the guys who inspired me had joked that I should start a blog and then come back the following year to talk about it. I don&amp;rsquo;t know if I&amp;rsquo;m ready to do that yet, but at least it no longer sounds at all like a crazy idea!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;think-about-it&#34;&gt;Think about it&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you haven&amp;rsquo;t attended PodCamp Pittsburgh before, check it out! Registration is open, and the whole weekend is &lt;em&gt;free&lt;/em&gt;! Unbelievable value for something that &lt;em&gt;changed my life forever&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Petrified at a music jam session so I didn&#39;t play but watched and listened</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/07/03/petrified-at-a-music-jam-session-so-i-didnt-play-but-watched-and-listened/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jul 2012 22:35:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/07/03/petrified-at-a-music-jam-session-so-i-didnt-play-but-watched-and-listened/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/02/my-first-french-music-jam-anxious-but-excited&#34;&gt;Just yesterday, I went to a music jam&lt;/a&gt; and was anxious but got over that and participated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today Abby and I went to a &lt;em&gt;very different&lt;/em&gt; one, a potluck/music jam hosted by Susan Waggoner, whom we&amp;rsquo;ve known for a long time through various Pittsburgh music and dance activities. Susan is involved particularly in the Cajun music/dance scene, and was also in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.post-gazette.com/stories/local/neighborhoods-city/accordion-pool-partys-another-use-for-empty-lawrenceville-pool-357459/&#34;&gt;Accordion Pool Party&lt;/a&gt; that Abby played in three years ago, and also has been doing &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/01/23/discovering-french-traditional-dance-in-pittsburgh/&#34;&gt;French dancing&lt;/a&gt; with us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was so &lt;em&gt;terrified&lt;/em&gt; at this party that I didn&amp;rsquo;t play &lt;em&gt;at all&lt;/em&gt;, despite bringing my instruments. I just didn&amp;rsquo;t feel up to it. But I learned a lot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;two-main-groups-of-musicians&#34;&gt;Two main groups of musicians&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that there were a bunch of musicians playing music outside in the back of the home. I wasn&amp;rsquo;t super familiar with what they were playing. Then there were some musicians playing music inside in the living room.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They really knew what they were doing, and were singing and playing by ear, no scores in sight. Without any scores, I had no clue how I could contribute, so I didn&amp;rsquo;t even take out my instruments. This was &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; jamming, not the kind that I did yesterday where most (but not all) of the stuff we did involved songs I had brought scores for or at least had heard before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;old-time-music&#34;&gt;Old time music&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was told by the men and women who were inside that those outside were playing &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Old-time_music&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;old time&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; music. I hadn&amp;rsquo;t been familiar with the term or genre.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby liked being outside, and also has been playing mandolin, so spent time checking out that group. I think she played along some too. It seemed to be mostly fiddlers, with banjo, mandolin, percussion, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I checked it out, but the music happened not to be quite so interesting to me; it moved fast, had a lot of notes, but seemed somewhat monotonous to my taste.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;country-blues-music&#34;&gt;Country blues music&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inside, however, I was really captivated by what was going on. They said that they were playing &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Country_blues&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;country blues&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. I liked the harmonic changes and the rhythmic qualities and improvisation. Guitars, harmonica, piano, singing. I was impressed by how the singers made up entire lyrics on the spot, often very funny or off-color.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I stayed around inside soaking in what was going on, and thought, I could see myself someday playing along.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was really excited to meet more musicians and widen my musical experience at the potluck/jam session. I felt pretty inspired by what I saw going on, music as a really communal, creative experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Noticing the huge gap between what these musicians were able to do and what I am able to do, I know that it takes a long time to get where they are, but I want to have that kind of everyday facility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2012-07-07&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-07-07)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Four days later, we went to another potluck/jam session, and &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/07/another-terrifying-music-jam-session-but-i-played-a-little-bit-of-blues-and-old-time/&#34;&gt;I played a little bit&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-01-28&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-01-28)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seven months later, I participated in &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/28/my-first-blues-music-jam-happened-after-the-regular-french-music-jam/&#34;&gt;my first blues jam&lt;/a&gt;. The pianist there, Anders, was the same one I first saw here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-07-03&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-07-03)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/07/03/second-year-at-july-3-music-party-still-only-listening-without-playing/&#34;&gt;my second year&lt;/a&gt; of this annual party, I still did not feel comfortable enough with the crowd to try to participate musically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2014-07-03&#34;&gt;(Update of 2014-07-03)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/07/03/third-year-at-july-3-music-party-and-finally-participated-in-jamming/&#34;&gt;my third year&lt;/a&gt; of this annual party, I actually played both piano and ukulele!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Visiting the House of Musical Traditions: looking at instruments including Irish flutes</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/05/28/visiting-the-house-of-musical-traditions-looking-at-instruments-including-irish-flutes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 May 2012 23:34:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/05/28/visiting-the-house-of-musical-traditions-looking-at-instruments-including-irish-flutes/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/house-of-musical-traditions.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;House of Musical Traditions in Takoma Park, MD&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One thing Abby and I wanted to do before we left Washington DC was to visit the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.hmtrad.com/&#34;&gt;House of Musical Traditions&lt;/a&gt; in Takoma Park, MD. We wanted to check out all their musical instruments. Abby wanted to look at their mandolin section, while I wanted to look at Irish flutes. I&amp;rsquo;ve been kind of thinking about getting an Irish flute since February when &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/02/20/enjoying-more-french-dancing-in-pittsburgh/&#34;&gt;seeing again Gregory play his Irish flute at French dancing&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We weren&amp;rsquo;t planning to buy anything, but we had fun looking at a large variety of musical instruments, from mandolins and ukuleles to bongo drums and jaw harps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;irish-flutes&#34;&gt;Irish flutes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the store, I looked at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.hmtrad.com/catalog/winds/dixon.html&#34;&gt;Tony Dixon plastic flutes&lt;/a&gt; that I&amp;rsquo;d read about before the trip to DC. Unfortunately, as I suspected, they were rather large for my hands. Also, the plastic flutes did not produce a very attractive sound.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.tonydixonmusic.co.uk/grafix/instruments/tb021.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Tony Dixon tuneable flute&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;casey-burns-folk-flute&#34;&gt;Casey Burns Folk Flute&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I left the store knowing I would have to do more research on affordable keyless Irish flutes that might both fit in my hands and produce a decent sound. After doing some research online, I concluded that no plastic Irish flute was really going to be what I wanted. But there were rave reviews of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.caseyburnsflutes.com/ff.php&#34;&gt;Casey Burns Folk Flute&lt;/a&gt; as a starter Irish flute, because of its quality and its unbeatable price.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, I noticed that there was option to order a special &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.caseyburnsflutes.com/ergo.php&#34;&gt;ergonomic version for small hands&lt;/a&gt;, which is precisely what I seem to need, given my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/05/18/got-my-new-and-more-ergonomic-flute/&#34;&gt;very real need for well-fitting instruments&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After we return to Pittsburgh, Abby and I will discuss whether my music goals and plans justify buying yet another musical instrument.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would like to thank the people at the House of Musical Traditions for letting us look at their large collection of musical instruments and try some out. Meanwhile, I have learned that if I do get an Irish flute, I should start out with the nice wooden Casey Burns Folk Flute.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My first time in a public music jam: intense fun with Chris Norman and David Greenberg</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/04/21/my-first-time-in-a-public-music-jam-intense-fun-with-chris-norman-and-david-greenberg/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Apr 2012 13:44:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/04/21/my-first-time-in-a-public-music-jam-intense-fun-with-chris-norman-and-david-greenberg/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://fbcdn-sphotos-a.akamaihd.net/hphotos-ak-ash3/544714_10150682065771513_55075526512_9775036_876594193_n.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;David Greenberg and Chris Norman and the rest of us&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Friday evening, Abby and I packed up various musical instruments of ours, and attended an event that I had been eagerly awaiting for over three weeks since I first found out about it from Annie of the local &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.andrew.cmu.edu/user/lukas/pcars/Welcome.html&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh recorder gang&lt;/a&gt;: a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rbsp.org/Jam%20Session%20Flyer.pdf&#34;&gt;jam session open to the public&lt;/a&gt; being offered by &lt;a href=&#34;http://chrisnorman.com/&#34;&gt;Chris Norman&lt;/a&gt;, flutist, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.davidgreenberg.ca/&#34;&gt;David Greenberg&lt;/a&gt;, violinist the day before &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rbsp.org/11-12c6.aspx&#34;&gt;their concert&lt;/a&gt; the next evening to close the current season of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rbsp.org/&#34;&gt;Renaissance and Baroque of Pittsburgh&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was so excited by this opportunity to jam with such esteemed musicians. Norman and Greenberg specialize in playing Irish, Scottish, Cape Breton and Baroque music. I&amp;rsquo;ve come to love playing the rhythmic, danceable music of the old days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I learned a lot from the experience, and would like to share what I learned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;some-photos-of-the-event&#34;&gt;Some photos of the event&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/pages/Pittsburgh-Renaissance-and-Baroque/55075526512&#34;&gt;Facebook page of the Pittsburgh Renaissance and Baroque&lt;/a&gt; has a bunch of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/media/set/?set=a.10150682065546513.394216.55075526512&amp;amp;type=3&#34;&gt;photos of the event&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;ve used a couple of these here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;preparation&#34;&gt;Preparation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;my-instruments&#34;&gt;My instruments&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been spending most of my daily music practice all year working on the modern &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/flute/&#34;&gt;flute&lt;/a&gt;; I have not reported on my progress in over a month because I&amp;rsquo;ve been too busy &lt;em&gt;doing&lt;/em&gt; rather than &lt;em&gt;writing&lt;/em&gt;, but will catch up with the writing sometime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But for this jam session, I had decided very quickly that I was &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; going to be bringing my modern flute to play, because I do prefer to play older music on other instruments; I planned to bring the following instruments instead:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;my &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/tin-whistle/&#34;&gt;tin whistle&lt;/a&gt;, which I bought the week of St. Patrick&amp;rsquo;s Day in March (for a party I haven&amp;rsquo;t written about yet but which radically changed my life)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;an assortment of &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/recorder/&#34;&gt;recorders&lt;/a&gt;: I decided to just bring my soprano and alto&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;my &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/baroque-flute/&#34;&gt;Baroque flute&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, interspersed with my continuing work on the modern flute, I have also done some maintenance practice of tin whistle and recorders. The most difficult challenge was trying to get serious about Baroque flute: the one-keyed flute is &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.oldflutes.com/charts/onekey/index.htm&#34;&gt;very, very, very tricky to play in tune&lt;/a&gt;. Sometimes I wonder whether it&amp;rsquo;s worth the bother. But I tend to be inspired by quirky challenges whose benefit I don&amp;rsquo;t fully understand immediately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ideally, I would own an &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.caseyburnsflutes.com/cat_d.php&#34;&gt;Irish flute&lt;/a&gt;, preferably with a number of keys to aid with intonation and fingering, but given that I don&amp;rsquo;t currently intend to specialize in Irish music, and am still working with the tin whistle anyway, I cannot at all justify buying an Irish flute at this time. So I&amp;rsquo;ve been working on using the related Baroque flute instead, for traditional Irish or Scottish music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;abby-s-instruments&#34;&gt;Abby&amp;rsquo;s instruments&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby started learning mandolin just this year, joining the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pittsburghmandolinsociety.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Mandolin Orchestra&lt;/a&gt;, so I was excited that she decided early on to bring it to the jam session. (And I look forward to seeing her play for the first time in the orchestra&amp;rsquo;s concert on Mother&amp;rsquo;s Day coming up in three weeks!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She also brought a frame drum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-event&#34;&gt;The event!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;arrival&#34;&gt;Arrival&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I arrived a little late, so I scrambled to get ready while a whole bunch of people were already gathered. Many people were sitting in back just to watch and listen, while maybe twenty of us were armed with instruments of all kinds, ready to have some fun!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://fbcdn-sphotos-a.akamaihd.net/hphotos-ak-prn1/541085_10150682067126513_55075526512_9775042_292845062_n.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;We played lots of different instruments&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We ran into half a dozen people we knew from various of our musical circles, including Annie from recorder, a guy Abby knew from mandolin, and some fellow &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/16/playing-recorder-and-flute-at-the-holiday-ball/&#34;&gt;Holiday Ball&lt;/a&gt; musicians.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was intrigued by the couple of people who had actual keyed Irish flutes and eager to hear them play (it would turn out, of course, that they were very, very good).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;music-scores&#34;&gt;Music scores&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So each of us got a packet of around twenty pages of music. We didn&amp;rsquo;t play all of it, of course, but it was a good basis for sight reading along with Chris and David leading the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much of the music went at breakneck pace that I&amp;rsquo;m still not proficient enough to sight reading perfectly, but my (yet unreported) musical adventures in the past month have made me far less self-conscious about perfection and figure out ways to cope:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it&amp;rsquo;s not necessary to play all the notes; in fast music, you can contribute just fine playing only one main note per measure or harmony change&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;you can also substitute a different, easier melodic line that is compatible with the chords&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;since sections are repeated many times, you can add more during repetitions as you feel ready to&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it&amp;rsquo;s not the end of the world to miscalculate sometimes and squeak out a harsh dissonant error; the music just keeps going, so don&amp;rsquo;t look back, only forward&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;learning-by-ear-improvisation&#34;&gt;Learning by ear, improvisation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I expected, much of the time we didn&amp;rsquo;t play music from the handed out scores at all. This was the fun I was anticipating all along (I had not really expected music scores at all, actually).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost half the time, Chris would ask us for music suggestions to offer up &lt;em&gt;by example&lt;/em&gt;, so that the volunteer would play (or sing) the melody, then the rest of us would start &amp;ldquo;learning&amp;rdquo; it by ear and join in and continue with repetitions. I had not anticipated the call for volunteers, else I would have come prepared with some favorite tunes to offer!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some people were more familiar with various tunes being offered up than I was, since they had a lot more experience with Irish, Scottish and other such music than me, so I felt awkward and lost trying to learn and play on the spot, without written music, but it was part of the whole fun, really stretching what I have usually been doing with music (very oriented toward following a written score).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve mentioned before my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/10/flute-loving-it-again/&#34;&gt;poor memory&lt;/a&gt; having a considerable impact on my life, and I worked around it again, given that I could not quickly learn the details of a melody, by just giving up and improvising around the harmony changes instead. I would like to find ways to improve my memory, but for now, I work around my limitations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;a-charming-tangent-involving-an-oboe&#34;&gt;A charming tangent involving an oboe&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it turned out that a young woman among us had come with a Baroque oboe tuned to A415 instead of the modern A440 tuning. This caused confusion, of course, when she tried to play from written scores. I&amp;rsquo;m not sure what she ended up doing: the only choices were to mentally transpose from the written scores (when we were playing music from them) or just ignore the scores and learn by ear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, Chris and David repeatedly wanted to play with her and asked her what music she had on her, and she had a variety of Baroque music scores with her (she said she was actually giving a recital the next day), and so they tried to play some stuff just with her while doing their own mental transposition so that she would get to play without mental transposition! Check out Chris hovering over the score trying to do the really hard work of transposing on the fly:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://fbcdn-sphotos-a.akamaihd.net/hphotos-ak-ash4/s720x720/295215_10150682067841513_395463764_n.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Baroque oboist with Chris and David&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;dancing&#34;&gt;Dancing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Periodically, a number of people got up to dance in the space at the side, especially when we played waltzes. It was nice to see people moving.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://fbcdn-sphotos-a.akamaihd.net/hphotos-ak-ash3/529154_10150682066471513_55075526512_9775039_758574985_n.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;A couple dancing&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;i-m-caught-on-a-photo-playing-baroque-flute&#34;&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m caught on a photo playing Baroque flute&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spent a fair amount of time playing the tin whistle, and some time on my recorders, but in the end gravitated toward the Baroque flute because it was mellower and I could draw less attention to my mistakes by playing it instead!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that a photo was taken that included me when I was playing my Baroque flute. In this photo, you can also see a guy playing tin whistle (this guy also at one point volunteered to sing a tune, and did so with quite a powerful voice, a great rendition).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://fbcdn-sphotos-a.akamaihd.net/hphotos-ak-ash2/35507_10150682067581513_55075526512_9775044_1738151368_n.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;A fellow tin whistle player, and me on Baroque flute&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My posture is really bad here. I need to sit up straight and keep my head over my body rather than straining over my neck. My only excuse is that this photo was probably taken two hours into the jam session when it was almost over, and I was having energy issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-note-on-energy-requirements&#34;&gt;A note on energy requirements&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was totally exhausted after the jam session. After Abby and I drove back home, we both had to eat something. We were starving. We should have taken a snack break at the jam session.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I weighed myself and I had lost weight. The mental demands on me were considerable, and I had really spent myself. Given that I have lost weight before when taking exams in school, or playing in chess tournaments, or doing similar activities that combine both mental demands and personal anxiety, I should have been better prepared with fuel at the event. I get the impression that I burn more energy by thinking hard than by running.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was my first time ever at a public music jam session, and I quite enjoyed it. I am grateful to Chris Norman and David Greenberg, and the Pittsburgh Renaissance and Baroque, for providing it to the community. I am always very happy for opportunities to play music with Abby, and keep remembering how she got me into this particular early traditional dance music world, through our first musical time together at the Holiday Ball.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got self-feedback about musical shortcomings for me to keep working on in order to enjoy future jam sessions, and I learned that I really need food to keep me fueled for optimal musicality!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>