<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Yoga on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/yoga/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Yoga on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/yoga/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Injuries from yoga are common: some tips on staying safe</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/01/06/injuries-from-yoga-are-common-some-tips-on-staying-safe/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jan 2012 22:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/01/06/injuries-from-yoga-are-common-some-tips-on-staying-safe/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;For years now, I&amp;rsquo;ve noticed that when people find out that I do yoga, they often say something like
&lt;blockquote&gt;
I tried yoga once and I got hurt. I thought it was supposed to be relaxing.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I read an article, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2012/01/08/magazine/how-yoga-can-wreck-your-body.html?pagewanted=all&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;How Yoga Can Wreck Your Body&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. I urge anyone who currently does yoga, or is thinking about starting it, to read this article. It discusses cases of quite serious injury in yoga practitioners, including instructors, and reveals a world of danger that many may not be aware of, given how popular and hip yoga has become in the past decade or two.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not a yoga instructor, and I&amp;rsquo;m also not a fanatic yoga devotee, but since I once did yoga every other day for a couple of years, and found it extremely, astoundingly beneficial, I&amp;rsquo;d like to share some ideas on how I have managed to avoid being injured by yoga. I&amp;rsquo;ll also discuss related issues with Pilates and sitting meditation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-discovery-of-yoga&#34;&gt;My discovery of yoga&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first exposure to yoga at all was an infamous episode of the TV show &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/That&#39;s_Incredible!&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;That&amp;rsquo;s Incredible!&lt;/a&gt; in which some guy named &amp;ldquo;Yogi Kudu&amp;rdquo; folded himself up into a box.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point, yoga became mainstream and offered as a &amp;ldquo;fitness&amp;rdquo; class. I got the impression that women and dancers took it up, and I had no interest in yoga until I got into ballroom dance in 2000, became very serious about it, and got my first exposure, from competition-oriented ballroom dancers, to such favorite dancer-oriented activities as yoga, Pilates, and Alexander technique. But any time I did even a basic yoga pose, I found myself embarrassingly inflexible and the whole idea seemed boring to me anyway, so I did not seriously pursue yoga for some time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, as I had also begun to run, and then continued to be very serious about it, I heard from various sources that yoga could be beneficial to runners also. It was not until 2002, when I started training for my first marathon, the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pittsburghmarathon.com/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Marathon&lt;/a&gt;, that I felt that maybe I should check out yoga.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went to some free sampler classes, but found them unsatisfactory. Ironically, I probably prevented early injury as a result. Here&amp;rsquo;s why: I &lt;strong&gt;think about what pain and discomfort mean&lt;/strong&gt;! I felt physically and mentally uncomfortable and did not continue going to group classes, but decided on some self-study.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-drawbacks-of-group-classes&#34;&gt;The drawbacks of group classes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a standard group class, there are many drawbacks to learning &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; subject. Yoga is no exception. Without individual instruction and detailed feedback, it is easy to do all kinds of horrible things to your body. Some people are &amp;ldquo;wimps&amp;rdquo;, and they are actually the smart ones, because they quit thinking (incorrectly, I would add), &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m not cut out for yoga.&amp;rdquo; Others push through the pain thinking, &amp;ldquo;no pain, no gain&amp;rdquo;. Having incorrectly adopted this attitude earlier, when overdoing my running, I knew from experience that I never wanted again to go too far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Worse, it&amp;rsquo;s discouraging when you can&amp;rsquo;t keep up some standard sequence the instructor leads everyone as a group through, while some people around you are doing just fine. Yes, we should check our &lt;em&gt;ego&lt;/em&gt; at the door, but sometimes that is hard, and trying to learn something difficult while ego interferes is not optimal. A good instructor will give detailed instructions on modifying poses or movements, or substituting them entirely with rest that does not break the flow, but given the sampler classes I have experienced, I can safely say that not every instructor pays this much attention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, the subtleties of each pose and its intention are hardly explained, in a typical drop-in yoga class. If yoga classes were structured within real progressing sequences with prerequisites, rather than existing as free-floating interchangeable drop-in commodities, maybe there would be better explanations. The typical yoga class I have gone to has instructors trying to scope out or ask aloud, &amp;ldquo;Who here is new?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-i-started-a-regular-private-practice-of-yoga&#34;&gt;How I started a regular private practice of yoga&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As my curiosity was whetted from the sampler classes, I decided to try out some books and videos on yoga. I am a big fan of self-learning, through books, videos, and the vast resource that is the entire Web. I can learn more detail about technique, I can read about comparisons, I can go at my own pace, and in privacy (eliminating the fear of embarrassment). I can choose which subsets to explore and use, rather than be subjected to someone else&amp;rsquo;s rigid ideas or instruction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I quickly found that the books and videos of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rodney_Yee&#34;&gt;Rodney Yee&lt;/a&gt; worked very well for me. For a couple of years, I ended up using a several of his &amp;ldquo;Power Yoga&amp;rdquo; DVDs as my primary half-hour-or-so yoga sessions every other day. I would definitely recommend them. Here&amp;rsquo;s what I like about Yee&amp;rsquo;s videos:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As a male, I happen to enjoy having a male instructor and role model to emulate; although I have used videos by female instructors also, I find it jarring to follow a female instructor who is far more flexible in various ways than a typical male instructor.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Yee has a soothing, encouraging voice and delivery of instructions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Yee&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;pace&lt;/em&gt; is usually pretty good for me, not too fast, not too slow.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Relatively few poses&lt;/em&gt; are used in most of his videos I have used. It is better to try to master a few important &lt;em&gt;simpler&lt;/em&gt; poses than to squander attention on a whole lot of poses. Also, I will claim that the more complex the pose, the greater the potential for injury.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are different workouts with different intensities: &amp;ldquo;stamina&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;strength&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;flexibility&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;benefits-i-have-experienced-from-yoga&#34;&gt;Benefits I have experienced from yoga&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result of yoga, every single year in the past decade, I have become more flexible. &lt;strong&gt;I am now more flexible than I was in high school.&lt;/strong&gt; That&amp;rsquo;s really something, and it&amp;rsquo;s great being more flexible. When your body is looser, it is less stressed and burdened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have improved my posture. Stretching out the spine through persistent practice of yoga really works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Increased awareness of breath is something I learned both from running and from yoga. A good yoga instructor reminds you to pay attention to inhaling and exhaling in harmony with your movements. The circulation helps clear up one&amp;rsquo;s mind and both awaken and relax the body.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Balance. Many of the poses challenge one&amp;rsquo;s balance. I have spent much of my life slumping in chairs and other furniture. Yoga helped reverse the bad habits and imbalance coming from a sedentary lifestyle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;some-yoga-poses-i-am-currently-careful-about-or-avoid&#34;&gt;Some yoga poses I am currently careful about or avoid&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t do all the poses Yee demonstrates, and the ones I do, I don&amp;rsquo;t necessarily do in the full extension given. Here are some issues I discovered apply to myself:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reclined leg stretch. Personally, I have tight hamstrings I&amp;rsquo;m still working on. I can&amp;rsquo;t do a full leg stretch. As recommended, I use a strap. I make sure not to compromise my &lt;em&gt;back&lt;/em&gt; when doing stuff like this. I have seen a lot of people straining.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Various deep back bends. I simply do not trust these. I have had back injuries in the past, and although I am fine now, I don&amp;rsquo;t ever want to injure my back again.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Downward-facing dog. I make sure to use the modified bent-knee variation if I feel too tight in my hamstrings or Achilles tendons or elsewhere. I have seen people with legs straight but &lt;em&gt;backs&lt;/em&gt; curved: this is not good.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Various forward bends. Again, I protect my &lt;em&gt;back&lt;/em&gt;, by bending my knees if I feel the need.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lunge. This is easy for me now, but at the very beginning, I had trouble doing this. A &lt;em&gt;block&lt;/em&gt; is a great prop for modification of poses by decreasing the distance to the ground. I used blocks extensively when first getting into yoga, and I still use them today as I feel the need. There are no bonus points for going without a block out of ego.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Triangle pose. I like this pose, but don&amp;rsquo;t ever expect to perform it without modification. To put the palm of my hand on the ground just twists and hurts my &lt;em&gt;back&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;hip&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anything that puts pressure on my &lt;em&gt;neck&lt;/em&gt;, I avoid or modify. Why do I really need to pull my head back far for cobra, or for upward-facing dog? It doesn&amp;rsquo;t feel right.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;More elaborate poses involving lifting off the ground can put pressure on the &lt;em&gt;neck&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;wrists&lt;/em&gt;. I avoid them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;current-group-class&#34;&gt;Current group class&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I sometimes attend a local free &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/24/roaring-like-a-lion-on-a-saturday/&#34;&gt;drop-in class at the Squirrel Hill Library&lt;/a&gt;. We don&amp;rsquo;t go often, but it is nice in small doses. Some of the reasons we don&amp;rsquo;t go often:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The session is very long, and we prefer shorter sessions. Some people do leave early, but breaking the flow of a complete workout (that includes a nice relaxation segment at the end) just seems inappropriate.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We don&amp;rsquo;t get detailed technical instruction on how to do things right. This is a very large group class.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We are encouraged or guided to go into difficult poses that we are not comfortable with. Yes, the instructor does tell us we don&amp;rsquo;t have to do them, and yes, we know to listen to our bodies, but still, it is somewhat disorienting to decide not to do something when other people are doing it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, the important thing when doing yoga is &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/04/against-just-putting-in-the-time/&#34;&gt;not to do it mechanically, but with awareness and no ego&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-current-practice&#34;&gt;My current practice&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I actually have not done full yoga sessions in two or three years. I do go into some yoga poses spontaneously as part of a stretch and then cool down for other activities, including running, dancing, and strength training. For this new year of 2012, I intend to get back into extended yoga practice. I will continue to write about deepening my yoga experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;pilates&#34;&gt;Pilates&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have to confess that I do not like Pilates. Many of the positions involved in Pilates cause me great stress. I have given Pilates a serious try. I don&amp;rsquo;t know if it&amp;rsquo;s just me, or if other people have a similar experience, but lifting my head up from the ground, for example, causes me great stress. It definitely increases my blood pressure and gives me a headache and strain on my neck and back. This is just my personal experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pilates confuses me. I avoid it. I like to try many different physical disciplines, but Pilates is one that I have abandoned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;sitting-meditation&#34;&gt;Sitting meditation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sitting meditation in a classic lotus position is incredibly difficult. Let me put it this way: after a few years of some periods of regular sitting, it is only in the past two or three months that I am able to sit in something resembling a full lotus position. And I don&amp;rsquo;t like to do this continuously for more than around twenty minutes. That&amp;rsquo;s my limitation. People have wrecked their knees or ankles doing meditation, so as with yoga, it&amp;rsquo;s extremely important not to force yourself into a position that you can&amp;rsquo;t handle. And take note of your motivations. Don&amp;rsquo;t reward yourself with bonus points for doing an &amp;ldquo;advanced&amp;rdquo; position. That&amp;rsquo;s not the point of meditation. I try for lotus purely because it really is more stable than some other more asymmetrical positions, such as Burmese and half Burmese. And I have tried kneeling with or without a bench, but that causes me various problems, for my knees and ankles. And sitting on a chair is definitely suboptimal for the meditation experience, because of the lack of a truly stable base.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even in simpler positions, I can get numb or feel pressure on my ligaments or something. There is always controversy, among different meditation leaders, over how much discomfort to tolerate as an essential part of the practice, and how much is harmful and justifies shifting position or changing position entirely, but I am happy that in the group practice I attend, we are allowed to err on the side of looking out for ourselves. If you meditate in a group, be sure to understand what your leader&amp;rsquo;s expectations are, and make sure they are in line with what you are prepared to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yoga can be very dangerous if you don&amp;rsquo;t have experience paying attention to your body and being really in touch with what is painful and harmful and what is merely challenging and beneficial. I advise that beginners progress very slowly when taking up yoga, ideally with feedback from an instructor who is aware of the dangers. I advise that experienced practitioners do a full review of what they do and what might be causing undue discomfort or pain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Caveats aside, I have found yoga to be a transformative part of my life, refreshing and rejuvenating, and recommend it as a practice to those wishing to deepen their understanding and experience of their mind, body, spirit.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reflections on 2011</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/12/31/reflections-on-2011/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Dec 2011 18:52:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/12/31/reflections-on-2011/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I reflect on my year of 2011 as it ends. Since I did not start blogging until September, I go into more detail of what happened before then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;january&#34;&gt;January&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I continued our project of massively reorganizing our home, a project that began when she moved in during summer 2010. We were very grateful that Abby&amp;rsquo;s father helped out a lot.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I continued getting rid of a lot of stuff, including another eighteen boxes of my books, as I became an initially reluctant &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/minimalism/&#34;&gt;minimalist&lt;/a&gt;. We sold or gave away a &lt;em&gt;huge&lt;/em&gt; number of various of belongings.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby started cooking much more than in the past, and we enjoyed trying new dishes of her making.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I enjoyed some light cross-country skiing in the winter, using the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Schenley_Park_Golf_Course&#34;&gt;Bob O&amp;rsquo;Connor Golf Course at Schenley Park&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I began a weekly Zen &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/meditation/&#34;&gt;meditation&lt;/a&gt; session offered at Carnegie Mellon University.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started moving very gradually toward a &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/paleo/&#34;&gt;paleo&lt;/a&gt; diet and exercise routine, and immediately experienced benefits. &amp;ldquo;The Paleo Solution&amp;rdquo; by &lt;a href=&#34;http://robbwolf.com/&#34;&gt;Robb Wolf&lt;/a&gt; was very useful.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started learning modern &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/javascript/&#34;&gt;JavaScript&lt;/a&gt; for a new project at work, getting into client-side Web development. As part of that, I learned &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/jquery/&#34;&gt;jQuery&lt;/a&gt; through a free &lt;a href=&#34;http://p2pu.org/&#34;&gt;P2PU&lt;/a&gt; course and used it in the project.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started using &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/XQuery&#34;&gt;XQuery&lt;/a&gt; at work to process XML in a clear and concise way. I had used XSLT in the past, but it was very unpleasant.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I decided, for various reasons, to stop writing new &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/perl/&#34;&gt;Perl&lt;/a&gt; scripts and move to &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/python/&#34;&gt;Python&lt;/a&gt; instead.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started playing in my final (and disastrous) &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/chess/&#34;&gt;chess&lt;/a&gt; tournament, the Pittsburgh Chess Club Championship (which I had won in 2006 and 2007).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;february&#34;&gt;February&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pittsburgh was all about the Steelers, and I went to a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Super_Bowl_XLV&#34;&gt;Super Bowl&lt;/a&gt; party for the first time, but we lost!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I read &amp;ldquo;The Art of Non-Conformity&amp;rdquo; by &lt;a href=&#34;http://chrisguillebeau.com/&#34;&gt;Chris Guillebeau&lt;/a&gt; and found it so inspiring that I decided to take action and start making big changes to my life, in my own way.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;One big change: I quit playing chess, cold turkey, after having been unenthusiastic about it for months already (and playing correspondingly poorly). When the passion and enjoyment are gone, there is no point in hanging onto something just because it has been such an important part of my life for years.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;After years of not playing any music at all, I started playing &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/recorder/&#34;&gt;recorder&lt;/a&gt;, and vowed to play every single day if possible. Ten months later, I am still playing recorder.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I began attending a lot of &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/16/pittsburgh-software-developer-communities/&#34;&gt;local software developer group meetings&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started learning the &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/scala/&#34;&gt;Scala&lt;/a&gt; programming language and decided to use it on a small project.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;march&#34;&gt;March&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I continued our meditation practice at CMU, and went to our first mini-&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sesshin&#34;&gt;sesshin&lt;/a&gt; on a Saturday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I continued practicing recorder every single day, and joined the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.andrew.cmu.edu/user/lukas/pcars/Welcome.html&#34;&gt;local chapter of the American Recorder Society&lt;/a&gt;. It was very exciting to meet new people and to get into a wide range of music I had never really listened to or played.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I saw a video of &lt;a href=&#34;http://jakeshimabukuro.com/&#34;&gt;Jake Shimabukuro&lt;/a&gt; playing &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/ukulele/&#34;&gt;ukulele&lt;/a&gt; so beautifully that I was inspired to buy a ukulele and start learning to play it. (Unfortunately, it would turn out that time constraints caused me not to pursue ukulele far. This will change in 2012.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I got pulled into the Ruby programming language because it is well-supported on Mac OS and it is easy to install libraries and tools, of which there are many that are quite useful.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I went to &lt;a href=&#34;http://farmtotablepa.com/&#34;&gt;Farm to Table&lt;/a&gt; in Pittsburgh, and after that, Abby started moving toward paleo eating, with even better results than my smaller experiments earlier.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I started our &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/hiking/&#34;&gt;hiking&lt;/a&gt; season in the spring. Hiking is special to us; it was one of our first shared activities (after initially meeting during salsa dancing), and one we return to again and again. When there is no calendar conflict and the weather is acceptable, we like hiking almost every weekend from spring through fall.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;{% img /images/steves-soup-hike-2011-03-26.jpg Abby in front of me at Steve&amp;rsquo;s Soup Hike %}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;april&#34;&gt;April&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started wearing &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/fivefingers/&#34;&gt;Vibram FiveFingers shoes&lt;/a&gt; almost all the time, whether walking or running (but not yet for hiking).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I went to &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/yoga/&#34;&gt;yoga&lt;/a&gt; at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.clpgh.org/locations/squirrelhill/&#34;&gt;Squirrel Hill Library&lt;/a&gt; for the first time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;may&#34;&gt;May&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I began my experiment with barefoot running, in observation of &lt;a href=&#34;http://barefootrunners.org/ibrd&#34;&gt;International Barefoot Running Day&lt;/a&gt;. I started walking around barefoot at work, ignoring the confused looks or comments of colleagues. (I still go barefoot at work.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I bought a &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/melodica/&#34;&gt;melodica&lt;/a&gt;, inspired by the amazing performances of &lt;a href=&#34;http://jnote.org/&#34;&gt;James Howard Young&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I took a little vacation, spending some days in New York visiting Nathaniel and Yael and their baby. I finally fulfilled my dream (from before marriage) of taking Abby to Coney Island to walk on the boardwalk and at the beach, eating pizza, and riding the Wonder Wheel, just as I once did when I was six years old.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I started doing research into major home renovations for the summer.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I visited my parents, and my sister Linda and her husband Andre also visited, with my mother throwing a delayed reception at home for the both of us who had gotten married in the past two years. Abby got to meet my parents&amp;rsquo; friends, finally. And I went running with my brother-in-law for the first time! Also, I took Abby to the little park in Ann Arbor where as a too-shy teenager I used to go and sit on a particular bench and wish I were sitting with my dream girl. Mission accomplished!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;june&#34;&gt;June&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;John and I did a tough 19-mile training hike on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rachelcarsontrails.org/rct&#34;&gt;Rachel Carson Trail&lt;/a&gt; and decided we&amp;rsquo;d had enough of that trail, and I decided I was probably not going to do the 35-mile &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rachelcarsontrails.org/rct/challenge&#34;&gt;Rachel Carson Trail Challenge&lt;/a&gt; again (having completed it three times in the past).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;{% img /images/rachel-carson-trail-2011-06-05.jpg John on Rachel Carson Trail %}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby started wearing Vibram FiveFingers more and more for walking and running, and even walking barefoot on the streets (something I had not yet seriously done myself at the time).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I stupidly threw out my back during exercise, and my back took weeks to fully recover (I could still run and hike, but not lift weights). Never again, I hope. I felt like a 90-year-old when my back was hurting constantly.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;We started some home improvement projects.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;july&#34;&gt;July&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started gravitating to almost exclusively body weight &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/strength-training/&#34;&gt;strength training&lt;/a&gt;, as a reaction to my having injured my back earlier.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I went kayaking on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kiskiminetas_River&#34;&gt;Kiski River&lt;/a&gt; with &amp;ldquo;Fireman Steve&amp;rdquo; and the kayaking gang.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;On a longish hike, Abby surprised me by wearing Vibram FiveFingers shoes and they worked great for her, making her much faster and less sore, and I made a note to ditch my trail running shoes (which I had been using for years for hiking) in favor of FiveFingers for my next hike (which I did, and I have not gone back to regular shoes for hiking!).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I finally took Abby to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sandhillberries.com/&#34;&gt;Sand Hill Berries&lt;/a&gt; for tasty pie for the first time, always having intended to take her there when dating, but never having been in the vicinity with her then.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Major home renovation finally began, after much research, and we got electrical upgrade, insulation, and bathroom demolition and rebuilding. Very disruptive to our lives for weeks!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I did another mini-&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sesshin&#34;&gt;sesshin&lt;/a&gt; at CMU.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;After a lifetime of almost never drinking coffee (average of maybe three or four cups a year), I became an avid espresso fan (one small cup a day) as a result of my boss getting a machine at work.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started doing more barefoot running.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;august&#34;&gt;August&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bathroom renovation done at last.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I were regularly hiking in Vibram FiveFingers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;{% img /images/abby-franklin-soup-hike-vibram.jpg Abby and Franklin on Steve&amp;rsquo;s Soup Hike part 3 wearing Vibram FiveFingers %}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby joined me to run in her first ever 5K race, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.runaroundthesquare.com/&#34;&gt;Run Around the Square&lt;/a&gt; in Regent Square (mostly on the trails of Frick Park). What a special day! This race was my first ever 5K race when I started running in races in 2000.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started to learn &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/accordion/&#34;&gt;accordion&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;september&#34;&gt;September&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started running to work two or three times a week.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I ran in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~kalp/PGR/&#34;&gt;CMU SCS Pretty Good Race 5K&lt;/a&gt; together, her second 5K race.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I went to &lt;a href=&#34;http://podcamppittsburgh.com/&#34;&gt;PodCamp Pittsburgh&lt;/a&gt;, and after that, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/22/starting-a-new-web-site/&#34;&gt;I started this blog&lt;/a&gt; and proceeded to maintain a habit of posting every day (a routine that has been modified since then).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;october&#34;&gt;October&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started expanding beyond just writing for my blog, and began contributing to the Web through &lt;a href=&#34;http://twitter.com/franklinchen&#34;&gt;my Twitter account&lt;/a&gt; as well as writing comments on other people&amp;rsquo;s blog posts.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started taking Stanford online classes: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ml-class.org/&#34;&gt;Machine Learning&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.db-class.org/&#34;&gt;Introduction to Databases&lt;/a&gt;. (Blog posts on my experiences to appear soon.) Unfortunately, as a result of the extra time commitment, October through December were quite hectic for me.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I continued to move more toward a paleo diet.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;november&#34;&gt;November&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started playing &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/flute/&#34;&gt;flute&lt;/a&gt; again.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Probably because of fatigue and a compromised immune system, I came down with a skin ailment that I got serious treatment for, but it took almost two months to completely clear up and I spent over a month truly miserable &lt;sup&gt;24&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;7&lt;/sub&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;december&#34;&gt;December&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started playing Baroque flute.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started playing tin whistle.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I prepared for and made it through two music performances, playing recorder and flute (and almost tin whistle).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I ended the year completely exhausted, on the verge of getting sick, and took a long break from blogging.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The final week, Abby and I were on a hectic travel schedule that involved meeting up with her parents, my parents, her sister Carrie, Carrie&amp;rsquo;s boyfriend Alain, Alain&amp;rsquo;s parents, Alain&amp;rsquo;s extended family, my sister Linda, and her husband Andre. I am grateful that we got to meet up with so many people (and arranged for various of the individuals to meet up with various of the others!), but the trip was quite stressful to me, because I was not physically or emotionally prepared for it at all. (I will report later on what I learned from the experience.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2011 was quite a year for me and Abby. We had many changes and adventures in our lives: our home, our diet, our exercise, our outdoors activities, travel. For me, the biggest changes were quitting chess, starting music practice and performance, throwing myself into blogging and tweeting, getting more and more active in local software developer groups, applying new (to me) development tools at work, and in the fall, taking Stanford online courses in computer science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although I ended the year in poor shape, because of being overbooked, I am very excited by how many positive changes took place. I have an entirely new set of plans and priorities to formulate soon for 2012 in collaboration with Abby, in hope of learning from the lessons of my failures and omissions of 2011, and restoring balance.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Disagreement on the use of time?</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/10/18/disagreement-on-the-use-of-time/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Oct 2011 19:14:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/10/18/disagreement-on-the-use-of-time/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On Sunday, I went to the monthly meeting of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.andrew.cmu.edu/user/lukas/pcars/Welcome.html&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh chapter&lt;/a&gt; of the American Recorder Society. I stopped by the room where beginner lessons were being held. I don&amp;rsquo;t go to those lessons any more, because I would say I&amp;rsquo;m an intermediate recorder player now. Fred, our director, was working with two women on soprano recorder. One of them was Rhonda, who had actually joined the local group at exactly the same time as me, back in March. I hadn&amp;rsquo;t seen her in a while and asked where she&amp;rsquo;d been. She said she had been playing French horn in the summer, so was getting back to recorder now. She happened to joke to the other woman, an older woman, that I was really serious and had been practicing an hour every day since starting out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To my surprise, the other woman (whom I don&amp;rsquo;t remember ever having met before) immediately launched into some remarks I found snarky. She said, &amp;ldquo;Well, that&amp;rsquo;s probably an hour he&amp;rsquo;s not washing dishes.&amp;rdquo; I paused in shock, and then she continued, &amp;ldquo;Or an hour he&amp;rsquo;s not taking out the trash.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was not quite sure how to respond.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-response&#34;&gt;My response&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously, this could have been an opportunity for me to use &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/11/communicating-through-dialogue/&#34;&gt;dialogue&lt;/a&gt; and try to understand why she said what she said, and what she really meant by her words that I found disparaging. In fact, thanks to my raised awareness from learning about dialogue just recently, at least I did not get angry or lose my temper. But I decided at the time that I was just passing by and was not interested in going off on a tangent, since I was heading back to the other room to set up my instruments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I simply replied calmly that actually, the hour of my time that went to recorder practice came out of time I used to spend on various forms of entertainment. I said that I don&amp;rsquo;t watch any TV and I don&amp;rsquo;t watch any movies. She didn&amp;rsquo;t respond to that. For all I know, she might be one of the average Americans who watch &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.csun.edu/science/health/docs/tv&amp;amp;health.html&#34;&gt;4 hours of TV a day&lt;/a&gt;, and perhaps I unintentionally offended her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Disclaimer: I am not one of those snobs who summarily look down on people who watch TV. I used to watch a lot of TV. In fact, I cannot imagine what my life would be today without having had access to TV, which expanded my emotional and intellectual world. But that was then; now, I simply make different choices with my time.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I left the room and didn&amp;rsquo;t see her again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I&amp;rsquo;m still curious about why she seemed annoyed that I spent an hour a day practicing music, as though I&amp;rsquo;m not getting chores done. I won&amp;rsquo;t speculate about why, since the only right way to satisfy my curiosity would be to ask her myself, and I passed up the opportunity to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My brief response to her was meant to convey a simple message: time management is important for all of us with our busy lives, but I&amp;rsquo;ve made certain choices, sacrificing some activities in order to gain others. The decisions are often quite difficult, because I have a &lt;em&gt;huge&lt;/em&gt; number of interests, and therefore have to sacrifice the majority of them in order to focus on the fewer that I have decided are most worthwhile to pursue. A breadth-first traversal of all possible life activities would result in completing nothing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;trading-passive-for-active&#34;&gt;Trading passive for active&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of my choices involve trading passive experiences for active experiences. Here are some examples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;music&#34;&gt;Music&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an earlier blog post, I already mentioned why &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/02/i-love-music-but-rarely-listen-to-it-now/&#34;&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t listen to music much&lt;/a&gt; any more, because of time constraints. In effect, I traded listening to music for playing music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;sports&#34;&gt;Sports&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of watching sports, I engage in my own competitive physical activity, to become the athlete instead of the spectator. I enjoy &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/races/&#34;&gt;running races&lt;/a&gt;. I am hardly super fast; at my fastest, I did periodically win age group medals and trophies, but only because competition happened not to be very tough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;exercise&#34;&gt;Exercise&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I run considerably less than I used to. One reason is that once upon a time, I got into a competitive mode, trying to see how fast I could race, and now I am no longer in that mode. It takes too much time and energy. Another reason is that I decided, based on personal experience and learning from the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paleolithic_lifestyle&#34;&gt;paleo/primal&lt;/a&gt; movement, that too much distance running isn&amp;rsquo;t actually all that great for my overall balanced health.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I traded distance training time for &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/24/roaring-like-a-lion-on-a-saturday-morning/&#34;&gt;yoga&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/17/the-joys-of-convict-conditioning-bodyweight-exercising/&#34;&gt;strength training&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I no longer run any more than every other day on average.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;reading&#34;&gt;Reading&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve always read a lot. I still do, using not only the vast web, but also the old-fashioned &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/30/free-to-the-people-since-1895/&#34;&gt;local library&lt;/a&gt;. (Pittsburghers, please &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ourlibraryourfuture.org/&#34;&gt;vote on November 8&lt;/a&gt;!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, at some point I had to make peace with the fact that I could not read everything I might be interested in reading. Abby and I worked on selling or donating over a thousand (!!) books I owned but were just taking up space. It was very difficult parting with them, since one of my childhood dreams had been to build up a large personal library, but reason prevailed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still encounter too much reading material, thanks to the web. I have tried to limit it by using Google Reader exclusively to access information, and never aimlessly loading up web sites, but I have to confess it is still hard to be selective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, now I am writing for my blog, so I am trading reading time for writing time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;computer-programming-languages&#34;&gt;Computer programming languages&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used to be a big computer language hobbyist. I enjoyed learning and playing with dozens of programming languages: if a language exists, I&amp;rsquo;ve probably at least seen sample code and written some sample code for it at some point. I was even obsessed enough with the concept of designing good programming languages that for a while I was enrolled in the Ph.D. program in computer science at CMU, specializing in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~fox/languages.html&#34;&gt;programming language theory&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then as a practicing software developer, I eventually realized that to &lt;em&gt;get stuff done&lt;/em&gt;, I needed to scale back on my hobby. Therefore, for example, as I mentioned in my post about &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/16/pittsburgh-software-developer-communities/&#34;&gt;local software developer groups&lt;/a&gt;, I have ceased following Python. Also, I have deliberately not even looked at new languages such as &lt;a href=&#34;http://fantom.org/&#34;&gt;Fantom&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://gosu-lang.org/&#34;&gt;Gosu&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://confluence.jetbrains.net/display/Kotlin/Welcome&#34;&gt;Kotlin&lt;/a&gt;. (On the other hand, I am committed to learning and using &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.scala-lang.org/&#34;&gt;Scala&lt;/a&gt; more, because the path from Java already exists.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I took only a quick look at Google&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dartlang.org/&#34;&gt;Dart&lt;/a&gt; after the big hype, and am not pursuing it further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trade-off: trading time spent playing with new languages for time spent mastering and implementing programs with old languages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;completely-abandoning-an-activity&#34;&gt;Completely abandoning an activity&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, I have freed up time by completely abandoning an activity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;dancing-part-one&#34;&gt;Dancing (part one)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once upon a time, I did a lot of ballroom dancing. I even trained seriously and entered competitions through the &lt;a href=&#34;http://cmubdc.org/&#34;&gt;CMU ballroom dance club&lt;/a&gt;. I was dancing something like 20 hours a week (note: this was when I was not doing any reading or music or chess, as my trade-off). I quit competitive ballroom dancing eventually, and then even social ballroom dancing. I had also taken up swing and tango, and salsa more seriously, but then quit those too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically, my trade-off was that I completely quit dancing and took up chess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;chess&#34;&gt;Chess&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past, chess was the most time-consuming hobby in my life. A couple of years ago, I was bent on finally achieving a national &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chess_master&#34;&gt;Master&lt;/a&gt; title. I studied hard, improved my game, played a lot. I won the &lt;a href=&#34;http://pscfchess.org/results/06040808.htm&#34;&gt;2006 Pennsylvania Game/29 Championship&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&#34;http://pscfchess.org/results/06101414.htm&#34;&gt;2006 Pennsylvania Action Chess Championship&lt;/a&gt;; I was on the verge of making Master by planning to win the &lt;a href=&#34;http://pscfchess.org/results/07071414.htm&#34;&gt;2007 Pennsylvania Action Chess Championship&lt;/a&gt; when I utterly &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Choke_(sports)&#34;&gt;choked&lt;/a&gt; and blew it by losing the last two games. I never really recovered from that. My life was changing at the time, having just starting to date Abby, and I stopped playing after a while, then after being married, I started playing again, but my heart was not in it, and I played terribly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I quit chess in February 2011. In effect, I traded chess for starting to play recorder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have not played any chess since February. I don&amp;rsquo;t really regret it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;update-of-2013-01-23&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-01-23)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, in the first half of 2012, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/02/07/on-playing-my-first-games-of-chess-in-a-year/&#34;&gt;some&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/05/31/some-pretty-attacking-chess-at-a-party-last-weekend/&#34;&gt;casual&lt;/a&gt; contact with chess led me to feel like playing again, and in August I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/08/21/returning-to-chess/&#34;&gt;decided to start playing in tournaments again&lt;/a&gt; and am right now in the middle of a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/16/pittsburgh-chess-club-championship-2013-round-1-the-art-of-swindling/&#34;&gt;six-week tournament&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;ve gone back to the chess with clear constraints on how much time and energy I spend on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;update-of-2015-12-21&#34;&gt;(Update of 2015-12-21)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Four years later, I made a focused push, temporarily putting many
things aside in my life, in the fall of 2015 to &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2016/01/22/on-finally-achieving-the-us-national-master-chess-title-at-age-45-part-1&#34;&gt;achieve my US Chess
National Master title&lt;/a&gt;, and finally made it, a dream come true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, I have been teaching private lessons since 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;dancing-part-two&#34;&gt;Dancing (part two)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I accidentally first met Abby when I returned to salsa dancing while still playing chess. Eventually, we started dating, and we were going dancing frequently, but eventually we both completely quit salsa dancing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trade-off was that we got into hiking and kayaking together, which was more fulfilling than our going to dances together and my wanting to dance with a lot of women but her only wanting to dance with me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I consciously traded dancing for a relationship and marriage!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;update-of-2013-01-23-1&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-01-23)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, Abby and I accidentally ended up doing some dancing together again, including discovering &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/01/23/discovering-french-traditional-dance-in-pittsburgh/&#34;&gt;French dancing&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/31/my-first-sampling-of-english-country-dance-and-contra-dance/&#34;&gt;English country and contra dancing&lt;/a&gt;. We don&amp;rsquo;t do it regularly, but it&amp;rsquo;s been great doing it on occasion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, for 2013, we decided that we should dance together a little bit every day, just for ourselves, simply to appreciate that we can!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;marriage&#34;&gt;Marriage&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Married life is a lot of trade-offs.  It&amp;rsquo;s nothing resembling single life or dating life!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Time is precious. We all have to make trade-offs. I&amp;rsquo;ve explored some ways in which I made certain trade-offs at certain points in my life. In your own life, do you periodically double-check what your priorities are, when you feel &amp;ldquo;too busy&amp;rdquo; for something you think you value?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Roaring Like a Lion on a Saturday Morning</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/09/24/roaring-like-a-lion-on-a-saturday-morning/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Sep 2011 08:31:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/09/24/roaring-like-a-lion-on-a-saturday-morning/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I woke up today eager to roar like a lion again on a Saturday morning. I hadn&amp;rsquo;t done that in a couple of months now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/3326415463_f9ea763180_m.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;[Lion&amp;#39;s roar]&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;

(&lt;a href=&#34;http://picturesandbox.com/browse/free-stock-photos/3326415463/-.html&#34;&gt;Source&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am, of course, referring to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.yogajournal.com/poses/1705&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;lion&amp;rsquo;s breath&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; performed in yoga.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.yogajournal.com/media/originals/lion_248.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;[Lion&amp;#39;s breath]&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Abby and I had not gone to the free Saturday morning &amp;ldquo;Yoga with Phyllis&amp;rdquo; sessions at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.clpgh.org/locations/squirrelhill/&#34;&gt;Squirrel Hill Library&lt;/a&gt; for a couple of months now, but we had scheduled it in for this morning, so we arrived at the library early enough to get our favorite spots and set up our mats (we learned the hard way the first time that space gets crowded quickly).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/saturday-yoga.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;[Yoga mats in place]&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The instructor, Phyllis Berkovitz, is great. She has a deep, soothing voice, a perpetual smile, and a twinkle in her eye. She is relaxed and funny, making everyone feel comfortable and happy. Phyllis has been teaching yoga here for three decades, and is a truly valuable contributor to the Squirrel Hill Library&amp;rsquo;s community programs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are curious about yoga and don&amp;rsquo;t yet have a practice, check out her weekly Saturday morning class (or Tuesday evening class)!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;pittsburgh-as-small-town&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh as small town&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When attending this yoga class, we often unexpectedly run into people we know (from other contexts) . Today, for example, we ran into a woman from West Virginia (whose sister is here, and was also at class) whom Abby had borrowed an accordion (named &amp;ldquo;Bob&amp;rdquo;) for us to try out in case we wanted to buy it. (I have only begun playing the accordion and have logged maybe two or three hours of practice on &amp;ldquo;Bob&amp;rdquo; so far. More on my new musical hobby later.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;addendum&#34;&gt;Addendum&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By chance, today I saw this feel-good story about how &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.csmonitor.com/World/Making-a-difference/Change-Agent/2011/0923/Ex-convict-teaches-yoga-to-help-calm-violence-in-Mexico-s-prisons&#34;&gt;an ex-convict is teaching yoga to help calm violence in Mexico&amp;rsquo;s prisons&lt;/a&gt; so I felt I should share it here.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/0923FreddieDiazblogpost_full_380.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;[Fredi Daz]&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>