<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Rubber Duck on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/rubber-duck/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Rubber Duck on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/rubber-duck/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>The biggest Pittsburgh Recorder Society meeting I have attended in two years!!</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/20/the-biggest-pittsburgh-recorder-society-meeting-i-have-attended-in-two-years/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Oct 2013 18:04:10 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/20/the-biggest-pittsburgh-recorder-society-meeting-i-have-attended-in-two-years/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;At the second meeting of this season of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/PittsburghRecorderSociety&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Recorder Society&lt;/a&gt;, I was amazed by the huge turnout. There were &lt;strong&gt;fourteen&lt;/strong&gt; of us, easily double the typical attendance in the past two seasons since &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/02/23/celebrating-two-years-of-playing-recorder/&#34;&gt;I first joined in 2011&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-recorder-society-2013-10-20/panorama.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Fred was very excited by the attendance and told us he would like for us to perform as an entire group sometime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/09/15/new-goals-for-a-new-season-of-the-pittsburgh-recorder-society/&#34;&gt;promised after last month&amp;rsquo;s meeting&lt;/a&gt;, I took the opportunity in this meeting to do some playing on my bass recorder. I also played tenor and soprano for some other pieces we worked on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;halloween-themed-desserts&#34;&gt;Halloween-themed desserts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since it is almost Halloween, Helen brought in some &amp;ldquo;scary&amp;rdquo; cupcakes that were, to me anyway, a sight to behold.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-recorder-society-2013-10-20/snacks.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-recorder-society-2013-10-20/scary-cupcake.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-recorder-society-2013-10-20/scary-cupcake-bottom.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;pittsburgh-s-rubber-duck&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh&amp;rsquo;s rubber duck&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People were talking about the planned departure later today of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/RubberDuckPittsburghPa&#34;&gt;our rubber duck&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, in the duck&amp;rsquo;s honor, I had brought my ukulele, and during the break I played &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/10/02/rubber-duckie-and-steel-city-ukuleles-rehearsal/&#34;&gt;Rubber Duckie on my ukulele&lt;/a&gt; while singing along, and Anita joined in the singing too. I had worked pretty hard to be able to passably play this song before our duck left. I still need more work on the song.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;more-recorders-for-me-to-play&#34;&gt;More recorders for me to play&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I picked up two recorders from Helen that I had bid on at the last meeting, when a large collection of recorders was given to us to be auctioned off. More on this later!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had another great time at the Pittsburgh Recorder Society monthly meeting. Every month, our Sunday afternoon meeting is something I truly look forward to.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rubber Duckie and Steel City Ukuleles rehearsal</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/02/rubber-duckie-and-steel-city-ukuleles-rehearsal/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2013 21:43:30 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/02/rubber-duckie-and-steel-city-ukuleles-rehearsal/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/Steel-City-Ukuleles/events/132647852&#34;&gt;This week&amp;rsquo;s Wednesday meeting of the Steel City Ukuleles&lt;/a&gt; was an unusual one: it was split into two halves, the first half being our regular meeting (involving going through a new playlist), the second half being the second of three &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/09/26/first-rehearsal-for-my-first-ukulele-gig/&#34;&gt;rehearsals for the Ecofest gig&lt;/a&gt;. The deal was that everyone was open to stick around for the rehearsal if they wanted to, but with the caveat that it was serious rehearsal time, rather than the more casual regular meetup atmosphere. It turned out that a few people who were not performing in the Ecofest gig did stick around, although most others left.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sunny was not present, so Amber took charge of this meetup session.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/steel-city-ukuleles-2013-10-02.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;rubber-duckie&#34;&gt;Rubber Duckie&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed learning some new songs in the first half.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One slightly crazy thing we tried was running through &amp;ldquo;Rubber Duckie&amp;rdquo;, which I had actually suggested to Sunny in email for the playlist for the next meetup, but apparently others had also suggested, for obvious reasons here in Pittsburgh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/n-kHSXQ_wwk&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This song is hard, with a lot of chord changes. I would like to actually master it and play it solo for Abby before Pittsburgh&amp;rsquo;s rubber duck leaves.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/steel-city-ukuleles-2013-10-02-rubber-duckie.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;rehearsal&#34;&gt;Rehearsal&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rehearsal was intense, but we managed to cover the rest of the songs we are to play in the Ecofest gig three days (!!) from now. A lot of homework for me to do, just as I have been doing with the first half of the program.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>