<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Ice Cream on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/ice-cream/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Ice Cream on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/ice-cream/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>The Joy of Eating Ice Cream for Breakfast</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/06/16/the-joy-of-eating-ice-cream-for-breakfast/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Jun 2012 19:27:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/06/16/the-joy-of-eating-ice-cream-for-breakfast/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/coffee-bean-blast.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Trader Joe&amp;#39;s Coffee Bean Blast ice cream&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Recently I started eating ice cream for breakfast. I was amused because this was something I haven&amp;rsquo;t done since I was a child, when my sister and I managed for a while to convince our parents to let us eat ice cream for breakfast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is there a contradiction between my eating ice cream for breakfast and my supposedly paying attention to my health?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-my-sister-and-i-got-to-eat-ice-cream-as-kids&#34;&gt;How my sister and I got to eat ice cream as kids&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As kids, my sister and I loved ice cream, of course. We managed to find a way to sometimes eat it for breakfast. Basically, we volunteered to make breakfast on some weekends. We had found some kid-oriented &amp;ldquo;cookbooks&amp;rdquo; at a garage sale or something at some point, and we learned about cinnamon toast and other such &amp;ldquo;American&amp;rdquo; breakfasts that were foreign to our parents. It was fun for us to take charge of breakfast once in a while, and have an excuse to make super-sugary concoctions to eat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frankly, it was easy enough for us in general to just say, &amp;ldquo;We&amp;rsquo;re eating American style&amp;rdquo;, in order to avoid eating rice porridge with dried shrimp bits and pork bone broth and greens (to tell the truth, I actually liked that, but at some point wanted to eat &amp;ldquo;American&amp;rdquo; like my classmates). But it was even more fun to be able to say, &amp;ldquo;We found this recipe in a &lt;em&gt;book&lt;/em&gt;.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A couple of times, we managed to get ice cream into the picture. We must have found a recipe that called for it. We got frozen waffles, and prepared them with syrup and topped with ice cream. I remember that being pretty good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;but-ice-cream-is-not-a-good-food&#34;&gt;But ice cream is not a good food&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have to explain that Abby and I don&amp;rsquo;t eat ice cream much any more. We&amp;rsquo;ve found that it is too sugary and makes us feel tired or bloated in large quantities. You don&amp;rsquo;t have to be &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/paleo/&#34;&gt;paleo&lt;/a&gt; to understand and experience the drawbacks of ice cream (not that we&amp;rsquo;re strictly paleo anyway).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I&amp;rsquo;m a big believer in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.t-nation.com/free_online_article/most_recent/in_defense_of_cheat_days&#34;&gt;intermittent cheating&lt;/a&gt;, so I&amp;rsquo;m happy to eat ice cream now and then as a special treat, but otherwise, I don&amp;rsquo;t really need it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-i-had-to-eat-ice-cream-for-breakfast&#34;&gt;Why I had to eat ice cream for breakfast&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t buy this bucket of Trader Joe&amp;rsquo;s Coffee Bean Blast ice cream; Abby did. She thought it would be a nice post-&lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/hiking/&#34;&gt;hike&lt;/a&gt; treat. Unfortunately, it has turned out in the past months that whenever we go out on a weekend for a hike or some other outdoors adventure, we come back in the evening, and it&amp;rsquo;s too late to eat this ice cream.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem is caffeine. Eating this ice cream would mess up our night of sleep. In fact, I verified this once, eating some of the ice cream in the evening: oops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frustrated, I didn&amp;rsquo;t know when I &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; eat this coffee ice cream. Clearly, the only time I could possibly eat it would be before late afternoon. Furthermore, the only safe context for me to eat something like this would be after I exercised. Since I have a preference for exercising in the morning before breakfast anyway, the perfect time for eating this ice cream was breakfast. Generally, after exercising, I can eat sugary foods to an extent without compromising my energy levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-i-did-to-earn-my-breakfast&#34;&gt;What I did to earn my breakfast&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went for a five-mile &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/running/&#34;&gt;run&lt;/a&gt; in &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/frick-park/&#34;&gt;Frick Park&lt;/a&gt;. I wore my Vibram FiveFingers Bikila LS shoes.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/vibram-fivefingers-bikila-ls.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Vibram FiveFingers Bikila LS shoes&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-real-breakfast&#34;&gt;My real breakfast&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At breakfast, I eat only two spoons of ice cream, actually. That is enough to satisfy me. At this rate, I&amp;rsquo;ll take forever to finish that tub. More reason for me to exercise every morning this summer!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I followed up with the rest of my breakfast, which is typical of what I&amp;rsquo;ve been eating since &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/23/paleo-diet-experimentation/&#34;&gt;completely abandoning my former oatmeal breakfast&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/breakfast-brentwood.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;My breakfast along with Brentwood 5K entry form&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Two &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/28/thankful-for-the-free-range-orange-yolked-eggs/&#34;&gt;eggs&lt;/a&gt; fried with spice mix and olive oil&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Spinach from our &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.kretschmannfarm.com/&#34;&gt;Kretschmann Farm&lt;/a&gt; box&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sweet potatoes and bacon bits&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Walnuts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Strawberries&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, and Abby I have signed up for the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.brentwood5k.com/&#34;&gt;Brentwood Firecracker 5K race&lt;/a&gt;. I last did that race eleven years ago, in 2001. I have a serious goal of beating my time from that year!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have only two more weeks of training with ice cream, before running the race. Wish me luck!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>