<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Waterfalls on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/waterfalls/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Waterfalls on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/waterfalls/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Happy New Year with a Boyce-Mayview Park hike: wetlands, creeks, beavers, woodpeckers, waterfalls...</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/01/01/happy-new-year-with-a-boyce-mayview-park-hike-wetlands/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2014 19:57:07 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/01/01/happy-new-year-with-a-boyce-mayview-park-hike-wetlands/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Happy New Year 2014!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I started off this new year with a lovely &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/pittsburghhikers/events/157809022&#34;&gt;hike with the Pittsburgh hiking meetup group&lt;/a&gt;, led by Gary Byrdman. It was in Boyce-Mayview Park, a park we&amp;rsquo;d never been to before &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.twpusc.org/rec-leisure/parks-fields&#34;&gt;in Upper St. Clair&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/boyce-mayview-2014-01-01/break.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a beautiful day, not too cold (over 20F), and mostly not too muddy or icy either, thankfully. Abby and I did each use a pair of hiking poles, and many of us used &lt;a href=&#34;http://kahtoola.com/product/microspikes/&#34;&gt;MICROSpikes&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.yaktrax.com/&#34;&gt;Yaktrax&lt;/a&gt; also during the hike, but it turned out that the spikes were actually something of a hassle because snow accumulated under them for people. If it had been more icy out, I would have used spikes, however.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was originally hoping to wear my relatively new minimalist New Balance Minimus Zero trail running shoes for this hike, but quickly decided that this would be a bad idea mainly because of the risk of getting my feet cold and wet, so I wrote my old Montrail Rockridge trail running shoes, which I haven&amp;rsquo;t worn in years because they have gotten a bit small for me, requiring me to wear very thin socks (which I did on this hike). Far from minimalist, but in the winter in the face of water dangers (and indeed, we had a couple of stream crossings in which I got a little wet), I don&amp;rsquo;t have a true minimalist shoe yet.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://s7d5.scene7.com/is/image/ColumbiaSportswear/S11_GM2098_654_f?$MTR_pdp_lg$&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Montrail Rockridge&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The hike lasted about two and a half hours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had a great group of people, and Gary even brought breakfast to share with us. After the hike, I eagerly sampled his treats. What a guy! During the hike, he pointed out interesting features, such as beaver dams, woodpecker holes (and we heard woodpeckers too), places that are great for birding in the spring, and a nice waterfall that was partially iced but running.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;photos&#34;&gt;Photos&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re a member of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/pittsburghhikers&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh hiking meetup group&lt;/a&gt;, you have access to the event page and the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/pittsburghhikers/photos/19309272/&#34;&gt;photo page for the hike&lt;/a&gt;, where I uploaded a couple dozen photos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m posting just a few here, to whet your appetite for this park. There was such varied terrain and so much to see!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Parking at the trail head:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/boyce-mayview-2014-01-01/trail-parking.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Breakfast by Gary:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/boyce-mayview-2014-01-01/gary-breakfast.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A beaver was at this tree:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/boyce-mayview-2014-01-01/beaver-tree.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Stream crossing:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/boyce-mayview-2014-01-01/stream-crossing.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;On a trail:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/boyce-mayview-2014-01-01/trail.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Waterfall:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/boyce-mayview-2014-01-01/waterfall.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Going uphill:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/boyce-mayview-2014-01-01/uphill.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Short break:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/boyce-mayview-2014-01-01/break.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the meadows we crossed:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/boyce-mayview-2014-01-01/meadow.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Up:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/boyce-mayview-2014-01-01/up.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I really enjoyed this hike. We promised ourselves that we would return to it next spring and summer. There&amp;rsquo;s clearly so much to enjoy and explore in Boyce-Mayview Park.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to check it out yourself, the Pittsburgh Meetup group often has hikes in this park.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love living in Western Pennsylvania. There is so much to see around here. I will never get bored here. I feel blessed to be living here in Pittsburgh.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>