<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Tv on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/tv/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Tv on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/tv/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Hiroo Onoda and the Six Million Dollar man: what does it mean to know how to die or live?</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/01/17/hiroo-onoda-and-the-six-million-dollar-man/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2014 22:50:24 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/01/17/hiroo-onoda-and-the-six-million-dollar-man/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A news article just came my way that fascinated me: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.washingtonpost.com/world/asia_pacific/hiroo-onoda-japanese-soldier-who-hid-in-philippine-jungle-for-29-years-dies-at-91/2014/01/17/7016d806-7f8b-11e3-93c1-0e888170b723_story.html&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Hiroo Onoda, Japanese soldier who hid in Philippine jungle for 29 years, dies at 91&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, I had long heard of &amp;ldquo;stragglers&amp;rdquo; who did not realize that a war or persecution was over and kept fighting or fleeing, away from &amp;ldquo;civilization&amp;rdquo;, unaware of how the rest of the world was changing. The most recent case of that I read about was a really moving story, astonishing and sad, about an Old Believer &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.smithsonianmag.com/history/for-40-years-this-russian-family-was-cut-off-from-all-human-contact-unaware-of-world-war-ii-7354256/&#34;&gt;Russian family that hid out for forty years&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in the case of this Japanese soldier, although I had not earlier read about his particular story, I instantly remembered an old TV episode I watched as a young child that was an astoundingly memorable episode, whose details are etched in my mind. This was &lt;a href=&#34;http://bionic.wikia.com/wiki/The_Last_Kamikaze&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Last Kamikaze&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, an episode of &amp;ldquo;The Six Million Dollar Man&amp;rdquo; TV series that I watched religiously back in the day. This episode was about a Japanese straggler from World War II. &lt;strong&gt;It changed my life forever.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-last-kamikaze&#34;&gt;The Last Kamikaze&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amazingly, I found the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dailymotion.com/video/xtp86d_the-six-million-dollar-man-the-last-kamikaze-jan-19-1975_shortfilms&#34;&gt;whole episode online&lt;/a&gt;. You may want to watch this episode before reading my spoilers below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe frameborder=&#34;0&#34; width=&#34;480&#34; height=&#34;270&#34; src=&#34;http://www.dailymotion.com/embed/video/xtp86d&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dailymotion.com/video/xtp86d_the-six-million-dollar-man-the-last-kamikaze-jan-19-1975_shortfilms&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;The Six Million Dollar Man&amp;ndash;The Last Kamikaze&amp;hellip;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;i&gt;by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dailymotion.com/dwyerjoss&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;dwyerjoss&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;discussion-with-spoilers&#34;&gt;Discussion, with spoilers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It made a profound impact on me when I watched it over 30 years ago. First, there was the exciting action aspect, of course (all the booby traps in the jungle). But mostly, it was in some sense my first exposure to something from Japanese culture, in particular regarding notions of &amp;ldquo;honor&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OK, it was just TV, and American 1970s TV at a time when there weren&amp;rsquo;t a lot of Asians even being portrayed at all, but in retrospect, it wasn&amp;rsquo;t bad at all. I was confused by the attempted &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Seppuku&#34;&gt;seppuku&lt;/a&gt;, and my parents had to explain what that was about (not being Japanese, but actually living during World War II in Taiwan under Japanese rule and remembering the Allies defeating Japan).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;death-and-life&#34;&gt;Death and life&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the real climax of the episode was when Steve Austin intervenes in the attempt and saves the character Kuroda, saying &amp;ldquo;You have shown that you know how to die. Now for the sake of your enemies, show me that you know how to live.&amp;rdquo; I reflected on what it might mean to &amp;ldquo;know how to die&amp;rdquo; or to &amp;ldquo;know how to live&amp;rdquo;. In that moment of the TV episode, &lt;em&gt;my life was changed forever&lt;/em&gt;. I was around seven years old at the time. I suppose you could say I lost my &amp;ldquo;innocence&amp;rdquo; at that exact moment in time; I became a philosopher then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought a lot about life and death after that episode. What is the meaning of life, or of death? And most of all, what do we choose, and why do we choose? What is honor?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My questioning may have begun at seven, but it has not yet ended. I do not have the final answer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that one TV episode got me started on a lifelong philosophical journey. When I was older, I studied the Christian Bible, which is all about exploring what it means to live and die: Jesus dying and living again, and the command to be &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=Romans%206&#34;&gt;dead to sin but alive in Christ&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, there is also the controversial choice of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Socrates&#34;&gt;Socrates&lt;/a&gt; to commit suicide, which I read various conflicting opinions about: when I had just finished high school, the book &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ifstone.org/trial_of_socrates.php&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Trial of Socrates&amp;rdquo; by I.F. Stone came out&lt;/a&gt; that was very provocative and turned me against Socrates, whom I had earlier considered a hero, from reading Plato&amp;rsquo;s dialogues about him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was also bothered but fascinated by the lore that &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gautama_Buddha&#34;&gt;Gautama Buddha&lt;/a&gt; deliberately ate rotting food in order not to offend his host, and died as a result.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And what of the controversial mass suicide by Jews at &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Masada&#34;&gt;Masada&lt;/a&gt;? Or that of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Self-immolation&#34;&gt;self-immolating&lt;/a&gt; Buddhist monks in Vietnam?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In college, I took a philosophy course by &lt;a href=&#34;http://philosophy.columbia.edu/directories/faculty/frederick-neuhouser&#34;&gt;Frederick Neuhouser&lt;/a&gt; and studied Nietzsche, who had his character Zarathustra say, &lt;a href=&#34;http://4umi.com/nietzsche/zarathustra/21&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Die at the right time&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. I was profoundly affected by the challenges that Nietzsche threw at his readers. That course changed my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Very recently, Stoicism has become popularized as a living philosophy for today, with proponents such as &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ttbook.org/book/transcript/transcript-william-irvine-stoic-life&#34;&gt;William Irvine&lt;/a&gt;, who talks about &amp;ldquo;contemplation of death&amp;rdquo;. I very much enjoyed his book &lt;a href=&#34;http://global.oup.com/academic/product/a-guide-to-the-good-life-9780195374612&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;A Guide to the Good Life: the Ancient Art of Stoic Joy&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; not long after it came out; reading it in early 2011, I changed the course of my life. (Don&amp;rsquo;t forget that &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Seneca_the_Younger&#34;&gt;Seneca&lt;/a&gt; was also forced to commit suicide.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am fascinated by deliberate, reasoned decisions about life and death.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On rewatching a TV episode after over 30 years</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/04/23/on-rewatching-a-tv-episode-after-over-30-years/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Apr 2013 23:54:33 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/04/23/on-rewatching-a-tv-episode-after-over-30-years/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Over 30 years ago, when I was in elementary school in the 1970s, I watched the TV series &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lost_in_Space&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Lost in Space&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. It was very silly, but did engage my imagination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;nightmares&#34;&gt;Nightmares&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One episode haunted me for weeks and gave me nightmares, such that I remembered some scenes very clearly: it was the one in which I first encountered the term &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Antimatter&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;antimatter&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. For decades, once in a while I wondered whether I would ever get to see that episode again. I was particularly curious about whether my memories were accurate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;today&#34;&gt;Today&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that now, it is &lt;em&gt;probably&lt;/em&gt; possible to find any TV episode or even commercial that one saw in one&amp;rsquo;s childhood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, on a whim, I searched for the &amp;ldquo;Lost in Space&amp;rdquo; episode, and not only quickly identified it, but also watched it online for free!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0772539/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Anti-Matter Man&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, and I watched it on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.hulu.com/watch/23809&#34;&gt;Hulu&lt;/a&gt;. Of course, it was not really &amp;ldquo;free&amp;rdquo;, because I had to suffer through some ads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My memories turned out to be quite accurate, although of course not complete. &amp;ldquo;Evil&amp;rdquo; John Robinson was convincingly violent and evil, with the beatings and the cage. The landscape was stark and barren. The misty bridge between two worlds was as creepy as I remembered it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The episode was really quite a dark one, perhaps too dark for me at the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Needless to say, as one who eventually obtained a physics degree, I have to say that the whole scenario is complete nonsense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;future&#34;&gt;Future&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The temptation can be high to relive the past by rewatching old TV shows, the way I used to listen to old music recordings for sentimental reasons. I&amp;rsquo;ve almost completely resisted this temptation in the past several years, but sometimes it is illuminating to compare one&amp;rsquo;s memories with reality, and also reflect on the changes in taste or maturity.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>