<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Meditation on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/meditation/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Meditation on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/meditation/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>How I forgot to meditate after sixty days in a row of remembering and what that means</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/01/24/how-i-forgot-to-meditate-after-sixty-days-in-a-row-of-remembering-and-what-that-means/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2015 13:58:29 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/01/24/how-i-forgot-to-meditate-after-sixty-days-in-a-row-of-remembering-and-what-that-means/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I woke up this morning feeling very tired. I also suddenly realized that yesterday, I forgot to set aside time for the daily meditation practice (just ten minutes a day) that I had successfully done for &lt;em&gt;sixty days in a row&lt;/em&gt;, having deliberately started it &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/11/24/report-on-my-first-day-of-stoic-week-2014/&#34;&gt;shortly before Thanksgiving&lt;/a&gt;. I was pretty angry at myself. But I also thought about how it was possible that I slipped after sixty days, and what that means.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-s-my-meditation-schedule&#34;&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s my meditation schedule?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The optimal way to maintain any habit is to make it as rigid and automatic as possible. Several years ago, when I went months at a time without missing a single day, my system was to meditate first thing in the morning, before eating or exercising or anything else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I confess that I still don&amp;rsquo;t have that kind of rigid schedule yet. Much of the time, I do meditate first thing. Other times, I feel pressed for time and want to get some work done. Or I&amp;rsquo;m feeling very hungry and decide to eat breakfast first. But usually I do complete meditation in the morning. Occasionally I &amp;ldquo;forget&amp;rdquo; but then remember well before bedtime, and get it in before sleeping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-my-forgetting-yesterday-says-about-my-life&#34;&gt;What my forgetting yesterday says about my life&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, I was feeling tired when I woke, because of a week of accumulated fatigue from doing many things, including going out last night with Abby for the second week of blues dance class at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.tartanswing.com/&#34;&gt;Tartan Swing&lt;/a&gt; at CMU. Adding an extra evening out every week is requiring some changes in how much other stuff I can get done in evenings, and apparently I have not scaled back enough to make up for that additional commitment; it is always a struggle for me to &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/12/15/thoughts-on-giving-up-an-old-project-to-make-room-for-the-new/&#34;&gt;give up something to make room for something else&lt;/a&gt;, but especially on short notice, since we had not originally planned, in December, to start checking out Tartan Swing this January!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, yesterday was Friday, and I tend to feel I have many things to try to get done on Friday. I ate breakfast immediately, did work stuff, then since I was scheduled to go for a run, I did that. I&amp;rsquo;ve been ramping up on my run distances, and I ran my second longest distance so far this month: the length was the sum of the length of my Monday and Wednesday runs this week! So that took more energy than I am used to yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I came home from work, I was extremely tired and hungry, to the point that I decided I wanted to eat a whole lot of food and do something different, so Abby and I went out for dinner. I came home totally stuffed. In any case, going out was an unscheduled, spontaneous decision, and by the time we came home, none of the whole day had gone according to my usual pattern. And so I somehow forgot to get in meditation before going to bed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;lessons-learned&#34;&gt;Lessons learned&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first lesson is that just because I missed one day of meditation after sixty in a row, that doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean I&amp;rsquo;ve lost everything. I meditated today, and will continue my practice. It&amp;rsquo;s important to recover as quickly as possible, to avoid what has happened to me before, which is to feel ashamed, start identifying (after too many days in a row missed) as a &amp;ldquo;non-meditator&amp;rdquo;, and give up the practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other is that I&amp;rsquo;m definitely overbooked and need to make sure I get rest, and get back on schedule for what I can manage to do. A busy week is coming up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What do you do when you find out that you&amp;rsquo;ve missed a day of meditation, exercise, or some other daily practice? Do you feel bad about yourself? Do you make excuses? Do you examine what is really important? Do you set up a system to prevent having to rely on will power? What is your latest experience of slipping, and how did you deal with it?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Report on my final day of Stoic Week 2014: the view from above</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/30/report-on-my-final-day-of-stoic-week-2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2014 22:16:07 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/30/report-on-my-final-day-of-stoic-week-2014/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s the seventh and final day of Stoic Week 2014! I am very glad I participated in the daily readings and reflections. I&amp;rsquo;ve made so many positive changes in my life already. Now it&amp;rsquo;s time to stick to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;health&#34;&gt;Health&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been spending all of the Thanksgiving long holiday weekend catching up on sleep. I have a meditation habit now and today it was warm out and I went for a run and ended up doing five miles in Frick Park. This is the longest distance I&amp;rsquo;ve run in months!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;nature-providence-the-larger-whole&#34;&gt;Nature, providence, the larger whole&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is fitting that today&amp;rsquo;s theme is the Stoic view of humanity as being embedded in something bigger, call it &amp;ldquo;nature&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;providence&amp;rdquo;. Part of why I enjoy running in the trails of Frick Park is that in its own small way, the experience puts me in touch &lt;em&gt;directly&lt;/em&gt; with something bigger than us; I encounter dogs, chipmunks, trees, creeks, leaves, mud, and even deer (not today, but Abby and I saw one during our hike there yesterday).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I honestly feel more whole and alive when I see more of nature, and not in some self-conscious sentimental way. It&amp;rsquo;s more subtle than that. And there&amp;rsquo;s nothing sentimental about those steep hills that make me gasp for air when I climb them. But I sure appreciate the cleaner air in the park than on the main urban roads of Pittsburgh! And I remember where air comes from and how fragile its quality and composition is. The big picture matters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am grateful for the organizers of Stoic Week for putting it on again this year. Here is something I&amp;rsquo;ve decided to do, to keep its spirit alive indefinitely: I will continue to explore various interpretations of Stoicism (note that I don&amp;rsquo;t feel compelled to buy into any particular school or even call myself a Stoic at all), as well as other philosophy (for example, the Zen I had begun looking into years ago) on a daily basis, to keep my mind always focused on applying principles of practical living.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Did you hear about Stoic Week this year? If you did, why did you choose to participate in it, or more interestingly, choose not to?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Report on my sixth day of Stoic Week 2014: preparing for adversity</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/29/report-on-my-sixth-day-of-stoic-week-2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Nov 2014 18:37:25 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/29/report-on-my-sixth-day-of-stoic-week-2014/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I guess death is the ultimate adversity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;whose-death-and-how-and-what-next&#34;&gt;Whose death and how and what next?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I fear death. Not only for myself, but for Abby, for her parents, for my parents, for our friends. We knew older people who have died even this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today&amp;rsquo;s Stoic theme, &amp;ldquo;preparing for adversity&amp;rdquo;, is particularly relevant to us because not only are our parents aging and already actively preparing for &amp;ldquo;what next&amp;rdquo; if they were to die or get sick and incapacitated, and trying to talk to us about such things, but also because being married, we need to have clear plans and instructions in case one of us suddenly goes. We are not invincible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;decluttering&#34;&gt;Decluttering&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing that makes us anxious is that there&amp;rsquo;s too much clutter in the house, and also clutter in the form of many random online accounts that we need to keep track of. We&amp;rsquo;ve seen how deaths in our families have caused a lot of trouble to survivors because of unfinished business, stuff left behind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel that part of preparing &lt;em&gt;mentally&lt;/em&gt; for adversity is preparing &lt;em&gt;in reality&lt;/em&gt; for adversity. I would have much more peace of mind if I knew that everything would continue as smoothly as possible at home and at work if I suddenly died.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So today I continued on a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/19/really-taking-up-the-challenge-of-minimalism/&#34;&gt;long-interrupted project&lt;/a&gt; of decluttering at home. I dug up old college course notes, exercise log books from a decade ago, and other stuff I just don&amp;rsquo;t need. Dozens of books I no longer read. I filled boxes of stuff to recycle or have Abby donate to the library. I am committed to leaving nothing accidental behind if I die, only what is purposeful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, we don&amp;rsquo;t have wills or the like yet. Time to get cracking on that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;adversity-more-generally&#34;&gt;Adversity, more generally&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel that &amp;ldquo;negative thinking&amp;rdquo; is very useful and that I could do more of it. As a software developer, anticipating failure modes helps me write better and more confident code. Playing chess, I know firsthand that wishful thinking results in big crashes when things don&amp;rsquo;t go your way. Teaching chess, I like to set up unpleasant situations and have the student struggle (in a safe, low stakes environment) to defend, as practice for real tournament chess when the strength to deal with the unexpected is a key to success in competition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;daily-habits&#34;&gt;Daily habits&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, I did meditate and exercise (more dumbbell and body weight strength training) today. Recall that yesterday I had a setback. The advantage of having once had a successful exercise routine is that when I think clearly, I am prepared for adversity, having faced it before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I appreciate the curious technique of envisioning and simulating future catastrophe in order to enable acting more calmly today. Figuring out death seems the ultimate challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How do you feel about the technique of deliberately imagining bad things? Does this seem perverse to you? Or useful?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Report on my fifth day of Stoic Week 2014: action and the reserve clause</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/28/report-on-my-fifth-day-of-stoic-week-2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2014 23:20:43 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/28/report-on-my-fifth-day-of-stoic-week-2014/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I had some setbacks today, the fifth day of Stoic Week, but dealt with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-coconut-oil-accident-yesterday-at-thanksgiving-party&#34;&gt;A coconut oil accident yesterday at Thanksgiving party&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the time we left &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/11/27/report-on-my-fourth-day-of-stoic-week-2014/&#34;&gt;yesterday&amp;rsquo;s Thanksgiving party&lt;/a&gt; in the evening, I wasn&amp;rsquo;t feeling so well. I had blamed eating that one cookie and also drinking a bit of spicy warm cider, but as unpleasant symptoms developed (you don&amp;rsquo;t need to know the details), I immediately knew what must have happened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A bit of history, years ago I experimented with &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/01/26/improving-my-breakfast-and-other-meals/&#34;&gt;using coconut oil&lt;/a&gt; but found that I could tolerate only a little bit, and in fact quickly decided to just not use it any more in cooking, after some incidents in which I experienced very unpleasant symptoms after a meal and found out that Abby had used a good amount of coconut oil in cooking. We had her limit the use of coconut oil in cooking anything I was to eat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it had been quite some time since I experienced those symptoms, but unfortunately, I suffered for over twelve hours with poor sleep overnight, and can only conclude that a large mount of coconut oil was used in Thanksgiving dinner!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-system-temporarily-wrecked-illustrating-today-s-theme&#34;&gt;My system temporarily wrecked, illustrating today&amp;rsquo;s theme&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I not only woke up late in the morning today, but was also still suffering physically, was hungry nonetheless, and grouchy. Normally I try to start my day with meditation, but I just wanted to eat breakfast. Abby had gotten up hours before me and was annoyed I had gotten up late, and snapped at me while I was bleary-eyed and trying to start eating breakfast. I snapped back, and she got very upset and disappeared.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While eating, I recognized that I had gone totally non-Stoic, and so after I finished eating and reading today&amp;rsquo;s theme on &amp;ldquo;action and the reserve clause&amp;rdquo;, I immediately went to meditate for ten minutes before talking with her again, in a much calmer mood, explaining what had been happening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went back to napping, and then before lunch time, after my final visit to the toilet, I finally felt like my coconut oil disaster was truly over and I could start my day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I felt I had &amp;ldquo;failed&amp;rdquo; in that, contrary to Stoic teaching, I had let my physical distress take over my mind and everything I was doing. I could have dealt better with my situation, acting the best I could despite my circumstance rather than giving into my foul mood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &amp;ldquo;reserve clause&amp;rdquo; in Stoicism refers to how we &lt;em&gt;act&lt;/em&gt; even though we may not like what has happened or what might happen. I did not start the morning with this attitude.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;exercise&#34;&gt;Exercise&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I eventually made up, but it really bothered me that I had started off the day so badly. I was also feeling like my muscles were trashed from yesterday&amp;rsquo;s workout (and party play with the two sisters). Later in the afternoon, we went for a hike in Frick Park and both felt better. I considered that my &amp;ldquo;exercise&amp;rdquo; for the day, a lower-intensity day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a setback in my practice of Stoicism but recovered, with even more appreciation for daily reading and study to get back on track.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How do you deal with setbacks? Do you have a system, a philosophical principle, to keep you on track?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Report on my fourth day of Stoic Week 2014: virtue and relationships with others</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/27/report-on-my-fourth-day-of-stoic-week-2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2014 21:47:45 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/27/report-on-my-fourth-day-of-stoic-week-2014/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today was Thanksgiving in the US, a surprisingly appropriate day to be in the middle of observing Stoic Week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;thanksgiving-dinner&#34;&gt;Thanksgiving dinner&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/11/27/report-on-my-third-day-of-stoic-week-2014/&#34;&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve reported on yesterday&amp;rsquo;s theme&lt;/a&gt; of self-discipline and simplicity. At Thanksgiving dinner this year, I decided for the very first time to limit what I ate. I&amp;rsquo;ve always overeaten in the past, with poor results. It was just something I did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year, I did not eat any of the cake or pumpkin pie that was offered. For dessert (after the turkey etc.), I limited myself to one scoop of pistachio gelato and one cookie. Actually, I ended up regretting that cookie, because it was more substantial and sugary than I expected, so I&amp;rsquo;ve made a note to watch myself with the cookies. The gelato I may not have needed, but I enjoyed it all the more knowing it was the one main dessert I was allowing myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;fourth-day-of-health-habits&#34;&gt;Fourth day of health habits&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s my fourth day now of daily meditation and exercise. Actually, I overdid it on the exercise today, but not intentionally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been increasing the intensity of my short (seven-minute or so) daily workouts every day, lifting heavier weights and working more muscles. What I didn&amp;rsquo;t expect was that at the Thanksgiving party, two young sisters (of ages around five and two) were bored and wanted to play, and I rather exerted myself. The older one was the ringleader. We played at scaring each other and I pretended to be sitting on the couch sleeping and suddenly spring up and boo or growl, and I accidentally pulled something in my right arm during one of these explosive, sudden movements. I also pulled my left shoulder when the two challenged me to lift them repeatedly, and the older one (tall for her age) was heavier than I expected and not so easy to repeatedly lift, given that I&amp;rsquo;d already had a workout in the morning at home. All in good fun, but left me a bit overextended.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;on-today-s-theme&#34;&gt;On today&amp;rsquo;s theme&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find sensible the Stoic teaching of developing our &amp;ldquo;natural affection&amp;rdquo;, and expanding outward from ourselves. I feel I have been the beneficiary of much good from many people in my life and am grateful for this. The Thanksgiving dinner that Abby and I went to today is one we have attended for some years now. The hosts I met through Abby, who met them (and other dinner guests) through music and dance circles. I appreciate and deeply admire the generosity that they have shown us and to many others. I look up to them as role models for the kind of genuine affection that human beings can display and share, not only with immediate family or closest friends but outward to larger communities (such as local music communities) and beyond.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tragic shooting and death that happened this year in &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shooting_of_Michael_Brown&#34;&gt;Ferguson, Missouri&lt;/a&gt; has been in the news for some months now, and this week the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shooting_of_Michael_Brown#Announcement_of_no_bill&#34;&gt;grand jury decided not to indict&lt;/a&gt;. I haven&amp;rsquo;t commented in public or in private on any of these events, or on any of the commentary about them, but I do not dismiss what has happened as irrelevant to my life. In fact, I feel that what has happened has been so important, in the biggest possible picture of what has been going on in American history for a long time, that I cannot afford to lightly spew sound bites about it. I do ask myself, how can I best talk about what I am feeling? How can I make a positive difference, in the Stoic &amp;ldquo;cosmopolitan&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;love of all humanity&amp;rdquo;? I don&amp;rsquo;t know the answer yet, but I know what is not the answer: fanning the flames of passion. But simply being silent is also not the answer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2015-01-19&#34;&gt;(Update of 2015-01-19)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wrote something in &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2015/01/19/for-martin-luther-king-jr-day-some-black-american-voices-that-spoke-to-me-recently/&#34;&gt;observation of Martin Luther King, Jr. Day&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I take seriously the Stoic call that we are ethically responsible for more than just ourselves, that we are to develop ourselves outward (not just on inner virtues) and work to honestly consider all human beings our brothers and sisters. I see how I have been treated in such a way by others through my life and aspire to expand beyond myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How do you feel about cosmopolitanism? Do you feel it is naive, that it is best to just look out after family and clan? If you have been following the Ferguson tragedy, do you easily choose a simple &amp;ldquo;side&amp;rdquo;, an &amp;ldquo;us&amp;rdquo; versus &amp;ldquo;them&amp;rdquo;?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Report on my third day of Stoic Week 2014: self-discipline and Stoic simplicity</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/27/report-on-my-third-day-of-stoic-week-2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2014 11:03:44 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/27/report-on-my-third-day-of-stoic-week-2014/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There is a reason I&amp;rsquo;m a little late in reporting on my third day of Stoic Week 2014: the theme, self-discipline and simplicity, had me cut short my intended plan of writing and publishing my thoughts at the end of each day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;health-and-self-control&#34;&gt;Health and self-control&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today&amp;rsquo;s reading for Stoic Week 2014 had us reflect on the importance of physical health and self-control in our daily routine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the third day in a row, I did a morning ten-minute sitting meditation, and noticed that my posture and breathing have improved. It took three days to notice this. It will take weeks to notice even more improvements; I know this because I&amp;rsquo;m a backslider, rather than one completely new to meditation. I imagine it must be much harder for a newcomer to adopt a practice like this where patience is required in order to experience the benefits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also kicked it up a notch with exercise. I mentioned in &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/11/25/report-on-my-second-day-of-stoic-week-2014/&#34;&gt;yesterday&amp;rsquo;s report&lt;/a&gt; that I need to do more weight training. I&amp;rsquo;m on that now. I&amp;rsquo;m making exercise a priority for the next several months in my life, at least.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve still been pretty good about refraining from unhealthy snacks. On &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/11/24/report-on-my-first-day-of-stoic-week-2014/&#34;&gt;day one&lt;/a&gt;, I noted that my work colleague brought back snacks from his first trip to Asia and I chose not to eat any of them. I opened up the bag of chips, but ate only a couple of them (in the past I have given into temptations, when confronted with a bag of chips, to eat the whole bag) and stashed the rest away. (By the way, the chips were unexceptional, tasting not much different than ordinary American potato chips, and the ingredients list was scary, with many weird chemicals included.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;sleep&#34;&gt;Sleep&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I haven&amp;rsquo;t been good with my sleep habits. I tend to stay up too late on the computer, for example. Abby wants me to have a &amp;ldquo;computer off plan&amp;rdquo; for my daily routine, but I&amp;rsquo;ve found this difficult because I like to work on personal projects (such as writing) on the computer and I find the time in the evening. I know the benefits of the &amp;ldquo;natural&amp;rdquo; life, and I&amp;rsquo;m sure Stoics would promote being a morning person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the point of this report isn&amp;rsquo;t to talk about becoming a morning person, or even so much about sleep. It&amp;rsquo;s about self-control. The reality is, yesterday when I came home from work, I was very tired. &amp;ldquo;Sleep when sleepy&amp;rdquo; is so logical and natural, yet I find that American culture does not value sleep. It seems countercultural to sleep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, I decided to simplify the evening and choose to stay off the computer (hence not writing this article). Apart from Wednesday evening being designed &amp;ldquo;us night&amp;rdquo; for Abby and me anyway, I decided that before sleeping, I would read (physical books and paper printouts) instead of use the computer, until ready to sleep. I did end up sleeping earlier. I did miss having the use of the computer to look up stuff that would have been helpful in my reading, but for this evening, at least, it was a tradeoff in favor of simplicity rather than stimulation. I&amp;rsquo;ll have to think about how to arrange my life differently if I want to continue to be more targeted in using the computer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Self-discipline and simplicity are not popular in American culture, which prizes maximization and stimulation. I don&amp;rsquo;t find it easy to maintain self-discipline, and am grateful to Stoic Week to remind me of its benefits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Is your gut impression of Stoic teachings that they want to take the fun out of your life, or that they are a guide to the truly good life? What is the balance you purposefully adopt between self-indulgence and renunciation?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Report on my second day of Stoic Week 2014: mindfulness</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/25/report-on-my-second-day-of-stoic-week-2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2014 23:50:38 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/25/report-on-my-second-day-of-stoic-week-2014/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, I reported on my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/11/24/report-on-my-first-day-of-stoic-week-2014/&#34;&gt;first day of Stoic Week 2014&lt;/a&gt;. Today, the second day&amp;rsquo;s theme was &amp;ldquo;Stoic mindfulness&amp;rdquo;. This is similar to the Buddhist teaching on mindfulness, and is basically a sound psychological observation that &amp;ldquo;You are just an impression and not at all the thing you claim to represent&amp;rdquo;: our thoughts and feelings are one thing but what we do about them is another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found it particularly useful to remember this today, because Tuesdays present an interesting challenge for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;chess&#34;&gt;Chess&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Tuesday nights, I have been playing in the latest 6-round current Tuesday night &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburghcc.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Chess Club&lt;/a&gt; tournament, one round every Tuesday. Tonight was round 4. I had experienced an extremely painful loss last week in round 3 when I was &lt;em&gt;not mindful&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://chessimprover.com/blockading-to-defend-when-things-get-tough/&#34;&gt;got carried away by emotions&lt;/a&gt;: I had an overwhelming advantage during an attack on my opponent&amp;rsquo;s King, but I allowed my excitement to cloud my judgment, make poor moves, and then worse, after I managed to recover and had the opportunity to survive with a draw, &lt;em&gt;and saw this&lt;/em&gt;, I passed it up out of wishful thinking that I could continue an attack, so I ended up losing. In chess, I face the stark reality that most losses at my level in local competition (where I am typically the top-rated player) are due to faulty psychology, rather than lack of sufficient understanding and skill. A loss of &lt;em&gt;objectivity&lt;/em&gt; (which all athletes and other performers under high pressure) is the reason we fail. Mindfulness directly addresses this all-too-human flaw.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;continuing-habits-from-yesterday&#34;&gt;Continuing habits from yesterday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, I noted that I began meditating and exercising again, because it was in my power to do so. I have continued. It&amp;rsquo;s been tricky to get going again, because my body is out of whack, but I remember to do what I can, no more, with faith that incremental progress will pay off. Instead of running, I did a &lt;a href=&#34;http://well.blogs.nytimes.com/projects/workouts/&#34;&gt;7-minute workout&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;ve lost a lot of strength over the years and plan to regain it. I have dumbbells lying around the house from when I was using them a decade ago; it&amp;rsquo;s time to get back to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;tonight-s-chess-game&#34;&gt;Tonight&amp;rsquo;s chess game&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I won a decent game tonight at the chess tournament. It was the third last to finish, taking almost four hours. I&amp;rsquo;ve played against my opponent many times before over the years, mostly winning, but the last time I played him, he held me to a draw, despite a 500-rating-point difference (which is huge). One thing that sometimes happens in tournament chess is overconfidence when facing someone who is on paper much weaker, or fear because of a past bad result. Mindfulness teaches us that although historical facts are facts, we should distance ourselves from distracting feelings about them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As in many hard-fought chess games, I experienced a range of emotions during the game. First of all, in the opening, although I was doing OK, I was frustrated that I allowed a certain kind of position I ordinarily do not allow, because of an oversight. Instead of kicking myself, I focused to do what I could with what I had, assessing that even though I did not want that position, it was actually still OK for me. (Actually, computer analysis afterwards showed that I was more than OK, so I was still more pessimistic than warranted during the game.) In the middlegame, I emerged with an advantage, but then faced a curious choice. My opponent gave me an opportunity to win some material (a Rook for a Bishop and Pawn) at the expense of destroying my Pawn structure and therefore creating good chances for a draw. At the time, I saw no better winning try, so I went for it, deciding that, unlike last week, I was going to settle for a draw if my opponent could prove he could defend; I simply made sure to play soundly and not recklessly. It turned out that he cracked eventually and I won. I was pleased that I remained psychologically strong in the game and was rewarded accordingly. (For those of you interested in the technical details of the game, I will be annotating it in an upcoming article I will write for &lt;a href=&#34;http://chessimprover.com/category/franklin-chen/&#34;&gt;my weekly column in The Chess Improver&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;heavy-traffic&#34;&gt;Heavy traffic&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another thing: when driving home from work to eat dinner before the chess game, I noticed that the traffic was unusually bad. Mindfulness is always helpful when facing stressful situations like this. I was upset with myself for not anticipating apparent pre-Thanksgiving-holiday traffic and therefore being pressed for time to get home and eat dinner before playing chess. I decided to let go of my self-annoyance because it wasn&amp;rsquo;t going to help me get home any sooner and would just sap my mental energy I needed for my game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mindfulness is something I&amp;rsquo;ve had prior experience in trying to adopt well before I even read about Stoicism. But having a daily theme and reading during Stoic Week has been surprisingly helpful in keeping me aware.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Are you familiar with the concept of mindfulness and the scientific underpinnings of it? If so, do you deliberately practice it? Do you have misgivings about it?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Report on my first day of Stoic Week 2014</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/24/report-on-my-first-day-of-stoic-week-2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2014 22:30:51 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/24/report-on-my-first-day-of-stoic-week-2014/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Last year, I heard about the first Stoic Week, &lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.exeter.ac.uk/stoicismtoday/stoic-week-2013/&#34;&gt;Stoic Week 2013&lt;/a&gt;, but did not participate because I was distracted at the time and did not feel like focusing. This week, I decided it was time to sign up for &lt;a href=&#34;http://modernstoicism.com/course/view.php?id=5&#34;&gt;Stoic Week 2014&lt;/a&gt;, and I did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-my-interest-in-stoicism&#34;&gt;Why my interest in Stoicism?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve mentioned Stoicism only briefly in my blog: once in 2012 when &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/11/22/thanking-the-best-of-all-possible-worlds/&#34;&gt;thinking about Thanksgiving&lt;/a&gt; and once earlier this year after &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/01/17/hiroo-onoda-and-the-six-million-dollar-man/&#34;&gt;rewatching an old TV episode&lt;/a&gt;. As I mentioned, it was in 2011, upon reading a book on Stoicism, that I made some major changes in my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that a couple of weeks ago, I decided to make major changes in my life again, but not while thinking about Stoicism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over a year ago, my meditation practice fell apart, and I never really regained it. As a result, my thoughts and habits have become disordered, I have felt. For example, I stopped writing regularly for my blog. I spent too much time on Facebook and Twitter instead, being distracted, annoyed, and worse, behaving in ways that I later came to feel counterproductive. I did &amp;ldquo;quit&amp;rdquo; Facebook in July, and also &amp;ldquo;quit&amp;rdquo; Twitter some weeks ago (part of the big life changes I set in motion), but still, I have felt ungrounded. I decided Stoic Week 2014 would be a good opportunity for me to return to the contemplative life that Buddhism and Stoicism in their different ways aspire to and that I had forgotten.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-i-did-the-first-day-of-stoic-week-2014&#34;&gt;What I did the first day of Stoic Week 2014&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, as I started the first day of Stoic Week 2014, I began by meditating ten minutes, Zen style. &lt;em&gt;This was my first meditation session in weeks&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I read the assigned text for today in the Stoic Week handbook, on &amp;ldquo;What is in our power?&amp;rdquo; A basic principle of Stoicism is that we should know what is under our control and what is not, and summarily refuse to dwell on or resent what is not under our control, and focus on making good decisions about what is under our control. A very simple but powerful concept, especially in a world in which it is easy to get annoyed or angry about many things we hear about in the news or encounter in our daily lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My exercise habit has been very spotty for months now. Well, today I reflected that, what the hell, it is completely under my control whether I choose to exercise or not, so why am I wasting this precious freedom? Some people don&amp;rsquo;t have this freedom. Others, including prisoners in jail, have little freedom but make use of what they have, and &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/17/the-joys-of-convict-conditioning-bodyweight-exercising/&#34;&gt;they exercise&lt;/a&gt;! It happened to be warm outside today, so I really had no excuse. I went for a run in Frick Park. It was short, less than three miles long, but I went. &lt;em&gt;This was my first run in weeks&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was my turn to cook today at home, so I made a substantial beef casserole dish. Abby has (rightfully) complained in the past when I didn&amp;rsquo;t completely clean up after cooking. Well, today I thought to myself that it is completely within my control whether I choose to attend to the details of cleanup as much as I attend to the details of using our skillets and baking pans. So I cleaned up as well as I could.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have not been feeling very well physically for weeks now since an incident involving emergency dental work that somehow resulted in complications. I am still in recovery. OK, so it is not under my control that I am not in good health right now. But what is under my control? After lunch I took a nap, because I felt like I needed it. I have been skimping on naps, but this is stupid, because I know that sleep is the best restorative practice when ill. It is under my control whether I choose to set aside time to sleep as needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At work, a colleague just came back from his first trip in Asia. He gave me samples of some odd snacks: chips, cookies, and candy. In recent months, I would have opened them up and eaten them on the spot. Indeed, I have been having problems with eating too many snacks for no rational reason. Today, I decided that it is up to me whether I choose to give in to random cravings or temptations, and so I chose to put the snacks aside for later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After work, I went to a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/Pittsburgh-Code-Supply/events/210396972/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Code and Supply Build Night&lt;/a&gt;, where food was served. Apart from a Thanksgiving dinner (!), some kind of cake lurked around. I took one glance, and chose not to even look at it again until leaving (when it was already all eaten).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leaving Build Night, I found myself annoyed that it was taking forever for the pedestrian light to change, but caught myself and observed that, first of all, the cycle is as it is, beyond my control; and second, I had mistakenly assumed that someone had pressed the button, so it was my fault I had to wait so long. I pressed the button and eventually got to cross. Next, while driving home, I made the mistake of driving behind a bus, which kept stopping. I got annoyed, not by the bus, but by myself, for mistakenly driving on the wrong street rather than the other one that does not have this problem; I got annoyed that I was too lazy to make a U-turn on the street I was parked on in order to get to that other street. But I stopped myself when I realized that what was done was done, and I simply had to endure the rest of the drive home behind the bus because it was not going to save any more time if I detoured around it late in the game: the best I can do is to be more careful in the future when making choices while driving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I felt I improved my life today by keeping in mind the fundamental Stoic principle of observing what is not under my control and what is under my control. I look forward to continuing to adopt this outlook for the rest of the week, and beyond that.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Emerging from my three months of illness, self-pitying, and self-loathing</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/08/10/emerging-from-my-three-months-of-illness-self-pitying-and-self-loathing/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Aug 2013 08:39:23 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/08/10/emerging-from-my-three-months-of-illness-self-pitying-and-self-loathing/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, I reported on my feelings after &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/08/09/getting-up-when-reality-punches-you-in-the-face-running-the-second-liberty-mile-in-pittsburgh/&#34;&gt;having a very painful and embarrassing performance in the Liberty Mile road race&lt;/a&gt;. I resolved to slowly return myself to health and fitness, starting &lt;em&gt;immediately&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, Leo Babauta wrote a great blog post that really spoke to me, &lt;a href=&#34;http://zenhabits.net/fraud/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Fear of Being Found a Fraud&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. Basically, he writes advice, but he&amp;rsquo;s not perfect, and doesn&amp;rsquo;t always successfully do what he preaches. I periodically have feelings like that, since I write about stuff too and also post &amp;ldquo;advice&amp;rdquo; links on Twitter, Facebook, and Google+. What would people think if they knew I have been failing myself in the past three months?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, I have to be honest. There&amp;rsquo;s no point lying. I sometimes &lt;em&gt;know&lt;/em&gt; what&amp;rsquo;s best and what has worked for me, but don&amp;rsquo;t take my own advice. This in itself is not the big problem. The real problem is the second-order problem, which is that of believing that I&amp;rsquo;m not only imperfect (we all are), but sometimes ending also deciding to give up on myself. That&amp;rsquo;s the worst thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, after health conditions disrupted my &amp;ldquo;normal&amp;rdquo; routines, I ended up not getting back on track when in fact I should and could have, through a gradual process. In a way, I was too proud to &lt;em&gt;adapt to reality&lt;/em&gt;. I was willing to operate under a different, better reality, but given the worse one, I chickened out, and entered a downward spiral of bad habits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;meditation-habit-destroyed&#34;&gt;Meditation habit, destroyed&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/02/01/a-report-on-one-month-of-daily-meditation/&#34;&gt;restarted a daily meditation practice for the new year&lt;/a&gt;, and entered into a 100-day meditation challenge. I encountered setbacks in my first month, but kept bouncing back. I even &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/01/dealing-with-setbacks-during-my-second-month-of-meditation/&#34;&gt;continued into a second month&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then things got worse, and as you can see in the archives to my blog, I &lt;em&gt;never wrote a report for the third month&lt;/em&gt;. According to my &lt;a href=&#34;http://insighttimer.com/&#34;&gt;Insight Timer&lt;/a&gt; journal, I actually did meditate in March almost every day, so I could have written a blog post on that, but I didn&amp;rsquo;t. &lt;em&gt;That was a mistake&lt;/em&gt;. I have found that public updates on progress keep me more accountable to myself; this is why I have written so much about my personal musical activities: not only to share my journey with those who are interested (because they are friends or because they are themselves on their own journeys), but also to keep myself honest about where I&amp;rsquo;ve been, what I still need to do, where I intend to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In April, my meditation practice started to fall apart. I missed April 10 and 11, then 13, 14, 15, then 18, 19, 20, 20, 23, and the rest of the month. In May I was erratic, till after May 13, &lt;em&gt;I completely stopped identifying myself as a &amp;ldquo;meditator&amp;rdquo; and quit&lt;/em&gt;. That&amp;rsquo;s right: I felt so ashamed of myself that I did not meditate between May 14 and August 9 this year. Big mistake, this pointless shame, especially given that I know, empirically, that &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/30/when-i-dont-have-time-to-sit-and-breathe-something-is-wrong-with-my-life/&#34;&gt;when I don&amp;rsquo;t &amp;ldquo;have time&amp;rdquo; to meditate, something is wrong with my life&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;exercise&#34;&gt;Exercise&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, my exercise schedule completely fell apart. &amp;ldquo;Normally&amp;rdquo;, I run every other day and do strength training the other days. None of this has to be a super-long session. Just enough to keep me mentally and physically alert. My strength training has generally been just a simple half-hour &amp;ldquo;core performance&amp;rdquo; type of workout at home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, I lost the habit, partially because marathon training caused me to cut back on strength training and because after the marathon, I took a break from running. The big lesson I learned here is that marathoning is very disruptive to my ordinary life, and I do not plan to ever do a marathon again in my life. But apart from that, I had non-marathon disruptions also, such as the skin rash after a hike that I&amp;rsquo;ve been dealing with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-i-did-today&#34;&gt;What I did today&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Today is the first day of the rest of my life.&lt;/strong&gt; Clean slate, forget the past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I meditated this morning. And I will continue to make this a high priority and do it daily. I must make sure that if I slip, I simply get back on track, rather than feel shame or whatever. It must simply be a habit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I ran yesterday, today was a non-running day. I decided that one way to prevent myself from completely slipping is to have a backup &amp;ldquo;very short&amp;rdquo; workout in case any kind of laziness or disruption causes me to think about just canceling a workout rather than do a longer one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So today was my first experiment with a &lt;a href=&#34;http://medium.com/editors-picks/e4975b151181&#34;&gt;7-minute workout&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s intense, but fast to get over with. I highly recommend checking it out!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are more links to this type of workout:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://journals.lww.com/acsm-healthfitness/Fulltext/2013/05000/HIGH_INTENSITY_CIRCUIT_TRAINING_USING_BODY_WEIGHT_.5.aspx&#34;&gt;Journal paper&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://7minworkoutapp.com/&#34;&gt;Online app&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifehack.org/articles/lifestyle/master-the-7-minute-workout-with-this-video.html&#34;&gt;Lifehack article&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if you&amp;rsquo;re lazy, surely you have 7 minutes a day to squeeze in this little circuit. I did!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-future&#34;&gt;The future&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back to meditating every day, just 10 minutes a day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I&amp;rsquo;m going to take it easy to ramp back up to fitness. I know it&amp;rsquo;s going to take &lt;em&gt;months&lt;/em&gt; to get back to where I was earlier in the year. &lt;em&gt;Patience is a virtue&lt;/em&gt;. I will start small. A little bit of slow running every other day, and the 7-minute workout every other day, to get started, before extending further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was time to stop my descent into endless self-pitying and self-loathing over all the misfortunes that have come my way in the past months. I&amp;rsquo;m taking my life back.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dealing with setbacks during my second month of meditation</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/03/01/dealing-with-setbacks-during-my-second-month-of-meditation/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Mar 2013 10:50:25 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/03/01/dealing-with-setbacks-during-my-second-month-of-meditation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A month ago, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/02/01/a-report-on-one-month-of-daily-meditation/&#34;&gt;I reported on my meditation practice in January 2013&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The month of February was even more problematic for me than January was. I&amp;rsquo;ve noticed a pattern that January tends to start our fairly well, because of rebooting after the winter holidays, but then &amp;ldquo;feature creep&amp;rdquo; catches up in life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; manage to meditate every single day, but thanks to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://insighttimer.com/&#34;&gt;Insight Timer&lt;/a&gt; mobile app I use, with its &amp;ldquo;journal&amp;rdquo; feature, I have a lot of when I did and my brief thoughts after each session.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;problems&#34;&gt;Problems&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;breaking-the-chain-for-the-first-time&#34;&gt;Breaking the chain for the first time&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I first &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/26/i-dont-feel-like-practicing-but-im-gonna-do-it-anyway/&#34;&gt;broke my chain&lt;/a&gt; of daily meditation on Wednesday, February 6. This was the day after a long &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/02/05/pittsburgh-chess-club-championship-2013-round-4-fascinating-attacking-defending-game/&#34;&gt;chess tournament game in the evening&lt;/a&gt;. According to my journal, I was very busy with exercise, work, and starting to pack for the &lt;a href=&#34;http://nescala.org/&#34;&gt;NE Scala&lt;/a&gt; conference that &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/02/10/ne-scala-2013-my-first-scala-conference/&#34;&gt;I was going to&lt;/a&gt; travel to Philadelphia for the next day, Thursday (which I took off from work). I ended up &amp;ldquo;forgetting&amp;rdquo; to meditate, and then staying up late, until I realized I had forgotten, and so it was past midnight when I did the meditation session, so it counted for Thursday rather than Wednesday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The piling up of being &amp;ldquo;too busy&amp;rdquo; clearly wrecked my routine. In retrospect, the only solution is to plan better when my routine is going to be broken up by travel or other significant disruptions. Also, there was the matter of just having too much in my routine anyway: I did recognize that Tuesday night chess tournaments were clearly  causing me to stay up too late at night, and so decided already in late January to &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/30/why-and-how-i-am-going-to-run-the-2013-pittsburgh-marathon/&#34;&gt;stop playing in them&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: I did manage to get in my daily meditation while at the conference, using the Android version of the app. I squeezed it in on the floor of the hotel suite I shared with Josh and Jamie while they were in the other room.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-one-minute-meditation-session&#34;&gt;A one-minute meditation session&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Monday, February 11 was a tough day for me (still recovering from the conference trip, and going back to work) and more so for Abby, who broke her foot late at night coming back from mandolin rehearsal. We spent nearly two hours at the emergency room (time mostly spent waiting; we spent another two hours Tuesday morning), during which I decided to steal a quiet minute meditating, so I did a &lt;em&gt;one-minute&lt;/em&gt; meditation using the mobile app at one point. In my whole meditation log, this is the only time in the past two months that I did anything other than a ten-minute meditation on a day when I meditated at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next two weeks of our lives were very tough. I put aside most of what I had planned to do in my life during that period, in order to take care of &lt;em&gt;our&lt;/em&gt; life, but I made sure to meditate every day. I think having the meditation practice really helped a lot, actually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;problems-with-the-evening-schedule&#34;&gt;Problems with the evening schedule&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I never got back onto a reliable morning meditation schedule, although I did continue to meditate before bed. But because of variability in my schedule, I again missed a daily evening session, by mere minutes, on Monday, February 25, when I had a crazy busy day that concluded with &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/02/25/stepping-it-up-at-the-french-and-blues-jam/&#34;&gt;not only stopping by OpenHack Pittsburgh but also attending a music jam&lt;/a&gt;. I didn&amp;rsquo;t forget to meditate; I just stayed up too late for the session to count for Monday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, the real solution is to get the meditation in early in the morning. Having a better home evening routine would also help: I have found that if I stay out too late outside the home for some event, I end up &amp;ldquo;shifting&amp;rdquo; my schedule at home rather than cutting things out that I would normally do during an evening staying at home. Abby has advised me on this and I agree with her that this is the right thing to do. On days when I&amp;rsquo;m out in the evening, I simply cannot expect to have the time to do what I would normally do when not out. I should not shift, but should cut out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite all the setbacks, I still keep on meditating. It is easy to stop doing something when you realize you&amp;rsquo;re doing it &amp;ldquo;badly&amp;rdquo;. It is easy to say &amp;ldquo;what&amp;rsquo;s the point?&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;ll never get this right&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m a loser&amp;rdquo;. But I keep in mind that meditation is meditation, however it is done. I don&amp;rsquo;t stop flossing my teeth just because I don&amp;rsquo;t always do it perfectly, after all. And sometimes the benefits do not become apparent until an unexpected turn (such as Abby&amp;rsquo;s accident) that showcases the need to be present and calm in the face of challenges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s been two months now since New Year. Do you have New Year habits that you threw yourself into with enthusiasm that you have now fallen away from or are ashamed of not keeping up the way you had hoped? How have you coped with your own imperfection?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-08-10&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-08-10)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I never wrote up a report on March meditation, or April, or my giving up meditation in May. Here is an &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/08/10/emerging-from-my-three-months-of-illness-self-pitying-and-self-loathing/&#34;&gt;explanation of what happened and how I decided to get back on track&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A report on one month of daily meditation</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/02/01/a-report-on-one-month-of-daily-meditation/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Feb 2013 21:00:58 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/02/01/a-report-on-one-month-of-daily-meditation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/30/when-i-dont-have-time-to-sit-and-breathe-something-is-wrong-with-my-life/&#34;&gt;As promised a month ago&lt;/a&gt;, here is a report on a month of meditation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite some real challenges, I managed to complete a month of daily meditation, and found some tricks and strategies to keep going, and will report again in another month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;virtual-communities&#34;&gt;Virtual communities&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By coincidence, as the New Year began, I found that a blog I occasionally look at, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wildmind.org/&#34;&gt;Wildmind&lt;/a&gt;, had issued a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wildmind.org/blogs/on-practice/join-us-for-wildminds-100-day-meditation-challenge&#34;&gt;100 day meditation challenge&lt;/a&gt;. I took this as a great opportunity to join a virtual &amp;ldquo;community&amp;rdquo; of meditators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;insight-timer-http-insighttimer-com&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://insighttimer.com/&#34;&gt;Insight Timer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that a mobile app called &lt;a href=&#34;http://insighttimer.com/&#34;&gt;Insight Timer&lt;/a&gt; was promoted, and I ended up immediately buying it for both iOS (for our iPad) and Android (for my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/22/paradox-i-will-observe-the-national-day-of-unplugging-but-just-bought-my-first-smartphone-this-week/&#34;&gt;phone&lt;/a&gt;). I had intended to buy a meditation app anyway, since it was time for me to stop being stingy (I had been using an adware version of a meditation app on iOS earlier).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I liked that this app not only existed on both iOS and Android (I expected to use the meditation app on my phone in case of travel and when finding quiet moments out of the home in general), but also provided a virtual community that showed who is meditating &amp;ldquo;with&amp;rdquo; you at any moment around the world using the app. When the going gets tough, I find it useful to remember that other people are also doing what they can to maintain their meditation practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;problems&#34;&gt;Problems&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as has happened repeatedly before, challenges popped up as the month progressed. For various reasons, my schedule was modified and so was Abby&amp;rsquo;s, and since we again had tried to meditate together, this led to some tough situations when we didn&amp;rsquo;t get in meditation as our first activity in the morning upon getting out of bed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first hope was that, well, we missed that moment, but maybe we could make it up later in the day. So on a weekend, if we got up at different times, maybe we could meditate before lunch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was a big mistake. It is very difficult to get back together to meditate when we have both started our days with numerous chores that we don&amp;rsquo;t want to interrupt. In fact, we ended up twice in January having fights in which Abby did not want to meditate when I was ready to do so, and the conflicts in turn made me not want to meditate either. In any case, it was very stressful negotiating every single day whether we would meditate together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;solutions&#34;&gt;Solutions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fundamental solution was to decouple meditation from Abby, who clearly did not particularly value meditation. People will differ on what they consider priorities in their lives. It was a fundamental mistake returning to my faint hope that Abby and I would sustain a joint meditation practice. I have to take &lt;em&gt;full responsibility&lt;/em&gt; for my own practice, just as I have again done so with my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/28/meditations-on-climbing-the-36-floors-of-the-pitt-cathedral-of-learning/&#34;&gt;physical exercise&lt;/a&gt;, which had also been disrupted once I met Abby years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby made a good suggestion, which was that I should meditate by myself, but we could sometimes meditate together also, but that this should be considered a supplemental activity because it might or might not happen any given day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other thing to note is that even after this decoupling of meditation activity, I was still having some problems with meditation because of the changes in my own routines, so by no means was Abby to blame for my difficulties. Often I felt &amp;ldquo;rushed&amp;rdquo; to get stuff done upon waking up, and delayed meditation to before bedtime. This was a symptom that something was wrong with my life, of course. If I can&amp;rsquo;t spare 10 minutes in the morning to meditate, and am really so &amp;ldquo;busy&amp;rdquo;, then clearly I have too many things going on in my life. January turned out to be much busier than I had originally wanted. This happened despite my previous knowledge that for many people, January ends up too busy because of decisions to take up new habits at the beginning of the year! Oops. I hope I start January 2014 better than I did January 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite setbacks, I did manage to go through an entire month of January with daily meditation. I will, of course, report back after the month of February on my progress in the 100 day meditation challenge.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>When I don&#39;t have time to sit and breathe, something is wrong with my life</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/12/30/when-i-dont-have-time-to-sit-and-breathe-something-is-wrong-with-my-life/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Dec 2012 16:35:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/12/30/when-i-dont-have-time-to-sit-and-breathe-something-is-wrong-with-my-life/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/zafus.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Our two zafus&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s been a long time since I&amp;rsquo;ve mentioned &lt;em&gt;meditation&lt;/em&gt; here. In fact, it&amp;rsquo;s been &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/02/23/saying-no-in-order-to-say-yes/&#34;&gt;ten months&lt;/a&gt;! This despite my knowledge of &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/02/02/2-new-daily-habits-of-mine-in-a-distracting-world/&#34;&gt;how beneficial it is&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a reason: I completely lost my &lt;em&gt;meditation practice&lt;/em&gt; at some point this year. I don&amp;rsquo;t even remember when I lost it. It may have had something to do with the fact that the iPad app we had been using as a meditation timer suddenly stopped making sound and we didn&amp;rsquo;t know why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yeah, what a sad excuse. But this is &lt;em&gt;exactly&lt;/em&gt; how, when one&amp;rsquo;s practice is already in trouble, any trivial glitch (so easily solved one way or another) is an excuse to stop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I have periodically &amp;ldquo;tried&amp;rdquo; to get back on, but as Yoda wisely said,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Try not! Do, or do not. There is no try.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/BQ4yd2W50No&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So now what?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;do&#34;&gt;Do&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;ve decided to &amp;ldquo;do&amp;rdquo;. This meant having to discuss the various reasons and chain reactions that lead to not doing meditation, and how to head them off. Meditation &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/02/10/meditation-is-hard/&#34;&gt;can be hard&lt;/a&gt;, but really, sitting and breathing for just &lt;em&gt;ten minutes&lt;/em&gt; in the morning is, objectively, not so hard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s not hard to realize that if I am so &amp;ldquo;busy&amp;rdquo; that I don&amp;rsquo;t have time to sit and breathe for ten minutes, &lt;em&gt;something is wrong with my life&lt;/em&gt;. Something has become unbalanced. Abby and I have had quite a year of many activities and experiences, but at some point, I started neglecting some basics. In particular, the last two months of this year have been something of a blur. Abby has tried to get us back to meditating, but I&amp;rsquo;ve resisted with some pretty bad excuses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But as of today, we are back. Being too &amp;ldquo;busy&amp;rdquo; means priorities are out of whack: did I really need to read those blog posts or tweets for ten minutes, instead of meditating? The answer is embarrassingly obvious when the mind is clear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, and as for the iPad meditation app: I checked the app and it&amp;rsquo;s making the start and end sounds just fine now. And if it didn&amp;rsquo;t, that wouldn&amp;rsquo;t stop us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meditation is good, and I&amp;rsquo;m back. In order to commit myself to keeping up the practice, I have decided that I should write about meditation on this blog at least once a month! It&amp;rsquo;s on my calendar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-02-01&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-02-01)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A report on &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/02/01/a-report-on-one-month-of-daily-meditation/&#34;&gt;my meditation in January 2013&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-03-01&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-03-01)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A report on &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/01/dealing-with-setbacks-during-my-second-month-of-meditation/&#34;&gt;my meditation in February 2013&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Saying No in order to say Yes</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/02/23/saying-no-in-order-to-say-yes/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Feb 2012 20:23:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/02/23/saying-no-in-order-to-say-yes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Lately I&amp;rsquo;ve been having to say &amp;ldquo;No&amp;rdquo; a lot to events and activities that appeal to me, in order to make room for &amp;ldquo;Yes&amp;rdquo;. Time and energy are finite for us every day and every week, and our &lt;a href=&#34;http://buddhism.about.com/b/2011/12/12/desires-are-inexhaustible.htm&#34;&gt;desires are inexhaustible&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, I wrote a post about &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/18/disagreement-on-the-use-of-time/&#34;&gt;how I use my time&lt;/a&gt;. A lot has changed since then, with various rebalancings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;music&#34;&gt;Music&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;listening-to-music&#34;&gt;Listening to music&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/02/i-love-music-but-rarely-listen-to-it-now/&#34;&gt;do not listen to music much&lt;/a&gt;, but I do more of it now than I did last year. I still minimize listening to recorded music (lately I listen to specific music that I am playing myself or attempting to), preferring to listen to live music where I don&amp;rsquo;t even know the program in advance. In particular, I&amp;rsquo;ve found it very stimulating to attend more &lt;a href=&#34;http://music.cmu.edu/index.php?sub_page=events&#34;&gt;Carnegie Mellon School of Music Convocations&lt;/a&gt;, which are targeted toward music students. One of my earliest blog posts was about going to a special convocation featuring &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/22/byron-janis-on-overcoming-adversity&#34;&gt;Byron Janis&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;ve been to some others since then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The group &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.fluteforce.org/&#34;&gt;Flute Force&lt;/a&gt; was here about a month ago for a convocation and of course I had to go, given how I&amp;rsquo;d gotten serious about playing flute. They gave a nice concert of a variety of music, all of which was unfamiliar to me and stimulating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/flute-force/flute-force-1.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Flute Force&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/flute-force/flute-force-2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Flute Force&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I went to a rather moving and thought-provoking presentation and performance by the violinist &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.myspace.com/sangeetosho&#34;&gt;Sangeet-Richard Downs&lt;/a&gt;, who was a CMU graduate. (I will write a blog post later about &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/RichardDownsmusic&#34;&gt;him&lt;/a&gt; and his message that completely resonates with me.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a &amp;ldquo;conventional&amp;rdquo; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.shadysideacademy.org/page.cfm?p=8593&#34;&gt;concert last Saturday&lt;/a&gt; by the Carnegie Mellon Chamber Orchestra that I was planning to take Abby to, and had already obtained tickets for, but this was an example of my saying &amp;ldquo;No&amp;rdquo; in order to say &amp;ldquo;Yes&amp;rdquo;: we decided instead to do &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/02/20/enjoying-more-french-dancing-in-pittsburgh&#34;&gt;French dancing&lt;/a&gt;. And there is no doubt we made the right decision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;playing-instruments&#34;&gt;Playing instruments&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lately, I&amp;rsquo;ve said &amp;ldquo;No&amp;rdquo; to practicing any musical instrument other than the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/02/22/flute-progress-still-hanging-in-there&#34;&gt;modern flute&lt;/a&gt;. I no longer practice the recorder, and have had to say &amp;ldquo;No&amp;rdquo; to the Friday evening gatherings that last year I was rather enjoying, and had led to my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/05/busy-evening-performing-at-phipps-followed-by-rehearsal-for-another-gig/&#34;&gt;performing at Phipps Conservatory&lt;/a&gt;. I told the recorder gang that I was going to return to recorder after my April 15 orchestra concert. This is an example of &amp;ldquo;No&amp;rdquo; meaning not &amp;ldquo;never again&amp;rdquo; but simply &amp;ldquo;not now&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, just today, Abby said the woman who &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/24/roaring-like-a-lion-on-a-saturday-morning/&#34;&gt;lent us an accordion&lt;/a&gt; for me to try out in case I wanted to buy it and take accordion needed to know whether we were buying it. Since I have barely touched accordion all these months, and will not be doing so for probably another half year at least, I said &amp;ldquo;No&amp;rdquo;, I am not prepared to buy it now. In the past I have bought stuff to use &amp;ldquo;sometime&amp;rdquo;, and this has only caused &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/19/really-taking-up-the-challenge-of-minimalism/&#34;&gt;clutter&lt;/a&gt;. (Yes, we are still incrementally decluttering, getting rid of stuff we don&amp;rsquo;t use. Just yesterday, I decided to throw away the remainder of my trophy and medal collections that no longer mean anything, except that I am still saving one trophy, from my winning the &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburghcc.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Chess Club&lt;/a&gt; Championship some years ago; I&amp;rsquo;m thinking of giving it back to the club so that they can remove my name plate and reuse it.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;dancing&#34;&gt;Dancing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One big change since last year is that Abby and I have gotten back into dancing again. Saying &amp;ldquo;Yes&amp;rdquo; to dancing has, of course, meant saying &amp;ldquo;No&amp;rdquo; to other things. For example, this year I have approximately halved my former blog output. I also reduced my Web reading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;meditation&#34;&gt;Meditation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, I didn&amp;rsquo;t have a daily meditation practice. &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/02/02/2-new-daily-habits-of-mine-in-a-distracting-world/&#34;&gt;Now I do&lt;/a&gt;. Just ten minutes a day in the morning, but it makes a difference. Saying &amp;ldquo;Yes&amp;rdquo; to meditation meant saying &amp;ldquo;No&amp;rdquo; to obsessively checking email and the like upon getting out of bed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;computer-usage-and-reading-books&#34;&gt;Computer usage and reading books&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A final tradeoff to mention is that my new habit of getting off the computer earlier in the evening, well before sleeping, has led me to do more paper book reading. Saying &amp;ldquo;Yes&amp;rdquo; to reading more books has been a good thing. I plan to start writing up reviews of the books I&amp;rsquo;ve been reading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;No&amp;rdquo; doesn&amp;rsquo;t just mean deprivation. It means making room for &amp;ldquo;Yes&amp;rdquo; too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What have you happily said &amp;ldquo;No&amp;rdquo; to that you wanted to do this year but decided not to do?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2014-01-16&#34;&gt;(Update of 2014-01-16)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ironically, I was just getting going with saying too much Yes even just as I was saying No, as I ended up taking two Coursera courses starting in late February: &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/04/13/free-course-review-software-engineering-for-software-as-a-service-part-i-from-coursera/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Software Engineering for Software as a Service (Part I)&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/06/16/review-of-coursera-course-model-thinking/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Model Thinking&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. As a result, I was really swamped from late February to June. I didn&amp;rsquo;t even have time to finish up reviews of the courses once I completed them, and only tried to fill in the gaps almost two years later!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The temptation after saying No is to take on new Yes. In retrospect, I should have been more careful.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Meditation is hard</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/02/10/meditation-is-hard/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Feb 2012 21:18:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/02/10/meditation-is-hard/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;About two weeks ago Abby and I started a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/02/02/2-new-daily-habits-of-mine-in-a-distracting-world/&#34;&gt;daily meditation practice&lt;/a&gt; in the morning. We&amp;rsquo;re still at it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently I&amp;rsquo;ve seen some articles about meditation &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.susanpiver.com/wordpress/2012/02/08/habit-2/&#34;&gt;habits&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wildmind.org/blogs/on-practice/how-we-use-effort-to-get-to-a-state-of-effortless-meditation&#34;&gt;difficulty&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The plain fact is that meditation is hard. There might be some kind of stereotype of meditation as &amp;ldquo;relaxing&amp;rdquo; or as blissing out or some such thing, but actually, meditation is quite hard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why is it so hard, and does putting effort into it somehow violate the point of it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;difficulty-of-meditation&#34;&gt;Difficulty of meditation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;physical&#34;&gt;Physical&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, there is always some &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/28/staring-at-the-wall-with-nowhere-to-go/&#34;&gt;physical difficulty&lt;/a&gt; in doing sitting meditation. Sitting &amp;ldquo;perfectly upright&amp;rdquo; is not easy for me when my legs are crossed and on the floor, because I&amp;rsquo;m not all that flexible where it matters (I&amp;rsquo;ve been working on that for years, with real incremental progress).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And because of asymmetry, I use a different &amp;ldquo;dominant&amp;rdquo; leg alternating
days. Trying to relax is difficult because the default result is
slumping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;mental&#34;&gt;Mental&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I slip into daydreams and weird thoughts very easily during meditation. I&amp;rsquo;ll have thoughts about things I need to do for the day, things I needed to do yesterday, or events coming up in weeks, or events in the past. In a single ten-minute session of meditation I might experience sadness over something, anxiety, anger, disgust, relief, excitement, you name it! My mind will go all over the place. If there are people who are blissing out doing meditation, I don&amp;rsquo;t know if I&amp;rsquo;m the same species as them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Way back when I first started meditation, my main problem was actually that I would get disappointed and disgusted about my thoughts during meditation, and this of course created a cycle of more unrest during meditation. I got one important insight out of this: that I had a lifelong habit of hating myself, of perfectionism that I needed to let go of. When I realized this, I was able to break the cycle, both in meditation and in my &amp;ldquo;regular&amp;rdquo; life. I still have silly thoughts during meditation, but the difference now is that I don&amp;rsquo;t let them take over. They are what they are, and I return to the breath, return to posture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, a year ago when I first started sitting with people, I got very self-conscious and worried about what they thought about my posture or breathing or whatever. After a couple of months, that anxiety completely disappeared. I&amp;rsquo;m doing what I&amp;rsquo;m doing; what is the point of adding extraneous thoughts and worries?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;effort&#34;&gt;Effort&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What level of effort do I apply when meditating? I think I go by feel. Basically, if I believe that putting a certain amount of effort in will disrupt me worse than the chaos that already exists, then I pull back. If I&amp;rsquo;m perpetually adjusting my shoulders or legs, then that will dominate the whole experience and I will be unsettled. If I try too hard to control my mind and make sure it doesn&amp;rsquo;t wander too far, then that can backfire too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I currently do more modest things that I believe from experience will not backfire. I&amp;rsquo;ll straighten my back enough to reboot my breath and awareness, but then let go of focusing on my back, and move to something else instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also helpful to me has been returning to an awareness of external noises (such as humming of appliances or traffic outside). This is because in the past, sometimes I would zone out and not be aware of external noises, and when the ending bell sounded, I would be startled and know instantly that I had zoned out instead of being present. Paying attention to physical sensations in my body as well as external noises outside my control has been helpful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meditation is hard work. There is no shortage of instruction on how to do it, but like everything else, I don&amp;rsquo;t really know any way to do it other than honest personal trial and error and experience.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2 new daily habits of mine in a distracting world</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/02/02/2-new-daily-habits-of-mine-in-a-distracting-world/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Feb 2012 09:02:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/02/02/2-new-daily-habits-of-mine-in-a-distracting-world/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;As of a week ago, I have developed two daily habits to reclaim my life from a distracting digital world:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/meditation/&#34;&gt;meditation&lt;/a&gt; in the morning, before breakfast&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;shutting down my computer at home in the evening two hours before going to bed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;meditation&#34;&gt;Meditation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The meditation habit is one I have wanted to develop for years now, but had not. Before around 2007, I was meditating every day for a year or two, but then I fell off the practice, and eventually stopped for long periods of time, and then just a year ago, thanks to a weekly meditation practice set up at Carnegie Mellon University, I began attending that (and Abby started meditating for the first time then).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I always felt guilty during the entire past year when noting that I wasn&amp;rsquo;t regularly meditating at home. I knew that &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m too tired&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;I don&amp;rsquo;t have time&amp;rdquo; are never valid excuses to avoid doing something one feels one &amp;ldquo;should&amp;rdquo; do. Those excuses almost always mean that something has gone wrong with priorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fact is, I was caught up with a huge number of projects, and became more and more unbalanced, especially when I lost the CMU practice for two months since it was no longer happening (thanks to the CMU academic calendar).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last week, Abby and I decided that we would meditate in the morning before breakfast, and keep it at ten minutes. Who doesn&amp;rsquo;t have ten minutes in a day, especially for something that, for me, gives me benefits that last the entire day? So we&amp;rsquo;ve established this new routine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;more-on-the-morning-routine&#34;&gt;More on the morning routine&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conjunction with the new meditation routine, I also decided that I would not check email or the Web generally until after meditation, and unless there was an emergency, I would not deal with email until after breakfast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, I have decided to significantly reduce reading the Web (through my blog subscriptions or Twitter feed) in the morning, so that I keep my morning focused. Now I&amp;rsquo;ll check the Web mostly at lunch time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;evening-information-diet&#34;&gt;Evening information diet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, I have cut out a good bit of computer time from my evening also, in order to promote better sleep as well as doing other things, such as reading paper (gasp!) books.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This has been a difficult cut, but I have managed so far, and yes, there have been repercussions. I have been doing less blog writing (because that happens on the computer), less Web reading, less tweeting. I have a large backlog of interesting Web articles that I&amp;rsquo;ve simply bookmarked without reading, and I have to confess that I&amp;rsquo;m not happy about this situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have yet to figure out the best balance to achieve in this digital age given my thirst for fresh ideas and information that are so easy to come by online, but I know for sure that I do not want to sacrifice essential calmness, exercise, sleep, and social time for the sake of addictive information overload that in the long run is not as beneficial as one might hope. What do I really need to know about? And how much of it can I apply? And even given that I have received much of value online, what is the opportunity cost of not using the time spent online on pursuits off-line? These are very hard questions for me to answer, so I&amp;rsquo;m taking my information diet one step at a time.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>