<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Gatorade on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/gatorade/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Gatorade on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/gatorade/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>A comeback from Pittsburgh Marathon overtraining</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/04/06/comeback-from-pittsburgh-marathon-overtraining/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Apr 2013 15:59:23 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/04/06/comeback-from-pittsburgh-marathon-overtraining/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Last week I reported on running Just A Short Run, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/30/report-on-just-a-short-run-my-first-half-marathon-in-nine-years/&#34;&gt;my first half marathon in nine years&lt;/a&gt;. One very real concern I had &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/03/my-first-steel-city-road-runners-winter-5k-race/&#34;&gt;when I put this race on my calendar a month ago&lt;/a&gt; was that recovery from it might interfere with my marathon training. Although I did not race Just A Short Run all out, I did put in a hard effort, and sure enough I did end up having a really tough training week afterwards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the overtraining this week was partly my doing. Here I explain how I ended up feeling like I was falling apart, and how I recovered and felt pretty good during today&amp;rsquo;s long run.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/wow-run.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Pittsburgh Marathon Warmup on Walnut run&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;after-the-half-marathon&#34;&gt;After the half marathon&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned in my report, I had some issues after the race: my right lower calf/Achilles area seized up for a bit, and also my right second and third toes did as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sure enough, a day later, I was feeling very sore in my right lower calf and second toe. I should mention that I have &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Morton%27s_toe&#34;&gt;Morton&amp;rsquo;s toe&lt;/a&gt; on both feet, although my left second toe is only barely longer than the big toe, while it is my right second toe that is noticeably longer than the big toe and therefore has a real tendency to cause me some problems:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mortons-toe.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;My Morton&amp;#39;s toes&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So I did take a day off running after the half marathon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;monday-trying-to-be-careful&#34;&gt;Monday: trying to be careful&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But even on Monday, I was still feeling sore. I decided that I should do some light running anyway, to avoid two days off completely from running.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, I very much wanted to finally start running in my new Luna Sandals, which I had received last week but put aside because of the half marathon. These are the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lunasandals.com/products/33-venado&#34;&gt;Venado with ATS laces and MGT footbed&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/lunastore/images/255/full.jpg?1351720427&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Luna Sandals: Venado, ATS laces, MGT footbed&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I ended up running just an easy 2 miles on the treadmill in the morning in my Vibram FiveFingers Bikila LS shoes, and then after work, running 1.5 miles in the Luna Sandals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;tuesday-new-shoes&#34;&gt;Tuesday: new shoes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tuesday, I was still not yet completely recovered either from the half marathon, but I felt I was ready to go for a normal run. I decided to do a real run in the Luna Sandals and did 5 miles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I encountered various problems while trying out the Luna Sandals, beginning to break them in. I got chafed in various places from the straps and buckle:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/luna-sandals-2013-04-02/feet.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Feet chafed&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/luna-sandals-2013-04-02/side.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Side view&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/luna-sandals-2013-04-02/wearing.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Feet in&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/luna-sandals-2013-04-02/heel.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;View of heel&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And it was tricky keeping the sandals on at all. I fidgeted a lot with the laces to try to keep my heels from slipping. I kept on having problems with my right heel slipping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, although my calf was healing up, I was more worried about my right second toe, which seemed sore and sensitive. I noticed that my tendency to impact the second toe (after all, it is my longest toe) was causing trouble. I had not really encountered any problems until after the half marathon, but the intensity of that effort, and the fact that my Bikila LS shoes were getting worn down at the toes, must have exposed this biomechanical weakness finally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;wednesday-overexcited&#34;&gt;Wednesday: overexcited&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wednesday, I was excited about running, and used the Luna Sandals again. I still had slippage and chafing issues, but figured that there was a break-in process. The soles were starting to shape to my feet, for example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, I accidentally (because of taking impromptu routes in Homewood Cemetery) ran 9 miles when I had originally intended to run more like 7.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My second toe was startling to tingle and really complain: even normal walking triggered pain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;thursday-admission-of-overtraining&#34;&gt;Thursday: admission of overtraining&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thursday was one of those days when I truly &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/14/three-questions-to-ask-yourself-when-you-dont-feel-like-doing-your-scheduled-workout/&#34;&gt;had to ask myself three questions&lt;/a&gt;. I was simply feeling &lt;em&gt;exhausted&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I forced myself to completely take Thursday off from running (or strength training, for that matter), while evaluating my situation. This was no longer just about my toe, but about my overall fatigue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, I had to fix this toe problem somehow, and soon, because I had a long run planned for Saturday. So I observed myself closely while walking. I noticed that I had a tendency to do a weird retracting motion on the toe when walking, a motion I do not use on my left foot. I questioned the purpose of this reflex. I found that I could &lt;em&gt;choose&lt;/em&gt; not to perform the retracting motion. It was difficult to make this choice, but if I really focused, I could control how I &lt;em&gt;used&lt;/em&gt; my foot. I remembered lessons from &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alexander_technique&#34;&gt;Alexander technique&lt;/a&gt; about observing and unlearning habits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, I discovered the reason my right hip has sometimes felt sore: my right hip has sagged in my posture. I also found that correcting this shifted the balance of weight on my right foot, and alleviated the pressure on my second toe, shifting more weight where it should be, more toward the big toe under the ball of the foot. These were very interesting discoveries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, I felt so tired that I decided to go ahead and cancel my Sunday plan to play in the final round of the Pittsburgh Chess League season; I had really wanted to put in one final appearance for our team, after not having actually played for us since &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/11/11/pittsburgh-chess-league-round-3-back-to-chess-after-a-month-off/&#34;&gt;last November&lt;/a&gt;, because something kept on coming up every month since then, but I had little confidence that I would be mentally alert on Sunday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;friday-still-playing-it-safe&#34;&gt;Friday: still playing it safe&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Friday, I was feeling energetic enough to run, but I forced myself to take another day off for the sake of my right toe. It was not easy, but I reminded myself that &lt;em&gt;not being able to do my long run&lt;/em&gt; was not worth one more missed day of training.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of running, I did one rep of the Cathedral of Learning stair climb, just to get some activity in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;saturday-my-14-mile-long-run&#34;&gt;Saturday: my 14-mile long run&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saturday morning, I felt my right toe had recovered sufficiently that I was going to be OK doing my planned long run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Steel City Road Runners had a 10-mile run lined up starting in Shadyside after a program of dynamics warmups by Dr. Vonda Wright, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pittsburghmarathon.com/wow.asp&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Warmup on Walnut&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, outside of sponsor &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.truerunner.com/&#34;&gt;True Runner&lt;/a&gt;. My plan was to skip that program, but create a 14-mile run by running 2 miles from home to the Shadyside point and then joining the group run and then running 2 miles back home afterwards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is the 10-mile loop:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe id=&#34;mapmyfitness_route&#34; src=&#34;http://snippets.mapmycdn.com/routes/view/embedded/187175578?width=560&amp;height=400&amp;elevation=true&amp;info=true&amp;line_color=E60f0bdb&amp;rgbhex=DB0B0E&amp;distance_markers=1&amp;unit_type=imperial&amp;map_mode=TERRAIN&amp;last_updated=2013-04-01T09:44:11-04:00&#34; height=&#34;590px&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: right; padding-right: 20px;&#34;&gt;&lt;a target=&#34;_blank&#34; href=&#34;http://mapmyrun.com/routes/create/&#34;&gt;Create Maps&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a target=&#34;_blank&#34; href=&#34;http://mapmyrun.com/routes/&#34;&gt;search&lt;/a&gt; from 80 million at &lt;a href=&#34;http://mapmyrun.com&#34;&gt;MapMyRun&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;my-goal&#34;&gt;My goal&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My goal for this long run was to make it a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mcmillanrunning.com/index.php/articlePages/article/2&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;fast finish long run&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. In particular, in planning my run, I had noted that the last 5 miles of the course involved a steady uphill as well as a steeper uphill through Oakland on Forbes Avenue. In the 2003 Pittsburgh Marathon ten years ago, this uphill had proved a bit discouraging to me (because I had, frankly, gone out too fast). In any case, for psychological and physiological reasons, I wanted to do this whole uphill fast and strong in this particular workout. In the actual marathon in a month, of course, I don&amp;rsquo;t plan to run it as fast, but I did want to remember the landmarks and mental state of doing something difficult but in a relaxed way. I wanted to focus on applying my newly discovered knowledge about my posture and stride asymmetry and &amp;ldquo;run tall&amp;rdquo; up the hill, with balanced hips, while monitoring my right second toe to make sure it did not get battered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was still not comfortable with the Luna Sandals, so I fell back to the shoes I&amp;rsquo;ve been wearing for almost all of my runs in the past three months, the Bikila LS shoes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;showed-up-late&#34;&gt;Showed up late&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, I strangely miscalculated my departure from home to run 2 miles to Aiken Avenue and Walnut Street, and showed up 4 minutes late, just as runners were already heading off. I grabbed a printed map and picked up the pace so that I could try to catch up to the 10:00 pace group. I did, realizing of course that I was making my task in the final miles of my run more difficult as a result.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;conquering-the-oakland-hill&#34;&gt;Conquering the Oakland hill&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I managed the Oakland hill pretty well, being very focused. I continued going hard all the way back to True Runner in Shadyside. Near the end, I felt my calves getting tight, just as in the half marathon last week when my right calf seized up after I was walking after the finish line. I thought it was very useful to have triggered this exact sensation and knowing where it was, because it meant that maybe I would be able to train my body to accept that state of fatigue (after running 12 miles) and continue. Also, the feeling cleared up fairly quickly after I stopped to walk, so I think last week the real trigger was my pointless little sprint near the end. If I avoid any sprinting during the marathon, I might well be able to avoid cramping. At least, that is the plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;a-decision-about-gatorade&#34;&gt;A decision about Gatorade&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I drank some more Gatorade back at Walnut Street, then ran home. I was really quite tired by this point and my stomach wasn&amp;rsquo;t feeling so great. I ate some actual food and eventually recovered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During this run, no gels were provided, so I drank Gatorade as my only fuel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is my final conclusion, solidifying a thought I had last week in the half marathon: &lt;em&gt;Gatorade is bad for me&lt;/em&gt;, and I should &lt;em&gt;completely&lt;/em&gt; avoid it in future runs and in the Pittsburgh Marathon! It was good to learn this for sure now. In fact, it is quite possible that some of the issues I had in the 2003 Pittsburgh Marathon were a result of Gatorade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GU gel works OK for me, but according to the official &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburghmarathon.com/Course.asp&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Marathon fluid station table&lt;/a&gt;, GU is provided only starting at mile 9.7. Therefore, I am going to pack some gels to ingest during the first 10 miles of the marathon! I will &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; drink any Gatorade!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After some ill-advised overtraining and injury this week after my half marathon, I forced myself to take two days off to recover, and used the time to diagnose possible causes of my biomechanical problems. I found some good hypotheses and possible solutions, and managed a high quality &amp;ldquo;fast finish long run&amp;rdquo; and am optimistic about my continuing training for the Pittsburgh Marathon.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Report on Just A Short Run: my first half marathon in nine years!</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/03/30/report-on-just-a-short-run-my-first-half-marathon-in-nine-years/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Mar 2013 15:06:18 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/03/30/report-on-just-a-short-run-my-first-half-marathon-in-nine-years/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;(Updated 2013-05-09 with official race videos!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until today, I had not run a half marathon in nine years. This distance had given me a lot of trouble the five times I did it in 2001-2004. So I was very anxious about running &lt;a href=&#34;http://eliterunners.com/just-a-short-run/&#34;&gt;Just A Short Run&lt;/a&gt; this morning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s why I feared it, and how I ended up unexpectedly pleased with the experience, including finishing over four minutes faster than my goal time.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/just-a-short-run-2013/franklin.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin done&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;past-participation-in-just-a-short-run&#34;&gt;Past participation in Just A Short Run&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was the fifth time I participated in Just A Short Run. This race began in 2001, when &lt;a href=&#34;http://eliterunners.com/running-shoes-pittsburgh/about-running-store/&#34;&gt;Kevin Smith&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href=&#34;http://eliterunners.com/&#34;&gt;Elite Runners and Walkers&lt;/a&gt; created in in memory of his younger brother who died of leukemia, to &lt;a href=&#34;http://eliterunners.com/just-a-short-run-about/&#34;&gt;support the Leukemia and Lymphoma Society&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/ipDidl-_qpM&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until today I have done the Just A Short Run four times:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;5K in 2001&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;half marathon in 2002&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;30K in 2003 (my only DNF in my life, because I went into it sick)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;5K in 2004&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;past-half-marathons&#34;&gt;Past half marathons&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have only once ever partly successfully executed a half marathon race, and even then, some things went rather wrong. Here&amp;rsquo;s a summary of what went wrong in each of my half marathons up till today:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;ikea-montour-trail-half-marathon-2001&#34;&gt;Ikea Montour Trail half marathon, 2001&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was my very first half marathon, after having run some good 5K races earlier in the year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went out too fast (because of an initial downhill that got me too excited), and paid the price. I finished in 1:47:23. My splits for the 13.1 miles:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;6:31.94&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;7:59.53&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;8:09.44&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;8:16.53&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;8:16.99&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;8:19.28&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;8:19.64&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;7:44.85&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;8:01.41&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;8:23.29&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;8:28.72&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;8:42.36&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;9:17.34&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;0:49.85&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was just struggling in the last miles, and very demoralized. I almost collapsed on my buddy Jude&amp;rsquo;s shoulder after I finished. Also, I had major blisters during the race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;just-a-short-run-half-marathon-2002&#34;&gt;Just A Short Run half marathon, 2002&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did this race without any real training at all, just because it was there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got blisters in the race, and also had to deal with weird existential thoughts like &amp;ldquo;Why am I running this?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I finished in 1:49:34, but actually, the course was found to be long by about a tenth of a mile, so that number does not mean much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;ikea-montour-trail-half-marathon-2002&#34;&gt;Ikea Montour Trail half marathon, 2002&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got my revenge in this race, actually training hard specifically for the distance, doing long intervals and a lot of tempo and race-pace runs. Overall I did very well, finishing in 1:38:48, but the experience was marred by some serious problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ran mile 4 too fast, but since I was carefully monitoring on my watch, I slowed down for mile 5. Still, one pays the price eventually for going too fast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, I still was not fueling consistently. I erred by taking both water and energy drink, resulting in dilution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In mile 12, my calves started cramping up and I had to stop at one point. I lost about half a minute because of this. In mile 13, I had to run conservatively to avoid cramps. It was very frustrating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, after I finished, while getting on the shuttle bus, I cramped up quite severely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;ikea-montour-trail-half-marathon-2003&#34;&gt;Ikea Montour Trail half marathon, 2003&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A total disaster. I finished in 1:45:32, which is 7:44 slower than the previous year. This was while having a 5K fitness similar to the previous year&amp;rsquo;s. Something just went wrong. I felt sluggish throughout, and I cramped up in mile 10. And I had digestive problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;chamber-classic-half-marathon-2004&#34;&gt;Chamber Classic half marathon, 2004&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1:46:12. No real training for it, just did it because it was there and I had not been able to do the Montour Trail one. A fiasco, in which I struggled with my usual problems (slowing down in the final miles, cramping).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;preparation&#34;&gt;Preparation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did not go into this race truly prepared to &lt;em&gt;race&lt;/em&gt; the half marathon. I know what it takes to race a half marathon for time: long tempo and race-pace runs, long intervals. I have done little of that so far this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My hardest training run so far has been &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/16/18-miles-in-vibram-fivefingers-training-for-the-pittsburgh-marathon/&#34;&gt;16 miles with the Steel City Road Runners, two weeks ago, on an 18 mile course&lt;/a&gt;. I did not truly taper for the half marathon race, although this week including the race I have a reduced mileage of 25 (easy 6, easy 3, speed ladder 3, and then the race).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather, what I am really training for is the Pittsburgh Marathon, but I felt that I should do a half marathon race in order to get a taste of what it is like to run in a long race. I have been doing long runs every week for a while now, so running the half marathon distance is not a problem: the challenge for me was to figure out if I could partially &lt;em&gt;race&lt;/em&gt; it, to find my limits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I wanted to fix the problems I had in my previous half marathons:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;blistering&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;going out too fast&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;slowing way down&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;cramping&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;digestive problems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;blistering&#34;&gt;Blistering&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Solving the problem of blistering has been trivial for me since I switched to wearing Vibram FiveFingers shoes. I just don&amp;rsquo;t get serious blisters any more; my feet have adapted completely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, I just got my Luna Sandals two days ago, but have not run in them yet. Friends helpfully convinced me that it would be crazy to wear them in the race without any actual test of them (I knew that, but just needed validation).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the &lt;em&gt;first half marathon&lt;/em&gt; I&amp;rsquo;m running in Vibram FiveFingers. Up till now, the longest distance I&amp;rsquo;ve raced in FiveFingers has been &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/25/blistered-but-blissful-in-the-burgh/&#34;&gt;10K, when I was still getting blistered by the Bikila LS&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;going-out-too-fast&#34;&gt;Going out too fast&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By not treating this as an all-out race whose goal is to minimize time, I could afford to run more conservatively and plan on negative-splitting. I decide to target a time of 1:55:00 (reasonable given &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/03/my-first-steel-city-road-runners-winter-5k-race/&#34;&gt;my recent 5K&lt;/a&gt; time of 25:11), with the idea of speeding up if it felt right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;slowing-way-down&#34;&gt;Slowing way down&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I consciously carb-loaded for this half marathon and had a race fueling plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;cramping&#34;&gt;Cramping&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have no idea how to really solve this problem. I think I must be genetically predisposed to cramping. People like to claim electrolyte deficiency is the cause, but I don&amp;rsquo;t believe this at all, because I have tried loading up on electrolytes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;digestive-problems&#34;&gt;Digestive problems&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have concluded that it is safest to avoid Gatorade and the like on the course because people mix it in funny proportions. Sticking with predictable gels and water is my new plan. One gel before starting the race, and then one gel every 45 minutes after that (which in the case of a half marathon means two gels on the course).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, I used to drink too much water, resulting in sloshing in the stomach. So I drink less now during a race, and drink more well before it starts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-route&#34;&gt;The route&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;iframe id=&#34;mapmyfitness_route&#34; src=&#34;http://snippets.mapmycdn.com/routes/view/embedded/24782?width=560&amp;height=400&amp;elevation=true&amp;info=true&amp;line_color=E60f0bdb&amp;rgbhex=DB0B0E&amp;distance_markers=1&amp;unit_type=imperial&amp;map_mode=TERRAIN&amp;last_updated=2006-03-10T16:46:31-05:00&#34; height=&#34;590px&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: right; padding-right: 20px;&#34;&gt;&lt;a target=&#34;_blank&#34; href=&#34;http://mapmyrun.com/routes/create/&#34;&gt;Create Maps&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a target=&#34;_blank&#34; href=&#34;http://mapmyrun.com/routes/&#34;&gt;search&lt;/a&gt; from 80 million at &lt;a href=&#34;http://mapmyrun.com&#34;&gt;MapMyRun&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

Note the big hill at the beginning. Control of effort going up and down hills is critical, to avoid bad spikes in energy usage.

## The race

Here are the [official race results](http://www.runhigh.com/2013RESULTS/R033013AA.html).

### Start


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/just-a-short-run-2013/announcements.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Announcements&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


I started out with the 1:55:00 finish pacer (8:47 pace):


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/just-a-short-run-2013/pacer.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;My initial pacer&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


Going up the big hill, however, he totally lost me, as I slowed down to avoid prematurely feeling the burn. In fact, a slower pacer even passed me. No problem.

On the downhill, I quickly started regaining ground. I think after around three miles, I had caught up to the original 8:47 pacer, and then that was feeling too slow for me, so I passed him for good, and never saw a pacer again in the race.

### Gatorade error

I made an error at one of the aid stations when I mistaken grabbed Gatorade and threw it in my face. I got stickiness all over my face and the front of my jacket and fingers. It was really disgusting, actually. I will be more careful in the future to ask what stuff is before taking a cup.

Otherwise, I stuck well to my plan of taking water and two gels during the entire half marathon. Note that the race provided [e-Gel](http://www.cranksports.com/products/eGel/), which I had not had before. If I were seriously racing this half marathon, obviously I would have bought and tried this stuff on long runs ahead of time.

### Passing people

The thing about Just A Short Run is that people are running different races and therefore are at different paces, and also in such a huge race, there are always those who are inexperienced and go out too fast and slow down. What this means, in practice, is that if you are running evenly (or for a negative split, like I was doing), you will be needing to pass people constantly. It is very important to be a good judge of your own pace, because otherwise you might think you are doing OK, while the reality is you&#39;re following someone who is slowing down.

I like to target someone who looks faster than me and then try to keep up with him or her. I did this repeatedly in the race.

At one point I asked a guy what his pace was, and he said 8:30. I was feeling good, so eventually I passed him. I realized at that moment that I was going to be able to run considerably faster than 1:55:00, despite my very slow start.

### Last five miles

I maintained speed in the last 5 miles of the race; I might even have gone faster, but without the data, I cannot tell, since when fatigue sets in, effort does not equal actual pace. I was definitely getting tired, but I kept pushing, trying to pretend I was running a 10K race or something. I thought that I just might have a shot at finishing under 1:50:00. I didn&#39;t, but that&#39;s OK. I finished in 1:50:52.

The official [split data](http://www.runhigh.com/2013RESULTS/R033013AF.html) shows that I did the last 5 miles in 42:03, which is about 8:25 pace. Since I averaged 8:28 pace for the whole race, I clearly ran faster in the last 5 miles than in the first 8.1 miles.

If I had known what I was capable of, I could have run faster and more evenly from the start, and finished faster, but that was quite explicitly *not* the goal today. The goal was to finish strong, which I did.

## SPIbelt

This was my first time running a race wearing a SPIbelt. It did not cause me any trouble at all; I barely noticed it. I will wear it during the Pittsburgh Marathon, in order to have my phone on me in case of emergency. I did not use my phone during the race, only before and after it, but it&#39;s always nice to know that I can directly contact Abby if something goes wrong.

## Cramping

I did a little bit of a final sprint across the finish line. The moment I crossed was the moment when I felt both of my calves start to twitch. I realized that I almost crossed the line to full-on cramping, and decided to keep moving. I grabbed a banana and ate it while jogging slowly, and planning to jog off the heaviness in my calves.

Then disaster struck: I stubbed my right toes on the ground and instantly two of my toes cramped up and my lower right calf also cramped up. I ripped off my shoe and luckily, after about twenty seconds, I was OK again. I decided it was unsafe to keep moving, and I went upstairs in the North Park Boat House to just keep warm and stretch in a safe environment. I did not cramp up again.

So I have not entirely solved the cramping problem. Apparently sprinting was enough to push me over the edge. Also, closed-toe shoes are a problem because my toes inevitably get at least somewhat jammed in the course of running in closed-toe shoes. This is why I want to test out the Luna Sandals, which may completely prevent toe jamming and cramping. As for my calves, I don&#39;t know, maybe I just need to do more hard longer runs in order to get them accustomed to the lactic acid buildup or something.

## Post-race eating

My stomach was entirely OK during the race. No water sloshing, no indigestion, no gnawing hunger. I was hungry after finishing, of course.


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/just-a-short-run-2013/food.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Post-race food&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


I made some mistakes after finishing, however. I ate not only a banana, but also a bagel, a Smiley Cookie, a little bag of chips, and a little bag of cookies. I believe I should have excluded the bag of cookies and the chips, and saved the Smiley Cookie for later. I had some digestive discomfort (nothing serious though) for a while after everything I ate. I will remember next time. After a 5K or 10K, I can eat anything, but apparently, after a half marathon, digestion is trickier.

But it is hard not to gobble up a Smiley Cookie:


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/just-a-short-run-2013/smiley-cookie.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Smiley Cookie&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


At home, I ended up deciding to eat familiar leftovers rather than going out to a buffet as I had originally thought of doing with Abby.

## Feet

My feet were sore, but actually, less sore than after each of my long runs in the past month. I think I&#39;ve become more efficient. No knee pain either. After the race, just general inflammation. I think I&#39;ll be OK tomorrow.


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/just-a-short-run-2013/shoes.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Vibram FiveFingers Bikila LS&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/just-a-short-run-2013/feet.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin&amp;#39;s feet&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/just-a-short-run-2013/soles.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin&amp;#39;s soles of feet&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


I did get one small blister, on my right pinkie toe, but I didn&#39;t actually notice it until I was home and took a shower.

## What does all this mean for the marathon?

This [race time predictor](http://www.runnersworld.co.uk/general/rws-race-time-predictor/1681.html) suggests that given that I ran a half marathon in 1:50:52, I can do a full marathon in 3:51:08. I am, frankly, skeptical that I can go under 4:00:00 at all a month from now. I know I want to be conservative in the marathon, and I rather doubt I will be able to negative-split it, and I still have concerns about late-stage cramping or other physical deterioration. We shall see how my training progresses. I am going to start adding &#34;quality&#34; work in the form of interval training in order to toughen up.

## Thanks

Many thanks to my wife Abby, who dropped me off at the race and picked me up after visiting her parents in the vicinity, saving me driving and parking hassles! And thanks to all my friends who have been supportive while I&#39;ve been so nervous for weeks about this race!

I like to thank [Elite Runners and Walkers](http://eliterunners.com/) for putting on a really well-organized race. The instructions were very clear, volunteers giving out water, Gatorade, and gels were everywhere, there was plenty of post-race food, bag check was convenient, and everything seemed to go smoothly. I would like to take this opportunity to say that without Elite Runners and Walkers, I do not know where I would be as a runner. Back over a decade ago, when I started running, the Internet was not what it is now. I got information about running from books and magazines and word of mouth more than anything else. I was told about the new store Elite Runners and Walkers and I got some of my first running shoes and clothing there. I even bought my very first pair of Vibram FiveFingers KSO shoes there, in 2009, before minimalist shoes suddenly became more mainstream and available in other stores, and last year when I got some rips in those first Vibram FiveFingers shoes, I got a new pair of KSO shoes through them also. And the races they put on in the winter and spring are great: I used to run their [Spring Thaw](http://eliterunners.com/events/annual-spring-thaw/) as well as Just A Short Run. And when picking up my race packet at the store this week, Abby and I bought some more shirts and shorts in preparation for summer!

## Conclusion

This was my slowest half marathon ever, but one of the most satisfying, and one of the best-executed, given my actual fitness level, which is substantially lower than that of a decade ago. I may consider *really* racing a half marathon in the fall. Meanwhile, I definitely found the successful completion of this half marathon to be a confidence booster for the upcoming Pittsburgh Marathon. Yes, there is no real comparison between the two distances, but it&#39;s just the fact that this is a long race at all, compared to, say, a 5K or 10K.

## Race videos are out! (Update of 2013-05-09)

### From start to 1:30:00

#### Start

I couldn&#39;t find myself in the half marathon start, because it&#39;s too congested.

#### Additional loop 1

I found myself arriving under &#34;Additional loops&#34; at 27:09 on the clock to begin the first of two 5-mile loops.

(To jump immediately to the spot, click [here](http://youtu.be/BukDHKvc7rk?t=12m50s).)

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/BukDHKvc7rk&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I crossed the start line after 21 seconds, I really ran 26:48 for the first 3.1 miles (average 8:39 pace).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;additional-loop-2&#34;&gt;Additional loop 2&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, watch me cross &amp;ldquo;Additional loops&amp;rdquo; at around 1:09:09 on the clock, which means I did 5 miles in 42:00 (average 8:24 pace).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(To jump immediately to the spot, click &lt;a href=&#34;http://youtu.be/BukDHKvc7rk?t=46m11s&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;from-1-31-00-to-3-21-00&#34;&gt;From 1:31:00 to 3:21:00&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;sprint-finish&#34;&gt;Sprint finish&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Watch my sprint finish from clock time around 1:51:03 to finish at 1:51:12 (my chip time was 1:50:51, meaning I crossed the start line after 21 seconds), which means I did the last 5 miles in 42:03, almost exactly the same time as I did the first 5-mile loop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(To jump immediately to the spot, click &lt;a href=&#34;http://youtu.be/wdjy7eLUlwQ?t=15m41s&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/wdjy7eLUlwQ&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;from-3-23-00-to-4-07-00&#34;&gt;From 3:23:00 to 4:07:00&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was already done, so I am not in this video.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/t4Zwv-tSLVM&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2014-03-09&#34;&gt;(Update of 2014-03-09)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2014, I did not set a goal to run a spring half marathon, so I did not train in the winter months for one, and so I am sadly missing Just A Short Run. Maybe there&amp;rsquo;s still time for me to get back into regular running and aim to do a half marathon in the fall.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>11 Pittsburgh bridge crossings in one 12-mile run</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/03/09/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings-in-one-12-mile-run/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Mar 2013 21:21:26 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/03/09/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings-in-one-12-mile-run/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://sphotos-b.xx.fbcdn.net/hphotos-ash3/602768_422297731198378_798317370_n.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;View from Mount Washington&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My first ever &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.steelcityrrc.org/scrrcevents?eventId=568739&amp;amp;EventViewMode=2&amp;amp;CalendarViewType=1&amp;amp;SelectedDate=3/16/2013&#34;&gt;Steel City Road Runners Saturday morning training run&lt;/a&gt; was a 12-mile run. My office mate John went with me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last time I ran as far as 12 miles &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/02/24/2013-pittsburgh-marathon-training-progress-since-signing-up-three-weeks-ago/&#34;&gt;was in February&lt;/a&gt;, so I expected to do OK. The important difference is that I have been increasing my weekly mileage. I had a monster training week last week, going up from 13 miles to 26 miles last week, the &lt;em&gt;largest&lt;/em&gt; training volume I have had in a single week in years. I&amp;rsquo;ll confess that this has taken a toll on me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result, I have backed off this week, such that including this 12-mile run (I will not run tomorrow), this week I will have 23 miles. In the long haul, &lt;em&gt;overtraining&lt;/em&gt; is a huge waste of time and energy. Unfortunately, in my attempt to &amp;ldquo;catch up&amp;rdquo; some because of the marathon coming in less than two months, I did in fact overtrain to an extent; last week I ran five out of seven days in order to reach that mileage of 26. This week, I tried to up the mileage but felt tired and wisely decided to rest when I needed to, even though that meant this week I ran only three days! Obviously, in retrospect, it would have been wiser to run four days last week and four this week, with better overall training.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I did enjoy today&amp;rsquo;s training run. It involved the most bridge crossings I have ever done in my life in a single day (by foot or otherwise): eleven!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is my report on the training run, including, of course, photos of bridge crossings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;sign-in&#34;&gt;Sign in&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;John and I signed in at 8 AM. It was going to be a beautiful, sunny day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We received printed maps of the route. I did have my smartphone with me, wearing it in my SPIbelt, so I felt pretty safe about knowing where I am or where to go in case I got lost.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings/sign-in.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Steel City Road Runners sign in&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There is indoor access to restrooms, water fountains, and warmth at these Steel City Road Runners training run meetings. Very nice for winter!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were designated pacers. I was uncertain about which pace group I should join, if any at all. I felt that probably the 10-minute pace group might be on the slow side, but definitely I did not expect to keep up with the 9-minute pace group for a long run. But we decided to start off with the 9-minute pace group and see what happens.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings/pace-groups.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Pacers&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I wore my Vibram FiveFingers Bikila LS shoes, which have been my main running shoes all winter (when there is no snow or water on the ground):&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings/vibram-fivefingers-bikila-ls.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin wearing Vibram FiveFingers Bikila LS&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-route&#34;&gt;The route&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is the route of the 12-mile training run:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe id=&#34;mapmyfitness_route&#34; src=&#34;http://snippets.mapmycdn.com/routes/view/embedded/178234904?width=560&amp;height=400&amp;elevation=true&amp;info=true&amp;line_color=E60f0bdb&amp;rgbhex=DB0B0E&amp;distance_markers=1&amp;unit_type=imperial&amp;map_mode=TERRAIN&amp;last_updated=2013-03-08T12:47:36-06:00&#34; height=&#34;590px&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: right; padding-right: 20px;&#34;&gt;&lt;a target=&#34;_blank&#34; href=&#34;http://mapmyrun.com/routes/create/&#34;&gt;Create Maps&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a target=&#34;_blank&#34; href=&#34;http://mapmyrun.com/routes/&#34;&gt;search&lt;/a&gt; from 80 million at &lt;a href=&#34;http://mapmyrun.com&#34;&gt;MapMyRun&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-bridge-crossings&#34;&gt;The bridge crossings&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 9-minute pace group was clearly going too fast for me. I hung off the back hoping to simply keep them in sight as they kept getting more ahead of me. To my surprise, John went with the group, even though he has not run in months. I was not sure it was wise of him not to have done any running before this training run, and am worried about his going too fast all of a sudden.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings/on-our-way.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;nine-minute pace group&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;rachel-carson-bridge-inbound-over-the-allegheny-river&#34;&gt;Rachel Carson Bridge, inbound over the Allegheny River&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings/rachel-carson-bridge.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;On Rachel Carson Bridge inbound&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We can see downtown Pittsburgh:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings/rachel-carson-bridge-see-downtown.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;On Rachel Carson Bridge, seeing downtown&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;7th-street-bridge-outbound&#34;&gt;7th Street Bridge, outbound&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings/7th-street-bridge.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;On 7th Street Bridge outbound&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;roberto-clemente-bridge-inbound&#34;&gt;Roberto Clemente Bridge, inbound&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings/roberto-clemente-bridge.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Approaching Roberto Clemente Bridge inbound&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;fort-duquesne-bridge-outbound&#34;&gt;Fort Duquesne Bridge, outbound&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings/fort-duquesne-bridge.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;On Fort Duquesne Bridge outbound&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;west-end-bridge-south-over-the-monongahela-river&#34;&gt;West End Bridge, south over the Monongahela River&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings/west-end-bridge.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;On West End Bridge south&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;first-water-stop-and-getting-lost&#34;&gt;First water stop and getting lost!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our first water stop was after 4 miles:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings/first-water-stop.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;First water stop&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;By the time I had reached this water stop, John and the rest of the 9-minute pace group were way ahead of me and barely visible. Unfortunately, after I drank some Gatorade, I noticed that I didn&amp;rsquo;t see them at all any more. So for almost the rest of the run, the following 8 miles, I was mostly alone! This was disconcerting because it meant that I&amp;rsquo;d have to try to follow the printed map and directions, and avoid getting lost. It would turn out that I would get lost a couple of times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;fort-pitt-bridge-inbound&#34;&gt;Fort Pitt Bridge, inbound&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings/fort-pitt-bridge.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;On Fort Pitt Bridge inbound&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;smithfield-street-bridge-outbound&#34;&gt;Smithfield Street Bridge, outbound&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings/smithfield-street-bridge.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;On Smithfield Street Bridge outbound&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Check out this view of bridges along the Monongahela River:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings/monongahela-river.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Monongahela River&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;10th-street-bridge-inbound&#34;&gt;10th Street Bridge, inbound&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leaving the South Side:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings/10th-street-bridge.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;On 10th Street Bridge inbound&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;liberty-bridge-outbound&#34;&gt;Liberty Bridge, outbound&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not having anyone to follow, I got confused about how to get onto the Liberty Bridge, missing the steps, and had to do some backtracking to find the way to get on.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings/liberty-bridge-outbound.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;On Liberty Bridge outbound&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;to-mount-washington&#34;&gt;To Mount Washington&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This training run featured a big, long uphill to Mount Washington, with a water stop at the very top!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings/to-mount-washington.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;To Mount Washington&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;After being alone for quite some time, I did encounter John and other runners coming back down Mount Washington when I was still going up. They were going really fast downhill!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings/up-to-mount-washington.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Uphill to Mount Washington&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;second-water-stop&#34;&gt;Second water stop&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My phone started acting funny when I got to the water stop at the top of Mount Washington, so I did not bother to try take any more photos after that. I was bummed that I didn&amp;rsquo;t get a photo of the view of Pittsburgh from the top, but someone did and posted it on Facebook, so here it is:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://sphotos-b.xx.fbcdn.net/hphotos-ash3/602768_422297731198378_798317370_n.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;View from Mount Washington&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At this water stop, at mile 9, I felt hungry, and saw some GU gels, and took one and ate it before continuing my run. It was &lt;a href=&#34;http://guenergy.com/products/products-roctane-gels&#34;&gt;GU Roctane&lt;/a&gt;. I didn&amp;rsquo;t look at the ingredients till after I got home and did a Web search on it. That explained a lot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While running down from Mount Washington, I felt a surge of energy and decided to run really, really fast, in hope of possibly catching sight of John at some point. In fact, I did not see any runner again for the next 3 miles until I reached the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;back-across-the-liberty-bridge-inbound&#34;&gt;Back across the Liberty Bridge, inbound&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then running through downtown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;16th-street-bridge-outbound&#34;&gt;16th Street Bridge outbound&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was kind of zoned out and missed the turn onto the bridge because I was just running fast, but luckily, I was off by just a block before I realized my mistake and backtracked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-end&#34;&gt;The end&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got back to the start in a bit less than two hours, so given my rest stops and getting lost, I definitely averaged under 10-minute pace. But I was definitely not running anywhere near 9-minute pace. I&amp;rsquo;ll keep that in my mind for the next training run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;John had finished well before me, but he himself had gotten lost near the end also.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We snacked on provided orange slices and chips:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings/after.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Steel City Road Runners snacks&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings/franklin.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Then I drove us back to our places. After both of us had showered and changed, we met up for lunch buffet at Coriander India Grill, a favorite place to eat &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/02/26/snowing-means-sambar-at-coriander-india-grill/&#34;&gt;after getting very hungry after a lot of exercise&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-next&#34;&gt;What next?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next week will be an 18-mile training run. As I have mentioned, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/02/24/2013-pittsburgh-marathon-training-progress-since-signing-up-three-weeks-ago/&#34;&gt;I do not intend to actually do such a long run&lt;/a&gt;, so I will think of a good way to run 16 miles instead: either I start walking earlier, or I walk near the end. And for sure, I will start with the 10-minute pace group rather than then 9-minute pace group. These training runs are not races. I don&amp;rsquo;t want to run too fast. In fact, I&amp;rsquo;m worried that I ran the last 3 miles today too fast, especially downhill from Mount Washington. My left knee is feeling a little funny. I hope it will recover after a day of rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve started to figure out the gel thing. I used eat gels a decade ago, but stopped because I had no reason to, but on these long runs, they do help, and I have to start planning what to use for fuel in the Pittsburgh Marathon, which will officially supply GU gel and Gatorade. I did learn, after the fact, that GU Roctane contains an insane amount of caffeine, and that&amp;rsquo;s probably what got me all hopped up to run super fast, but to my detriment today. So I need to be careful if I use Roctane in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a very instructive and tiring training run. I have a long way to go before being ready for the marathon in less than two months, but am happy to have finally joined a group training run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m very grateful for the opportunity to train with the Steel City Road Runners. Sometimes, it is much easier to commit to getting up early and going for a long run when you know that you&amp;rsquo;ll have company, that there will be support (in the form of a planned route and aid stations). Even for an introvert like me who usually prefers to run alone, the unique pains of marathon training cause me to value camaraderie for some tough runs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>