<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Politics on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/politics/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Politics on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/politics/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>How learning about the Magna Carta in high school changed my life</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/06/13/how-learning-about-the-magna-carta-in-high-school-changed-my-life/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Jun 2015 15:35:30 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/06/13/how-learning-about-the-magna-carta-in-high-school-changed-my-life/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I couldn&amp;rsquo;t help noticing the headlines in the news lately about the
800th anniversary of the
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Magna_Carta&#34;&gt;Magna Carta&lt;/a&gt;, that
historical document from 1215 in England. As I write, apparently there
is a
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bbc.com/news/uk-england-33116579&#34;&gt;celebration being held on the River Thames&lt;/a&gt;,
even. And I just found a Web site devoted entirely to this
&lt;a href=&#34;http://magnacarta800th.com/&#34;&gt;800th anniversary&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Magna Carta has not been on my mind for over thirty years since I
first learned about it in a social studies class in the ninth grade high
school in the early 1980s. But when I think about it, the surprising
truth is that learning about the Magna Carta was a &lt;em&gt;turning point&lt;/em&gt; in
my life as a new teenager (age twelve or thirteen), and the lessons I
learned have informed me throughout my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-is-the-magna-carta-associated-with&#34;&gt;What is the Magna Carta associated with?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Magna Carta in popular imagination is associated with &amp;ldquo;liberty&amp;rdquo;,
with &amp;ldquo;the people&amp;rdquo; rising up in revolt against arbitrary monarchy and
making King John sign a document guaranteeing basic rights, such as
the right to a fair trail and no taxation without representation; and
&amp;ldquo;equality&amp;rdquo;, putting the king himself under the scope of law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Magna Carta is thought of as an inspiration for
subsequent milestones in history such as the United States Declaration
of Independence and the &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/constitution/&#34;&gt;Constitution&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-truth-as-i-learned-it&#34;&gt;The truth as I learned it&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I took a required &amp;ldquo;social studies&amp;rdquo; class in the ninth grade in high
school. It was one of the most interesting and life-changing classes I
ever took. I remember more from that class than probably any other in
all of high school. I loved the class because it was a small honors
class, didn&amp;rsquo;t follow a standard textbook, the teacher had us engage in
discussions, and we did many interesting activities such as watch
films and play games and do simulations. She used a kind of &amp;ldquo;Socratic
method&amp;rdquo; to direct us and get us thinking and offering our opinions
with reasons. &lt;em&gt;This was the one of the first (and few) times in school
in which I felt I was being treated as an independent adult-to-be, not
as a child.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is what I learned in ninth grade social studies class from the
coverage of the Magna Carta:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John,_King_of_England&#34;&gt;King John&lt;/a&gt; was
just one of a line of random kings in history who gained their power
from accident of birth rather than anything else.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Our teacher made fun of an artist&amp;rsquo;s fictional depiction of King
John&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;signing&amp;rdquo; the Magna Carta, arguing that since King John was
illiterate, he could not have signed it, and usual practice was to
press his seal on documents. (Amusingly, there is still
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bbc.com/news/blogs-magazine-monitor-30879124&#34;&gt;online discussion of this detail&lt;/a&gt;
decades after my class.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The whole Magna Carta thing came out of a civil war. It wasn&amp;rsquo;t like
one side was really right and the king was particularly evil as far
as kings went back in the day.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A bunch of &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Landed_gentry&#34;&gt;landed nobility&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Collusion&#34;&gt;colluded&lt;/a&gt; to protect their
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Collective_bargaining&#34;&gt;collective interests&lt;/a&gt;.
Basically, they tried to form the first &amp;ldquo;union&amp;rdquo; against royal
interests.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This document did not have anything to do with &amp;ldquo;the people&amp;rdquo; as such
(who in those days lived in abject misery whether under the nobility
or the king). The Magna Carta was not for the &amp;ldquo;little people&amp;rdquo;. Its
clauses were specific about whom they applied to, i.e., &amp;ldquo;free men&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Magna Carta was the product of a power struggle among those who
already had power. It was about power and money. A bunch of
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rent-seeking&#34;&gt;rent-seeking&lt;/a&gt; nobility
didn&amp;rsquo;t like that the king was arbitrarily cutting in on them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Magna Carta was originally a flop: civil war continued, King
John ignored its rules. But it proved useful later symbolically when
conditions changed, proved to be something to rally around and
reinterpret for a new age.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;no-untarnished-heroes&#34;&gt;No untarnished heroes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest question that arose in discussion was, should we be
cynical about the Magna Carta because of what it was originally for,
as opposed to what it later became to stand for or how it inspired
more far-reaching change? I think we can ask that of anything,
especially, for those of us in the United States, of our own
perception of our Founding Fathers and the nature of the American
Revolution, which all occurred five hundred years after the Magna
Carta.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I learned from the study of history (which I enjoyed so much I
took two non-required world history courses in the tenth grade before
the required American history sequence in the eleventh grade) that
there are no easy answers, and that it is important to be skeptical of
mythologizing the past. I have remembered these lessons long after not
thinking about the Magna Carta again after that class in the ninth
grade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The noblemen who came up with the Magna Carta may have been thinking
only of themselves, but might have unwittingly paved the way for
others. Intention is one thing, but the final result is another
thing. (And history shows that there never is a final result either.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;some-interesting-resources-on-the-magna-carta&#34;&gt;Some interesting resources on the Magna Carta&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a &lt;a href=&#34;http://the-orb.net/textbooks/muhlberger/magna_carta.html&#34;&gt;medieval studies textbook section on the Magna Carta&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did not touch upon the religion aspect of the power struggles in the
medieval era (such as King John&amp;rsquo;s fights with the Pope; three hundred
years after King John, the whole
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Church_of_England&#34;&gt;Church of England&lt;/a&gt;
finally split off from Catholicism when King Henry VIII wanted to
annul a marriage but the Pope wouldn&amp;rsquo;t let him), but here is a
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/09531a.htm&#34;&gt;Catholic encyclopedia article about the Magna Carta&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s an article about a Magna Carta skeptic, a British judge who
calls it an insignificant, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/uknews/law-and-order/11670716/Magna-Carta-Turgid-document-was-eclipsed-by-the-French-says-top-judge.html&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;turgid document&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can search online for a whole lot more commentary, given the
hugeness of this 800th anniversary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;here-s-that-fictional-depiction&#34;&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s that fictional depiction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:A_Chronicle_of_England_-_Page_226_-_John_Signs_the_Great_Charter.jpg#/media/File:A_Chronicle_of_England_-_Page_226_-_John_Signs_the_Great_Charter.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;A Chronicle of England - Page 226 - John Signs the Great Charter.jpg&#34; src=&#34;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/d/d6/A_Chronicle_of_England_-_Page_226_-_John_Signs_the_Great_Charter.jpg&#34; height=&#34;480&#34; width=&#34;598&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#34;&lt;a href=&#34;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:A_Chronicle_of_England_-_Page_226_-_John_Signs_the_Great_Charter.jpg#/media/File:A_Chronicle_of_England_-_Page_226_-_John_Signs_the_Great_Charter.jpg&#34;&gt;A Chronicle of England - Page 226 - John Signs the Great Charter&lt;/a&gt;&#34; by &lt;a href=&#34;//en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_William_Edmund_Doyle&#34; class=&#34;extiw&#34; title=&#34;en:James William Edmund Doyle&#34;&gt;James William Edmund Doyle&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;a href=&#34;//en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_William_Edmund_Doyle&#34; class=&#34;extiw&#34; title=&#34;w:James William Edmund Doyle&#34;&gt;Doyle, James William Edmund&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;span style=&#34;white-space:nowrap&#34;&gt;1864&lt;/span&gt;) &#34;&lt;a rel=&#34;nofollow&#34; class=&#34;external text&#34; href=&#34;http://books.google.com.sg/books?id=YcM_AAAAYAAJ&amp;amp;pg=PA226&#34;&gt;John&lt;/a&gt;&#34; in &lt;a rel=&#34;nofollow&#34; class=&#34;external text&#34; href=&#34;http://books.google.com.sg/books?id=YcM_AAAAYAAJ&#34;&gt;A Chronicle of England: B.C. 55 – A.D. 1485&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;//en.wikipedia.org/wiki/London&#34; class=&#34;extiw&#34; title=&#34;en:London&#34;&gt;London&lt;/a&gt;: Longman, Green, Longman, Roberts &amp;amp; Green, pp.&amp;nbsp;p. 226 Retrieved on &lt;span style=&#34;white-space:nowrap&#34;&gt;12 November 2010&lt;/span&gt;.. Licensed under Public Domain via &lt;a href=&#34;//commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/&#34;&gt;Wikimedia Commons&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;extrapolations&#34;&gt;Extrapolations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, all around us we see fights that are supposedly about principle
but are really power struggles. Instead of landed nobility, we have
powerful lobbying groups, multinational corporations, you name
it. When any of these interests collude to win a battle over some
other one, they might not be in the game for you and me, but for
themselves. The purported idea of &amp;ldquo;democracy&amp;rdquo; is in fact under siege
today on many fronts. In future blog posts, I will begin exploring
what some of these are; they mostly involve technology-based power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2015-06-14&#34;&gt;(Update of 2015-06-14)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the local paper, I just read this really interesting article by
University of Pittsburgh law professor Bernard Hibbits on the
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.post-gazette.com/news/world/2015/06/14/How-Magna-Carta-helped-make-America/stories/201506150001&#34;&gt;opportunistic use of the Magna Carta by Americans&lt;/a&gt; throughout history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2015-06-16&#34;&gt;(Update of 2015-06-16)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A random
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bbc.com/news/uk-33126723&#34;&gt;news article about the celebrations&lt;/a&gt;
feature nothing but photos or descriptions of an Archbishop, the
Queen, various Dukes, a Prince, a Princess, a Lord, a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.therichest.com/celebnetworth/politician/minister/david-cameron-net-worth/&#34;&gt;Prime Minister&lt;/a&gt;
who
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_Cameron#Inheritance_and_family_wealth&#34;&gt;inherited much wealth (a lot hidden in tax shelters)&lt;/a&gt;,
and had no photos of &amp;ldquo;regular people&amp;rdquo;, or quotes from them asking what
they thought of the lavish occasion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yeah, same old, same old, 800 years later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Learning about the Magna Carta as a twelve-year-old was an important
part of my growing up in life. I learned that people are human and
selfish and have different motivations, but sometimes can work toward
agreements at least among themselves as equals, and some other party
as well. But I also learned the lesson that there are always those
who are left out at the bargaining table, and that the nobility are
always looking out for themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When did you learn about the Magna Carta in school? Did you learn it
  in the same gritty way that I did, or in a more romanticized way?
  Are there things you learned in history classes in school that
  changed your life, changed what you believe and how you act (as a
  voter or activist)?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thoughts on Cuba while watching Cuban musicians performing the 1947 bolero &#34;La gloria eres tú&#34;</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/12/13/thoughts-on-cuba-while-watching-cuban-musicians-performing-the-1947-bolero-la-gloria-eres-tu/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Dec 2014 21:01:47 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/12/13/thoughts-on-cuba-while-watching-cuban-musicians-performing-the-1947-bolero-la-gloria-eres-tu/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t expect to be thinking so much about Cuba today. It all started with a random musical itch I was scratching.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;la-comparsa-and-the-wooden-flute-headjoint&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;La comparsa&amp;rdquo; and the wooden flute headjoint&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I was in a Latin music mood as I was playing my flute at home, and started looking up flute versions of music on YouTube for fun and inspiration. One piece that came to mind was the famous &amp;ldquo;La comparsa&amp;rdquo;, by Cuban composer &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ernesto_Lecuona&#34;&gt;Ernesto Lecuona&lt;/a&gt;. Last year when Bebo Valdés died, I wrote about being moved by the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/22/rip-bebo-valdes/&#34;&gt;reunion of Bebo with his son Chucho in a tearful duet performance of this piece on two pianos&lt;/a&gt;, and thinking about their separation as Bebo abandoned his family to flee Cuba for Sweden while his son stayed behind to become one of Cuba&amp;rsquo;s great musicians.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found a really quirky Latin jazz performance of &amp;ldquo;La comparsa&amp;rdquo; on YouTube by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.chipboaz.com/blog/2014/07/10/cuban-flautist-bobby-ramirez-releases-jazz-flute/&#34;&gt;Cuban-American&lt;/a&gt; jazz flutist &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bobbyramirez.com/&#34;&gt;Bobby Ramirez&lt;/a&gt; and Puerto Rican &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.negronistrio.com/&#34;&gt;Jose Negroni&lt;/a&gt; on keyboard:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/4Nro7myJ6Nw&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ramirez on flute was unfortunately out of tune with the keyboard, but what I noticed was his wooden headjoint. I&amp;rsquo;ve never seen the old traditional Cuban wooden &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.descarga.com/cgi-bin/db/archives/Article15&#34;&gt;Charanga flute&lt;/a&gt;, but do see flutists playing the modern Boehm flute with a wooden headjoint for a different sound. In fact, I love and prefer wooden flutes, but they are expensive and I own only one, a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/30/got-my-new-casey-burns-small-handed-irish-flute/&#34;&gt;Casey Burns Irish flute&lt;/a&gt;. So just for the fun of it (I can&amp;rsquo;t really justify the investment right now), I decided to search the Web for makers of wooden headjoints.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;juan-novo-wooden-flute-headjoints&#34;&gt;Juan Novo wooden flute headjoints&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the top Web hits was &lt;a href=&#34;http://jnovoheadjoints.com/&#34;&gt;Juan Novo&lt;/a&gt;. It had the benefit of having an embedded YouTube video with the caption &amp;ldquo;This musician appreciated Mr. Novo’s craftsmanship so much, that this song was dedicated to him.&amp;rdquo; So I checked out the video. Indeed, the young woman playing the flute said, &amp;ldquo;Está para Juan Novo&amp;rdquo;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/kBzrwhpVvDE&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, I noticed that Juan Novo&amp;rsquo;s biography said he was sent from Cuba to the US all alone by his parents in 1962 to &lt;a href=&#34;http://jnovoheadjoints.com/about-juan-novo/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;escape the rampant communist indoctrination&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;la-gloria-eres-tú&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;La gloria eres tú&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was captivated not so much by the flute playing, but by the beautiful singing, of the young woman in this video of the classic bolero &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cancioneros.com/nc/2806/0/la-gloria-eres-tu-jose-antonio-mendez&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;La gloria eres tú&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; written by Cuban composer &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.encaribe.org/es/article/jose-antonio-mendez-garcia/1296&#34;&gt;José Antonio Méndez&lt;/a&gt; in 1947. I was really touched by her clear, unexaggerated but free expression and style, especially in light of much more famous performances of the song in my memory:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;La gloria eres tú&amp;rdquo; is one of my favorite boleros (&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/08/10/rip-eydie/&#34;&gt;my favorite being &amp;ldquo;Sabor a mî&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;) of all time. For comparison:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;luis-miguel&#34;&gt;Luis Miguel&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first exposure to &amp;ldquo;La gloria eres tú&amp;rdquo; was, like probably many others of my generation or younger worlwide, through the revival of the bolero by Mexican pop star &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Luis_Miguel&#34;&gt;Luis Miguel&lt;/a&gt; in the 1990s and onwards. I have all his bolero albums, a result of taking up Latin ballroom dancing in 2000 and hearing him singing in much of the music we practiced, performed, and competed to, including my first discovery of &amp;ldquo;Sabor a mî&amp;rdquo;, which was also on the 1997 album &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Romances_%28Luis_Miguel_album%29&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Romances&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. Luis Miguel is a great musician, I will continue to admit, but in time I drew away from his high-powered, slick performances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here he is live, from his 2000 DVD &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vivo_%28Luis_Miguel_album%29&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Vivo&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, which was the last thing I bought by him before backing away from his work:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/GNldCVbD4b4&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;olga-guillot&#34;&gt;Olga Guillot&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, the gold standard for &amp;ldquo;La gloria eres tú&amp;rdquo; is the performance by Cuban &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Olga_Guillot&#34;&gt;Olga Guillot&lt;/a&gt;, the &amp;ldquo;queen of the bolero&amp;rdquo;. (In 1961, she was yet another musician who fled Cuba.) I like how she alternates between different moods, starting out gently and almost like a prayer, but then gets more and more passionate. She very quickly changes the color of her voice and dynamics. For me it&amp;rsquo;s still the greatest performance of this bolero:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/xEAOX2nxsEo&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;elena-burke&#34;&gt;Elena Burke&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another recording I have of the bolero is from an album by Cuban singer &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elena_Burke&#34;&gt;Elena Burke&lt;/a&gt;. She has her own style, with a low voice, and more staccato delivery:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/yuHpvIvukOg&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elena died in Havana in 2002. Her daughter &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Malena_Burke&#34;&gt;Malena&lt;/a&gt; came to Miami in the US in 1995 with her family. Here is Malena Burke performing the bolero with Arturo Sandoval on piano:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/2_LxxwXda8Y&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Malena Burke&amp;rsquo;s oldest daughter &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lena_Burke&#34;&gt;Lena&lt;/a&gt; is also a musician, a pianist and singer, and has worked with Gloria Estefan and others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s Lena singing the famous 1929 bolero-son &lt;a href=&#34;http://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/L%C3%A1grimas_negras&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Lágrimas negras&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; with Bebo Valdés and others. This is such a weird combo, with her being sixty years younger than Bebo and stylistically very &amp;ldquo;American pop&amp;rdquo;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/x56VtBF6iGo&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;arturo-sandoval&#34;&gt;Arturo Sandoval&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arturo_Sandoval&#34;&gt;Arturo Sandoval&lt;/a&gt;, he defected from Cuba to the US in 2000. I discovered him initially when his biographical film &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/For_Love_or_Country:_The_Arturo_Sandoval_Story&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;For Love or Country&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; about his life before defection came out, and I saw him perform in the Three Rivers Arts Festival in Pittsburgh in 2002.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a Latin jazz version by Arturo Sandoval on flugelhorn, from his 1994 album &amp;ldquo;Tenderly&amp;rdquo;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/AZW15092fx4&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;where-is-blau-colonial-cayo-coco&#34;&gt;Where is Blau Colonial Cayo Coco?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So there were many thoughts and questions already in my mind as a result of listening to this old Cuban bolero, as a result of my remembering past performances by musicians who had left Cuba. When I hear classic boleros, I think about old Cuba, the culture and society that produced this kind of music and musicians, the political upheaval, the consequences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But back to that little band Nucay, captured presumably on a phone outside on a windy day by a random tourist who posted the video on YouTube in 2010. What has life been like for the members of Nucay, and for the charming young flutist/singer?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, what and where is &amp;ldquo;Blau Colonial Cayo Coco&amp;rdquo;? Apparently it&amp;rsquo;s a resort now named just &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cayocococuba.net/hotel_colonialcayococo.html&#34;&gt;Colonial Cayo Coco&lt;/a&gt; on the island of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cayo_Coco&#34;&gt;Cayo Coco&lt;/a&gt; that is part of Cuba. In particular, this place was designed to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cubahotelreservation.com/hotel.asp?hotel_code=sctblacolonial&#34;&gt;look like a village&lt;/a&gt;. This kind of thing makes me uncomfortable. I guess tourists fly in to pretend to have a nice &amp;ldquo;village&amp;rdquo; experience, while the hired musicians are probably paid to look and act the part.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;nucay&#34;&gt;Nucay&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I looked up more performances on YouTube by this band Nucay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;oye-como-va-cha-cha&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Oye como va&amp;rdquo;, cha-cha&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The caption for this video reads, &amp;ldquo;Ramon Almeida and daughter Arleytis [sic] lead this wonderful group of talented Cuban musicians.&amp;rdquo; So now we have some names. I presume the leader with maracas is the father? (Later I determined his daughter&amp;rsquo;s name is actually &amp;ldquo;Arletis&amp;rdquo;: read on.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was a fine performance of the classic cha-cha &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oye_Como_Va&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Oye coma va&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; written by &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tito_Puente&#34;&gt;Tito Puente&lt;/a&gt; in 1963. No, Puente was not Cuban; he was born in New York and was a big force in creating the mambo/salsa scene in the US in the 1950s. A great Latin jazz musician. I should have gone to see him perform live when he was in Pittsburgh in 2000 before he died. His music was great for listening to as well as dancing to; I still remember practicing my dancing to the first album of his I bought, &amp;ldquo;Mambo Birdland&amp;rdquo; (which has an &amp;ldquo;Oye como va&amp;rdquo; track).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I&amp;rsquo;ll confess that hearing performances of this work over a decade ago inspired me to think about taking up flute again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arletis did a fine job on flute here, jazzing things up:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/l4uWBPD7y70&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;ay-maria-merengue&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Ay Maria!&amp;rdquo;, merengue&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The musicians seem to be having fun; how could one not, given the catchy music and all of them singing? I really enjoyed flute action by Arletis in this upbeat classic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Merengue_music&#34;&gt;merengue&lt;/a&gt; is not Cuban, but comes from the Dominican Republic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/tAgVVL_ZTmI&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;sabor-a-mî&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Sabor a mî&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My favorite bolero, performed well. The caption reads &amp;ldquo;Cuban Music with the help of young percussionist from Quebec&amp;rdquo;, but this is wrong: &lt;a href=&#34;http://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sabor_a_m%C3%AD_%28canci%C3%B3n%29&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Sabor a mî&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; was composed in 1959 by a Mexican composer, &lt;a href=&#34;http://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/%C3%81lvaro_Carrillo&#34;&gt;Álvaro Carrillo&lt;/a&gt;. These distinctions matter to me: &amp;ldquo;Latin&amp;rdquo; music is not all the same, any more than the people or the distinct cultures are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/RmOIKdY3LYw&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;some-salsa-song&#34;&gt;Some salsa song&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is some salsa song; I&amp;rsquo;m afraid I cannot identify it offhand, the way I did the other songs. I&amp;rsquo;d have to try to transcribe the lyrics and hope that a Web search finds something, but have my doubts when it comes to salsa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I loved the father-daughter musical interplay here, with Ramón singing and Arletis on flute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/sAMdEezxYJs&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;summary-of-nucay&#34;&gt;Summary of Nucay&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OK, so Nucay is a pretty good band and plays a lot of classics to please the tourists. What else?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;arletis-almeida-sentirse-asi&#34;&gt;Arletis Almeida, &amp;ldquo;Sentirse Asi&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that a search for more Nucay material on YouTube reveals the following slick, professionally produced video uploaded by someone in 2012, promoting Arletis Almeida as a singer, with the caption &amp;ldquo;Arletis Almeida, flutist of Grupo Nucay in Cayo Coco Cuba, with her original song Sentirse Asi written by her father and band member Ramon Almeida&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, she is almost unrecognizable to me, very much made up and glamorous and placed in an urban nightlife setting, with shots of handsome men, alcohol, cigarettes. The contrast between this angsty, sensualized persona and the cheerful flutist playing at Colonial Cayo Coco with her father was quite jarring to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The singing is beautiful, and the song actually breaks out into a standard bolero accompaniment. It&amp;rsquo;s really something hearing bolero singing of this quality from a young person today. My overall feeling when hearing either this newly composed bolero or the classic music in the earlier videos is this: there&amp;rsquo;s some kind of time bubble that can still happen in the world, for better or for worse (a subject bigger than this blog post), and Nucay and Arletis Almeida illustrate it. Here in the US, no young people sing in this way. The many influences from pop, hip hop, and much more result in much more &amp;ldquo;fusion&amp;rdquo;. You saw that above in Lena Burke&amp;rsquo;s singing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/P1PZhDtCmLM&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;thoughts-on-cuba&#34;&gt;Thoughts on Cuba&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After watching this video, I wonder what has become of Arletis Almeida. Does she still play flute? Has she embarked on some kind of lounge career? Who knows? She&amp;rsquo;s in Cuba. Cuba is a world away. It took tourists to make her name even register on the Web, through the links to the YouTube videos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve waited for decades for an end to the senseless &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_States_embargo_against_Cuba&#34;&gt;embargo of Cuba&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;ve already run out of space here to even begin talking about the politics of the Cold War, about the human cost of isolating Cuba. Cuba, a place with a complicated history, but once an advanced nation by any standard, filled with culture, music classical and popular, home of world chess champion &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jos%C3%A9_Ra%C3%BAl_Capablanca&#34;&gt;Capablanca&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;con-los-años-que-me-quedan-and-nostalgia&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Con los años que me quedan&amp;rdquo; and nostalgia&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For some reason, I was reminded of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gloria_Estefan&#34;&gt;Gloria Estefan&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s music video of the bolero &amp;ldquo;Con los años que me quedan&amp;rdquo; from her nostalgic 1993 album &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mi_Tierra&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Mi Tierra&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s an odd kind of nostalgia, given that her parents fled Cuba when she was young. She made this album to embrace her Cuban heritage. But what world is portrayed here? Something like the world the tourists at Cayo Cayo hope to see? And what is Arletis trying to do as she sings boleros today?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, it&amp;rsquo;s definitely a beautiful song, and Estefan sings it soulfully:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/l6LjNOYvhMk&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2014-12-17&#34;&gt;(Update of 2014-12-17)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Totally by coincidence, news has come of the apparent &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2014/12/18/world/americas/us-cuba-relations.html&#34;&gt;plan by President Obama to normalize relations with Cuba&lt;/a&gt; after half a century. I cannot process this news right now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Life for Arletis and her father may well change one day in interesting ways.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Some good science-based reading for Election Day, whether or not you voted</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/04/some-good-science-based-reading-for-election-day/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2014 15:41:25 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/04/some-good-science-based-reading-for-election-day/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/11/01/how-i-avoid-demotivating-myself-away-from-voting/&#34;&gt;I voted&lt;/a&gt; today, on Election Day in the US.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/franklinmingchen/15527007380&#34; title=&#34;IMG_20141104_153326 by Franklin Chen, on Flickr&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7496/15527007380_abfb7f5691.jpg&#34; width=&#34;375&#34; height=&#34;500&#34; alt=&#34;IMG_20141104_153326&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, now is as good a time as any for some interesting articles about politics and voting. Here are some that came my way:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;motive-attribution-asymmetry&#34;&gt;Motive attribution asymmetry&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/oliver-burkeman-column/2014/nov/04/get-along-enemies-motive-attribution&#34;&gt;Oliver Burkeman&lt;/a&gt; discusses a study that shows that you argue that your side is motivated by &lt;em&gt;love&lt;/em&gt;, while the other side is motivated by &lt;em&gt;hate&lt;/em&gt;. But since the other side thinks the same, what is the &amp;ldquo;truth&amp;rdquo;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;One of the reasons it’s so hard to accept the notion that our enemies might be motivated by love, I suspect, is because that conclusion seems to suggest that our enemies’ cause must therefore have merit.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Actually, those two issues are completely unrelated.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I agree with this: it is quite possible (I&amp;rsquo;m not saying it&amp;rsquo;s always the case) for someone you disagree with to have the most loving intentions, but simply be &lt;em&gt;mistaken&lt;/em&gt; rather than &lt;em&gt;evil&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;dangers-of-accurate-statistical-prediction-by-data-journalism&#34;&gt;Dangers of accurate statistical prediction by data journalism&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A good article in the Berkeley Journal of Sociology about &lt;a href=&#34;http://berkeleyjournal.org/2014/11/what-should-the-fox-say/&#34;&gt;Nate Silver&amp;rsquo;s statistical journalism&lt;/a&gt; argues that data journalism should focus on understanding rather than prediction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;This extensive use of Big Data for election forecasting passively promotes our current sense of political fatalism.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;If our politicians can’t risk making public appearances or trying to appear human without navigating at least three levels of performative irony, then our political culture has entered a state of structural crisis.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;emotions-of-election-day-asymmetric-hedonic-response&#34;&gt;Emotions of Election Day: asymmetric hedonic response&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://harvardmagazine.com/2014/11/emotions-of-elections-study-todd-rogers&#34;&gt;Harvard Kennedy School research result&lt;/a&gt; on asymmetric hedonic response: after an election, losing makes you far sadder than winning makes you happy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I confess to having been really bummed out fairly often in the past two decades of voting. I&amp;rsquo;ve been trying to be more detached.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;in-praise-of-the-occasional-voter&#34;&gt;In praise of the occasional voter&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, some people make fun of people who do not vote (I never do this; there are often quite rational reasons to avoid voting). Here&amp;rsquo;s an interesting article arguing that the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2014/11/02/upshot/the-vital-role-of-the-occasional-voter.html&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;occasional voter&amp;rdquo; is actually quite valuable&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From an economics point of view, &amp;ldquo;voting is a classic example of a free-rider problem&amp;rdquo; because the possible gain for each individual is so tiny, statistically, that it may not make sense to go out of one&amp;rsquo;s way to vote.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, voting has an interesting cost to the voter: &amp;ldquo;The very act of voting for a given candidate or party ties us mentally to that candidate and inadvertently costs us some measure of our neutrality.&amp;rdquo; This is because we &lt;em&gt;rationalize&lt;/em&gt; what we do in order to resolve our &lt;em&gt;cognitive dissonance&lt;/em&gt; about the apparent pointlessness of voting. We try to fool ourselves into thinking we did something really important. &amp;ldquo;We don’t just choose what we like; we like more and more what we choose.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the &amp;ldquo;occasional voter&amp;rdquo; can be an outsider not subject to cognitive dissonance as much as the regular and party-registered voter, countering partisanship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, it could be argued that partisanship, and the resulting gridlock, is good. But is it? That&amp;rsquo;s another topic entirely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-strange-sameness-of-political-candidates-in-the-face-of-competition&#34;&gt;The strange sameness of political candidates in the face of competition&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Conversable Economist, Timothy Taylor, offered an explanation for &lt;a href=&#34;http://conversableeconomist.blogspot.com/2014/11/the-excessive-sameness-of-politics-and.html&#34;&gt;why politicians end up in the same squishy middle&lt;/a&gt;, based on &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Harold_Hotelling&#34;&gt;Hotelling&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s famous 1929 mathematical model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Mainstream politicians thus face a continual dynamic where they seek to reassure their more ardent partisans that they are on their side, while shading and tacking as needed to pick up voters in the middle.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, if you are interested in more mathematical modeling, check out Scott Page&amp;rsquo;s free MOOC on &amp;ldquo;model thinking&amp;rdquo;, which I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/06/16/review-of-coursera-course-model-thinking/&#34;&gt;reviewed here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;bloggers-reactions-to-election-day&#34;&gt;Bloggers&amp;rsquo; reactions to Election Day&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a blogger I follow, &lt;a href=&#34;http://ayjay.tumblr.com/post/101755797073/and-one-more-note-on-politics&#34;&gt;Alan Jacobs, on his options&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/the-fix/wp/2013/05/09/people-hate-congress-but-most-incumbents-get-re-elected-what-gives/&#34;&gt;People hate Congress, but 90% of incumbents get re-elected&lt;/a&gt;. &amp;ldquo;The message from voters to Congress? Throw the bums out. But not my bum.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope you enjoyed this taste of research results concerning psychology, sociology, and economics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not staying up to watch the returns from today&amp;rsquo;s election. I did what I did, and it&amp;rsquo;s over for me until next May.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Did you learn anything surprising in the links I shared here? Is there anything that will change how you think or behave when it comes to politics?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How I avoid demotivating myself away from voting</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/01/how-i-avoid-demotivating-myself-away-from-voting/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Nov 2014 22:11:10 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/01/how-i-avoid-demotivating-myself-away-from-voting/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s that time of year again: three days from today is Election Day. I&amp;rsquo;ve written a few posts about voting over the past couple of years here already, and I&amp;rsquo;ve clearly changed my attitude about it over time:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/08/i-dont-know-if-i-should-vote-but-i-did/&#34;&gt;November 2011&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;April 2012: I was too apathetic to vote.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/11/06/i-decided-to-resign-myself-to-continue-voting/&#34;&gt;November 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/05/21/voting-in-the-face-of-election-apathy/&#34;&gt;May 2013&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;November 2013: I voted but wrote nothing about it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/05/20/why-i-voted-yet-again/&#34;&gt;May 2014&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is my first post &lt;em&gt;before&lt;/em&gt; an Election Day rather than &lt;em&gt;after&lt;/em&gt; having voted. Why the change this time?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;reflections-on-my-past-behavior-and-attitudes&#34;&gt;Reflections on my past behavior and attitudes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have always been frustrated by politics and voting. That showed in my posts in the last three years. I always got very &lt;em&gt;emotional&lt;/em&gt; and torn about the whole process. I finally settled on a habit of trying to &lt;em&gt;minimize&lt;/em&gt; my involvement, not paying attention to any races or &amp;ldquo;debates&amp;rdquo; or any political coverage in the news until the night before Election Day, but I was still unhappy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-situation-now&#34;&gt;The situation now&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, it is still the case that I have not looked at any political coverage for Tuesday. In fact, I have no idea who&amp;rsquo;s running for what, with one major exception: Governor of Pennsylvania. That&amp;rsquo;s been in the news for a year now, and totally unavoidable if you live in PA at all, and especially if you bothered to vote in the primary in May, which I did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that I am accidentally less &lt;em&gt;angry&lt;/em&gt; now than I used to be, because unknown to me, Abby has intercepted all political flyers arriving in our mailbox or &lt;em&gt;on our doorknob&lt;/em&gt; (how dare they!) and recycled them, with one exception.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;negative-emotions-came-back&#34;&gt;Negative emotions came back&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I saw a flyer in a pile of mail. I tried not to see anything as I picked it up and recycled it, but it was impossible to see &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt;. I have to hand it to the designer: the name of the politician reached my eye somehow, even though I prided myself on not seeing a single word (at least consciously) of anything else on the flyer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A rush of disgust and anger came my way, as I reflected that actually, this is someone I already decided last May in the primary to vote for in the general election. As I&amp;rsquo;ve mentioned in previous posts, flyers that are shouting, negative, fear-mongering, and deceptive &lt;em&gt;piss me off&lt;/em&gt; and make me want to &lt;em&gt;puke down the throats&lt;/em&gt; of these politicians, &lt;em&gt;especially those I expect to vote for&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Note that in order to minimize bias, I have never heard this guy talk, and barely recall what he looks like, although I think I saw some head shot back in May. Also, I have no idea what he&amp;rsquo;s been doing or saying since May, or whether any truly major scandal has broken out, although I assume I would have heard by now if so. I will learn what I need to know on Monday night.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;taking-more-control&#34;&gt;Taking more control&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But now, after having &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/10/31/win-ugly-or-lose-pretty-do-you-agree/&#34;&gt;read that fascinating article yesterday about emotional manipulation&lt;/a&gt;, I have decided that these politicians are only doing the rational thing in their game, nothing personal. You might want to argue that this is a flaw in democracy, as many ancient and modern philosophers have, of course, but that would be another topic of discussion entirely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was also annoyed by the robocall on the answering machine at home today, from the same guy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;action-to-further-minimize-annoyance&#34;&gt;Action to further minimize annoyance&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We shut off the answering machine for our land line. We will not be answering any phone calls until after Election Day. Actually, we are not sure why we need any phones connected to our land line anyway, because in principle we could make sure all relevant accounts list our cell phones as our primary phone numbers (most already do but some old ones don&amp;rsquo;t yet). We only need the land line for DSL purposes. The land line has been mostly nothing but trouble, a target for robocalls of all kinds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, I wish there were a way to stop getting junk mail in general. Not just the election season junk mail, but all junk mail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There will be no Election Day blog post on Tuesday. I&amp;rsquo;ve said all I need to say for this Election Day.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Win ugly or lose pretty: do you agree?</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/10/31/win-ugly-or-lose-pretty-do-you-agree/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2014 22:53:18 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/10/31/win-ugly-or-lose-pretty-do-you-agree/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I read a juicy article &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2014/10/31/us/politics/pr-executives-western-energy-alliance-speech-taped.html&#34;&gt;Hard-Nosed Advice From Veteran Lobbyist: &amp;ldquo;Win Ugly or Lose Pretty&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; that exposed a speech by a political consultant, Rick Berman, that remarkably, offended one of the participants enough to cause a leak to the public.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The full transcript is &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2014/10/31/us/politics/31lobbyist-docs.html&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you love preserving your independence of mind, get angry when secretly manipulated, and want to learn a bunch of tricks of the trade, you&amp;rsquo;ll want to read the whole thing!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some highlights I found worth making note of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;public-opinion-versus-public-judgment&#34;&gt;Public opinion versus public judgment&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Berman makes a point of distinguishing between &lt;em&gt;public opinion&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;public judgment&lt;/em&gt;. He focuses on how to influence public judgment when the war cannot be won on opinion. Opinion is good to influence when possible, of course, but judgment is what actually matters, because it is the act of deciding to vote for some &lt;em&gt;policy&lt;/em&gt; because of some &lt;em&gt;facts&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;offense-versus-defense&#34;&gt;Offense versus defense&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Berman advocates always being on the offense, not defense. Being on defense is &lt;em&gt;reacting&lt;/em&gt; to someone else. All students of psychology know that reacting is very poor tactics, because it leaves the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Framing_effect_%28psychology%29&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;framing&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; of a situation up to the opponent, and therefore gives the opponent the advantage as far as natural human cognitive bias.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example: in order to &lt;em&gt;prevent change&lt;/em&gt;, throw around a lot of information and hypotheticals about what could happen upon change, in such a way as to confuse people and get them into a state of &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;I don&amp;rsquo;t know who to believe&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;. You want to make it sound like a possible &lt;em&gt;tie&lt;/em&gt; to be broken. Because then by default, the psychological tendency is to give up and not decide, because &amp;ldquo;People are not prepared to get aggressive and in moving one way or another&amp;rdquo;. Therefore, the status quo remains, and the status quo is a &lt;em&gt;win&lt;/em&gt; for the side that wants to prevent change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, apparently it&amp;rsquo;s good to toss in &lt;em&gt;children&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;animals&lt;/em&gt; to make one&amp;rsquo;s opponents seem cartoonish and not to be taken seriously. Also, these kinds of images or videos are popular, helping the spread of such material.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And &amp;ldquo;I like to use humor to minimize or marginalize the people on the other side.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;common-knowledge&#34;&gt;Common knowledge&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Berman says that the goal is not to just send a message out there but to make it &amp;ldquo;common knowledge&amp;rdquo;, something that people just assume because they heard it somewhere enough (completely independently of its truth, of course). And not just somewhere, but &amp;ldquo;enough times from enough different places&amp;rdquo;. It&amp;rsquo;s important to make it look like the message came from different sources, hence the &amp;ldquo;different places&amp;rdquo;. (Nobody will be fooled if they know exactly where the message came from and that it came from one mastermind.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;jack-hubbard-on-diminishing-moral-authority&#34;&gt;Jack Hubbard on diminishing moral authority&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Diminishing moral authority of the opposition means winning through making the other side &lt;em&gt;lose&lt;/em&gt;. (Jack Hubbard took over from Rick Berman to speak at this point.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One obvious way is to go &lt;em&gt;personal&lt;/em&gt;. Rip apart the personal lives of people on the opposition. For example, the left-wing Congressman who is discovered to have a large investment in the energy industry: the public enjoys exposing &lt;em&gt;hypocrisy&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;We have a section on every single activist. Their rap sheets, their criminal records that they have. We&amp;rsquo;re really making this personal.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And &amp;ldquo;engaging unique or third party messengers to get involved on this stuff.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;The public really does have a celebrity worship culture. But&amp;hellip;there is nothing the public likes more than tearing down celebrities and playing up the hypocrisy angle.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;rick-berman-on-emotions-and-flags&#34;&gt;Rick Berman on emotions and FLAGS&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Berman reminded the audience that some did not want to go offensive in that nasty way, but you have to &amp;ldquo;win ugly or lose pretty&amp;rdquo;. &amp;ldquo;I was convinced you could not get into people&amp;rsquo;s heads and convince them to do something as easily as you could get into their hearts or into their gut to convince them to do something.&amp;rdquo; It&amp;rsquo;s all about &lt;em&gt;emotions&lt;/em&gt;. His acronym FLAGS:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fear&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Love&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anger&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Greed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sympathy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the particular campaign he was describing, he deliberately wanted to tap &lt;em&gt;fear&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;anger&lt;/em&gt;. Because &amp;ldquo;we&amp;rsquo;re not going to get people to like the oil and gas industry over the next few months&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;endless-war&#34;&gt;Endless war&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Berman reminded his audience that &amp;ldquo;this is an endless war&amp;rdquo;. Winning one battle is not enough because the opposition will keep trying win; it does not think of any single loss as a loss for the cause, but just &amp;ldquo;haven&amp;rsquo;t won &lt;em&gt;yet&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Berman used the metaphor &amp;ldquo;natural enemy&amp;rdquo;: the Sierra Club has no &amp;ldquo;natural enemy&amp;rdquo;. It is hard to fight against something that does not have a natural enemy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-not-to-be-found-out&#34;&gt;How not to be found out&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;We run all of this stuff through nonprofit organizations that are insulated from having to disclose donors&amp;hellip; we&amp;rsquo;ve been doing this for 20 something years&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;study-the-other-side&#34;&gt;Study the other side&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good quote from Berman: &amp;ldquo;I studied what the other side did to be successful and then translated it into how businesses can use those tactics&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;always-aim-for-the-middle&#34;&gt;Always aim for the middle&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;We&amp;rsquo;re always aiming with our messages for the people in the middle. I don&amp;rsquo;t try to appeal to the people who already believe in us. And I don&amp;rsquo;t try to convince people who are never going to agree with me, so I&amp;rsquo;m always playing the middle.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People like Rick Berman are master psychologists. Whether you agree with his tactics or not, know them and know that they are effective. Now it&amp;rsquo;s your turn:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Do you or would you use these tactics yourself, for some cause that you deeply believe in? Why or why not?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Was there something you learned that surprised you?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Is there some decision you made in the past that you now consider as having been triggered by a FLAGS emotional manipulation?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Disclaimer: Berman&amp;rsquo;s messages have no effect on me; I am not his intended &amp;ldquo;middle&amp;rdquo; audience.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why I voted yet again</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/05/20/why-i-voted-yet-again/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 May 2014 22:52:11 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/05/20/why-i-voted-yet-again/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I voted again, as I&amp;rsquo;ve been doing regularly for some years now.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/voter-receipt-primary-2014.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;2014 PA primary election voter receipt&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But why?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/05/21/voting-in-the-face-of-election-apathy/&#34;&gt;vented a bit about voting&lt;/a&gt; but did so anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year, I paid almost no attention to any media coverage before the election. This included deleting answer machine messages, and summarily recycling all campaign flyers sent to my home, with an attempt not to even see who sent them. I don&amp;rsquo;t know if it&amp;rsquo;s just my imagination, but these flyers have gotten louder and more annoying and inane. I made the mistake of actually seeing &lt;em&gt;one&lt;/em&gt; of these flyers (and therefore know who it was from). In all caps and colored, bold text (if I recall correctly), it said something like&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Mike knows us.

And we know Mike.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That pretty much sums up what political campaigns are. And we know that psychologically, this stuff works. Just slamming someone&amp;rsquo;s name into our brains, creating &amp;ldquo;familiarity&amp;rdquo;, influences votes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yeah, I voted for Mike anyway. After all, &amp;ldquo;I know him&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;governor&#34;&gt;Governor&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I knew very little about the main race, the primary election for Pennsylvania governor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The night before, I did a little bit of research, largely on whom to vote &lt;em&gt;against&lt;/em&gt;. One candidate apparently stood out for pretty harsh negative ads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the whole, such negative ads turn me off. Now, I understand that psychologically, some people are motivated by negative ads to go vote against the target. But it&amp;rsquo;s actually difficult to anticipate exactly what the tradeoff is, in terms of attracting support vs. fueling the opposition. Obviously, I would never make a decision based purely on campaign tactics, but in this case, I figured I would go with someone not particularly different on issues who did &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; engage in this kind of behavior.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;but-why-vote-at-all&#34;&gt;But why vote at all?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wish I could tell you that I feel I&amp;rsquo;m making a difference by voting. I&amp;rsquo;m not sure that&amp;rsquo;s true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wish I could tell you that I feel it is my &amp;ldquo;civic duty&amp;rdquo; to vote, because I have the privilege of having the right to do so as a citizen of the United States. I&amp;rsquo;m not sure I feel that is my duty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The truth is, I vote every election day now simply because I&amp;rsquo;ve developed a &lt;em&gt;habit&lt;/em&gt; of it, and a &lt;em&gt;system&lt;/em&gt; (avoiding media coverage that would piss me off, and doing a bit of homework the night before election day). So, it&amp;rsquo;s just what I do now. I no longer question whether I will get out there and press the big red button. I just do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Do you vote? In every election or just high-profile primary or general elections, such as presidential? Why do you vote or not vote?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reflections on Richard Wagner&#39;s 200th birthday: beautiful music without a future</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/05/22/reflections-on-richard-wagners-200th-birthday/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 May 2013 08:14:55 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/05/22/reflections-on-richard-wagners-200th-birthday/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A couple of days ago, I was driving and had the radio on and heard Richard Wagner&amp;rsquo;s prelude to act 1 of his opera &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Die_Meistersinger_von_N%C3%BCrnberg&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Die Meistersinger&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, and was transported into the lush musical world that is so uniquely Wagner: seductive orchestral colors, chromatic harmony, melodic motifs, fine storytelling, stirring climaxes, and in this particular musical excerpt, ironic yet clever use of counterpoint. I had to pull over for a while to finish listening to the prelude and fully enjoy the &lt;em&gt;guilty&lt;/em&gt; rush of emotional excitement in this fun but over-the-top piece. Why the guilt?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;controversy&#34;&gt;Controversy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The controversial music composer &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_Wagner&#34;&gt;Richard Wagner&lt;/a&gt; was born 200 years ago. In keeping with the media&amp;rsquo;s love of arbitrarily nice round numbers and anniversaries, there&amp;rsquo;s a lot of commentary about celebrations of his birthdays or reasons &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; to celebrate. Here are just a few articles that came up during a Web search:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.washingtonpost.com/entertainment/music/germany-celebrates-200th-birthday-of-composer-richard-wagner/2013/05/22/b8f93924-c2b2-11e2-9642-a56177f1cdf7_story.html?tid=pm_entertainment_pop&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Germany celebrates 200th birthday of Richard Wagner, Hitler&amp;rsquo;s favorite composer&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://fullcomment.nationalpost.com/2013/05/22/barbara-kay-if-you-must-listen-to-wagner-do-it-in-private/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;If you must listen to Wagner, do it in private&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.towntopics.com/wordpress/2013/05/22/whistling-in-the-dark-on-wagners-200th-birthday/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Whistling in the dark on Wagner&amp;rsquo;s 200th birthday&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://jessicamusic.blogspot.com/2013/05/dear-richard-i-need-to-tell-you.html&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Dear Richard, I need to tell you something&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.newyorker.com/online/blogs/culture/2013/05/wagner-bicentennial-birthday-music-recordings.html&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;A Wagner birthday roast&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;None of this commentary actually addresses my mixed feelings about Wagner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;wagner-s-anti-semitism&#34;&gt;Wagner&amp;rsquo;s anti-Semitism?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much of the commentary touches upon Wagner&amp;rsquo;s anti-Semitism and Adolf Hitler&amp;rsquo;s use of Wagner in Germany for Nazi purposes. I will &lt;em&gt;not be discussing&lt;/em&gt; these (important) issues because others already do, and because I tend toward the view that people are imperfect and I would like to be able to assess their important and good work even if they could be judged as unpleasant or downright evil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;love-the-music-hate-the-man&#34;&gt;Love the music, hate the man?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I also do not agree with the sentiment of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.independent.co.uk/voices/comment/on-the-200th-anniversary-of-wagners-birth-lets-learn-to-love-the-music--yet-still-hate-the-man-8614155.html&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Let&amp;rsquo;s learn to love the music, yet still hate the man&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. I don&amp;rsquo;t think there is a total separation between Wagner&amp;rsquo;s music and everything else about him. In Wagner&amp;rsquo;s case, in particular, he specifically designed his music around a certain philosophy about the world, about &lt;em&gt;art&lt;/em&gt;. And that is what I really find interesting and unsettling, somewhat along the lines of Friedrich Nietzsche&amp;rsquo;s critique of his one-time friend, &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Case_of_Wagner&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Case of Wagner&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nietzsche_contra_Wagner&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Nietzsche contra Wagner&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;music-and-philosophy&#34;&gt;Music and philosophy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wagner&amp;rsquo;s philosophizing about the nature of and purpose of music embraced the notion of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gesamtkunstwerk&#34;&gt;Gesamtkunstwerk&lt;/a&gt;, the &amp;ldquo;total work of art&amp;rdquo;, that would unify all the arts, hence his development of his form of opera, the &amp;ldquo;music drama&amp;rdquo;, whose purpose was to unify music, poetry, theater in a grand and serious spectacle to inspire the audience. He proposed the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Music_of_the_Future&#34;&gt;Zukunftsmusik&lt;/a&gt;, or &amp;ldquo;music of the future&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;modernism&#34;&gt;Modernism?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Wagner&amp;rsquo;s day in the late 19th century, there was &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/War_of_the_Romantics&#34;&gt;fierce rivalry among the German Romantics&lt;/a&gt; on the direction of musical evolution. Roughly, there was the camp of Johannes Brahms (whose &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/05/07/happy-birthday-johannes-brahms/&#34;&gt;birthday I celebrated a few weeks ago&lt;/a&gt;, considered &amp;ldquo;conservative&amp;rdquo;, and the camp of Wagner, which considered itself &amp;ldquo;modern&amp;rdquo;. Aspects of this &amp;ldquo;war&amp;rdquo; seem quaint and exaggerated now, and Brahms has been &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.economist.com/node/367351&#34;&gt;re-evaluated&lt;/a&gt; in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/1996/09/29/arts/old-brahms-a-modernist-in-more-ways-than-one.html&#34;&gt;recent&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.americansymphony.org/concert_notes/the-other-voice-of-johannes-brahms&#34;&gt;decades&lt;/a&gt;, and the big tent of Western art music has historically learned from both camps&amp;rsquo; methods and sensibilities, but Wagner, at least, took very seriously his own self-importance and self-promotion as an artist/philosopher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An interesting question to me is, what is Wagner&amp;rsquo;s relationship to &lt;em&gt;modernism&lt;/em&gt;, both in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Modernism_%28music%29&#34;&gt;musical sense&lt;/a&gt; and in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Modernism&#34;&gt;more general sense&lt;/a&gt;, typically applied to the late 19th century and early 20th century trends in literature, art, architecture, and society that are still relevant today?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;tristan&#34;&gt;Tristan&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.guardian.co.uk/friday_review/story/0,,381181,00.html&#34;&gt;harmonic and other innovations&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tristan_und_Isolde&#34;&gt;Tristan und Isolde&lt;/a&gt; in 1865 (it is arguable that Franz Liszt was the real innovator first) can be considered the beginning of modernism in music (in the sense of dissolution of Western tonality). Check out this performance of the beginning of the prelude to act 1 along with a score annotated with harmonic analysis:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/Pwk3BKipjtQ&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s my favorite full performance of the prelude as well as the final sung Liebestod, by the great Wilhelm Furtwängler conducting and Kirsted Flagstad singing. It truly blew my mind when I first discovered and heard this music while in college.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/SQO7QIgNvA0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;who-claims-modernism&#34;&gt;Who claims modernism?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the modernist &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Second_Viennese_School&#34;&gt;Second Viennese School&lt;/a&gt; under Arnold Schönberg liked to claim Brahms as one of their own, and in even more revisionism recently, there have been attempts to situate &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.upress.umn.edu/book-division/books/modernism-after-wagner&#34;&gt;Wagner as the inspiration for modernism in the larger sense&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(A few of my notes about Schönberg &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/25/thank-you-glenn-gould/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Also, it is too large a topic for now, but I plan to write more later about modernism and postmodernism and post-postmodernism in music, in the context of today&amp;rsquo;s music and in my own experience of music, whether listening or performing.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;wagner-s-legacy&#34;&gt;Wagner&amp;rsquo;s legacy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe Wagner failed, that his philosophy was a dead end, and that his music was a dead end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This despite the fact that, of course, he changed the course of Western musical history, both by provoking the modernist backlash against his theatricalism and chromaticism, while paving the way for, say, Mahler and Bruckner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have enjoyed and continue to occasionally listen again to marvelous music by Wagner, but &lt;em&gt;not in the way he intended&lt;/em&gt;. I have never attended a performance of one of his operas. I have only seen (on TV or video) or listened to bits of his operas that are sung (rather than purely instrumental excerpts). Two decades ago, I did try to watch the mammoth &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Der_Ring_des_Nibelungen&#34;&gt;Ring cycle&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/1990/06/18/arts/review-television-taking-the-17-hour-plunge-with-wagner-s-ring-at-the-met.html&#34;&gt;broadcast on TV by the Metropolitan Opera&lt;/a&gt; over four long evenings, but my attention span allowed me to only drift in and out of consciousness periodically during that attempt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps most damning of all is that shortly after that TV experience, I rather enjoyed listening to Lorin Maazel&amp;rsquo;s album, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/music/dp/B000003CUJ&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Ring Without Words&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, basically showing that for me, Wagner totally failed as a philosopher, because I like his music best without the &amp;ldquo;poetry&amp;rdquo; (his lyrics, which he wrote himself, don&amp;rsquo;t make much sense to me) and without the on-stage drama.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even then, I cannot listen to his music much without feeling unclean. There is a sense in which I cannot separate his music from his philosophy and his wider artistic and cultural aims. Even if he had not been an anti-Semite, there should be controversy over him and his legacy. There is a sense in which I agree with some of the old-fashioned concerns about his music: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.guardian.co.uk/music/2013/may/22/wagner-bad-for-your-mental-health&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Wagner as mental health menace?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. In Nietzsche&amp;rsquo;s words, Wagner and his music are &lt;em&gt;decadent&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2014-07-13&#34;&gt;(Update of 2014-07-13)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/07/13/what-i-remember-lorin-maazel-for/&#34;&gt;RIP, Lorin Maazel&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;music-is-powerful&#34;&gt;Music is powerful&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it&amp;rsquo;s pretty delicious decadence. Last month a friend splurged on going to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://ringcycle.metoperafamily.org/&#34;&gt;Metropolitan Opera&amp;rsquo;s performance of the Ring&lt;/a&gt;, and I decided to indulge in listening to Siegfried&amp;rsquo;s funeral march in &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/G%C3%B6tterd%C3%A4mmerung&#34;&gt;Götterdämmerung&lt;/a&gt;. As usual, the experience left me in tears. Wagner, master psychologist, master manipulator of emotions, master composer, weaving the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leitmotif&#34;&gt;leitmotifs&lt;/a&gt;, summing up the whole tragic story of the Ring:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/L8wHteSOwW4&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And for sheer &lt;em&gt;hypnotism&lt;/em&gt;, listen to Furtwängler again, with the prelude to act 1 of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lohengrin_%28opera%29&#34;&gt;Lohengrin&lt;/a&gt;. Close your eyes, turn out the lights, and listen. Beautiful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/I_m7PN5sn1U&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More hypnosis: prelude to act 1 of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parsifal&#34;&gt;Parsifal&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;ve chosen an old Furtwängler performance again:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/EZhSUX5Ix68&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;back-to-die-meistersinger&#34;&gt;Back to Die Meistersinger&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, to end where I started, with the prelude to act 1 of Die Meistersinger that I happened to enjoy on the radio, here is Furtwängler again, conducting a performance of it live. &lt;strong&gt;Warning: this is a video of a live performance in 1942 in Germany with swastikas in the background, so you may not wish to view this.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/3rM96_RS1Os&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, this video is totally creepy, but I thought it would be appropriate to close on this jarring note. Die Meistersinger was, after all, Wagner&amp;rsquo;s telling of a story to glorify old Germany, and was a favorite opera of the Nazis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(And the subject of Furtwängler, a conductor I have many mixed feelings about, will have to wait for another blog post as well.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I cannot help but admire and be affected by Wagner&amp;rsquo;s music, but at the same time feel that his entire philosophy and aim was bankrupt. I&amp;rsquo;ve touched on only a little bit of how I have come to feel this, since the larger issues go beyond Wagner, but I don&amp;rsquo;t yet have complete thoughts and rationales to offer at this time. As with the towering figure of Beethoven, his musical and cultural legacy is still controversial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;postscript&#34;&gt;Postscript&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided I wanted to end more positively. My favorite piece of Wagner&amp;rsquo;s is one that was actually always intended to be purely instrumental and is self-contained, not just an excerpt: the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Siegfried_Idyll&#34;&gt;Siegfried Idyll&lt;/a&gt;. Oh wait, again we all subvert his intention anyway, because he composed it for his wife Cosima&amp;rsquo;s birthday (what a beautiful present to wake up to in the morning) and only ever intended it to be performed privately!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furtwängler again:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/_jlzEFg-zkY&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2014-07-11&#34;&gt;(Update of 2014-07-11)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I just saw yet another article about &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.newrepublic.com/article/118331/forbidden-music-michael-haas-reviewed-james-loeffler&#34;&gt;Wagner and anti-Semitism&lt;/a&gt;. The topic never goes anyway, and I don&amp;rsquo;t think it should. That said, I don&amp;rsquo;t personally have anything to add to the discussion, but offer the link if you feel you need to engage further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2015-01-14&#34;&gt;(Update of 2015-01-14)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I saw yet another (and excellent) article &lt;a href=&#34;http://mosaicmagazine.com/essay/2015/01/wagner-and-the-jews/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Wagner and the Jews&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Voting in the face of election apathy</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/05/21/voting-in-the-face-of-election-apathy/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 May 2013 19:17:44 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/05/21/voting-in-the-face-of-election-apathy/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/voter-receipt-primary-2013.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;My voter receipt, May 2013&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Those of you who follow my blog know that I have been conflicted about voting, but go and do it anyway, &lt;em&gt;most of the time&lt;/em&gt;, e.g., &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/08/i-dont-know-if-i-should-vote-but-i-did/&#34;&gt;in November 2011 for the municipal election&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/11/06/i-decided-to-resign-myself-to-continue-voting/&#34;&gt;in November 2012 for the general election&lt;/a&gt;, when I felt there were some politicians very important to &lt;em&gt;vote against&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;apathy-or-ignorance&#34;&gt;Apathy or ignorance?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In April 2012&amp;rsquo;s general primary, however, I was sufficiently apathetic that I didn&amp;rsquo;t bother voting, although Abby did. For that election, it seemed to me that the winners were all going to be obvious no matter what I did, and there were no close races where I really cared about who won. I feel that in the absence of an informed opinion, the only rational and moral thing to do is to stay out. It is &lt;em&gt;unfashionable&lt;/em&gt; in our society to admit &lt;a href=&#34;http://opinionator.blogs.nytimes.com/2013/04/29/the-power-of-i-dont-know/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;I don&amp;rsquo;t know&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, but if I truly don&amp;rsquo;t know, then I see no point in participating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Primary_election&#34;&gt;Primary elections&lt;/a&gt; are particularly problematic for me, because I simply oppose the concept and also resent being forced to register for one of the two major American political parties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;may-2013-municipal-primary-choosing-mayor&#34;&gt;May 2013 municipal primary: choosing mayor!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this year&amp;rsquo;s Democratic primary is &lt;em&gt;critical&lt;/em&gt;, because it will basically determine who becomes the next &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pittsburgh_mayoral_election,_2013&#34;&gt;mayor of Pittsburgh&lt;/a&gt;, given that a Democrat will win in the general election in November. And since &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Luke_Ravenstahl&#34;&gt;Luke Ravenstahl&lt;/a&gt; decided to step down, there is a possibility of &lt;em&gt;real change&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I was pretty excited to vote today to make a difference (I hope). This will be the first time I have voted for a &lt;a href=&#34;http://triblive.com/politics/politicalheadlines/4052165-74/percent-mayor-turnout&#34;&gt;mayoral candidate in a primary&lt;/a&gt; in my 15 years as a Pittsburgh resident. For once there may be a crack in the rusty Democratic political machine here?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.post-gazette.com/stories/local/neighborhoods-city/polls-open-for-primary-election-688496/&#34;&gt;Voter turnout today has been crazy low&lt;/a&gt;. There was no line whatsoever when I went to vote or when Abby went. I&amp;rsquo;ve never participated in an election, I think, with such low turnout.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Maybe this low turnout will end up being a good thing&lt;/em&gt;. If people choose not to vote because they don&amp;rsquo;t have informed opinions, then it means that I and the surprisingly large number of people I know who also voted for the same guy I did will &lt;em&gt;win&lt;/em&gt;! (That said, it&amp;rsquo;s sad if &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pittsburghmagazine.com/Best-of-the-Burgh-Blogs/Pitt-Girl/June-2013/Why-You-Must-Vote-in-Pittsburghs-Mayoral-Election/&#34;&gt;only 2 percent of us decide the mayor&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;media-coverage&#34;&gt;Media coverage&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I avoided &lt;em&gt;most&lt;/em&gt; media coverage of the election (hard to avoid everything completely, admittedly) until I had already voted. (Yes, that includes ignoring the basically meaningless &amp;ldquo;endorsements&amp;rdquo; of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.post-gazette.com/&#34;&gt;Post-Gazette&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://triblive.com/&#34;&gt;Tribune-Review&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I enjoyed reading &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pghcitypaper.com/Blogh/archives/2013/05/21/election-day-thoughts&#34;&gt;this little look at what&amp;rsquo;s been going on with the mayoral race&lt;/a&gt;. And tomorrow I am back to ignoring the news.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, I had to recycle probably 30 or so paper flyers during election season. What a waste. And summarily delete dozens of robocalls on the answering machine. Note to everyone who sent me junk or left junk messages on my answering machine: &lt;em&gt;I did not read a single thing you sent, or listen to a single word you spoke; your junk only made me angry and at least partly less likely to vote for you, if I caught your name and remembered it&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;Pathetic.&lt;/strong&gt; I realize this crap works on some people, but I&amp;rsquo;m afraid it doesn&amp;rsquo;t work on me: I&amp;rsquo;m not going to believe that your opponent eats children for breakfast, no matter what large fonts you use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a moment of relief from apathy and cynicism about politics, I eagerly voted today. I hope I&amp;rsquo;ll get to see whether I was justified.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I decided to resign myself to continue voting</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/11/06/i-decided-to-resign-myself-to-continue-voting/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Nov 2012 12:05:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/11/06/i-decided-to-resign-myself-to-continue-voting/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/voter-receipt-2012.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;My voter receipt 2012&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Last year I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/08/i-dont-know-if-i-should-vote-but-i-did/&#34;&gt;wondered aloud about the act of voting&lt;/a&gt;, being unsure about how to justify my annual participation in this ritual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This being a presidential election, avoiding getting sucked in is a perpetual chore, given that it is impossible for me to completely avoid people&amp;rsquo;s political pontifications on their blogs, Twitter, Facebook, Google+, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I even had to stay home from work in order to avoid &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/06/obama-is-speaking-outside-my-office-window-so-why-did-i-stay-home/&#34;&gt;politicians annoyingly disrupting the workplace&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My conclusion was that, for me, the only rational response (that didn&amp;rsquo;t result in my getting frustrated and angry, which seems the tone of most of the politics-related chatter I see on social media) is to spend as little time as possible on politics, spend the evening before an election to do some research, and then go out and vote for the &amp;ldquo;lesser evil&amp;rdquo; for each race (yes, it&amp;rsquo;s not just about President, and in fact, local races are the ones in which voting is most likely to make a difference).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So last night, I held my nose, read up on various PA state candidates, made my choices, and this morning I went and voted. And now I&amp;rsquo;m going to simply proceed with my day. I&amp;rsquo;m not going to follow any election news coverage whatsoever. Instead, I&amp;rsquo;m going to try to get stuff done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, and whoever wins in each of these races, please go and do your job for us the best you can. Get stuff done. Stop blabbering lies and promises.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Obama is speaking outside my office window, so why did I stay home?</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/07/06/obama-is-speaking-outside-my-office-window-so-why-did-i-stay-home/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jul 2012 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/07/06/obama-is-speaking-outside-my-office-window-so-why-did-i-stay-home/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Right now, President Obama is &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cmu.edu/news/stories/archives/2012/july/july3_obama.html&#34;&gt;speaking&lt;/a&gt; on the College of Fine Arts lawn at Carnegie Mellon University, right outside my office window. Apparently, &lt;a href=&#34;http://twitter.com/thetartan/status/221267182707949569&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;the line for President Obama&amp;rsquo;s visit to CMU goes from Purnell to Gesling Stadium&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. That&amp;rsquo;s some line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday at work I saw a lot of setup going on out on the lawn:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/obama-cmu-setup.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;CFA lawn being set up for Obama&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, today I stayed at home. Why did I stay at home when I could have picked up a free ticket yesterday for this event? (Below is a photo of someone else&amp;rsquo;s ticket since I did not get one.)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/obama-cmu-ticket.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Ticket for Obama event at CMU&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;it-s-not-about-obama&#34;&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s not about Obama&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, I want to make it clear that this is not about Obama. It is not about whether I like or hate him, or whether I will vote for or against him this fall. If it were Mitt Romney, I would not be attending.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;it-s-about-politics&#34;&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s about politics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t like politics, but &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/08/i-dont-know-if-i-should-vote-but-i-did/&#34;&gt;I do vote&lt;/a&gt;. In fact, just in the last couple of years, I even do what I have to do in order to vote in closed primaries. I find it extremely distasteful to have to register for some official &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.goodreads.com/quotes/show/401859&#34;&gt;party&lt;/a&gt; in order to vote in primaries, but I did it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At various points in my life, I have either been apathetic, cynical, or idealistic about politics. Right now, I would say I am simply realistic and take a rational approach, devoid of all emotion. I minimize following of political news or getting into heated arguments. I go out twice a year to vote.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nothing Obama is saying right now or not saying would likely affect my vote, so from a rational point of view, there is nothing to be gained from wasting valuable time (and suffering in the summer heat outside) just to hear him on his campaign tour. Furthermore, if he really is saying anything truly interesting, I&amp;rsquo;m sure I&amp;rsquo;ll get the executive summary from someone and if I really wanted to, I could get a transcript too, probably.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a world of too much pointless information, I don&amp;rsquo;t need political speeches to use up my brain cells.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;it-s-especially-about-presidents&#34;&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s especially about presidents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m particularly uninterested in following presidential politics, because the cult of the presidency has overwhelmed American politics. The president gets credit or blame for everything. People forget that the US was founded with three branches of government, and the executive is just one of those three. Congress and the Supreme Court are critical. In fact, just recently we saw how important the Supreme Court is, when the Roberts Supreme Court &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.forbes.com/sites/aroy/2012/07/01/the-supreme-courts-john-roberts-changed-his-obamacare-vote-in-may/&#34;&gt;surprisingly upheld Obamacare&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At a time when monarchy was still the norm, George Washington chose not to become a king. We&amp;rsquo;re not supposed to have kings in this country. Yet people really do long for king-like figures, whether as saviors or villains. This longing is &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.enduringword.com/commentaries/0908.htm&#34;&gt;part of human nature&lt;/a&gt;, unfortunately. I&amp;rsquo;m doing my part to choose to buck human nature and ignore presidents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d be more likely to attend a speech by a prospective candidate for Mayor of Pittsburgh than to attend speeches by any future presidents or presidential candidates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obama&amp;rsquo;s talking, and I stayed at home to get stuff done.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Today is Bill of Rights Day, the irony!</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/12/15/today-is-bill-of-rights-day-the-irony/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Dec 2011 13:07:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/12/15/today-is-bill-of-rights-day-the-irony/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/us-constitution-at-cmu.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Actual copy of the US Constitution at Carnegie Mellon University&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Today, in the United States, is December 15, &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_States_Bill_of_Rights&#34;&gt;Bill of Rights&lt;/a&gt; Day, the day in 1791 when the new nation of the United States amended its Constitution by adding the &amp;ldquo;bill of rights&amp;rdquo; in order to address the concerns of those who feared that the Constitution as proposed without the amendments did not sufficiently protect Americans&amp;rsquo; rights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, &lt;a href=&#34;http://americancensorship.org/&#34;&gt;today is also the day&lt;/a&gt; on which the House is voting on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stop_Online_Piracy_Act&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Stop Online Piracy Act&amp;rdquo; (SOPA)&lt;/a&gt;. SOPA, in the name of protecting copyright, gives the government tremendous powers that amount to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2011/12/internet-inventors-warn-against-sopa-and-pipa&#34;&gt;suppression of free speech and censorship of the Internet&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Shame, shame&lt;/strong&gt; on Congress and on the special interests and lobbyists supporting SOPA!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are an American, do you know &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.billofrightsinstitute.org/&#34;&gt;your rights&lt;/a&gt;? If you are not an American, how well do you feel we are doing in the United States protecting our rights?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Censored</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/11/16/censored/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Nov 2011 20:03:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/11/16/censored/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This site has temporarily been &lt;a href=&#34;http://americancensorship.org/&#34;&gt;censored&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Updated November 20: I have now removed the black-out banner and popup that I had put up for American Censorship Day. I hope some of you in the past couple of days have looked at the link to understand the issues involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The code was as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;script type=&amp;quot;text/javascript&amp;quot; src=&amp;quot;http://americancensorship.org/js&amp;quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/script&amp;gt;

&amp;lt;a style=&amp;quot;width:400px;height:100px;vertical-align:middle;text-align:center;background-color:#000;position:absolute;z-index:5555;top:50px;left:50px;background-image:url(http://americancensorship.org/images/stop-censorship-small.png);background-position:center center;background-repeat:no-repeat;&amp;quot; href=&amp;quot;http://americancensorship.org&amp;quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I don&#39;t know if I should vote but I did</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/11/08/i-dont-know-if-i-should-vote-but-i-did/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Nov 2011 09:09:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/11/08/i-dont-know-if-i-should-vote-but-i-did/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t like politics, and I don&amp;rsquo;t like voting. When I turned eighteen years old, I didn&amp;rsquo;t celebrate by getting registered to vote and participating in the presidential election the very same year. The first time I ever voted, I was twenty-two. In recent years, I have been voting almost every chance I have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/voter-receipt-2011.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin&amp;#39;s voter receipt for 2011&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-vote&#34;&gt;Why vote?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, I don&amp;rsquo;t know exactly why. I know all the arguments &lt;em&gt;for&lt;/em&gt; voting: it&amp;rsquo;s my civic duty, I can&amp;rsquo;t complain about what politicians do if I&amp;rsquo;m not involved in selecting them, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-not-vote&#34;&gt;Why not vote?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also know all the arguments &lt;em&gt;against&lt;/em&gt; voting: what difference do I make anyway (empirically, the vast proportion of the time, whenever I vote for someone, that person &lt;strong&gt;loses&lt;/strong&gt;), why should I vote for someone I find loathsome, why should I vote for someone who is going to do a lot of things I oppose, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-is-actually-at-stake&#34;&gt;What is actually at stake?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, it seems to me that what is at stake is often purely personal gratification. People like to feel good about themselves, by imagining that they are doing their civic duty or that they are &amp;ldquo;sending a message&amp;rdquo; by refusing to compromise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;lesser-evil&#34;&gt;Lesser evil&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is another perspective that I used to strongly dislike: voting as choosing a &amp;ldquo;lesser evil&amp;rdquo;. Once framing voting as an unpleasant task, with low expectations, it&amp;rsquo;s easier to hold your nose and do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, there are arguments against &amp;ldquo;lesser evilism&amp;rdquo;: because the American political system is completely broken, captured by lobbyists, and unfriendly to third parties, choosing a lesser evil narrows debate and does nothing to encourage politicians to adopt alternative points of view outside the narrow bipartisan consensus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The argument for lesser evilism is that maybe on some issues, the other side has views and intentions that are considerably worse, maybe even &lt;em&gt;crazy&lt;/em&gt;, and it&amp;rsquo;s worth doing everything possible to stop the other side. Hence, politicians love using negative ads in order to paint the other side as crazy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I try to avoid all exposure to robocalls and negative ads, because I tend to think that politicians who go out of their way to smear their opponents in filth are themselves the filthy ones I don&amp;rsquo;t want to vote for, and therefore if I see too many ads, I end up not wanting to vote for anyone at all!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;local-pittsburgh-referendum&#34;&gt;Local (Pittsburgh) referendum&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today&amp;rsquo;s election I was going to turn up for, independent of all I have said above, because of the Carnegie Library &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Referendum&#34;&gt;referendum&lt;/a&gt; on a 0.25 mill special tax on all taxable real estate in the City of Pittsburgh to be allocated and used only for the maintenance and operation of the Carnegie Library of Pittsburgh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are lot of people who don&amp;rsquo;t like referenda, because as a form of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Direct_democracy&#34;&gt;direct democracy&lt;/a&gt; it bypasses the overall framework of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Representative_democracy&#34;&gt;representative democracy&lt;/a&gt; in which we, the people, are supposed to elect politicians to decide matters for us, rather than act as a mob. The upsides and downsides of both forms of democracy are well-known (California&amp;rsquo;s political system, incorporating both the representative process as well as its infamous &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/California_ballot_proposition&#34;&gt;ballot propositions&lt;/a&gt;, is completely broken).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the case of the Carnegie Library referendum, I&amp;rsquo;ve heard a lot of very heated rhetoric on both sides of it. This time, at least, I appreciated the opportunity to have a say rather than depend on politicians to decide for me, because I feel strongly about the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/30/free-to-the-people-since-1895/&#34;&gt;importance of libraries&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2012-11-06&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-11-06)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following year, I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/11/06/i-decided-to-resign-myself-to-continue-voting/&#34;&gt;continued to vote&lt;/a&gt; and expect to continue, year after year.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why soda bans don&#39;t work</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/11/07/why-soda-bans-dont-work/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Nov 2011 19:13:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/11/07/why-soda-bans-dont-work/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I just saw an article, &lt;a href=&#34;http://well.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/11/07/soda-bans-in-schools-have-limited-benefit/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Soda Bans in Schools Have Limited Impact&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. It boggles my mind that anyone would advocate soda bans in school as a policy in isolation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are my thoughts on the economics and politics, and health and cultural aspects of the issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;economics-101&#34;&gt;Economics 101&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The article describes the empirical results from soda bans:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Students were drinking other sugary beverages instead&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Students were bringing in their own sugary beverages&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;economics&lt;/em&gt; of the situation are obvious:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are plenty of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Substitute_good&#34;&gt;substitute goods&lt;/a&gt; for soda that satisfy students&amp;rsquo; demand for sugary beverages.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Since the school is not a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Monopoly&#34;&gt;monopoly&lt;/a&gt;, and there are plenty of other &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Supply_(economics)&#34;&gt;suppliers&lt;/a&gt; of soda and other sugary beverages outside of school, all that happens is that students buy from another supplier.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basic economic theory has a way to reduce consumption of sugary beverages, of course: a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pigovian_tax&#34;&gt;Pigovian tax&lt;/a&gt; such as the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sin_tax&#34;&gt;sin tax&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cigarette_taxes_in_the_United_States&#34;&gt;cigarettes&lt;/a&gt;. A tax on the entire category of sugary beverages would do the trick. There is reason to believe the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Price_elasticity_of_demand&#34;&gt;price elasticity&lt;/a&gt; is sufficient that such a tax would considerably reduce consumption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;politics-101&#34;&gt;Politics 101&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And such a wide-ranging tax is completely impossible, politically. Even an overall &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Soda_tax&#34;&gt;soda tax&lt;/a&gt; is, I believe, politically impossible. Worse, it would not solve the problem, because as we know from the school example, there are other sugary beverages that pose the very same health problems but are not labeled as &amp;ldquo;soda&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;bigger-picture-of-economics&#34;&gt;Bigger picture of economics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Worse, the &lt;em&gt;problem&lt;/em&gt; as narrowly defined, that of decreasing consumption of sugary beverages, is only the tip of the iceberg when it comes to the bigger picture of public health. People will eat cookies and any number of other less perfect substitutes for sugary beverages anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;beyond-economics-to-health&#34;&gt;Beyond economics to health&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the purported motivation for reducing sugary beverages has been to reduce obesity. Obesity happens for all kinds of reasons. Worse, I don&amp;rsquo;t even like the focus on &lt;em&gt;weight&lt;/em&gt;. Poor health has to do with a lot more than weight. Most people, when thinking about their weight, and try to lose it, don&amp;rsquo;t even apply healthy strategies to lose weight, or even to do so permanently rather than temporarily. I don&amp;rsquo;t believe stopgap politically controversial initiatives can do much to address the real problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;culture-and-a-personal-note&#34;&gt;Culture and a personal note&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am bombarded daily with access to sugary beverages. Every time I go to a lunch seminar or party or reception, cans and bottles of soda, sports beverages, juices, and sweetened teas are provided. Clearly American culture is simply not ready to give up on these beverages. I get the impression that I am in the minority in choosing not to drink them. I have had maybe &lt;em&gt;four or five&lt;/em&gt; cans or bottles of such beverages in the past ten years. I get the impression that a lot of people I see around have had approximately &lt;em&gt;ten thousand&lt;/em&gt; cans or bottles in the past ten years. I don&amp;rsquo;t lecture people on why they should abstain, because it is useless even when directed toward, say, my own parents. I don&amp;rsquo;t know what it will take for the culture to change, or what I can do to help. Right now, I just silently abstain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you have any suggestions of what I could really do to help spread the word that life really might be more enjoyable without consuming sugary beverages all the time?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>