<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Stalemate on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/stalemate/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Stalemate on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/stalemate/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>The importance of stalemate in chess: how chess is completely different from life</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/06/16/the-importance-of-stalemate-in-chess-how-chess-is-completely-different-from-life/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Jun 2015 22:16:19 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/06/16/the-importance-of-stalemate-in-chess-how-chess-is-completely-different-from-life/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I just saw a cute end to a top-level chess game that ended in a forced
draw because the would-be losing side &lt;a href=&#34;http://dejanbojkov.blogspot.com/2015/06/jakovenko-and-stalemate.html&#34;&gt;managed a swindle&lt;/a&gt; by giving away
all his pieces by force in order to create a
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stalemate&#34;&gt;stalemate&lt;/a&gt;. If you don&amp;rsquo;t
play chess, a stalemate is what happens when it&amp;rsquo;s your turn to move
and you have no legal moves. You can claim a draw when you are &lt;em&gt;totally
trapped&lt;/em&gt; in this way. So one way of saving an otherwise losing game,
when you are outnumbered and about to be checkmated (losing when your
King comes under attack and it&amp;rsquo;s your move and you cannot stop the
check), is to find a brilliant way to be &lt;em&gt;unable to move&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/stalemate.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Black forced a draw through being stalemated!&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Is this a totally bizarre concept or what? Why was this rule of chess
invented anyway? Wouldn&amp;rsquo;t it make more sense if being trapped meant
&lt;em&gt;losing&lt;/em&gt;, like it does in real life conflicts?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;history-of-stalemate&#34;&gt;History of stalemate&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stalemate was apparently
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stalemate#History_of_the_stalemate_rule&#34;&gt;standardized to be a draw in the 19th century&lt;/a&gt;. Before
that, conventions differed on what the outcome of the game was
supposed to be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now and then, notable chess players have called for the abolishment of
his rule, to replace the stalemate with a win for the side that
trapped the other side, because this is &amp;ldquo;logical&amp;rdquo; and corresponds to
what you would expect in war or in some other &amp;ldquo;real life&amp;rdquo; situation in
which you have pressed hard for a long time, accumulated a lot of
force, and can cause your opponent to not be able to move at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;i-like-that-stalemate-is-illogical&#34;&gt;I like that stalemate is illogical&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m going to be blunt: I like that stalemate is &amp;ldquo;illogical&amp;rdquo;! It
creates tremendous difficulty for the side with more material to win
in endgames. I like that it gives the underdog a chance to avoid
losing by being clever. If stalemate were not a draw, then it would be
trivial to win many games in which one side has made a mistake and
lost a Pawn, because then all that has to be done is trade everything
off until all that remains is a King and Pawn versus King, and declare
victory. Stalemate means that the side with the extra Pawn has to work
super hard to avoid trading everything off, to avoid just mechanically
fighting battles with equal losses on both sides until one Pawn is
left.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like stalemate because in real life, often it is too easy for one
side to win just because of an early error by the loser. &lt;em&gt;Chess is not
real life&lt;/em&gt;, and I like it that way. Stalemate and other rules of chess
add bizarre whimsy and creativity to the game, just as the rule of
checkmate at all is counter to real life. In real life, you can kill
the general of an army and still lose the war. In chess, it&amp;rsquo;s always
like in the movies, on the other hand: you can have a lone hero defy
all odds to get at the enemy King and sacrifice everything else for
this objective, and have a happy ending. There is something &lt;em&gt;romantic&lt;/em&gt;
about chess that is part of its appeal to me. Chess is a game of logic
but according to weird heroic rules, where sheer &lt;em&gt;material wealth&lt;/em&gt; is
not enough to guarantee a win.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is unfortunate that many top-level chess games end in a draw, but
to abolish stalemate would change the capricious character of the
game in a way that ruins its appeal to me (on a lower level of play).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you are not a chess player, what do you think of the stalemate
  rule? If you are a chess player, what do you think of it?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>