<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Wetlands on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/wetlands/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Wetlands on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/wetlands/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Hiking again in Boyce-Mayview Park three months later</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/04/12/hiking-again-in-boyce-mayview-park-three-months-later/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Apr 2014 20:58:26 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/04/12/hiking-again-in-boyce-mayview-park-three-months-later/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;For the New Year in January, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/01/01/happy-new-year-with-a-boyce-mayview-park-hike-wetlands/&#34;&gt;Abby and I went on a brisk winter hike through the Pittsburgh hiking meetup group in Boyce-Mayview Park&lt;/a&gt;, which was new to us at the time. We enjoyed the experience so much that we knew that we were going to return in the spring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So on a warm and sunny afternoon (temperature rising beyond 70 degrees F), we went (by ourselves) to Boyce-Mayview Park to do some hiking. We ended up doing maybe eight miles. Obviously, things just looked different without the snow and ice, and with some vegetation and more active life forms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;parking&#34;&gt;Parking&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(You can download a detailed map of the park &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.twpusc.org/magazine/pdf/boyce-mayview-park_map.pdf&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We originally headed to parking at the trail head right next to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ardolinopizza.com/&#34;&gt;Ardolino&amp;rsquo;s Pizza&lt;/a&gt;, off Boyce Road, but the small parking lot was full, not unexpectedly, so we drove all the way around to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.twpusc.org/crc/crc-home&#34;&gt;Boyce-Mayview community and recreation center&lt;/a&gt; entrance from Mayview Road, to park in a lot further in near the Outdoor Classroom, use the restroom building next to it, and enter the trail systems from there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;our-hike&#34;&gt;Our hike&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We encountered a bit of mud on the trails that we took, but nothing too unpleasant. We both wore our Vibram FiveFingers KSO Trek shoes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We just basically wandered around, without any map or GPS, knowing that as long as we kept Chartiers Creek in sight, we could get back to where we started. Also, with all the many elevation changes, we could often see the community and recreation center up high. So we did not have to worry about getting lost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I very much enjoy hiking in the vicinity of water, seeing it and hearing it, so we spent a good deal time on the trails near Chartiers Creek, just following its curves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At one point in the wetlands we got excited and thought we saw an island and so we went there and hiked a trail there all the way till we realized it wasn&amp;rsquo;t really an island after all. It was fun being surrounded by water on both sides on a strip of land, but also that part of the hike involved a lot of bugs happy to try to bite us!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After about two hours, we eventually ended up at the Boyce Road trail head and I was really hungry and peeked into Ardolino&amp;rsquo;s, but Abby didn&amp;rsquo;t think it was a good idea for us to order pizza (we had packed our own lunch anyway), so we turned around and hiked back up, and stopped somewhere on a trail to sit and eat lunch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then we made our way back to our start. At one point it wasn&amp;rsquo;t clear how to get to a trail connecting where we were, high up, back to the trail next to Chartiers Creek, so we just took a &amp;ldquo;shortcut&amp;rdquo; (hiking poles are very helpful for the Boyce-Mayview Park in general), scrambling down to that trail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-few-photos-of-stuff-we-saw&#34;&gt;A few photos of stuff we saw&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;View from where we parked:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/boyce-mayview-2014-04-12/parking.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Parking&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The Outdoor Classroom and the restroom building:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/boyce-mayview-2014-04-12/outdoor-classroom.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Abby spotting an interesting bird:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/boyce-mayview-2014-04-12/critter.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A view of Chartiers Creek:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/boyce-mayview-2014-04-12/chartiers-creek.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A little garter snake crossed our path. You might be able spot it in this photo. At my request, Abby did &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; pick it up to show to me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/boyce-mayview-2014-04-12/garter-snake.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A sample trail winding around a hill:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/boyce-mayview-2014-04-12/hill-trail.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Rapids! We did see someone in a canoe further upstream.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/boyce-mayview-2014-04-12/rapids.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Flowers (sorry, I know very little about identifying flowers):&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/boyce-mayview-2014-04-12/flowers.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Crossing over to the &amp;ldquo;island&amp;rdquo;:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/boyce-mayview-2014-04-12/island.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We saw woodpeckers, geese, vultures, groundhogs, and other critters during the hike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without leaves on trees obstructing the view, it is fairly easy to see where one is, as far as elevation and landmarks (we knew we had to get back down to the creek level and then back upward to where we parked):&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/boyce-mayview-2014-04-12/elevation.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was great to return to Boyce-Mayview Park in the spring. I expect that we&amp;rsquo;ll go back in a couple more weeks, as more vegetation grows and even more birds hang out. I highly recommend checking out this park, located in Upper St. Clair just half an hour drive from the city of Pittsburgh.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cold but pretty winter hike in Wingfield Pines</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/01/18/cold-but-pretty-winter-hike-in-wingfield-pines/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Jan 2014 20:10:22 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/01/18/cold-but-pretty-winter-hike-in-wingfield-pines/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Less than three weeks ago, Abby and I went on a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/01/01/happy-new-year-with-a-boyce-mayview-park-hike-wetlands/&#34;&gt;great hike in Boyce-Mayview Park in Upper St. Clair, led by Gary Byrdman&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today we went on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/pittsburghhikers/events/160997422/&#34;&gt;another hike with Gary, very close to the Boyce-Mayview Park, but in a neighboring park&lt;/a&gt;, the Wingfield Pines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;cold&#34;&gt;Cold!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a beautiful day, clear sky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it was pretty freaking cold, hovering around 10F, I think, maybe a bit higher. I was slightly underdressed, and paid the price. I should have worn my thicker gloves and also long underwear. After getting home, it took a long time for my body to return to normal. The problem is that in previous winters of my life, I have not gone out hiking when the temperature is below 20F, so this was a first for me. Now I know better what I need to wear.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/wingfield-pines-abby-franklin.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Wingfield Pines&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;about-the-park&#34;&gt;About the park&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We parked across the street from the park entrance because the parking area at the entrance is pretty small. Across the street is a large parking lot for the community center.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were just six of us braving the cold for this hike. Gary and others being locals, told us a lot about the history of the park. It was really fascinating. The land has undergone many changes of ownership and restoration over the years. I looked online after the hike and found useful information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The land is currently owned by the Allegheny Land Trust and here is the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.alleghenylandtrust.org/properties/wingfield/overview/&#34;&gt;official site of the area&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had a leisurely hike, going about five miles in two and a half hours, stopping often to check out the sights. One of us brought her dog along. She lives nearby and walks her dog twice a day here! What she really loves is that it&amp;rsquo;s officially a legal off-leash area for dogs. So this place is great for dog lovers who want their dogs to truly get their exercise! We bumped into some happy-looking dogs and their owners during the hike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.hedinenv.com/projectpages/wingfieldpines.htm&#34;&gt;water treatment system&lt;/a&gt; is pretty interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;photos&#34;&gt;Photos&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t take many photos because every time I took off my gloves to be able to use my phone camera, my fingers got super cold, so I gave up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But photos some others of us took are available &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/pittsburghhikers/photos/19589162&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Julie took particularly detailed and beautiful photos of cardinals, bluebirds, woodpeckers, and ducks that we saw.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;coming-back-in-spring-and-summer&#34;&gt;Coming back in spring and summer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I will definitely come back in spring and summer. The park is lovely in winter, but it will be even more gorgeous in spring and summer, quite obviously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To get an idea of what the place is like when it&amp;rsquo;s not winter, here is a sample link I found to &lt;a href=&#34;http://upperstclair.patch.com/groups/around-town/p/wingfield-pines-shines-on-a-wet-afternoon&#34;&gt;local coverage&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A video:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/4KmHnkG4Enc&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out Wingfield Pines, in Upper St. Clair. It&amp;rsquo;s less than a half-hour drive from Pittsburgh. It&amp;rsquo;s beautiful.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Happy New Year with a Boyce-Mayview Park hike: wetlands, creeks, beavers, woodpeckers, waterfalls...</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/01/01/happy-new-year-with-a-boyce-mayview-park-hike-wetlands/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2014 19:57:07 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/01/01/happy-new-year-with-a-boyce-mayview-park-hike-wetlands/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Happy New Year 2014!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I started off this new year with a lovely &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/pittsburghhikers/events/157809022&#34;&gt;hike with the Pittsburgh hiking meetup group&lt;/a&gt;, led by Gary Byrdman. It was in Boyce-Mayview Park, a park we&amp;rsquo;d never been to before &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.twpusc.org/rec-leisure/parks-fields&#34;&gt;in Upper St. Clair&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/boyce-mayview-2014-01-01/break.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a beautiful day, not too cold (over 20F), and mostly not too muddy or icy either, thankfully. Abby and I did each use a pair of hiking poles, and many of us used &lt;a href=&#34;http://kahtoola.com/product/microspikes/&#34;&gt;MICROSpikes&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.yaktrax.com/&#34;&gt;Yaktrax&lt;/a&gt; also during the hike, but it turned out that the spikes were actually something of a hassle because snow accumulated under them for people. If it had been more icy out, I would have used spikes, however.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was originally hoping to wear my relatively new minimalist New Balance Minimus Zero trail running shoes for this hike, but quickly decided that this would be a bad idea mainly because of the risk of getting my feet cold and wet, so I wrote my old Montrail Rockridge trail running shoes, which I haven&amp;rsquo;t worn in years because they have gotten a bit small for me, requiring me to wear very thin socks (which I did on this hike). Far from minimalist, but in the winter in the face of water dangers (and indeed, we had a couple of stream crossings in which I got a little wet), I don&amp;rsquo;t have a true minimalist shoe yet.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://s7d5.scene7.com/is/image/ColumbiaSportswear/S11_GM2098_654_f?$MTR_pdp_lg$&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Montrail Rockridge&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The hike lasted about two and a half hours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had a great group of people, and Gary even brought breakfast to share with us. After the hike, I eagerly sampled his treats. What a guy! During the hike, he pointed out interesting features, such as beaver dams, woodpecker holes (and we heard woodpeckers too), places that are great for birding in the spring, and a nice waterfall that was partially iced but running.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;photos&#34;&gt;Photos&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re a member of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/pittsburghhikers&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh hiking meetup group&lt;/a&gt;, you have access to the event page and the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/pittsburghhikers/photos/19309272/&#34;&gt;photo page for the hike&lt;/a&gt;, where I uploaded a couple dozen photos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m posting just a few here, to whet your appetite for this park. There was such varied terrain and so much to see!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Parking at the trail head:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/boyce-mayview-2014-01-01/trail-parking.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Breakfast by Gary:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/boyce-mayview-2014-01-01/gary-breakfast.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A beaver was at this tree:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/boyce-mayview-2014-01-01/beaver-tree.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Stream crossing:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/boyce-mayview-2014-01-01/stream-crossing.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;On a trail:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/boyce-mayview-2014-01-01/trail.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Waterfall:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/boyce-mayview-2014-01-01/waterfall.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Going uphill:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/boyce-mayview-2014-01-01/uphill.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Short break:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/boyce-mayview-2014-01-01/break.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the meadows we crossed:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/boyce-mayview-2014-01-01/meadow.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Up:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/boyce-mayview-2014-01-01/up.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I really enjoyed this hike. We promised ourselves that we would return to it next spring and summer. There&amp;rsquo;s clearly so much to enjoy and explore in Boyce-Mayview Park.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to check it out yourself, the Pittsburgh Meetup group often has hikes in this park.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love living in Western Pennsylvania. There is so much to see around here. I will never get bored here. I feel blessed to be living here in Pittsburgh.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>