<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Old Time on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/old-time/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Old Time on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/old-time/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Third year at July 3 music party and finally participated in jamming</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/07/03/third-year-at-july-3-music-party-and-finally-participated-in-jamming/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jul 2014 22:11:59 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/07/03/third-year-at-july-3-music-party-and-finally-participated-in-jamming/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;The past two years, Abby and I have gone to an annual July 3 music potluck/party, and we went again this year. Both &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/03/petrified-at-a-music-jam-session-so-i-didnt-play-but-watched-and-listened/&#34;&gt;in 2012&lt;/a&gt; as well as &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/07/03/second-year-at-july-3-music-party-still-only-listening-without-playing/&#34;&gt;in 2013&lt;/a&gt;, I was too intimidated to participate in music jamming, and only watched. This year I was determined to contribute, and I brought my ukulele (which I only started learning &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/08/23/another-unexpected-life-change-one-month-of-learning-to-play-ukulele/&#34;&gt;a month after last year&amp;rsquo;s party&lt;/a&gt;, actually) and my Irish flute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;piano&#34;&gt;Piano&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After my first round of food at the potluck, I went to Susan&amp;rsquo;s piano and played David Raksin&amp;rsquo;s theme from &amp;ldquo;Laura&amp;rdquo;, which I had so botched up last month at the annual Pittsburgh Recorder Society potluck/recital. I play it much better now, although I somehow messed up the final chords today. There were a few people sitting around listening, and they wanted to hear more, but I didn&amp;rsquo;t have any more, so I scurried away to eat more food.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;old-time&#34;&gt;Old time&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As dinner started winding down, the old time musicians started gathering outside to play. I saw fiddles, banjos, and other instruments make an appearance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;blues&#34;&gt;Blues&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inside, the main guy who plays guitar and ukulele unpacked his soprano ukulele, and so I took out my concert ukulele, and two other guys with guitars appeared. Eventually a woman who sang also appeared, as well as a guy on fiddle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I felt very intimidated, because although I&amp;rsquo;ve gotten some experience jamming while on recorder or flute or tin whistle, my ukulele experience &lt;em&gt;without written music&lt;/em&gt; is still very minimal. Nevertheless, I joined in. I fumbled around, and had to ask what key each song was being played in, and even then, I&amp;rsquo;m still quite shaky in anticipating and knowing chord changes beyond the simplest I, IV, V, and some dominant and major 7th chords. I strummed very softly.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/music-2014-07-04/jamming.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Music jamming&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;They&amp;rsquo;re a great bunch, improvising melodic lines at will and even making up lyrics right on the spot, just as they had at the last two years when I only watched. And the singing in harmony was fantastic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby got a little bit of video footage of us at one point:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/zYb1aBioAao&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For two years, I was afraid to join in the music jams at this annual July 3 party. This year I joined in a little bit. If we attend the party again next year, I hope to be in a position to contribute even more! Many thanks to Susan for hosting this annual party!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Second year at July 3 music party: still only listening without playing</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/07/03/second-year-at-july-3-music-party-still-only-listening-without-playing/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jul 2013 22:10:07 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/07/03/second-year-at-july-3-music-party-still-only-listening-without-playing/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/03/petrified-at-a-music-jam-session-so-i-didnt-play-but-watched-and-listened/&#34;&gt;Last year Abby and I went&lt;/a&gt; to a July 3 music potluck/party at Susan&amp;rsquo;s for the first time. We attended again. I brought my flute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again I enjoyed hearing two groups of people playing music. I am not so much into the &amp;ldquo;old time&amp;rdquo; music, however, which the group outside in the backyard was playing, so I hung out inside instead, where I liked much better the blues guitar and ukulele and singing and piano. &lt;em&gt;I would like to join in one day&lt;/em&gt; myself, but today did not feel up to it. I never took out my flute; it didn&amp;rsquo;t seem appropriate for any of the music anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2014-07-04&#34;&gt;(Update of 2014-07-04)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/07/03/third-year-at-july-3-music-party-and-finally-participated-in-jamming/&#34;&gt;my third year&lt;/a&gt; of this annual party, I actually played both piano and ukulele!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Another terrifying music jam session but I played a little bit of blues and old time</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/07/07/another-terrifying-music-jam-session-but-i-played-a-little-bit-of-blues-and-old-time/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Jul 2012 23:37:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/07/07/another-terrifying-music-jam-session-but-i-played-a-little-bit-of-blues-and-old-time/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/03/petrified-at-a-music-jam-session-so-i-didnt-play-but-watched-and-listened&#34;&gt;Just earlier this week, I went to a music jam where I was afraid to play&lt;/a&gt; and so I didn&amp;rsquo;t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today Abby and I went to another intimidating potluck/jam session, this time hosted by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.appalasia.com/Mimi.htm&#34;&gt;Mimi Jong&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://classic-sculpture.com/&#34;&gt;Susan Wagner&lt;/a&gt;. Mimi had invited Abby, but hadn&amp;rsquo;t yet met me; I knew who she was through having been to an &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.appalasia.com/&#34;&gt;Appalasia&lt;/a&gt; performance with Abby at some point earlier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This time I played a little bit. I almost didn&amp;rsquo;t, but felt that I had to start with something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;lots-of-music&#34;&gt;Lots of music&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was music going on outside in back of the home. Wow. It was fantastic stuff, what everyone was doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was Mimi on &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Erhu&#34;&gt;erhu&lt;/a&gt;, of course. There was a keyboard and sound system set up. People on bass, guitars, drums of all kinds, claves, banjos, violin, singing, you name it. All kinds of music was being jammed to. A lot of Latin music, sung by someone who seemed a native Spanish speaker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recognized a violinist as being someone who had played Baroque violin at a recital I had been at in April.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, there were clearly a lot of professional musicians here and so I felt really intimidated. I did a lot of watching and listening and quite enjoyed experiencing joy and inventiveness unfold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was fascinating seeing Mimi kicking off &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Summertime_(song)&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Summertime&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; on erhu. Hey, why not?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the Latin and Brazilian songs I knew the melodies for, and if I only knew all lyrics and could actually sing, I would have wanted to join in for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;joining-in&#34;&gt;Joining in&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But Mimi encouraged Abby and me to join in. At some point, Abby did join in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of the problem for me, besides the fact that I felt naked and helpless without a music score to read, was that I&amp;rsquo;d brought one case of instruments this time, which included some recorders as well as a Baroque flute, and it didn&amp;rsquo;t seem like any of these instruments was really suitable for the occasion. In my hurry to arrive at the potluck already running late, I had forgotten to bring my modern flute!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did the best I could and took out my Baroque flute and tried joining in. Some old time music came on and I found it not so difficult to do something for that, although nothing I was proud of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I remember mainly is when Mimi started some blues and at some point I came in and gave it a shot, and although I didn&amp;rsquo;t last very long, I got something in that wasn&amp;rsquo;t totally horrible. Somehow that was very liberating, getting those few seconds in for the evening. At least I didn&amp;rsquo;t walk away from the party this evening without playing anything at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Attending this potluck/jam session was an immensely exciting experience for me. I feel like I am truly expanding my musical world, and getting inspired. I too would like to be singing my favorite Latin songs. And I really like blues improvisation. I will start doing these things eventually; they are no longer just remote possibilities, but what I have seen people doing in front of my own eyes and not in an impersonal concert but at a casual, fun party.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-01-28&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-01-28)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Six months later, I participated in &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/28/my-first-blues-music-jam-happened-after-the-regular-french-music-jam/&#34;&gt;my first blues jam&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-09-28&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-09-28)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over a year later, I reported on &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/09/28/an-erhu-player-and-a-tuba-player-at-a-party-said-lets-jam/&#34;&gt;participating in a music jam at another one of these parties with Mimi&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Petrified at a music jam session so I didn&#39;t play but watched and listened</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/07/03/petrified-at-a-music-jam-session-so-i-didnt-play-but-watched-and-listened/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jul 2012 22:35:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/07/03/petrified-at-a-music-jam-session-so-i-didnt-play-but-watched-and-listened/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/02/my-first-french-music-jam-anxious-but-excited&#34;&gt;Just yesterday, I went to a music jam&lt;/a&gt; and was anxious but got over that and participated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today Abby and I went to a &lt;em&gt;very different&lt;/em&gt; one, a potluck/music jam hosted by Susan Waggoner, whom we&amp;rsquo;ve known for a long time through various Pittsburgh music and dance activities. Susan is involved particularly in the Cajun music/dance scene, and was also in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.post-gazette.com/stories/local/neighborhoods-city/accordion-pool-partys-another-use-for-empty-lawrenceville-pool-357459/&#34;&gt;Accordion Pool Party&lt;/a&gt; that Abby played in three years ago, and also has been doing &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/01/23/discovering-french-traditional-dance-in-pittsburgh/&#34;&gt;French dancing&lt;/a&gt; with us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was so &lt;em&gt;terrified&lt;/em&gt; at this party that I didn&amp;rsquo;t play &lt;em&gt;at all&lt;/em&gt;, despite bringing my instruments. I just didn&amp;rsquo;t feel up to it. But I learned a lot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;two-main-groups-of-musicians&#34;&gt;Two main groups of musicians&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that there were a bunch of musicians playing music outside in the back of the home. I wasn&amp;rsquo;t super familiar with what they were playing. Then there were some musicians playing music inside in the living room.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They really knew what they were doing, and were singing and playing by ear, no scores in sight. Without any scores, I had no clue how I could contribute, so I didn&amp;rsquo;t even take out my instruments. This was &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; jamming, not the kind that I did yesterday where most (but not all) of the stuff we did involved songs I had brought scores for or at least had heard before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;old-time-music&#34;&gt;Old time music&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was told by the men and women who were inside that those outside were playing &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Old-time_music&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;old time&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; music. I hadn&amp;rsquo;t been familiar with the term or genre.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby liked being outside, and also has been playing mandolin, so spent time checking out that group. I think she played along some too. It seemed to be mostly fiddlers, with banjo, mandolin, percussion, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I checked it out, but the music happened not to be quite so interesting to me; it moved fast, had a lot of notes, but seemed somewhat monotonous to my taste.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;country-blues-music&#34;&gt;Country blues music&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inside, however, I was really captivated by what was going on. They said that they were playing &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Country_blues&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;country blues&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. I liked the harmonic changes and the rhythmic qualities and improvisation. Guitars, harmonica, piano, singing. I was impressed by how the singers made up entire lyrics on the spot, often very funny or off-color.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I stayed around inside soaking in what was going on, and thought, I could see myself someday playing along.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was really excited to meet more musicians and widen my musical experience at the potluck/jam session. I felt pretty inspired by what I saw going on, music as a really communal, creative experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Noticing the huge gap between what these musicians were able to do and what I am able to do, I know that it takes a long time to get where they are, but I want to have that kind of everyday facility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2012-07-07&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-07-07)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Four days later, we went to another potluck/jam session, and &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/07/another-terrifying-music-jam-session-but-i-played-a-little-bit-of-blues-and-old-time/&#34;&gt;I played a little bit&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-01-28&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-01-28)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seven months later, I participated in &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/28/my-first-blues-music-jam-happened-after-the-regular-french-music-jam/&#34;&gt;my first blues jam&lt;/a&gt;. The pianist there, Anders, was the same one I first saw here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-07-03&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-07-03)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/07/03/second-year-at-july-3-music-party-still-only-listening-without-playing/&#34;&gt;my second year&lt;/a&gt; of this annual party, I still did not feel comfortable enough with the crowd to try to participate musically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2014-07-03&#34;&gt;(Update of 2014-07-03)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/07/03/third-year-at-july-3-music-party-and-finally-participated-in-jamming/&#34;&gt;my third year&lt;/a&gt; of this annual party, I actually played both piano and ukulele!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>