<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>James Galway on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/james-galway/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in James Galway on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/james-galway/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>James Galway made me hate flute, but Emmanuel Pahud made me love it</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/11/22/james-galway-made-me-hate-flute/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Nov 2011 22:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/11/22/james-galway-made-me-hate-flute/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;So it&amp;rsquo;s been less than two weeks since I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/09/taking-up-flute-again-after-decades/&#34;&gt;started playing flute again&lt;/a&gt;. One thing I forgot to mention is that &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_Galway&#34;&gt;James Galway&lt;/a&gt; made me hate flute for decades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bottom line is that I never liked Galway&amp;rsquo;s distinctive vibrato and sound. Unfortunately, for some reason, I kept on seeing him on TV and hearing him on the radio, and so he sort of represented to me &amp;ldquo;flute&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-08-23&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-08-23)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have periodically received comments from people very unhappy with my dislike of the playing of James Galway. I mean no disrespect: everyone has different taste. I should add that I actually love and respect James Galway as a musician and as an educator. I will write a detailed blog post about that at some point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;revival-through-jazz&#34;&gt;Revival through jazz&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, I started to enjoy hearing the flute again mainly from getting into jazz. I loved hearing &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Herbie_Mann&#34;&gt;Herbie Mann&lt;/a&gt; on flute, for example, and others as well. In fact, my original intention when buying a flute several years ago was to get into jazz flute: I had sort of lost interest in playing classical music by then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;discovery-of-emmanuel-pahud&#34;&gt;Discovery of Emmanuel Pahud&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;syrinx&#34;&gt;Syrinx&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just a couple of years ago, I was driving and listening to the local classical radio station, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wqed.org/fm/&#34;&gt;WQED&lt;/a&gt;, when I was put totally under a spell by a performance of a work for solo flute. Being completely unfamiliar with the classical flute repertoire, I didn&amp;rsquo;t know what the piece was, but the announcer said it was &amp;ldquo;Syrinx&amp;rdquo; by Claude Debussy, and performed by one &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Emmanuel_Pahud&#34;&gt;Emmanuel Pahud&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went and found CDs by Pahud at the library. Great stuff! He is definitely my flute hero.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a beautiful video of Pahud performing &amp;ldquo;Syrinx&amp;rdquo; on YouTube:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/aw53VrbI4l0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;update-of-2013-08-23-1&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-08-23)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/08/23/celebrating-claude-debussys-151st-birthday-through-unusual-performances-of-syrinx/&#34;&gt;I wrote for Debussy&amp;rsquo;s 151st birthday a note on unusual performances of Syrinx.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;entr-acte-from-carmen&#34;&gt;Entr&amp;rsquo;acte from Carmen&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that today I was practicing an arrangement of the Entr&amp;rsquo;acte from Bizet&amp;rsquo;s Carmen from the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.musicminusone.com/used-play-flute-innovative-method-adults-returning-play-p-60414222.html&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;I Used to Play Flute&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; book, and out of curiosity, looked up Pahud on YouTube.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here he is playing it under the young Venezuelan superstar conductor &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gustavo_Dudamel&#34;&gt;Gustavo Dudamel&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/eChLCFAGyx0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Very nice, although his interpretation differs in various ways from my personal conception of the Entr&amp;rsquo;acte: I would play it faster and more passionately. One reason I feel compelled to play music, and not only listen to it, is that nobody ever plays a piece just how I would play it. To &lt;em&gt;live&lt;/em&gt; music, I must create it or recreate it afresh. To not do so would be like watching a video of a hike rather than being on the trail hiking and experiencing it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>