<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Frick Park on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/frick-park/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Frick Park on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/frick-park/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Report on my final day of Stoic Week 2014: the view from above</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/30/report-on-my-final-day-of-stoic-week-2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2014 22:16:07 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/30/report-on-my-final-day-of-stoic-week-2014/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s the seventh and final day of Stoic Week 2014! I am very glad I participated in the daily readings and reflections. I&amp;rsquo;ve made so many positive changes in my life already. Now it&amp;rsquo;s time to stick to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;health&#34;&gt;Health&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been spending all of the Thanksgiving long holiday weekend catching up on sleep. I have a meditation habit now and today it was warm out and I went for a run and ended up doing five miles in Frick Park. This is the longest distance I&amp;rsquo;ve run in months!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;nature-providence-the-larger-whole&#34;&gt;Nature, providence, the larger whole&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is fitting that today&amp;rsquo;s theme is the Stoic view of humanity as being embedded in something bigger, call it &amp;ldquo;nature&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;providence&amp;rdquo;. Part of why I enjoy running in the trails of Frick Park is that in its own small way, the experience puts me in touch &lt;em&gt;directly&lt;/em&gt; with something bigger than us; I encounter dogs, chipmunks, trees, creeks, leaves, mud, and even deer (not today, but Abby and I saw one during our hike there yesterday).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I honestly feel more whole and alive when I see more of nature, and not in some self-conscious sentimental way. It&amp;rsquo;s more subtle than that. And there&amp;rsquo;s nothing sentimental about those steep hills that make me gasp for air when I climb them. But I sure appreciate the cleaner air in the park than on the main urban roads of Pittsburgh! And I remember where air comes from and how fragile its quality and composition is. The big picture matters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am grateful for the organizers of Stoic Week for putting it on again this year. Here is something I&amp;rsquo;ve decided to do, to keep its spirit alive indefinitely: I will continue to explore various interpretations of Stoicism (note that I don&amp;rsquo;t feel compelled to buy into any particular school or even call myself a Stoic at all), as well as other philosophy (for example, the Zen I had begun looking into years ago) on a daily basis, to keep my mind always focused on applying principles of practical living.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Did you hear about Stoic Week this year? If you did, why did you choose to participate in it, or more interestingly, choose not to?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>World Toilet Day is not just another crappy holiday</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/19/world-toilet-day-is-not-just-another-crappy-holiday/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2014 23:41:34 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/19/world-toilet-day-is-not-just-another-crappy-holiday/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;From an excellent blog I follow, Timothy Taylor&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://conversableeconomist.blogspot.com/&#34;&gt;Conversable Economist&lt;/a&gt;, I read his &lt;a href=&#34;http://conversableeconomist.blogspot.com/2014/11/world-toilet-day.html&#34;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; about &lt;a href=&#34;http://worldtoilet.org/&#34;&gt;World Toilet Day&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, every day is some kind of observed day somewhere in the world promoted by someone, but World Toilet Day is not just another crappy commercial holiday. It&amp;rsquo;s about a serious problem, which is that 15 percent of the world population still lives without proper sanitation. Open sanitation, especially in densely populated areas, is a cause of much serious illness (especially to children, who are especially vulnerable). So I&amp;rsquo;m happy about the invention of World Toilet Day in 2001 by the World Toilet Organization global non-profit. It&amp;rsquo;s curious that I hadn&amp;rsquo;t heard about it for thirteen years, but I&amp;rsquo;m grateful Timothy Taylor pointed it out in his blog. Because this is a serious issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I, for one, am grateful to live in the industrialized US where toilets abound everywhere, and even in parks such as my local Frick Park in Pittsburgh, there are port-a-potties in various locations within the park. I used to make fun of my immigrant parents for being strangely fixated on and happy about functioning and clean toilets, but the reality is that their generation and their parents&amp;rsquo; generation in rural Taiwan did not necessarily have this luxury. In fact, even today, apparently, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ketagalanmedia.com/2014/09/03/dreaming-odor-free-bathroom-taiwan/&#34;&gt;the sewage system is not great in Taiwan&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A pretty exploratory fall hike in Frick Park and Duck Hollow</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/10/05/a-pretty-exploratory-fall-hike-in-frick-park-and-duck-hollow/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Oct 2014 20:25:28 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/10/05/a-pretty-exploratory-fall-hike-in-frick-park-and-duck-hollow/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Abby and I hadn&amp;rsquo;t gone hiking for a while, because of schedules, but decided on a free Sunday afternoon to simply go for an exploratory hike in our local Frick Park, as we&amp;rsquo;ve done many times before. There&amp;rsquo;s never any shortage of ways to try something new. Lately, this has meant exploring narrow and hilly trails that mountain bikers use. We have to be careful on these to avoid a bike coming down out of nowhere!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We hiked about eight miles, starting with familiar territory but then entering the very strange!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;photos&#34;&gt;Photos&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I took a few &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/franklinmingchen/sets/72157648426944075/&#34;&gt;photos&lt;/a&gt; along the way that you can check out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/franklinmingchen/15264950369/in/set-72157648426944075/player/&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; height=&#34;375&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen oallowfullscreen msallowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;frick-park&#34;&gt;Frick Park&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We started by walking to and then entering Frick Park at the Blue Slide Playground at Beechwood and Nicholson, then taking Riverview Trail and then the Firelane Trail Extension down into Fern Hollow onto the Firelane Trail, meeting up with the Deer Creek Trail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After crossing Commercial St, leaving Frick Park, we headed onto Nine Mile Run Trail. We noticed that the construction site that had been there for something like two years had finally been cleared away. It was about time!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was peaceful and relaxing on Nine Mile Run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/franklinmingchen/15451702525/in/set-72157648426944075/player/&#34; width=&#34;375&#34; height=&#34;500&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen oallowfullscreen msallowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;slag-heap&#34;&gt;Slag heap&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Continuing on Nine Mile Run Trail, we reached the bridge and I was originally planning to continue on Nine Mile Run Trail, but happened to notice an intriguing steep trail up on a slag heap area right at the bridge. What the heck, why not explore it? We wished we had brought hiking poles, but fashioned some sticks from tree branches lying around, and proceeded up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In theory I could have tried to figure out where we were, since I had my phone on me, but I like randomly exploring without having any idea where we are going; there was no way to get hopelessly lost anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were a whole bunch of switchbacks leading upward and we followed them for some time until reaching a particularly roller-coaster section going into a valley, and decided we had enough, especially since we spotted a mountain biker further up somewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/franklinmingchen/15428655696/in/set-72157648426944075/player/&#34; width=&#34;375&#34; height=&#34;500&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen oallowfullscreen msallowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We turned off and took a trail heading just downhill, hoping to emerge somewhere in &amp;ldquo;civilization&amp;rdquo; eventually, maybe rejoin Nine Mile Run Trail that we had abandoned at the bridge. Meanwhile, we had clear views of the Waterfront across the Monongahela River. I figured we were in Duck Hollow somewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;railroad-tracks&#34;&gt;Railroad tracks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/franklinmingchen/15265131148/in/set-72157648426944075/player/&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; height=&#34;375&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen oallowfullscreen msallowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, we emerged by the railroad tracks along the Mon. We walked along the railroad tracks for a bit and reached familiar territory, McFarren St. We got back onto the Nine Mile Run Trail to start heading home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/franklinmingchen/15428681816/in/set-72157648426944075/player/&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; height=&#34;375&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen oallowfullscreen msallowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/franklinmingchen/15265195427/in/set-72157648426944075/player/&#34; width=&#34;375&#34; height=&#34;500&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen oallowfullscreen msallowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/franklinmingchen/15448608681/in/set-72157648426944075/player/&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; height=&#34;375&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen oallowfullscreen msallowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;back-into-frick-park-and-home&#34;&gt;Back into Frick Park and home&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Many trails lead to home.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of returning the way we came, we took the very windy Iron Grate Trail instead, and eventually made it back to the Blue Slide Playground (taking Jay&amp;rsquo;s Short Cut) and back onto the streets of Squirrel Hill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-were-those-slag-heap-trails-anyway&#34;&gt;What were those slag heap trails anyway?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went online and looked for information on those slag heap trails and that whole area. As far as I can tell, the following are useful information from mountain bike community descriptions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mtbproject.com/trail/5492893/slag-heap-switchbacks-to-plateau&#34;&gt;Slag heap switchbacks to plateau&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mtbproject.com/trail/4676264/crater-trail&#34;&gt;Crater trail&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I had fun time on a great fall afternoon exploring trails we&amp;rsquo;d never been on before. We definitely plan to go back and explore more, with hiking poles, ha!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m amazed by and grateful for what we can experience outdoors in nature even while embedded in the city of Pittsburgh.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thoughts on the construction of the new Frick Environmental Center</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/08/05/thoughts-on-the-construction-of-the-new-frick-environmental-center/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2014 21:12:30 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/08/05/thoughts-on-the-construction-of-the-new-frick-environmental-center/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Almost exactly twelve years ago, in 2002, tragedy struck in Frick Park in Pittsburgh. I was on a long evening run in Frick Park when I unwittingly came across what had happened earlier in the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;from-my-journal-august-4-2002&#34;&gt;From my journal, August 4, 2002&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;91 degrees, heat index 93. The Frick Park entrance was closed off for
some reason with tape, so that I could not access the water fountain I
had counted on using, so I ran up to Forbes instead and to Braddock to
get a fountain at that end of the park.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later in the evening, I found out what had happened:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Whoa!!!  The Frick Environmental Center was burned down in the
morning.  No wonder it was all closed off when I tried to run to the
water fountain.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was &lt;a href=&#34;http://old.post-gazette.com/neigh_city/20020805frickpark0805p1.asp&#34;&gt;reported the next day in the Post-Gazette&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;construction&#34;&gt;Construction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.post-gazette.com/local/city/2014/08/04/Frick-Environmental-Center-construction-begins/stories/201408040171&#34;&gt;Yesterday&lt;/a&gt;, construction of the new &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pittsburghparks.org/environmentalcenter&#34;&gt;Frick Environmental Center&lt;/a&gt; began, finally, after twelve years of uncertainty and controversy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On my evening run tonight (very cool, in the 60s, this summer, unlike the summer of twelve years ago!), I checked out the construction site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Road sign on Beechwood Blvd:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/franklinmingchen/14817138516&#34; title=&#34;Road sign for Frick Environmental Center by Franklin Chen, on Flickr&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3882/14817138516_f9529cdba9.jpg&#34; width=&#34;375&#34; height=&#34;500&#34; alt=&#34;Road sign for Frick Environmental Center&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Old burned building still there:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/franklinmingchen/14653568337&#34; title=&#34;Old Frick Environmental Center by Franklin Chen, on Flickr&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5581/14653568337_6f5ec39932.jpg&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; height=&#34;375&#34; alt=&#34;Old Frick Environmental Center&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some trail detour signs:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/franklinmingchen/14840109625&#34; title=&#34;Trails detoured for Frick Environmental Center construction by Franklin Chen, on Flickr&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3914/14840109625_f49a9061fb.jpg&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; height=&#34;375&#34; alt=&#34;Trails detoured for Frick Environmental Center construction&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;controversy&#34;&gt;Controversy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was controversy because of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pghcitypaper.com/pittsburgh/natural-selection-critics-question-choice-of-site-for-new-frick-environmental-center/Content?oid=1760832&#34;&gt;concerns&lt;/a&gt; about the impact of the major development planned on Frick Park, which has been prized by many (certainly by me!) as the &amp;ldquo;wildest&amp;rdquo; space in Pittsburgh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I understand the concerns, and realize there are some major tradeoffs in creating a new, fancy Environmental Center. It is &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburghparks.wordpress.com/2014/06/26/like-a-pheonix-rebuilding-a-new-frick-environmental-center/&#34;&gt;argued by the Pittsburgh Parks Conservancy&lt;/a&gt; that there are potentially tremendous benefits to having a modern community facility for education, especially for children. While I regret that some of the wildness of this part of Frick Park will be demolished, I hope that bringing interesting programs to children, especially urban children who might otherwise fail to ever appreciate nature, will be worth the development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will miss not accessing some trails of the park from this direction for a while, but having sadly seen the old burned building lying around abandoned for twelve years, I look forward to its being replaced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;questions&#34;&gt;Questions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you live in the neighborhood of Frick Park, how do you feel about the controversy over the new Frick Environmental Center? Do you believe the risks are uncertain or not worthwhile? What do you think will be the actual outcome and impact, to the environment as well as to the community, of the development and of the planned educational center?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you do not live in the neighborhood, how do you feel about these fancy developments in general? Have you seen them turn out badly somewhere else? Or turn out well?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thoughts on National Running Day 2014</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/06/04/thoughts-on-national-running-day-2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2014 19:19:21 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/06/04/thoughts-on-national-running-day-2014/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;This is my third year of celebrating &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.runningday.org/&#34;&gt;National Running Day&lt;/a&gt;. The first year, I did so by &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/06/06/i-celebrated-national-running-day-in-schenley-park-remembering-how-i-began-to-run-13-year-ago/&#34;&gt;running in Schenley Park&lt;/a&gt;; last year, I quietly did &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/06/05/celebrating-national-running-day-quietly-in-frick-park/&#34;&gt;my usual Frick Park run&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year, I ran in Frick Park again, a shorter run, because I took such a long break from running since last October, and only recently returned to regular running.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/frick-park-2014-06-04/frick.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;luna-venado-sandals&#34;&gt;Luna Venado Sandals&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since it was a shorter run of just 3 miles, I wore my thin &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lunasandals.com/products/luna-venado&#34;&gt;Luna Venado Sandals&lt;/a&gt; (only 7 mm thick) instead of the Luna Mono Sandals that I wore on last year&amp;rsquo;s run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/frick-park-2014-06-04/luna-venado-sandals-top.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Luna Venado Sandals&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/frick-park-2014-06-04/luna-venado-sandals-side.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Luna Venado Sandals&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;thoughts&#34;&gt;Thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m grateful that I have returned to running after many months off. It&amp;rsquo;s good for my body and most of all, my mind, actually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m grateful that I have no excuse to go out since I live so close to Frick Park.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m grateful that running is one of those things that (assuming your legs and feet are doing OK) you can do as slowly or as easily as you need or want to. I&amp;rsquo;m just ramping up slowly right now, and feel no anxiety about what level of fitness I&amp;rsquo;m at now. If I get tired, I can always walk, no shame. It&amp;rsquo;s all good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Do you run? Do you make it a ritual, as apparently I have, of taking time out periodically to reflect on what running means to you?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>When I&#39;m feeling too tired to venture out, there&#39;s always Frick Park</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/05/18/when-im-feeling-too-tired-to-venture-out-theres-always-frick-park/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 May 2014 22:27:39 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/05/18/when-im-feeling-too-tired-to-venture-out-theres-always-frick-park/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Because of the rain forecast and fatigue (I had a tough week), Abby and I ended up not venturing out of the city of Pittsburgh for a hike yesterday. But this afternoon, things seemed to clear up enough that we went for a hike in our local Frick Park. It was a bit chilly actually, so we wore raincoats and also I wore a hat in gloves (yes, it&amp;rsquo;s May).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s been a real blessing that Frick Park is so close to where we live, because that means we have no excuse not to go out into nature and to get some exercise, even if time or energy means we can&amp;rsquo;t do something more adventurous. Fact is, I took Abby around a bunch of trails that she had not yet explored, so there is no shortage of novelty in Frick Park itself! We were out for almost three hours. I led Abby to the network of trails by Nine Mile Run, then backtracked and went north of Fern Hollow, going up Tranquil Trail and branching off, before coming back down, and then back up toward home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Do you have a local favorite hangout (in nature or otherwise) that provides comfort and stimulation when you want to get out of the home but don&amp;rsquo;t want to go too far? How do you keep your experiences there interesting?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A short Sunday hike in Frick Park</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/05/11/a-short-sunday-hike-in-frick-park/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 May 2014 21:09:24 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/05/11/a-short-sunday-hike-in-frick-park/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Abby and I had planned to go on a hike yesterday, but rain discouraged us, plus we had a late start to the day, and we were planning to check out part of the Bach Festival in Pittsburgh anyway (and did). This afternoon, it was nice and clear, so we did a little exploratory hike in Frick Park.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A little stream crossing:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/frick-park-2014-05-11/stream-crossing.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Poison ivy lurks everywhere:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/frick-park-2014-05-11/poison-ivy.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A bridge that has gotten lopsided:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/frick-park-2014-05-11/bridge.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Ducks:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/frick-park-2014-05-11/ducks.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A note on running in warm weather</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/04/13/a-note-on-running-in-warm-weather/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Apr 2014 21:43:14 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/04/13/a-note-on-running-in-warm-weather/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I haven&amp;rsquo;t been running much at all in recent months; actually, I barely ran all winter, in contrast to last winter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since it&amp;rsquo;s warmer now, I no longer have an excuse. I went out for a short run in Frick Park late in the afternoon, when it was warm and sunny, probably around 80 degrees F.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a really tough time out there, going less than three miles before I turned around and started walking home. I know from prior experience that after not running much, I have to ramp up slowly, but in this case, the suddenly warm weather (after months of a seemingly endless winter) took a toll on me. So I&amp;rsquo;d like to remind anyone else coming out of &amp;ldquo;hibernation&amp;rdquo; not to feel discouraged if feeling unfit: just do a little bit of running at a time, &lt;em&gt;hydrate&lt;/em&gt; (I was grateful that the water fountains in the park are operational), and &lt;em&gt;be patient&lt;/em&gt;! If I didn&amp;rsquo;t know any better, I would be feeling quite discouraged after my excursion today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I treated myself to some cookies after my run. These are cookies I saved from an event at work last week, specifically for only after hiking or running. &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/01/16/a-system-for-quitting-eating-cookies/&#34;&gt;I would not eat&lt;/a&gt; these unremarkable cookies otherwise!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/frick-park-2014-04-13/cookie1.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Cookie 1&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/frick-park-2014-04-13/cookie2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Cookie 2&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/frick-park-2014-04-13/franklin.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A few sights from the Iron Grate Trail in Frick Park</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/04/06/a-few-sights-from-the-iron-grate-trail-in-frick-park/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Apr 2014 18:41:58 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/04/06/a-few-sights-from-the-iron-grate-trail-in-frick-park/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I did a leisurely hike in Frick Park near home, exploring a trail that I don&amp;rsquo;t usually run on, the Iron Grate Trail, because it is a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mtbproject.com/trail/3003110&#34;&gt;favorite trail for mountain bikers&lt;/a&gt;, and therefore tends to have muddy ruts that are not so pleasant for pedestrians, and also someone on a mountain bike could always come out of nowhere. But we were careful to keep our eyes and ears open, and share the trail, yielding to mountain bikers when perceiving them coming along.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An advantage of occasionally checking out these trails is simply that they are quieter, in terms of fewer pedestrians and dogs, and also, you get to see parts of the park that you wouldn&amp;rsquo;t otherwise see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Iron Grate Trail briefly became infamous in the local news a year ago because of reports of a &lt;a href=&#34;http://foresthills-regentsquare.patch.com/groups/police-and-fire/p/frick-park-visitors-on-edge-after-reports-of-violence&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;hatchet-wielding&amp;rdquo; person&lt;/a&gt; attacking someone on the trail, but I think that was an isolated incident.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;photo&#34;&gt;Photo&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s an amusing photo I took of Abby finding a hiding place along the trail:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/frick-park-hiding.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby hiding in a tree&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t take any photos of the new-looking signs reading &amp;ldquo;Iron Grate Trail&amp;rdquo; that we saw, but I just found out that &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburghparks.org/PTAGworkday04052014&#34;&gt;they were put up just days ago thanks to volunteers for the Pittsburgh Trail Advocacy Group&lt;/a&gt;. We did notice that the trail showed other evidence of having been maintained recently. Very nice work and thank you!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also saw some chickens running around in someone&amp;rsquo;s back yard, from a section of the trail behind a residential area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;video&#34;&gt;Video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a random video I found of someone riding into and along the Iron Grate Trail:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/x-FxY3BoHag&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My promise to prioritize my sleep</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/12/my-promise-to-prioritize-my-sleep/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Oct 2013 22:33:48 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/12/my-promise-to-prioritize-my-sleep/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Despite my knowledge (both firsthand and from reading research results) that sleep is important to healthy living, I have been failing to get my optimal sleep for a long time now. There are several reasons of this, but I am taking steps to address each one of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;too-many-activities&#34;&gt;Too many activities&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I began the process of catching up on sleep today by sleeping almost all day. Abby and I had yesterday decided to cancel our hiking plan for today because we both felt tired and decided it was a good time to just rest. We both have a bad habit of doing too many activities and not getting enough down time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I already mentioned some of the things I&amp;rsquo;m scaling down on: &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/10/04/final-rehearsal-for-my-first-ukulele-gig/&#34;&gt;musical activities&lt;/a&gt;. Today was the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.coolhanduke.com/&#34;&gt;Cool Hand Uke&lt;/a&gt; workshop and concert, both of which I had decided earlier to skip.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;night-time-distractions&#34;&gt;Night time distractions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not sleeping as early or deeply as I should, because of not turning down the lights and getting off the computer at night. I&amp;rsquo;m going to change that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In particular, social media at night are the worst. My decision today to &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/10/12/taking-a-break-from-twitter/&#34;&gt;take a break from Twitter, Facebook, and Google+&lt;/a&gt; will help a lot. Too much stimulation at night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;exercise&#34;&gt;Exercise&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a symbiotic relationship between sleep and exercise: the better the sleep, the more energy for stimulating exercise, and the more exercise, the more ready the body is to sleep in the evening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, after I slept almost all day, I found myself with energy to go for a run (I&amp;rsquo;ve barely been running in the past week). To my surprise, I effortlessly kept going and going, and ended up doing ten miles, no problem, in Frick Park and Summerset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was huge confirmation to me, that just catching up on sleep enabled me to enjoy a ten-mile run when I&amp;rsquo;ve barely been feeling like running at all in the past week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-2013-10-12/1.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-2013-10-12/2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-2013-10-12/3.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-2013-10-12/4.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-2013-10-12/5.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-2013-10-12/6.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m going to keep up good habits in order to improve my life. Sleep is the number one priority that I believe will benefit everything else.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Was that a ukulele I heard in Frick Park? No, a cavaquinho</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/06/was-that-a-ukulele-i-heard-in-frick-park-no-a-cavaquinho/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Oct 2013 14:19:09 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/06/was-that-a-ukulele-i-heard-in-frick-park-no-a-cavaquinho/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I had just run into Frick Park past the blue slide playground entrance when I thought I heard someone playing a ukulele! I looked around and saw a guy sitting on a park bench. I thought of approaching him, but decided not to interrupt my run, and kept going.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s what Frick Park looked today on a trail, with some fallen leaves. Bizarre that it&amp;rsquo;s still summer temperatures right now though.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/frick-park-2013-10-06.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Frick Park trail with fallen leaves&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When I came back around out of the trails, I saw the guy again and he was packing up to leave, so I approached him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out to be Ben, to whom &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/01/run-shadyside-5k-outrunning-mickey-mouse-and-lending-a-trumpet/&#34;&gt;I had lent a trumpet two years ago&lt;/a&gt; (since returned)! I asked him if the instrument in his case was a ukulele. He said no. I asked if it was a guitar. He said no. It was a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cavaquinho&#34;&gt;cavaquinho&lt;/a&gt;, the Portuguese ancestor of the Hawaiian ukulele! He pulled it out of the case and let me check it out. It&amp;rsquo;s tuned differently from the ukulele:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/cavaquinho.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Ben&amp;#39;s cavaquinho&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I had heard of this instrument, from reading something about the history of the ukulele (in particular, I had looked at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.coolhanduke.com/worldukehistory.html&#34;&gt;Cool Hand Uke&amp;rsquo;s booklet on ukulele history&lt;/a&gt; recently). Also, Handerson (who is from Brazil) had asked me if I knew where to buy a cavaquinho. Ben said he was looking for other cavaquinho players in Pittsburgh, so I sent him Handerson&amp;rsquo;s contact information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So no, I was not just hallucinating &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/10/05/performing-with-the-steel-city-ukuleles-at-the-wilkins-school-community-center-ecofest-2013-with-videos/&#34;&gt;post-ukulele-gig&lt;/a&gt; when I thought I heard a ukulele in Frick Park.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You never know what or who you might encounter in the park on a nice day.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reflections on my slowest Run Around the Square 5K in 13 years</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/08/24/reflections-on-my-slowest-run-around-the-square-5k-in-13-years/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Aug 2013 12:45:47 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/08/24/reflections-on-my-slowest-run-around-the-square-5k-in-13-years/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This year was the ninth time I ran in the annual &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.runaroundthesquare.com/&#34;&gt;Run Around The Square 5K race&lt;/a&gt;, and Abby&amp;rsquo;s third year in a row. The conditions were great: cool and dry, in contrast to the usual hot and humid conditions at this time of year. (Last year I reported on &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/08/25/my-eighth-time-doing-run-around-the-square-5k/&#34;&gt;my eighth running of the race&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both Abby and I ran this race rather slowly, but were happy and enjoyed the day. Here&amp;rsquo;s why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;both-of-us-coming-back-from-setbacks&#34;&gt;Both of us coming back from setbacks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing to note is that both Abby and I have been recovering from setbacks this year, as I reported two weeks ago after I ran the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/08/09/getting-up-when-reality-punches-you-in-the-face-running-the-second-liberty-mile-in-pittsburgh/&#34;&gt;second GNC Live Well Liberty Mile&lt;/a&gt; 18 seconds slower than last year. That race had me vowing to get back on track, and the very next day I did &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/08/10/emerging-from-my-three-months-of-illness-self-pitying-and-self-loathing/&#34;&gt;begin getting back on track&lt;/a&gt;. The road back to a regular exercise routine has not been easy in the past two weeks, but I have very gradually ramping up on running as well as minimal strength training every single day since then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, I ran the Run Around The Square 5K in 24:35.6 and was pretty to have recovered from several years of decline in fitness and self-care, by running my best time since 2006. For this year, I wrote, &amp;ldquo;I don&amp;rsquo;t know what goal to set for next year. I suppose I could set a goal of getting yet faster, breaking 24:15. That sounds reasonable to me. Going back down to 24:00 may even be possible. It&amp;rsquo;s too early right now to tell. But one thing is for sure: I have no intention of slowing down from this year to next.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, I did not set a firm enough goal. I have learned the hard way that if you don&amp;rsquo;t make a commitment (and then follow up with the discipline and sacrifices required to achieve it), then even in the absence of accidents, a maybe-goal is worthless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year, I went into the 5K race so untrained (two weeks of slowly ramping up before the race is not enough for any training benefits to kick in) that I basically knew that I was going to be super slow. I figured that since I lost 18 seconds in the mile, I would be happy if I lost only one minute in a 3K. So that was my expectation: finish around 25:36 this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;before-the-race&#34;&gt;Before the race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided that this was the race in which I debut my new orange running singlet, to replace my over-decade use of a blue singlet that Abby has gotten very annoyed with:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-around-the-square-2013/franklin-orange.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin wearing orange singlet&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Also, note that since I bought a SPIbelt earlier this year, I now always run races wearing a SPIbelt to carry my phone. This is particularly convenient when running a race where you have to park far from the start line and want access to your phone after a race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wore my Vibram FiveFingers KSO Trek shoes again. Since last year&amp;rsquo;s fiasco in which I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/30/running-my-10th-great-race-10k-obscene-but-in-a-good-way/&#34;&gt;injured my left foot from having the straps on my left foot too tight&lt;/a&gt;, I never again put the straps on too tight!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hanging out before the race start in Regent Square:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-around-the-square-2013/before.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Before start&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-around-the-square-2013/franklin-ready.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin ready&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Start line just a few minutes before race start:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-around-the-square-2013/start-line.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Start line&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-race&#34;&gt;The race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(&lt;a href=&#34;http://runhigh.com/2013RESULTS/R082413AA.html&#34;&gt;Race results.&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;different-race-logistics&#34;&gt;Different race logistics&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One very important change to the race, and one I greatly appreciated, was the staggered start. Faster runners were told to line up front and start up first. This is very helpful to control the congestion and confusion that happens in a large race when too many slower people start up front and have to be passed (including unfortunately young children that Abby and I have seen trampled on every year!). In particular, it is really tricky to be passing lots of people once in the trails of Frick Park.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;first-mile&#34;&gt;First mile&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of the ridiculous problems I created for myself by going too fast two weeks ago in the Liberty Mile, I vowed to go out at a reasonable pace in this 5K. I found this easy to do because of the staggered start, which meant that there were fewer people to have to accelerate past throwing off one&amp;rsquo;s own internal speedometer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The usual lot of young and old musicians were playing music along the course. What a great neighborhood tradition!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still get confused seeing the champagne stop near the end of the first mile at the entrance into the trails of Frick Park.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did the first mile in a leisurely 8:15 (compared to 7:18 last year).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;second-mile&#34;&gt;Second mile&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did the second mile in 10:17 (compared to 10:11 last year). I did not feel too bad. I was running a bit conservatively, because my training runs had been so slow and short and tough for me in the past two weeks. I wanted to be in position to run really well the final downhill in the third mile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;third-mile&#34;&gt;Third mile&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I let loose in the third mile. Because I had avoided going pukey in the second mile, I covered it in 7:06, actually a second faster than the 7:07 of last year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of the staggered start, there was not bad congestion during the third mile, and I found it safe to pass people at will.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;final-sprint&#34;&gt;Final sprint&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t have a gut-wrenching final sprint. I wasn&amp;rsquo;t even looking at the clock or my watch. This wasn&amp;rsquo;t one of those races in which I put it all out there on the course. Instead, this was a race where I was grateful to be running at all, and had no expectations other than to finish strong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I finished in 25:38, just a bit longer than a minute over last year&amp;rsquo;s 24:35.6. My &lt;em&gt;slowest&lt;/em&gt; Run Around The Square 5K time &lt;em&gt;in 13 years&lt;/em&gt;. But it was a clean finish, and I was so excited to simply be back and running faster than 26 minutes, at least.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;after-the-race&#34;&gt;After the race&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although I was not pukey, I was certainly breathing hard when I finished.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-around-the-square-2013/franklin-after.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin after the race&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I went off to drink water and start eating some food.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-around-the-square-2013/view.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;View&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;improvement&#34;&gt;Improvement&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I went back to the finish line to wait for Abby to finish. I saw Todd and his wife Gabrielle hanging around. Gabrielle said she took my &amp;ldquo;advice&amp;rdquo; (from last year) to go all out to the point of feeling pukey. I admitted that this time around, I didn&amp;rsquo;t follow my own advice. Gabrielle finished over 5 minutes faster this year than last year!! Todd finished over 8 minutes faster!! It&amp;rsquo;s great to see people in their late 40s improve their fitness so much in a single year. I saw the couple running together a couple of times in Frick Park this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;decline&#34;&gt;Decline&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby finished. She was out of breath and pukey, but I was proud of her for finishing. Because of the tremendous decline in health and fitness she has experienced this year, I was not sure she would actually finish the race.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-around-the-square-2013/abby-finish.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby finishing&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;more-food-and-refreshments&#34;&gt;More food and refreshments&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We lined up to sample more food and recovered. It was a beautiful day to be outside.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-around-the-square-2013/abby-recovered.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-around-the-square-2013/franklin-recovered.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The hot dogs and beer line was particularly long, but we finally reached the tables.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-around-the-square-2013/hot-dogs-beer.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Hot dogs and beer&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;walking-out-of-frick-park-back-to-the-car&#34;&gt;Walking out of Frick Park back to the car&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I couldn&amp;rsquo;t help taking a photo of the sign for beer and champagne that was still up on the trail entrance as we passed by:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-around-the-square-2013/beer-champagne.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Dunning&amp;#39;s beer and champagne stop&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;concern-about-abby&#34;&gt;Concern about Abby&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although I was happy that Abby managed to finish the 5K race, I was very concerned about her overall health and fitness, which have continued to be poor this year since she broke her foot in February. Here are her Run Around The Square 5K times since she started doing it with me:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2011: 37:15&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2012: 36:04&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2013: 39:54&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She was almost 4 minutes slower than last year. She&amp;rsquo;s lost &lt;em&gt;several years of fitness&lt;/em&gt; this year, and came in 105th of 116 in her age group. Again, we are grateful she is walking and running at all, but this has been a very bad year for her, and this impacts not only her own life, but ours more generally. We need to work on getting her back on track.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;goal-for-next-year&#34;&gt;Goal for next year?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right now, my real goal is to simply continue my exercise program and not break it again, and that includes the winter slump I usually enter. Last year, I had a slump in the final months of the year, and then woke up and &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/28/meditations-on-climbing-the-36-floors-of-the-pitt-cathedral-of-learning/&#34;&gt;started exercising again around New Year&lt;/a&gt;, and even signed up for the Pittsburgh Marathon as a way to force myself to stay active in the winter. I believe that if I simply avoid self-caused setbacks, I should be able to return myself to a decent level of fitness. I am &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; going to sign up for the Pittsburgh Marathon again. Almost certainly, however, I will sign up for the Pittsburgh Half Marathon! Last winter, I rather enjoyed &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/30/report-on-just-a-short-run-my-first-half-marathon-in-nine-years/&#34;&gt;training for and running the Just A Short Run half marathon&lt;/a&gt;. I reached good fitness through that, but squandered my fitness through overtraining and injury leading up to the marathon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;races-this-year&#34;&gt;Races this year&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the shorter term, I have two races to run in the coming month: the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/07/running-my-8th-pretty-good-race-5k-dealing-with-disappointment/&#34;&gt;CMU Pretty Good Race 5K&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/30/running-my-10th-great-race-10k-obscene-but-in-a-good-way/&#34;&gt;Great Race 10K&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, I did very poorly in the Pretty Good Race 5K because I was injured and exhausted, running 26:05. This year, I expect to do better than that. I&amp;rsquo;m not going to do the 24:36 of 2011, but given that I easily beat 26 minutes today, I will beat 26 minutes two weeks from now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Great Race 10K last year, I was still in a state of exhaustion and undertraining, so I didn&amp;rsquo;t even pay any attention to time goals, and finished slowly in 48:23. I see no reason why, if I continue improving my fitness in the next month (in contrast to last year&amp;rsquo;s dreadful September), I should not be able to run under 48:00.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;update-of-2013-09-06&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-09-06)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/09/06/was-it-worth-sprinting-to-a-terrible-fall-to-finish-25th-in-the-cmu-pretty-good-race-5k/&#34;&gt;my report on running the Pretty Good Race 5K this year&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Run Around The Square continued to thrive and improve, and I&amp;rsquo;m grateful for both the registration cap (to maintain the quality of the event) as well as the staggered start. And all the sponsors feeding us afterwards!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I were happy to have finished the race, even if we are both less fit now than we have been in years. But I think this is a wake up call for us to get back in shape. For example, I miss the long hikes we used to do last year when we had the stamina to actually do and enjoy them. The example Todd and Gabrielle set as they massively improved their fitness in the past year is inspiring. Abby and I should be able to do this too, if we make it a priority.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why I was so happy to run 5 miles in 63 minutes today when I was doing it in 50 earlier this year</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/08/13/why-i-was-so-happy-to-run-5-miles-in-63-minutes-today-when-i-was-doing-it-in-50-earlier-this-year/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Aug 2013 21:18:29 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/08/13/why-i-was-so-happy-to-run-5-miles-in-63-minutes-today-when-i-was-doing-it-in-50-earlier-this-year/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I went for a run in Frick Park, my usual 5-mile route, which I haven&amp;rsquo;t done in a while. It took me 63 minutes. Earlier this year I was doing it in 50. My fitness is pretty low right now, as &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/08/10/emerging-from-my-three-months-of-illness-self-pitying-and-self-loathing/&#34;&gt;I explained three days ago&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I&amp;rsquo;m happy to be on the upswing. I&amp;rsquo;m getting out there, not pushing too hard, but challenging myself. I have faith that I will get back out of my slump. I have done this before. Other people have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you also have this experience of being happy to do something worse than you used to do it, because you&amp;rsquo;re doing it at all rather than doing nothing?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A new hike in Frick Park with Abby</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/08/04/a-new-hike-in-frick-park-with-abby/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 Aug 2013 17:00:55 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/08/04/a-new-hike-in-frick-park-with-abby/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s August and Abby and I have been upset that, unlike all the other years since we&amp;rsquo;ve been together, most of the year has already gone by without our having gone on a substantial hike together. This is a big deal because hiking is one of the things that &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/05/12/my-rachel-carson-trail-hike-for-the-year/&#34;&gt;first drew us together and that we most enjoy doing together&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reasons for this utterly unfortunate situation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Abby broke her foot in February, at the same time she started a new job, and this totally threw both our lives into chaos. Her full recovery was very slow, and she has still not regained her fitness, and is not in any shape to do any of the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/11/fascinating-bushwhacking-hike-at-pa-state-game-land-51-dunbar/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Hiking meetup hikes that we normally start doing in the spring and throughout the summer&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I got occupied with Pittsburgh Marathon training, then after the marathon, during a hike, came down with a skin rash that resulted in a lot of trouble for me despite multiple trips to the doctor and treatments, still not completely cleared up even today, and that resulted in my not only losing fitness but also being wary of going out on hikes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, we decided that the past is the past, and we should start doing some smaller-scale hiking on our own, just to enjoy being out together again. Today we simply chose to do a little exploratory (for me, anyway) hike of Frick Park. The hike was probably just over 4 miles long (including walking to the park from home and back), so it was quite short, but it was good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s what I discovered:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;showing-me-some-trails&#34;&gt;Showing me some trails&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically, Abby showed me some trails she had discovered when taking her own walk in Frick at some point. These were not the trails I usually run on, but narrower, craggier, steeper trails that clearly are used by mountain bikers (in fact, one came our way during the hike).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby leading the way:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/frick-hike-2013-08-04/abby.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Some views:

&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/frick-hike-2013-08-04/view.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;View from trail&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/frick-hike-2013-08-04/another-view.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Another view from trail&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Fungi:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/frick-hike-2013-08-04/fungi.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Fungi&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A little bridge:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/frick-hike-2013-08-04/bridge.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;A bridge&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We ended up in Fern Hollow, familiar territory:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/frick-hike-2013-08-04/fern-hollow.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;View from Fern Hollow&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Do you see the spider web?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/frick-hike-2013-08-04/spider-web.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Spider web&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We went up the Falls Ravine Trail from Fern Hollow, and then Abby showed me a small trail that leads back up to &amp;ldquo;civilization&amp;rdquo;, emerging behind a bench near the meadow across from the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pittsburghparks.org/frick-kids&#34;&gt;Blue Slide Playground&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This meadow is popular for sledding in the snowy winter, but right now it is popular for some kind of medieval play fighting:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/frick-hike-2013-08-04/fighting.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Play fighting in the meadow&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was very happy to be hiking with Abby again, even if &amp;ldquo;only&amp;rdquo; in our backyard park and for a short distance.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Celebrating National Running Day quietly in Frick Park</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/06/05/celebrating-national-running-day-quietly-in-frick-park/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Jun 2013 22:19:02 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/06/05/celebrating-national-running-day-quietly-in-frick-park/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Last year, I made something of a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/06/06/i-celebrated-national-running-day-in-schenley-park-remembering-how-i-began-to-run-13-year-ago/&#34;&gt;big deal&lt;/a&gt; of celebrating &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.runningday.org/&#34;&gt;National Running Day&lt;/a&gt; in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pittsburghparks.org/schenley&#34;&gt;Schenley Park&lt;/a&gt; in Pittsburgh, for sentimental reasons. This year, I celebrated more quietly, by simply running one of my standard easy runs, a 5-mile run in &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburghparks.org/frick&#34;&gt;Frick Park&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have nothing to say, other than I&amp;rsquo;m happy to be out there running.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;luna-mono-sandals&#34;&gt;Luna Mono Sandals&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wore my &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lunasandals.com/products/luna-mono&#34;&gt;Luna Mono Sandals&lt;/a&gt;, which is much thicker (12mm) than the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lunasandals.com/products/luna-venado&#34;&gt;Luna Venado Sandals&lt;/a&gt; (7mm) that I wore a lot last year. The Mono&amp;rsquo;s thickness makes it feel much different from the Venado: welcome cushioning, but at the expense of ground feel and flexibility. It&amp;rsquo;s all about tradeoffs.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/frick-park-2013-06-05/luna-sandals-mono.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Luna Mono Sandals&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;some-photos-from-the-run&#34;&gt;Some photos from the run&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/frick-park-2013-06-05/frick1.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Frick Park&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/frick-park-2013-06-05/frick2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Frick Park&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/frick-park-2013-06-05/frick3.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Frick Park&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/frick-park-2013-06-05/frick4.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Frick Park&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/frick-park-2013-06-05/frick5.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Frick Park&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>