<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Flanders Recorder Quartet on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/flanders-recorder-quartet/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Flanders Recorder Quartet on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/flanders-recorder-quartet/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Final rehearsal for my first ukulele gig: and some hard decisions about music in my life</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/04/final-rehearsal-for-my-first-ukulele-gig/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2013 22:15:33 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/04/final-rehearsal-for-my-first-ukulele-gig/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;The night before our Ecofest gig, those of us in the Steel City Ukuleles who are performing in it had one final rehearsal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a very good rehearsal. We&amp;rsquo;re sounding more and more together as an ensemble, ending solidly on each song the way we agreed, and singing more in tune and balance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, Sunny reminded us that we are &lt;em&gt;performing&lt;/em&gt;, and so we should not just grimly look at our music booklets, but instead, when we can, we should look up and smile and engage with the audience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;singing&#34;&gt;Singing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still don&amp;rsquo;t have all the songs down as much as I would like, but by the end of the two-hour rehearsal, I was totally &lt;em&gt;hoarse&lt;/em&gt;. I am ready to sing out strong while simultaneously playing my ukulele.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I just realized that &lt;strong&gt;in the past three months, I have sung more than in the previous forty years of my life combined&lt;/strong&gt;. Wow. And I&amp;rsquo;m loving it. There&amp;rsquo;s nothing like singing, especially singing with others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;performance-is-time-and-energy-consuming&#34;&gt;Performance is time and energy consuming&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I almost didn&amp;rsquo;t make it to the rehearsal. I&amp;rsquo;ve completely exhausted myself this week with work and other activities, and badly need a break. There are times, such as earlier today, when I felt overwhelmed by everything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, yesterday, in discussing my musical plans for the coming months with Abby, I made some decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is my last ukulele gig for the year, for sure. I want to get back to basics and work on my technique and in really mastering some songs, rather than get back on the treadmill of more material for performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, this winter, I am not planning to participate in performing on recorder for the holiday gigs at Phipps Conservatory &amp;ldquo;candlelight evenings&amp;rdquo; that I&amp;rsquo;ve treasured &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/05/busy-evening-performing-at-phipps-followed-by-rehearsal-for-another-gig/&#34;&gt;in 2011&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/09/playing-music-on-recorders-at-a-phipps-conservatory-candlelight-evening/&#34;&gt;in 2012&lt;/a&gt;. That was always a huge amount of work for me. Unless I can participate in significantly reduced capacity, I don&amp;rsquo;t see how I can manage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will probably perform in the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/14/pittsburgh-contras-and-squares-holiday-ball-2012/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Contras and Squares Holiday Ball&lt;/a&gt; again, because it&amp;rsquo;s something I&amp;rsquo;ve been doing with Abby every year, and because after two years of doing it, I know the music, and therefore it will not require much work to participate in (if I want to do some Irish flute and tin whistle solos, of course, then I can add as much extra work for myself that I want, ha).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-is-the-best-use-of-my-limited-time-and-energy-for-music&#34;&gt;What is the best use of my limited time and energy for music?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, there have been announcements and reminders for some time about recorder and ukulele &lt;em&gt;workshops&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;concerts&lt;/em&gt; coming up soon. I have decided not to sign up for any of them, because I really need some rest time on &lt;em&gt;weekends&lt;/em&gt; that I have not been getting; weekends are also the time when I can do more household chores and spend time with Abby.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find that my main enjoyment and improvement in music comes form what I do daily, anyway, rather than what I can possibly do in a long, extended workshop format. I&amp;rsquo;ve always been frustrated that when I attend a one or two day conference or workshop on any subject (computer programming, salsa dance, etc.), I don&amp;rsquo;t actually retain or engage with as much as I would like. There are ways to optimize these experiences, but that requires a certain kind of immediate followup that I don&amp;rsquo;t have time for right now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I will sadly miss the fantastic &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flanders-recorder-quartet.be/en/home/&#34;&gt;Flanders Recorder Quartet&lt;/a&gt; when they come to Pittsburgh in November, and I will miss the workshop Annie has arranged for them to give here for the local recorder community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I am going to miss &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.coolhanduke.com/&#34;&gt;Cool Hand Uke&lt;/a&gt; when he comes to Pittsburgh to give a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/Steel-City-Ukuleles/events/135233932/&#34;&gt;workshop&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/Steel-City-Ukuleles/events/138577782/&#34;&gt;concert&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Life is full of choices, especially for those of us who have many interests, not just one. This week I made some decisions about my involvement with music in October, November, and December.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>