<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Information Diet on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/information-diet/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Information Diet on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/information-diet/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>What I did immediately after the National Day of Unplugging</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/03/24/what-i-did-immediately-after-the-national-day-of-unplugging/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Mar 2012 19:40:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/03/24/what-i-did-immediately-after-the-national-day-of-unplugging/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/22/paradox-i-will-observe-the-national-day-of-unplugging-but-just-bought-my-first-smartphone-this-week/&#34;&gt;The past 24 hours&lt;/a&gt;, I observed the &lt;a href=&#34;http://nationaldayofunplugging.org/&#34;&gt;National Day of Unplugging&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not a report on what I learned during that experience. I will be working on that report, which will probably be spread out over multiple posts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a report of what I did, &amp;ldquo;plugged in&amp;rdquo;, right after the event ended.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-i-immediately-did-after-finishing-the-national-day-of-unplugging&#34;&gt;What I immediately did after finishing the National Day of Unplugging&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Made a phone call to Abby, who has been in North Carolina since yesterday.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Turned on my home computer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Announced on Facebook and Twitter that I was back from unplugging! (Funny that this is the first thing I did online.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Checked my emails: I have around 30 to deal with. That&amp;rsquo;s not bad, but I know that usually, I receive the least email on Saturdays.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Started to &amp;ldquo;catch up&amp;rdquo; on my RSS feeds, Facebook, Twitter, Google+.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;emails-i-missed&#34;&gt;Emails I missed&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Notification about a Meetup event for tomorrow morning. If I had known about it earlier, I might have planned today differently. It is &amp;ldquo;too late&amp;rdquo; now to change tomorrow&amp;rsquo;s plans, so I will not be attending that event. (There is a different Meetup event I&amp;rsquo;m going to in the afternoon.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Notification about multiple Meetup events further in the future I may be interested in attending; need to look at the details and add to my online calendar if I decide to go.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Party invitation on Facebook. &lt;strong&gt;This is why I can&amp;rsquo;t quit Facebook; people actually use it.&lt;/strong&gt; Need to look at my online calendar and discuss with Abby.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Continuing old and new email threads involving various friends; I need to catch up and participate.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Notifications about new comments in my blog&amp;rsquo;s threads and other people&amp;rsquo;s blogs&amp;rsquo; threads where I&amp;rsquo;d indicated I want to be notified; sometimes this is useful, but other times less so. I will respond promptly to the comment on my old blog post.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Never-ending emails about new bills and statements I need to inspect and deal with.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Notifications about a bunch of new people following me on Twitter. I&amp;rsquo;ve long since given up on looking up every single new follower (or unfollower). I do like to make note of Pittsburgh locals I may have met in person or should meet, however.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Various mailing lists and other notifications.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;facebook&#34;&gt;Facebook&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OK, so it took about 15 minutes to catch up on browsing Facebook. That&amp;rsquo;s actually longer than I expected. Typically I check Facebook once or twice a day, and I&amp;rsquo;ve imagined that I don&amp;rsquo;t spend more than 5 minutes a day on Facebook, but apparently I&amp;rsquo;m wrong. Interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe I should spend less time on Facebook, because in reality, most of what I see there is not really necessary for me to see; it&amp;rsquo;s just idle people-watching for me, and the value of that is unclear to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;google&#34;&gt;Google+&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll be honest: I spend very little time on Google+. It&amp;rsquo;s just not where most people I know (as in &amp;ldquo;non-geeks&amp;rdquo;) are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;rss-feeds&#34;&gt;RSS feeds&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lots of articles to sort through. For fun, as I go through them to save those I cannot just skim in 15 seconds, but want to read in depth later, I am listing the topics of the saved ones here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Eclipse plugin for automatic Javadoc comments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Improvised Persian music for Nowruz&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Claims that Twitter Bootstrap is the way to go for web site design&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Privacy and how to pay for it&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Formal mathematical model of film success or failure&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to fix local issues: government or not?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The stresses on women in today&amp;rsquo;s world&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Plight of the introvert&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Calibre and freedom for ebooks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Guido and callbacks in Python&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A new blogging platform called Svbtle (sic)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Collection of historical chess footage on YouTube&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saturday is a slow day. On a weekday I typically find more new stuff to read.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;twitter&#34;&gt;Twitter&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I hit Twitter, to scroll down and see what I missed. I get tremendous value from Twitter, actually, that I cannot get from other sources. Perhaps that is the subject for a future blog post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-new-smartphone&#34;&gt;My new smartphone&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still need to get going on setting up and really using my new smartphone. This task may need to wait until Monday or Tuesday, since I have a lot of stuff I need to get done tonight and tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve talked about the first things I&amp;rsquo;ve done after getting back online. I&amp;rsquo;ll continue monitoring my online activities as they happen. One thing &amp;ldquo;unplugging&amp;rdquo; has done for me is give me (at least temporarily) a more conscious than usual awareness of what I do online. This will be a step toward streamlining my online activities.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Paradox? I will observe the National Day of Unplugging but just bought my first smartphone this week!</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/03/22/paradox-i-will-observe-the-national-day-of-unplugging-but-just-bought-my-first-smartphone-this-week/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Mar 2012 21:22:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/03/22/paradox-i-will-observe-the-national-day-of-unplugging-but-just-bought-my-first-smartphone-this-week/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/unplug.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;National Day of Unplugging 2012&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Just in February, I heard of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://nationaldayofunplugging.org/&#34;&gt;National Day of Unplugging&lt;/a&gt; scheduled for March 23-24, 2012, and immediately put it on my calendar, with the hope of observing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For some time, I&amp;rsquo;ve been &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/02/02/2-new-daily-habits-of-mine-in-a-distracting-world/&#34;&gt;struggling with being increasingly plugged into the Internet&lt;/a&gt;, and Clay Johnson has been advocating an &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.informationdiet.com/&#34;&gt;information diet&lt;/a&gt;, so I decided to do this day of unplugging as an experiment, to observe what my habits have been and learn something about myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ironically, on Wednesday I just bought my first smartphone, after years of never having used one. So what&amp;rsquo;s going on?!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/phones/samsung-galaxy-s-ii.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Brand new Samsung Galaxy S II&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-an-information-diet&#34;&gt;Why an information diet?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spend a lot of time in front of a computer, whether at work, at home on my main computer (a 2008 MacBook connected to an external display), or on my iPad 2. The first thing I have to say up front is that &lt;strong&gt;I am not a Luddite&lt;/strong&gt;. I actively use technology as a tool, as an extension of myself. As a software developer, I actively create tools to help people do their jobs. I use the Web as a source of knowledge, wisdom, and social connection. It is completely unimaginable what my life would be like if not for the past 15 years of Web access. In fact, my life was completely different in every possible way before the Web came along, and I was a completely different person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So my goal is not to &amp;ldquo;unplug&amp;rdquo; permanently, or &lt;em&gt;arbitrarily&lt;/em&gt; set limits on computer or Internet use. My goal is to take control of the resources in an active, deliberate way, rather than default to passively being overwhelmed both by distractions and by too much of a good thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The diet needs to extend to every aspect of being plugged in. For me, the main problem is too much useful information: given any topic I&amp;rsquo;m interested in, I could spend forever learning about it online, even if I need to focus my limited time and attention on fewer topics rather than many. For others, the social aspect may be the main problem. Even for me, an introvert, it is hard to keep up with the social networks I&amp;rsquo;m part of; I always have too many emails to deal with at length.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Michael Ellsberg just put up a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ellsberg.com/friendlessness&#34;&gt;heartfelt video&lt;/a&gt; in which he talks about the social aspect of overload; I recommend watching it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;observing-the-national-day-of-unplugging&#34;&gt;Observing the National Day of Unplugging&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the National Day of Unplugging, I will monitor in detail what I miss when I unplug, and what I gain when I unplug, and then report back on what I learned, what surprised me, and how I might change up my regular routines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have not already made plans that require being plugged in on Saturday, I suggest joining me in observing the &lt;a href=&#34;http://nationaldayofunplugging.org/&#34;&gt;National Day of Unplugging&lt;/a&gt; and sharing what you learned from it also!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-my-first-smartphone&#34;&gt;Why my first smartphone?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;old-phone-died&#34;&gt;Old phone died&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/phones/motorola-razr-v3t.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Motorola Razr V3t with blank display&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The short story is that on Tuesday, the display of my five-year-old cell phone, a Motorola Razr V3t I bought in January 2007, went blank, and so it was time to finally upgrade my phone. I had been thinking for a year or two now of getting a smartphone, because the display had become flaky and battery life decreasing, but had not because&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I did not really &lt;em&gt;need&lt;/em&gt; a smartphone.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Smartphones are expensive.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data plans are expensive.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;why-a-smartphone-not-a-new-dumbphone&#34;&gt;Why a smartphone, not a new &amp;ldquo;dumbphone&amp;rdquo;?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing I missed about not having a smartphone was having a high-quality camera on me at all times. I believe a camera is a very useful tool in many situations, for photos and videos. I hardly ever used the terrible camera of my old cell phone. I also never put any apps on it, never listened to any music on it. My old cell phone was just for making phone calls; I never texted either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many other reasons a smartphone could be useful in my life (for example, during travel I could have used a smartphone in the past couple of years!), but instead of listing speculations, I&amp;rsquo;ll just see what happens and report on the benefits. Meanwhile, I realize that the potential for it becoming a distraction truly exists, because for five years since the iPhone came out, I see, on a daily basis, people being completely, &lt;em&gt;utterly&lt;/em&gt; distracted by their smartphones in a way that I hope I never will be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are much cheaper data plans now than in the past, so it finally seemed reasonable to get a smartphone now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s been two days since I bought my new phone, and I actually haven&amp;rsquo;t had any time yet to do much with it. All I&amp;rsquo;ve done is learn how to make a call and answer the phone, and connect it to WiFi and email.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have an interest in possibly getting into developing apps for mobile devices, and maybe actually owning a smartphone will encourage me to give it a shot!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;which-smartphone&#34;&gt;Which smartphone?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have an iPad 2 and use Macs, so you might think I would get an iPhone, but I didn&amp;rsquo;t. Why? First of all, I&amp;rsquo;m on T-Mobile, and there&amp;rsquo;s no iPhone support for T-Mobile. Second, developing for Android is more pleasant than developing for iOS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.samsung.com/global/microsite/galaxys2/html/&#34;&gt;Samsung Galaxy S II&lt;/a&gt;. Yes, it&amp;rsquo;s expensive, but given my policy of using devices for many years (my first car lasted me 14 years, and I&amp;rsquo;m still using a 2008 MacBook), I have found from experience that I last longer between upgrades if I get something that isn&amp;rsquo;t entry level. I don&amp;rsquo;t want to be buying a new smartphone for another five years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ironically, just after I bought this phone, I saw an article saying that &lt;a href=&#34;http://lifehacker.com/5895699/if-youre-in-the-market-for-an-android-phone-you-might-want-to-wait&#34;&gt;now is the time to wait for the Samsung Galaxy S III and the like&lt;/a&gt;. (I didn&amp;rsquo;t even bother to skim that article, after following the link to it, because the last thing I need is &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Buyer&#39;s_remorse&#34;&gt;buyer&amp;rsquo;s remorse&lt;/a&gt;.) But let&amp;rsquo;s face it, one could wait forever for everything. I needed a new phone now. And the iPad 3 just came out, but Abby and I have made much use of the iPad 2 during the time we&amp;rsquo;ve owned it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, I&amp;rsquo;ll keep note of advice such Henrik Edberg&amp;rsquo;s recent blog post about &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.positivityblog.com/index.php/2012/03/22/smartphone-attention/&#34;&gt;how not to let your smartphone take over your attention and life&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I look forward both to observing the National Day of Unplugging and also to exploring how my new smartphone can benefit my life. I don&amp;rsquo;t think it is necessarily paradoxical to embrace technology while also being careful and reflective about it, just being honest with ourselves and observing ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2 new daily habits of mine in a distracting world</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/02/02/2-new-daily-habits-of-mine-in-a-distracting-world/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Feb 2012 09:02:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/02/02/2-new-daily-habits-of-mine-in-a-distracting-world/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;As of a week ago, I have developed two daily habits to reclaim my life from a distracting digital world:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/meditation/&#34;&gt;meditation&lt;/a&gt; in the morning, before breakfast&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;shutting down my computer at home in the evening two hours before going to bed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;meditation&#34;&gt;Meditation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The meditation habit is one I have wanted to develop for years now, but had not. Before around 2007, I was meditating every day for a year or two, but then I fell off the practice, and eventually stopped for long periods of time, and then just a year ago, thanks to a weekly meditation practice set up at Carnegie Mellon University, I began attending that (and Abby started meditating for the first time then).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I always felt guilty during the entire past year when noting that I wasn&amp;rsquo;t regularly meditating at home. I knew that &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m too tired&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;I don&amp;rsquo;t have time&amp;rdquo; are never valid excuses to avoid doing something one feels one &amp;ldquo;should&amp;rdquo; do. Those excuses almost always mean that something has gone wrong with priorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fact is, I was caught up with a huge number of projects, and became more and more unbalanced, especially when I lost the CMU practice for two months since it was no longer happening (thanks to the CMU academic calendar).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last week, Abby and I decided that we would meditate in the morning before breakfast, and keep it at ten minutes. Who doesn&amp;rsquo;t have ten minutes in a day, especially for something that, for me, gives me benefits that last the entire day? So we&amp;rsquo;ve established this new routine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;more-on-the-morning-routine&#34;&gt;More on the morning routine&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conjunction with the new meditation routine, I also decided that I would not check email or the Web generally until after meditation, and unless there was an emergency, I would not deal with email until after breakfast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, I have decided to significantly reduce reading the Web (through my blog subscriptions or Twitter feed) in the morning, so that I keep my morning focused. Now I&amp;rsquo;ll check the Web mostly at lunch time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;evening-information-diet&#34;&gt;Evening information diet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, I have cut out a good bit of computer time from my evening also, in order to promote better sleep as well as doing other things, such as reading paper (gasp!) books.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This has been a difficult cut, but I have managed so far, and yes, there have been repercussions. I have been doing less blog writing (because that happens on the computer), less Web reading, less tweeting. I have a large backlog of interesting Web articles that I&amp;rsquo;ve simply bookmarked without reading, and I have to confess that I&amp;rsquo;m not happy about this situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have yet to figure out the best balance to achieve in this digital age given my thirst for fresh ideas and information that are so easy to come by online, but I know for sure that I do not want to sacrifice essential calmness, exercise, sleep, and social time for the sake of addictive information overload that in the long run is not as beneficial as one might hope. What do I really need to know about? And how much of it can I apply? And even given that I have received much of value online, what is the opportunity cost of not using the time spent online on pursuits off-line? These are very hard questions for me to answer, so I&amp;rsquo;m taking my information diet one step at a time.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>