<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Temperature on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/temperature/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Temperature on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/temperature/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>A note on running in warm weather</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/04/13/a-note-on-running-in-warm-weather/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Apr 2014 21:43:14 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/04/13/a-note-on-running-in-warm-weather/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I haven&amp;rsquo;t been running much at all in recent months; actually, I barely ran all winter, in contrast to last winter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since it&amp;rsquo;s warmer now, I no longer have an excuse. I went out for a short run in Frick Park late in the afternoon, when it was warm and sunny, probably around 80 degrees F.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a really tough time out there, going less than three miles before I turned around and started walking home. I know from prior experience that after not running much, I have to ramp up slowly, but in this case, the suddenly warm weather (after months of a seemingly endless winter) took a toll on me. So I&amp;rsquo;d like to remind anyone else coming out of &amp;ldquo;hibernation&amp;rdquo; not to feel discouraged if feeling unfit: just do a little bit of running at a time, &lt;em&gt;hydrate&lt;/em&gt; (I was grateful that the water fountains in the park are operational), and &lt;em&gt;be patient&lt;/em&gt;! If I didn&amp;rsquo;t know any better, I would be feeling quite discouraged after my excursion today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I treated myself to some cookies after my run. These are cookies I saved from an event at work last week, specifically for only after hiking or running. &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/01/16/a-system-for-quitting-eating-cookies/&#34;&gt;I would not eat&lt;/a&gt; these unremarkable cookies otherwise!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/frick-park-2014-04-13/cookie1.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Cookie 1&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/frick-park-2014-04-13/cookie2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Cookie 2&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/frick-park-2014-04-13/franklin.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>