<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Inspirational on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/inspirational/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Inspirational on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/inspirational/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>I Don&#39;t Feel Like Practicing; but I&#39;m Gonna Do It Anyway</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/09/26/i-dont-feel-like-practicing-but-im-gonna-do-it-anyway/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Sep 2011 19:07:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/09/26/i-dont-feel-like-practicing-but-im-gonna-do-it-anyway/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This morning I felt pretty tired, still recovering from yesterday&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/25/blistered-but-blissful-in-the-burgh/&#34;&gt;race&lt;/a&gt;, so the thought crossed my mind, &amp;ldquo;Maybe I should take a little break, and skip recorder practice today&amp;rdquo;. Also, I hadn&amp;rsquo;t improved as much during the past week as I had planned and felt frustrated.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/s-a-t-recorders.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin&amp;#39;s soprano, alto, and tenor recorders&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;No effing way!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to a lot of great web sites and books out there on &lt;a href=&#34;http://lifehacker.com/&#34;&gt;productivity&lt;/a&gt; and psychology, and advice from &lt;a href=&#34;http://zenhabits.net/&#34;&gt;wise people&lt;/a&gt; from all walks of life, I&amp;rsquo;ve learned to watch very carefully for signs of loss of self-discipline and direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jerry Seinfeld said, &lt;a href=&#34;http://lifehacker.com/281626/jerry-seinfelds-productivity-secret&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t break the chain&lt;/em&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;/a&gt;. If you want to get good at something and achieve a tough goal, you have to work at it every day, even if only a little bit a day. It is easy for our minds to wander and make up excuses to skip one day, to skip one practice. This applies to every aspect of life, not just matters such as music practice. It applies to whether to exercise every day, whether to write a blog post every day, whether to avoid eating cookies for a week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, I don&amp;rsquo;t necessarily kick myself if in fact I really have to alter my planned schedule. Sometimes I&amp;rsquo;m sick and it&amp;rsquo;s better to sleep than to try to go for a run, or I have a respiratory ailment and don&amp;rsquo;t want to blow into a wind instrument.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But too many times I&amp;rsquo;ve seen people (including myself) make up excuses to not do something, and become so creative as to put off a &amp;ldquo;plan&amp;rdquo; for years at a time. Maybe there&amp;rsquo;s that book I always meant to read, but it&amp;rsquo;s yellow now since college and somehow I have &amp;ldquo;no time&amp;rdquo; for it. Or maybe I wanted to learn to draw, but kept on &amp;ldquo;needing&amp;rdquo; fancy paper and pencils. Or maybe I wanted to lose weight, but every day I make an &amp;ldquo;exception&amp;rdquo; and eat a side of fries or cup of ice cream. Or maybe I always &amp;ldquo;wanted&amp;rdquo; to learn to dance the samba, but mysteriously, my leg seems to be &amp;ldquo;injured&amp;rdquo; remarkably often every time I&amp;rsquo;m not eating ice cream and looking for pencils to buy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What it comes down to is, you have to decide what is important, and act accordingly. What is important may not be what your friends think is important. It may not be what your spouse thinks is important. It may not be what your society thinks is important. But if you truly believe, then you have a stark choice: go ahead anyway, or quit. Do not go halfway. A &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yoda&#34;&gt;wise sage&lt;/a&gt; said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Do or do not. There is no try.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/9/96/CGIYoda.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Yoda with light saber&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Why waste time aimlessly practicing recorder only maybe once a week, and not getting anywhere at all, if I could spend that one hour doing something that I could find that I cared more about?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;applying-the-lessons-to-my-life&#34;&gt;Applying the lessons to my life&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, the day I really committed to playing recorder, March 7 of 2011 (after starting to play the alto recorder on February 19 and informally practicing every day until the initial excitement wore off), I printed out a music practice log/journal, and vowed to practice every single day, indefinitely (as far as this was reasonable). I had decided to join the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.andrew.cmu.edu/user/lukas/pcars/Welcome.html&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh chapter&lt;/a&gt; of the American Recorder Society, whose next meeting was March 20. I had two weeks to teach myself as much alto recorder as I could before the meeting. I attended, was warmly welcomed as a newcomer, and have continued to attend and participate in group playing, while getting lots of helpful advice from everyone there. The group is not too big, and is informal and friendly: I love how the communities for different hobbies of mine in Pittsburgh are so inviting. This city is just the right size for me. I&amp;rsquo;d feel lost living in New York or something, where there are a lot more things to do, more polish, more glamour, more hotshots, but also more distance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have missed probably an average of one day of recorder practice every two weeks. I can live with that. &lt;em&gt;The point of the planned schedule is not, paradoxically, to rigidly stick to it.&lt;/em&gt; The point is to set a personal standard, a mind set, a reference point, an &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/Anchoring&#34;&gt;anchor&lt;/a&gt;. When I was twelve years old, I was struck by this &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikiquote.org/wiki/Robert_Browning&#34;&gt;quote&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Ah, but a man&#39;s reach should exceed his grasp,
Or what&#39;s a heaven for?
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I immediately interpreted this as meaning, if I want to achieve something, I must aim beyond it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was learning &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.andrew.cmu.edu/user/shotokan/pska.org/CMU.shtml&#34;&gt;karate&lt;/a&gt; several years ago, I was taught that when punching someone, aim to punch through him, and not just to hit the surface.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of inevitable uncertainties and setbacks, it is necessary to aim beyond where one wants to go, in order to get there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I picked up my recorder and &lt;a href=&#34;http://musiciansway.com/&#34;&gt;practiced&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Namaste&#34;&gt;Namaste&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/alto-recorder-practice.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Running My Ninth Pittsburgh Great Race 10K: Blistered but Blissful in the &#39;Burgh</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/09/25/blistered-but-blissful-in-the-burgh/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Sep 2011 15:28:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/09/25/blistered-but-blissful-in-the-burgh/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m temporarily using a walking stick right now, because of bad blisters I got on my right foot this morning. But I am very happy today, and it was a &lt;a href=&#34;http://rungreatrace.com/&#34;&gt;Great&lt;/a&gt; day in the &amp;lsquo;Burgh.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/franklin-finishing-great-race-10k-2011.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin finishing Great Race 10K (photo by Abby)&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/great-race-2011-official/0020.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin giving it all he has&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/great-race-2011-official/0093.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin crossing finish line&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/great-race-2011-official/0094.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin over finish line&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/great-race-2011-official/0072.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin stopping his watch&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have now run the Pittsburgh &lt;a href=&#34;http://rungreatrace.com/&#34;&gt;Great Race&lt;/a&gt; 10K nine times now, beginning in 2000: I have only missed 2003 (the year it was canceled), 2009, and 2010. I have run it in all kinds of conditions (both in terms of weather and my physical state). There is no other race I have run for so many years, so it is always special to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But beyond that, today&amp;rsquo;s race was special because Abby participated in it, for the first time. She did not run the 10K, but did run the 5K (and took the photo of me above nearing the finish line). She just started running in races with me this year, and I am very proud of her for getting into running! Having once been a non-runner, it gives me great pleasure to encourage others to take up this wonderful form of exercise.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/abby-before-great-race-5k-2011.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby in Oakland before Great Race 5K start&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Of course, right after catching my breath and finding Abby, my first instinct was to ask her, &amp;ldquo;Where are the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.eatnpark.com/smiley.asp&#34;&gt;Smiley Cookies&lt;/a&gt;?&amp;rdquo; I limped over to pick one up, even as sweat was still dripping down my face, and eagerly gobbled it!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/franklin-great-race-2011-smiley-cookie.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin with Smiley Cookie after race&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;tradition&#34;&gt;Tradition&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Great Race is a wonderful Pittsburgh tradition. It is not only thrilling to be on the Boulevard of the Allies heading downtown getting a fine view of our city (although the uphill during mile 5 of the race is admittedly tough), but the sight of so many people participating in this event is heartwarming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/great-race-2011-crowd.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/great-race-2011-crowd-2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-great-race-stats&#34;&gt;My Great Race stats&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was also very happy about my finish time. I had a plan to break 48:00 this year, and I succeeded handily (all times mentioned are &amp;ldquo;chip times&amp;rdquo;, not &amp;ldquo;gun times&amp;rdquo;). My time was, of course, not one of my fastest times in this race (my fastest time was 42:49 nine years ago), but it was faster than my time in 2008. The last three years of my life have been very tough for me physically, so I have enjoyed starting to get back into shape this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s my record in the Great Race 10K over the years:
&lt;table style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 15px&#34;&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;th style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px; font-size: 1.1em&#34;&gt;Year&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;th style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px; font-size: 1.1em&#34;&gt;Chip time&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;th style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px; font-size: 1.1em&#34;&gt;Comment&lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;2000&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;53:53&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;First time ever ran more than 3 miles continuously at all!&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;2001&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;45:02&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;Lost weight, trained seriously.&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;2002&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;42:49&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;Trained really hard.&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;2003&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;(not held)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;2004&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;45:36&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;Very sick, but was preregistered, and didn&amp;rsquo;t want to break tradition.&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;2005&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;46:49&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;Was too busy to train.&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;2006&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;46:55&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;Again untrained. Slower and slower.&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;2007&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;47:11&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;Not trained at all; extreme pain halfway, but kept going.&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;2008&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;49:12&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;Not trained at all, left shin hurting, unmotivated.&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;2009&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;(did not run)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;Too untrained to even think of running.&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;2010&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;(did not run)&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;Too untrained to even think of running.&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;tr&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;2011&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;47:46&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;td style=&#34;border: 1px solid black; padding: 3px&#34;&gt;Lightly trained, but put in a genuine effort on race day.&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;details-of-the-race&#34;&gt;Details of the race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My splits (for each mile, then the final 0.22 mile) are below. I tried to run an even effort (till the final mile, when I simply tried to keep going hard despite the pain), accounting for the changes in elevation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;7:40.73&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;7:07.52&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;8:09.14&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;7:23.90&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;8:24.08&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;7:29.08&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1:31.03&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One trick I try to use in a race is to pick someone ahead of me who is running just a bit faster than what I feel I can hold, and see if I can slowly catch up (and maybe overtake eventually). In the Great Race, this is hard to do because there are so many runners, and people starting at different times, so there is always a lot of passing and slowing down going on, unlike in smaller races where things get spread out and you know people are basically running at the pace they can hold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have to work harder in these big races to maintain my own sense of pace. I do this by &amp;ldquo;feel&amp;rdquo;: having run in races from a mile up to the marathon, I know what a sustainable pace feels like. 5K pace gives me a burning, pukey sensation, for example, while half-marathon pace is not at all pukey. 10K pace is in between: uncomfortable but tolerable, till the final mile when I just do whatever I can without completely falling apart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;don-slusser&#34;&gt;Don Slusser&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it was after around two miles that I noticed ahead of me &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.newsandsentinel.com/page/content.detail/id/538234.html&#34;&gt;Don Slusser&lt;/a&gt;, a local legend in the running scene. OK, he is not at all what he used to be, and has had a lot of knee surgeries, but still, I felt it was an honor to be see him out there still running.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As long as Don was still ahead of me, he was going to be my target. He pulled away from me slightly over the next three miles, but was always in my sight. So in the final mile, I finally blasted past him. Then somehow he passed me at one point downtown, and that pushed me to pick up the pace again and finish ahead of him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After he finished, I went up to him and shook his hand. He probably has no idea who I am or why I respect him or how he helped provide focus for me in my own attempt to run as well as I could today, but what can I say, it was a spontaneous gesture on my part. I salute you, Don: you and your wife Tammy have done much for the Pittsburgh running community and I am grateful for that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-note-on-shoes&#34;&gt;A note on shoes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the second race in which I&amp;rsquo;ve run in my &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.vibramfivefingers.com/products/Five-Fingers-BikilaLS-Mens.htm&#34;&gt;Bikila LS&lt;/a&gt; shoes (the first race was &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/23/happiness-is-finishing-39th-of-43-men-in-a-race/&#34;&gt;three days ago&lt;/a&gt;). Unfortunately, these shoes tend to give me blisters if I run over three miles and fast. I&amp;rsquo;ve run a slow eight miles before without blisters, but going fast, and in warm weather, my feet sweat and chafing happens. These shoes are nice but have a ventilation problem. I have never had any problems with my &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.vibramfivefingers.com/products/Five-Fingers-KSO-Trek-Mens.htm&#34;&gt;KSO Trek&lt;/a&gt; shoes that I use for trail running and hiking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see in the photo above that Abby wore her &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.vibramfivefingers.com/products/five-fingers-komodo-sport-ls-mens.htm&#34;&gt;KomodoSport LS&lt;/a&gt; shoes in the race. Wearing &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.vibramfivefingers.com/&#34;&gt;Vibram FiveFingers&lt;/a&gt; shoes for walking, hiking, and running has really improved our lives. (More on that in a later blog post.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;photo-update-on-september-28-2011&#34;&gt;Photo update on September 28, 2011&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some official photos from Island Photography have appeared online. I have to confess that my original plan was to try to spot the cameras and try to look good for any photos of me that might be taken. Unfortunately, I was in such pain in the final mile of the race that I had tunnel vision and could not really perceive anything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve added some of these photos to the beginning of this blog post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2012-09-30&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-09-30)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following year, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/30/running-my-10th-great-race-10k-obscene-but-in-a-good-way/&#34;&gt;I ran in the Great Race again&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Happiness Is: Finishing 39th of 43 Men in a Race!</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/09/23/happiness-is-finishing-39th-of-43-men-in-a-race/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Sep 2011 19:31:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/09/23/happiness-is-finishing-39th-of-43-men-in-a-race/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, on a late, muggy afternoon, I ran in a race, and finished 39th of 43 men in the race. I ran as hard as I could, just as I do in every race: my goal is always to run fast and beat as many competitors as I can. I don&amp;rsquo;t run in a race for &amp;ldquo;fun&amp;rdquo; (in the conventional sense of the word): I race to know pain and to stretch my limits. (I save my &amp;ldquo;fun&amp;rdquo; running for when I&amp;rsquo;m not racing.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So why was I pretty happy, despite getting my butt totally kicked?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For amusement, here is an excerpt of the men&amp;rsquo;s individual results of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cmu.edu/athletics/recreation/intramurals/activities.html&#34;&gt;CMU intramural&lt;/a&gt; XC race yesterday (billed as 2 miles but the course was clearly shorter than that): &lt;ol start=&#34;38&#34;&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;13:17.3&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;13:27.7 (me)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;14:33.7&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;14:33.71&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;14:33.72&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;14:59.9&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, I was happy for a number of reasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For one thing, this is the first &amp;ldquo;cross-country&amp;rdquo; race I have done, so I was just plain excited to do something different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, my expectations were low. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ted.com/talks/barry_schwartz_on_the_paradox_of_choice.html&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Low expectations are the secret to happiness.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; I entered the race knowing there was a definite possibility that I would finish last. I knew many of the runners would be undergrads less than half my age, and a self-selected group too, a group that does not include the (sadly numerous) students I see around every day who take the bus down one or two blocks or take the elevator up one floor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I was one of those students once&lt;/em&gt;. I was not a runner as a child, or in high school, or in college, or even in graduate school. I was sickly as a child, and also I was raised to pay no attention to physical fitness and even to look down on those who were fit (I know, &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sour_grapes&#34;&gt;sour grapes&lt;/a&gt;). I started running only after I left graduate school and embarked on several radical life changes (including losing 30 pounds, altering my diet, and taking up competitive ballroom dancing). So in a way, taking advantage of the opportunity (as CMU staff) to take part in the CMU intramural cross-country race was a way to fill in a gap in my collection of novel and exciting lifetime experiences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can bet I&amp;rsquo;ll be running this race again next year, and with every intention of placing higher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2012-09-27&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-09-27)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/27/why-i-missed-the-cmu-intramural-xc-race-this-year/&#34;&gt;I ended up not running this race in 2012&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-note-on-shoes&#34;&gt;A note on shoes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ran yesterday&amp;rsquo;s race in my &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.vibramfivefingers.com/products/Five-Fingers-BikilaLS-Mens.htm&#34;&gt;Vibram FiveFingers Bikila LS shoes&lt;/a&gt;, the first time I&amp;rsquo;d worn this pair of shoes in a race. I will run the Great Race in these shoes also. (More later on this blog about &amp;ldquo;minimalist shoes&amp;rdquo; and how they saved my life.)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/my-bikila-ls.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin&amp;#39;s Vibram FiveFingers Bikila LS shoes&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;preview-for-sunday&#34;&gt;Preview for Sunday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Sunday I will be running the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rungreatrace.com/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Great Race 10K&lt;/a&gt;. This will be the ninth time I have run the race. Stay tuned for a race report on Sunday!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below is a photo of my running it for the first time, in 2000, as the second race I had ever done (and I had never run more than three miles continuously in my life at that time). It was quite an ordeal. The following year I ran the race better prepared, 8:51 faster.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/great-race-2000.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin nearing the finish of the Great Race in 2000&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2011-09-25&#34;&gt;(Update of 2011-09-25)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/25/blistered-but-blissful-in-the-burgh/&#34;&gt;Great Race 2011 report&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Byron Janis on Overcoming Adversity</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/09/22/byron-janis-on-overcoming-adversity/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Sep 2011 20:57:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/09/22/byron-janis-on-overcoming-adversity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Imagine this.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You are an 11-year-old boy who is already an established prodigy at the piano, and you have an accident with your little finger and a glass door. Your finger is shredded, and losing a tendon and nerve in the surgery, and not being able to feel anything in the finger, you are told by the doctor to think of doing something else with your life than continue with piano.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do you do?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.byronjanis.com/&#34;&gt;Byron Janis&lt;/a&gt;, you decide to pursue your passion, finding ways to work around the defective finger, using other fingers and using your vision to monitor what the little finger is doing. The world doesn&amp;rsquo;t even know about your difficulty until you tell them after another sixty years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, I was privileged to hear Byron Janis speak today and perform a few pieces at the piano at a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cmu.edu/news/stories/archives/2011/september/sept12_byronjanis.html&#34;&gt;convocation at Carnegie Mellon University&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/byron-janis-speaking.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Byron Janis speaking&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/byron-janis-playing.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Byron Janis playing piano&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Janis spoke of overcoming not only the problem with his finger, but also the psoriatic arthritis he developed later. At a low point in his life, he ended up beginning to compose, and finding meaning in music through that avenue. &amp;ldquo;&lt;strong&gt;Passion&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;perseverance&lt;/strong&gt;!&amp;rdquo; he repeated again and again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I liked how down-to-earth he was in his talk. He grew up in Pittsburgh, after all: he&amp;rsquo;s one of ours!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-his-talk-touched-me&#34;&gt;Why his talk touched me&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a long time in my life, I was a musical dilettante, unwilling to put in the truly focused, disciplined effort to play an instrument well (I piddled around with flute and piano). I grew up believing that my hands were &amp;ldquo;too&amp;rdquo; small and my fingers &amp;ldquo;too&amp;rdquo; short. Also, my left hand&amp;rsquo;s pinky finger (and less so, my ring finger) got genuinely damaged in elementary school, and my left thumb got damaged in high school. (I do live with the consequences of those accidents every day.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, none of that should really have stopped me from doing what I can with what I have, if I care. Only when older and wiser did I realize that in the end, this is all we can do in life, and it is enough!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This February, I made a decision to seriously practice the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Recorder&#34;&gt;recorder&lt;/a&gt;. I joined the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.andrew.cmu.edu/user/lukas/pcars/Welcome.html&#34;&gt;local chapter&lt;/a&gt; of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.americanrecorder.org/&#34;&gt;American Recorder Society&lt;/a&gt;. For the first time in my life, I have made the effort to practice intelligently and efficiently, and most importantly, &lt;em&gt;regularly&lt;/em&gt; (as in approximately an hour every day of the week). And I believe I have done pretty well in the past eight months. I am continuing to improve my playing, and my enjoyment has deepened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not going to lie: every time I pick up my alto or tenor recorder (I also have a soprano and am planning to get a bass), I momentarily wish my hands were bigger, my right pinky longer, and my entire left hand less messed up, but such thoughts disappear quickly, because I am no longer willing to play victim, and instead focus on doing what I need to do to make music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wish Byron Janis well in his current mission to inspire everyone, from disadvantaged youths to injured veterans, to overcome adversity and follow their passion with perseverance!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>