<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Apple on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/apple/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Apple on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/apple/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Four generations of Apple laptops</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/09/21/four-generations-of-apple-laptops/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Sep 2012 13:52:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/09/21/four-generations-of-apple-laptops/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/transferring-macbook.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Transferring MacBook to MacBook Pro&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I just bought a new &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.apple.com/macbook-pro/&#34;&gt;Apple MacBook Pro&lt;/a&gt; to replace my old black plastic 2008 MacBook, in order to get more memory and hard drive space, plus be able to run Mountain Lion. Abby and I also used this upgrade of mine as an opportunity to give her the old MacBook and switch her from running Windows computers. We have various reasons to switch her to Mac, one of them simply being that it&amp;rsquo;s easier for me to administer Macs (which I primarily use, at work and at home) than for me to have to deal with Windows computers also. Much easier to troubleshoot just one type of machine!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This new purchase means that I have now owned four different generations of Apple laptops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;powerbook-duo-280c-http-en-wikipedia-org-wiki-powerbook-duo-bought-used-in-1995&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/PowerBook_Duo&#34;&gt;PowerBook Duo 280c&lt;/a&gt;, bought used in 1995&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first Apple laptop was a PowerBook Duo 280c that I sold not long after I bought it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;powerbook-145b-http-en-wikipedia-org-wiki-powerbook-140-powerbook-145b-bought-used-in-1995&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/PowerBook_140#PowerBook_145B&#34;&gt;PowerBook 145B&lt;/a&gt;, bought used in 1995&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/powerbook-145b/finder.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;PowerBook 145B up in System 7 Finder&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I [mentioned this laptop earlier]((/blog/2011/11/14/my-powerbook-145b/). It actually came out in 1993.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2 MB RAM&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;40 MB hard drive&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I last used this in 1998 when traveling to a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.informatik.uni-trier.de/~ley/db/conf/pldi/pldi98.html&#34;&gt;conference while in graduate school&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;powerbook-g4-12-inch-http-en-wikipedia-org-wiki-powerbook-g4-bought-new-in-2003&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/PowerBook_G4&#34;&gt;PowerBook G4, 12-inch&lt;/a&gt;, bought new in 2003&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;256 MB RAM&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;40 GB hard drive&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note how in 3 years, from 1995 to 1998, I multiplied my amount of RAM by a factor of &lt;em&gt;128&lt;/em&gt;, and multiplied my hard drive by a factor of &lt;em&gt;1000&lt;/em&gt;. That was wild. The PowerBook G4 marked the end of my buying desktop computers: my last desktop computer I ever bought was actually a brand new Gateway PC in 1995.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a photo of my (still running &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mac_OS_X_Leopard&#34;&gt;Mac OS Leopard&lt;/a&gt; PowerBook G4 next to my new MacBook Pro:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/powerbook-g4-2003-macbook-pro-2012.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;PowerBook G4 2003 and MacBook Pro 2012&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;macbook-13-inch-http-en-wikipedia-org-wiki-macbook-bought-new-in-2008&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MacBook&#34;&gt;MacBook, 13-inch&lt;/a&gt;, bought new in 2008&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a matter of frugality, I try to put off new computer purchases as long as possible. I probably should be &lt;em&gt;less&lt;/em&gt; frugal, since at some point decreased productivity does kick in, but in any case, I did move from the old PowerPC G4 PowerBook eventually, buying the entry level black plastic Intel MacBook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dual processor&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3 GB RAM&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;250 GB hard drive&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note the dual processor. Also, note how in 5 years, from 2003 to 2008, I multiplied RAM by a factor of &lt;em&gt;12&lt;/em&gt;, and multiplied my hard drive by a factor of about &lt;em&gt;6&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eventually I had to replace the battery, which swelled. I also upgraded to 4 GB of RAM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a photo of my (still running &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mac_OS_X_Lion&#34;&gt;Mac OS Lion&lt;/a&gt; PowerBook G4 next to my new MacBook Pro:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/macbook-2008-macbook-pro-2012.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;MacBook 2008 and MacBook Pro 2012&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve given this laptop to Abby as her first Mac.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;macbook-pro-13-inch-http-en-wikipedia-org-wiki-macbook-pro-bought-new-in-2012&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MacBook_Pro&#34;&gt;MacBook Pro, 13-inch&lt;/a&gt;, bought new in 2012&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am very happy with my new MacBook Pro. I was having difficulties with my old laptop because of not quite enough RAM or hard drive space to work the way I wanted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;4 cores&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;8 GB RAM&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;750 GB hard drive&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 4 years, from 2008 to 2012, I multiplied RAM by &lt;em&gt;2.7&lt;/em&gt;, and hard drive by &lt;em&gt;3&lt;/em&gt;. I bet that in another 4 years, I&amp;rsquo;ll feel pinched again and need yet another upgrade! But for now, I am totally content. This machine is &lt;em&gt;fast&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;spacious&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/macbook-pro-in-box.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;MacBook Pro 2012 in box&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s amusing looking back at the progression of the Apple laptops I&amp;rsquo;ve owned over the past 17 years. Speed, number of cores, amount of memory needed, amount of storage space needed, all have gone up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing I have learned from experience is that I should really upgrade sooner than I usually do. So maybe I should expect to upgrade in 3 years rather than in 4 years. But who knows? How demanding of resources are my Web browsers and programming tools going to be in the coming years?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My PowerBook 145B</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/11/14/my-powerbook-145b/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Nov 2011 20:51:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/11/14/my-powerbook-145b/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not sure what to do with my old Apple Macintosh &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/PowerBook_140#PowerBook_145B&#34;&gt;PowerBook 145B&lt;/a&gt; laptop. It still boots, but is obviously not of much use to me any more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here it is booting &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/System_7&#34;&gt;System 7&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/powerbook-145b/booting-system-7.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;PowerBook 145B booting System 7&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The machine had crashed years ago before I booted it:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/powerbook-145b/last-crashed.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;PowerBook 145B booting after crash&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Finally, boot is complete:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/powerbook-145b/finder.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;PowerBook 145B up in System 7 Finder&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Some personal history and observations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This PowerBook 145B was the second laptop I owned; the first was a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/PowerBook_Duo&#34;&gt;PowerBook Duo&lt;/a&gt; that I bought used, found problematic, and sold. I also bought the 145B used. I didn&amp;rsquo;t splurge and buy a new Mac till the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Power_Macintosh_6100&#34;&gt;Power Macintosh 6100&lt;/a&gt; in 1995.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With only 2 MB (that&amp;rsquo;s no typo; these days computers come with &lt;em&gt;one thousand times&lt;/em&gt; as much RAM, more like 2 GB typically), it was necessary to monitor memory usage and quit unused applications. It was a mistake upgrading to System 7.5 on this machine, I have to admit. And with a 40 MB hard drive, I was always having to put stuff onto floppies. I bought software like RAM Doubler and Disk Doubler and Speed Doubler, but they were obviously not a panacea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still, I got stuff done with this laptop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eventually, the battery refused to hold any more real charge, and since the adapter connection got flaky, that is why the last time I used the laptop, it suddenly just lost power and shut down uncleanly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I already threw away all my floppies years ago, and there is no network card for the laptop, so it really is useless now. I have a cute ADB-based 28.8k modem that I used with the laptop for many years. I even browsed the Web, having &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mosaic_%28web_browser%29&#34;&gt;Mosaic&lt;/a&gt; installed, although I preferred using &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MacWeb&#34;&gt;MacWeb&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I haven&amp;rsquo;t seriously used this laptop since 1998, when I was still taking it with me on travel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My PowerBook 145B is such a museum piece now. What should I do with it? Wipe the hard drive and donate it somewhere, or keep around myself to amuse the millennial generation who are now babies playing with iPads?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pittsburgh software developer communities</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/10/16/pittsburgh-software-developer-communities/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Oct 2011 19:38:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/10/16/pittsburgh-software-developer-communities/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the past couple of years, I started to get involved in various local Pittsburgh groups of people who are committed enough to the art and science of software development to actually meet up outside of work to share ideas and experiences. Now and then, there has been talk of bringing the different groups together for special events, to share even more (especially outside the boundaries of particular computer language communities), so I felt it was a good time for me to compile a list of the different groups whose meetings I have attended or at least have heard about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I welcome additions and corrections as well as further discussion of this list. I will update the list upon feedback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Last update: 2011-10-18)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;ruby&#34;&gt;Ruby&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://pghrb.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Ruby group&lt;/a&gt; is quite active. It has been meeting the first Thursday of every month at Vivisimo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been attending this more as I finally started getting into Ruby in 2010.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;python&#34;&gt;Python&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://pghpython.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Python group&lt;/a&gt; is also active. It has been meeting the fourth Wednesday of every month at Vivisimo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a lot of use of Python for scientific computing, such as natural language processing and machine learning, among this community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do not attend this group&amp;rsquo;s meetings regularly because I currently only use Python to maintain an &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.scons.org/&#34;&gt;SCons&lt;/a&gt; script at work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;javascript&#34;&gt;JavaScript&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/Pittsburgh-JavaScript-Developers/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh JavaScript meetup group&lt;/a&gt; only came into being in June 2011, thanks to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.fusioncube.net/&#34;&gt;Steve Brownlee&lt;/a&gt;, who hosts the meetup at Smith Micro up in McCandless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The group has been pretty active, despite the location.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;jquery&#34;&gt;jQuery&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jburgh.com/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh jQuery user group&lt;/a&gt; is scheduled to meet once a month at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.hackpittsburgh.org/&#34;&gt;HackPittsburgh&lt;/a&gt; in Uptown. However, I get the impression that it has not been meeting very regularly. I attended the meeting in March and another in August, but otherwise, have had to miss a meeting or there was none.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There has been some talk of merging with the JavaScript meetup group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;java&#34;&gt;Java&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://java.net/projects/pittjug/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Java User Group&lt;/a&gt; has been around for quite some time. It meets at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pghtech.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Technology Council&lt;/a&gt; on Second Avenue. When there are meetings, they are announced on the mailing list and posted at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pghtech.org/events/default.aspx&#34;&gt;pghtech calendar&lt;/a&gt; where one should register before attending.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PittJUG was more active in the past: I was attending fairly regularly in 2009 and 2010, but now meetings have been infrequent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, an experiment is about to begin to revitalize the group: on October 25, we&amp;rsquo;ll be trying an &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pghgeekoutday.com/home/open-spaces&#34;&gt;Open Spaces&lt;/a&gt; format to take place of the old format that seemed to result in long presentations by people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;pittsburgh-geek-out-day&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Geek Out Day&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pghgeekoutday.com/home/open-spaces&#34;&gt;Open Spaces&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pghgeekoutday.com/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Geek Out Day&lt;/a&gt; was created specifically to use that very format. There have been three &amp;ldquo;geek out day&amp;rdquo; meetings so far, in April, May, and August 2011. The first two involved blocking out a Saturday morning each, and the second was on a Wednesday evening, and I attended all three.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am sold on the virtues of Open Spaces. The format of long presentations by people is, I think, usually quite inefficient of everyone&amp;rsquo;s time and attention. A lot of the users groups have moved toward &amp;ldquo;lightning talks&amp;rdquo;, which are definitely an improvement, but opening things up toward even more active participation by everyone was a revelation to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next meeting of Pittsburgh Geek Out Day is November 5, so sign up if you haven&amp;rsquo;t been to one yet and can spare a Saturday morning!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;agile&#34;&gt;Agile&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/PittsburghAgile/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Agile meetup group&lt;/a&gt; is fairly new, having its first meeting in April 2011. It has been meeting at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.matrixformedia.com/&#34;&gt;Matrix Solutions&lt;/a&gt; on the North Shore and is active.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This group involves a mix of people who are developers as well as those who are managers, and of course, those who fall into both categories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;apple&#34;&gt;Apple&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Developers for Apple platforms, i.e., MacOS X and iOS, have a home at &lt;a href=&#34;http://cocoaheads.org/us/PittsburghPennsylvania/index.html&#34;&gt;CocoaHeads&lt;/a&gt;.  I have never been to their meetings, but have a friend who attends, and it seems to be pretty active.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It meets the third Thursday of every month at Smith Micro.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;apple-ios&#34;&gt;Apple iOS&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is an &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/iPhone-iPad-Mobile-App-Developers-Pittsburgh-Meetup/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Apple iOS meetup group&lt;/a&gt;, but I have not been to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;clojure&#34;&gt;Clojure&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/Clojure-PGH/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Clojure users group&lt;/a&gt; that used to meet, but I never made it to any of the meetings, and it seems to be inactive now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;coding-dojo&#34;&gt;Coding dojo&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://tech.groups.yahoo.com/group/PghCodingDojo/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Coding Dojo&lt;/a&gt; was active many years ago, but has been rather inactive recently. The last meeting I went to was in March 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;net&#34;&gt;.NET&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is an active &lt;a href=&#34;http://pghdotnet.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh .NET users group&lt;/a&gt;, but I have never been to any of its meetings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope that this list will be useful to those who are already a member of one or more groups and interested in checking out the others, and perhaps in creating cross-group learning experiences and events.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are there any other groups of interest that I am missing? Please let me know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also: since I have always taken notes for myself at each meeting of each user group that I have attended in the past couple of years (ha, I should have started blogging earlier, given my obsession with writing), if anyone is interested in any summaries or the like, let me know. So far, the only meeting I have written up for my blog has been a recent &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/14/agile-anti-patterns/&#34;&gt;Agile meetup on anti-patterns&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;updates&#34;&gt;Updates&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;2011-10-18&#34;&gt;2011-10-18&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://twitter.com/akinsgre&#34;&gt;Greg&lt;/a&gt; reminded me to mention this useful calendar of &lt;a href=&#34;http://pghtechevents.com/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh tech events&lt;/a&gt;. Some months ago, I subscribed to it using Google Calendar, and it really is quite helpful to have around.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I Cannot Imagine My Life Without the Influence of Steve Jobs</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/10/05/i-cannot-imagine-my-life-without-the-influence-of-steve-jobs/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Oct 2011 21:39:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/10/05/i-cannot-imagine-my-life-without-the-influence-of-steve-jobs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Steve Jobs is gone, tonight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But he&amp;rsquo;s not really gone. Everything he did is with us. With me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m typing this blog post on an early 2008 model MacBook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t like eulogies. But I have a few emotions right now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Omitting mention of a couple of generations of other Macs I&amp;rsquo;ve owned: I became a programmer largely because his work showed that computers could be beautiful, useful, and liberating to ordinary human beings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Steve Jobs altered my direction in life. I wrote my first Kernighan and Ritchie &lt;code&gt;hello world\n&lt;/code&gt; C program on a Mac Classic. I learned C++ on a Mac SE/30. I got my first job writing my resume on the SE/30.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before that, I wrote my first Pascal program using MacPascal on the original 128K Macintosh in school.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before that, I wrote BASIC programs on an Apple IIe, my first computer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Skipping forward: at one point I bought an early PowerMac, but it was uninspiring: Apple had lost its way without Steve Jobs. I cursed Apple and abandoned it, bought a PC, and ran Linux for years. I never touched a Mac again until OS X came out. Steve Jobs was back!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Steve Jobs was a programmer, an artist, a businessman, a philosopher, a psychologist, a salesman, a speechwriter, a fighter. He cared about beauty, about consistency, stuck to his visions, failed and succeeded and failed and succeeded. I live because humanity produces men like Steve Jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is all. Tomorrow is another day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-2011-10-25&#34;&gt;Update (2011-10-25)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I write this short update to note that I never did get around to writing my intended in-depth discussion of Steve Jobs, but will do so at some point. For example, it was too close in time for me to launch into a personal exploration of the dark, negative sides of his legacy.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>