<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Time Management on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/time-management/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Time Management on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/time-management/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Dealing with setbacks during my second month of meditation</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/03/01/dealing-with-setbacks-during-my-second-month-of-meditation/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Mar 2013 10:50:25 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/03/01/dealing-with-setbacks-during-my-second-month-of-meditation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A month ago, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/02/01/a-report-on-one-month-of-daily-meditation/&#34;&gt;I reported on my meditation practice in January 2013&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The month of February was even more problematic for me than January was. I&amp;rsquo;ve noticed a pattern that January tends to start our fairly well, because of rebooting after the winter holidays, but then &amp;ldquo;feature creep&amp;rdquo; catches up in life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; manage to meditate every single day, but thanks to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://insighttimer.com/&#34;&gt;Insight Timer&lt;/a&gt; mobile app I use, with its &amp;ldquo;journal&amp;rdquo; feature, I have a lot of when I did and my brief thoughts after each session.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;problems&#34;&gt;Problems&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;breaking-the-chain-for-the-first-time&#34;&gt;Breaking the chain for the first time&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I first &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/26/i-dont-feel-like-practicing-but-im-gonna-do-it-anyway/&#34;&gt;broke my chain&lt;/a&gt; of daily meditation on Wednesday, February 6. This was the day after a long &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/02/05/pittsburgh-chess-club-championship-2013-round-4-fascinating-attacking-defending-game/&#34;&gt;chess tournament game in the evening&lt;/a&gt;. According to my journal, I was very busy with exercise, work, and starting to pack for the &lt;a href=&#34;http://nescala.org/&#34;&gt;NE Scala&lt;/a&gt; conference that &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/02/10/ne-scala-2013-my-first-scala-conference/&#34;&gt;I was going to&lt;/a&gt; travel to Philadelphia for the next day, Thursday (which I took off from work). I ended up &amp;ldquo;forgetting&amp;rdquo; to meditate, and then staying up late, until I realized I had forgotten, and so it was past midnight when I did the meditation session, so it counted for Thursday rather than Wednesday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The piling up of being &amp;ldquo;too busy&amp;rdquo; clearly wrecked my routine. In retrospect, the only solution is to plan better when my routine is going to be broken up by travel or other significant disruptions. Also, there was the matter of just having too much in my routine anyway: I did recognize that Tuesday night chess tournaments were clearly  causing me to stay up too late at night, and so decided already in late January to &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/30/why-and-how-i-am-going-to-run-the-2013-pittsburgh-marathon/&#34;&gt;stop playing in them&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: I did manage to get in my daily meditation while at the conference, using the Android version of the app. I squeezed it in on the floor of the hotel suite I shared with Josh and Jamie while they were in the other room.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-one-minute-meditation-session&#34;&gt;A one-minute meditation session&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Monday, February 11 was a tough day for me (still recovering from the conference trip, and going back to work) and more so for Abby, who broke her foot late at night coming back from mandolin rehearsal. We spent nearly two hours at the emergency room (time mostly spent waiting; we spent another two hours Tuesday morning), during which I decided to steal a quiet minute meditating, so I did a &lt;em&gt;one-minute&lt;/em&gt; meditation using the mobile app at one point. In my whole meditation log, this is the only time in the past two months that I did anything other than a ten-minute meditation on a day when I meditated at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next two weeks of our lives were very tough. I put aside most of what I had planned to do in my life during that period, in order to take care of &lt;em&gt;our&lt;/em&gt; life, but I made sure to meditate every day. I think having the meditation practice really helped a lot, actually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;problems-with-the-evening-schedule&#34;&gt;Problems with the evening schedule&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I never got back onto a reliable morning meditation schedule, although I did continue to meditate before bed. But because of variability in my schedule, I again missed a daily evening session, by mere minutes, on Monday, February 25, when I had a crazy busy day that concluded with &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/02/25/stepping-it-up-at-the-french-and-blues-jam/&#34;&gt;not only stopping by OpenHack Pittsburgh but also attending a music jam&lt;/a&gt;. I didn&amp;rsquo;t forget to meditate; I just stayed up too late for the session to count for Monday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, the real solution is to get the meditation in early in the morning. Having a better home evening routine would also help: I have found that if I stay out too late outside the home for some event, I end up &amp;ldquo;shifting&amp;rdquo; my schedule at home rather than cutting things out that I would normally do during an evening staying at home. Abby has advised me on this and I agree with her that this is the right thing to do. On days when I&amp;rsquo;m out in the evening, I simply cannot expect to have the time to do what I would normally do when not out. I should not shift, but should cut out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite all the setbacks, I still keep on meditating. It is easy to stop doing something when you realize you&amp;rsquo;re doing it &amp;ldquo;badly&amp;rdquo;. It is easy to say &amp;ldquo;what&amp;rsquo;s the point?&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;ll never get this right&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m a loser&amp;rdquo;. But I keep in mind that meditation is meditation, however it is done. I don&amp;rsquo;t stop flossing my teeth just because I don&amp;rsquo;t always do it perfectly, after all. And sometimes the benefits do not become apparent until an unexpected turn (such as Abby&amp;rsquo;s accident) that showcases the need to be present and calm in the face of challenges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s been two months now since New Year. Do you have New Year habits that you threw yourself into with enthusiasm that you have now fallen away from or are ashamed of not keeping up the way you had hoped? How have you coped with your own imperfection?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-08-10&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-08-10)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I never wrote up a report on March meditation, or April, or my giving up meditation in May. Here is an &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/08/10/emerging-from-my-three-months-of-illness-self-pitying-and-self-loathing/&#34;&gt;explanation of what happened and how I decided to get back on track&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A report on one month of daily meditation</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/02/01/a-report-on-one-month-of-daily-meditation/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Feb 2013 21:00:58 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/02/01/a-report-on-one-month-of-daily-meditation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/30/when-i-dont-have-time-to-sit-and-breathe-something-is-wrong-with-my-life/&#34;&gt;As promised a month ago&lt;/a&gt;, here is a report on a month of meditation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite some real challenges, I managed to complete a month of daily meditation, and found some tricks and strategies to keep going, and will report again in another month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;virtual-communities&#34;&gt;Virtual communities&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By coincidence, as the New Year began, I found that a blog I occasionally look at, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wildmind.org/&#34;&gt;Wildmind&lt;/a&gt;, had issued a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wildmind.org/blogs/on-practice/join-us-for-wildminds-100-day-meditation-challenge&#34;&gt;100 day meditation challenge&lt;/a&gt;. I took this as a great opportunity to join a virtual &amp;ldquo;community&amp;rdquo; of meditators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;insight-timer-http-insighttimer-com&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://insighttimer.com/&#34;&gt;Insight Timer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that a mobile app called &lt;a href=&#34;http://insighttimer.com/&#34;&gt;Insight Timer&lt;/a&gt; was promoted, and I ended up immediately buying it for both iOS (for our iPad) and Android (for my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/22/paradox-i-will-observe-the-national-day-of-unplugging-but-just-bought-my-first-smartphone-this-week/&#34;&gt;phone&lt;/a&gt;). I had intended to buy a meditation app anyway, since it was time for me to stop being stingy (I had been using an adware version of a meditation app on iOS earlier).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I liked that this app not only existed on both iOS and Android (I expected to use the meditation app on my phone in case of travel and when finding quiet moments out of the home in general), but also provided a virtual community that showed who is meditating &amp;ldquo;with&amp;rdquo; you at any moment around the world using the app. When the going gets tough, I find it useful to remember that other people are also doing what they can to maintain their meditation practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;problems&#34;&gt;Problems&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as has happened repeatedly before, challenges popped up as the month progressed. For various reasons, my schedule was modified and so was Abby&amp;rsquo;s, and since we again had tried to meditate together, this led to some tough situations when we didn&amp;rsquo;t get in meditation as our first activity in the morning upon getting out of bed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first hope was that, well, we missed that moment, but maybe we could make it up later in the day. So on a weekend, if we got up at different times, maybe we could meditate before lunch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was a big mistake. It is very difficult to get back together to meditate when we have both started our days with numerous chores that we don&amp;rsquo;t want to interrupt. In fact, we ended up twice in January having fights in which Abby did not want to meditate when I was ready to do so, and the conflicts in turn made me not want to meditate either. In any case, it was very stressful negotiating every single day whether we would meditate together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;solutions&#34;&gt;Solutions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fundamental solution was to decouple meditation from Abby, who clearly did not particularly value meditation. People will differ on what they consider priorities in their lives. It was a fundamental mistake returning to my faint hope that Abby and I would sustain a joint meditation practice. I have to take &lt;em&gt;full responsibility&lt;/em&gt; for my own practice, just as I have again done so with my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/28/meditations-on-climbing-the-36-floors-of-the-pitt-cathedral-of-learning/&#34;&gt;physical exercise&lt;/a&gt;, which had also been disrupted once I met Abby years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby made a good suggestion, which was that I should meditate by myself, but we could sometimes meditate together also, but that this should be considered a supplemental activity because it might or might not happen any given day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other thing to note is that even after this decoupling of meditation activity, I was still having some problems with meditation because of the changes in my own routines, so by no means was Abby to blame for my difficulties. Often I felt &amp;ldquo;rushed&amp;rdquo; to get stuff done upon waking up, and delayed meditation to before bedtime. This was a symptom that something was wrong with my life, of course. If I can&amp;rsquo;t spare 10 minutes in the morning to meditate, and am really so &amp;ldquo;busy&amp;rdquo;, then clearly I have too many things going on in my life. January turned out to be much busier than I had originally wanted. This happened despite my previous knowledge that for many people, January ends up too busy because of decisions to take up new habits at the beginning of the year! Oops. I hope I start January 2014 better than I did January 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite setbacks, I did manage to go through an entire month of January with daily meditation. I will, of course, report back after the month of February on my progress in the 100 day meditation challenge.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>When I don&#39;t have time to sit and breathe, something is wrong with my life</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/12/30/when-i-dont-have-time-to-sit-and-breathe-something-is-wrong-with-my-life/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Dec 2012 16:35:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/12/30/when-i-dont-have-time-to-sit-and-breathe-something-is-wrong-with-my-life/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/zafus.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Our two zafus&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s been a long time since I&amp;rsquo;ve mentioned &lt;em&gt;meditation&lt;/em&gt; here. In fact, it&amp;rsquo;s been &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/02/23/saying-no-in-order-to-say-yes/&#34;&gt;ten months&lt;/a&gt;! This despite my knowledge of &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/02/02/2-new-daily-habits-of-mine-in-a-distracting-world/&#34;&gt;how beneficial it is&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a reason: I completely lost my &lt;em&gt;meditation practice&lt;/em&gt; at some point this year. I don&amp;rsquo;t even remember when I lost it. It may have had something to do with the fact that the iPad app we had been using as a meditation timer suddenly stopped making sound and we didn&amp;rsquo;t know why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yeah, what a sad excuse. But this is &lt;em&gt;exactly&lt;/em&gt; how, when one&amp;rsquo;s practice is already in trouble, any trivial glitch (so easily solved one way or another) is an excuse to stop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I have periodically &amp;ldquo;tried&amp;rdquo; to get back on, but as Yoda wisely said,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Try not! Do, or do not. There is no try.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/BQ4yd2W50No&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So now what?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;do&#34;&gt;Do&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;ve decided to &amp;ldquo;do&amp;rdquo;. This meant having to discuss the various reasons and chain reactions that lead to not doing meditation, and how to head them off. Meditation &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/02/10/meditation-is-hard/&#34;&gt;can be hard&lt;/a&gt;, but really, sitting and breathing for just &lt;em&gt;ten minutes&lt;/em&gt; in the morning is, objectively, not so hard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s not hard to realize that if I am so &amp;ldquo;busy&amp;rdquo; that I don&amp;rsquo;t have time to sit and breathe for ten minutes, &lt;em&gt;something is wrong with my life&lt;/em&gt;. Something has become unbalanced. Abby and I have had quite a year of many activities and experiences, but at some point, I started neglecting some basics. In particular, the last two months of this year have been something of a blur. Abby has tried to get us back to meditating, but I&amp;rsquo;ve resisted with some pretty bad excuses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But as of today, we are back. Being too &amp;ldquo;busy&amp;rdquo; means priorities are out of whack: did I really need to read those blog posts or tweets for ten minutes, instead of meditating? The answer is embarrassingly obvious when the mind is clear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, and as for the iPad meditation app: I checked the app and it&amp;rsquo;s making the start and end sounds just fine now. And if it didn&amp;rsquo;t, that wouldn&amp;rsquo;t stop us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meditation is good, and I&amp;rsquo;m back. In order to commit myself to keeping up the practice, I have decided that I should write about meditation on this blog at least once a month! It&amp;rsquo;s on my calendar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-02-01&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-02-01)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A report on &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/02/01/a-report-on-one-month-of-daily-meditation/&#34;&gt;my meditation in January 2013&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-03-01&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-03-01)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A report on &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/01/dealing-with-setbacks-during-my-second-month-of-meditation/&#34;&gt;my meditation in February 2013&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Saying No in order to say Yes</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/02/23/saying-no-in-order-to-say-yes/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Feb 2012 20:23:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/02/23/saying-no-in-order-to-say-yes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Lately I&amp;rsquo;ve been having to say &amp;ldquo;No&amp;rdquo; a lot to events and activities that appeal to me, in order to make room for &amp;ldquo;Yes&amp;rdquo;. Time and energy are finite for us every day and every week, and our &lt;a href=&#34;http://buddhism.about.com/b/2011/12/12/desires-are-inexhaustible.htm&#34;&gt;desires are inexhaustible&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, I wrote a post about &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/18/disagreement-on-the-use-of-time/&#34;&gt;how I use my time&lt;/a&gt;. A lot has changed since then, with various rebalancings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;music&#34;&gt;Music&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;listening-to-music&#34;&gt;Listening to music&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/02/i-love-music-but-rarely-listen-to-it-now/&#34;&gt;do not listen to music much&lt;/a&gt;, but I do more of it now than I did last year. I still minimize listening to recorded music (lately I listen to specific music that I am playing myself or attempting to), preferring to listen to live music where I don&amp;rsquo;t even know the program in advance. In particular, I&amp;rsquo;ve found it very stimulating to attend more &lt;a href=&#34;http://music.cmu.edu/index.php?sub_page=events&#34;&gt;Carnegie Mellon School of Music Convocations&lt;/a&gt;, which are targeted toward music students. One of my earliest blog posts was about going to a special convocation featuring &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/22/byron-janis-on-overcoming-adversity&#34;&gt;Byron Janis&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;ve been to some others since then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The group &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.fluteforce.org/&#34;&gt;Flute Force&lt;/a&gt; was here about a month ago for a convocation and of course I had to go, given how I&amp;rsquo;d gotten serious about playing flute. They gave a nice concert of a variety of music, all of which was unfamiliar to me and stimulating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/flute-force/flute-force-1.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Flute Force&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/flute-force/flute-force-2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Flute Force&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I went to a rather moving and thought-provoking presentation and performance by the violinist &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.myspace.com/sangeetosho&#34;&gt;Sangeet-Richard Downs&lt;/a&gt;, who was a CMU graduate. (I will write a blog post later about &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/RichardDownsmusic&#34;&gt;him&lt;/a&gt; and his message that completely resonates with me.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a &amp;ldquo;conventional&amp;rdquo; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.shadysideacademy.org/page.cfm?p=8593&#34;&gt;concert last Saturday&lt;/a&gt; by the Carnegie Mellon Chamber Orchestra that I was planning to take Abby to, and had already obtained tickets for, but this was an example of my saying &amp;ldquo;No&amp;rdquo; in order to say &amp;ldquo;Yes&amp;rdquo;: we decided instead to do &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/02/20/enjoying-more-french-dancing-in-pittsburgh&#34;&gt;French dancing&lt;/a&gt;. And there is no doubt we made the right decision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;playing-instruments&#34;&gt;Playing instruments&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lately, I&amp;rsquo;ve said &amp;ldquo;No&amp;rdquo; to practicing any musical instrument other than the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/02/22/flute-progress-still-hanging-in-there&#34;&gt;modern flute&lt;/a&gt;. I no longer practice the recorder, and have had to say &amp;ldquo;No&amp;rdquo; to the Friday evening gatherings that last year I was rather enjoying, and had led to my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/05/busy-evening-performing-at-phipps-followed-by-rehearsal-for-another-gig/&#34;&gt;performing at Phipps Conservatory&lt;/a&gt;. I told the recorder gang that I was going to return to recorder after my April 15 orchestra concert. This is an example of &amp;ldquo;No&amp;rdquo; meaning not &amp;ldquo;never again&amp;rdquo; but simply &amp;ldquo;not now&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, just today, Abby said the woman who &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/24/roaring-like-a-lion-on-a-saturday-morning/&#34;&gt;lent us an accordion&lt;/a&gt; for me to try out in case I wanted to buy it and take accordion needed to know whether we were buying it. Since I have barely touched accordion all these months, and will not be doing so for probably another half year at least, I said &amp;ldquo;No&amp;rdquo;, I am not prepared to buy it now. In the past I have bought stuff to use &amp;ldquo;sometime&amp;rdquo;, and this has only caused &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/19/really-taking-up-the-challenge-of-minimalism/&#34;&gt;clutter&lt;/a&gt;. (Yes, we are still incrementally decluttering, getting rid of stuff we don&amp;rsquo;t use. Just yesterday, I decided to throw away the remainder of my trophy and medal collections that no longer mean anything, except that I am still saving one trophy, from my winning the &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburghcc.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Chess Club&lt;/a&gt; Championship some years ago; I&amp;rsquo;m thinking of giving it back to the club so that they can remove my name plate and reuse it.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;dancing&#34;&gt;Dancing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One big change since last year is that Abby and I have gotten back into dancing again. Saying &amp;ldquo;Yes&amp;rdquo; to dancing has, of course, meant saying &amp;ldquo;No&amp;rdquo; to other things. For example, this year I have approximately halved my former blog output. I also reduced my Web reading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;meditation&#34;&gt;Meditation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, I didn&amp;rsquo;t have a daily meditation practice. &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/02/02/2-new-daily-habits-of-mine-in-a-distracting-world/&#34;&gt;Now I do&lt;/a&gt;. Just ten minutes a day in the morning, but it makes a difference. Saying &amp;ldquo;Yes&amp;rdquo; to meditation meant saying &amp;ldquo;No&amp;rdquo; to obsessively checking email and the like upon getting out of bed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;computer-usage-and-reading-books&#34;&gt;Computer usage and reading books&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A final tradeoff to mention is that my new habit of getting off the computer earlier in the evening, well before sleeping, has led me to do more paper book reading. Saying &amp;ldquo;Yes&amp;rdquo; to reading more books has been a good thing. I plan to start writing up reviews of the books I&amp;rsquo;ve been reading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;No&amp;rdquo; doesn&amp;rsquo;t just mean deprivation. It means making room for &amp;ldquo;Yes&amp;rdquo; too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What have you happily said &amp;ldquo;No&amp;rdquo; to that you wanted to do this year but decided not to do?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2014-01-16&#34;&gt;(Update of 2014-01-16)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ironically, I was just getting going with saying too much Yes even just as I was saying No, as I ended up taking two Coursera courses starting in late February: &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/04/13/free-course-review-software-engineering-for-software-as-a-service-part-i-from-coursera/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Software Engineering for Software as a Service (Part I)&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/06/16/review-of-coursera-course-model-thinking/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Model Thinking&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. As a result, I was really swamped from late February to June. I didn&amp;rsquo;t even have time to finish up reviews of the courses once I completed them, and only tried to fill in the gaps almost two years later!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The temptation after saying No is to take on new Yes. In retrospect, I should have been more careful.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Starting a mini Digital Sabbath</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/11/12/starting-a-mini-digital-sabbath/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Nov 2011 09:52:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/11/12/starting-a-mini-digital-sabbath/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been writing at least one blog post a day now for 42 days. I had started the blog bent on making it a real habit to maintain, and felt that forcing myself to write and upload every single day was necessary to keep the momentum going. I&amp;rsquo;m sure I was right, but now that I am confident in my self-discipline to maintain regularity, I am going to relax the arbitrary rule I set for myself, and start observing a mini Digital Sabbath in which I take a day off every week from blogging. I&amp;rsquo;m starting today (considering this little note as equivalent to taking a break).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you observe or considered observing your own Digital Sabbath in this busy, &lt;sup&gt;24&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;7&lt;/sub&gt; world?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Against just putting in the time</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/11/04/against-just-putting-in-the-time/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Nov 2011 21:37:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/11/04/against-just-putting-in-the-time/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently I saw a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.scottberkun.com/blog/2011/let-time-work-for-you/&#34;&gt;blog post by Scott Berkun&lt;/a&gt; that made me profoundly sad. He described not liking running on a treadmill but doing it anyway and watching the clock, and he turned around and praised this attitude.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I totally disagree with this with every fiber of my being, and here&amp;rsquo;s why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;for-deliberate-practice&#34;&gt;For &lt;em&gt;deliberate practice&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, I have to emphasize that I totally believe in putting in the time to achieve excellence and mastery of anything. The recently popularized phrase &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Practice_%28learning_method%29#Deliberate_practice&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;deliberate practice&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; describes genuine practice (as opposed to just putting in the time) that aims at expert performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I try to apply this to every aspect of my life, whether when &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/programming/&#34;&gt;programming&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/running/&#34;&gt;running&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/recorder/&#34;&gt;playing music&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/strength-training/&#34;&gt;strength training&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/cooking/&#34;&gt;cooking&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/zen/&#34;&gt;meditating&lt;/a&gt;, or any other of the dozens of activities or chores that come up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So my disagreement with &amp;ldquo;just putting in the time&amp;rdquo; is not a disagreement with the need for hard work and even drudgery. There is no shortcut to expertise and achievement. Insofar as Scott Berkun tries to make this point, I agree with him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;mindless-versus-mindful&#34;&gt;Mindless versus mindful&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;mindless&#34;&gt;Mindless&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, Scott describes an attitude toward running on the treadmill that is &amp;ldquo;mindless&amp;rdquo; rather than &amp;ldquo;mindful&amp;rdquo;. He writes, &amp;ldquo;As long as I didn’t think much at all, I’d achieve my goal.&amp;rdquo; (His goals was running four miles.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I call this &amp;ldquo;mindless&amp;rdquo; because it implies zoning out and basically opting out of life while waiting for something to happen, like a bell going off that says &amp;ldquo;class is over!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Think about it. Think about a time in a classroom in elementary school or high school or college, or a conference room at work, where you didn&amp;rsquo;t want to be there, hated being there, watched the clock, and just thought to yourself, &amp;ldquo;As long as I don&amp;rsquo;t think much at all, I&amp;rsquo;ll achieve my goal (of surviving until the bell rings and you get to leave).&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did you enjoy this &amp;ldquo;being there&amp;rdquo;? Did you learn something? Or did you feel that you wasted your life?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After being done, did you feel proud of having achieved your goal of just plain sticking it out? Or did you feel frustrated or embarrassed or resentful?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am more worried about the high school student who stuck it out and felt proud of it than of the student who maybe endured the experience but saw it for what it really was: soul-sucking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no guarantee that the student who simply sticks it out through school has actually learned anything and graduates stronger in mind or body or spirit. In fact, sometimes sticking it out is so deadening that it would have been better to leave.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But although sometimes the student who didn&amp;rsquo;t stick it out, and maybe skipped class or dropped out, did the right thing, there is a third path: &lt;em&gt;mindfulness&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;mindful&#34;&gt;Mindful&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many definitions of &amp;ldquo;mindfulness&amp;rdquo;. The problem is that many people have used it independently. There is the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mindfulness&#34;&gt;mindfulness from Buddhism&lt;/a&gt;, and notions in Western &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mindfulness_(psychology)&#34;&gt;psychology&lt;/a&gt;, sometimes borrowed from Buddhism. Ellen Langer has written &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ellenlanger.com/books/3/mindfulness&#34;&gt;books&lt;/a&gt; on what she calls &amp;ldquo;mindfulness&amp;rdquo;, for example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll just use the term loosely to refer to a basic attitude of being attuned to what you&amp;rsquo;re doing, keeping your mind open and attentive, rather than dissociating, or blocking thoughts or emotions, or zoning out as though sleepwalking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;classroom-example&#34;&gt;Classroom example&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some examples of how one could be mindful as a bored student in a class.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The student could at least, while putting in the time, do something with that time, such as doodle, write poetry, count the number of times the teacher said &amp;ldquo;umm&amp;rdquo;. Just doing something at all is better than doing nothing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A step up: the student could try to pick up on little aspects of the class that actually interest him, and attend to those. Who knows, one thing could lead to another, and the class material eventually could actually becoming truly fascinating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The student could realize that the two strategies above will not work so well, and decide to transfer to a different class, either in the same subject but with a teacher who is a better match in whatever way, or into a different subject entirely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;other-scenarios&#34;&gt;Other scenarios&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I bring my lunch in to work, every afternoon there I wash my bowl, fork, empty Pyrex containers, etc. Once upon a time in my life, I dreaded washing dishes. I tried doing things like listening to music in order to take my mind off the unpleasantness. But then I discovered the power of mindfulness. It&amp;rsquo;s actually quite interesting washing dishes. The sensations of warm water, detergent. Stubborn spots on dishes, residual oiliness, slipperiness, wiping the curve of a spoon or the handle of a knife: everything is really an amazing sensory experience. Now when I wash dishes, I don&amp;rsquo;t listen to music or think about my schedule. During those minutes, I am simply washing dishes, as though that were my whole universe. It&amp;rsquo;s different every time. It&amp;rsquo;s not the same boring experience repeated mindlessly where all I&amp;rsquo;m thinking of is, &amp;ldquo;I hate this but it has to get done.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;applications-to-the-treadmill-situation&#34;&gt;Applications to the treadmill situation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, let&amp;rsquo;s discuss Scott&amp;rsquo;s treadmill situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past, I have sometimes run on treadmills when winter weather discouraged me from running outside (of course, I do have suitable winter running gear, and am not a stranger to coming home from a run with icicles on my balaclava). But, like many people, I found the experience soul-sucking. In the end, I simply chose to walk away, but there were some strategies I used to improve the experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One was to simply vary the workout, by doing intervals or ladders of pace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another was to focus on my form and my body sensations in general. Are my shoulders relaxed? Am I overstriding? Are my hips tight? Is my left leg doing something funny so that my knee hurts?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, I used a more radical solution to my treadmill dislike: I stopped using the treadmill. Either I run outside or I don&amp;rsquo;t run at all. This was my choice. It is not necessarily the best choice for everyone. There are other things I can do besides run. I tend to favor dance workouts when indoors, and strength training with body weight and balance balls and medicine balls. I&amp;rsquo;m not a running addict or professional who needs to run all the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;achieving-a-limited-goal-so-what&#34;&gt;Achieving a limited goal: so what?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is the irony: I don&amp;rsquo;t believe that the time I spent on the treadmill was that useful. I may have put in the miles, but so what?  To some extent it may have kept me conditioned, but now I&amp;rsquo;m inclined to believe that mindless exercise is far less beneficial than mindful exercise, and so I would rather not exercise than do mindless exercise. The body is not just a mechanical machine that improves because it goes through the motions. It is much more than that. By treating our bodies as impersonal machines, we violate our sacred temples. We create imbalances and injuries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And running on a treadmill did not prepare me very well for real running. It&amp;rsquo;s nothing like real running where you are pushing off the stationary ground, into wind resistance, getting from one place to another and seeing the world move past you. Foot landing patterns are different when running on a treadmill than running on the track or the road or the rocky trail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I would ask any treadmill runner: what is your &lt;em&gt;ultimate goal&lt;/em&gt;, rather than the limited goal of going a certain number of miles in your workout, or watching the (misleading) calorie burning counter go up to a certain number? Is your time on the treadmill actually contributing maximally to your ultimate goal, or is it a deceptive tangent that benefits you less than you think?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion-avoid-the-fruits-of-mindlessness&#34;&gt;Conclusion: avoid the fruits of mindlessness&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scott says, &amp;ldquo;Studying for a college degree, practicing the piano, going for a daily run, these are all ways to let time work on our behalf, if we just give in.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But how many students just go through the motions, &amp;ldquo;study&amp;rdquo;, graduate from college, and find themselves not really having the applicable skills to do something useful?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How many people &amp;ldquo;practice&amp;rdquo; a musical instrument and are frustrated that after ten years, they are still nowhere as good as some friend who took only a month to get as good?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How many people do their daily run for ten years but again, are frustrated that they don&amp;rsquo;t seem to be running any faster at local 5K races?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not suggesting that everyone should try to be the best at everything; there is not enough time or energy or talent for that. But, I know that a lot of people mindlessly put in time at something and expect a lot more to come from it that don&amp;rsquo;t. And some end up resentful of others who achieve more (usually using words like &amp;ldquo;luck&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;talent&amp;rdquo;) or feeling like they got cheated of what they &amp;ldquo;deserved&amp;rdquo; from having put in so much drudgery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m suggesting that being more aware, rather than less aware, while doing something, is something we can all do, to improve not only our enjoyment of the process, but also the increased productivity and achievement and health that comes from being in tune with our mind/body.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is time money?</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/11/01/is-time-money/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Nov 2011 21:52:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/11/01/is-time-money/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently I came across a blog post claiming that &lt;a href=&#34;http://thenonconsumeradvocate.com/2011/10/time-is-not-money/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;time is not money&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. Reading it, and the many comments that supported the author&amp;rsquo;s thesis, I felt oddly concerned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not here to refute &amp;ldquo;time is not money&amp;rdquo;, but to briefly explain my concern.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;life&#34;&gt;Life&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s start with life itself, rather than time or money. We are born. We live, by making sure our fundamental needs are met: eating, drinking, maintaining health, recovering from illnesses and accidents, etc. Beyond providing for our fundamental needs, we may do all kinds of other activities also, ranging from more sophisticated entertainment, socializing, trying to achieve fame, etc. At some point, we die.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;time&#34;&gt;Time&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because we die, time is important, since we want to live and enjoy it and our time is limited. All things being equal, we would rather have more of life rather than less of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;money&#34;&gt;Money&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unless we are hunter-gatherers who have access to free food, etc., we need some kind of money, as a store of value and a means of exchange for what we need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;time-is-money&#34;&gt;Time is money&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In modern industrial society, much of what we depend on and assume as a basic need (such as a non-primitive, legal, stable place to live) can only be obtained through money. We obtain that money by trading time for it, by using our time to be productive to society and obtain money in return. Hence, &amp;ldquo;time is money&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;money-is-time&#34;&gt;Money is time&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The relation between time and money is symmetry. Time is money, and money is time. The entire history of the modern industrialized world has been to enable conversion of money to time. Division of labor, so that we don&amp;rsquo;t have to spend our lives making all our own clothing and growing all our own food, has increased efficiency. Labor-saving technologies such as swords, knives, pencils, microwaves, and dishwashers save us time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;time-is-money-is-time&#34;&gt;Time is money is time&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So there is a cycle in our lives in which we have time, some of which we spend &amp;ldquo;employed&amp;rdquo; doing &amp;ldquo;work&amp;rdquo;, convert it into money, and then spend some of that money to buy us more time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are, of course, opportunities to use time or money elsewhere than in that cycle. We may have extra time that we can choose to spend in some other way than converting it directly to money. We can spend the extra time hanging out with family and friends, watching a movie, and doing all kinds of things we enjoy; in other words, use the extra time to &lt;em&gt;live&lt;/em&gt;. The author of the blog post seems to be arguing that she enjoys doing all those things, and therefore time is not money. It is this last leap that does not make sense to me. Nobody ever said that all time must be converted to money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, some break the cycle by not converting money back to time, but converting it into possessions instead. Unfortunately, at some point one has to remember that &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.library.csi.cuny.edu/dept/history/lavender/cherries.html&#34;&gt;you can&amp;rsquo;t take your dough when you go, go, go&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;for-some-time-really-is-money&#34;&gt;For some, time really is money&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason I am disturbed by the attack on &amp;ldquo;time is money&amp;rdquo; is that a lot of people have very little money, and the best way for them to get more, in order to be able to live better and create a virtuous cycle in which they can generate more time, is precisely to convert as much of their time as possible into money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Time is money&amp;rdquo; is a powerful message that immigrants to our nation have applied again and again to start out starving and end up feeding themselves and their families. The single mother who spends a large amount of her time working multiple jobs so that she can feed her children and proudly see them be the first in the family to graduate from college is living &amp;ldquo;time is money&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, I wonder if the attack on &amp;ldquo;time is money&amp;rdquo; is a perspective resulting from having enough money and therefore not needing to generate more. That is a state of living that is obviously pleasant, and congratulations to all who have put in enough time that they have all the money they need and can scale back. I&amp;rsquo;m actually quite sympathetic to the &amp;ldquo;minimalist&amp;rdquo; view of life and money: know how much money you need, and spend the extra on time. I just don&amp;rsquo;t think the minimalist message is useful, yet, to the unemployed single mother without health insurance, who will have very little time on this earth if she doesn&amp;rsquo;t convert the time she has to money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although I support minimalism, I don&amp;rsquo;t think it is in conflict with &amp;ldquo;time is money&amp;rdquo;, or equivalently, &amp;ldquo;money is time&amp;rdquo;. I see minimalism as a way to maximize one&amp;rsquo;s own life choices, rather than a way to be angry at other people for making different ones. I fear that blogs such as the &lt;a href=&#34;http://thenonconsumeradvocate.com/&#34;&gt;Non-Consumer Advocate&lt;/a&gt; may be more of a preaching-to-the-choir forum than a way to help non-minimalists evaluate different ways of living. I sense anger and contempt in that blog.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Disagreement on the use of time?</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/10/18/disagreement-on-the-use-of-time/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Oct 2011 19:14:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/10/18/disagreement-on-the-use-of-time/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On Sunday, I went to the monthly meeting of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.andrew.cmu.edu/user/lukas/pcars/Welcome.html&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh chapter&lt;/a&gt; of the American Recorder Society. I stopped by the room where beginner lessons were being held. I don&amp;rsquo;t go to those lessons any more, because I would say I&amp;rsquo;m an intermediate recorder player now. Fred, our director, was working with two women on soprano recorder. One of them was Rhonda, who had actually joined the local group at exactly the same time as me, back in March. I hadn&amp;rsquo;t seen her in a while and asked where she&amp;rsquo;d been. She said she had been playing French horn in the summer, so was getting back to recorder now. She happened to joke to the other woman, an older woman, that I was really serious and had been practicing an hour every day since starting out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To my surprise, the other woman (whom I don&amp;rsquo;t remember ever having met before) immediately launched into some remarks I found snarky. She said, &amp;ldquo;Well, that&amp;rsquo;s probably an hour he&amp;rsquo;s not washing dishes.&amp;rdquo; I paused in shock, and then she continued, &amp;ldquo;Or an hour he&amp;rsquo;s not taking out the trash.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was not quite sure how to respond.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-response&#34;&gt;My response&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously, this could have been an opportunity for me to use &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/11/communicating-through-dialogue/&#34;&gt;dialogue&lt;/a&gt; and try to understand why she said what she said, and what she really meant by her words that I found disparaging. In fact, thanks to my raised awareness from learning about dialogue just recently, at least I did not get angry or lose my temper. But I decided at the time that I was just passing by and was not interested in going off on a tangent, since I was heading back to the other room to set up my instruments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I simply replied calmly that actually, the hour of my time that went to recorder practice came out of time I used to spend on various forms of entertainment. I said that I don&amp;rsquo;t watch any TV and I don&amp;rsquo;t watch any movies. She didn&amp;rsquo;t respond to that. For all I know, she might be one of the average Americans who watch &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.csun.edu/science/health/docs/tv&amp;amp;health.html&#34;&gt;4 hours of TV a day&lt;/a&gt;, and perhaps I unintentionally offended her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Disclaimer: I am not one of those snobs who summarily look down on people who watch TV. I used to watch a lot of TV. In fact, I cannot imagine what my life would be today without having had access to TV, which expanded my emotional and intellectual world. But that was then; now, I simply make different choices with my time.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I left the room and didn&amp;rsquo;t see her again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I&amp;rsquo;m still curious about why she seemed annoyed that I spent an hour a day practicing music, as though I&amp;rsquo;m not getting chores done. I won&amp;rsquo;t speculate about why, since the only right way to satisfy my curiosity would be to ask her myself, and I passed up the opportunity to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My brief response to her was meant to convey a simple message: time management is important for all of us with our busy lives, but I&amp;rsquo;ve made certain choices, sacrificing some activities in order to gain others. The decisions are often quite difficult, because I have a &lt;em&gt;huge&lt;/em&gt; number of interests, and therefore have to sacrifice the majority of them in order to focus on the fewer that I have decided are most worthwhile to pursue. A breadth-first traversal of all possible life activities would result in completing nothing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;trading-passive-for-active&#34;&gt;Trading passive for active&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of my choices involve trading passive experiences for active experiences. Here are some examples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;music&#34;&gt;Music&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an earlier blog post, I already mentioned why &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/02/i-love-music-but-rarely-listen-to-it-now/&#34;&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t listen to music much&lt;/a&gt; any more, because of time constraints. In effect, I traded listening to music for playing music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;sports&#34;&gt;Sports&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of watching sports, I engage in my own competitive physical activity, to become the athlete instead of the spectator. I enjoy &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/races/&#34;&gt;running races&lt;/a&gt;. I am hardly super fast; at my fastest, I did periodically win age group medals and trophies, but only because competition happened not to be very tough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;exercise&#34;&gt;Exercise&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I run considerably less than I used to. One reason is that once upon a time, I got into a competitive mode, trying to see how fast I could race, and now I am no longer in that mode. It takes too much time and energy. Another reason is that I decided, based on personal experience and learning from the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paleolithic_lifestyle&#34;&gt;paleo/primal&lt;/a&gt; movement, that too much distance running isn&amp;rsquo;t actually all that great for my overall balanced health.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I traded distance training time for &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/24/roaring-like-a-lion-on-a-saturday-morning/&#34;&gt;yoga&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/17/the-joys-of-convict-conditioning-bodyweight-exercising/&#34;&gt;strength training&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I no longer run any more than every other day on average.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;reading&#34;&gt;Reading&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve always read a lot. I still do, using not only the vast web, but also the old-fashioned &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/30/free-to-the-people-since-1895/&#34;&gt;local library&lt;/a&gt;. (Pittsburghers, please &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ourlibraryourfuture.org/&#34;&gt;vote on November 8&lt;/a&gt;!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, at some point I had to make peace with the fact that I could not read everything I might be interested in reading. Abby and I worked on selling or donating over a thousand (!!) books I owned but were just taking up space. It was very difficult parting with them, since one of my childhood dreams had been to build up a large personal library, but reason prevailed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still encounter too much reading material, thanks to the web. I have tried to limit it by using Google Reader exclusively to access information, and never aimlessly loading up web sites, but I have to confess it is still hard to be selective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, now I am writing for my blog, so I am trading reading time for writing time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;computer-programming-languages&#34;&gt;Computer programming languages&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used to be a big computer language hobbyist. I enjoyed learning and playing with dozens of programming languages: if a language exists, I&amp;rsquo;ve probably at least seen sample code and written some sample code for it at some point. I was even obsessed enough with the concept of designing good programming languages that for a while I was enrolled in the Ph.D. program in computer science at CMU, specializing in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~fox/languages.html&#34;&gt;programming language theory&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then as a practicing software developer, I eventually realized that to &lt;em&gt;get stuff done&lt;/em&gt;, I needed to scale back on my hobby. Therefore, for example, as I mentioned in my post about &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/16/pittsburgh-software-developer-communities/&#34;&gt;local software developer groups&lt;/a&gt;, I have ceased following Python. Also, I have deliberately not even looked at new languages such as &lt;a href=&#34;http://fantom.org/&#34;&gt;Fantom&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://gosu-lang.org/&#34;&gt;Gosu&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://confluence.jetbrains.net/display/Kotlin/Welcome&#34;&gt;Kotlin&lt;/a&gt;. (On the other hand, I am committed to learning and using &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.scala-lang.org/&#34;&gt;Scala&lt;/a&gt; more, because the path from Java already exists.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I took only a quick look at Google&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dartlang.org/&#34;&gt;Dart&lt;/a&gt; after the big hype, and am not pursuing it further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trade-off: trading time spent playing with new languages for time spent mastering and implementing programs with old languages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;completely-abandoning-an-activity&#34;&gt;Completely abandoning an activity&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, I have freed up time by completely abandoning an activity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;dancing-part-one&#34;&gt;Dancing (part one)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once upon a time, I did a lot of ballroom dancing. I even trained seriously and entered competitions through the &lt;a href=&#34;http://cmubdc.org/&#34;&gt;CMU ballroom dance club&lt;/a&gt;. I was dancing something like 20 hours a week (note: this was when I was not doing any reading or music or chess, as my trade-off). I quit competitive ballroom dancing eventually, and then even social ballroom dancing. I had also taken up swing and tango, and salsa more seriously, but then quit those too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically, my trade-off was that I completely quit dancing and took up chess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;chess&#34;&gt;Chess&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past, chess was the most time-consuming hobby in my life. A couple of years ago, I was bent on finally achieving a national &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chess_master&#34;&gt;Master&lt;/a&gt; title. I studied hard, improved my game, played a lot. I won the &lt;a href=&#34;http://pscfchess.org/results/06040808.htm&#34;&gt;2006 Pennsylvania Game/29 Championship&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&#34;http://pscfchess.org/results/06101414.htm&#34;&gt;2006 Pennsylvania Action Chess Championship&lt;/a&gt;; I was on the verge of making Master by planning to win the &lt;a href=&#34;http://pscfchess.org/results/07071414.htm&#34;&gt;2007 Pennsylvania Action Chess Championship&lt;/a&gt; when I utterly &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Choke_(sports)&#34;&gt;choked&lt;/a&gt; and blew it by losing the last two games. I never really recovered from that. My life was changing at the time, having just starting to date Abby, and I stopped playing after a while, then after being married, I started playing again, but my heart was not in it, and I played terribly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I quit chess in February 2011. In effect, I traded chess for starting to play recorder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have not played any chess since February. I don&amp;rsquo;t really regret it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;update-of-2013-01-23&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-01-23)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, in the first half of 2012, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/02/07/on-playing-my-first-games-of-chess-in-a-year/&#34;&gt;some&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/05/31/some-pretty-attacking-chess-at-a-party-last-weekend/&#34;&gt;casual&lt;/a&gt; contact with chess led me to feel like playing again, and in August I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/08/21/returning-to-chess/&#34;&gt;decided to start playing in tournaments again&lt;/a&gt; and am right now in the middle of a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/16/pittsburgh-chess-club-championship-2013-round-1-the-art-of-swindling/&#34;&gt;six-week tournament&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;ve gone back to the chess with clear constraints on how much time and energy I spend on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;update-of-2015-12-21&#34;&gt;(Update of 2015-12-21)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Four years later, I made a focused push, temporarily putting many
things aside in my life, in the fall of 2015 to &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2016/01/22/on-finally-achieving-the-us-national-master-chess-title-at-age-45-part-1&#34;&gt;achieve my US Chess
National Master title&lt;/a&gt;, and finally made it, a dream come true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, I have been teaching private lessons since 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;dancing-part-two&#34;&gt;Dancing (part two)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I accidentally first met Abby when I returned to salsa dancing while still playing chess. Eventually, we started dating, and we were going dancing frequently, but eventually we both completely quit salsa dancing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trade-off was that we got into hiking and kayaking together, which was more fulfilling than our going to dances together and my wanting to dance with a lot of women but her only wanting to dance with me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I consciously traded dancing for a relationship and marriage!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;update-of-2013-01-23-1&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-01-23)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, Abby and I accidentally ended up doing some dancing together again, including discovering &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/01/23/discovering-french-traditional-dance-in-pittsburgh/&#34;&gt;French dancing&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/31/my-first-sampling-of-english-country-dance-and-contra-dance/&#34;&gt;English country and contra dancing&lt;/a&gt;. We don&amp;rsquo;t do it regularly, but it&amp;rsquo;s been great doing it on occasion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, for 2013, we decided that we should dance together a little bit every day, just for ourselves, simply to appreciate that we can!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;marriage&#34;&gt;Marriage&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Married life is a lot of trade-offs.  It&amp;rsquo;s nothing resembling single life or dating life!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Time is precious. We all have to make trade-offs. I&amp;rsquo;ve explored some ways in which I made certain trade-offs at certain points in my life. In your own life, do you periodically double-check what your priorities are, when you feel &amp;ldquo;too busy&amp;rdquo; for something you think you value?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I Love Music but Rarely Listen to It Now</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/10/02/i-love-music-but-rarely-listen-to-it-now/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Oct 2011 17:15:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/10/02/i-love-music-but-rarely-listen-to-it-now/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Yesterday there was a concert, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.post-gazette.com/pg/11272/1178247-388.stm&#34;&gt;much-anticipated&lt;/a&gt;, part of the current season of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rbsp.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Renaissance &amp;amp; Baroque&lt;/a&gt;, that I didn&amp;rsquo;t attend. I felt slightly sad because I&amp;rsquo;m sure it was interesting, and also because fellow members of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.andrew.cmu.edu/user/lukas/pcars/Welcome.html&#34;&gt;local chapter&lt;/a&gt; of the American Recorder Society had been talking about going and urging me to come along.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.post-gazette.com/pg/images/201109/renbar0929_juilliard_baroqu_330.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Juilliard Baroque Ensemble&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This was not the only concert in the past couple of years that I have chosen not to attend. So why have I chosen to skip these opportunities?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once upon a time I listened to a lot of music. I listened to the radio, I bought a lot of LPs, cassette tapes, and finally, CDs. I went to concerts. It&amp;rsquo;s not as though I have completely lost interest in listening to music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What happened was simply that I ran out of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Time is &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.my168hours.com/&#34;&gt;limited to 168 hours a week&lt;/a&gt;. Therefore, the phrase &amp;ldquo;I don&amp;rsquo;t have time for X&amp;rdquo; is usually a euphemism for, &amp;ldquo;I do have time for Y and Z, but not for X&amp;rdquo;. Example translations of &amp;ldquo;don&amp;rsquo;t have time&amp;rdquo; language that people use:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;dl&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I don&#39;t have time to exercise.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;I chose to spend an hour watching sports on TV rather than playing a sport myself.&lt;/dd&gt;

  &lt;dt&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I don&#39;t have time to talk with my children.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;I do have time to work crazy hours at the office and play golf with my boss in order to make a lot of money.&lt;/dd&gt;

  &lt;dt&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I don&#39;t have time to cook.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;I don&#39;t like to cook or clean up, and therefore instead of whipping up a 15-minute stir-fry, I would rather commute to a restaurant, wait, order, wait, eat, wait, pay, wait, and return home hours later.&lt;/dd&gt;

  &lt;dt&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I don&#39;t have time to get good at salsa dancing.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;I have time to spend hours going to clubs to dance, and prefer to spend vast amounts of time being social and having fun than perfecting my basic technique.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;scarcity-and-decision-making&#34;&gt;Scarcity and decision making&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, time management is all a matter of &lt;em&gt;priorities&lt;/em&gt;. Time is a scarce resource. We &lt;em&gt;choose&lt;/em&gt; how to work within constraints of scarcity. (Note that some people like to make a lot of judgments about how we &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; be spending our time, but that is not the topic at hand; time management is.) In the end, I make my choices, and you make your choices. And we can and do change our choices over our lifetime, based on either our preferences or information about what is required to achieve various goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier in life, I was more of a spectator of life than I am now. I watched a lot of TV and movies, listened to a lot of music, went to concerts and lectures. It just happens that now, I prefer to be more &lt;em&gt;active&lt;/em&gt;. Not that listening to music is necessarily &lt;em&gt;passive&lt;/em&gt;: you can&amp;rsquo;t call it passive that I collected probably two dozen recordings of my favorite symphony, Beethoven&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Symphony_No._3_(Beethoven)&#34;&gt;Eroica&lt;/a&gt;, listened to them repeatedly, compared them, hummed along to them (I was not quite as obsessive as &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.grunin.com/eroica/&#34;&gt;Eric Grunin&lt;/a&gt;, however). But eventually I made a decision to more or less stop listening when I could be playing, and also to seek out what is new to me rather than continue with the old.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last night, instead of sitting in a concert hall listening to music, I stayed home, practiced &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/recorder/&#34;&gt;recorder&lt;/a&gt;, started reading some &lt;a href=&#34;blog/2011/09/30/free-to-the-people-since-1895/&#34;&gt;library books&lt;/a&gt;, and spent time with Abby. This is what I preferred to do with my evening hours yesterday instead of attending a concert. Life is good when you know your priorities, make your choices, act accordingly, and don&amp;rsquo;t go around in &lt;a href=&#34;http://psychcentral.com/blog/archives/2011/04/14/fomo-addiction-the-fear-of-missing-out/&#34;&gt;fear of missing out&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;postscript&#34;&gt;Postscript&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, now and then I still watch a movie or pull out a CD or attend a concert, and enjoy it. Just not so often.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And since the Eroica symphony is a permanent and profound part of my psyche, sometimes I find myself humming it to myself from memory. This tends to happen when it&amp;rsquo;s a nice sunny day and I&amp;rsquo;m on a run in the woods and feeling in a &amp;ldquo;heroic&amp;rdquo; mood. The music then fits perfectly because I will then run at a decent stride rate of &lt;a href=&#34;http://runningtimes.com/Article.aspx?ArticleID=11419&#34;&gt;180 steps per minute&lt;/a&gt;, corresponding exactly to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.marathonguide.com/training/coachmindy/everybreath.cfm&#34;&gt;breathing in a 3-3 rhythm&lt;/a&gt; and following Beethoven&amp;rsquo;s infamous (but I believe appropriate) metronome marking of 60 for the first movement! Great running music, 15 minutes of genius.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/variations/scores/adh1166/large/sco10001.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Beethoven&amp;#39;s Eroica, first page&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>