<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Pittsburgh Chess League on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/pittsburgh-chess-league/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Pittsburgh Chess League on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/pittsburgh-chess-league/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Saying No: on not playing in the Pittsburgh Chess League this season for the CMU Tartans</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/09/15/saying-no-on-not-playing-in-the-pittsburgh-chess-league-this-season-for-the-cmu-tartans/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Sep 2013 00:14:55 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/09/15/saying-no-on-not-playing-in-the-pittsburgh-chess-league-this-season-for-the-cmu-tartans/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://twitchfilm.com/assets/2011/07/120889.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Chess&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Later today, the first round of the 2013-14 season of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pitt.edu/~schach/ChessPA/ChessLeague/wpapcl.htm&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Chess League&lt;/a&gt; will start, and I will not be there to play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;last-season&#34;&gt;Last season&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last season, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/04/29/celebrating-the-victory-of-the-cmu-tartans-in-the-2012-13-pittsburgh-chess-league-season/&#34;&gt;I played in the Pittsburgh Chess League as a member of the CMU Tartans and we won&lt;/a&gt;. As I mentioned, out of the six rounds our team played in (one round was a bye for each team), I ended up playing only in the first two of those rounds, the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/10/14/pittsburgh-chess-league-round-2-natural-moves-are-often-bad/&#34;&gt;October&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/11/11/pittsburgh-chess-league-round-3-back-to-chess-after-a-month-off/&#34;&gt;November&lt;/a&gt;. After that, I simply kept running into trouble:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;having &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/02/oblivion-obsession-time-to-start-playing-melodica/&#34;&gt;schedule conflicts&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/0130/why-and-how-i-am-going-to-run-the-2013-pittsburgh-marathon&#34;&gt;getting sick&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/02/20/pittsburgh-chess-club-championship-2013-round-6-winning-as-black-like-a-madman/&#34;&gt;having to take care of Abby after an accident&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/04/06/comeback-from-pittsburgh-marathon-overtraining/&#34;&gt;being exhausted from marathon training&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One way or another, I kept on not being up to the prospect of spending up to &lt;em&gt;five hours&lt;/em&gt; on a single chess game on a Sunday afternoon from 2 PM to 7 PM. Repeatedly, when asked whether I could play in an upcoming round, I felt guilty about saying that I would play only in case of an emergency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;saying-no&#34;&gt;Saying &amp;ldquo;No&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This fall, I made the tough decision to leave the Pittsburgh Chess League, telling CMU Tartans team captain Jeff some weeks ago that I preferred not to be on the roster this year at all, even as an alternate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve had a lifelong difficulty with saying &amp;ldquo;No&amp;rdquo;, not only &lt;a href=&#34;http://zenhabits.net/say-no/&#34;&gt;to others&lt;/a&gt; but also to myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heck, I even wrote a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/02/23/saying-no-in-order-to-say-yes/&#34;&gt;blog post well over two years ago about saying &amp;ldquo;No&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, but I don&amp;rsquo;t also optimally apply to myself my own advice!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve had a habit of taking on all kinds of obligations or activities that stretched myself thin, resulting in subpar performance and dependability, and meanwhile, anxiety, guilt, and shame. People deserve better than this from me. I deserve better than this from me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;chess&#34;&gt;Chess&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love chess, but it can be very time and energy-consuming, so I have to be careful about how much time I spend on it at all. This year, it turns out that I completely stopped playing chess in February, and &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/09/12/my-first-post-on-the-chess-improver-the-value-of-thematic-complete-games-against-a-weaker-opponent/&#34;&gt;just came back now in September, along with becoming a new contributor to the Chess Improver blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually looking at my calendar and my overall plans for the next half year, I decided that if I cannot be a dependable team member for the CMU Tartans (in terms of regularly showing up to play for the team as well as playing well for the team), then it is better not to be on the team at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, I also decided that after the current Pittsburgh Chess Club Tuesday night tournament concludes in October (I just finished the first two of six rounds in the 15th Fred Sorensen Memorial), I will, unlike last year, &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; continue on in the following Tuesday night tournament (November-December), because based on how my schedule went in the past two years, those two months are very busy for me, and the last two years I barely stumbled to winter break alive, and performed terribly in the tournament last year, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/11/round-5-of-pittsburgh-chess-club-tournament-psychology-of-losing-another-won-game/&#34;&gt;ridiculously losing two won games&lt;/a&gt;, and also performed suboptimally in other projects I was doing. I&amp;rsquo;m not going to let that happen this year. It is not only chess I am cutting out for November-December, but most likely some musical activities as well (yet to be finalized).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was better for the CMU Tartans to find a reliable replacement for me than for me to be undependable for them. Luka has left town, and I have dropped out, but the team has managed to get Joe Mucerino on board, so I hope all will go well for the team in the new season of the Pittsburgh Chess League with the reduced number of members.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saying &amp;ldquo;No&amp;rdquo; to others and to myself is very difficult. I enjoy new projects and challenges. But if doing too much means not doing everything optimally well, then what&amp;rsquo;s the point? So I&amp;rsquo;ve taken a big step toward reclaiming my sanity by choosing not to be a part of the Pittsburgh Chess League this year.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Celebrating the victory of the CMU Tartans in the 2012-13 Pittsburgh Chess League season</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/04/29/celebrating-the-victory-of-the-cmu-tartans-in-the-2012-13-pittsburgh-chess-league-season/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Apr 2013 23:36:01 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/04/29/celebrating-the-victory-of-the-cmu-tartans-in-the-2012-13-pittsburgh-chess-league-season/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;The CMU Tartans won the 2012-13 &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pitt.edu/~schach/ChessPA/ChessLeague/wpapcl.htm&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Chess League&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pitt.edu/~schach/ChessPA/ChessLeague/pcli.htm&#34;&gt;division I&lt;/a&gt;)!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Out of 6 matches (there were 7 rounds with a bye round for each team), we won the first 5 matches, losing only the final match.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We celebrated by having dinner at Curry on Murray in Squirrel Hill, organized by our team captain, Jeff. Our team had 8 members, 6 of whom were able to make it to the dinner (Ruan and Ed were unable to attend).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;meet-the-cmu-tartans-team&#34;&gt;Meet the CMU Tartans team&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I should note that Carnegie Mellon University actually has more than one team. In addition to the CMU Tartans, there is also Carnegie Mellon University I, a lower-rated team in division I, and Carnegie Mellon University II, a team in division II. I assume that these teams are composed primarily of Carnegie Mellon undergrad students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On paper, the CMU Tartans was a very strong team, with the highest rating in division I, and therefore a favorite to win (which we did):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not all 8 of our team members played in every round. Since it is very important to have at least 4 members show up for each match, because the team match score is based on 4 official games for each team during a round, I would like to recognize, in order of number of games played:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Daniel Malkiel: all 6 games!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jeffrey Quirke, Edward Dean: 5 games&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ruan Lufei, Franklin Chen, Avi Schreiber: 2 games&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Iryna Zenyuk, Luka Glinsky: 1 game&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are the team members, in board order:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;ruan-lufei-current-rating-2569-http-www-uschess-org-msa-mbrdtlmain-php-14477796-played-2-games&#34;&gt;Ruan Lufei, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.uschess.org/msa/MbrDtlMain.php?14477796&#34;&gt;current rating 2569&lt;/a&gt; (played 2 games)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ruan scored 2-0.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ruan_Lufei&#34;&gt;Ruan&lt;/a&gt; is actually world famous, being one of the top woman chess players in the world. She has the Woman Grand Master (WGM) title and was the runner-up in the 2010 Women&amp;rsquo;s World Championship, in which she faced Hou Yifan but lost. She is hard at work &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.tepper.cmu.edu/news-multimedia/tepper-stories/queens-gambit-ruan-balances-chess-with-phd-studies/index.aspx&#34;&gt;in the CMU PhD program in accounting&lt;/a&gt;, so she has these years been focused on completing her studies rather than on chess. She is far, far stronger than the rest of the CMU Tartans team!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;iryna-zenyuk-current-rating-2327-http-www-uschess-org-msa-mbrdtlmain-php-12846035-played-1-game&#34;&gt;Iryna Zenyuk, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.uschess.org/msa/MbrDtlMain.php?12846035&#34;&gt;current rating 2327&lt;/a&gt; (played 1 game)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iryna scored 0.5-0.5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.uschesschamps.com/bio/zenyuk&#34;&gt;Iryna&lt;/a&gt; has the Woman International Master (WIM) title and is one of the top ten woman chess players in the United States. She has been &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.contrib.andrew.cmu.edu/~izenyuk/&#34;&gt;in the CMU PhD program in mechanical engineering&lt;/a&gt;, but has managed to find time to play in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.uschesschamps.com/&#34;&gt;US Chess Championships&lt;/a&gt;. Here is a recent &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.uschesschamps.com/meet-players-iryna-zenyuk&#34;&gt;interview of her&lt;/a&gt; leading up to the 2013 US Chess Championships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;daniel-malkiel-current-rating-2182-http-www-uschess-org-msa-mbrdtlmain-php-12693164-played-6-games&#34;&gt;Daniel Malkiel, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.uschess.org/msa/MbrDtlMain.php?12693164&#34;&gt;current rating 2182&lt;/a&gt; (played 6 games)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dan scored 4.0-2.0.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dan has an &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.hss.cmu.edu/philosophy/alumni.php&#34;&gt;MS from CMU in Logic and Computation&lt;/a&gt;. He was the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pscfchess.org/results/12110304.htm&#34;&gt;2012 PA State Champion&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;jeffrey-quirke-current-rating-2179-http-www-uschess-org-msa-mbrdtlmain-php-12431107-played-5-games&#34;&gt;Jeffrey Quirke, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.uschess.org/msa/MbrDtlMain.php?12431107&#34;&gt;current rating 2179&lt;/a&gt; (played 5 games)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jeff scored 3-2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jeff is also a CMU alumnus, with an MSEE in Electrical and Computer Engineering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;franklin-chen-current-rating-2164-http-www-uschess-org-msa-mbrdtlmain-php-12226800-played-2-games&#34;&gt;Franklin Chen, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.uschess.org/msa/MbrDtlMain.php?12226800&#34;&gt;current rating 2164&lt;/a&gt; (played 2 games)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I scored 2-0.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I only played in the first two of the six team matches, my first games upon &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/08/21/returning-to-chess/&#34;&gt;returning to chess after a long absence&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/10/14/pittsburgh-chess-league-round-2-natural-moves-are-often-bad/&#34;&gt;round 2&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/11/11/pittsburgh-chess-league-round-3-back-to-chess-after-a-month-off/&#34;&gt;round 3&lt;/a&gt;. After that, I became very busy, unfortunately, and did not play for the team in the final four rounds. I took a complete break from chess early this year after &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/02/20/pittsburgh-chess-club-championship-2013-round-6-winning-as-black-like-a-madman/&#34;&gt;winning the 2013 Pittsburgh Chess Club Championship&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;edward-dean-current-rating-2136-http-www-uschess-org-msa-mbrdtlmain-php-12670976-played-5-games&#34;&gt;Edward Dean, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.uschess.org/msa/MbrDtlMain.php?12670976&#34;&gt;current rating 2136&lt;/a&gt; (played 5 games)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ed scored 3.5-1.5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.andrew.cmu.edu/user/edean/&#34;&gt;Ed&lt;/a&gt; is currently in the CMU PhD program in Pure and Applied Logic. He was Pittsburgh Chess Club champion in both 2011 and 2012. I have covered two of my games against him on my blog, neither of which I won: &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/10/09/final-round-of-pittsburgh-chess-club-tournament-clawing-back-from-a-terrible-position-to-draw-and-tie-for-first/&#34;&gt;a draw&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/04/round-4-of-pittsburgh-chess-club-tournament-the-agony-of-losing-a-won-game-against-the-difficult-opponent/&#34;&gt;a loss&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;luka-glinsky-current-rating-2032-http-www-uschess-org-msa-mbrdtlmain-php-12864884-played-1-game&#34;&gt;Luka Glinsky, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.uschess.org/msa/MbrDtlMain.php?12864884&#34;&gt;current rating 2032&lt;/a&gt; (played 1 game)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luka played in the final round, scoring 0-1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://lukaglinsky.com/&#34;&gt;Luka&lt;/a&gt; is a CMU undergrad in drama (acting), graduating with a BFA in a couple of weeks! I first met him on the chess scene when he was about 14 years old, a strong junior player. He has had very little time for chess in the past 4 years as a student at CMU, ha! We will miss him as he leaves Pittsburgh to pursue his acting career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;avi-schreiber-current-rating-1926-http-www-uschess-org-msa-mbrdtlmain-php-12691059-played-2-games&#34;&gt;Avi Schreiber, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.uschess.org/msa/MbrDtlMain.php?12691059&#34;&gt;current rating 1926&lt;/a&gt; (played 2 games)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Avi scored 2-0.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I first met Avi years ago when he was an undergrad at Pitt playing for one of the Pitt teams, but since he joined the staff at CMU, he joined the CMU Tartans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;some-interesting-discussions&#34;&gt;Some interesting discussions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During dinner we had fun just socializing for a while, but then of course Jeff pulled out a chess set, and we enjoyed solving chess puzzles together and analyzing some games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought it was interesting that people had different opinions about the weight of &amp;ldquo;talent&amp;rdquo; versus hard work in getting good at chess, and how good an &amp;ldquo;average&amp;rdquo; person could get at chess. Some of us seemed very optimistic about how far one could get in chess simply through hard work, using &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Practice_%28learning_method%29&#34;&gt;deliberate practice&lt;/a&gt;; others of us acknowledged the importance of work, but felt that there was a lower ceiling of possibility because of talent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We went through one of Dan&amp;rsquo;s games that was particularly interesting that I plan to write a separate blog post about, and also one of Jeff&amp;rsquo;s games that illustrated subtleties in apparently simplified positions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The CMU Tartans rule again! It was a fun time. Thank you, Jeff, for organizing this dinner! I hope to be able to play more than two rounds for the team next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2016-01-09&#34;&gt;(Update of 2016-01-09)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t play in the Pittsburgh Chess League in 2013-2014 or
2014-2015, but have been enjoying being with the CMU Tartans again,
now on board two, for the 2015-2016 season, which has three more
rounds to go. Jeff and Ed are still on the team, but the rest of the
2012-2013 team have left town.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A comeback from Pittsburgh Marathon overtraining</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/04/06/comeback-from-pittsburgh-marathon-overtraining/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Apr 2013 15:59:23 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/04/06/comeback-from-pittsburgh-marathon-overtraining/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Last week I reported on running Just A Short Run, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/30/report-on-just-a-short-run-my-first-half-marathon-in-nine-years/&#34;&gt;my first half marathon in nine years&lt;/a&gt;. One very real concern I had &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/03/my-first-steel-city-road-runners-winter-5k-race/&#34;&gt;when I put this race on my calendar a month ago&lt;/a&gt; was that recovery from it might interfere with my marathon training. Although I did not race Just A Short Run all out, I did put in a hard effort, and sure enough I did end up having a really tough training week afterwards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the overtraining this week was partly my doing. Here I explain how I ended up feeling like I was falling apart, and how I recovered and felt pretty good during today&amp;rsquo;s long run.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/wow-run.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Pittsburgh Marathon Warmup on Walnut run&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;after-the-half-marathon&#34;&gt;After the half marathon&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned in my report, I had some issues after the race: my right lower calf/Achilles area seized up for a bit, and also my right second and third toes did as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sure enough, a day later, I was feeling very sore in my right lower calf and second toe. I should mention that I have &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Morton%27s_toe&#34;&gt;Morton&amp;rsquo;s toe&lt;/a&gt; on both feet, although my left second toe is only barely longer than the big toe, while it is my right second toe that is noticeably longer than the big toe and therefore has a real tendency to cause me some problems:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mortons-toe.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;My Morton&amp;#39;s toes&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So I did take a day off running after the half marathon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;monday-trying-to-be-careful&#34;&gt;Monday: trying to be careful&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But even on Monday, I was still feeling sore. I decided that I should do some light running anyway, to avoid two days off completely from running.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, I very much wanted to finally start running in my new Luna Sandals, which I had received last week but put aside because of the half marathon. These are the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lunasandals.com/products/33-venado&#34;&gt;Venado with ATS laces and MGT footbed&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/lunastore/images/255/full.jpg?1351720427&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Luna Sandals: Venado, ATS laces, MGT footbed&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I ended up running just an easy 2 miles on the treadmill in the morning in my Vibram FiveFingers Bikila LS shoes, and then after work, running 1.5 miles in the Luna Sandals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;tuesday-new-shoes&#34;&gt;Tuesday: new shoes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tuesday, I was still not yet completely recovered either from the half marathon, but I felt I was ready to go for a normal run. I decided to do a real run in the Luna Sandals and did 5 miles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I encountered various problems while trying out the Luna Sandals, beginning to break them in. I got chafed in various places from the straps and buckle:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/luna-sandals-2013-04-02/feet.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Feet chafed&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/luna-sandals-2013-04-02/side.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Side view&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/luna-sandals-2013-04-02/wearing.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Feet in&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/luna-sandals-2013-04-02/heel.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;View of heel&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And it was tricky keeping the sandals on at all. I fidgeted a lot with the laces to try to keep my heels from slipping. I kept on having problems with my right heel slipping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, although my calf was healing up, I was more worried about my right second toe, which seemed sore and sensitive. I noticed that my tendency to impact the second toe (after all, it is my longest toe) was causing trouble. I had not really encountered any problems until after the half marathon, but the intensity of that effort, and the fact that my Bikila LS shoes were getting worn down at the toes, must have exposed this biomechanical weakness finally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;wednesday-overexcited&#34;&gt;Wednesday: overexcited&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wednesday, I was excited about running, and used the Luna Sandals again. I still had slippage and chafing issues, but figured that there was a break-in process. The soles were starting to shape to my feet, for example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, I accidentally (because of taking impromptu routes in Homewood Cemetery) ran 9 miles when I had originally intended to run more like 7.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My second toe was startling to tingle and really complain: even normal walking triggered pain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;thursday-admission-of-overtraining&#34;&gt;Thursday: admission of overtraining&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thursday was one of those days when I truly &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/14/three-questions-to-ask-yourself-when-you-dont-feel-like-doing-your-scheduled-workout/&#34;&gt;had to ask myself three questions&lt;/a&gt;. I was simply feeling &lt;em&gt;exhausted&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I forced myself to completely take Thursday off from running (or strength training, for that matter), while evaluating my situation. This was no longer just about my toe, but about my overall fatigue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, I had to fix this toe problem somehow, and soon, because I had a long run planned for Saturday. So I observed myself closely while walking. I noticed that I had a tendency to do a weird retracting motion on the toe when walking, a motion I do not use on my left foot. I questioned the purpose of this reflex. I found that I could &lt;em&gt;choose&lt;/em&gt; not to perform the retracting motion. It was difficult to make this choice, but if I really focused, I could control how I &lt;em&gt;used&lt;/em&gt; my foot. I remembered lessons from &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alexander_technique&#34;&gt;Alexander technique&lt;/a&gt; about observing and unlearning habits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, I discovered the reason my right hip has sometimes felt sore: my right hip has sagged in my posture. I also found that correcting this shifted the balance of weight on my right foot, and alleviated the pressure on my second toe, shifting more weight where it should be, more toward the big toe under the ball of the foot. These were very interesting discoveries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, I felt so tired that I decided to go ahead and cancel my Sunday plan to play in the final round of the Pittsburgh Chess League season; I had really wanted to put in one final appearance for our team, after not having actually played for us since &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/11/11/pittsburgh-chess-league-round-3-back-to-chess-after-a-month-off/&#34;&gt;last November&lt;/a&gt;, because something kept on coming up every month since then, but I had little confidence that I would be mentally alert on Sunday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;friday-still-playing-it-safe&#34;&gt;Friday: still playing it safe&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Friday, I was feeling energetic enough to run, but I forced myself to take another day off for the sake of my right toe. It was not easy, but I reminded myself that &lt;em&gt;not being able to do my long run&lt;/em&gt; was not worth one more missed day of training.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of running, I did one rep of the Cathedral of Learning stair climb, just to get some activity in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;saturday-my-14-mile-long-run&#34;&gt;Saturday: my 14-mile long run&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saturday morning, I felt my right toe had recovered sufficiently that I was going to be OK doing my planned long run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Steel City Road Runners had a 10-mile run lined up starting in Shadyside after a program of dynamics warmups by Dr. Vonda Wright, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pittsburghmarathon.com/wow.asp&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Warmup on Walnut&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, outside of sponsor &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.truerunner.com/&#34;&gt;True Runner&lt;/a&gt;. My plan was to skip that program, but create a 14-mile run by running 2 miles from home to the Shadyside point and then joining the group run and then running 2 miles back home afterwards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is the 10-mile loop:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe id=&#34;mapmyfitness_route&#34; src=&#34;http://snippets.mapmycdn.com/routes/view/embedded/187175578?width=560&amp;height=400&amp;elevation=true&amp;info=true&amp;line_color=E60f0bdb&amp;rgbhex=DB0B0E&amp;distance_markers=1&amp;unit_type=imperial&amp;map_mode=TERRAIN&amp;last_updated=2013-04-01T09:44:11-04:00&#34; height=&#34;590px&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: right; padding-right: 20px;&#34;&gt;&lt;a target=&#34;_blank&#34; href=&#34;http://mapmyrun.com/routes/create/&#34;&gt;Create Maps&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a target=&#34;_blank&#34; href=&#34;http://mapmyrun.com/routes/&#34;&gt;search&lt;/a&gt; from 80 million at &lt;a href=&#34;http://mapmyrun.com&#34;&gt;MapMyRun&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;my-goal&#34;&gt;My goal&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My goal for this long run was to make it a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mcmillanrunning.com/index.php/articlePages/article/2&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;fast finish long run&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. In particular, in planning my run, I had noted that the last 5 miles of the course involved a steady uphill as well as a steeper uphill through Oakland on Forbes Avenue. In the 2003 Pittsburgh Marathon ten years ago, this uphill had proved a bit discouraging to me (because I had, frankly, gone out too fast). In any case, for psychological and physiological reasons, I wanted to do this whole uphill fast and strong in this particular workout. In the actual marathon in a month, of course, I don&amp;rsquo;t plan to run it as fast, but I did want to remember the landmarks and mental state of doing something difficult but in a relaxed way. I wanted to focus on applying my newly discovered knowledge about my posture and stride asymmetry and &amp;ldquo;run tall&amp;rdquo; up the hill, with balanced hips, while monitoring my right second toe to make sure it did not get battered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was still not comfortable with the Luna Sandals, so I fell back to the shoes I&amp;rsquo;ve been wearing for almost all of my runs in the past three months, the Bikila LS shoes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;showed-up-late&#34;&gt;Showed up late&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, I strangely miscalculated my departure from home to run 2 miles to Aiken Avenue and Walnut Street, and showed up 4 minutes late, just as runners were already heading off. I grabbed a printed map and picked up the pace so that I could try to catch up to the 10:00 pace group. I did, realizing of course that I was making my task in the final miles of my run more difficult as a result.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;conquering-the-oakland-hill&#34;&gt;Conquering the Oakland hill&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I managed the Oakland hill pretty well, being very focused. I continued going hard all the way back to True Runner in Shadyside. Near the end, I felt my calves getting tight, just as in the half marathon last week when my right calf seized up after I was walking after the finish line. I thought it was very useful to have triggered this exact sensation and knowing where it was, because it meant that maybe I would be able to train my body to accept that state of fatigue (after running 12 miles) and continue. Also, the feeling cleared up fairly quickly after I stopped to walk, so I think last week the real trigger was my pointless little sprint near the end. If I avoid any sprinting during the marathon, I might well be able to avoid cramping. At least, that is the plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;a-decision-about-gatorade&#34;&gt;A decision about Gatorade&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I drank some more Gatorade back at Walnut Street, then ran home. I was really quite tired by this point and my stomach wasn&amp;rsquo;t feeling so great. I ate some actual food and eventually recovered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During this run, no gels were provided, so I drank Gatorade as my only fuel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is my final conclusion, solidifying a thought I had last week in the half marathon: &lt;em&gt;Gatorade is bad for me&lt;/em&gt;, and I should &lt;em&gt;completely&lt;/em&gt; avoid it in future runs and in the Pittsburgh Marathon! It was good to learn this for sure now. In fact, it is quite possible that some of the issues I had in the 2003 Pittsburgh Marathon were a result of Gatorade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GU gel works OK for me, but according to the official &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburghmarathon.com/Course.asp&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Marathon fluid station table&lt;/a&gt;, GU is provided only starting at mile 9.7. Therefore, I am going to pack some gels to ingest during the first 10 miles of the marathon! I will &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; drink any Gatorade!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After some ill-advised overtraining and injury this week after my half marathon, I forced myself to take two days off to recover, and used the time to diagnose possible causes of my biomechanical problems. I found some good hypotheses and possible solutions, and managed a high quality &amp;ldquo;fast finish long run&amp;rdquo; and am optimistic about my continuing training for the Pittsburgh Marathon.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pittsburgh Chess League Round 3: back to chess after a month off</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/11/11/pittsburgh-chess-league-round-3-back-to-chess-after-a-month-off/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Nov 2012 23:24:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/11/11/pittsburgh-chess-league-round-3-back-to-chess-after-a-month-off/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/chen-winwood-2012-11-11_files/pcl3.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Round 3 in progress&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;i-had-a-break-from-chess&#34;&gt;I had a break from chess&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I took &lt;em&gt;a whole month&lt;/em&gt; off from playing chess, after completing both a six-round &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburghcc.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Chess Club&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/10/09/final-round-of-pittsburgh-chess-club-tournament-clawing-back-from-a-terrible-position-to-draw-and-tie-for-first/&#34;&gt;Tuesday night tournament&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/10/14/pittsburgh-chess-league-round-2-natural-moves-are-often-bad/&#34;&gt;a round&lt;/a&gt; of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pitt.edu/~schach/ChessPA/ChessLeague/wpapcl.htm&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Chess League&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I welcomed the break because there were many projects I had temporarily put on hold during my comeback to chess. But after about three weeks, I mysteriously began to have chess dreams arrive in my sleep, and I felt the craving for battle. So I looked forward not only to round 3 of the Pittsburgh Chess League, but also signed up for the next Pittsburgh Chess Club Tuesday night tournament, which starts this week!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;today-s-lesson&#34;&gt;Today&amp;rsquo;s lesson&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this round of the Pittsburgh Chess League, round 3, our team, the CMU Tartans, was paired against the Phalanx Lords. We ended up winning another match (we won our match in round 2, and had a byte in round 1). My game was the next-to-last to finish, taking almost four and a half hours to complete. I was so exhausted afterwards!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today&amp;rsquo;s lesson: &lt;em&gt;passive&lt;/em&gt; moves are not only bad, but often clump together psychologically, magnifying their badness!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-complete-annotated-game&#34;&gt;The complete annotated game&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At your convenience, you can &lt;a href=&#34;../../chess/chen-winwood-2012-11-11.htm&#34;&gt;enjoy playing over the game with my annotations, including diagrams.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;preparation&#34;&gt;Preparation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I took a month off from chess, and had no time to engage in any chess study whatsoever, I went into my game without any preparation. I didn&amp;rsquo;t even know exactly whom I was going to face, or what color I would play. In fact, I had originally guessed that I was going to play Black on third board against someone, but I ended up playing White on second board against someone else. Of course, because of the uncertainty, I had scoped out the possibility of playing someone else on the opposing team, so I was not faced with a complete surprise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;strength&#34;&gt;Strength&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My opponent was someone I&amp;rsquo;d played three times before, years ago, and won against each time. So at the board, I wasn&amp;rsquo;t worried. He is an Expert rated a hundred points below me, so he nevertheless had to be taken quite seriously, of course. He had been playing well recently, apparently, tying for second for prize money at &lt;a href=&#34;http://pscfchess.org/results/12110304.htm&#34;&gt;last weekend&amp;rsquo;s Pennsylvania State Chess Championship&lt;/a&gt; (which I had no time to attend but stopped by for a few minutes to check out while in Oakland for four hours of music workshops).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;overview-of-my-game&#34;&gt;Overview of my game&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-opening&#34;&gt;The opening&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a slight state of confusion, straight out of the opening (an &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/English_Opening&#34;&gt;English Opening&lt;/a&gt;) I ended up suddenly deciding to play an opening variation I had never played before!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What happened was that on the fly, I decided I simply did not feel like playing yet another &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/19/round-3-of-pittsburgh-chess-club-tournament-another-approach-against-the-sicilian-squeezing-with-the-bind/&#34;&gt;Maróczy Bind&lt;/a&gt; type of position, and varied. What can I say? I just didn&amp;rsquo;t feel like it. There is no logic to this kind of decision. It was an impulse I gave into.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, it turns out that apparently my opponent also had not encountered this opening variation, and he played inaccurately, resulting in my gaining a large advantage in time and space:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/chen-winwood-2012-11-11_files/diag3FED81D0E4996A38.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Opening&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-middle&#34;&gt;The middle&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I made what I consider to be an elementary sort of error, in needlessly allowing the exchange of some minor pieces by Black, because of my rush to expand on the Queen side already. Nevertheless, I retained a real advantage despite the exchanges:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/chen-winwood-2012-11-11_files/diag3FED81D4129ADD7E.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Opening after exchanges&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Black made some passive moves that allowed me to build up to a great position in preparation for a King side attack; a quicker &lt;code&gt;a5&lt;/code&gt; and without the weakening &lt;code&gt;b6&lt;/code&gt; would have created counterplay more reliably:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/chen-winwood-2012-11-11_files/diag3FED81D66D578ACA.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Rook lift&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I started losing the thread when, instead of closing off the Queen side and turning my attention to the King side, I tried to &amp;ldquo;keep my options open&amp;rdquo; (as far as pushing for &lt;code&gt;c5&lt;/code&gt;), and not only allowed Black to take control of the &lt;code&gt;a&lt;/code&gt; file, but also I gave up my back rank, believing that there was no harm in doing that. In some sense, maybe that was correct (I was in fact never in danger of losing in this game), but from a practical point of view, I was creating conditions in which I could (and did) make further inaccuracies:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/chen-winwood-2012-11-11_files/diag3FED81DAACC10D54.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Black has counterplay&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In a critical position in which I could have continued strongly, I made the mistake of the &lt;em&gt;wrong exchange of pieces&lt;/em&gt; in which I took Black&amp;rsquo;s Bishop for my Knight:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/chen-winwood-2012-11-11_files/diag3FED81DE25533EF3.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Exchange coming&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I cannot hide the fact that I made a similar mistake in a previous &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/12/round-2-of-the-pittsburgh-chess-club-tournament-winning-in-the-sicilian-defense-the-philosophy-and-psychology-of-struggle/&#34;&gt;chess game in September&lt;/a&gt;. If you look at that game, you will see that I created a dominant position and then &amp;ldquo;greedily&amp;rdquo; exchanged a good Knight for a bad Bishop. &lt;strong&gt;I have therefore uncovered a weakness of my play that I was not entirely aware of before: I like Bishops too much!&lt;/strong&gt; I am stating this weakness publicly in hope of forcing myself to be careful in the future. It&amp;rsquo;s funny because I did not always have this prejudice; I used to play openings in which I quickly gave up a Bishop for a Knight. But then something changed. Now is the time to restore balance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My opponent and I traded inaccuracies in which we did not play the most active moves possible (in particular, he made one of his Rooks pointlessly passive, as did I), but overall, we reached a point at which I was in danger of not getting anywhere at all, and I finally continued my King side attack:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/chen-winwood-2012-11-11_files/diag3FED81F021BD28CB.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;King side attack&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Objectively, this should not have worked at all, but somehow, I had momentum and my opponent became passive at the &lt;em&gt;worst&lt;/em&gt; possible moment, and after a single passive move with the Queen, the following position was reached, which I consider to be probably won for White:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/chen-winwood-2012-11-11_files/diag3FED81F502B59D15.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Strong for White&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Black should have &lt;em&gt;actively&lt;/em&gt; defended against the King side attack, by fearlessly moving the Pawn up with &lt;code&gt;f5&lt;/code&gt; instead of sitting around:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/chen-winwood-2012-11-11_files/diag3FED81F3EB16D349.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Strong defense&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There is a fear some of us have of moving Pawns in front of our King in the face of an attack. But tactically, sometimes that is the correct thing to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-end&#34;&gt;The end&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the Pawn attack &lt;code&gt;h5&lt;/code&gt; by White, the game was basically over:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/chen-winwood-2012-11-11_files/diag3FED81F5FB42C23C.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;White&amp;#39;s King side attack is overwhelming&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Check out the game annotations for details, but this is the final position, in which Black resigned because of impending loss of a piece:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/chen-winwood-2012-11-11_files/diag3FED820A14461016.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Final position&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Notice how passive Black&amp;rsquo;s position was at this point, with the Rook on &lt;code&gt;b7&lt;/code&gt; doing nothing, the Knight pinned on the back rank, Black&amp;rsquo;s King suffocated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;lessons-learned&#34;&gt;Lessons learned&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Many of the problems faced by both sides in the game were a result of playing passively rather than immediately going on an attack or an active defense.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I have to stop wanting to take Bishops with my Knights, despite the fact that in both games so far in which I&amp;rsquo;ve mistakenly done so, I have managed to activate my Bishop eventually to advantage after all, by accident.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is no secret that human chess play is annoyingly imperfect and sentimental compared to computer analysis; human play features blocks of related moves that are either a series of passive moves or a series of over-aggressive moves, rather than a &amp;ldquo;living in the present&amp;rdquo; choice of a good move in a given position without regard to what bad plan one started executing earlier. The task of any chess improver must be to be more computer-like, which is ironically more Zen-like.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-next&#34;&gt;What next?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next Pittsburgh Chess Club Tuesday night tournament starts on Tuesday. I hope to play well in it. Obviously, I would like to win all six rounds and the tournament, but more than that, I simply wish to play well and let the wins take care of themselves from that. Also, there will be another round of the Pittsburgh Chess League in early December. After those are over, I will get another break from chess until sometime in January.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was pleased at finally winning my game and helping the team win the match. And I am continuing to observe these patterns of passivity in my play as well as in the play of my opponents, hoping to learn something as I document them.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pittsburgh Chess League Round 2: natural moves are often bad</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/10/14/pittsburgh-chess-league-round-2-natural-moves-are-often-bad/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Oct 2012 20:35:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/10/14/pittsburgh-chess-league-round-2-natural-moves-are-often-bad/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/chen-osipovich-2012-10-14_files/final.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Final position&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Today I played in a round at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pitt.edu/~schach/ChessPA/ChessLeague/wpapcl.htm&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Chess League&lt;/a&gt; for the first time in almost two years!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was round 2 of the current season; I was fortunate that our team got a bye in round 1 last month, because that bye had made it possible for me to &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/16/excited-by-the-new-season-of-the-pittsburgh-recorder-society/&#34;&gt;attend the Pittsburgh Recorder Society meeting&lt;/a&gt; instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today&amp;rsquo;s lesson: &amp;ldquo;natural&amp;rdquo; looking moves in chess are often bad, and even fatal. My game contained a lot of &amp;ldquo;natural&amp;rdquo; moves by both myself and my opponent that were no good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-complete-annotated-game&#34;&gt;The complete annotated game&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At your convenience, you can &lt;a href=&#34;../../chess/chen-osipovich-2012-10-14.htm&#34;&gt;enjoy playing over the game with my annotations, including diagrams.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;preparation&#34;&gt;Preparation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You never know exactly whom you&amp;rsquo;ll play in the Pittsburgh Chess League team match, because although the schedules for the teams are set, it is usually not known until arrival which members of a team are actually going to play and represent the team. Individuals on a team can choose not to play, for whatever reason, and inform the team captain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A couple of days before the team match, I had an idea of whom I might play, and I turned out to be right. It was a guy I&amp;rsquo;ve only played with once, when I was Black, and I had won. But since I was going to be White in the match, I had no idea what kind of Black openings he plays. Therefore, I went in just ready to play one of my usual White openings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;strength&#34;&gt;Strength&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I knew I was considerably stronger than my opponent, who was on his rating floor of 1900.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;psychology&#34;&gt;Psychology&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, I also knew that my opponent was very aggressive, and therefore, it was possible to get into trouble if I allowed him to get an attack of any kind. So I set a goal for myself of erring on the side of being more &lt;em&gt;cautious&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;defensive&lt;/em&gt; than I ordinarily am. As my games in my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/10/09/final-round-of-pittsburgh-chess-club-tournament-clawing-back-from-a-terrible-position-to-draw-and-tie-for-first/&#34;&gt;recent Pittsburgh Chess Club tournament&lt;/a&gt; have shown, I have usually chosen to find the most committal, &amp;ldquo;best&amp;rdquo; move. That&amp;rsquo;s great if I can be confident of following up correctly. It&amp;rsquo;s not great if I make a mistake. The pragmatic question of how to synchronize my style of play with the realities of my opponent and the moment is one I have never answered perfectly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;other-factors&#34;&gt;Other factors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also a serious issue for me going into this game was the fact that I was entering it in a physically and mentally less-energetic state than I would have liked. Yesterday I went on a tough 13-mile run with a friend in the morning, then went to a potluck/music jam in the evening, so I basically had no rest this weekend. I felt that I truly needed to conserve energy during the game, so that I would not run out in case the game lasted a long time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;overview-of-my-game&#34;&gt;Overview of my game&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-opening&#34;&gt;The opening&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My opponent surprised me with the bizarre &lt;em&gt;first move&lt;/em&gt; he played!!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/chen-osipovich-2012-10-14_files/diag3FDC28E3E53716F5.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;St. George Defense&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Objectively, his opening, the infamous &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St._George_Defence&#34;&gt;St. George Defense&lt;/a&gt; was bad, and I knew it, but I decided to play calmly and &amp;ldquo;normally&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I was partly right, but also partly wrong.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being calm is always good, but being overly cautious deprived me of playing stronger moves. I was clearly reacting to my having been too hotheaded in my tough game from just some days ago, in which I created a great position and then lost the thread.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;ignoring-the-obvious&#34;&gt;Ignoring the obvious&lt;/h4&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/chen-osipovich-2012-10-14_files/diag3FDC28F4E2DD211F.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;e5 outpost&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We reached a position in which Black&amp;rsquo;s &lt;code&gt;e5&lt;/code&gt; square is obviously weak. If I had not been in my overly cautious, slow mode, I would have occupied it and secured a clear advantage immediately. Instead, I chose to just &amp;ldquo;naturally&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;develop&amp;rdquo; my Queen Bishop and Knight, as though playing like a beginner who is told to &amp;ldquo;develop&amp;rdquo; pieces before starting any attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Playing too &amp;ldquo;naturally&amp;rdquo; is something a beginner does.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An expert is not supposed to just play &amp;ldquo;naturally&amp;rdquo;, but evaluate the position as it uniquely exists, and strike immediately if the context allows, or &lt;em&gt;demands&lt;/em&gt;, immediate action. I wasn&amp;rsquo;t playing quite like an expert today, unfortunately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, in just a few moves, all my opening advantage had evaporated, as Black slowly deployed his pieces optimally:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/chen-osipovich-2012-10-14_files/diag3FDC28FFCF110316.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;e5 OK for Black&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-middle&#34;&gt;The middle&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I realized that I had messed up the late opening, I tried to recover, by fighting for the &lt;code&gt;e5&lt;/code&gt; square afresh. My opponent returned my early favor by not playing the most critical fighting moves and instead also playing &amp;ldquo;naturally&amp;rdquo;, developing his final Bishop rather than beginning an attack on my King side that would have disrupted my late buildup and guaranteed equality. So I planted my Knight on &lt;code&gt;e5&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/chen-osipovich-2012-10-14_files/diag3FDC2905BB3ACC1D.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;e5 taken&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The game was basically over as soon as I occupied that outpost.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not joking: White&amp;rsquo;s advantage is so large that if you gave me this position again, against anybody, I believe I could force a win. Black has no counterplay against White&amp;rsquo;s impending King side attack once &lt;code&gt;e5&lt;/code&gt; is occupied, especially given that Black also weakened &lt;code&gt;g6&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;h7&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rest of the game was mostly anti-climactic, because Black is so lost. But there is one more observation to make.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-end&#34;&gt;The end&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After Black played terribly and quickly lost the Exchange (a Rook for a Bishop) and was dead lost, this position arose:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/chen-osipovich-2012-10-14_files/diag3FDC29117AB3740E.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;What to do with the attacked Bishop?&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The &amp;ldquo;natural&amp;rdquo; move, &lt;code&gt;Bb1&lt;/code&gt;, saving the Bishop and keeping it attacking Black along the diagonal, happens to be &lt;em&gt;obvious&lt;/em&gt; and also &lt;em&gt;best&lt;/em&gt;. But for once in the game, I didn&amp;rsquo;t play the &amp;ldquo;natural&amp;rdquo; move. I got sloppy. I played a &amp;ldquo;clever&amp;rdquo; move instead, &lt;code&gt;g3&lt;/code&gt;, attacking Black&amp;rsquo;s remaining Rook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That was stupid, and cost me some hard thinking I could have avoided, because Black just &amp;ldquo;naturally&amp;rdquo; sacrificed another Exchange in order to reach this bizarre position:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/chen-osipovich-2012-10-14_files/diag3FDC2913C2CBF1C4.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;White is attacked&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;White is obviously totally winning, but at a price: Black has some kind of &amp;ldquo;attack&amp;rdquo; going on now whereas if the Bishop had retreated, Black would have had nothing. So I had to actually defend for a couple of moves to consolidate before finally beating back Black&amp;rsquo;s (admittedly futile) &amp;ldquo;attack&amp;rdquo; once and for all:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/chen-osipovich-2012-10-14_files/diag3FDC291C66E75605.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;White smashes through&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And the game finally ended:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/chen-osipovich-2012-10-14_files/diag3FDC291EC7DABDD8.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Black resigned&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;lessons-learned&#34;&gt;Lessons learned&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I (re)learned some important lessons during this game:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sometimes the &amp;ldquo;natural&amp;rdquo; move is terrible.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sometimes the &amp;ldquo;natural&amp;rdquo; move is clearly best.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am considering scrapping the whole concept of &amp;ldquo;natural&amp;rdquo; altogether from my mind. Chess is a discrete game with clear consequences and a tree of possible future game states. &amp;ldquo;Natural&amp;rdquo; is not good enough for a high level of play; it is a metaphor grounded in the continuous world. Even when I&amp;rsquo;m tired, I should not be thinking &amp;ldquo;natural&amp;rdquo; as an energy-saver. The question of how to gracefully degrade my play when trying to save energy, however, is difficult to answer, in this domain: I know how to run more slowly or do arithmetic sums more approximately or handwrite more sloppily, to save time or energy, but what is the best way to deliberately play chess less precisely at &amp;ldquo;less critical&amp;rdquo; moments and save the energy for &amp;ldquo;critical&amp;rdquo; moments?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-next&#34;&gt;What next?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still haven&amp;rsquo;t lost a tournament game since &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/04/round-1-of-the-pittsburgh-chess-club-tournament-the-greek-gift-sacrifice/&#34;&gt;returning to tournament play last month after an almost two-year absence&lt;/a&gt;. That&amp;rsquo;s good, of course, but on the flip side, I have been considerably higher-rated than most of my opponents. So my current record is nothing whatsoever to boast about. And, as I have shown in my annotations to my games, I have made various errors in some of my games that could have caused me real trouble if I had made those errors against stronger opponents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, it&amp;rsquo;s been nice to be playing at least relatively decently. I expect to be playing next month in round 3 of the Pittsburgh Chess League matches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was happy to contribute a win to our team match (we ended up easily winning our match) in our first match in the Pittsburgh Chess League, but left my imperfect game with questions about how to keep my play sharp.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>