<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>John Coltrane on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/john-coltrane/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in John Coltrane on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/john-coltrane/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>How Ornette Coleman changed my life</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/06/12/how-ornette-coleman-changed-my-life/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jun 2015 23:59:40 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/06/12/how-ornette-coleman-changed-my-life/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The legendary jazz musician
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ornette_Coleman&#34;&gt;Ornette Coleman&lt;/a&gt;
recently died at age 85. He had not been on my radar for a long
time. In fact, I never actually listened to much of his music at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, my immediate first thought on hearing this news was, &lt;strong&gt;Ornette
Coleman permanently changed the course of my life&lt;/strong&gt;. How can this be?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;first-reactions-to-ornette-coleman-s-music&#34;&gt;First reactions to Ornette Coleman&amp;rsquo;s music&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2000, during a huge transition in my life that turned everything
upside down, I began experimenting with listening to a lot of kinds of
music I had never experienced before. I was exploring Cuban,
Brazilian, Argentinian music. I was exploring Western classical music
of the 20th century (I had a fairly narrow taste up till then focused
primarily on the Classical 18th century and Romantic 19th century,
with little before or after this range). In jazz, I was expanding
beyond the swing, bebop, hard bop eras of jazz. I frequently reached
areas that made me confused or disgusted. For example, in jazz I got
&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/23/celebrating-the-birthday-of-john-coltrane/&#34;&gt;as far as I could with John Coltrane&lt;/a&gt;
as Coltrane ventured into &amp;ldquo;free jazz&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided to try out Ornette Coleman for another approach to &amp;ldquo;free
jazz&amp;rdquo;, and checked out the album
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Shape_of_Jazz_to_Come&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Shape of Jazz to Come&amp;rdquo; (1959)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;lonely-woman&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Lonely Woman&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Immediately, I was struck by the track
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lonely_Woman_%28composition%29&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Lonely Woman&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. Conventional
concerns such as being strictly &amp;ldquo;in tune&amp;rdquo; were out the window, in
favor of extremely flexibility of pitch and raw, wailing emotional
expression. It showcased Coleman&amp;rsquo;s lyrical side and was easy to
love. OK, not too weird.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/DNbD1JIH344&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;other-tracks&#34;&gt;Other tracks&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But bam, that was just a warmup. For example, check out
&amp;ldquo;Eventually&amp;rdquo;. It&amp;rsquo;s very free indeed, a lot of notes, an expression of
hyperactive motion, conventional tonality unimportant. Still, not too
harsh, and not totally random.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/WoC69lxnS_Y&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, what I really understood from his music was that he was doing
what came naturally to him. It did not feel forced, it was not to
prove a point. He was enjoying what he was doing. This sense of
&lt;em&gt;freedom&lt;/em&gt; really impressed me. It wasn&amp;rsquo;t reaction, it wasn&amp;rsquo;t
rebellion. I respected that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;free-jazz-a-collective-improvisation&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Free Jazz: A Collective Improvisation&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next album I checked out was
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Free_Jazz:_A_Collective_Improvisation&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Free Jazz: A Collective Improvisation&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was a step beyond, and confusing to me because of the
simultaneous playing that often seemed chaotic. I confess to taking no
huge pleasure in attempting to listen to it all at once (note that
apart from lack of conventional structure, it also keeps going on and
on at length). I found it more enjoyable to listen to only a couple of
random minutes, trying to absorb some stretch of order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, although this was not really my thing, it opened up my mind
to &amp;ldquo;why not?&amp;rdquo; Maybe this particular experiment didn&amp;rsquo;t work, but I
could imagine a simpler setting, say, with fewer instruments, in which
collective improvisation could work out better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check it out yourself:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/xbZIiom9rDA&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;something-else&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Something Else!!!!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I checked out
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Something_Else!!!!&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Something Else!!!!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;,
which actually was his first album and closer to bebop and so forth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t have much to say about it, but it&amp;rsquo;s not too confusing to
enjoy, because of still audible ties to some traditional forms and
styles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;freedom&#34;&gt;Freedom&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, I didn&amp;rsquo;t continue exploring Coleman&amp;rsquo;s music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the sense of &lt;em&gt;freedom&lt;/em&gt;, of &lt;em&gt;permission&lt;/em&gt; to ignore boundaries and
go wherever, musically, really affected me. Was what he was doing
&amp;ldquo;jazz&amp;rdquo;? Listening to him, I made up my mind that I was never again
going to get involved in debates about what jazz &amp;ldquo;really is&amp;rdquo; or what
classical music &amp;ldquo;really is&amp;rdquo; or even what music &amp;ldquo;really is&amp;rdquo;. These
labels stopped being meaningful to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That was what I really learned from him and his life. By coincidence,
I just read this Rolling Stone article,
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rollingstone.com/music/news/vernon-reid-on-ornette-coleman-he-set-a-lot-of-people-free-20150612&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Vernon Reid on Ornette Coleman: &amp;lsquo;He set a lot of people free&amp;rsquo;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;,
that echoes exactly what I felt I learned fifteen years ago from my
brief exposure to him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past year or so, there have been times when, alone and not
likely to bother anyone, I pull out my bass recorder (ha, my lowest
instrument) and just go wild, play some melodic shapes, make up
rhythms, go multiphonic, whatever, for the sheer joy of it. And I&amp;rsquo;m
not embarrassed, because I remember Ornette Coleman and he gave us all
permission to express our unconscious in whatever honest way it comes
out. And he gave us permission to accept and encourage each other to
do that, whether or not we personally like or understand everything
that comes out of tapping the unconscious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hadn&amp;rsquo;t expected to think so much upon hearing of Ornette Coleman&amp;rsquo;s
death. But he set an example that I respected deeply, forever changing
not only my perceptions of music but of what musicians can and should
be allowed to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Are you an Ornette Coleman fan or detractor? Did he change your
  life? If so, how exactly?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Celebrating the birthday of John Coltrane, the Beethoven of jazz</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/09/23/celebrating-the-birthday-of-john-coltrane/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Sep 2012 00:44:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/09/23/celebrating-the-birthday-of-john-coltrane/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://userserve-ak.last.fm/serve/252/50664911.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;John Coltrane&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So today is the birthday of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Coltrane&#34;&gt;John Coltrane&lt;/a&gt; (1926-1967), a towering figure in the history of jazz like no other. Several years ago, in a moment of inspiration, I quipped to a friend that while it was clear to me that &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charlie_Parker&#34;&gt;Charlie Parker&lt;/a&gt; the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mozart&#34;&gt;Mozart&lt;/a&gt; of jazz, it was even more clear that Coltrane was the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beethoven&#34;&gt;Beethoven&lt;/a&gt; of jazz.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What did I mean by that remark? I meant it on philosophical, historical, and musical levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;mozart-to-beethoven-parker-to-coltrane&#34;&gt;Mozart to Beethoven; Parker to Coltrane&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mozart refined the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Classical_period_(music)&#34;&gt;Classical style&lt;/a&gt; inherited from Haydn and became a most admired practitioner of it; Mozart was accused (perhaps only fictionally) of writing &amp;ldquo;too many notes&amp;rdquo; in his music.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Beethoven started off in the Classical tradition and then went beyond that in his &amp;ldquo;middle&amp;rdquo; period, and then even further beyond that in his &amp;ldquo;late&amp;rdquo; period, to the point where he became completely unique and an existential challenge (to emulate or reject) to all future composers of Western art music.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Charlie Parker refined &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bebop&#34;&gt;bebop&lt;/a&gt; in jazz, which, among other things, involved packing in quite a lot of notes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Coltrane started off in the bebop tradition and then went beyond that along with Miles Davis and others, and then even further beyond that, to the point of challenging notions of what jazz even was or should be.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as I find Beethoven in his late period to be among the most sublime, yet most bizarre music of the entire history of Western art music, and was a hard act to follow, so too Coltrane. Just as many composers after Beethoven judged that he ruined Western art music permanently, so did many jazz musicians react in the same way toward Coltrane.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-coltrane-sampler&#34;&gt;A Coltrane sampler&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a lot of good music by Coltrane I could discuss for pages and pages. Look up popular examples such as &amp;ldquo;My Favorite Things&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;A Love Supreme&amp;rdquo;, for example. But for today, I celebrated not with those favorites (which I do love), but a different set:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;giant-steps-1960&#34;&gt;Giant Steps (1960)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Giant Steps&amp;rdquo; features some of the most amazing yet fluid improvisation I have ever encountered, and I love this video someone created to show transcribed notes. This is a classic that I never tire of listening to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/2kotK9FNEYU&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;vigil-1965&#34;&gt;Vigil (1965)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Vigil&amp;rdquo; is intense and even almost chaotic. It makes strange sense to me, a flow, an expression. I love it, although I don&amp;rsquo;t watch it very often; I have to be in the right mood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/5UHZaqG87N0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;ascension-1965&#34;&gt;Ascension (1965)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OK, &amp;ldquo;Ascension&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;makes no sense to me&lt;/em&gt;, and is not something I enjoy trying to listen to. You be the judge, but he lost me here. I&amp;rsquo;m just speaking the truth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/tgrQhBTDfhk&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-beethoven-sampler&#34;&gt;A Beethoven sampler&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For kicks, even though I&amp;rsquo;m not celebrating Beethoven today, here are examples of my favorite late Beethoven.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;diabelli-variations-http-en-wikipedia-org-wiki-diabelli-variations-1819&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Diabelli_Variations&#34;&gt;Diabelli Variations&lt;/a&gt; (1819)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Truly amazing set of theme and variations for the piano, taking the listener to alternate realities before returning back to earth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/wctoxElV8Os&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;große-fuge-http-en-wikipedia-org-wiki-gro-c3-9fe-fuge-1825&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gro%C3%9Fe_Fuge&#34;&gt;Große Fuge&lt;/a&gt; (1825)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nobody at this point in history was writing stuff like this. Beethoven just went wild and created this dissonant, difficult, and emotionally cathartic movement. Amazing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/XEZXjW_s0Qs&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>