<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Food on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/food/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Food on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/food/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Finally making rhubarb tasty to myself: flour-less rhubarb crisp</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/06/09/finally-making-rhubarb-tasty-to-myself/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Jun 2014 18:15:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/06/09/finally-making-rhubarb-tasty-to-myself/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;For the first forty years of my life, I believe I never ate any rhubarb. At least, I don&amp;rsquo;t ever recall anything identified as rhubarb that I ate. It was just something I heard about, in the context of pie, and I rarely eat pies, and am rather particular about pie when I do eat it (for example, I have sometimes eaten pumpkin pie, because my father likes it, but I never once really enjoyed it).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My Krestschmann Farm box subscription has always recognized that some people don&amp;rsquo;t like rhubarb, and allows opting out of receiving it. Since I never ate it, I didn&amp;rsquo;t know whether I liked it, but looking up its description online, I felt no need to try it, so I always indicated that I did not want it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today was the first time I cooked rhubarb and made something that I actually enjoyed eating. Here&amp;rsquo;s the story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-first-time-cooking-rhubarb-was-a-disaster&#34;&gt;My first time cooking rhubarb was a disaster&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost exactly a year ago, Abby and I accidentally did not specify rhubarb exclusion from our farm box (upon renewing our subscription). So we received rhubarb.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t know what the heck to do with it. I decided to make an Indian-style lentil dish and &amp;ldquo;hide&amp;rdquo; rhubarb in it. At first I thought it was OK, but then I decided it was weird. Unfortunately, I had to finish the whole batch. Abby didn&amp;rsquo;t help me finish it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rhubarb-lentils-2013-06-10.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Rhubarb lentils&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;abby-s-experiment-didn-t-work-for-me&#34;&gt;Abby&amp;rsquo;s experiment didn&amp;rsquo;t work for me&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby also tried an experiment, cooking rhubarb with banana on the stove. The resulting concoction caused an argument, because after trying it, I refused to eat any more of it, but she had made a huge batch and so she was stuck with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-experiment-today&#34;&gt;My experiment today&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I decided that instead of randomly making crap up, I would look for some kind of &amp;ldquo;recipe&amp;rdquo;, and also incorporate the advice of friends from last year. The following is what I made. I found it surprisingly edible, and even had to stop myself from eating too much after dinner:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rhubarb-2014-06-09.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Rhubarb crisp&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My ingredients:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Coconut oil&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rhubarb, chopped up&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Honey (I tried to go easy with this!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cinnamon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cloves&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Orange zest&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lemon juice&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Salt&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cocoa powder (a tiny sprinkle, just an improvisation)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Raw walnuts and pecans, chopped&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Preheat oven to 350 degrees F, layer the nuts on top of the remainder of the mixture, and bake for 40 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to everyone who offered suggestions to me last year!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result was fairly tart, which is fine, but I didn&amp;rsquo;t want to put too much sugar into this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-next&#34;&gt;What next?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was planning to notify Kretschmann Farm that we don&amp;rsquo;t want to receive rhubarb, but I have second thoughts now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, we will probably go ahead as planned and put rhubarb on our &amp;ldquo;do not want&amp;rdquo; list, simply because we&amp;rsquo;d rather get other stuff instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;lessons-learned&#34;&gt;Lessons learned&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I learned some lessons from this whole rhubarb incident:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I can learn to &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/03/21/time-to-taste-the-world-thoughts-on-expanding-my-food-tastes-as-an-adult/&#34;&gt;like stuff I never ate for decades&lt;/a&gt;, if I prepare it just so. (More generally, I try to continuously find opportunities to &lt;a href=&#34;http://sivers.org/hate&#34;&gt;love what I used to hate&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is wise to listen to accumulated wisdom, especially from my friends (whose taste might be correlated a bit with mine).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Accidentally &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; choosing to opt out of my &amp;ldquo;default&amp;rdquo; preference led to some interesting experiences.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s the latest food you feared or hated or didn&amp;rsquo;t know about that you recently tried? How did it go? If it went poorly, will you try again, or just write it off?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>&#34;Time to Taste the World&#34;: thoughts on expanding my food tastes as an adult</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/03/21/time-to-taste-the-world-thoughts-on-expanding-my-food-tastes-as-an-adult/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Mar 2014 21:37:07 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/03/21/time-to-taste-the-world-thoughts-on-expanding-my-food-tastes-as-an-adult/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This evening, right after work, I attended an event called &amp;ldquo;Time to Taste the World&amp;rdquo;, organized by Carnegie Mellon University&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cmu.edu/dietrich/modlang/student-organizations/mlsac.html&#34;&gt;Modern Languages Student Advisory Council&lt;/a&gt; for the Department of Modern Languages. It was an informal event featuring some food selections followed by a German film that I opted not to watch, since I needed to go home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were three tables of food, one for &amp;ldquo;Asian&amp;rdquo;, another for &amp;ldquo;Mediterranean&amp;rdquo;, and another for &amp;ldquo;European&amp;rdquo;. Obviously, only a very tiny fraction of the world was actually represented in this event, and the selections were mostly not very exciting, but it was interesting and even jarring going from one table to another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/time-to-taste-the-world-2014/mediterranean.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Mediterranean&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/time-to-taste-the-world-2014/asian.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Asian&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/time-to-taste-the-world-2014/european.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;European&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that standard CMU catering cookies were also provided.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did try a bit of everything, including stuff I less frequently encounter. Unexpectedly, the experience of hopping from one table to another, and sampling every single item, led me to reflect on how unfamiliar some of these items were to me until later in life, and how my taste in food has expanded considerably in my &lt;em&gt;30s and 40s&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;linking-my-history-of-eating-to-time-to-taste-the-world&#34;&gt;Linking my history of eating to &amp;ldquo;Time to Taste the World&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Most of what I like to eat now is what I never ate or knew existed before I was 30 years old&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This probably goes against &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.theguardian.com/lifeandstyle/wordofmouth/2013/jan/29/changing-tastes-food-and-aging&#34;&gt;most people&amp;rsquo;s eating histories&lt;/a&gt;, but heck, I&amp;rsquo;m a late bloomer, because for various reasons, I had very limited life experiences until my 30s and even more so, my 40s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For fun, I decided to think back about when it was that I first ate or even encountered, each of the items I sampled in &amp;ldquo;Time to Taste the World&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;mediterranean-table&#34;&gt;Mediterranean table&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pita bread: OK, I suppose I probably encountered this first in college, when the dorm cafeteria provided it and I used it to eat with tuna fish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grape leaves stuffed with rice: first time encountered and eaten was as a grad student at CMU in 1997, age 27, from Sree&amp;rsquo;s food truck, actually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hummus: also discovered in Pittsburgh upon arrival in 1997.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Baba ghanoush: also discovered in Pittsburgh upon arrival in 1997.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, I still love grape leaves and hummus. Baba ghanoush I still find a bit harsh and biting, but happily eat it in small quantities at a time. By the way, I should note that I discovered olive oil in 1997 also. At first its strong taste and appearance were confusing to me, but I got used to them, and have been using olive oil since as part of my everyday cooking, in fact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;asian-table&#34;&gt;Asian table&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OK, my parents were immigrants from Taiwan, so these foods have never been unfamiliar to me!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spring rolls: my mother makes them sometimes, and of course much better than the commercial frozen ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chicken wings: some of my favorite childhood food memories involve my mother&amp;rsquo;s chicken wings with soy sauce and ginger. Still my favorite flavor of wings!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Noodle dishes: again, my mother makes this stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.npr.org/2011/08/08/139033757/babys-palate-and-food-memories-shaped-before-birth&#34;&gt;our initial food tastes are actually formed in the womb&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;european-table&#34;&gt;European table&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OK, this is the stuff that I&amp;rsquo;m least familiar with, find overall least appealing, and still encounter surprises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was some &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gorgonzola&#34;&gt;gorgonzola&lt;/a&gt; cheese appetizer thing that I&amp;rsquo;ve had before, and I had some here, but it&amp;rsquo;s not really my thing. I don&amp;rsquo;t think I ever ate something like this until my 30s. The taste and texture is interesting. Not my favorite thing to eat, but I could have a little bit now and then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was also &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prosciutto&#34;&gt;prosciutto&lt;/a&gt; wrapped around some cheesy stuff, something I think I never tried until my 40s. Again, it still tastes weird to me, but I can eat it if I have to. It&amp;rsquo;s not revolting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main thing is that I have historically &lt;em&gt;fundamentally&lt;/em&gt; disliked all dairy. I emerged into the world seemingly hating milk: I don&amp;rsquo;t like the taste, I don&amp;rsquo;t like the smell. I was forced to drink milk as a toddler and basically accepted that I was supposed to drink it, and that it was the only thing to go with cereal, so I tolerated it all the way till I went to college. Then in freshman year in college, I came down with severe puzzling health problems, and finally found out by accident (upon missing breakfast for a couple of days) that cutting out my usual breakfast cereal with milk completely solved my problems: I was simply &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lactose_intolerance&#34;&gt;lactose intolerant&lt;/a&gt;. I cut down significantly on dairy consumption (which for me was only milk for cereal, and cheese on pizza).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point in my late 30s, I found that my lactose intolerance had let up, and with care I could eat some forms of dairy without having problems. Cheese on pizza is OK, if it&amp;rsquo;s not &amp;ldquo;extra thick&amp;rdquo;. Cheese in a serving of lasagna is typically not OK, in the quantities provided. Also, in my late 30s I began developing a taste for hard cheeses, which smell less bad to me, and happen to also have far less lactose, and so I do enjoy eating some hard cheeses occasionally: my favorite is &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gruy%C3%A8re_cheese&#34;&gt;Gruyère&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is some food awkwardness at home, because I&amp;rsquo;m married to Abby, who comes from the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nature.com/news/archaeology-the-milk-revolution-1.13471&#34;&gt;dairy-loving peoples&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;m perpetually having to tolerate the odor of dairy of all kinds at home. This is &lt;em&gt;quite difficult&lt;/em&gt; for me, but such is life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;notes-on-more-recent-food-adventures&#34;&gt;Notes on more recent food adventures&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I explored a tremendous amount of new food when I went vegetarian (for several months) at age 29, and got serious for the first time in my life, about cooking for myself. All kinds of bean, lentils, unfamiliar nuts, spices, herbs, vegetables such as kale, etc. Although I didn&amp;rsquo;t stay vegetarian long, that phase of my life resulted in the biggest explosion in my food taste diversity ever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I didn&amp;rsquo;t even touch beets until my mid-30s, when I was &amp;ldquo;forced&amp;rdquo; to because they came in my &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.kretschmannfarm.com/&#34;&gt;farm subscription box&lt;/a&gt;. A whole bunch of other unfamiliar vegetables have come my way through my annual subscription since I began it. The latest was celeriac, which I had never even heard of until it started showing up in our farm box last year. I figured out stuff to do with it, and I like it! It&amp;rsquo;s fantastic continuing to discover new stuff to cook and eat. Life is not boring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m even learning to eat &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brussels_sprout&#34;&gt;Brussels sprouts&lt;/a&gt;. My initial experiences in my 30s made me want to vomit, but there are ways to cook these to make them much more palatable, and in the past couple of years, I have enough tolerable experiences that I can see myself trying them more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;cookies&#34;&gt;Cookies&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did eat some cookies at the event, but only three, in accordance with &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/03/16/pittsburgh-recorder-society-something-new-recently-recording-our-practice-sessions/&#34;&gt;my recent findings about how many I should eat at a time&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/time-to-taste-the-world-2014/cookie1.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Cookie 1&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/time-to-taste-the-world-2014/cookie2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Cookie 2&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/time-to-taste-the-world-2014/cookie3.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Cookie 3&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s never too late to try new foods. You might be surprised and enjoy something new. And if you don&amp;rsquo;t like it, you don&amp;rsquo;t have to keep eating it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m very grateful to have had the opportunity to try new foods now and then, and add to my enjoyment of life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many thanks to the Modern Languages Department at CMU for sponsoring this little event! I hope many of the students attending it got some exposure to new foods that they will remember for the rest of their lives.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>First time in my life not eating cookies or cake at a party</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/01/31/first-time-in-my-life-not-eating-cookies-or-cake-at-a-party/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Jan 2014 23:11:21 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/01/31/first-time-in-my-life-not-eating-cookies-or-cake-at-a-party/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I was at a birthday party. There were cookies of various varieties around. Also, there was a birthday cake. I did not eat the cookies or the cake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have to say this was a first for me. Usually, my rule at parties is &amp;ldquo;anything goes&amp;rdquo;. But it was time to admit that this rule caused many problems. If I load up on junk food at a party, I end up feeling crappy afterwards: maybe bloated, maybe sleepy, but in any case, I end up being a &lt;em&gt;worse guest&lt;/em&gt; to be around. And after going home I don&amp;rsquo;t feel well either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is exactly what happened to me just two days ago at a party where &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/01/29/my-no-cookie-rule-a-photo-update/&#34;&gt;I ate two cookies unnecessarily&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;good-food-to-drive-out-the-bad&#34;&gt;Good food to drive out the bad&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was plenty of good, healthy food at the party: the hosts provided great appetizers and entrees, and guests made and brought in delicious contributions also. There was no reason to pig out on the junk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, a salad Abby assembled when we arrived at the party:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/abby-salad.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;future&#34;&gt;Future&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My job is not yet done. It turns out that at the party, although I mostly ate healthy food, I also ate pita chips and similar bready items along with hummus that left me not feeling optimal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I&amp;rsquo;m extending my rule to these bready chip things also. Note that I have not yet banned potato chips or corn tortilla chips!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My no-cookie rule: a photo update</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/01/29/my-no-cookie-rule-a-photo-update/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2014 21:50:22 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/01/29/my-no-cookie-rule-a-photo-update/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Two weeks ago &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/01/16/a-system-for-quitting-eating-cookies/&#34;&gt;I vowed never to eat a cookie again, unless I took a photo of it and posted it&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was at a party tonight, and originally saw no cookies, so I thought I was safe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was wrong. After hours of eating a lot of pretty good food, I saw that cookies were brought out and place next to the coffee in back. I paused, remembering my promise, but then thought, &amp;ldquo;what the heck&amp;rdquo;, and &amp;ldquo;carefully&amp;rdquo; chose just two cookies, photographed them, and ate them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/cookie1.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Cookie&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/cookie2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Cookie&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;consequences&#34;&gt;Consequences&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first observation was that it was actually not so easy to choose two cookies to take. Visually, on close inspection, I did not actually believe that any of the cookies were really going to be so tasty. In fact, the more deliberate I was, the more I visualized that these things as assembled sugar, fat, and wheat bombs serving no useful purpose for my body.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I could have just stopped there, and chosen not to take any cookies, but habit or curiosity caused me to take two anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that I didn&amp;rsquo;t really enjoy the cookies. They weren&amp;rsquo;t so good. Also, they seemed much bigger when I started eating them, in that I had enough and wanted to stop but felt like I should finish what I started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I proceeded to feel bloated and sleepy. I went home really thinking about the stupid thing that I did, and the fact that I was going to have to write about my experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;future&#34;&gt;Future&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suspect that I will eventually break my habit of eating cookies at social occasions where they present themselves. I had a really bad experience tonight. Because I documented it, I will remember it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2014-01-31&#34;&gt;(Update of 2014-01-31)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out what happened &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/01/31/first-time-in-my-life-not-eating-cookies-or-cake-at-a-party/&#34;&gt;two days later&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A system for quitting eating cookies?</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/01/16/a-system-for-quitting-eating-cookies/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2014 20:29:33 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/01/16/a-system-for-quitting-eating-cookies/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I decided last night, after eating too many cookies at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/Steel-City-Ukuleles/events/154668232/&#34;&gt;Steel City Ukuleles meetup&lt;/a&gt;, that I have to stop eating cookies. I cannot justify them on the grounds of health (and how crappy I sometimes feel after eating them).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/scu-desserts.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Steel City Ukuleles after new year party&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My &amp;ldquo;creative&amp;rdquo; idea that I shared with Abby: I will never eat a cookie again in my life unless I take a photo of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, the cookie has somehow appeal to me so much that I bother to pause, &lt;em&gt;deliberately&lt;/em&gt; take a photo, and risk social embarrassment (and better yet, explain my system to people so they know I&amp;rsquo;m not supposed to eat cookies).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, I must post publicly any cookie that I eat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;ll see how well this system works. I can sense cookie opportunities coming up already!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2014-01-29&#34;&gt;(Update of 2014-01-29)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out what happened &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/01/29/my-no-cookie-rule-a-photo-update/&#34;&gt;two days later&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2014-01-31&#34;&gt;(Update of 2014-01-31)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out what happened &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/01/31/first-time-in-my-life-not-eating-cookies-or-cake-at-a-party/&#34;&gt;four days later&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;current-updates&#34;&gt;(Current updates)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For current updates, just check out the &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/cookies/&#34;&gt;cookies category&lt;/a&gt; to find out when I last mentioned cookies.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Broccoli and friends</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/11/01/broccoli-and-friends/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2013 18:26:40 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/11/01/broccoli-and-friends/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Today I saw an article about &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2013/11/03/magazine/broccolis-extreme-makeover.html&#34;&gt;marketing broccoli and other vegetables&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By coincidence, I had this morning whipped up a vegetable dish in the kitchen that included some broccoli.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-my-father-got-me-to-eat-broccoli&#34;&gt;How my father got me to eat broccoli&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the basic story of why I ate broccoli as a child and through adulthood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I distinctly remember not really liking broccoli as a toddler of around two and a half to three years old (my childhood memories do not go earlier than age two and a half). I also remember a major turning point, after which I &amp;ldquo;happily&amp;rdquo; ate it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My mother was unsuccessful in nagging me to eat my brocolli. It was when my father called broccoli florets &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;baby trees&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo;. All of a sudden it seemed cool to eat them, as though I were a large beast swooping down from the sky (I liked trees and all my youthful drawings and watercolors included them; I have fond memories of sitting outside under a tree).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;simple-vegetable-medley&#34;&gt;Simple vegetable medley&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/broccoli-medley.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Broccoli and other vegetables&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I used a wok, but for the volume, not at high heat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Time: 25 minutes&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;olive oil&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;onion, sliced&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;carrots, sliced&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;celery stalks, sliced&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;broccoli florets and thinly sliced stems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;assorted peppers, sliced&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;garlic&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;seasoning mix&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically, I used what was at hand from our farm box subscription.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still love to eat those florets as though I were a giant beast feasting on trees.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>All India: great new Indian restaurant in Pittsburgh</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/07/25/all-india-great-new-indian-restaurant-in-pittsburgh/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Jul 2013 22:22:09 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/07/25/all-india-great-new-indian-restaurant-in-pittsburgh/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have a new favorite Indian restaurant in Pittsburgh: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.allindiapgh.com/&#34;&gt;All India&lt;/a&gt; in Oakland on North Craig Street.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being a fan of Indian food, I&amp;rsquo;ve tried basically all the Indian restaurants in the city for over a decade in Pittsburgh. Many are not worth mentioning at all. Some I have enjoyed to a degree, but none have really excited me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The relatively new All India is now &lt;em&gt;my clear favorite&lt;/em&gt;. Recently, I went with some friends there for their lunch buffet, and it was great. A large selection, very fresh and tasty. Nice interior with pleasant furniture and settings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not really a restaurant reviewer, so I apologize for not being more specific.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I took Abby there for a dinner date tonight. Unfortunately, I accidentally cracked apart a tooth in a freak accident while on my second plate, so we had to leave early. But we will definitely go again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first plate, which I finished:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/all-india.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;All India&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Primanti&#39;s and the Cathedral of Learning</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/01/07/primantis-and-the-cathedral-of-learning/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Jan 2013 21:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/01/07/primantis-and-the-cathedral-of-learning/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today I was scheduled to do the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/04/i-had-no-choice-but-to-barefoot-climb-the-cathedral-of-learning/&#34;&gt;Cathedral of Learning stair climb again, two repetitions like last time&lt;/a&gt;. Since I had stayed later at work than expected, I was hungry already, so I decided I would go do the two reps and then eat a lot of food.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;John was still around at work too and he was interested in doing two reps for the first time (years ago we&amp;rsquo;d periodically done one), so we went. We had a plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;two-reps&#34;&gt;Two reps&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did both reps barefoot this time, and with a fully stuffed backpack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided to lead the way with a slightly slow pace, in order to guarantee we would go faster during the second rep. We saw two people in shorts doing reps also. Both John and I were in street clothing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first rep we did in 9:07 (on Friday, alone, I had done 9:02).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This time I timed the break, because this is actually important information for the future when comparing improvement. We took a random break of 10:42 before doing the second rep, which we did in 8:54 (at some point before floor 31, we had an opportunity to overtake the other two people, who were on their third rep, and so I decided to just kick it up a notch for the rest of the way up).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-progression-plan&#34;&gt;My progression plan&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;John liked going two steps up at a time, but I am still on one by one, because it&amp;rsquo;s easier on my quads. My intuition tells me that a good cadence is important for efficiency, and until my quads are strong enough, I cannot keep a good cadence going up two steps at a time. Right now I&amp;rsquo;m focusing on simply getting some endurance and efficiency, and increasing the number of reps. After maybe two or three weeks of this, I will work on powering up two steps at a time over maybe no more than ten floors at a time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was amused to see the man wearing one of the old Rachel Carson Trail Challenge T-shirts that I also have, from 2008 (when I was a volunteer, not a participant as I was in 2005-2007). Also, the woman said she had done the Fight for Air Climb last year and placed third in the women&amp;rsquo;s division, I think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;primanti-s&#34;&gt;Primanti&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then we went to &lt;a href=&#34;http://primantibros.com/&#34;&gt;Primanti&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/a&gt; in Oakland, as planned. I stuffed myself with a huge roast beef sandwich, my usual order when I go there (just a couple of times a year).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I heard recently that Primanti&amp;rsquo;s may be &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wpxi.com/news/news/local/primanti-bros-receives-investment-hopes-expanding-/nTmGP/&#34;&gt;expanding nationwide&lt;/a&gt;. Cool! Why should the Pittsburgh area be the only one privileged to enjoy the huge &amp;ldquo;fully loaded&amp;rdquo; sandwiches with fries and cole slaw inside?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/primantis-roast-beef-oakland.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Primanti&amp;#39;s roast beef sandwich&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A winter red cabbage slaw for the New Year</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/01/01/a-winter-red-cabbage-slaw-for-the-new-year/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2013 21:34:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/01/01/a-winter-red-cabbage-slaw-for-the-new-year/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Happy New Year!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/red-cabbage-slaw.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Red cabbage slaw&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For a party, I used what was at hand at home to make something to share. I decided on a red cabbage slaw, after doing a Google search for ingredients and seeing some recipes. I didn&amp;rsquo;t follow any one recipe, but merged a couple of ideas. Since people seemed to eat up the cabbage slaw, and several complimented me on it and asked for the recipe, here it is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;recipe-for-red-cabbage-slaw&#34;&gt;Recipe for red cabbage slaw&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; red cabbage, sliced thin&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2 &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.orangepippin.com/apples/goldrush&#34;&gt;Gold Rush&lt;/a&gt; apples, peeled and sliced thin&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;4 carrots, grated&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.organicgardeninfo.com/growing-cylindra-beets.html&#34;&gt;long beet&lt;/a&gt;, grated&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; red onion, sliced thin&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dressing:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;6 tablespoons extra virgin olive oil&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;6 tablespoons raw apple cider vinegar&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;4 tablespoons honey mustard&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2 cloves of garlic, minced&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Toppings:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;pecans&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;walnuts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;raisins&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Put all the prepared ingredients into a large bowl.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mix the dressing into the bowl.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover and leave in the refrigerator for 24 hours. Stir again once or twice during that period to make sure everything is even.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;notes&#34;&gt;Notes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some recipes for cabbage slaw that I saw called for added sugar, but given the specific ingredients I chose, there was no need at all for extra sugar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I chose some nuts that seemed to make sense. Other nuts could be used also, or left out if someone is allergic to nuts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I could see dried cranberries being used instead of raisins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other substitutions are easy to imagine also; in fact, my recipe involved substitutions for ingredients in recipes I found online.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;thanks&#34;&gt;Thanks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The red cabbage, Gold Rush apples, carrots, long beet happen to have come from our &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.kretschmannfarm.com/Winter%20Boxes/Winter%20boxes.htm&#34;&gt;winter box subscription from Kretschmann Farm&lt;/a&gt;. Abby and I are really happy that they offer a winter box subscription as well as the regular season subscription, so that we can continue to get quality organic, local produce all year long.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having a subscription not only allows us to eat seasonally, but also explore foods we may not necessarily have eaten much of or even seen before. For example, I like these long beets and Gold Rush apples.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>East End Food Co-op Winterfest 2012</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/12/15/east-end-food-co-op-winterfest-2012/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Dec 2012 23:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/12/15/east-end-food-co-op-winterfest-2012/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Abby and I went to the annual &lt;a href=&#34;http://eastendfoodcoop.com/&#34;&gt;East End Food Co-op&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/events/433775433346947/&#34;&gt;Winterfest&lt;/a&gt; again, as we have done with John for the third year now. It was held again at the Jewish Community Center in Squirrel Hill.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/eefc-winterfest-2012/flyer.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Flyer&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;people&#34;&gt;People&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/eefc-winterfest-2012/people.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;People&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There seemed to be more people than last year, possibly because of the very mild weather this December. I remember marching or driving in the snow in the past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As usual, there were children of all ages, from a tiny baby to older kids running around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;food&#34;&gt;Food&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/eefc-winterfest-2012/food.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Food&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There was a relatively limited selection of vegetarian and vegan food. There was not as much food as last year, and not as much variety either. Some items (such as the tasty latkes) ran out quickly, so that when I went back for seconds, they were already gone. I guess it&amp;rsquo;s hard to calculate how much food is needed each year; last year there was so much left over that we were told to box up leftovers to take home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were surprised that there was no salad. There were many appetizer-type breaded foods and some generic-looking cheese cubes. Starved for more protein options, I tried to load up on a lentil-based spread, but quantities of that were limited. The food selection and allocation was strange this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In another twist, all rather than some of the desserts this year were apparently gluten-free. This was great for Abby, since she has discovered over the past year that she does well to minimize wheat in her diet. I have also noticed that I also do better without wheat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;music&#34;&gt;Music&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was a little confused this year because the local live musical entertainment was not identified in the flyers or online. I asked on the event page and even asked on the Food Co-op&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/pages/East-End-Food-Co-op/125568984134681&#34;&gt;Facebook page&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://plus.google.com/101694168941295846546&#34;&gt;Google+ page&lt;/a&gt;, but nobody responded. It seems that nobody is really engaging in conversations on these sites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, we went and there were three local guitarists who performed solo sets, one after another, while we were stuffing ourselves with food and hanging out, running into some people we knew.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/eefc-winterfest-2012/guitarist1.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Guitarist&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/eefc-winterfest-2012/guitarist2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Guitarist&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/eefc-winterfest-2012/guitarist3.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Guitarist&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Abby and I felt bad because the musical format didn&amp;rsquo;t seem to work so well. A solo guitarist speaking about his or her musical selections and then performing from the heart seems out of place at an event like this that is not quiet and intimate, where the musicians are just background entertainment. A bigger, louder group commands more attention and engagement, especially if playing uptempo dance-oriented music. Here, we could barely hear the solo guitarists talk and sing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We left the Winterfest relatively early, after about two hours there (around 9:39 PM, so I don&amp;rsquo;t know if there were other musicians after the three we saw. We left slightly early because we were still tired from all we&amp;rsquo;d done over the week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was good to see so many people come to the Winterfest this year, but the format of the food and the musical entertainment was kind of strange. Nevertheless, I welcomed the annual opportunity to hang out and eat with other members and supporters of the East End Food Co-op.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My favorite Uncle Sam&#39;s sub</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/12/08/my-favorite-uncle-sams-sub/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Dec 2012 21:24:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/12/08/my-favorite-uncle-sams-sub/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Last Sunday, after a long first rehearsal for the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/11/24/preparing-to-play-irish-flute-in-the-holiday-ball/&#34;&gt;Holiday Ball Orchestra&lt;/a&gt;, I was starving, and since Abby was off in Weirton performing in a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pittsburghmandolinsociety.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Mandolin Orchestra&lt;/a&gt;, I decided to indulge in a dinner alone at the local &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.unclesamssubs.com/&#34;&gt;Uncle Sam&amp;rsquo;s Subs&lt;/a&gt; in Squirrel Hill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been eating at Uncle Sam&amp;rsquo;s Subs periodically since moving to Pittsburgh 15 years ago. I&amp;rsquo;ve tried all the options (I ate out a lot more during my early grad school days in Pittsburgh), including, during my vegetarian phase, the really tasty Mediterranean, Vegetarian Combo, Roma Vegetable, Vegetable Florentine, and Grilled Portabella subs (see the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.unclesamssubs.com/menu&#34;&gt;menu&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nowadays I indulge in an Uncle Sam&amp;rsquo;s sub only maybe two or three times a year, as a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/06/16/the-joy-of-eating-ice-cream-for-breakfast/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;cheat&amp;rdquo; meal&lt;/a&gt; when I&amp;rsquo;m feeling the big craving for one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; eat in, because they give you a whole bunch of fries for free when you eat in rather than take out. For me, it&amp;rsquo;s all about the fries!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve settled on the Uncle Sam&amp;rsquo;s Special Steak as my usual selection these days, because it strikes a good balance of cheese steak, mushrooms, peppers, and cheese.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;before-and-after-photos&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Before&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;after&amp;rdquo; photos&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Uncle Sam&amp;rsquo;s Special steak:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/uncle-sams-subs/uneaten.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Uncle Sam&amp;#39;s Special Steak&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I ate the whole thing! It took me some time:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/uncle-sams-subs/eaten.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Finished eating&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I was very satisfied afterwards.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/uncle-sams-subs/franklin.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Full Franklin&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I totally recommend Uncle Sam&amp;rsquo;s Subs if you&amp;rsquo;re very hungry and need to refuel. Whether you&amp;rsquo;re an omnivore or a vegetarian, check it out! Eat in for the fries. And make sure to get your metabolism up by exercising or something beforehand, because else you&amp;rsquo;ll get carb coma.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reflections on Food Day</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/10/24/reflections-on-food-day/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Oct 2012 22:38:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/10/24/reflections-on-food-day/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/food-day-2012-breakfast-1.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Soup and veggies&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A year ago I celebrated &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.foodday.org/&#34;&gt;Food Day&lt;/a&gt; for the first time, by sharing &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/24/every-day-is-food-day/&#34;&gt;some reflections on what food means to me&lt;/a&gt;. Today I review my reflections and some more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;buying-food&#34;&gt;Buying food&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I still take care to shop carefully for groceries and make our own tasty meals to eat. Some of our sources:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://kretschmannfarm.com/&#34;&gt;Kretschmann Farm&lt;/a&gt; CSA subscription for local produce&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.localharvest.org/miseras-organic-farm-M14896&#34;&gt;Misera&amp;rsquo;s Organic Farm&lt;/a&gt; for local &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/24/whats-a-nice-acorn-squash-like-you-doing-in-a-pot-of-spicy-lentils/&#34;&gt;chickens&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lewisfamilyfarms.com/&#34;&gt;Lewis Family Farms&lt;/a&gt; for local beef&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://pine-richland.patch.com/articles/stoney-lane-farm-a-little-bit-country-in-suburbia&#34;&gt;Stoney Lane Farm&lt;/a&gt; for local &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/28/thankful-for-the-free-range-orange-yolked-eggs/&#34;&gt;eggs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.traderjoes.com/&#34;&gt;Trader Joe&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.eastendfood.coop/&#34;&gt;East End Food Co-op&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our food choices are based on our concerns for both &lt;em&gt;health&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;sustainability&lt;/em&gt;. Our choices may have an impact on one or the other or both.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;cooking&#34;&gt;Cooking&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I started my blog over a year ago, I had thought I would be posting more about cooking, since I was doing a good amount of it, but as it turned out, during this year (2012), Abby took over almost all of the cooking for us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;diet&#34;&gt;Diet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both Abby and I have experimented in paleo directions in the past year. As a reminder, this doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean that we&amp;rsquo;re just going around chowing down on all the meat we can eat. It does mean that we have&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;considerably increased our consumption of vegetables&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;increased our consumption of various fats and oils&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;reduced our consumption of carbs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-question-of-carbs&#34;&gt;The question of carbs&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What we seemed to discover was that we needed some base level of carbs in order to maintain energy and weight levels. Through experimentation, Abby has focused on getting carbs through potatoes and sweet potatoes primarily, going almost completely off wheat. I, on the other hand, am still hooked on rice; I also still eat some wheat, but frankly, I can tell from the effects that I would probably do best to eliminate it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;rice-disaster&#34;&gt;Rice disaster?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, I wondered about brown rice, and even briefly experimented with &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/07/is-brown-rice-healthy-or-not/&#34;&gt;switching to white rice&lt;/a&gt;. The white rice experiment was a fast failure: the high glycemic index and lack of fiber didn&amp;rsquo;t help me at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More recently, there have been reports of &lt;em&gt;brown rice&lt;/em&gt; in particular having &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.consumerreports.org/cro/magazine/2012/11/arsenic-in-your-food/index.htm&#34;&gt;high levels of arsenic&lt;/a&gt;. This is rather disturbing, and Abby and I have agreed that I need to quickly re-evaluate my consumption of brown rice. I&amp;rsquo;ve committed to trying out some alternative source of calories/fiber.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-breakfast&#34;&gt;My breakfast&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My breakfast has remained fairly &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/01/26/improving-my-breakfast-and-other-meals/&#34;&gt;stable&lt;/a&gt; since &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/23/paleo-diet-experimentation/&#34;&gt;I quit oatmeal&lt;/a&gt;. Basically, I eat&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;veggies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;eggs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;nuts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a prune&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Depending on how I feel and what&amp;rsquo;s available, occasionally I&amp;rsquo;ll eat some bacon or fish, and sometimes I&amp;rsquo;ll add some sweet potatoes or other carbs, but typically that&amp;rsquo;s it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(I stopped the flax seeds, largely out of inconvenience of grinding them!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s what I happened to eat today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/food-day-2012-breakfast-1.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Soup and veggies&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/food-day-2012-breakfast-2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Eggs&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The soup and veggies were leftovers from big batches Abby or I had made earlier:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;my cauliflower leaf soup with garlic, carrots, sweet potatoes, curry powder, extra virgin olive oil&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;my stir-fried cauliflower florets with garlic, green peppers, coconut oil&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Abby&amp;rsquo;s spaghetti squash with onion and other stuff&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And on top of that I also ate two fried eggs with walnuts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-lunch-and-dinner&#34;&gt;My lunch and dinner&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lunch and dinner were combinations of various leftovers, all originally made by Abby (hence my not knowing the exact ingredients):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ground beef stew with green peppers, jalapeno, onion, various seasoning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;slow-cooked chicken with veggies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;leftover kale and onion&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;dinner included sauteed zucchini and other veggies Abby cooked tonight&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;brown rice&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;fasting&#34;&gt;Fasting&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes I deliberately fast for a meal or two. This happens when I just don&amp;rsquo;t feel all that hungry. I treat that as a signal from my body that I don&amp;rsquo;t really need to eat. My experiments have convinced me that &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Intermittent_fasting&#34;&gt;intermittent fasting&lt;/a&gt; helps with fat loss and mental clarity. It also helps me remember to be grateful, when I do eat again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are human beings, not robots. We need food. And food isn&amp;rsquo;t just &amp;ldquo;fuel&amp;rdquo;. It lives or has lived. It is complex. I am grateful to be living in a land of plenty, and that Abby has taken so much care to make varied and tasty dishes for us. But as the recent reports on arsenic reminds me, there is much we must continue to do to prevent the degradation of what we eat.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My end-of-summer vegetable medley recipe</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/09/17/end-of-summer-vegetable-medley-recipe/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Sep 2012 08:41:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/09/17/end-of-summer-vegetable-medley-recipe/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/end-of-summer-vegetable-medley.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin&amp;#39;s end-of-summer vegetable medley&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I whipped up what I&amp;rsquo;ll call my &amp;ldquo;end-of-summer vegetable medley&amp;rdquo; (since summer is basically over now), using ingredients we happened to have on hand, from &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/kretschmann-farm/&#34;&gt;Kretschmann Farm&lt;/a&gt; as well as from Abby&amp;rsquo;s parents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;recipe&#34;&gt;Recipe&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;equipment&#34;&gt;Equipment&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Large skillet (I happened to use a wok)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;ingredients&#34;&gt;Ingredients&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Oil for high heat (I used coconut oil)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One green pepper&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One green zucchini&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One yellow zucchini&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One tomato&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Garlic, one large clove&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Seasoning mix (I used sea salt and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.traderjoes.com/fearless-flyer/article.asp?article_id=539&#34;&gt;Trader Joe&amp;rsquo;s 21 Seasoning Salute&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fresh cilantro&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Extra virgin olive oil&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;preparation&#34;&gt;Preparation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Green pepper: slice into strips.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Green zucchini: slice into thin coins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yellow zucchini: slice into thin coins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tomato: slice thinly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Garlic: crush and mince a large clove (or more if you prefer).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cilantro: chop up a bunch of fresh cilantro.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;cooking&#34;&gt;Cooking&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the ingredients are ready, the rest only takes a few minutes at high heat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heat the oil in the skillet to high heat. When the skillet is ready, put the green pepper and zucchinis into the skillet and toss/stir to coat with oil. Then add the seasoning mix and continue to toss/stir for a while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the vegetables look to be half done (to your liking; I prefer them to retain some bite rather than be soggy), add the tomato and garlic and continue to toss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When everything is almost done, add the cilantro and toss/stir briefly, then turn off the heat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Add extra virgin olive oil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Joy of Eating Ice Cream for Breakfast</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/06/16/the-joy-of-eating-ice-cream-for-breakfast/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Jun 2012 19:27:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/06/16/the-joy-of-eating-ice-cream-for-breakfast/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/coffee-bean-blast.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Trader Joe&amp;#39;s Coffee Bean Blast ice cream&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Recently I started eating ice cream for breakfast. I was amused because this was something I haven&amp;rsquo;t done since I was a child, when my sister and I managed for a while to convince our parents to let us eat ice cream for breakfast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is there a contradiction between my eating ice cream for breakfast and my supposedly paying attention to my health?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-my-sister-and-i-got-to-eat-ice-cream-as-kids&#34;&gt;How my sister and I got to eat ice cream as kids&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As kids, my sister and I loved ice cream, of course. We managed to find a way to sometimes eat it for breakfast. Basically, we volunteered to make breakfast on some weekends. We had found some kid-oriented &amp;ldquo;cookbooks&amp;rdquo; at a garage sale or something at some point, and we learned about cinnamon toast and other such &amp;ldquo;American&amp;rdquo; breakfasts that were foreign to our parents. It was fun for us to take charge of breakfast once in a while, and have an excuse to make super-sugary concoctions to eat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frankly, it was easy enough for us in general to just say, &amp;ldquo;We&amp;rsquo;re eating American style&amp;rdquo;, in order to avoid eating rice porridge with dried shrimp bits and pork bone broth and greens (to tell the truth, I actually liked that, but at some point wanted to eat &amp;ldquo;American&amp;rdquo; like my classmates). But it was even more fun to be able to say, &amp;ldquo;We found this recipe in a &lt;em&gt;book&lt;/em&gt;.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A couple of times, we managed to get ice cream into the picture. We must have found a recipe that called for it. We got frozen waffles, and prepared them with syrup and topped with ice cream. I remember that being pretty good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;but-ice-cream-is-not-a-good-food&#34;&gt;But ice cream is not a good food&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have to explain that Abby and I don&amp;rsquo;t eat ice cream much any more. We&amp;rsquo;ve found that it is too sugary and makes us feel tired or bloated in large quantities. You don&amp;rsquo;t have to be &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/paleo/&#34;&gt;paleo&lt;/a&gt; to understand and experience the drawbacks of ice cream (not that we&amp;rsquo;re strictly paleo anyway).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I&amp;rsquo;m a big believer in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.t-nation.com/free_online_article/most_recent/in_defense_of_cheat_days&#34;&gt;intermittent cheating&lt;/a&gt;, so I&amp;rsquo;m happy to eat ice cream now and then as a special treat, but otherwise, I don&amp;rsquo;t really need it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-i-had-to-eat-ice-cream-for-breakfast&#34;&gt;Why I had to eat ice cream for breakfast&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t buy this bucket of Trader Joe&amp;rsquo;s Coffee Bean Blast ice cream; Abby did. She thought it would be a nice post-&lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/hiking/&#34;&gt;hike&lt;/a&gt; treat. Unfortunately, it has turned out in the past months that whenever we go out on a weekend for a hike or some other outdoors adventure, we come back in the evening, and it&amp;rsquo;s too late to eat this ice cream.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem is caffeine. Eating this ice cream would mess up our night of sleep. In fact, I verified this once, eating some of the ice cream in the evening: oops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frustrated, I didn&amp;rsquo;t know when I &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; eat this coffee ice cream. Clearly, the only time I could possibly eat it would be before late afternoon. Furthermore, the only safe context for me to eat something like this would be after I exercised. Since I have a preference for exercising in the morning before breakfast anyway, the perfect time for eating this ice cream was breakfast. Generally, after exercising, I can eat sugary foods to an extent without compromising my energy levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-i-did-to-earn-my-breakfast&#34;&gt;What I did to earn my breakfast&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went for a five-mile &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/running/&#34;&gt;run&lt;/a&gt; in &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/frick-park/&#34;&gt;Frick Park&lt;/a&gt;. I wore my Vibram FiveFingers Bikila LS shoes.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/vibram-fivefingers-bikila-ls.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Vibram FiveFingers Bikila LS shoes&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-real-breakfast&#34;&gt;My real breakfast&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At breakfast, I eat only two spoons of ice cream, actually. That is enough to satisfy me. At this rate, I&amp;rsquo;ll take forever to finish that tub. More reason for me to exercise every morning this summer!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I followed up with the rest of my breakfast, which is typical of what I&amp;rsquo;ve been eating since &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/23/paleo-diet-experimentation/&#34;&gt;completely abandoning my former oatmeal breakfast&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/breakfast-brentwood.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;My breakfast along with Brentwood 5K entry form&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Two &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/28/thankful-for-the-free-range-orange-yolked-eggs/&#34;&gt;eggs&lt;/a&gt; fried with spice mix and olive oil&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Spinach from our &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.kretschmannfarm.com/&#34;&gt;Kretschmann Farm&lt;/a&gt; box&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sweet potatoes and bacon bits&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Walnuts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Strawberries&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, and Abby I have signed up for the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.brentwood5k.com/&#34;&gt;Brentwood Firecracker 5K race&lt;/a&gt;. I last did that race eleven years ago, in 2001. I have a serious goal of beating my time from that year!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have only two more weeks of training with ice cream, before running the race. Wish me luck!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tasty Vietnamese lunch at Thanh Tòng in Eden Center, and how we chose to eat there</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/06/14/tasty-vietnamese-lunch-at-thanh-tong-in-eden-center/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Jun 2012 22:20:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/06/14/tasty-vietnamese-lunch-at-thanh-tong-in-eden-center/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Some weeks ago when Abby and I were in DC to stay with my sister and her husband in order to see and help out with our new &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/nephew/&#34;&gt;nephew&lt;/a&gt;, we took a trip to go to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.gw-supermarket.com/&#34;&gt;Great Wall supermarket&lt;/a&gt; in Virginia to buy groceries for the household.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;eden-center&#34;&gt;Eden Center&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But on the way, we stopped at this place we found about called &lt;a href=&#34;http://edencenter.com/&#34;&gt;Eden Center&lt;/a&gt; that is unique all-Vietnamese shopping/dining center with over a hundred stores. We figured on just exploring a little, then eating lunch, before heading further out to Great Wall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We didn&amp;rsquo;t feel like looking up reviews or anything to get a quick lunch. While we were wandering around, Abby ended up picking a place to eat. It was called &amp;ldquo;Thanh Tòng&amp;rdquo; (we don&amp;rsquo;t know any Vietnamese at all, by the way), and we ordered two items and they quickly arrived and we had a very filling lunch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How did Abby choose where to eat, given the bewildering number of choices?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/thanh-tong-salad.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Salad at Thanh Tòng&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/thanh-tong-soup.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Soup at Thanh Tòng&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-we-chose&#34;&gt;How we chose&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were quite a few restaurants in Eden Center that we saw as we were just walking around. In theory, we could have looked up reviews or looked at menu selections and prices to decide where to eat, but we didn&amp;rsquo;t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby basically just saw this one little hole-in-the-wall place, remembered it, and we came back to it after looking for alternatives, and she said, &amp;ldquo;Let&amp;rsquo;s eat here.&amp;rdquo; I asked her why, and she noted that the place was small, there were &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; Vietnamese people (as opposed to &amp;ldquo;foreigners&amp;rdquo;) in there eating (and a reasonable number of them) and they looked happy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://edencenter.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/thanhtong-150x150.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Store front&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;

(Photo by Corbo E. from Eden Center web site)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That sounded like reasonable logic to me. I&amp;rsquo;ve applied similar logic in the past, when in an unfamiliar city looking for Chinese or Indian food. We&amp;rsquo;re not really interested in fancy furniture or elaborately &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Purple_prose&#34;&gt;purple-prosed&lt;/a&gt; menu items, just affordable and tasty &amp;ldquo;authentic&amp;rdquo; meals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby&amp;rsquo;s choice worked out pretty well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;lunch&#34;&gt;Lunch&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://edencenter.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/06/thanhtong2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Menu board&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;

(Photo by Corbo E. from Eden Center web site)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;salad&#34;&gt;Salad&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The salad was large and the main novelty for us was all the bamboo shoots that provided crunch and fiber. It was a filling, tasty salad that came topped with shrimp and a sweet, tangy dressing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;soup&#34;&gt;Soup&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The soup had thick noodles and broth and was chock full of pork, shrimp, scallions, basil, etc. It was satisfying and I slurped down the rest of the broth after Abby was full already with her share.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The time-honored strategy of finding a decent place to eat by looking inside and seeing who&amp;rsquo;s eating and how fast the action is served us well when grabbing some Vietnamese lunch in Eden Center.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>