<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Jacob Van Eyck on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/jacob-van-eyck/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Jacob Van Eyck on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/jacob-van-eyck/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>I never expected my first wooden recorders to be Renaissance recorders</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/21/i-never-expected-my-first-wooden-recorders-to-be-renaissance-recorders/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2013 21:24:54 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/21/i-never-expected-my-first-wooden-recorders-to-be-renaissance-recorders/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/10/20/the-biggest-pittsburgh-recorder-society-meeting-i-have-attended-in-two-years/&#34;&gt;Yesterday, I noted&lt;/a&gt; that I picked up two recorders during the Pittsburgh Recorder Society meeting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They were these &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.vonhuene.com/Default.aspx?tabid=42&#34;&gt;Renaissance&lt;/a&gt; instruments:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mollenhauer-kynseker-recorders/boxed.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;In boxes&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mollenhauer-kynseker-recorders/assembled.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Assembled&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nice maple recorders, Mollenhauer Kynseker models:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mollenhauer.com/en/catalogue?page=shop.product_details&amp;amp;flypage=flypage.tpl&amp;amp;product_id=170&amp;amp;category_id=121&#34;&gt;Kynseker Soprano 4107&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mollenhauer.com/en/catalogue?page=shop.product_details&amp;amp;flypage=flypage.tpl&amp;amp;product_id=172&amp;amp;category_id=121&#34;&gt;Kynseker Alto 4217&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are my very first wooden recorders. All my other recorders are Yamaha plastic recorders, because they are inexpensive and easy to maintain. I&amp;rsquo;ve periodically considered buying wooden recorders, but to get some of clearly higher quality than the plastic ones is expensive!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-bother-with-renaissance&#34;&gt;Why bother with Renaissance?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I jumped at the opportunity to bid in the auction for these two Renaissance recorders to acquire them inexpensively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Up till recently, I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t have considered buying Renaissance recorders at all, because of the difference in construction and tonal quality from the Baroque-style recorders that I have and that we play in the Pittsburgh Recorder Society meetings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this summer at the Mideast early music workshop, I paid attention to people playing Renaissance recorders (for Renaissance music and other music too) and found the louder and &amp;ldquo;reedier&amp;rdquo; sound intriguing. I could see myself playing them in contexts in which this kind of sound quality would be advantageous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So now I have these two wooden recorders to play with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that the solo soprano recorder music by Jacob van Eyck from the Renaissance that &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/28/my-first-appearance-on-a-music-recital-program/&#34;&gt;I played last year&lt;/a&gt; would have entirely been suited to my new soprano Renaissance recorder! I may revisit that music to play it on the new instrument.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My first appearance on a music recital program</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/07/28/my-first-appearance-on-a-music-recital-program/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Jul 2012 23:41:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/07/28/my-first-appearance-on-a-music-recital-program/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-ars-recital-summer-2012.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Pittsburgh Recorder Society spring 2012 recital program&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A month and a half ago, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/06/15/preparing-for-my-first-solo-flute-performance-notes-on-perfectionism-and-high-standards/&#34;&gt;I reported on an upcoming music recital I was going to perform in&lt;/a&gt;. In fact, I did perform, on Sunday, June 17, 2012. &lt;em&gt;It was my first appearance in my life on a musical recital program, and my first time solo on modern flute.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The event was an informal spring dinner party/recital at Helen&amp;rsquo;s home for the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.andrew.cmu.edu/user/lukas/pcars/Welcome.html&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh chapter of the American Recorder Society&lt;/a&gt;. (By the way, we also have a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/PittsburghRecorderSociety&#34;&gt;Facebook page&lt;/a&gt; now.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why did I put myself on the spot, by volunteering to play, and what did I choose to play?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-recital-program&#34;&gt;The recital program&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The program had several of us perform a dozen musical selections in a variety combinations (also performing at the end but not listed on the program were Mike and Fred).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(This year, Abby had submitted for the program a piece for Bulgarian tambura, &amp;ldquo;Ihtimansko Horo&amp;rdquo;, and this is on the printed program, but at the last minute, she had problems as a result of restringing her instrument during the week, and ended up not performing, unfortunately.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Myself, I had chosen three musical selections to play:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Doen Daphne D&amp;rsquo;over Schoone Maeght&amp;rdquo; from Jacob Van Eyck&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Der Fluyten Lust-Hof&amp;rdquo;; solo soprano recorder&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lachlann Dubh (Scottish slow air); Baroque flute&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;II. Allegro from C.P.E. Bach&amp;rsquo;s sonata in A minor for solo flute, Wq 132; modern flute&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;background-why-i-played&#34;&gt;Background: why I played&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;last-year-s-party-recital&#34;&gt;Last year&amp;rsquo;s party/recital&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I only started playing recorder and joining the Pittsburgh Recorder Society just over a year ago. After I had only spent a couple of months playing alto recorder (and therefore being at a total beginner level), Helen held her party/recital on June 19, 2011, and invited people to volunteer to play. I was, of course, not ready to prepare anything I felt interesting enough to perform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, it did not even occur to me at the time that I would perform at all any time soon. But in fact, in addition to the prepared performances by several of the people, we also ended up playing something in a large group that we had worked on at the monthly meeting of the Pittsburgh Recorder Society. Even in such casual circumstances, I found myself almost paralyzed with anxiety, sitting there while Abby and other people sat and watched us play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It should be noted that at this point in my life last year, &lt;em&gt;I had not played music in front of a sitting audience in decades&lt;/em&gt;, and never with any seriousness; I was thirteen when I was last stumbling around playing in marching band with no enthusiasm and just an anonymous figure in a crowd:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/lamphere-high-marching-band.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin in Lamphere High School marching band uniform&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I survived playing casually in the group, as Abby watched and took photos that day:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-ars-recital-summer-2011/group.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Pittsburgh Recorder Society group performing at summer 2011 recital&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I have to confess that I was actually shaking and hyperventilating at times, messing up my breathing. It all seems so silly now, but that&amp;rsquo;s how it was. We do what we need to do, eventually become less sensitive, and move on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;setting-a-goal-and-deadline&#34;&gt;Setting a goal and deadline&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t tell anyone that June day last year, but after going home, I made a solemn vow to myself: I was going to spend the entire following year practicing recorder seriously and effectively, in order to be able to prepare something to play at the next party/recital. I had no idea what I was going to play, because the first step was simply to continue improving using some recorder method books, before actually trying to learn a real piece. My goal was to have something substantial to play, to display how much I had learned and improved. (And not shake with anxiety.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-i-chose-the-selections-i-played-this-year&#34;&gt;Why I chose the selections I played this year&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;which-instrument-s&#34;&gt;Which instrument(s)?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that in a single year, I had not only improved at alto recorder, but had also learned soprano recorder. I had also bought a tenor recorder and begun playing it (same fingerings as soprano recorder). And by fall last year, I had also &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/03/my-new-bass-and-sopranino-recorders-and-having-fun/&#34;&gt;bought a bass recorder&lt;/a&gt; and begun playing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Completely unexpectedly, in November I had begun &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/09/taking-up-flute-again-after-decades/&#34;&gt;trying to play modern flute again&lt;/a&gt;. Even more unexpectedly, later I also &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/30/bought-a-baroque-flute/&#34;&gt;decided to take up the Baroque flute&lt;/a&gt;, after having explained &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/17/flute-versus-recorder/&#34;&gt;why I had no plan to try Baroque flute anytime soon&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I also started playing the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/11/learning-another-instrument-the-tin-whistle/&#34;&gt;Irish tin whistle&lt;/a&gt;. It has been quite a year of music for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what instruments and music was I going to play for the recital at Helen&amp;rsquo;s?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-answer-play-three-of-my-instruments&#34;&gt;The answer: play three of my instruments&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided that I would pick three fairly short music selections and play them on three different instruments as appropriate for the music&amp;rsquo;s style and period. Also, to simply my preparation, I looked for music I could play alone rather than, say, requiring a keyboard accompaniment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;late-renaissance-or-early-baroque-1650s&#34;&gt;Late Renaissance or early Baroque (1650s?)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I chose to play a selection from Van Eyck to show off the soprano recorder. Actually, I had played this selection for an audience before (a blog post about that life-changing experience, a &amp;ldquo;Baroque jam session&amp;rdquo;, on Friday, April 27, is still to be written). It was by pure accident that I came across Van Eyck&amp;rsquo;s music to play; I had found the score in the Carnegie Library of Pittsburgh&amp;rsquo;s catalog while looking for any recorder music at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A personal reason I wanted to play this was that I had not heard any interpretation that I really liked, from CDs or YouTube. Therefore, I wanted to fill a hole and try to play the music the way I felt it. This is the fundamental reason I have been playing music rather than just listening to others do it: self-expression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;update-of-2012-10-30&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-10-30)&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is the finally published post about the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/04/27/baroque-jam-session-at-cmu/&#34;&gt;Baroque jam session&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;traditional-scottish-air-1700s&#34;&gt;Traditional Scottish air (1700s?)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Baroque flute seemed appropriate to play this slow song. It could have used accompaniment, but I added it to the program too late to have someone accompany me on harp or mandolin or something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was a little hesitant to play the Baroque flute in public, because I had only really started playing it, and was clearly in need of serious improvement (in fact, it has been my main instrument of focus in the past month), but I thought I might as well put in a two-minute song for variety&amp;rsquo;s sake, and as a baseline since I had already decided that next year, I want to play the Baroque flute again at the 2013 party/recital, and much better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;late-baroque-or-pre-classical-1750s&#34;&gt;Late Baroque or pre-Classical (1750s?)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The CPE Bach sonata I had fallen in love with hearing it by accident on modern flute performed by &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/22/james-galway-made-me-hate-flute/&#34;&gt;Emmanuel Pahud&lt;/a&gt; when I was browsing YouTube one day for solo flute material. After hearing it, I vowed that one day I would play the whole thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I chose what seemed to be the easiest movement to focus on, and practiced it on modern flute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is, of course, a question of which flute is best suited for this music. Given the period, perhaps a simple system keyed wooden flute? But I don&amp;rsquo;t have one, and currently have no intention of getting one or learning to play it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would be possible to play it on a Baroque flute, but much more difficult. When I get better at Baroque flute, I just might consider playing CPE Bach on it, but I feel that the modern flute is not inappropriate for this music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-i-fared&#34;&gt;How I fared&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, I played. I got nervous, I made various errors I did not make in practice, I made errors that I made in practice, but I actually did manage to go up alone and play. I can&amp;rsquo;t pretend that I played very well (in fact, now, over a month later, I could play each of these selections noticeably better than I did), but I did what I could at the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, since Abby&amp;rsquo;s parents came to the party/recital this year, this was also the first time they ever saw me perform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was considerably less nervous than a year ago, but still more nervous than I really need to be. So next year, 2013, I expect to be more seasoned and more performance-ready.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After we all played, we enjoyed the potluck dinner and had a good time. What else could I ask for, an evening of music, food, and friends?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Sorry, I have no photos or videos of any of the activities. I was too busy experiencing rather than spectating, and I don&amp;rsquo;t think anyone actually took any photos or videos.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Pittsburgh Recorder Society spring potluck/recital means a lot to me because it was there last year that I continued to get to know the members, after having just joined, met new people, heard people play, and got the idea that I too could perform, if I worked at improving. I set some goals, was happy that Abby and her parents came along to see me perform, and the experience renewed my commitment to continuing to play and improve in the Pittsburgh Recorder Society group as well as on my own on Baroque flute and modern flute. I have every intention of having even more fun in my upcoming year of music!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Baroque jam session at CMU: first time my parents ever watched me perform music</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/04/27/baroque-jam-session-at-cmu/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Apr 2012 23:20:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/04/27/baroque-jam-session-at-cmu/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Three days ago, I suddenly saw this poster on a bulletin board in the hallway at work at CMU:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/baroque-jam-session/poster.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;CMU poster for Baroque jam session&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
A night of music by some of these cool dead dudes.

A chance to hear CMU School of Music majors do their thing, 18th Century style.

An opportunity to bring your own instrument &amp; play along.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought to myself, I have to go to this event, even at short notice!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also experienced terror at the thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I went, and survived. It was a &lt;em&gt;life-changing&lt;/em&gt; experience for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;contact&#34;&gt;Contact&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I noticed that the contact person on the poster, Maria, was someone I had just recently seen a couple of days ago, at the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/04/21/my-first-time-in-a-public-music-jam-intense-fun-with-chris-norman-and-david-greenberg/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Renaissance and Baroque jam session by Chris Norman and David Greenberg&lt;/a&gt;. She was the Baroque oboist, student at CMU, who had been something of a center of attention during the session, because of her having a Baroque-tuned instrument rather than a modern-tuned one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I wrote Maria asking her if I could come play, and she said OK. She said the format was not a real jam session, but that it would be people bring stuff to play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;logistics&#34;&gt;Logistics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a complication: my parents were scheduled to drive in to visit me and Abby and stay for tonight. This meant that we had to clean up at home in preparation for their visit, make dinner, etc. If I was going to this Baroque music jam session, then it was going to be a hectic day. I figured that we could all attend together, and then my parents would actually finally see me play music in public, &lt;em&gt;for the first time in my life&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seriously: back when I was in elementary school and middle school and high school and piddled around without enthusiasm on the flute, they were similarly unenthusiastic and didn&amp;rsquo;t go around coming to my band concerts and applauding me or whatever. I don&amp;rsquo;t actually remember their presence at all; maybe my mother dropped me off or something and came back, when I needed any aid at all. I remember thinking the detachment odd because I had classmates whose parents hovered over their kids&amp;rsquo; music and sports involvement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;preparation&#34;&gt;Preparation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had to figure out what music to play. I couldn&amp;rsquo;t count necessarily on any accompanists. I quickly decided to work on something for solo recorder, and happened to recently have discovered a book of pieces for solo soprano recorder. I chose one set of theme and variations, &amp;ldquo;Doen Daphne D&amp;rsquo;over Schoone Maeght&amp;rdquo; from Jacob Van Eyck&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Der Fluyten Lust-Hof&amp;rdquo;, to work on. This music is earlier than Baroque, strictly, but hey, I thought maybe it would be good to provide contrast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also wanted to play some Baroque music, so my attention immediately turned to Henry Holcombe&amp;rsquo;s Air in E minor that I had &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/30/bought-a-baroque-flute/&#34;&gt;discovered in a volume of &amp;ldquo;English Airs and Dances&amp;rdquo; half a year ago&lt;/a&gt; and immediately fallen in love with. I was not prepared at all to play this on a Baroque flute, so I decided to risk embarrassment by playing on a modern flute instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-event&#34;&gt;The event&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So Abby and I took my parents to the Skibo Coffeehouse at CMU where the event was happening. A lot of familiar faces were there; I&amp;rsquo;ve been going to CMU student music recitals lately, primarily of flute students, and therefore have been seeing some of the same faces of graduating students and their friends. So I was feeling very intimidated because these students are &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt;. I had seen and heard them doing their thing. I wondered whether I had made a huge mistake by coming to play. I checked in with Maria, then decided to sit around and watch for a while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that a lot of what happened was random sight reading, and also some people playing an instrument that wasn&amp;rsquo;t their primary instrument. In any case, it was all pretty casual and in fun, and a lot of mistakes were being made, so I felt much better about the prospect of eventually taking my turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were also people who had come just watch, either because they had seen the poster earlier or because they happened to be in Skibo for a meal and decided to hang out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My parents seemed to be enjoying their evening of entertainment. I explained to them that it wasn&amp;rsquo;t a concert, that these students were just having fun sight reading. They were impressed with the sight reading skill, and the voices of the young men and women who sang.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;my-turn&#34;&gt;My turn&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It started getting late, and Abby was very tired. She left to take a little walk to get some air.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point, Maria asked me whether I wanted to play something. I felt I had to go now, so I couldn&amp;rsquo;t wait for Abby to come back. I offered to play the Holcombe piece for flute, and asked if someone could play continuo, since I had a score with the figured bass. A cellist stepped up. But as I got on stage and prepared to play, we suddenly realized that I was playing a modern flute at modern pitch, while the cello was at Baroque tuning. I felt so embarrassed. Someone I had seen in recitals playing clarinet volunteered to play continuo on the digital keyboard (which of course could be set for any tuning), so we proceeded. I was so nervous that I somehow botched up some passages, but I tried to play what I felt, even if my technique and mental condition were not entirely up to it. And so we did it, including my on-the-fly ornamentation during the repeats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apparently Abby had returned to see that I was in the middle of performing, and she was upset to have missed me. I told her that it was OK, not a big deal. There would be plenty of future opportunities for her to see me perform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We listened to some more student performances, then it really was getting late, and my parents wanted to leave, because they had to drive next morning to my sister in DC. So I announced that I had one more piece to perform and then had to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I played the solo soprano recorder piece. I think the audience liked that, because it was so different from what had gone on all evening. I didn&amp;rsquo;t play it perfectly, but I felt much more relaxed and capable on recorder than on flute, and I enjoyed hearing my ringing sound in the space of Skibo, with its very high ceilings. I thought I did pretty well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I packed up and we went home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was not only really my first time performing alone (in the recorder piece) in public, but also the first time my parents had seen me perform music, and the first time Abby had seen me do a solo. So it was a very special evening for me. I felt like, if I could accept myself playing among these much better musicians, despite my being nowhere as good (yet), I was going to continue to seek out all opportunities to share the music I love and feel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t know how to explain it, but working up the courage to participate in this Baroque jam session, and actually carrying through (despite almost chickening out by waiting until the evening was almost over), meant a lot to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2012-07-28&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-07-28)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three months later, I ended up playing the Van Eyck piece in the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/28/my-first-appearance-on-a-music-recital-program/&#34;&gt;summer recital of the Pittsburgh recorder group&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2012-09-08&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-09-08)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It took me four months from this Baroque jam session before I performed Holcombe&amp;rsquo;s Air in E minor again anywhere, and &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/08/finally-performing-some-sonatas-for-baroque-flute/&#34;&gt;that time I finally played it on a Baroque flute&lt;/a&gt; rather than a modern flute!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2012-11-01&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-11-01)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My parents were visiting me and Abby yesterday for the first time since this Baroque jam six months ago. Yes, they were stopping by for the night to break up the long drive to visit my sister in DC again to see their &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/05/31/some-pretty-attacking-chess-at-a-party-last-weekend/&#34;&gt;baby grandson&lt;/a&gt; again and help out with care again for two weeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did some flute playing for them last night (on Irish flute, modern flute, and Baroque flute) and they seemed to enjoy the diversion. They still remembered how totally nervous I had been six months ago at the Baroque jam session and have been supportive of my musical activities of the past year. I am very grateful for that.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>