<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Baroque Flute on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/baroque-flute/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Baroque Flute on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/baroque-flute/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>My first time at an English country dance music jam</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/01/25/my-first-time-at-english-country-dance-music-jam/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Jan 2014 19:39:03 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/01/25/my-first-time-at-english-country-dance-music-jam/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Relatively recently, a new English country dance music jam in the Pittsburgh area has been organized by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amarillismusic.com/aboutus.html&#34;&gt;Maro Avakian&lt;/a&gt;, whom I first met through joining in playing for the Holiday Ball &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/16/playing-recorder-and-flute-at-the-holiday-ball/&#34;&gt;two years ago&lt;/a&gt;. I was unable to make it to the first couple of meetings, but finally, on a nasty snowy Saturday, my schedule happened to be open, so I went.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not completely new to English country dance music. It was almost two years ago when I first encountered it, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/31/my-first-sampling-of-english-country-dance-and-contra-dance/&#34;&gt;as a dancer&lt;/a&gt;. As has happened several times now in my life, becoming familiar with the dance got me interested in the &lt;em&gt;music&lt;/em&gt; and in the idea of actually playing the music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that I&amp;rsquo;d already played some of this kind of music for myself as a result of my study of the Baroque flute, because method books I have for the instrument include a good amount of dance music from the era. In any case, the book we use for many tunes is the volume by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.canispublishing.com/&#34;&gt;Peter Barnes&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://mysite.verizon.net/peterabarnes/books.htm&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Barnes Book of English Country Dance Tunes&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, a fine anthology. Actually, I ordered my copy only last week and was lucky it arrived in the mail just in time!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://mysite.verizon.net/peterabarnes/Book1.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;instruments&#34;&gt;Instruments&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had a pretty good turnout given the weather. Apart from Maro on piano, we had people playing flute, Baroque flute, recorders, ukulele, mandolin, percussion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d brought my flute, Baroque flute, and soprano, alto, tenor recorders, but since there were already two others on modern flute and soprano recorder, I ended up playing just the Baroque flute, alto recorder, and tenor recorder. The Baroque flute is pretty hard to play in some of the keys, and also is kind of soft, so I mostly played the alto and tenor recorders. I gradually gravitated toward improvising inner voices with the tenor recorder. I think I will do that in the future also. In addition, I should bring my bass recorder, to add a yet lower instrument to our group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;improvisation&#34;&gt;Improvisation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had great discussions about tips and tricks for improvising lines and filling out chords. Needless to say, I was botching up a lot of stuff as I experimented, but you can&amp;rsquo;t learn if you don&amp;rsquo;t try!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It looks like I have a new musical outlet, English country dance music. I hope to continue participating in it. As with French traditional dance music, I like the improvisational nature of working with a tune with repetition.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Chamber music concert at CMU featured Bach&#39;s Goldberg Variations arranged for string trio</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/11/19/chamber-music-concert-at-cmu-featured-bachs-goldberg-variations-arranged-for-string-trio/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Nov 2013 23:04:37 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/11/19/chamber-music-concert-at-cmu-featured-bachs-goldberg-variations-arranged-for-string-trio/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.cmu.edu/news/stories/archives/2013/november/images/chamber-recital_400x340.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;David Harding, Noah Bendix-Balgley, Lorna McGhee, Amit Peled&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I attended a special &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cmu.edu/news/stories/archives/2013/november/nov8_chambermusic.html&#34;&gt;chamber music concert at CMU&lt;/a&gt; that featured some truly excellent musicians.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-musicians&#34;&gt;The musicians&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was particularly interested in seeing &lt;a href=&#34;http://trioverlaine.com/bios/lorna-mcghee/&#34;&gt;Lorna McGhee&lt;/a&gt;, the current principal flute of the Pittsburgh Symphony Orchestra, and violinist &lt;a href=&#34;http://noahbendixbalgley.com/&#34;&gt;Noah Bendix-Balgley&lt;/a&gt;, the concertmaster, both of whom are relatively recent additions to the orchestra. The other two musicians, also fantastic, were violist and CMU professor &lt;a href=&#34;http://trioverlaine.com/bios/david-harding/&#34;&gt;David Harding&lt;/a&gt; and cellist &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amitpeled.com/&#34;&gt;Amit Peled&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;mozart-s-flute-quartet-no-1-in-d-major&#34;&gt;Mozart&amp;rsquo;s flute quartet no. 1 in D major&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lorna McGhee played in the first part of the program, which was Mozart&amp;rsquo;s first flute quartet. I was very curious how she would approach the work, because I&amp;rsquo;m very picky nowadays about the performance of music from the 18th century or earlier, which I far prefer to be both on period instruments and in period style. The typical &amp;ldquo;modern&amp;rdquo; performance I can no longer enjoy, because of stylistic anachronisms that in my mind invalidate the beauty and freshness of early music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed the quartet&amp;rsquo;s performance of the Mozart. The playing was crisp, lively, and transparent. There was little to quibble with in Lorna McGhee&amp;rsquo;s performance: she played with verve, sensitivity, and clarity. In some phrases she held a legato longer than I would like, but overall I quite liked the performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;bach-s-goldberg-variations-arranged-for-string-trio-by-dmitry-sitkovetsky&#34;&gt;Bach&amp;rsquo;s Goldberg Variations arranged for string trio by Dmitry Sitkovetsky&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bulk of the program was devoted to a performance by the string trio of the entire Goldberg Variations by Bach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past quarter century, I&amp;rsquo;ve listened to countless performances of the Goldberg Variations on all kinds of keyboard instrument, including harpsichord, fortepiano, and modern piano, but until tonight, I hadn&amp;rsquo;t bothered listening to Sitkovetsky&amp;rsquo;s arrangement for string trio that came out several years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought it worked out pretty well tonight, with the three string players working really hard to create dynamism and contrast along with unity in this monumental work. I couldn&amp;rsquo;t help but think that it&amp;rsquo;s actually harder to pull off as a trio than as a solo keyboard piece. What was particularly interesting was visually seeing and hearing (in the different tonal qualities) all the different voices in the music. They are there in the original version, of course, but experiencing the spatial separation just made me even more amazed by Bach&amp;rsquo;s creation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I appreciate the time the four musicians took to perform in this chamber music recital free to the public, and thank you, CMU, for bringing them in for these invigorating performances of Mozart and Bach!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>More summer musical partying, and another ten-year-old dream fulfilled!</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/07/04/more-summer-musical-partying/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Jul 2013 23:25:39 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/07/04/more-summer-musical-partying/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I went to a party at Gina&amp;rsquo;s. We hadn&amp;rsquo;t been over in &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/22/playing-tango-on-melodica-and-singing-christmas-carols/&#34;&gt;more than half a year&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had a great time, sharing a ton of food (I made a cabbage dish of my own invention that included onion, garlic, olive oil, cumin seeds, thyme, lime juice, salt and pepper) and hanging out inside as well as in the backyard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I somehow started an arm wrestling competition with the guys, and then we challenged each other to pullups and chinups too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also ended up playing three games of speed chess at a time handicap (my 3 minutes to his 10 minutes). I barely managed to win all three games. The final game should have been a draw, but I won through a swindle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;music&#34;&gt;Music&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I told Henry I was much improved musically since &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/05/03/playing-violin-music-on-flute/&#34;&gt;we played together two months ago&lt;/a&gt;. A lot of things have been falling in place for me. Of course, this only makes me be more ambitious about music to play, and in return, get humbled yet again by how much more improvement is left for me!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;telemann-s-flute-sonata-in-b-minor-tmv-41-h4&#34;&gt;Telemann&amp;rsquo;s flute sonata in B minor, TMV 41:h4&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One piece we tackled was &lt;a href=&#34;http://imslp.org/wiki/Flute_Sonata,_TWV_41:h4_%28Telemann,_Georg_Philipp%29&#34;&gt;Telemann&amp;rsquo;s flute sonata in B minor, TMV 41:h4&lt;/a&gt;. I had only actually gone over the first two movements, so we were both sight reading the last two. That was something of a wreck for me, but gives me homework to do: originally I had not actually planned on learning the whole sonata, now I want to!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;bach-s-flute-sonata-in-e-major-bwv-1035&#34;&gt;Bach&amp;rsquo;s flute sonata in E major, BWV 1035&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another piece we did was &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sonata_in_E_major_for_flute_or_recorder_and_basso_continuo&#34;&gt;Bach&amp;rsquo;s flute sonata in E major, BWV 1035&lt;/a&gt;, which I have already mentioned my obsession with in a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/21/my-second-year-of-celebrating-johann-sebastian-bachs-birthday/&#34;&gt;blog post over three months ago&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: I am still not playing this on Baroque flute or modern flute, because of the difficulty! I have been working with a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.universaledition.com/Sonata-F-major-BWV-1035-for-treble-recorder-basso-continuo-Johann-Sebastian-Bach/composers-and-works/composer/32/work/4801&#34;&gt;recorder transcription for F major&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because I have actually been playing more of this sonata myself in the past months, I have come to change my mind about performances I listed in that blog post! There is nothing like actually studying and playing a piece of music to change one&amp;rsquo;s perception of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My favorite performance so far I&amp;rsquo;ve found on YouTube is by Wilbert Hazelzet on Baroque flute. It&amp;rsquo;s split over two parts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/ZGtjxNeBTAs&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/Oetbg7eRa60&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, Henry and I ran through the sonata. Again, I had not actually ever run through the final movement, so it was an embarrassing sight reading scramble for me. But he really enjoyed the last movement, and I did too, and realized that I wanted to actually study and practice it. It&amp;rsquo;s funny how I came to enjoy this movement much more after having tried to play it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;gabriel-fauré-après-un-rêve-fulfilling-my-ten-year-old-dream&#34;&gt;Gabriel Fauré, Après un rêve: fulfilling my ten-year-old dream&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After all the Baroque stuff, I decided to play something different with Henry. I pulled out my modern flute, and we did Fauré&amp;rsquo;s song &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trois_m%C3%A9lodies,_Op.7_%28Faur%C3%A9%29&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Après un rêve&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; in a flute and piano arrangement that I bought in 2003.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a story I have never told anyone until now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I bought that score because I was in love with the song, but never imagined that I would be able to sing it properly. So I thought to myself that if I ever played flute again (recall that the last time I had touched flute was twenty years earlier, in childhood), my goal would be to at least be able to play &lt;em&gt;this one song&lt;/em&gt; on flute reasonably close to how I feel it should be played or sung. (There is also a second piece for flute that I wanted to play as well. I will reveal it once I have actually played it with someone.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ever since I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/09/taking-up-flute-again-after-decades/&#34;&gt;got back to flute almost two years ago&lt;/a&gt;, &amp;ldquo;Après un rêve&amp;rdquo; has been on my mind as well as on my shelf, and as a measure of progres, I have actually periodically pulled it out to try to play it. For well over a year, I could not play it anywhere near how I want it to sound. Here&amp;rsquo;s a piano accompaniment track I&amp;rsquo;ve been using in the past months:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/EAAe0GDO928&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eight months ago, I fulfilled a childhood dream, by throwing myself into singing, and in fact, one song I did sing was &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/11/17/a-childhood-dream-come-true-i-am-now-finally-singing-for-real/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Après un rêve&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;! I still don&amp;rsquo;t sing it as well as I&amp;rsquo;d like, and will continue working on singing it, but singing in general has had a tremendous positive transferring effect on my flute playing! I am now almost able to play &amp;ldquo;Après un rêve&amp;rdquo; how I want (the remaining difficulties being cleaning up the high passages in the arrangement as well as controlling the breath there as well). In any case, I went and played it with Henry for the first time, and it wasn&amp;rsquo;t horrible. In summary, ten years after I bought that score with wishful thinking, I made my dream reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, here&amp;rsquo;s a nice performance on flute that inspires me:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/95f57lYWgks&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;roland-de-lassus-http-en-wikipedia-org-wiki-orlande-de-lassus-as-recorder-duets&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Orlande_de_Lassus&#34;&gt;Roland de Lassus&lt;/a&gt;, as recorder duets&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The surprise of the day was when, after watching me mess around with bass recorder, Henry got the idea of playing recorder duets with me. I hadn&amp;rsquo;t known that he played recorder. He said he could play recorders in C (soprano and tenor), and since I didn&amp;rsquo;t have my tenor on me, I gave him my soprano recorder. He picked up a book and went through it to find some early music duets that we could do on recorders. We did some with soprano and bass, then I switched to alto and we did soprano and alto for the rest we found in the book. It was immense fun!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/recorder-duets-with-henry.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Henry and Franklin on recorders&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel blessed to have the opportunity and inspiration from Henry to continue improving at playing music, and stretch myself further. I have come so far in the past two years.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Attending a fascinating Robert Dick flute lecture and master class</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/04/04/attending-a-fascinating-robert-dick-flute-lecture-and-master-class/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Apr 2013 22:38:33 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/04/04/attending-a-fascinating-robert-dick-flute-lecture-and-master-class/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;It was a real treat that flutist &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.robertdick.net/&#34;&gt;Robert Dick&lt;/a&gt; came to Pittsburgh to give lectures, master classes, and performances in town. He&amp;rsquo;s most known for being a pioneer in &amp;ldquo;extended techniques&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;interviews&#34;&gt;Interviews&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some interviews with Robert Dick before he came to Pittsburgh, thanks to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pittsburghnewmusicnet.com/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh New Music Net&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;part-1&#34;&gt;Part 1&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/AGZgHmNZlGc&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;part-2&#34;&gt;Part 2&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/Mnx5Svsnb7s&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;lecture-and-master-class&#34;&gt;Lecture and master class&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I attended his lecture and master class held at CMU.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was fantastic. I learned a huge amount about tone, articulation, expression. He began by talking about &amp;ldquo;throat tuning&amp;rdquo;. The most fascinating thing he said was that he found that when he was studying flute, he had problems with his tone and found out that when he went to France, he found that nobody had this particular problem. He concluded eventually that it was because American instrumentalists did not have vocal training like Europeans did! He became convinced that everyone should &lt;em&gt;sing&lt;/em&gt;. Hearing him say this, and demonstrate &amp;ldquo;throat tuning&amp;rdquo;, immediately had me thinking that of course all musicians should sing, even if not very well, because instruments, especially wind instruments, are surely an extension of our built-in instrument, our body, as Dick said!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He made mention of various YouTube videos he recommended as supplements to his teaching. Check out his &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/user/robertdick9&#34;&gt;YouTube channel&lt;/a&gt;. An example: &amp;ldquo;Your first multiphonic&amp;rdquo;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/yB6_iPUaTWs&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went home and practiced this. Not because I necessarily want to play a lot of music with multiphonics, because the exercise really sharpened my awareness of sound, and of isolation of the upper and lower lips. Furthermore, his illustration of the finger that leads to the basic multiphonic of D and C immediately brought to mind how the C fingered on Baroque flute is this exact fingering and sounds &amp;ldquo;hollow&amp;rdquo;. Everything started to seem unified to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I learned from Robert Dick a huge amount, as a starting point for further investigations into sound as a science, and the flute in particular. Wow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2014-01-16&#34;&gt;(Update of 2014-01-16)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an unfinished post that is one of many in the past two years that lay unfinished because I had originally planned to write a very detailed report but never got around to it. I decided that I might as well release all these unfinished posts rather than leave them completely out of the record.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My second year of celebrating Johann Sebastian Bach&#39;s birthday: a tale of accidental love</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/03/21/my-second-year-of-celebrating-johann-sebastian-bachs-birthday/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Mar 2013 20:55:43 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/03/21/my-second-year-of-celebrating-johann-sebastian-bachs-birthday/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Last year I reported on celebrating the birthday of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Johann_Sebastian_Bach&#34;&gt;Johann Sebastian Bach, born in 1685&lt;/a&gt;. I was still just barely beginning to play the flute seriously then, and I read through some music of his transcribed for flute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have progressed tremendously on flute in the past year; the difference between having played flute for a few months and playing it for a few months &lt;em&gt;plus a whole year&lt;/em&gt; is really huge. So this year, to celebrate, I played for myself some of Bach&amp;rsquo;s actual music written for flute: selections from his flute sonatas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/20/my-first-bobblehead-doll-guess-who/&#34;&gt;my Bach bobblehead&lt;/a&gt; still watches over me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/bach-and-franklin.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;J S Bach bobblehead and Franklin&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I have a tale of accidental love to tell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;falling-instantly-in-love-with-bach-s-flute-sonata-in-e-major-bwv-1035-first-movement&#34;&gt;Falling instantly in love with Bach&amp;rsquo;s flute sonata in E major, BWV 1035, first movement&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;alto-recorder&#34;&gt;Alto recorder&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2011, I started playing alto &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/recorder/&#34;&gt;recorder&lt;/a&gt;, teaching myself and joining the Pittsburgh Recorder Society. I first completed the two-volume method by Orr, over the course of approximately two months, February through April 2011. Then I moved on to the two-volume method by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.aswltd.com/adultmet.htm#begin&#34;&gt;Mario Duschenes&lt;/a&gt;. One of the great things about the second volume of the Duschenes method is that it contains excerpts of real music. One excerpt that came up was the first movement of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sonata_in_E_major_for_flute_or_recorder_and_basso_continuo&#34;&gt;Bach&amp;rsquo;s flute sonata in E major&lt;/a&gt;, transposed for alto recorder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had never heard this music before, so I looked for recordings of it. This was not so easy! The reason is that I kept on finding recordings of the original flute version, but at the time, I was not yet playing the flute, only recorder, and only interested in recorder. Then I found a recording by &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michala_Petri&#34;&gt;Michala Petri&lt;/a&gt; and Keith Jarrett. So I worked on this &lt;em&gt;adagio ma non tanto&lt;/em&gt; first movement and periodically played along with Petri&amp;rsquo;s recording.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, I didn&amp;rsquo;t much like Petri&amp;rsquo;s performance at all: it lacked in articulation, contrast, and expression:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/809awZvxx80&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;falling-in-love&#34;&gt;Falling in love&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What really got to me was this passionate performance I found on YouTube on recorder by Maurice Steger. There are idiosyncratic things he does that I don&amp;rsquo;t do, but there is no doubt about his commitment to full emotional expression:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/_MGBQy33pkE&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I couldn&amp;rsquo;t explain why, but seeing this video was one of the first times I really fell in love with Baroque music. To me, the long phrases, chromaticism, and Bach&amp;rsquo;s own style of ornamentation give a meditative expression of melancholy and longing. I poured myself into playing this on recorder, inspired by Maurice Steger&amp;rsquo;s passion for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;baroque-flute-vs-modern-flute&#34;&gt;Baroque flute vs. modern flute?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/09/taking-up-flute-again-after-decades/&#34;&gt;accidentally started playing modern flute again in late 2011&lt;/a&gt;, I eventually looked up actual flute recordings of Bach&amp;rsquo;s flute sonatas. I completely stopped playing Bach transposed for the recorder. I just felt that, despite Maurice Steger&amp;rsquo;s example, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/17/flute-versus-recorder/&#34;&gt;I could not get everything I wanted out of the recorder&lt;/a&gt;, and I wanted to move to flute. However, the modern flute seemed not so well suited to the music. &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/30/bought-a-baroque-flute/&#34;&gt;Eventually, I bought a Baroque flute&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, because Bach on the &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/baroque-flute/&#34;&gt;Baroque flute&lt;/a&gt; has remained much more difficult for me to play than on the modern flute, I have resigned myself to mostly playing Bach&amp;rsquo;s flute music on modern flute, while trying to keep the music crisply articulated and with minimal vibrato.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(I played the first movement of Bach&amp;rsquo;s flute sonata in E minor, BWV 1034, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/26/music-i-just-played-for-the-first-time-recorder-sonata-tangos/&#34;&gt;at a party earlier this year&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some videos illustrating a little bit of how the sounds and interpretations may differ.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;baroque-flute-jed-wentz&#34;&gt;Baroque flute: Jed Wentz&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A performance by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jedwentz.com/jedwentz.com/Welcome.html&#34;&gt;Jed Wentz&lt;/a&gt; on Baroque flute:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/m0CiLHDH5FQ&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;update-of-2013-07-04&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-07-04)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I no longer like this performance as much as I did initially. It is a bit frantic, with some blazing fast playing that I would like to be a bit slower.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;modern-flute-emmanuel-pahud&#34;&gt;Modern flute: Emmanuel Pahud&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A performance by Emmanuel Pahud on modern flute, but playing with fine sensitivity to elements of Baroque style:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/YyePpU1_lKo&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;update-of-2013-07-04-1&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-07-04)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My, taste changes in three months: I no longer like this performance. It is simultaneously still too smooth and too restrained.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;another-modern-flutist-nikos-nikopoulos&#34;&gt;Another modern flutist: Nikos Nikopoulos&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A random modern flutist playing in a bland legato-all-the-time style:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/uc3ck2MayjE&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bach&amp;rsquo;s birthday is a good time to remember and re-create and re-experience what was beautiful and special about the music of the Baroque era, before changes in taste and style came along in the late 18th century and onward. For me, the flute sonatas will always be a source of rediscovery and exploration of the Baroque world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-07-04-2&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-07-04)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have more &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/07/04/more-summer-musical-partying/&#34;&gt;thoughts on this sonata&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Celebrating two years of playing recorder</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/02/23/celebrating-two-years-of-playing-recorder/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Feb 2013 23:33:58 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/02/23/celebrating-two-years-of-playing-recorder/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I was very excited to celebrate two years of playing recorder by attending the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.andrew.cmu.edu/user/lukas/pcars/Welcome.html&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Recorder Society&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ldquo;Midwinter Musical Feast&amp;rdquo; potluck and informal recital at Helen&amp;rsquo;s. Last year (2012) we didn&amp;rsquo;t have a winter party, but I still remember when two years ago (2011), on February 19, I started learning the alto recorder at home by myself, and then &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/26/i-dont-feel-like-practicing-but-im-gonna-do-it-anyway/&#34;&gt;decided to join the Pittsburgh Recorder Society&lt;/a&gt;. Helen was actually my first email contact from the group, and she had immediately invited me to come to the Midwinter Musical Feast, but not having actually met anybody yet, and also barely just beginning to play recorder, I was too intimidated and decided to skip the party and instead practice for two weeks before attending my first meeting of the group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last recorder potluck/recital I went to was &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/28/my-first-appearance-on-a-music-recital-program/&#34;&gt;half a year ago&lt;/a&gt;, when I played a bit on soprano recorder, Baroque flute, and modern flute. Abby had come with me, and her parents also attended. This time, Abby came again, as did her parents, and Abby brought her &lt;a href=&#34;tambura&#34;&gt;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tamburica&lt;/a&gt; to play some Balkan music selections:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/recorder-midwinter-2013/DSCN0017.JPG&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby on tamburitza&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(Additional photos of food and people are now &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/media/set/?set=a.445931198818142.1073741825.330712777006652&amp;amp;type=3&#34;&gt;up on Facebook&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-two-collaborations&#34;&gt;My two collaborations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for me, I prepared two pieces to play, both of which required a continuo accompanist. Because of time constraints, I did not actually get together with either of my collaborators, but did send them sound files of myself playing at home, as well as scores. So we never had any rehearsal together, but heck, this was just a party, so it wasn&amp;rsquo;t a big deal that we were going to wing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;handel-s-recorder-sonata-in-g-minor&#34;&gt;Handel&amp;rsquo;s recorder sonata in G minor&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last month, I ran through Handel&amp;rsquo;s short four-movement recorder sonata in G minor &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/26/music-i-just-played-for-the-first-time-recorder-sonata-tangos/&#34;&gt;with Henry on piano at a party&lt;/a&gt;, but my goal was always to perform it for real, to the best of my technical and interpretive ability, with period accompaniment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I actually rehearsed this with Annie, with her playing my portable electronic keyboard that has a harpsichord setting, but then it turned out she could not make it to the party, so I scrambled to find someone else, and I was thankful that Mike agreed to step in and play the continuo on bass recorder!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I worked rather hard on this piece, actually, in the sense of coming up with some fluency to be able to come up with spontaneous and personally expressive Baroque ornamentation in all the movements, especially the first. (I did not want to compose a fixed ornamentation to play.) I believe I had some success doing so, and felt that my effort was a respectful way to celebrate two years of recorder playing.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/recorder-midwinter-2013/DSCN0018.JPG&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin and Mike playing Handel&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;niccolò-dôthel-s-first-flute-and-cello-sonata-first-movement&#34;&gt;Niccolò Dôthel&amp;rsquo;s first flute and cello sonata, first movement&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/recorder-midwinter-2013/DSCN0020.JPG&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin and Karen playing Dôthel&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Two months ago, I had actually run through this piece on Baroque flute with piano accompaniment &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/22/playing-tango-on-melodica-and-singing-christmas-carols/&#34;&gt;at a party&lt;/a&gt;, but just sight read by Henry on piano and in a noisy environment that was not ideal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This time, I actually worked on playing it in a quiet environment. Karen Parsons, whom I actually formally met just before &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/21/mideast-early-music-workshop-a-life-changing-experience/&#34;&gt;last year&amp;rsquo;s Mideast early music workshop&lt;/a&gt;, which we both participated in, was kind enough to agree to play the continuo part on viola da gamba.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a false start and a scare though! What happened was that I had planned to play the piece on Annie&amp;rsquo;s wooden Baroque flute that she had lent to me, and I had in fact practiced it on this instrument just fine for days, but somehow, I could not make a sound at all on her flute after I performed the Handel recorder sonata. I was completely mystified. Luckily, I had a backup plan: I had brought along my own plastic Aulos Baroque flute, and I was perfectly able to play it instead, and so we proceeded. I am still not entirely certain why Annie&amp;rsquo;s flute suddenly failed to work for me; upon arriving at the party, I had actually warmed up the flute and played a few notes on it for confidence. My speculation is that it was a mistake to play recorder right before flute, and maybe my embouchure was slightly off on the particular instrument I had only been playing for a few days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, Karen and I had fun playing this light, elegant piece. I do wish I could have played it on Annie&amp;rsquo;s flute, though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;other-people&#34;&gt;Other people&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed hearing others in the recorder group playing their musical selections as well, especially those who were newer to the group. It makes me profoundly happy to be among others sharing music together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Pittsburgh Recorder Society usually holds these potluck/recitals twice a year, in winter and summer. I always cherish the opportunity to make a special dish to share for the potluck (this time I brought my own hearty vegetable soup) as well as prepare interesting music to share that I hope others will enjoy. And this time, being basically the second anniversary of my playing recorder, I felt especially grateful for all that everyone in the group has shared with me in the past two years! I actually do not know what my life would be like today if I had not begun playing music with the Pittsburgh Recorder Society two years ago. It changed everything for me.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Music I just played for the first time: recorder sonata, tangos</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/01/26/music-i-just-played-for-the-first-time-recorder-sonata-tangos/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Jan 2013 23:03:10 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/01/26/music-i-just-played-for-the-first-time-recorder-sonata-tangos/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Abby and I went to Henry&amp;rsquo;s birthday party, marking an important anniversary: we attended his birthday party for the first time a year ago, and that began &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/01/27/a-new-friends-very-musical-birthday-party-changed-my-life/&#34;&gt;one of the most important developments in my entire life, my decision to make music playing an integral part of my life&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of music happened, as usual, and this time, unlike a year ago, I played. What a year it&amp;rsquo;s been!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;handel-s-recorder-sonata-in-g-minor&#34;&gt;Handel&amp;rsquo;s recorder sonata in G minor&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided to finally give a shot at playing, for the first time outside of home, &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Recorder_sonata_in_G_minor_%28HWV_360%29&#34;&gt;Handel&amp;rsquo;s recorder sonata in G minor, op. 1 no. 2&lt;/a&gt;, me being on alto recorder and Henry on piano.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This piece is extremely special to me, because I discovered it by accident as one of the first &amp;ldquo;real&amp;rdquo; recorder pieces that I started working on when I was just a beginner at recorder. A method book I was using at the time, one and half years ago, in May 2011, by Mario Duschenes, had a section with the title &amp;ldquo;How to practise a difficult piece&amp;rdquo;, and the example and suggestions on practice was the Andante from this recorder sonata by Handel. I hunted down the complete score of the recorder sonata and started to learn the whole thing. I did this intermittently over the course of a year or so while doing other things, but always had the intention of at some point polishing it up for actual performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main holdup eventually was that I wanted to be able to really express myself well, and incorporate my own ornamentations. To this end, I made some study of Baroque ornamentation and checked out a book I found in the library, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.oup.com/us/catalog/general/subject/Music/PerformanceStudiesAppliedMusic/WindsBrass/?view=usa&amp;amp;ci=9780198790013&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Playing Recorder Sonatas&amp;rdquo;, by Anthony Rowland-Jones&lt;/a&gt;. I have found this book quite useful as a guide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I had fun reading through this with Henry. Eventually I want to play it for real, as performance, in a setting with harpsichord continuo, rather than with piano.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-02-23&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-02-23)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ended up performing the recorder sonata with bass recorder accompaniment at the Pittsburgh Recorder Society&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/02/23/celebrating-two-years-of-playing-recorder/&#34;&gt;Midwinter Musical Feast&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;bach-s-flute-sonata-in-e-minor-bwv-1034&#34;&gt;Bach&amp;rsquo;s flute sonata in E minor, BWV 1034&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I played music by Johann Sebastian Bach on flute for the first time outside the home. I&amp;rsquo;ve held back because I feel like I&amp;rsquo;m still not doing the music justice, but decided I can&amp;rsquo;t hide forever my love of Bach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On modern flute with Henry on piano, I played the first movement of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sonata_in_E_minor_for_flute_or_recorder_and_basso_continuo&#34;&gt;Bach&amp;rsquo;s flute sonata in E minor&lt;/a&gt;. I would have considered playing it on Baroque flute, but the piano as well as the the party environment &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/21/my-first-time-singing-bossa-nova-also-a-temporary-farewell-to-baroque-flute/&#34;&gt;is not friendly for Baroque flute&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-03-21&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-03-21)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Bach&amp;rsquo;s birthday in 2013, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/21/my-second-year-of-celebrating-johann-sebastian-bachs-birthday/&#34;&gt;I reflected on&lt;/a&gt; how the very same recorder method book by Duschenes I mentioned above was the impetus for my getting into Bach flute sonatas!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;tangos&#34;&gt;Tangos&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I played tango on flute for the first time ever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/11/17/a-childhood-dream-come-true-i-am-now-finally-singing-for-real/&#34;&gt;sing tango for the first time recently&lt;/a&gt;, and also played &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/22/playing-tango-on-melodica-and-singing-christmas-carols/&#34;&gt;tango on melodica for the first time&lt;/a&gt;, but had not yet dared to play on flute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, I did, and not only that, one of them ended up becoming a flute-violin duet, in which Barbara (whom I met exactly a year ago at the last birthday party) played violin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story is that several months ago, in October, I got hold of a book of tangos for violin duet. I judged that with some modifications I could play the first part on flute, if only I could simultaneously find someone on violin (and someone on piano). The opportunity did not spontaneously arise until today!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, I played &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/El_Choclo&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;El Choclo&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; with just Henry on piano.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then Barbara joined in on violin and we played &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Por_una_Cabeza&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Por una Cabeza&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; with Henry. This was one of the most satisfying experiences of my life. It&amp;rsquo;s one thing playing duets with Henry, but it&amp;rsquo;s another having three to really fill in the harmonies and textures and two melodic voices playing off each other. Wow. I need to do this more often. And I have to confess, I never tire of this particular classic tango, because it&amp;rsquo;s so dramatic and expressive, and has that suddenly shift from major to the lyrical chorus in minor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;more-bach-double-violin-concerto&#34;&gt;More Bach: double violin concerto&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Barbara was so excited that she goaded me into trying to sight read &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Concerto_for_Two_Violins_%28Bach%29&#34;&gt;Bach&amp;rsquo;s double violin concerto&lt;/a&gt; on the spot together with Henry. I knew I was probably going to cause a minor disaster, but heck, it&amp;rsquo;s a party, we&amp;rsquo;re just having fun. And indeed, I got confused or lost many times, because first of all, I&amp;rsquo;m not so great on flute right now at all, and second, this music was for violin and some stuff was not very suitable for flute and also needed me to go up an octave all of a sudden because the violin has a bigger range. So, it was a struggle for me, but I enjoyed some nice moments in the less frantic slow movement, where the two melodic voices really combine beautifully.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, it was all in fun, Bach forgive me!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As at all of Henry&amp;rsquo;s parties, I strive to go to them prepared to do something better and new and interesting musically, for our enjoyment as well as that of the other guests. I had a great time again. I am so grateful for the past year of getting to know Henry and his sharing the gift of music with me!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Playing tango on melodica and singing Christmas carols</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/12/22/playing-tango-on-melodica-and-singing-christmas-carols/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Dec 2012 23:57:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/12/22/playing-tango-on-melodica-and-singing-christmas-carols/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I went to a Christmas party at Gina&amp;rsquo;s, and of course there had to be a lot of music-making. Probably ten of us at some point or another were playing music. There was singing, flutes, accordions, piano, mandolin, etc., on all kinds of music, for hours and hours, even in separate rooms simultaneously. I did a lot of sitting and listening to others and also some participation of my own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, personally, my favorite moments that I was involved in were the following.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;piazzolla-s-oblivion-on-melodica-and-piano&#34;&gt;Piazzolla&amp;rsquo;s Oblivion on melodica and piano&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Henry and I did Piazzolla&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Oblivion&amp;rdquo;, with me on melodica, and him accompanying on piano. I&amp;rsquo;ve &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/02/oblivion-obsession-time-to-start-playing-melodica/&#34;&gt;recently mentioned wanting to do this&lt;/a&gt;, so I was happy to have this opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My cheap secondhand student melodica has poor intonation on the lower notes, unfortunately, as &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/14/pittsburgh-contras-and-squares-holiday-ball-2012/&#34;&gt;I observed recently when playing it in the Pittsburgh Contras and Squares Holiday Ball&lt;/a&gt;. So the results were not ideal. I&amp;rsquo;ve decided that if I want to continue playing the melodica seriously, I need a better instrument.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve decided that next time I play &amp;ldquo;Oblivion&amp;rdquo; again, it will be on flute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;niccolò-dôthel-s-first-flute-and-cello-sonata-first-movement-http-imslp-org-wiki-6-sonatas-for-flute-and-cello-op-2-28d-c3-b4thel-niccol-c3-b2-29&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://imslp.org/wiki/6_Sonatas_for_Flute_and_Cello,_Op.2_%28D%C3%B4thel,_Niccol%C3%B2%29&#34;&gt;Niccolò Dôthel&amp;rsquo;s first flute and cello sonata, first movement&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For variety, I threw in some Baroque music to play with Henry on piano for continuo. We did the first movement of Dôthel&amp;rsquo;s first flute and cello sonata. I had first heard this by accident, while following a discussion &lt;a href=&#34;http://launch.groups.yahoo.com/group/earlyflute/message/12041&#34;&gt;three months ago&lt;/a&gt; on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://launch.groups.yahoo.com/group/earlyflute/&#34;&gt;Yahoo &amp;ldquo;early flute&amp;rdquo; group&lt;/a&gt;, in which one of the posters, Javier Gelati, put up a link to a YouTube video of himself playing it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/HmMoNwm-Hx8&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found this piece so delightful and suitable for the Baroque flute that I decided I wanted to play it, and worked on it, and so I finally got the chance to play it with someone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-02-23&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-02-23)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ended up playing this piece again, but in a quiet recital environment, with viola da gamba continuo, at the Pittsburgh Recorder Society&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/02/23/celebrating-two-years-of-playing-recorder/&#34;&gt;Midwinter Musical Feast&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;have-yourself-a-merry-little-christmas&#34;&gt;Have Yourself a Merry Little Christmas&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of my favorite Christmas songs is &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Have_Yourself_a_Merry_Little_Christmas&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Have Yourself a Merry Little Christmas&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. It can still bring tears to my eyes. It brings back a lot of winter memories of being alone for one reason or another, while out and about and hearing it playing in stores and subway stations. Those days are over, but still, the song is really quite moving. Especially, I prefer the original lyrics, &amp;ldquo;Until then we&amp;rsquo;ll have to muddle through somehow&amp;rdquo;, to the alternate lyrics Frank Sinatra popularized, &amp;ldquo;Hang a shining star upon the highest bough&amp;rdquo;. The original melancholy lyrics underline the message of a hope for the future that is not yet reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So for the first time, I sang this song for others to hear, with Henry on piano.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, the classic performance (with the original lyrics) is the beautiful one by Judy Garland:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/5g4lY8Y3eoo&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;christmas-carols-with-other-people&#34;&gt;Christmas carols with other people&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I had the opportunity to sing a lot of Christmas carols with a number of other guests, some of whom were music students with astounding voices. Since they were female, I tried to blend in along with the pianist to fill in some harmony. I have basically no real experience in doing this, but it was fun, and I really enjoyed singing with other people.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Report on CMU Baroque Ensemble concert, with Stephen Schultz on Baroque flute</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/11/18/report-on-cmu-baroque-ensemble-concert-with-stephen-schultz-on-baroque-flute/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Nov 2012 20:53:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/11/18/report-on-cmu-baroque-ensemble-concert-with-stephen-schultz-on-baroque-flute/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I attended a free concert of the CMU Baroque Ensemble concert for the second time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/04/29/attending-my-first-cmu-baroque-ensemble-concert/&#34;&gt;My first time&lt;/a&gt;, several months ago, I enjoyed as my main attraction Bach&amp;rsquo;s Brandenburg concerto no. 2; this time, although the Brandenburg concerto no. 3 was performed, it was not the main draw for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I really looked forward to was simply seeing Stephen Schultz playing Baroque flute (amplified), premiering a new piece by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nancygalbraith.com/&#34;&gt;Nancy Galbraith&lt;/a&gt;, &amp;ldquo;Effervescent Air&amp;rdquo;. I had never seen him playing Baroque flute before, other than a demo of a few seconds when I was taking his course &amp;ldquo;Survey of Western Musical History&amp;rdquo; in 2006. That was actually the very first time I had ever seen a Baroque flute, and the first time I learned that anyone still played this instrument.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/cmu-baroque-2012-11-18.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Stephen Schulz&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed the concert. The standard Baroque pieces were performed with energy, and the newly composed piece for electric, amplified Baroque flute and piano, with orchestra, was a pleasant, fluttery soundscape, with some lovely textures as well as special echo effects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can listen to &amp;ldquo;Effervescent Air&amp;rdquo; here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;100%&#34; height=&#34;450&#34; scrolling=&#34;no&#34; frameborder=&#34;no&#34; src=&#34;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fapi.soundcloud.com%2Fplaylists%2F4222492&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I look forward to hearing more new music composed for Baroque flute in future CMU Baroque Ensemble concerts!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Another French music jam; also, announcing CATS Dance</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/09/28/another-french-music-jam-also-announcing-cats-dance/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Sep 2012 20:55:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/09/28/another-french-music-jam-also-announcing-cats-dance/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://thebridge.cmu.edu/images/W170xL170/0/noshadow/Organization/603b06cbdc7847018dce159a5ed99543.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;CATS Dance photo&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;On Monday I participated for my third time in Lisa&amp;rsquo;s French traditional dance music jam.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/08/27/my-second-french-music-jam-playing-my-irish-flute-in-public-for-the-first-time/&#34;&gt;Last time&lt;/a&gt;, I started playing my &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/irish-flute/&#34;&gt;Irish flute&lt;/a&gt; at the jam, continued playing my &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/baroque-flute/&#34;&gt;Baroque flute&lt;/a&gt;, and left my modern flute at home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This time, I changed things up. Also, we got a new musician playing a new instrument!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;instruments-and-musicians&#34;&gt;Instruments and musicians&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lisa was on fiddle as usual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we had John, who brought and used various kinds of accordions and his mandolin. (He had also brought recorders, in case I wanted to play with him, but I did not bring my recorders.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Allison was on piano.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Donna was on fiddle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most exciting to me was that Cindy came and played &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Autoharp&#34;&gt;autoharp&lt;/a&gt;. I think the addition of the harmonic accompaniment and countermelodies she provided was really nice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-instruments&#34;&gt;My instruments&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; bring my Baroque flute this time. I made a decision this week that I was no longer going to try to play my Baroque flute in most public situations. I have been frustrated that its soft sound gets drowned out by other instruments and just by people talking and socializing at parties. Therefore, when playing the Baroque flute in public, I will reserve it for very quiet performance situations only.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did bring my Irish flute, which served well when we were playing in appropriate keys.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have begun caving in and bringing my modern flute. It can be played more easily in all kinds of keys, and has the power to actually be heard. Maybe one day I&amp;rsquo;ll have a keyed wooden flute to play traditional music on, but that day is not near at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So after some experimentation, I believe I&amp;rsquo;m come to the right instrument(s) for different situations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;carnegie-alliance-of-traditional-and-social-dance-cats-dance&#34;&gt;Carnegie Alliance of Traditional and Social Dance (CATS Dance)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d like to take this opportunity to promote the new CMU-based dance group, the &lt;a href=&#34;http://thebridge.cmu.edu/organization/catsdance&#34;&gt;Carnegie Alliance of Traditional and Social Dance&lt;/a&gt;. Check out also their &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/catsdancepgh&#34;&gt;Facebook page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This group has been formed in order to grow a local community of people interested in all kinds of traditional and social dance, French dance being just one example; contra dancing and other folk dancing are also being explored.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In particular, this group exists because there is increasing interest among young people in these kinds of dances and music. The Pittsburgh dance scene has sometimes been dominated by older people, and it&amp;rsquo;s good to get younger people involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last week CATS Dance organized an outing to the regular &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburghcontra.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Contras and Squares&lt;/a&gt; Friday dance. Tomorrow there will be a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/events/105195582969170/&#34;&gt;French dance workshop and social dance&lt;/a&gt; held directly on CMU campus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These workshops and dances are, of course, open to everyone, not just CMU students. Abby and I are not CMU students, but &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/01/23/discovering-french-traditional-dance-in-pittsburgh/&#34;&gt;started attending&lt;/a&gt; these workshops at CMU in January. All ages and levels of dancers are always welcome! If you&amp;rsquo;re curious, drop by and check it out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first contra dance workshop to be hosted at CMU has also already been scheduled, for Sunday, October 7. Since I&amp;rsquo;ve never been to a contra dance workshop (although I had a sampling of contra dance at a birthday party &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/31/my-first-sampling-of-english-country-dance-and-contra-dance&#34;&gt;six months ago&lt;/a&gt;; I was very confused by it then), I hope Abby and I will make it to this workshop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2012-10-07&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-10-07)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/10/07/my-first-contra-dance-workshop-unexpected-fun/&#34;&gt;Abby and I did make it to the contra dance workshop&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I continue to greatly enjoy the regular French music jam and meeting and playing with more musicians. Meanwhile, although I have not done much dancing lately, I am excited about the creation of CATS Dance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2012-10-15&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-10-15)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out the latest update on the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/10/15/french-music-jam-with-unexpected-new-musicians/&#34;&gt;French music jam&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My first time singing bossa nova; also, a temporary farewell to Baroque flute</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/09/21/my-first-time-singing-bossa-nova-also-a-temporary-farewell-to-baroque-flute/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Sep 2012 23:33:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/09/21/my-first-time-singing-bossa-nova-also-a-temporary-farewell-to-baroque-flute/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Two weeks ago, I reported on &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/08/finally-performing-some-sonatas-for-baroque-flute/&#34;&gt;finally performing some sonatas for Baroque flute&lt;/a&gt;, at a party at my friend Henry&amp;rsquo;s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ironically, tonight, at another party of Henry&amp;rsquo;s, this time a birthday party for his father (his parents have been visiting), I ended up deciding to temporarily stop playing the Baroque flute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, more significantly: this was the &lt;em&gt;first time in my life singing a song at all as a solo vocalist with accompaniment&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Why and how?!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;music-plan&#34;&gt;Music plan&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since at the last party two weeks ago, I ended up playing on Baroque flute some selections from &amp;ldquo;English Airs and Dances&amp;rdquo;, this time I decided to play some other Baroque selections instead, from the &amp;ldquo;4 Scottish Sonatas&amp;rdquo; album.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;at-the-party&#34;&gt;At the party&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The party was great fun. We met more people, Henry&amp;rsquo;s parents were great, we ate a lot of food, and a surprising number of people played music, including some of the young children who came to the party. Accordions, tambourines, violin, piano, me on Baroque flute, Abby on tambura, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed doing some Scottish Baroque flute sonatas with Henry, but felt frustrated, as I have for some time now, both by the difficulty of playing the Baroque flute as well as the quietness of it, particularly noticeable tonight because of the large crowd of people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-i-ended-up-singing-bossa-nova-unexpectedly&#34;&gt;How I ended up singing bossa nova unexpectedly&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The musical highlight of the evening was Henry&amp;rsquo;s friends Gabe and Eric entertaining us with some virtuosic and often hilarious four-hand piano music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After they were done, Gabe hung around and periodically jammed with other people, including some who decided they wanted to sing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was so inspired that some &amp;ldquo;non-singers&amp;rdquo; (as they billed themselves) had the courage to sing, that I said, hey, I want to sing something! I didn&amp;rsquo;t have anything prepared, but asked Gabe if he could play bossa nova for me, and he said, sure, where&amp;rsquo;s a score?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I said I wanted to sing my favorite, &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chega_de_Saudade&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Chega de Saudade&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, so in a comic frenzy, I brought up the score on my smartphone, accessing my Dropbox. Someone gave me another smartphone so that I could do a Web search for the lyrics (which are in Portuguese, and which I have not memorized yet) and sing them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gabe did what he could, but it was difficult for him to read the score off the smartphone while someone tried to scroll and zoom in on it in real time. Still, we did sort of go through the song before giving up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;breaking-the-barrier&#34;&gt;Breaking the barrier&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, this was the &lt;em&gt;first time in my life singing a song at all as a solo vocalist with accompaniment&lt;/em&gt;. I was crazy nervous, but tried not to let on that this was my first time. I didn&amp;rsquo;t do too badly, considering the ad hoc circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The important thing was, &lt;em&gt;I had broken a barrier&lt;/em&gt;. I knew after this experience that &lt;em&gt;there was no turning back&lt;/em&gt;. I want to sing, &lt;em&gt;seriously&lt;/em&gt;, in the future. It&amp;rsquo;s time I started. I&amp;rsquo;ve wanted to do this for &lt;em&gt;decades&lt;/em&gt;, since I was a toddler singing along to records and to TV and to myself and to my sister. The singing impulse got &lt;strong&gt;killed&lt;/strong&gt; in me in middle school by a music teacher who made me feel incompetent and unworthy at a time when that was the last thing an adolescent needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I never expected that I&amp;rsquo;d get my start goofing around at a party. I have gone to karaoke-type events before, at which I &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; once considered singing, even while everyone else was doing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;after-the-party&#34;&gt;After the party&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I made some decisions after the party:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I am switching focus from Baroque flute to modern flute (with corresponding change in repertoire) in order to play music that is more audible and more party-friendly. I want to be playing bossa nova, for example.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I am going to start working on voice, so that I can sing at the next party of Henry&amp;rsquo;s, whenever that will be.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If I&amp;rsquo;m going to sing bossa nova seriously, I need to know Portuguese better.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet another musical party has &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/01/27/a-new-friends-very-musical-birthday-party-changed-my-life/&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;changed my life&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I now sing. Also, with some sadness, I am taking a break from Baroque flute.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My first bobblehead doll: guess who?</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/09/20/my-first-bobblehead-doll-guess-who/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Sep 2012 09:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/09/20/my-first-bobblehead-doll-guess-who/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/j-s-bach-bobblehead.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Johann Sebastian Bach bobblehead&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I now own my first &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bobblehead&#34;&gt;bobblehead doll&lt;/a&gt;! Abby was reluctant to let me take him home, but I argued that he would inspire me in the playing of his music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So &lt;em&gt;who&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;pittsburgh-music-alliance-launch-party&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Music Alliance launch party&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;about&#34;&gt;About&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburghmusicalliance.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Music Alliance&lt;/a&gt; had a launch party that Abby and I attended, held at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.contemporarycraft.org/&#34;&gt;Contemporary Craft&lt;/a&gt; in the Strip.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Pittsburgh Music Alliance is a new collaboration of five Pittsburgh music organizations for the purpose of increasing their audience:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bachchoirpittsburgh.org/&#34;&gt;Bach Choir of Pittsburgh&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pittsburghcamerata.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Camerata&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.chathambaroque.org/&#34;&gt;Chatham Baroque&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rbsp.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Renaissance and Baroque&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pittsburghchambermusic.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Chamber Music Society&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can find more information on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/PittsburghMusicAlliance&#34;&gt;Facebook page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;food-and-information-tables&#34;&gt;Food and information tables&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/189232_472125132808229_857638441_n.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Food and tables&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As we wandered around at the party, we sampled the food and checked out the tables of the five organizations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(There are &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/media/set/?set=a.472125112808231.106189.197956923558386&amp;amp;type=3&#34;&gt;photos of the party here&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;live-music&#34;&gt;Live music&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/199595_10151047722351513_1243992903_n.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Recorder quartet&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We arrived in time to see my &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/recorder/&#34;&gt;recorder&lt;/a&gt; friends perform as a recorder quartet, playing a variety of selections. Fred, Helen, Mike, and Annie were delightful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Afterwards, members of the five music organizations took turns performing for us. Unfortunately, the acoustic situation was quite poor amidst the party conversations going on everywhere, but I enjoyed watching the people who sang and played for us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-bobbleheads&#34;&gt;The bobbleheads&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We saw approximately ten bobbleheads, each in its unopened box, sitting around. I got very excited. It turned out that they were being given away. I secretly always wanted one since seeing my friend Henry with one on top of his piano; he had one of Beethoven:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/beethoven-bobblehead.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Beethoven bobblehead&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;By the bobbleheads, there was a sheet saying something like, &amp;ldquo;Name a piece I wrote and you can take me home.&amp;rdquo; It seemed that nobody was really enforcing this, but when I offered to take one, I said the bobblehead would help me as I worked on the composer&amp;rsquo;s [flute sonatas]().&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;notes-on-johann-sebastian-bach-s-flute-sonatas&#34;&gt;Notes on Johann Sebastian Bach&amp;rsquo;s flute sonatas&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The composer whose bobblehead I got was, of course, &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/johann-sebastian-bach/&#34;&gt;Johann Sebastian Bach&lt;/a&gt;, a hero of mine in the past year during which I&amp;rsquo;ve gradually fallen in love with Baroque music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-instrument&#34;&gt;What instrument?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am faced with a conundrum when trying to play Bach&amp;rsquo;s flute sonatas: &lt;em&gt;what instrument should I use to play this music?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the case of his son, &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carl_Philipp_Emanuel_Bach&#34;&gt;CPE Bach&lt;/a&gt;, two months ago in a recital &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/28/my-first-appearance-on-a-music-recital-program/&#34;&gt;I played a movement of CPE Bach&amp;rsquo;s solo flute sonata&lt;/a&gt; using a modern flute. I feel that the nature of CPE Bach&amp;rsquo;s music, more dramatic and agitated, makes the modern flute a reasonable instrument for the piece; I feel that it is definitely reasonable to play the music on a Baroque flute instead, but that I actually prefer it on modern flute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Plus, CPE Bach&amp;rsquo;s music is much easier to play on modern flute.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, Johann Sebastian Bach&amp;rsquo;s flute sonatas, although I prefer them on Baroque flute than to modern flute, are much harder to play on Baroque flute. It turns out that I dislike almost all recordings I&amp;rsquo;ve come across of this music on modern flute, with one exception: the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pahudbach.com/&#34;&gt;recordings&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/emmanuel-pahud/&#34;&gt;Emmanuel Pahud&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;my-decision&#34;&gt;My decision&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve made an unpleasant decision. I work on the slow, easy movements of the flute sonatas on Baroque flute, and I don&amp;rsquo;t currently work on the harder movements at all. I&amp;rsquo;m still far worse on Baroque flute than on modern flute, and those fast movements are beyond me on Baroque flute. And I don&amp;rsquo;t really want to play the music on modern flute. This is just my personal choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a great time at the Pittsburgh Music Alliance season launch party. It was inspiring to see my recorder friends playing, and to see others in the early music community performing with enthusiasm. (Seeing people singing as an ensemble even got me thinking about getting into that sometime maybe.) If you enjoy fresh, vital performances of early music, check out the five organizations mentioned!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I&amp;rsquo;m grateful to now be the proud owner of a Johann Sebastian Bach bobblehead doll. Every time I see him, I remember that I must play his music with verve and soul, because he&amp;rsquo;s watching.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The passion of Bach&#39;s Air on the G String: three very different interpretations</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/09/14/passion-of-bachs-air-on-the-g-string-three-different-interpretations/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Sep 2012 06:45:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/09/14/passion-of-bachs-air-on-the-g-string-three-different-interpretations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, while driving home from work, I had my radio on, tuned to Pittsburgh&amp;rsquo;s classical music station, &lt;a href=&#34;http://wqed.org/fm&#34;&gt;WQED FM&lt;/a&gt;, as usual, and I immediately recognized the piece that was being performed. I listened with curiosity and then anger and disappointment as I made my way home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a movement from one of Johann Sebastian Bach&amp;rsquo;s orchestra suites
(Orchestral Suite No. 3 in D major, BWV 1068), the movement that has been popularized in the form of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Air_on_the_G_String&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Air on the G String&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think this piece is a good litmus test of how we perceive and appreciate Baroque music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2015-06-10&#34;&gt;(Update of 2015-06-10)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many readers have commented on this post, and therefore I have written
an &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2015/06/10/revisiting-bachs-air-on-g-string-from-a-singing-and-dancing-viewpoint/&#34;&gt;important sequel&lt;/a&gt; to this post, 3 years later!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-listening-test&#34;&gt;A listening test&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please click around on the YouTube videos to get a taste of different ways of performing the Air from Bach&amp;rsquo;s suite. I&amp;rsquo;ve embedded three very different interpretations, each with its own qualities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Which do you like most of the three?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Which do you dislike most of the three?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People can get very emotional about differences in musical taste, and I&amp;rsquo;m not here to start an argument (just look at any of the comment threads on YouTube videos and you see what I mean!), but rather a discussion. I recognize that your choices might be &lt;em&gt;completely different&lt;/em&gt; from mine, and I&amp;rsquo;m &lt;em&gt;completely OK&lt;/em&gt; with that, and hope that you might be &lt;em&gt;completely OK&lt;/em&gt; with my choices also!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/e2OoJamNLMQ&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/SZ6nS1wau0I&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/VEpCjxOJgms&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;objective-comparisons&#34;&gt;Objective comparisons&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;stokowski&#34;&gt;Stokowski&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first version is an arrangement by Leopold Stokowski, from maybe the 1950s. It is a very slow, richly scored, melodically oriented version with emphasis on a deep, swelling vibrato-filled string sound. Different lines are given emphasis, one after another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;croatian-baroque-ensemble&#34;&gt;Croatian Baroque Ensemble&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second version is a live performance from 2010 by the Croatian Baroque Ensemble. It is played on period instruments, very briskly, with a prominent harpsichord continuo, with minimal vibrato in the strings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;karajan&#34;&gt;Karajan&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third version is from a recording by Herbert von Karajan and the Berlin Philharmonic, from maybe the 1980s. It is marked by a blend of legato voices, with an emphasis on unified beautiful tone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-your-preference-means&#34;&gt;What your preference means&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, I would like to point out that of these three versions, although I have a clear personal ranking, there are many things I don&amp;rsquo;t like about my favorite version of the three. If I were setting up a performance of this piece, I would make many different interpretive choices. Therefore, my indication of my preference is not an endorsement of every element of my preferred version.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The style classification system I&amp;rsquo;m using here is directly taken from the fascinating book by &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bruce_Haynes&#34;&gt;Bruce Haynes&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.oup.com/us/catalog/general/subject/Music/MusicHistoryWestern/EarlyMusicMedievalRenaissance/~~/dmlldz11c2EmY2k9OTc4MDE5NTE4OTg3Mg==&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The End of Early Music&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. In fact, the Air from the G String is used as an example in his book. My observations and descriptions here, however, are my own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;stokowski-the-romantic-style&#34;&gt;Stokowski: the Romantic style&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you liked the Stokowski best, you favor the old-fashioned Romantic style, music played with a long heart-throbbing melodic line and rich accompaniment. Soulful cellos are your thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you dislike, you have a problem with odd composer-unintended arrangements, super-slow sentimentality, and personal idiosyncrasies such as slowing down to savor a particular romantic moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;croatian-baroque-ensemble-the-period-style&#34;&gt;Croatian Baroque Ensemble: the Period style&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you like the Croatian Baroque Ensemble best, you favor a quick rhythm and counterpoint, with an emphasis on dissonance, as the carrier of heightened emotion. You like music to be played as though spoken, with many separated phrases, as though question and answer pairs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you dislike, you don&amp;rsquo;t like the rougher sound of non-vibrato violins, the dissonant attacks, and most of all, the speed and detachment of phrases that removes the relaxing, romantic mood you prefer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;karajan-the-modern-style&#34;&gt;Karajan: the Modern style&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you like Karajan, you focus on clear, beautiful tone, and seamless integration of instruments, avoidance of roughness and imperfection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you dislike, you find the endless legato lifeless and missing the extra edge of passion, and you perceive that the emphasis on integration detracts from the clarity of individual voices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-preferences&#34;&gt;My preferences&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I prefer the Period approach of the Croatian Baroque Ensemble. I find it the most poignant and passionate of the three selections. I like the pauses of silence, the emphasis and swelling into the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bach.org/bach101/instrumental/3rd_suite_orch_bwv1068.html&#34;&gt;dissonant moments&lt;/a&gt;. The tempo is fast enough that the phrases feel like speaking and breathing. This is the Bach I have fallen in love with and have been enjoying playing myself in the past two years on &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/recorder/&#34;&gt;recorder&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/baroque-flute/&#34;&gt;Baroque flute&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, I have an honest, real emotional response to the Romantic approach of Stokowski, however perverse and bizarre it may be. It&amp;rsquo;s clearly nothing resembling what Bach would have expected in a performance. But on its own, it&amp;rsquo;s an ingenious product of Stokowski&amp;rsquo;s personal vision. You could say that Stokowski stole Bach&amp;rsquo;s notes and then composed his own thing using them as a starting point, changing everything else (from instrumentation to tempo to dynamics to articulation). I respect that. So even though part of me is horrified by this kind of plagiarism, part of me is also excited and wish that more of this perverse creativity would happen today. The Romantic approach went out of style decades ago, however, in favor of the Modern approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, the Modern approach basically leaves me cold. Yes, the Karajan version was the one I heard in my car while driving home from work. I felt angry and sad by how the performance did not really inspire me. It was boring and muddy to me. Karajan may have been playing the pitch values of the notes the way Bach wrote them down, and not &amp;ldquo;disrespectfully&amp;rdquo; messed with the elements that Stokowski eagerly transformed and added to, but to me, his performance was more of a boring lecture to sit through than something that made me sit up and engage with the music. &lt;em&gt;It was muzak to me.&lt;/em&gt; That was my reaction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;period-contrast-ton-koopman-with-amsterdam-baroque-orchestra&#34;&gt;Period contrast: Ton Koopman with Amsterdam Baroque Orchestra&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I mentioned earlier that there are many things I would do differently than the Croation Baroque Ensemble. The Period approach, like the Romantic and Modern ones, is not a single interpretation: it&amp;rsquo;s an entire approach with much diversity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a live performance in Period style that is noticeably different from the Croatian Baroque Ensemble performance. It is slower and sweeter, for example. But it also has more contrast between the long legato lines and the detached figures within them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/NlT8yeEYbMs&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;which-do-i-like-better&#34;&gt;Which do I like better?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of the two sample Period performances, which do I prefer?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Who knows??&lt;/em&gt; When there are things I like and dislike about both? At some point (I try to make this quick), I stop being a listener or critic, and feel the need to &lt;em&gt;stop listening&lt;/em&gt;, and go to work &lt;em&gt;myself&lt;/em&gt; on how I would do things very differently, from anyone else, as a performer, to express my personal feeling for the music. That is why I&amp;rsquo;ve switched in the past two years from being a listener to being a performer. I can&amp;rsquo;t sit around pining away waiting from someone to play something the way I really like it. I have to do the work myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope this little exercise is helpful in clarifying some of the differences in the approach to performing and enjoying Baroque era music. The question of how to best deal with music from the 1700s is one that everyone who plays or listens to it has to grapple with, whether implicitly or explicitly. I think Haynes&amp;rsquo; basic framework of three different styles is a useful one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Myself, in the past year or two during which I have suddenly fallen in love with Baroque music, after a lifetime of not really liking it at all, I have been persuaded by the Period approach, both as a listener and now also as a performer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2015-06-10-1&#34;&gt;(Update of 2015-06-10)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many readers have commented on this post, and therefore I have written
an &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2015/06/10/revisiting-bachs-air-on-g-string-from-a-singing-and-dancing-viewpoint/&#34;&gt;important sequel&lt;/a&gt; to this post, 3 years later!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Finally performing some sonatas for Baroque flute</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/09/08/finally-performing-some-sonatas-for-baroque-flute/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Sep 2012 23:26:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/09/08/finally-performing-some-sonatas-for-baroque-flute/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.boosey.com/imagesw/shop/product/$wm1_0x700_$_ED_12861-English_Airs_cov.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;English Airs and Dances&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Abby and I went to another party at Henry&amp;rsquo;s, the first one we&amp;rsquo;ve been to &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/30/a-delayed-st-patricks-day-party-playing-tin-whistle-and-alto-recorder/&#34;&gt;in five months&lt;/a&gt;. He&amp;rsquo;s had other parties, but we&amp;rsquo;ve been very busy all spring and summer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tonight was another big musical milestone for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;music-plan&#34;&gt;Music plan&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Henry had actually announced two parties coming up. This party was going to feature a four-hand piano recital after dinner, to be performed by his friends Gabe and Eric. The second party was going to be for his father&amp;rsquo;s birthday, as his parents were going to be visiting him. He was asking whether anyone wanted to play for his father&amp;rsquo;s birthday party, so I volunteered for that, saying that I would like to play some music for Baroque flute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Henry was very curious to hear me play Baroque flute, since I had in fact never played it at one of his earlier parties. He said I should bring along the music to the first party so that he could read the keyboard part, before his father&amp;rsquo;s birthday party.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;baroque-flute&#34;&gt;Baroque flute&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the past couple of months, the Baroque flute has been my main focus of music practice, because of my fascination with Baroque music and the special qualities of the Baroque flute (in contrast with the modern flute). It&amp;rsquo;s a very difficult instrument to play, unfortunately. Nevertheless, I want to get at least close to using the Baroque flute to create the kind of sound and texture I want to get from Baroque music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I have been using the book/CD sets from the Carnegie Library that I found in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.boosey.com/pages/shop/prod_series_list.asp?seriesID=10214&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Baroque Around the World&amp;rdquo; series&lt;/a&gt;. Ironically, the first of those sets that I had taken out, I had done not even knowing it was Baroque music, and &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/30/bought-a-baroque-flute/&#34;&gt;used it for practicing with modern flute&lt;/a&gt;! In fact, I once performed one of the selections, Henry Holcombe&amp;rsquo;s Air in E minor, on modern flute (gasp), at a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/04/27/baroque-jam-session-at-cmu/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Baroque music jam session&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. It was not until recently that I decided to start playing the music on Baroque flute. Now, I don&amp;rsquo;t want to play this music on modern flute if I can help it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, I took out some of the other volumes from the &amp;ldquo;Baroque Around the World&amp;rdquo; series. For example, I was intrigued by the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.boosey.com/shop/prod/Johnson-David-4-Scottish-Sonatas-Baroque-Around-the-World-series-Book-CD/2001256&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;4 Scottish Sonatas&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; volume. Much of the music is clearly for violin, but some of it seems to work pretty well for flute also. In any case, it is different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Henry&amp;rsquo;s parties, I decided to focus on playing well a few of the selections &amp;ldquo;English Airs and Dances&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;at-the-party&#34;&gt;At the party&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The usual things happened at the party before our pianists showed up to perform after dinner: good food, conversation, chess, music jamming. Abby brought her various stringed instruments to play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ended up reading almost the whole book of &amp;ldquo;English Airs and Dances&amp;rdquo; with Henry on piano. &amp;ldquo;Oops&amp;rdquo;. I should know by now that if I bring a book of music, we&amp;rsquo;ll go through a lot more than the few selections I thought I was preparing. So I had to sight read some stuff I had never actually played. I can&amp;rsquo;t play very fast on Baroque flute, so I was botching things up here and there. No matter, it was fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Up till now, I had never actually performed Baroque flute sonatas and other works with keyboard accompaniment. This is partly because I am not very good at Baroque flute and also because I just don&amp;rsquo;t have as many opportunities to play Baroque flute with other people as I do using other instruments. In any case, I was pleased to finally be out there on Baroque flute.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My second French music jam: playing my Irish flute in public for the first time</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/08/27/my-second-french-music-jam-playing-my-irish-flute-in-public-for-the-first-time/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Aug 2012 22:37:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/08/27/my-second-french-music-jam-playing-my-irish-flute-in-public-for-the-first-time/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Tonight I participated for the second time in a new little &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/groups/182324948478861/&#34;&gt;French traditional dance&lt;/a&gt; music jam session that &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/02/my-first-french-music-jam-anxious-but-excited/&#34;&gt;started up in July&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This time, I played not only my &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/baroque-flute/&#34;&gt;Baroque flute&lt;/a&gt; (which happens to be the instrument I&amp;rsquo;ve mostly been playing for the past two months), but also my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/30/got-my-new-casey-burns-small-handed-irish-flute/&#34;&gt;new Irish flute I got a month ago&lt;/a&gt;. I did &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; bring my modern flute at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we did the last time, after we played around for an hour or so, we then played for dancers for another hour. I enjoyed the experience a lot, and was less nervous than I was the first time. I am slowly improving at learning a tune, without a score, while someone is playing it, and then imitating the melodic line or filling in a harmonically sensible line on the fly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;instruments-and-musicians&#34;&gt;Instruments and musicians&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I finally received my Irish flute a month ago and have spent some minutes every day breaking it in at home. Tonight was its &amp;ldquo;debut&amp;rdquo; in public. I enjoyed the louder, stronger sound.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still used the Baroque flute, for key signatures that my keyless Irish flute does not work well for (half-holing is a pain).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also had fiddles, melodeon, guitar, mandolin (not all at the same time, since John was switching between melodeon and mandolin depending on the key of the song, given the limitations of the melodeon), and I felt that the Irish flute was balanced pretty well with the other instruments, better than the Baroque flute did in the first session in July (when it was often drowned out).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We lost some musicians from last time, because one of them left town, and the clarinetist has a class in the evening and therefore cannot arrive till later, when she comes to dance. But we had two new people!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our little French music group is gaining momentum. I&amp;rsquo;m very excited! Also, as the CMU fall semester starts, there are plans to really promote French and other traditional music and dance in the form of an official CMU student organization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2012-09-28&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-09-28)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/28/another-french-music-jam-also-announcing-cats-dance/&#34;&gt;CATS Dance successfully launched in September&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>