<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Kretschmann Farm on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/kretschmann-farm/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Kretschmann Farm on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/kretschmann-farm/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Why we decided to compile our own family cookbook</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/12/07/why-we-decided-to-compile-our-own-family-cookbook/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Dec 2014 19:46:48 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/12/07/why-we-decided-to-compile-our-own-family-cookbook/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Cooking has been a significant part of my life since 1999 when, shortly before reaching age 30, my bachelor self decided to completely change his unhealthy diet and lifestyle, and that meant &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/03/21/time-to-taste-the-world-thoughts-on-expanding-my-food-tastes-as-an-adult/&#34;&gt;finally getting down and dirty with seriously cooking for myself&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After getting married to Abby ten years later, cooking responsibilities have rotated between us based on the situation; there have been long stretches of time during which I did all the cooking every day, and there have been long periods during which she did all the cooking. Currently, we roughly split the cooking between us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-compile-our-own-cookbook&#34;&gt;Why compile our own cookbook?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve occasionally posted on this blog a recipe and/or photos of some food I&amp;rsquo;ve cooked, but for the most part, cooking is just a mundane everyday activity that I don&amp;rsquo;t keep track of, since the task of cooking is primarily utilitarian for us, not innovative or artistic. We simply need to eat every day, and prefer not to eat out often, for various reasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently I decided that we should start compiling our own family cookbook, noting details of what we prepare and how, in order to better replicate good results and improve on bad results, and make planning and impromptu cooking more efficient. Without our own cookbook, we have to rely on our faulty memories, and things sometimes don&amp;rsquo;t come out right (especially where the oven is concerned).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below is an example of the kind of cooking we do. This is not a cooking blog, so I don&amp;rsquo;t expect to write much or often about our cooking, but I just felt like it tonight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-i-prepared-tonight&#34;&gt;What I prepared tonight&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;raw-veggie-sticks&#34;&gt;Raw veggie sticks&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/franklinmingchen/15945039966&#34; title=&#34;IMG_20141207_174932 by Franklin Chen, on Flickr&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7535/15945039966_f2273fbf1d.jpg&#34; width=&#34;375&#34; height=&#34;500&#34; alt=&#34;IMG_20141207_174932&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We like to regularly cut up raw veggie sticks to eat as daytime snacks at work, or sometimes also as crunchy variety during regular meals as part of salads. I chopped up some carrots and celery for this purpose tonight. We often use other ingredients also, but tonight I just stuck to the basics. A list of some random options we&amp;rsquo;ve used (depending on season, availability in our &lt;a href=&#34;http://kretschmannfarm.com/&#34;&gt;Kretschmann Farm&lt;/a&gt; box subscription, and whim while out grocery shopping):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;carrots&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;celery&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;cucumbers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;peppers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;radishes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;parsnips&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;beets&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;turnips&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trick is simply to slice stuff lengthwise into reasonable widths, then chop them across to create reasonable lengths. No need to be exact. Also, &lt;a href=&#34;http://groovygreenlivin.com/5-vegetables-that-you-don%E2%80%99t-need-to-peel/&#34;&gt;we don&amp;rsquo;t bother to peel carrots&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;kale-boiled&#34;&gt;Kale, boiled&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/franklinmingchen/15970795205&#34; title=&#34;IMG_20141207_174941 by Franklin Chen, on Flickr&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7560/15970795205_3e6492769a.jpg&#34; width=&#34;375&#34; height=&#34;500&#34; alt=&#34;IMG_20141207_174941&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We like kale. There are actually many different varieties with different colors and textures. Here&amp;rsquo;s some ordinary kale. I find it easiest to just boil it while preparing other foods. I test it periodically to make sure it is no longer tough to eat but still has some bite also and is not soggy. We boil the kale either in water or in our own homemade chicken broth that we make with the bones and other parts of whole chickens after eating the muscle meat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;turnips-sauteed&#34;&gt;Turnips, sauteed&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/franklinmingchen/15970797965&#34; title=&#34;IMG_20141207_174949 by Franklin Chen, on Flickr&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm9.staticflickr.com/8671/15970797965_64a385e5dd.jpg&#34; width=&#34;375&#34; height=&#34;500&#34; alt=&#34;IMG_20141207_174949&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OK, this is an example of something of an experiment that is going into the family cookbook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have cooked turnips in many ways (including, of course, as raw veggie sticks). Possibly the most common way we cook them is in the oven along with beets, potatoes, or the like, either as chunks or in &amp;ldquo;home fries&amp;rdquo; shapes. I&amp;rsquo;ve also prepared them as part of beef casserole dishes in the oven. Or as chicken stir fry with turnips. The possibilities are endless. You just have to be aware of how long they take to cook, and how thinly to slice for the purpose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tonight, I decided to slice the turnips very thin, for the purpose of creating a nice topping for the main dish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;extra virgin olive oil&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;turnips, sliced very thin&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;some onion bits&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;fresh rosemary&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;salt and pepper&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;garlic, generous amount&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My habit these days when cooking in the skillet is to delay the introduction of the garlic, in order to give the result more kick.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;baked-salmon&#34;&gt;Baked salmon&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/franklinmingchen/15968891841&#34; title=&#34;IMG_20141207_180014 by Franklin Chen, on Flickr&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7570/15968891841_7e3aa84a19.jpg&#34; width=&#34;375&#34; height=&#34;500&#34; alt=&#34;IMG_20141207_180014&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, some fish (salmon). I have to confess that I&amp;rsquo;m not yet very happy about the results when I cook fish. Abby does a better job than me overall, so I usually let her cook fish. Still, both of us find it tricky to get fish just so: what&amp;rsquo;s the perfect balance between undercooked and overcooked?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I slightly overcooked the salmon tonight, for a couple of reasons: I forgot to get it out of the fridge earlier in the day to warm it up more before preparation, and I baked a bit too long as an attempt to make up for that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using the oven is always tricky for me. Higher temperature means cooking faster, but also means drying things out. For this dish, I decided on a temperature of 400 F for 30 minutes. Next time, if I have the salmon fully defrosted, I believe 20 should do the trick.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;extra virgin olive oil&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;lemon slices&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;salmon fillets, skin side down on top of the lemon slices&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;salt and pepper&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;fresh rosemary&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;garlic, generous amount&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;some onion bits&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result came out a bit dry, but other than that tasted great to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re wondering &amp;ldquo;why rosemary in particular&amp;rdquo;, the answer is &amp;ldquo;our farm box from last week gave us a bunch and we need to use it&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cooking is a necessity but can be a pleasure or a frustration as well. There are times when I feel &amp;ldquo;lazy&amp;rdquo; and don&amp;rsquo;t want to cook and feel it&amp;rsquo;s a chore, but there are times when I feel slightly creative or experimental and want to make something I will find enjoyable to eat (and hopefully Abby will find enjoyable to eat also). Hopefully collecting our efforts into a cookbook will make it easier to whip up more variety when we are feeling &amp;ldquo;lazy&amp;rdquo; and don&amp;rsquo;t want to think too much.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Finally making rhubarb tasty to myself: flour-less rhubarb crisp</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/06/09/finally-making-rhubarb-tasty-to-myself/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Jun 2014 18:15:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/06/09/finally-making-rhubarb-tasty-to-myself/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;For the first forty years of my life, I believe I never ate any rhubarb. At least, I don&amp;rsquo;t ever recall anything identified as rhubarb that I ate. It was just something I heard about, in the context of pie, and I rarely eat pies, and am rather particular about pie when I do eat it (for example, I have sometimes eaten pumpkin pie, because my father likes it, but I never once really enjoyed it).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My Krestschmann Farm box subscription has always recognized that some people don&amp;rsquo;t like rhubarb, and allows opting out of receiving it. Since I never ate it, I didn&amp;rsquo;t know whether I liked it, but looking up its description online, I felt no need to try it, so I always indicated that I did not want it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today was the first time I cooked rhubarb and made something that I actually enjoyed eating. Here&amp;rsquo;s the story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-first-time-cooking-rhubarb-was-a-disaster&#34;&gt;My first time cooking rhubarb was a disaster&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost exactly a year ago, Abby and I accidentally did not specify rhubarb exclusion from our farm box (upon renewing our subscription). So we received rhubarb.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t know what the heck to do with it. I decided to make an Indian-style lentil dish and &amp;ldquo;hide&amp;rdquo; rhubarb in it. At first I thought it was OK, but then I decided it was weird. Unfortunately, I had to finish the whole batch. Abby didn&amp;rsquo;t help me finish it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rhubarb-lentils-2013-06-10.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Rhubarb lentils&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;abby-s-experiment-didn-t-work-for-me&#34;&gt;Abby&amp;rsquo;s experiment didn&amp;rsquo;t work for me&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby also tried an experiment, cooking rhubarb with banana on the stove. The resulting concoction caused an argument, because after trying it, I refused to eat any more of it, but she had made a huge batch and so she was stuck with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-experiment-today&#34;&gt;My experiment today&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I decided that instead of randomly making crap up, I would look for some kind of &amp;ldquo;recipe&amp;rdquo;, and also incorporate the advice of friends from last year. The following is what I made. I found it surprisingly edible, and even had to stop myself from eating too much after dinner:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rhubarb-2014-06-09.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Rhubarb crisp&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My ingredients:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Coconut oil&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rhubarb, chopped up&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Honey (I tried to go easy with this!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cinnamon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cloves&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Orange zest&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lemon juice&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Salt&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cocoa powder (a tiny sprinkle, just an improvisation)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Raw walnuts and pecans, chopped&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Preheat oven to 350 degrees F, layer the nuts on top of the remainder of the mixture, and bake for 40 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to everyone who offered suggestions to me last year!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result was fairly tart, which is fine, but I didn&amp;rsquo;t want to put too much sugar into this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-next&#34;&gt;What next?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was planning to notify Kretschmann Farm that we don&amp;rsquo;t want to receive rhubarb, but I have second thoughts now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, we will probably go ahead as planned and put rhubarb on our &amp;ldquo;do not want&amp;rdquo; list, simply because we&amp;rsquo;d rather get other stuff instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;lessons-learned&#34;&gt;Lessons learned&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I learned some lessons from this whole rhubarb incident:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I can learn to &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/03/21/time-to-taste-the-world-thoughts-on-expanding-my-food-tastes-as-an-adult/&#34;&gt;like stuff I never ate for decades&lt;/a&gt;, if I prepare it just so. (More generally, I try to continuously find opportunities to &lt;a href=&#34;http://sivers.org/hate&#34;&gt;love what I used to hate&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is wise to listen to accumulated wisdom, especially from my friends (whose taste might be correlated a bit with mine).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Accidentally &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; choosing to opt out of my &amp;ldquo;default&amp;rdquo; preference led to some interesting experiences.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s the latest food you feared or hated or didn&amp;rsquo;t know about that you recently tried? How did it go? If it went poorly, will you try again, or just write it off?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A winter red cabbage slaw for the New Year</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/01/01/a-winter-red-cabbage-slaw-for-the-new-year/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2013 21:34:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/01/01/a-winter-red-cabbage-slaw-for-the-new-year/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Happy New Year!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/red-cabbage-slaw.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Red cabbage slaw&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For a party, I used what was at hand at home to make something to share. I decided on a red cabbage slaw, after doing a Google search for ingredients and seeing some recipes. I didn&amp;rsquo;t follow any one recipe, but merged a couple of ideas. Since people seemed to eat up the cabbage slaw, and several complimented me on it and asked for the recipe, here it is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;recipe-for-red-cabbage-slaw&#34;&gt;Recipe for red cabbage slaw&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; red cabbage, sliced thin&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2 &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.orangepippin.com/apples/goldrush&#34;&gt;Gold Rush&lt;/a&gt; apples, peeled and sliced thin&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;4 carrots, grated&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.organicgardeninfo.com/growing-cylindra-beets.html&#34;&gt;long beet&lt;/a&gt;, grated&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; red onion, sliced thin&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dressing:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;6 tablespoons extra virgin olive oil&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;6 tablespoons raw apple cider vinegar&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;4 tablespoons honey mustard&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2 cloves of garlic, minced&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Toppings:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;pecans&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;walnuts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;raisins&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Put all the prepared ingredients into a large bowl.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mix the dressing into the bowl.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover and leave in the refrigerator for 24 hours. Stir again once or twice during that period to make sure everything is even.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;notes&#34;&gt;Notes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some recipes for cabbage slaw that I saw called for added sugar, but given the specific ingredients I chose, there was no need at all for extra sugar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I chose some nuts that seemed to make sense. Other nuts could be used also, or left out if someone is allergic to nuts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I could see dried cranberries being used instead of raisins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other substitutions are easy to imagine also; in fact, my recipe involved substitutions for ingredients in recipes I found online.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;thanks&#34;&gt;Thanks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The red cabbage, Gold Rush apples, carrots, long beet happen to have come from our &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.kretschmannfarm.com/Winter%20Boxes/Winter%20boxes.htm&#34;&gt;winter box subscription from Kretschmann Farm&lt;/a&gt;. Abby and I are really happy that they offer a winter box subscription as well as the regular season subscription, so that we can continue to get quality organic, local produce all year long.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having a subscription not only allows us to eat seasonally, but also explore foods we may not necessarily have eaten much of or even seen before. For example, I like these long beets and Gold Rush apples.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reflections on Food Day</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/10/24/reflections-on-food-day/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Oct 2012 22:38:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/10/24/reflections-on-food-day/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/food-day-2012-breakfast-1.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Soup and veggies&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A year ago I celebrated &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.foodday.org/&#34;&gt;Food Day&lt;/a&gt; for the first time, by sharing &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/24/every-day-is-food-day/&#34;&gt;some reflections on what food means to me&lt;/a&gt;. Today I review my reflections and some more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;buying-food&#34;&gt;Buying food&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I still take care to shop carefully for groceries and make our own tasty meals to eat. Some of our sources:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://kretschmannfarm.com/&#34;&gt;Kretschmann Farm&lt;/a&gt; CSA subscription for local produce&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.localharvest.org/miseras-organic-farm-M14896&#34;&gt;Misera&amp;rsquo;s Organic Farm&lt;/a&gt; for local &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/24/whats-a-nice-acorn-squash-like-you-doing-in-a-pot-of-spicy-lentils/&#34;&gt;chickens&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lewisfamilyfarms.com/&#34;&gt;Lewis Family Farms&lt;/a&gt; for local beef&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://pine-richland.patch.com/articles/stoney-lane-farm-a-little-bit-country-in-suburbia&#34;&gt;Stoney Lane Farm&lt;/a&gt; for local &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/28/thankful-for-the-free-range-orange-yolked-eggs/&#34;&gt;eggs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.traderjoes.com/&#34;&gt;Trader Joe&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.eastendfood.coop/&#34;&gt;East End Food Co-op&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our food choices are based on our concerns for both &lt;em&gt;health&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;sustainability&lt;/em&gt;. Our choices may have an impact on one or the other or both.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;cooking&#34;&gt;Cooking&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I started my blog over a year ago, I had thought I would be posting more about cooking, since I was doing a good amount of it, but as it turned out, during this year (2012), Abby took over almost all of the cooking for us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;diet&#34;&gt;Diet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both Abby and I have experimented in paleo directions in the past year. As a reminder, this doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean that we&amp;rsquo;re just going around chowing down on all the meat we can eat. It does mean that we have&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;considerably increased our consumption of vegetables&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;increased our consumption of various fats and oils&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;reduced our consumption of carbs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-question-of-carbs&#34;&gt;The question of carbs&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What we seemed to discover was that we needed some base level of carbs in order to maintain energy and weight levels. Through experimentation, Abby has focused on getting carbs through potatoes and sweet potatoes primarily, going almost completely off wheat. I, on the other hand, am still hooked on rice; I also still eat some wheat, but frankly, I can tell from the effects that I would probably do best to eliminate it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;rice-disaster&#34;&gt;Rice disaster?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, I wondered about brown rice, and even briefly experimented with &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/07/is-brown-rice-healthy-or-not/&#34;&gt;switching to white rice&lt;/a&gt;. The white rice experiment was a fast failure: the high glycemic index and lack of fiber didn&amp;rsquo;t help me at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More recently, there have been reports of &lt;em&gt;brown rice&lt;/em&gt; in particular having &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.consumerreports.org/cro/magazine/2012/11/arsenic-in-your-food/index.htm&#34;&gt;high levels of arsenic&lt;/a&gt;. This is rather disturbing, and Abby and I have agreed that I need to quickly re-evaluate my consumption of brown rice. I&amp;rsquo;ve committed to trying out some alternative source of calories/fiber.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-breakfast&#34;&gt;My breakfast&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My breakfast has remained fairly &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/01/26/improving-my-breakfast-and-other-meals/&#34;&gt;stable&lt;/a&gt; since &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/23/paleo-diet-experimentation/&#34;&gt;I quit oatmeal&lt;/a&gt;. Basically, I eat&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;veggies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;eggs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;nuts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a prune&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Depending on how I feel and what&amp;rsquo;s available, occasionally I&amp;rsquo;ll eat some bacon or fish, and sometimes I&amp;rsquo;ll add some sweet potatoes or other carbs, but typically that&amp;rsquo;s it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(I stopped the flax seeds, largely out of inconvenience of grinding them!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s what I happened to eat today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/food-day-2012-breakfast-1.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Soup and veggies&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/food-day-2012-breakfast-2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Eggs&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The soup and veggies were leftovers from big batches Abby or I had made earlier:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;my cauliflower leaf soup with garlic, carrots, sweet potatoes, curry powder, extra virgin olive oil&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;my stir-fried cauliflower florets with garlic, green peppers, coconut oil&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Abby&amp;rsquo;s spaghetti squash with onion and other stuff&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And on top of that I also ate two fried eggs with walnuts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-lunch-and-dinner&#34;&gt;My lunch and dinner&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lunch and dinner were combinations of various leftovers, all originally made by Abby (hence my not knowing the exact ingredients):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ground beef stew with green peppers, jalapeno, onion, various seasoning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;slow-cooked chicken with veggies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;leftover kale and onion&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;dinner included sauteed zucchini and other veggies Abby cooked tonight&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;brown rice&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;fasting&#34;&gt;Fasting&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes I deliberately fast for a meal or two. This happens when I just don&amp;rsquo;t feel all that hungry. I treat that as a signal from my body that I don&amp;rsquo;t really need to eat. My experiments have convinced me that &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Intermittent_fasting&#34;&gt;intermittent fasting&lt;/a&gt; helps with fat loss and mental clarity. It also helps me remember to be grateful, when I do eat again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are human beings, not robots. We need food. And food isn&amp;rsquo;t just &amp;ldquo;fuel&amp;rdquo;. It lives or has lived. It is complex. I am grateful to be living in a land of plenty, and that Abby has taken so much care to make varied and tasty dishes for us. But as the recent reports on arsenic reminds me, there is much we must continue to do to prevent the degradation of what we eat.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Learning about gardening from Grow Pittsburgh</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/01/27/learning-about-gardening-from-grow-pittsburgh/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Jan 2012 06:57:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/01/27/learning-about-gardening-from-grow-pittsburgh/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/-8fnzFicG66o/Ts0QOtxEeUI/AAAAAAAABvU/aZOUP36NlJo/s576/GardenPrimerSOCIAL.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;A Garden Primer&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, Abby and I finished the third and final session of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.showclix.com/search/A%20Garden%20Primer&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;A Garden Primer&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, a basic course on organic gardening offered by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.growpittsburgh.org/&#34;&gt;Grow Pittsburgh&lt;/a&gt;. We took this course because we would like to start our own little urban garden.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/a-garden-primer.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Third meeting of A Garden Primer&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As an utter beginner with no experience, I thought the course was a very useful and friendly introduction to organic gardening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;our-goal&#34;&gt;Our goal&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I have a small front yard which we would like to use to grow vegetables to eat. Although we are subscribers to a CSA, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.kretschmannfarm.com/&#34;&gt;Kretschmann Farm&lt;/a&gt;, we could always use more vegetables to eat, especially since we have increased their proportion in our diet relative to the proportion of grains we formerly consumed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;attendance&#34;&gt;Attendance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were about 25-30 of us in this three-week course, which met for two hours each Thursday evening at the East Liberty Presbyterian Church. There was a mix of people who participated: mostly young people in their twenties, but also older folks as well; most of us are from the city, but there were also those from further out with more space. Some already had serious gardening experience, while some were total novices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dinner was included, a nice touch given everyone&amp;rsquo;s busy schedules: burritos provided by Chipotle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;format&#34;&gt;Format&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The format of the course was that there were lectures with slide presentations, during which we were free to ask questions, and we received a 90-page reference manual at the beginning of the course that goes into much more detail about topics and is designed for reference when we actually start getting our hands dirty (I took some notes in my copy during lectures).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the second two weeks, we had homework in which we each came up with a preliminary design for our garden and discussed it in class, and homework in which we decided what to grow and discussed that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also received a seed catalog so that we could learn what criteria to look for when selecting seeds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;syllabus&#34;&gt;Syllabus&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A fundamental goal of the course, emphasized repeatedly, was to learn to grow in a way that is constructive to the land in the long run, rather than stripping resources from it in a short-term way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, the first thing we learned about was how to compost, and use compost as the basis of a healthy soil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then we learned about how to choose a location for a garden, and discussed different ways of constructing one. Many useful suggestions were provided for materials.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We learned about the seasons and life cycles of seeding, transplanting, harvesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, we learned about thinking of the whole ecosystem: how to deal with the real issues of pests, disease, and weeds without just getting out the machine gun and using nasty chemicals. We discussed mulching, crop rotation, taking advantage of beneficial insects (which will eat up the pests that actually harm leaves and fruit and roots).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Advice on garden maintenance and winding down the season ended the course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;our-plan&#34;&gt;Our plan&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I have yet to test the soil in the front yard, but in any case, we may go for a raised bed instead of an in-ground garden. We are thinking of a 12-by-3 foot area to use in the front yard. We will do more study and preparation before the spring comes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Doing some serious gardening will be a new adventure for Abby and me. I am grateful that Grow Pittsburgh has promoted urban gardening for local food production, and spread the word so that more of us in the city can comfortably start getting involved ourselves. I highly recommend the &amp;ldquo;Garden Primer&amp;rdquo; course to anyone who is a novice at organic gardening (whether urban or suburban or rural).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note&lt;/strong&gt;: the course is being offered again this winter two more times, so there is still time to jump in for this year:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tuesdays: February 7, 14, 21&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mondays: March 12, 19, 26&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What&#39;s a Nice Acorn Squash Like You Doing in a Pot of Spicy Lentils?</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/09/24/whats-a-nice-acorn-squash-like-you-doing-in-a-pot-of-spicy-lentils/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Sep 2011 18:09:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/09/24/whats-a-nice-acorn-squash-like-you-doing-in-a-pot-of-spicy-lentils/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A nice acorn squash was sitting on the kitchen counter, lonely since arriving days ago from the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.kretschmannfarm.com/&#34;&gt;farm&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When some lentils decided to soak in a bowl next to her on the counter, she decided she wanted to join them. Next thing she knew, there was a whole party gathering!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/lentil-acorn-squash-soup-ingredients.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Ingredients for lentil acorn squash soup&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trying to use up various ingredients from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.kretschmannfarm.com/&#34;&gt;Kretschmann Farm&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Community-supported_agriculture&#34;&gt;CSA&lt;/a&gt; we&amp;rsquo;ve been subscribing to for years now, I searched the web for ideas, of course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We always have a lot of legumes on hand to us (bought in bulk), especially lentils, so I found a &lt;a href=&#34;http://eatingplaces.wordpress.com/2011/01/21/acorn-squash-lentil-soup/&#34;&gt;simple recipe&lt;/a&gt;, and modified the recipe slightly to make a large batch of soup. We had some for dinner, and will have it for many more meals (we typically freeze some stuff for later when making big batches like this one).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The acorn squash and the carrots came from Kretschmann. The soup was not vegetarian, since we used a jar of homemade chicken broth from the batch that we had created after roasting a whole chicken (from our subscription to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.localharvest.org/miseras-organic-farm-M14896&#34;&gt;Misera Farm&lt;/a&gt; through Kretschmann) and using the leftover bones, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yummy!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/lentil-acorn-squash-soup-done.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Cooked lentil acorn squash soup&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>