<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Literature on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/literature/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Literature on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/literature/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Check out the unsanitized first edition of the Grimms&#39; fairy tales finally translated into English</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/20/check-out-the-unsanitized-first-edition-of-the-grimms-fairy-tales-finally-translated-into-english/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2014 23:11:02 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/20/check-out-the-unsanitized-first-edition-of-the-grimms-fairy-tales-finally-translated-into-english/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;What do you think of when you think of fairy tales? Cutesy kiddie stuff suitable for cartoons and school skits and costumes? Or &lt;strong&gt;murder, rape, cannibalism, cruelty, torture&lt;/strong&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve perversely loved fairy tales since coming across a huge collection of Grimms&amp;rsquo; and Hans Christian Andersen&amp;rsquo;s fairy tales in a tattered album at a flea market when I was five and having my mother buy it for me. I spent four years reading this book (until all the pages fell out; the binding was horrible) as well as I could (since these were not actually children&amp;rsquo;s editions but adult translations to English and my reading comprehension was limited), before deciding that I &amp;ldquo;outgrew&amp;rdquo; the genre and moving on. I spent many nights sleepless with terror, as well as many private moments crying with sadness while reading some of the stories: the one that affected me the most (since I have a younger sister) was &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brother_and_Sister&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Brother and Sister&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; from the Grimms&amp;rsquo; collection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have always been so fascinated by fairy tales, mythology, Biblical and other ancient stories in general, that I even briefly considered a major in folklore and mythology in college (and took two literature courses in the subject). And it was early in college that a friend of mine alerted me to the fact that the brothers Grimm repeatedly &lt;em&gt;sanitized&lt;/em&gt; the stories that they had originally collected in the field: &lt;a href=&#34;http://people.fas.harvard.edu/~tatar/Maria_Tatar/About_Me.html&#34;&gt;Maria Tatar&lt;/a&gt; had just published (this was 1987) her book &lt;a href=&#34;http://scholar.harvard.edu/tatar/publications/hard-facts-grimms-fairy-tales&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Hard Facts of the Grimms&amp;rsquo; Fairy Tales&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, and I was excited to buy a copy (which I still have today). (A &lt;a href=&#34;http://press.princeton.edu/titles/2575.html&#34;&gt;second edition&lt;/a&gt; came out in 2003, but I have not looked at it.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A couple of years ago, after accidentally discovering Maria Tatar&amp;rsquo;s 2002 &lt;a href=&#34;http://scholar.harvard.edu/tatar/publications/annotated-classic-fairy-tales&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Annotated Classic Fairy Tales&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; while browsing a library &amp;ldquo;new book&amp;rdquo; shelf, I also learned that she was blogging, so I started following &lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tatar/&#34;&gt;her blog, &amp;ldquo;Breezes from Wonderland&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. It was from this blog that I just learned now that &lt;a href=&#34;http://press.princeton.edu/titles/10300.html&#34;&gt;Jack Zipes&lt;/a&gt; has finally &lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tatar/2014/11/20/the-grimms-straight-up/&#34;&gt;translated the first edition of the Grimms&amp;rsquo; fairy tales into English&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://press.princeton.edu/images/k10300.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Jack Zipes&amp;#39; book&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I look forward to checking out Zipes&amp;rsquo; new translation. It&amp;rsquo;s been a decade since I last revisited the Grimms&amp;rsquo; fairy tales, and I still perversely love a dark story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What are your memories of fairy tales as a child? Have you ever read (or read about) the original unsanitized versions of well-known fairy tales? If you are a parent, do you tell your children fairy tales, thinking of them as harmless imaginative entertainment? Would you tell them unsanitized versions of the tales, as people used to do before modern Western sentimentalized views of what is appropriate for children? Or do you think it was wrong how parents used to terrify their children?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2014-12-23&#34;&gt;(Update of 2014-12-23)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.newstatesman.com/culture/2014/12/rowan-williams-why-we-need-fairy-tales-now-more-ever&#34;&gt;A beautiful essay on the importance of fairy tales&lt;/a&gt;, by &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rowan_Williams&#34;&gt;Rowan Williams&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Are you familiar with the Nutcracker story? Check out ETA Hoffmann&#39;s other creepy tales!</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/12/27/are-you-familiar-with-the-nutcracker-story-check-out-eta-hoffmanns-other-creepy-tales/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Dec 2013 19:15:36 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/12/27/are-you-familiar-with-the-nutcracker-story-check-out-eta-hoffmanns-other-creepy-tales/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s the season when many of us either watch for the first time a production of the ballet &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Nutcracker&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Nutcracker&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, or remember having seen it at some point, or remember some non-ballet production of the story (I personally still remember seeing some children&amp;rsquo;s adaptation of it when I was young).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But how many of you have actually read the original story by the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/German_Romanticism&#34;&gt;German Romantic&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/E._T._A._Hoffmann&#34;&gt;ETA Hoffmann&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Nutcracker_and_the_Mouse_King&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Nutcracker and the Mouse King&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.press.uchicago.edu/dms/ucp/books/jacket/0226/34/0226347893.jpeg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Tales of ETA Hoffmann&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;eta-hoffmann-a-forgotten-writer&#34;&gt;ETA Hoffmann, a forgotten writer?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was reminded of the creepy tales of Hoffmann when this &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.npr.org/2013/12/25/257139160/the-dark-roots-of-the-nutcracker-and-the-man-who-wrote-it&#34;&gt;article about him came my way&lt;/a&gt;. It suggested that people don&amp;rsquo;t know about him any more. I don&amp;rsquo;t know how true that is, but because he is one of my all-time favorite writers, I decided to do my part to help promote the work of this fascinating 19th century writer. He wrote not only amazing fiction, but also wrote on philosophy and music: in particular, as this article notes, he was one of the first critics who welcomed the strange figure of Ludwig van Beethoven when Beethoven came on the scene and freaked everyone out with his revolutionary new music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;first-encounter&#34;&gt;First encounter&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first time I heard of ETA Hoffmann was purely a result of hearing a musical excerpt from &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jacques_Offenbach&#34;&gt;Jacques Offenbach&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s opera, &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Tales_of_Hoffmann&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Les contes d&amp;rsquo;Hoffmann&amp;rdquo; (&amp;ldquo;The tales of Hoffmann&amp;rdquo;)&lt;/a&gt;. This was when I was in high school.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OK, I have never watched this opera or listened to it, except for the famous &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Belle_nuit,_%C3%B4_nuit_d%27amour&#34;&gt;Barcarolle&lt;/a&gt;. So basically, I only knew that there was someone whose name was Hoffmann and wrote some &amp;ldquo;tales&amp;rdquo; that were used in an opera. That was all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;second-encounter&#34;&gt;Second encounter&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My second encounter was when I was in college and learning to like the music of Mozart and Beethoven. I came across the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/10/rip-charles-rosen/&#34;&gt;book by the late Charles Rosen, &amp;ldquo;The Classical Style&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, and early on in the book, Rosen mentioned this music critic who so loved Mozart that he changed one of his names from &amp;ldquo;Friedrich&amp;rdquo; to &amp;ldquo;Amadeus&amp;rdquo; (hence our knowing him as ETA Hoffmann rather than ETF Hoffmann)! So that was intriguing. I looked at some of his writing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-fine-english-translation-of-selected-stories&#34;&gt;A fine English translation of selected stories&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I immersed myself more in the music of the era, I grew increasingly interested in the philosophy developing that would later be called &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/German_Romanticism&#34;&gt;German Romanticism&lt;/a&gt;. I began reading Fichte, Schlegel, Jean Paul, Kleist, Hölderlin, Jean Paul, Hegel, Goethe, and other figures of the period. I even took a course in German. And of course I ran into ETA Hoffmann again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I bought &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.press.uchicago.edu/ucp/books/book/chicago/T/bo3627741.html&#34;&gt;this really good English translation of selected stories of his&lt;/a&gt; and was not disappointed.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.press.uchicago.edu/dms/ucp/books/jacket/0226/34/0226347893.jpeg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Tales of ETA Hoffmann&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I looked online and there are more recent English translations since my college days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The stories are really surreal, raising many questions about humanity and reality. And yes, they are pretty disturbing too: I will confess to having had nightmares based on the stories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;ve read Edgar Allan Poe, think of Hoffmann the fiction writer as a much, much superior German analogue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-golden-pot&#34;&gt;The Golden Pot&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you read only one story by Hoffmann, I suppose it would have to be &amp;ldquo;The Golden Pot&amp;rdquo;. It&amp;rsquo;s long and vivid, although in the end I could not really make coherent sense of it. It&amp;rsquo;s a weird fantasy and has a lot of funny elements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s an &lt;a href=&#34;http://gutenberg.net.au/ebooks06/0605801h.html&#34;&gt;English translation online&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-sandman&#34;&gt;The Sandman&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story that really got under my skin, however, was &amp;ldquo;The Sandman&amp;rdquo;. Very dark.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s an &lt;a href=&#34;http://germanstories.vcu.edu/hoffmann/sand_e.html&#34;&gt;English translation online&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was interesting to be reminded of the stories of ETA Hoffmann at this time of year. Check some out if you haven&amp;rsquo;t read any before. I have to confess they&amp;rsquo;re not for everyone, and at this point in my life I am less interested in (and more wary of) this kind of Romantic literature, because I consider it &amp;ldquo;unhealthy&amp;rdquo;, frankly, along with other aspects of German Romanticism in general, but I can&amp;rsquo;t deny the guy was a genius.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;questions-for-you&#34;&gt;Questions for you&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;ve read some of Hoffmann&amp;rsquo;s stories before, which ones are your favorites? Why? Do you think they&amp;rsquo;re still as interesting now as when coming out from a mindset of the beginnings of Romanticism in the 19th century, or do they feel dated to you?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>