<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Ballroom Dance on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/ballroom-dance/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Ballroom Dance on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/ballroom-dance/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>On re-experiencing VHS tapes again</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/16/on-re-experiencing-vhs-tapes-again/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Nov 2014 21:27:49 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/16/on-re-experiencing-vhs-tapes-again/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I stopped serious study of ballroom dance sometime around 2003, over ten years ago, because I was discouraged by not finding a maximally compatible dance partner. I ended up closing the chapter of my life that started in 2000 when ballroom dance consumed almost all of my time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently I brought up several boxes of ballroom dance instruction videos from those days, with the idea that even though I&amp;rsquo;m not longer doing ballroom dancing with anyone any more (Abby is not very interested in ballroom dance), I might find it enjoyable to continue developing my dance skills and use the videos as part of exercise also. Almost all of these videos are VHS tapes. I have almost no dance videos on DVD, as I was very late in acquiring a DVD player: actually, one day, my mother bought me a DVD player because she was tired of visiting me and having no way to watching any DVDs she brought!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had mixed emotions and memories as I started going through these videos again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-was-i-late-to-cds-and-dvds&#34;&gt;Why was I late to CDs and DVDs?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier in life, I was very late in getting a CD player also; I bought only &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/09/12/rip-ray-dolby-yes/&#34;&gt;cassette tapes&lt;/a&gt; and LPs until late in college, around 1990, when I finally buckled to pressure and bought a CD player. I am generally not an early adopter of technology. I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/22/paradox-i-will-observe-the-national-day-of-unplugging-but-just-bought-my-first-smartphone-this-week/&#34;&gt;bought my first smartphone in 2012&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why the resistance to technology? Partly it&amp;rsquo;s just a matter of cost. But more fundamentally, I worried about the long-term durability of digital media. It turns out that I shouldn&amp;rsquo;t have worried quite so much, because backing up has turned out to be quite feasible and inexpensive. But in the early days of CDs and DVDs, I was not going to be ripping them and storing them on super-expensive hard drives, so my worry was about the physical media of CDs and DVDs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;was-i-was-right-about-the-disadvantages-of-digital-media&#34;&gt;Was I was right about the disadvantages of digital media?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that I was partially right. Some of my old CDs and DVDs did become unplayable after a decade or two, but very few.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bigger problem is that Abby and I sometimes check out DVDs from the public library and find that they have enough scratches that when watching a film we often miss entire minutes and scenes because of damaged playback! This has happened so many times that I question the value of ever checking out a DVD from the library again that looks even a little scratched. What a waste!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The advantage of analog media such as LPs and cassette tapes and VHS tapes is that in some ways they are more fault tolerant. I remember the old days of splicing tape, for example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But actually, analog media get corrupted easily enough by magnetism, mold, etc. I do have tapes that are unplayable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The killer feature of digital media was always indexing and random access. It&amp;rsquo;s a real hassle not being able to skip from one dance lesson to the next, or get a table of contents, in these dance videos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s far less efficient using VHS videos for instruction than indexed digital media. That said, I see why people stream video these days rather than buy or borrow DVDs; physical digital media are fragile. But what would libraries do if they stopped acquiring and serving CDs and DVDs?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Watching &#34;Hable con ella&#34; (&#34;Talk to her&#34;) (2002): thoughts on art, crime, and ethics</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/12/26/hable-con-ella-talk-to-her-thoughts-on-art/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Dec 2013 10:38:33 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/12/26/hable-con-ella-talk-to-her-thoughts-on-art/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/4/43/Talk_to_Her_English_movie_poster_fairuse.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Talk to her&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;After a decade of putting it off, I finally watched &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pedro_Almod%C3%B3var&#34;&gt;Pedro Almodóvar&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s 2002 film, &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Talk_to_Her&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Hable con ella&amp;rdquo; (&amp;ldquo;Talk to her&amp;rdquo;)&lt;/a&gt;. I was actually on the verge of going to a local movie theater to watch it a decade ago when circumstances in my life changed and I put it on hold. But Abby and I just watched it together, partially because Almodóvar has been on my mind since &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/12/19/appreciating-the-unique-singer-la-lupe/&#34;&gt;I re-listened to some music sung by La Lupe a couple of days ago&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out to be a fantastic film, totally gripping and moving, no slow or pointless moments, really tight. One of my favorite films of all time, surely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was also disturbing on many levels, as great art often is. Abby and I had some conversations about some of the issues, but there was even more still on my mind, so I decided to share them here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: there are some serious &lt;strong&gt;spoilers&lt;/strong&gt; in this post, so if you haven&amp;rsquo;t watched the film yet, please stop reading now and &lt;em&gt;go watch it&lt;/em&gt; first. In any case, I am skipping important plot elements in order to focus on particular themes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-rape&#34;&gt;The rape&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s cut to the chase. In this film, a really weird guy, Benigno, who is depicted as unhealthily obsessed with a young woman ends up being one of her primary caretakers (he is a nurse) in the hospital when she slips into a coma after an accident. When we encounter him in the story, he&amp;rsquo;s already been taking care of her for four years. We see him bathing her and massaging her in a way that might be considered loving and caring, but also creepy and too intimate, especially given how he had secretly stalked her before the whole accident. Everyone thinks he&amp;rsquo;s gay (he lied to fool her father), so nobody seems to seriously question his care of her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the story, we are led to believe (it was not depicted) that during the course of the story, he raped her and got her pregnant. Miraculously, at some point after her pregnancy was discovered, she woke from her four-year coma, but the child was stillborn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;my-reaction&#34;&gt;My reaction&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can go online and see a lot of reactions to this rape, say, the IMDB forums. Some disbelieve, some try to justify her awakening as making up for his crime, others say they refuse to watch the film because they heard what the story is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Myself, I disbelieved at first, despite the very clear signal straight from the film director himself. I thought, maybe it was the other main character, or the other man besides him. I thought this even though I knew it could not be. I found it &lt;em&gt;very interesting&lt;/em&gt; that despite the obvious (except that I didn&amp;rsquo;t see it happen), I &lt;em&gt;did not want to believe&lt;/em&gt; that his man, even though he was clearly weird and inappropriately obsessed with the comatose woman, did this. I examined myself and asked why I did not want to believe. One reason was that other being all weird, he came across as being very gentle and caring, both towards her (taking care of her inert body) and to the other main character Marco, who became a close friend of his. For all we knew, he was still a virgin. And she hadn&amp;rsquo;t gotten pregnant after four years of his care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, my &amp;ldquo;reasoning&amp;rdquo; was completely ridiculous. How did I know that he wasn&amp;rsquo;t molesting her for four years, and just being careful about it, and only accidentally slipping up one night after watching that silent film he talked to her about?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I was very uncomfortable that aspects of his personality and behavior that made me feel sympathetic to him &lt;em&gt;in general&lt;/em&gt; led me to doubt that he was capable of something horrible. This brought up memories of being confused and cynical in the light of revelations in recent years that some people&amp;rsquo;s heroes were in fact very flawed: for example, the big Penn State scandal involving &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jerry_Sandusky&#34;&gt;Jerry Sandusky&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joe_Paterno&#34;&gt;Joe Paterno&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s apparent role in concealing Sandusky&amp;rsquo;s repeated sexual abuse of young boys. Or &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lance_Armstrong&#34;&gt;Lance Armstrong&lt;/a&gt; finally confessing to being a drug doper in sport. Or the history of sexual abuse by priests and other leaders in many religious institutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that I was detached from all those cases, not having any emotional involvement with the &amp;ldquo;heroes&amp;rdquo; in question, so it was easy for me to scoff at those who went out of their way to demonize the victims and proclaim their heroes innocent. So I was pretty disturbed that just through skillful storytelling, the film director here was able, for a split second, to cause me to doubt the obvious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;bullfighting-and-respect-for-different-cultures&#34;&gt;Bullfighting and respect for different cultures&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another thing that disturbed me was the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bullfighting&#34;&gt;bullfighting&lt;/a&gt;. I am hardly a member of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.peta.org/issues/animals-in-entertainment/animals-used-entertainment-factsheets/bullfighting-tradition-tragedy/&#34;&gt;PETA&lt;/a&gt;, but I find bullfighting frightening and perverse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, I am slightly ambivalent about this attitude. But only slightly. OK, it&amp;rsquo;s an important cultural institution in Spain, and I am definitely not one to lightly dismiss long-standing traditions that clearly have served a purpose of some kind over centuries, even millennia. But I&amp;rsquo;m not a relativist who thinks everything&amp;rsquo;s OK somewhere. For example, there are long traditions of human slavery that &amp;ldquo;we&amp;rdquo; (in, say, the US where I live and grew up) consider &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; to be OK, and &amp;ldquo;we&amp;rdquo; believe that women should have the right to vote, that &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Female_genital_mutilation&#34;&gt;female genital mutilation&lt;/a&gt; is unacceptable, that the ancient Chinese &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Foot_binding&#34;&gt;foot binding&lt;/a&gt; of women was an atrocity, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You could argue that it&amp;rsquo;s just sheer cultural conditioning that I happen to believe in what &amp;ldquo;we&amp;rdquo; believe, but nevertheless, I feel justified in my judgment and can&amp;rsquo;t apologize for it. So if you&amp;rsquo;re reading this and you&amp;rsquo;re Spanish and offended, I don&amp;rsquo;t know how to sugarcoat it, but bullfighting freaks me out. The best I can say is, there are probably things I believe in or do that you find disgusting also.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;cognitive-dissonance-and-hypocrisy&#34;&gt;Cognitive dissonance and hypocrisy?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The weird thing is, even as I felt disgust at seeing all the blood during the bullfighting scenes in the film, I felt unease at my participating in a very sanitized version of the whole thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m talking about the ballroom dance &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pasodoble&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;paso doble&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, which is a kind of weird, transformed re-enactment of a bullfight theme. I have never actually danced paso doble in competition, but have practiced basic steps and movements, and have &lt;em&gt;fantasized&lt;/em&gt; about being some kind of macho bullfighter. See, in most of the standard ballroom dances, the focus of display and movement is almost entirely on the follower, the woman. In &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; the paso doble, the man is really the focus, being the bullfighter. (The follower is, bizarrely, his cape: the bull is invisible and only implied.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still periodically do a paso doble &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/13/video-review-dancing-with-the-stars-cardio-dance-2006/&#34;&gt;dance workout&lt;/a&gt;. When I do this dance workout, you can bet I&amp;rsquo;m not thinking about bloody bulls or the possibility of being gored to death. Somehow the whole thing has been sanitized. I feel slightly weird about this &amp;ldquo;Anglo&amp;rdquo; appropriation of a cultural tradition. I would say I feel slightly weird about the other sanitized and standardized Latin ballroom dances too (rumba, cha cha, samba) that have &amp;ldquo;authentic&amp;rdquo; roots from, for example, Cuba and Brazil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I feel only &amp;ldquo;slightly&amp;rdquo; weird, because cultural borrowing and appropriation is something that has always happened. I don&amp;rsquo;t think we can or ought to stop it, any more than I can go around sniffing that a lot of &amp;ldquo;Chinese food&amp;rdquo; in American restaurants is not much like what I know to be more &amp;ldquo;authentic&amp;rdquo;. The best I can do is &lt;em&gt;know the difference&lt;/em&gt;, rather than reject evolution or borrowing of traditions. So, for example, I have watched videos of Cuban salsa, which differs from urban North American studio or club salsa. I did study &amp;ldquo;Argentine tango&amp;rdquo; after engaging in the heavily stylized and very different ballroom tango. I think these can all reasonably coexist, as long as one knows what each is and not pretend something is what it is not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;gender-roles&#34;&gt;Gender roles&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then somehow everything brought me to the issue of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gender_role&#34;&gt;gender roles&lt;/a&gt;. In the film, the bullfighter main character is a woman, Lydia. Unusual. That led me to think about other weird issues I have dealt with concerning ballroom dancing, and couple dancing in general where there is a clear separation between leader and follower. Are these dances a weird kind of anachronism? I have definitely met women who rejected or were openly uneasy about taking part in this kind of dancing, but obviously, as Abby and I have gone out dancing, we know of plenty of women who are OK with it. In fact, we often see women dancing the leader role, and admittedly less often, men dancing the follower role. I tend to think there&amp;rsquo;s not really a problem with this kind of dancing, given that people really can and do switch roles these days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;do-the-ends-justify-the-means&#34;&gt;Do the ends justify the means?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some final thoughts: what happens when we accept that something is disturbing? Especially when we rationalize away our discomfort?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, why did Almodóvar tell a story about a rapist who some would like to say possibly &amp;ldquo;helped&amp;rdquo; a comatose woman awake? What if that were true? Does it make his crime any less bad? And what about intent? Does intent matter in an action? Fodder for your philosophy classes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And what about the film itself? What is the response to those who refuse to watch this film because of a rape? Has Almodóvar committed a crime by making the character a sympathetic, tragic one? Or is this &amp;ldquo;only&amp;rdquo; art? Or is it because it is high art that it is justified?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that reminds me of the controversy over &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roman_Polanski&#34;&gt;Roman Polanski&lt;/a&gt;, many of whose beautiful, profound films I have enjoyed through my life? He fled the US in 1977 after statutory rape of a 13-year-old girl. In 2009 there was controversy after the US tried to extradite him, and a lot of film fans apparently came to his defense. Were they making the mistake of making an allowance for a great film maker that they would not have made for some random guy? Is my continuing to watch his films a crime? Should I be boycotting his films?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of questions, and I think no easy answers. Of course, our actions reveal our implicit answers. What we say does not matter. What we do does.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-science-added-2014-01-05&#34;&gt;The science (added 2014-01-05)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing I forgot to discuss was the matter of whether people in vegetative states are actually aware of what is going on around them. Assuming they have some awareness, that makes a lot of what happened in the film kind of creepy (but also, what happens in real life in hospitals).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a recent post about &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.spring.org.uk/2014/01/patients-in-vegetative-state-can-respond-emotionally-to-loved-ones.php&#34;&gt;emotional awareness in patients in a vegetative state&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2014-04-27&#34;&gt;(Update of 2014-04-27)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A great article on &lt;a href=&#34;http://mosaicscience.com/story/mind-readers&#34;&gt;vegetative states&lt;/a&gt; just came my way, reminding me of the discomfort I felt when watching this film.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, a great film is one that somehow makes me think about life and humanity in the broadest possible ways, even though I didn&amp;rsquo;t really want to. I guess Pedro Almodóvar struck a home run with this film.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not the kind of film I want to watch every night, because then I end up spending hours thinking about stuff. But there it is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Do you find this kind of film too disturbing to watch or to think about? Are you concerned by inaccurate scientific portrayals in film? Are you concerned about films that make you sympathetic toward someone who is not only disturbed but also a criminal?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>First rehearsal for my first ukulele gig: dealing with anxiety</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/09/26/first-rehearsal-for-my-first-ukulele-gig/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Sep 2013 23:09:23 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/09/26/first-rehearsal-for-my-first-ukulele-gig/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s now officially &lt;em&gt;two months&lt;/em&gt; since &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/08/23/another-unexpected-life-change-one-month-of-learning-to-play-ukulele/&#34;&gt;I started learning to play ukulele&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s hard to believe, but two months ago, I was still struggling to play three chords: I could play C, of course, but had trouble with G7, and had even worse trouble with F: I had no finger strength or dexterity and could not arch my fingers and everything was a painful buzz, and I could spend only five minutes a day practicing because of the pain on my uncalloused fingers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And after just over a month of playing, and joining the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/Steel-City-Ukuleles/&#34;&gt;Steel City Ukuleles&lt;/a&gt;, I had volunteered to &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/09/04/my-second-meeting-of-the-steel-city-ukuleles/&#34;&gt;perform in a gig for Ecofest in Regent Square&lt;/a&gt;, as a way to force myself to maintain momentum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this week, just in time, I got my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/09/23/finally-got-a-nice-new-ukulele-mainland-classic-mahogany-concert/&#34;&gt;brand new concert-sized ukulele&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/ecofest-2013-rehearsal-1.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;First Ecofest rehearsal&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The gig is in just over a week. I attended my first rehearsal with extreme anxiety. I was even thinking about bailing out instead of attending. Here&amp;rsquo;s why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;new-music-for-me&#34;&gt;New music for me&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/steel-city-ukuleles-bound-thing-1.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/steel-city-ukuleles-bound-thing-2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I went into rehearsal with basically &lt;em&gt;none&lt;/em&gt; of the songs we were going to perform. So it was basically a sight reading and singing session for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One reason is that I was waiting to get the official bound compilation of performance songs that we were to receive at the first rehearsal, which we did. I had not requested to get one ahead of time, because I was too busy all week anyway to make good use of it if I had possessed it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, it turns out that many of these songs are already familiar and played by most of the other members of the performance group; they are part of the general repertoire, for previous years&amp;rsquo; Ecofests as well as for other gigs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;new-performance-group-for-me&#34;&gt;New performance group for me&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that breaking into a performance group for the first time always involves an initial learning curve because there are those who already know everything inside and out. I still have very vivid memories of other times in my life when I have entered a performance group and felt lost for a while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was briefly in marching band, during the 9th grade in high school. As a new freshman, I was unfamiliar with the repertoire, the choreography, etc. It was a tricky experience for all us freshmen, of course, amidst the 10th, 11th, and 12th graders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, over a decade ago, for a couple of years I was a member of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://cmubdc.org/&#34;&gt;Carnegie Mellon University ballroom dance club&lt;/a&gt;, and I was on both the competition team as well as the formation team. I&amp;rsquo;d made ballroom dancing the main focus of my life, throwing myself into lessons and competition and being in performances with the formation team while still a beginner. I improved my dancing significantly and quickly as a result of jumping in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And more recently, I have been performing in a small &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/09/playing-music-on-recorders-at-a-phipps-conservatory-candlelight-evening/&#34;&gt;recorder quartet/quintet at winter holiday time&lt;/a&gt;. Practicing so that I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t totally flub everything always took a huge amount of work for me, but the side effect was that I really improved my recorder playing and musicianship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I know firsthand the benefits of just jumping in and being around very experienced team members who are inspirational to emulate and learn from, and to exert some healthy pressure on myself not to let the team down!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;listening-watching&#34;&gt;Listening, watching&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of what I did during rehearsal was listening and watching, while doing what I could to keep up and go and make dozens of mistakes everywhere. (It&amp;rsquo;s particularly important to boldly make those mistakes and write down what to work on for homework.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was no way I was going to be able to play everything at first sight. In fact, that&amp;rsquo;s not even the right way to think about the situation. This isn&amp;rsquo;t classical music where you really do &amp;ldquo;sight read&amp;rdquo;. This is music where almost everything is transmitted &lt;em&gt;by ear&lt;/em&gt;. Not knowing the melodies, and not having an actual score, I have to listen and figure out where the melodic lines roughly are, and where the chord changes are. I have to learn what the prevailing strum rhythms and breaks and mood the group has largely decided on. The goal is to learn how to blend in and contribute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t do much extended &lt;em&gt;singing&lt;/em&gt; during this rehearsal. But we have two more rehearsals after this one, so it was not necessary to get everything down right away. I would, of course, be doing my own homework, looking up YouTube videos, in between official rehearsals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For consistency, I found it very useful to focus my listening on one person at a time to emulate. Usually that person was Sunny, because she is leading us. Sometimes that was Adam, because I was sitting near him and because as a strong male voice, I could follow him especially in songs where we had male and female voices split.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fact that there were over a dozen of us in the group for this gig was very helpful to me, because it meant that there was much less pressure on me to get everything right. I don&amp;rsquo;t always have to sing, or sing everything. I don&amp;rsquo;t always have to play the tricky chord progressions that I&amp;rsquo;m not ready yet to get right. I can leave stuff out judiciously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;half-the-songs&#34;&gt;Half the songs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In two hours, we covered half the songs we planned to play at Ecofest. I felt there was still a huge amount of work for me to do in order to really contribute to the group, but no longer felt helpless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-cost-of-excellence&#34;&gt;The cost of excellence&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still think it&amp;rsquo;s a little crazy that I jumped into committing to performing when still a beginner at ukulele, but in the past couple of years, I have learned that shorter, tighter learning and creating cycles considerably speed up the improvement process, provided that one actually puts in the hard work on a daily basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s been a huge cost, unfortunately. I have let some things slide while focusing on ukulele in the past two months. For example, I have been playing chess very poorly. Last week, I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/09/26/the-chess-improver-the-psychology-of-not-winning-the-won-game/&#34;&gt;drew a game that I should have won&lt;/a&gt;. And just two days ago, disaster struck: in my fatigue, I lost a game I should have won. If I had known I was going to have ukulele take over my life outside of work, I would have chosen &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; to play in the current chess tournament.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now as in the past couple of years, I have chosen to sacrifice my chess performance when other things come up. This is why I rarely play chess tournaments any more: I hate playing worse than I am actually capable of playing. As I mentioned two weeks ago, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/09/15/saying-no-on-not-playing-in-the-pittsburgh-chess-league-this-season-for-the-cmu-tartans/&#34;&gt;I had anticipated becoming busy in November&lt;/a&gt;, but I had not anticipated being so busy now already, in September!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sunny led a great rehearsal for our Ecofest gig coming up. I really like some of these songs we&amp;rsquo;re working on, and left feeling that after more work, we can sound really good and have a lot of fun at the gig!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>RIP, Eydie Gormé</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/08/10/rip-eydie/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Aug 2013 23:08:41 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/08/10/rip-eydie/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I learned that American singer &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eydie_Gorm%C3%A9&#34;&gt;Eydie Gormé&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.npr.org/blogs/thetwo-way/2013/08/10/210927460/reports-singer-eydie-gorme-dies-at-84&#34;&gt;just died&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I actually knew very little about her until reading about her death.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But she made a huge difference in my life!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/c/ca/Eydie_Gorme.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Eydie Gormé&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;eydie-gormé-and-los-panchos&#34;&gt;Eydie Gormé and Los Panchos&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know of her only through her famous recordings from the 1960s of Latin music with &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Los_Panchos&#34;&gt;Los Panchos&lt;/a&gt;. They recorded a number of classic &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/bolero/&#34;&gt;boleros&lt;/a&gt; that constantly kept me company when I was doing &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/ballroom-dance/&#34;&gt;ballroom dance&lt;/a&gt; over a decade ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In particular, I really enjoyed their performance of &amp;ldquo;Sabor a mî&amp;rdquo;, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/11/17/a-childhood-dream-come-true-i-am-now-finally-singing-for-real/&#34;&gt;my favorite bolero of all time&lt;/a&gt;, both to listen to and to dance to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/0Uz6ZDJjXvE&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was interesting for me to learn, just now, that her parents were Sephardic Jews, her father from Sicily and her mother from Turkey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;should-i-thank-people-before-they-die&#34;&gt;Should I thank people before they die?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is always strange to me when people die and I realize I barely knew anything about them, but feel deep gratitude for how they&amp;rsquo;ve so much enhanced my life. This was the case with Eydie Gormé.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve never been into &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fandom&#34;&gt;fandom&lt;/a&gt;, but lately I&amp;rsquo;ve been wondering, in an era when it actually is much easier to contact &amp;ldquo;celebrities&amp;rdquo;, whether sending a simple one-shot note to someone expressing gratitude, well before death, might be appropriate. Especially in the case of people who are actually not major celebrities (either because their prime time has passed or because their contribution is in a narrow niche). &lt;strong&gt;What do you think?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The paradox of practice: it&#39;s harder to go slow than go fast</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/08/02/the-paradox-of-practice-its-harder-to-go-slow-than-go-fast/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Aug 2012 23:09:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/08/02/the-paradox-of-practice-its-harder-to-go-slow-than-go-fast/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently, by coincidence, I&amp;rsquo;ve seen a lot of articles about the benefits of &lt;em&gt;slow&lt;/em&gt; practice of a skill, whether in music or martial arts. Some good links that really apply to all physical skills:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bulletproofmusician.com/is-slow-practice-really-necessary/&#34;&gt;Is slow practice really necessary?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://musiciansway.com/blog/2011/02/a-different-kind-of-slow-practice/&#34;&gt;A different kind of slow practice&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://billplakemusic.org/2012/07/18/keep-this-aim-in-mind-when-practicing-slowly/&#34;&gt;Keep this aim in mind when practicing slowly&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://themartialartscoach.com/train-slow-to-learn-fast&#34;&gt;Train slow to learn fast&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We live in an era of &lt;em&gt;speed&lt;/em&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s gotten to the point that there have arisen some movements against speed, for &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Slow_Movement&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;slow&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a confession to make: it&amp;rsquo;s really hard for me to practice music slowly. I myself am guilty of often practicing music too quickly, not making the most of my practice. For a while, when I was starting to play music again after an absence of three decades, I was pushing myself with a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/29/a-musicians-best-friend/&#34;&gt;metronome&lt;/a&gt;. That was useful for a while, but eventually I realized I had to slow down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am now actually trying to apply the advice in the articles mentioned and &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; slow down in music. Because I know in my heart that slowing down works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I think about it, I have successfully used slow practice in many fields in the past, from ballroom dance to running to chess. I&amp;rsquo;d like to give examples of what slow practice actually means in each of these and how I attribute my success to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;ballroom-dance&#34;&gt;Ballroom dance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was learning &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/ballroom-dance/&#34;&gt;ballroom dance&lt;/a&gt; over a decade ago, I started out as a very uncoordinated, clumsy, confused beginner in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://cmubdc.org/&#34;&gt;Carnegie Mellon University Ballroom Dance Club&lt;/a&gt;. I was &lt;em&gt;very lucky&lt;/em&gt; that I stumbled around only about a month before I started getting quality professional instruction in a small group setting (a benefit of the club) supplementing the large group classes (which I had found barely helpful, frankly).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;rumba-to-cha-cha&#34;&gt;Rumba to cha cha&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will never forget the Latin (International style) dance technique lessons of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.artandstyledancestudio.com/&#34;&gt;Rozana Sweeney&lt;/a&gt;. She basically treated us as she would little kids intending to become professional ballroom dancers. Unlike in the group classes at CMU, where we were just shown steps and patterns and told to go do them, we were shown a very limited repertoire of movements that were broken down to atomic components (so much as that is possible for a continuous art form) and practiced &lt;em&gt;very slowly&lt;/em&gt;. We were not allowed to move on until we had at least some rudimentary &amp;ldquo;mastery&amp;rdquo; of the &amp;ldquo;basics&amp;rdquo;. I&amp;rsquo;d never had any dance experience before, so it was quite eye-opening how effective this stern approach to instruction was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We started off practicing the International rumba basics. We were taught about straight legs, bent legs, foot turnout, hip rotation, contrary motion of body and arms, etc. We went through the movements so slowly (to beats or music much slower than the actual standardized-tempo dance music) that many of us lost balance and tripped over ourselves. &lt;em&gt;It is harder to move slow than fast.&lt;/em&gt; Balance is important. If you go fast, you cheat because you can move without full balance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eventually we moved on to cha cha, which is a rather faster dance, but similar to a sped-up rumba with a very fast extra three &amp;ldquo;cha cha cha&amp;rdquo; steps. I couldn&amp;rsquo;t help noticing how my cha cha &amp;ldquo;magically&amp;rdquo; improved, &lt;em&gt;without ever practicing cha cha&lt;/em&gt;, just from practicing rumba so much. The reason was clear: making the slow precise is the key to making the fast precise. If the slow is not efficient and exact, then going fast will only result in a magnification of inefficiency and sloppiness. I believe nobody can dance a good cha cha who can&amp;rsquo;t also dance a good rumba. That&amp;rsquo;s just how it works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;slow-waltz-and-foxtrot-to-quickstep-and-viennese-waltz&#34;&gt;Slow waltz and foxtrot to quickstep and Viennese waltz&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Focusing on the slow was also true of our International standard dance instruction, which came from some other instructors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We started off with slow waltz and foxtrot, working on the technique in slow motion, before dancing the fast quickstep and Viennese waltz. The fast dances are quite strenuous (as a runner, I compare dancing them with a partner to be as tiring as running) and things fall apart if you haven&amp;rsquo;t figured out how to move efficiently and together slowly first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;results&#34;&gt;Results&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I improved very quickly in ballroom dance once I started having the serious technique lessons and worked on basic movements by myself outside of class, repeatedly. I still feel I had a lot of potential improvement still in me, because of the foundational slow practice, at the time &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/10/flute-loving-it-again/&#34;&gt;when I quit competitive ballroom dancing&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;running&#34;&gt;Running&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I started &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/running/&#34;&gt;running&lt;/a&gt;, I was 29 years old and had been sedentary all my life. I didn&amp;rsquo;t know what I was doing when I first started running. I would just go out and run hard, get out of breath very quickly, stop, and go on. I got sore this way, and also did not actually improve my speed much during my first sloppy year of running. I only got &lt;em&gt;much faster&lt;/em&gt; when I learned the science of how to run &lt;em&gt;slowly&lt;/em&gt;. I got much faster than friends I was running with who were still running the unsystematic way, at a faster training pace than me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is possible to run too slowly for benefit. But the trick is to run slowly enough in order to be relaxed, observe one&amp;rsquo;s form, correct it, and put in the time to slowly build up endurance. Running too fast only led me to go for a shorter period of time, execute with poor form, and get injured.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not actually easy to run slowly, properly. It is trivial to run slowly sloppily. Many people you see on the roads or in the parks who are &amp;ldquo;jogging&amp;rdquo; are going slowly and sloppily. Stomping loudly into the ground, head tilted back, slow long strides: that&amp;rsquo;s not a good way to run slowly. If you want to run slowly, the right way to do it is to adopt a good upright, balanced posture, be aware of landing under the hip, using the glutes and not the knees, and most important, making sure the cadence is &lt;em&gt;not too slow&lt;/em&gt;. In other words, slow doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean everything is slow; it means slowing down some variables but maintaining structural and dynamic integrity of the whole. Taking a super long stride slowly violates the physics of how to move.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Needless to say, for optimal training one must also run fast. Again, here the principle of adjusting variables applies, however. Running very fast for a long time is not the most effective way to train. The most effective way to train is known to be &lt;em&gt;interval training&lt;/em&gt;, in which you run fast but for a short period of time, then rest, then continue. In a sense, here the &amp;ldquo;slow&amp;rdquo; variable is distance covered while not resting. In slow running, the &amp;ldquo;slow&amp;rdquo; variable is the speed, not the distance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;results-1&#34;&gt;Results&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a couple of years, upon finding good running technique books and Web sites, and applying them, I went from nothing to winning age-group medals and trophies in local races in Pittsburgh (admittedly not so competitive in my age group). I am a believer in the importance of having learned to run sufficiently slowly when the training situation calls for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;chess&#34;&gt;Chess&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/chess/&#34;&gt;chess&lt;/a&gt; players, myself included, enjoying playing &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fast_chess&#34;&gt;fast chess&lt;/a&gt;. Five-minute games are exciting and fun because you can play so many of them in a given time and there is little time to think. But we all know that playing too much blitz chess can harm one&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;serious&amp;rdquo; slow chess games, games in which you may get two hours of time on your clock rather than five minutes. The problem, of course, is that getting used to making moves without thinking much does not train you to know how to think more deeply when you have much more time to use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Learning to play chess slowly is a challenge. I was never very good at playing slowly as a child, because I was impatient, and did not have a chess teacher to discipline me. When I returned to playing serious tournament chess, twenty years after not playing a single game, I suffered tremendously, because I had no idea how to make use of time during slow games. But with practice, analyzing games at home slowly in order to simulate the process, I learned how to look more deeply in the tree of possible game continuations. I would give myself three minutes, say, to do an analysis, and then computer-check it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I noticed that getting better at playing slowly actually helped me get better at playing quickly too (to some extent). There is a statistical correlation, indeed, between the regular strength of a chess player (as measured by an official rating) and his or her speed strength (as measured by an official speed rating). This should not be surprising: in distance running, there is a correlation between speed at running a mile and speed at running a marathon. The mile and marathon are very different distances, but a certain kind of fundamental efficiency is involved in both.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;results-2&#34;&gt;Results&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just over a year after I started playing chess again, initially poorly, my practice in playing slow chess at Tuesday night &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburghcc.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Chess Club&lt;/a&gt; tournaments (at two hours per game for each player) in combination with some (but not too much) casual fast chess at the club resulted in my surprising excellence at &amp;ldquo;slow fast&amp;rdquo; chess: I won the &lt;a href=&#34;http://pscfchess.org/results/06040808.htm&#34;&gt;2006 Pennsylvania State Game/29 Championship&lt;/a&gt; with a perfect score, and also won the &lt;a href=&#34;http://pscfchess.org/results/06101414.htm&#34;&gt;2006 Pennsylvania State Action Chess Championship&lt;/a&gt; with a perfect score (at time controls of 29 minutes per game and 30 minutes per game, respectively). Doing well at two-hour games made me even better at 29-minute games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slow practice works. It has worked for me in different fields. I want to make it work for music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slow practice requires much discipline, patience, and metacognitive awareness It is easy to take shortcuts unless one has bootstrapped a skill enough in order to be able to know oneself and to recognize one&amp;rsquo;s weaknesses and deliberately work on correcting them. Wonderful Web sites and books and videos on technique do exist that can help these days, even without a personal instructor.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Flute: loving it again, remembering why I dance, and how I met my wife!</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/03/10/flute-loving-it-again/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Mar 2012 21:28:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/03/10/flute-loving-it-again/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, after four days of &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/07/flute-taking-a-break-while-clarifying-my-goals&#34;&gt;not even touching my (modern) flute&lt;/a&gt; and having spent the time having fun with my Baroque flute instead, I felt the urge to return to the modern flute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still have not regained the inclination to continue working on the orchestra music I still have to improve a lot on in the coming week, but I rediscovered the joy of simply playing my instrument.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;sound-intonation&#34;&gt;Sound, intonation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The perpetual challenges of getting clean sounds and accurate pitches on the Baroque flute in the past four days have given me an increased appreciation for the modern flute. I picked it up and spent time just trying to make beautiful sounds. Freed from the stress of orchestra practice, I felt much more relaxed on the instrument than I have for a while now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To my surprise (but not really), I have improved considerably on the flute after not playing it for four days. I really needed a break, a consolidation of lessons learned. My production of tones is much improved, and high notes are squeaking less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;music-for-dance&#34;&gt;Music for dance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing I&amp;rsquo;ve truly come to realize is that I particularly enjoy playing rhythmic music suitable for dancing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, every time I attend a dance, and there is live music, I experience a strange internal conflict: I do like to dance, but sometimes, I&amp;rsquo;d rather be on the other side of the dance floor, being the musical performer! The &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; time I&amp;rsquo;ve been on the other side has been at last year&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburghcontra.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Contras and Squares&lt;/a&gt; Holiday Ball.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most recent instance of my wishing I could sometimes stop dancing and just join the musicians has been at the local &lt;a href=&#34;http://coalcountry.org/frenchdance.html&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh French dance workshop and social&lt;/a&gt;, where we&amp;rsquo;ve had live piano, fiddle, and of course, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~gdyke/&#34;&gt;Gregory&lt;/a&gt; on his Irish flute. I wonder whether at some point I might be qualified to play for the event, using either my modern flute or Baroque flute. (By the way, it was held again today, but unfortunately, Abby and I chose not to go because we had too many things to do this weekend.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;remembering-dancing&#34;&gt;Remembering dancing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday I spent time playing along to a score/CD set I&amp;rsquo;ve mentioned before, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/World-Music-Cuba-Flute-play-along/dp/3702465804&#34;&gt;World Music Cuba&lt;/a&gt;. While playing the bolero, cha cha, and mambo pieces in particular, I felt I was returning &amp;ldquo;home&amp;rdquo; in many ways. This was among the first music I heard and saw people dancing to when I was curious and visited the &lt;a href=&#34;http://cmubdc.org/&#34;&gt;CMU Ballroom Dance Club&lt;/a&gt; in 2000, and fell in love with, and learned to dance to. I also played along to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Play-along-Argentina-Flute-World-Music/dp/3702465871&#34;&gt;World Music Argentina&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;some-photos-of-my-ballroom-dance-days&#34;&gt;Some photos of my ballroom dance days&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some photos of me dancing in 2002 with my last dance partner, Amy, before I quit competitive ballroom dancing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here we are at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dcdancesportinferno.com/&#34;&gt;DC DanceSport Inferno&lt;/a&gt; in 2002 doing a hockey stick in international rumba:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/ballroom/dcdi-2002-hockey-stick.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Amy and Franklin at DCDI 2002 in rumba&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And here were are at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://comp.cornelldancesport.org/&#34;&gt;Cornell DanceSport Classic&lt;/a&gt; in 2002 in cha cha, rumba, and tango:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/ballroom/cornell-2002-new-yorker.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Amy and Franklin at Cornell 2002 in cha cha&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/ballroom/cornell-2002-hockey-stick.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Amy and Franklin at Cornell 2002 in rumba&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/ballroom/cornell-2002-tango-promenade.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Amy and Franklin at Cornell 2002 in tango&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;dancing-with-abby&#34;&gt;Dancing with Abby&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But never mind the ballroom dance days. It was through salsa dancing that I met my wife!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;how-i-met-abby&#34;&gt;How I met Abby&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was through dancing that I met Abby in the first place. After quitting dancing in 2003, I never danced again until late 2006, when my friend Jon told me he had recently started salsa dancing (because of a girlfriend who got him into it) and invited me to join him at a free outdoors dance, and I went. Then as I re-entered the Pittsburgh salsa dance scene, I kept running into Abby.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;some-photos-of-us-dancing-salsa&#34;&gt;Some photos of us dancing salsa&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are not many photos of Abby dancing with me, because when I&amp;rsquo;m dancing, I&amp;rsquo;m not holding my camera, but here are some photos a friend took at a big salsa dance weekend at the Palisades in McKeesport in April 2008, a year after we started dating in 2007.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/palisades-2008/abby-franklin.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby and Franklin dancing salsa at Palisades&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/palisades-2008/abby-franklin-hair.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby and Franklin dancing salsa at Palisades, hair flying&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;expression-and-improvisation-in-dance-and-in-music&#34;&gt;Expression and improvisation in dance and in music&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;dance&#34;&gt;Dance&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One reason I gave up ballroom dancing was that I felt there was an overemphasis on &amp;ldquo;syllabus steps&amp;rdquo; (I realize this is an oversimplification of the ballroom dance culture; all very good ballroom dancers go beyond the syllabus mindset). After quitting ballroom dancing, I explored Argentine tango, which is all about improvisation, but I left it because (at the time) it seemed that most of the women in the local scene were very tall, which made dancing awkward for me. I got into salsa because freed from the closed embrace, there was clearly a lot of room for personal improvisation. Ironically, I first got into making stuff up as a result of my imperfect memory: I could never memorize long choreography of step patterns, whether I was doing ballroom dancing or anything else. So I would always make a &amp;ldquo;mistake&amp;rdquo;, then I would make something out of the mistake. I learned that as long as you get back in time with the music, and keep the lead and follow communication strong, there is no such thing really as a mistake. You just keep going, with whatever is happening at the present moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I now have a long-term goal of developing my technique and releasing my inhibitions so that I can improvise musically at will. Yesterday, I played with improvising when playing bolero, cha cha, and tango. It was a lot of fun and profoundly satisfying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;music&#34;&gt;Music&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I actually credit my study of the recorder and the Baroque flute for reawakening me to my dream of free expression and improvisation. Baroque music leaves room for a lot of interpretation of trills and ornamentation and articulation (subject, of course, to &amp;ldquo;good taste&amp;rdquo;). I want to go beyond that, but it has been a great starting point. For some reason, too much exposure to later music (such as Beethoven) had turned me into a score-reader, since such later music has so much already marked up for the performer to simply &lt;em&gt;obey&lt;/em&gt;. The sparse annotations in Renaissance and Baroque music give one much more freedom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am enjoying playing the flute again, now that I know what I really want to do with it. And I would like to merge my dance and music lives, just as Abby has always played the Balkan music she also dances to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2012-03-12&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-03-12)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ended up &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/12/quitting-the-cmu-all-university-orchestra-one-of-the-hardest-decisions-in-my-life/&#34;&gt;quitting the CMU AUO&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2013-01-26&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-01-26)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost a year later, I finally played tangos on flute &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/26/music-i-just-played-for-the-first-time-recorder-sonata-tangos/&#34;&gt;at a party&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2013-03-17&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-03-17)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost exactly a year later, I ended up playing selections from the World Music Cuba book &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/17/finally-doing-some-latin-music-jamming-on-flute/&#34;&gt;at a party&lt;/a&gt;, and improvising freely with two other guys!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Discovering French traditional social dance in Pittsburgh</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/01/23/discovering-french-traditional-dance-in-pittsburgh/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jan 2012 21:53:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/01/23/discovering-french-traditional-dance-in-pittsburgh/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/bourree.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Dancing to bourree&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/LwyH1viCibo&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Saturday, Abby and I went for the first time to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/events/344055168957638/&#34;&gt;latest meeting&lt;/a&gt; of a &lt;a href=&#34;http://coalcountry.org/frenchdance.html&#34;&gt;local French traditional social dance&lt;/a&gt; workshop and dance here in Pittsburgh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a lot of fun!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;attendance&#34;&gt;Attendance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the recently fallen snow at the time (now all but melted!), around twelve of us eventually showed up, and the male-female ratio happened to be very good. For most of us, it was our first time trying out French dancing, but some of us just happened to have had prior some experience with other dancing, such as ballroom and swing and Cajun. The workshop was very friendly to beginners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;dances-we-learned&#34;&gt;Dances we learned&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We spent an hour or so learning various dances, taught by Gregory Dyke and Lisa Tamres.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We warmed up by learning a simple &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Circle_dance&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;circle dance&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; to a waltz rhythm, and Gregory made it more challenging by having us sing along in French (which not all of us knew, but that was OK; I know some French but half the time I just hummed rather than try to sing French while doing dance steps).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then we went to the partnered &lt;em&gt;waltz&lt;/em&gt;, which we did at various tempos, but all pretty fast. There was discussion of toning down the long gliding and lifting actions that some of us reflexively use from having experience with the slow waltz from ballroom dancing, because there is not enough time to use those actions for every step. (I immediately remembered being constantly reminded not to perform these actions when I was dancing &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Viennese_Waltz&#34;&gt;Viennese waltz&lt;/a&gt; in my ballroom dance days. The tempo range for French waltz seems basically the same.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then we learned the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Schottische&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Schottische&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, in a variant that had a triple step, followed by a triple step, and then four single steps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then we changed things up to a variant of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bourrée&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;bourrée&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, in double time, in which there are two lines formed, and the partners facing each other alternate dancing toward each other and past each other, leaving room for personal expression as they do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We returned to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mazurka&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;mazurka&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which was very tricky for many of us because of the asymmetric step pattern: 1-2-hold, 1-2-3, followed by the same starting with the other foot. I still don&amp;rsquo;t completely have the hang of it, but I could feel how it could be pretty exciting because of the holding and building momentum for the second half of the pattern, on which I like to turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, we learned a really fun circle dance, the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mts.net/~jinks/fd/circassi.htm&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Circassian Circle&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;social-dancing&#34;&gt;Social dancing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the workshop instruction, the pianist, Ellen Gozian, had arrived, and the social dance began to live music performed by her and also by Gregory on his wooden flute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About another hour of dancing followed, till it was time for Ellen to leave. Abby and I decided to leave shortly afterwards, but social dancing was going to continue with recorded music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a lot of fun exploring new dances, and would like to attend future workshops and social dances. It&amp;rsquo;s great that so many different dance and music groups exist here in Pittsburgh!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am grateful to Gregory and Lisa for the instruction, Ellen for the piano playing, and every person who was on the dance floor. I think I can safely claim that everyone was smiling and laughing and having a great time at this event!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;invitation&#34;&gt;Invitation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re in the Pittsburgh area and interested in French traditional social dance, check out the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/groups/182324948478861/&#34;&gt;Facebook group&lt;/a&gt; for announcements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2012-02-20&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-02-20)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I have &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/02/20/enjoying-more-french-dancing-in-pittsburgh/&#34;&gt;continued enjoying French dancing&lt;/a&gt; over the year.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Injuries from yoga are common: some tips on staying safe</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/01/06/injuries-from-yoga-are-common-some-tips-on-staying-safe/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jan 2012 22:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/01/06/injuries-from-yoga-are-common-some-tips-on-staying-safe/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;For years now, I&amp;rsquo;ve noticed that when people find out that I do yoga, they often say something like
&lt;blockquote&gt;
I tried yoga once and I got hurt. I thought it was supposed to be relaxing.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I read an article, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2012/01/08/magazine/how-yoga-can-wreck-your-body.html?pagewanted=all&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;How Yoga Can Wreck Your Body&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. I urge anyone who currently does yoga, or is thinking about starting it, to read this article. It discusses cases of quite serious injury in yoga practitioners, including instructors, and reveals a world of danger that many may not be aware of, given how popular and hip yoga has become in the past decade or two.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not a yoga instructor, and I&amp;rsquo;m also not a fanatic yoga devotee, but since I once did yoga every other day for a couple of years, and found it extremely, astoundingly beneficial, I&amp;rsquo;d like to share some ideas on how I have managed to avoid being injured by yoga. I&amp;rsquo;ll also discuss related issues with Pilates and sitting meditation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-discovery-of-yoga&#34;&gt;My discovery of yoga&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first exposure to yoga at all was an infamous episode of the TV show &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/That&#39;s_Incredible!&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;That&amp;rsquo;s Incredible!&lt;/a&gt; in which some guy named &amp;ldquo;Yogi Kudu&amp;rdquo; folded himself up into a box.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point, yoga became mainstream and offered as a &amp;ldquo;fitness&amp;rdquo; class. I got the impression that women and dancers took it up, and I had no interest in yoga until I got into ballroom dance in 2000, became very serious about it, and got my first exposure, from competition-oriented ballroom dancers, to such favorite dancer-oriented activities as yoga, Pilates, and Alexander technique. But any time I did even a basic yoga pose, I found myself embarrassingly inflexible and the whole idea seemed boring to me anyway, so I did not seriously pursue yoga for some time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, as I had also begun to run, and then continued to be very serious about it, I heard from various sources that yoga could be beneficial to runners also. It was not until 2002, when I started training for my first marathon, the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pittsburghmarathon.com/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Marathon&lt;/a&gt;, that I felt that maybe I should check out yoga.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went to some free sampler classes, but found them unsatisfactory. Ironically, I probably prevented early injury as a result. Here&amp;rsquo;s why: I &lt;strong&gt;think about what pain and discomfort mean&lt;/strong&gt;! I felt physically and mentally uncomfortable and did not continue going to group classes, but decided on some self-study.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-drawbacks-of-group-classes&#34;&gt;The drawbacks of group classes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a standard group class, there are many drawbacks to learning &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; subject. Yoga is no exception. Without individual instruction and detailed feedback, it is easy to do all kinds of horrible things to your body. Some people are &amp;ldquo;wimps&amp;rdquo;, and they are actually the smart ones, because they quit thinking (incorrectly, I would add), &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m not cut out for yoga.&amp;rdquo; Others push through the pain thinking, &amp;ldquo;no pain, no gain&amp;rdquo;. Having incorrectly adopted this attitude earlier, when overdoing my running, I knew from experience that I never wanted again to go too far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Worse, it&amp;rsquo;s discouraging when you can&amp;rsquo;t keep up some standard sequence the instructor leads everyone as a group through, while some people around you are doing just fine. Yes, we should check our &lt;em&gt;ego&lt;/em&gt; at the door, but sometimes that is hard, and trying to learn something difficult while ego interferes is not optimal. A good instructor will give detailed instructions on modifying poses or movements, or substituting them entirely with rest that does not break the flow, but given the sampler classes I have experienced, I can safely say that not every instructor pays this much attention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, the subtleties of each pose and its intention are hardly explained, in a typical drop-in yoga class. If yoga classes were structured within real progressing sequences with prerequisites, rather than existing as free-floating interchangeable drop-in commodities, maybe there would be better explanations. The typical yoga class I have gone to has instructors trying to scope out or ask aloud, &amp;ldquo;Who here is new?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-i-started-a-regular-private-practice-of-yoga&#34;&gt;How I started a regular private practice of yoga&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As my curiosity was whetted from the sampler classes, I decided to try out some books and videos on yoga. I am a big fan of self-learning, through books, videos, and the vast resource that is the entire Web. I can learn more detail about technique, I can read about comparisons, I can go at my own pace, and in privacy (eliminating the fear of embarrassment). I can choose which subsets to explore and use, rather than be subjected to someone else&amp;rsquo;s rigid ideas or instruction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I quickly found that the books and videos of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rodney_Yee&#34;&gt;Rodney Yee&lt;/a&gt; worked very well for me. For a couple of years, I ended up using a several of his &amp;ldquo;Power Yoga&amp;rdquo; DVDs as my primary half-hour-or-so yoga sessions every other day. I would definitely recommend them. Here&amp;rsquo;s what I like about Yee&amp;rsquo;s videos:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As a male, I happen to enjoy having a male instructor and role model to emulate; although I have used videos by female instructors also, I find it jarring to follow a female instructor who is far more flexible in various ways than a typical male instructor.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Yee has a soothing, encouraging voice and delivery of instructions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Yee&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;pace&lt;/em&gt; is usually pretty good for me, not too fast, not too slow.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Relatively few poses&lt;/em&gt; are used in most of his videos I have used. It is better to try to master a few important &lt;em&gt;simpler&lt;/em&gt; poses than to squander attention on a whole lot of poses. Also, I will claim that the more complex the pose, the greater the potential for injury.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are different workouts with different intensities: &amp;ldquo;stamina&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;strength&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;flexibility&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;benefits-i-have-experienced-from-yoga&#34;&gt;Benefits I have experienced from yoga&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result of yoga, every single year in the past decade, I have become more flexible. &lt;strong&gt;I am now more flexible than I was in high school.&lt;/strong&gt; That&amp;rsquo;s really something, and it&amp;rsquo;s great being more flexible. When your body is looser, it is less stressed and burdened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have improved my posture. Stretching out the spine through persistent practice of yoga really works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Increased awareness of breath is something I learned both from running and from yoga. A good yoga instructor reminds you to pay attention to inhaling and exhaling in harmony with your movements. The circulation helps clear up one&amp;rsquo;s mind and both awaken and relax the body.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Balance. Many of the poses challenge one&amp;rsquo;s balance. I have spent much of my life slumping in chairs and other furniture. Yoga helped reverse the bad habits and imbalance coming from a sedentary lifestyle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;some-yoga-poses-i-am-currently-careful-about-or-avoid&#34;&gt;Some yoga poses I am currently careful about or avoid&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t do all the poses Yee demonstrates, and the ones I do, I don&amp;rsquo;t necessarily do in the full extension given. Here are some issues I discovered apply to myself:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reclined leg stretch. Personally, I have tight hamstrings I&amp;rsquo;m still working on. I can&amp;rsquo;t do a full leg stretch. As recommended, I use a strap. I make sure not to compromise my &lt;em&gt;back&lt;/em&gt; when doing stuff like this. I have seen a lot of people straining.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Various deep back bends. I simply do not trust these. I have had back injuries in the past, and although I am fine now, I don&amp;rsquo;t ever want to injure my back again.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Downward-facing dog. I make sure to use the modified bent-knee variation if I feel too tight in my hamstrings or Achilles tendons or elsewhere. I have seen people with legs straight but &lt;em&gt;backs&lt;/em&gt; curved: this is not good.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Various forward bends. Again, I protect my &lt;em&gt;back&lt;/em&gt;, by bending my knees if I feel the need.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lunge. This is easy for me now, but at the very beginning, I had trouble doing this. A &lt;em&gt;block&lt;/em&gt; is a great prop for modification of poses by decreasing the distance to the ground. I used blocks extensively when first getting into yoga, and I still use them today as I feel the need. There are no bonus points for going without a block out of ego.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Triangle pose. I like this pose, but don&amp;rsquo;t ever expect to perform it without modification. To put the palm of my hand on the ground just twists and hurts my &lt;em&gt;back&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;hip&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anything that puts pressure on my &lt;em&gt;neck&lt;/em&gt;, I avoid or modify. Why do I really need to pull my head back far for cobra, or for upward-facing dog? It doesn&amp;rsquo;t feel right.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;More elaborate poses involving lifting off the ground can put pressure on the &lt;em&gt;neck&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;wrists&lt;/em&gt;. I avoid them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;current-group-class&#34;&gt;Current group class&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I sometimes attend a local free &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/24/roaring-like-a-lion-on-a-saturday/&#34;&gt;drop-in class at the Squirrel Hill Library&lt;/a&gt;. We don&amp;rsquo;t go often, but it is nice in small doses. Some of the reasons we don&amp;rsquo;t go often:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The session is very long, and we prefer shorter sessions. Some people do leave early, but breaking the flow of a complete workout (that includes a nice relaxation segment at the end) just seems inappropriate.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We don&amp;rsquo;t get detailed technical instruction on how to do things right. This is a very large group class.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We are encouraged or guided to go into difficult poses that we are not comfortable with. Yes, the instructor does tell us we don&amp;rsquo;t have to do them, and yes, we know to listen to our bodies, but still, it is somewhat disorienting to decide not to do something when other people are doing it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, the important thing when doing yoga is &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/04/against-just-putting-in-the-time/&#34;&gt;not to do it mechanically, but with awareness and no ego&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-current-practice&#34;&gt;My current practice&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I actually have not done full yoga sessions in two or three years. I do go into some yoga poses spontaneously as part of a stretch and then cool down for other activities, including running, dancing, and strength training. For this new year of 2012, I intend to get back into extended yoga practice. I will continue to write about deepening my yoga experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;pilates&#34;&gt;Pilates&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have to confess that I do not like Pilates. Many of the positions involved in Pilates cause me great stress. I have given Pilates a serious try. I don&amp;rsquo;t know if it&amp;rsquo;s just me, or if other people have a similar experience, but lifting my head up from the ground, for example, causes me great stress. It definitely increases my blood pressure and gives me a headache and strain on my neck and back. This is just my personal experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pilates confuses me. I avoid it. I like to try many different physical disciplines, but Pilates is one that I have abandoned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;sitting-meditation&#34;&gt;Sitting meditation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sitting meditation in a classic lotus position is incredibly difficult. Let me put it this way: after a few years of some periods of regular sitting, it is only in the past two or three months that I am able to sit in something resembling a full lotus position. And I don&amp;rsquo;t like to do this continuously for more than around twenty minutes. That&amp;rsquo;s my limitation. People have wrecked their knees or ankles doing meditation, so as with yoga, it&amp;rsquo;s extremely important not to force yourself into a position that you can&amp;rsquo;t handle. And take note of your motivations. Don&amp;rsquo;t reward yourself with bonus points for doing an &amp;ldquo;advanced&amp;rdquo; position. That&amp;rsquo;s not the point of meditation. I try for lotus purely because it really is more stable than some other more asymmetrical positions, such as Burmese and half Burmese. And I have tried kneeling with or without a bench, but that causes me various problems, for my knees and ankles. And sitting on a chair is definitely suboptimal for the meditation experience, because of the lack of a truly stable base.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even in simpler positions, I can get numb or feel pressure on my ligaments or something. There is always controversy, among different meditation leaders, over how much discomfort to tolerate as an essential part of the practice, and how much is harmful and justifies shifting position or changing position entirely, but I am happy that in the group practice I attend, we are allowed to err on the side of looking out for ourselves. If you meditate in a group, be sure to understand what your leader&amp;rsquo;s expectations are, and make sure they are in line with what you are prepared to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yoga can be very dangerous if you don&amp;rsquo;t have experience paying attention to your body and being really in touch with what is painful and harmful and what is merely challenging and beneficial. I advise that beginners progress very slowly when taking up yoga, ideally with feedback from an instructor who is aware of the dangers. I advise that experienced practitioners do a full review of what they do and what might be causing undue discomfort or pain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Caveats aside, I have found yoga to be a transformative part of my life, refreshing and rejuvenating, and recommend it as a practice to those wishing to deepen their understanding and experience of their mind, body, spirit.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Video review: Dancing with the Stars: Cardio Dance (2006)</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/12/13/video-review-dancing-with-the-stars-cardio-dance-2006/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Dec 2011 22:46:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/12/13/video-review-dancing-with-the-stars-cardio-dance-2006/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;When the weather is cold, I confess that I don&amp;rsquo;t enjoy running outside. I have done so in the past when much more serious about running, but I do not like it much. So I end up doing exercise indoors that is something of a substitute for running. I should really take up swimming (Abby wants to get me to do that), but traditionally, I have enjoyed doing &lt;strong&gt;dance&lt;/strong&gt; workouts to videos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of my favorite dance workout DVDs, which I have used for almost half a decade now since it came out, is &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Dancing-Stars-Cardio-Dance/dp/B000MMMTC8&#34;&gt;Dancing with the Stars: Cardio Dance (2006)&lt;/a&gt;. I have never tired of it (as long as I don&amp;rsquo;t use it all the time, of course; I have a number of other exercise videos I will review later).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://ecx.images-amazon.com/images/I/51j9ihJucML._SL500_AA300_.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Dancing with the Stars: Cardio Dance (2006) DVD&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-tv-show&#34;&gt;The TV show&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The DVD came out, of course, as a result of the popularity of the TV series &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dancing_with_the_Stars_%28U.S._TV_series%29&#34;&gt;Dancing with the Stars&lt;/a&gt;. I had watched several episodes in 2006, out of curiosity, since in 2000-2002 I had been pretty serious about &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/18/disagreement-on-the-use-of-time/&#34;&gt;doing competitive ballroom dancing&lt;/a&gt;, so I wanted to see just how good the celebrities could get, with training. I was actually impressed by how good some of them got, although there were many who were not very good at all and really had no business trying to perform complicated routines rather than mastering basic technique (my instructors were always adamant about our not trying to do what we weren&amp;rsquo;t yet ready for, lest we develop poor habits difficult to unlearn).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-content-of-the-workout&#34;&gt;The content of the workout&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-dancers&#34;&gt;The dancers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One reason I enjoy the workout is that the dancers on video are actually decent. The pro instructors on the video, Kym, Maksim, Ashly, are good, and the other dancers hold up too. I find it important to see good technique at work, because we learn by imitation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, I like that there are a number of different male and female dancers, with different ethnicities and body types. All are in great shape, of course. For me, it was important to see not only Maksim, but two other male dancers. I enjoy exercise videos more when I see men doing stuff, and have role models to emulate. Also, to be frank, the women are always more flexible, and I feel odd whenever I can&amp;rsquo;t quite do something that I see on a video. So I feel comforted seeing men who are more limited and remind me that I&amp;rsquo;m doing OK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a guy on this video who looks kind of Asian. I always like to see someone whose body type seems close to mine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-moves&#34;&gt;The moves&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The moves are basic and real ballroom dance moves put together to form routines. There are very few gimmicky, tricky moves. Things get repetitious, so I can&amp;rsquo;t use this video more than maybe twice a week, but that&amp;rsquo;s fine. I happen to enjoy continuing to refine my technique on the same steps again and again. And I feel that over the years as I&amp;rsquo;ve used this video, I have indeed improved considerably in my technique, speed, stamina, and expressiveness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, I quite like the paso doble workout, because it is all about showing off in macho fashion, by using the arms, twisting, pretending to wield a cape, standing tall. It&amp;rsquo;s a very masculine dance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second dance, the cha cha, is repetitious, and unfortunately is danced on 1 rather than on 2 (obviously for the sake of not confusing beginners), but is a nice workout for the core, if one pays attention to technique and doing crisp cha-cha-cha and proper Latin hip motion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third dance, the samba, is a lot of fun and faster and more strenuous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final dance, the jive, definitely generates a lot of sweat. It&amp;rsquo;s almost like running. My calves get a real workout from the jive. Amusingly, you can see how the non-pros get more and more tired and struggle. I did initially also, but eventually I became more efficient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In each of these dances, the instructors are very enthusiastic, and the other dancers seem to be enjoying themselves also. I really like that vibe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-warmup-and-cooldown&#34;&gt;The warmup and cooldown&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The warmup and cooldown framing the workout are very brief, as typical of these videos, unfortunately. I simply warm up by myself before even popping in the DVD, and I skip the video&amp;rsquo;s cooldown in favor of my own stretching, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;caveats&#34;&gt;Caveats&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, there is a reason ratings for the DVD on Amazon are all over the map. Dance exercise videos can never please everyone, because of differences in people&amp;rsquo;s levels of fitness and technique.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For someone like me, who has had a bit of serious ballroom dance training and is looking for a reasonable workout based on Latin dance, the video is perfect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would &lt;em&gt;not at all&lt;/em&gt; recommend this video for a total newcomer to ballroom dance. There is no instruction on technique. Without proper technique, it&amp;rsquo;s not really possible to get through the workout efficiently and enjoyably. You could get injured, in fact. The samba and jive, in particular, could result in a lot of pounding on joints, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I enjoy this dance workout video very much, but I hesitate to recommend it to anyone other than people who have already at least received rudimentary instruction on each of the dances covered: paso doble, cha cha, samba, jive.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Disagreement on the use of time?</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/10/18/disagreement-on-the-use-of-time/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Oct 2011 19:14:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/10/18/disagreement-on-the-use-of-time/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On Sunday, I went to the monthly meeting of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.andrew.cmu.edu/user/lukas/pcars/Welcome.html&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh chapter&lt;/a&gt; of the American Recorder Society. I stopped by the room where beginner lessons were being held. I don&amp;rsquo;t go to those lessons any more, because I would say I&amp;rsquo;m an intermediate recorder player now. Fred, our director, was working with two women on soprano recorder. One of them was Rhonda, who had actually joined the local group at exactly the same time as me, back in March. I hadn&amp;rsquo;t seen her in a while and asked where she&amp;rsquo;d been. She said she had been playing French horn in the summer, so was getting back to recorder now. She happened to joke to the other woman, an older woman, that I was really serious and had been practicing an hour every day since starting out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To my surprise, the other woman (whom I don&amp;rsquo;t remember ever having met before) immediately launched into some remarks I found snarky. She said, &amp;ldquo;Well, that&amp;rsquo;s probably an hour he&amp;rsquo;s not washing dishes.&amp;rdquo; I paused in shock, and then she continued, &amp;ldquo;Or an hour he&amp;rsquo;s not taking out the trash.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was not quite sure how to respond.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-response&#34;&gt;My response&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously, this could have been an opportunity for me to use &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/11/communicating-through-dialogue/&#34;&gt;dialogue&lt;/a&gt; and try to understand why she said what she said, and what she really meant by her words that I found disparaging. In fact, thanks to my raised awareness from learning about dialogue just recently, at least I did not get angry or lose my temper. But I decided at the time that I was just passing by and was not interested in going off on a tangent, since I was heading back to the other room to set up my instruments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I simply replied calmly that actually, the hour of my time that went to recorder practice came out of time I used to spend on various forms of entertainment. I said that I don&amp;rsquo;t watch any TV and I don&amp;rsquo;t watch any movies. She didn&amp;rsquo;t respond to that. For all I know, she might be one of the average Americans who watch &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.csun.edu/science/health/docs/tv&amp;amp;health.html&#34;&gt;4 hours of TV a day&lt;/a&gt;, and perhaps I unintentionally offended her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Disclaimer: I am not one of those snobs who summarily look down on people who watch TV. I used to watch a lot of TV. In fact, I cannot imagine what my life would be today without having had access to TV, which expanded my emotional and intellectual world. But that was then; now, I simply make different choices with my time.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I left the room and didn&amp;rsquo;t see her again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I&amp;rsquo;m still curious about why she seemed annoyed that I spent an hour a day practicing music, as though I&amp;rsquo;m not getting chores done. I won&amp;rsquo;t speculate about why, since the only right way to satisfy my curiosity would be to ask her myself, and I passed up the opportunity to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My brief response to her was meant to convey a simple message: time management is important for all of us with our busy lives, but I&amp;rsquo;ve made certain choices, sacrificing some activities in order to gain others. The decisions are often quite difficult, because I have a &lt;em&gt;huge&lt;/em&gt; number of interests, and therefore have to sacrifice the majority of them in order to focus on the fewer that I have decided are most worthwhile to pursue. A breadth-first traversal of all possible life activities would result in completing nothing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;trading-passive-for-active&#34;&gt;Trading passive for active&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of my choices involve trading passive experiences for active experiences. Here are some examples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;music&#34;&gt;Music&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an earlier blog post, I already mentioned why &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/02/i-love-music-but-rarely-listen-to-it-now/&#34;&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t listen to music much&lt;/a&gt; any more, because of time constraints. In effect, I traded listening to music for playing music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;sports&#34;&gt;Sports&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of watching sports, I engage in my own competitive physical activity, to become the athlete instead of the spectator. I enjoy &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/races/&#34;&gt;running races&lt;/a&gt;. I am hardly super fast; at my fastest, I did periodically win age group medals and trophies, but only because competition happened not to be very tough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;exercise&#34;&gt;Exercise&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I run considerably less than I used to. One reason is that once upon a time, I got into a competitive mode, trying to see how fast I could race, and now I am no longer in that mode. It takes too much time and energy. Another reason is that I decided, based on personal experience and learning from the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paleolithic_lifestyle&#34;&gt;paleo/primal&lt;/a&gt; movement, that too much distance running isn&amp;rsquo;t actually all that great for my overall balanced health.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I traded distance training time for &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/24/roaring-like-a-lion-on-a-saturday-morning/&#34;&gt;yoga&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/17/the-joys-of-convict-conditioning-bodyweight-exercising/&#34;&gt;strength training&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I no longer run any more than every other day on average.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;reading&#34;&gt;Reading&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve always read a lot. I still do, using not only the vast web, but also the old-fashioned &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/30/free-to-the-people-since-1895/&#34;&gt;local library&lt;/a&gt;. (Pittsburghers, please &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ourlibraryourfuture.org/&#34;&gt;vote on November 8&lt;/a&gt;!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, at some point I had to make peace with the fact that I could not read everything I might be interested in reading. Abby and I worked on selling or donating over a thousand (!!) books I owned but were just taking up space. It was very difficult parting with them, since one of my childhood dreams had been to build up a large personal library, but reason prevailed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still encounter too much reading material, thanks to the web. I have tried to limit it by using Google Reader exclusively to access information, and never aimlessly loading up web sites, but I have to confess it is still hard to be selective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, now I am writing for my blog, so I am trading reading time for writing time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;computer-programming-languages&#34;&gt;Computer programming languages&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used to be a big computer language hobbyist. I enjoyed learning and playing with dozens of programming languages: if a language exists, I&amp;rsquo;ve probably at least seen sample code and written some sample code for it at some point. I was even obsessed enough with the concept of designing good programming languages that for a while I was enrolled in the Ph.D. program in computer science at CMU, specializing in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~fox/languages.html&#34;&gt;programming language theory&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then as a practicing software developer, I eventually realized that to &lt;em&gt;get stuff done&lt;/em&gt;, I needed to scale back on my hobby. Therefore, for example, as I mentioned in my post about &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/16/pittsburgh-software-developer-communities/&#34;&gt;local software developer groups&lt;/a&gt;, I have ceased following Python. Also, I have deliberately not even looked at new languages such as &lt;a href=&#34;http://fantom.org/&#34;&gt;Fantom&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://gosu-lang.org/&#34;&gt;Gosu&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://confluence.jetbrains.net/display/Kotlin/Welcome&#34;&gt;Kotlin&lt;/a&gt;. (On the other hand, I am committed to learning and using &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.scala-lang.org/&#34;&gt;Scala&lt;/a&gt; more, because the path from Java already exists.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I took only a quick look at Google&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dartlang.org/&#34;&gt;Dart&lt;/a&gt; after the big hype, and am not pursuing it further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trade-off: trading time spent playing with new languages for time spent mastering and implementing programs with old languages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;completely-abandoning-an-activity&#34;&gt;Completely abandoning an activity&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, I have freed up time by completely abandoning an activity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;dancing-part-one&#34;&gt;Dancing (part one)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once upon a time, I did a lot of ballroom dancing. I even trained seriously and entered competitions through the &lt;a href=&#34;http://cmubdc.org/&#34;&gt;CMU ballroom dance club&lt;/a&gt;. I was dancing something like 20 hours a week (note: this was when I was not doing any reading or music or chess, as my trade-off). I quit competitive ballroom dancing eventually, and then even social ballroom dancing. I had also taken up swing and tango, and salsa more seriously, but then quit those too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically, my trade-off was that I completely quit dancing and took up chess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;chess&#34;&gt;Chess&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past, chess was the most time-consuming hobby in my life. A couple of years ago, I was bent on finally achieving a national &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chess_master&#34;&gt;Master&lt;/a&gt; title. I studied hard, improved my game, played a lot. I won the &lt;a href=&#34;http://pscfchess.org/results/06040808.htm&#34;&gt;2006 Pennsylvania Game/29 Championship&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&#34;http://pscfchess.org/results/06101414.htm&#34;&gt;2006 Pennsylvania Action Chess Championship&lt;/a&gt;; I was on the verge of making Master by planning to win the &lt;a href=&#34;http://pscfchess.org/results/07071414.htm&#34;&gt;2007 Pennsylvania Action Chess Championship&lt;/a&gt; when I utterly &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Choke_(sports)&#34;&gt;choked&lt;/a&gt; and blew it by losing the last two games. I never really recovered from that. My life was changing at the time, having just starting to date Abby, and I stopped playing after a while, then after being married, I started playing again, but my heart was not in it, and I played terribly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I quit chess in February 2011. In effect, I traded chess for starting to play recorder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have not played any chess since February. I don&amp;rsquo;t really regret it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;update-of-2013-01-23&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-01-23)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, in the first half of 2012, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/02/07/on-playing-my-first-games-of-chess-in-a-year/&#34;&gt;some&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/05/31/some-pretty-attacking-chess-at-a-party-last-weekend/&#34;&gt;casual&lt;/a&gt; contact with chess led me to feel like playing again, and in August I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/08/21/returning-to-chess/&#34;&gt;decided to start playing in tournaments again&lt;/a&gt; and am right now in the middle of a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/16/pittsburgh-chess-club-championship-2013-round-1-the-art-of-swindling/&#34;&gt;six-week tournament&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;ve gone back to the chess with clear constraints on how much time and energy I spend on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;update-of-2015-12-21&#34;&gt;(Update of 2015-12-21)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Four years later, I made a focused push, temporarily putting many
things aside in my life, in the fall of 2015 to &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2016/01/22/on-finally-achieving-the-us-national-master-chess-title-at-age-45-part-1&#34;&gt;achieve my US Chess
National Master title&lt;/a&gt;, and finally made it, a dream come true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, I have been teaching private lessons since 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;dancing-part-two&#34;&gt;Dancing (part two)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I accidentally first met Abby when I returned to salsa dancing while still playing chess. Eventually, we started dating, and we were going dancing frequently, but eventually we both completely quit salsa dancing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trade-off was that we got into hiking and kayaking together, which was more fulfilling than our going to dances together and my wanting to dance with a lot of women but her only wanting to dance with me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I consciously traded dancing for a relationship and marriage!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;update-of-2013-01-23-1&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-01-23)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, Abby and I accidentally ended up doing some dancing together again, including discovering &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/01/23/discovering-french-traditional-dance-in-pittsburgh/&#34;&gt;French dancing&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/31/my-first-sampling-of-english-country-dance-and-contra-dance/&#34;&gt;English country and contra dancing&lt;/a&gt;. We don&amp;rsquo;t do it regularly, but it&amp;rsquo;s been great doing it on occasion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, for 2013, we decided that we should dance together a little bit every day, just for ourselves, simply to appreciate that we can!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;marriage&#34;&gt;Marriage&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Married life is a lot of trade-offs.  It&amp;rsquo;s nothing resembling single life or dating life!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Time is precious. We all have to make trade-offs. I&amp;rsquo;ve explored some ways in which I made certain trade-offs at certain points in my life. In your own life, do you periodically double-check what your priorities are, when you feel &amp;ldquo;too busy&amp;rdquo; for something you think you value?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>