<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Baroque on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/baroque/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Baroque on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/baroque/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Revisiting Bach&#39;s Air on G String, from a singing and dancing viewpoint</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/06/10/revisiting-bachs-air-on-g-string-from-a-singing-and-dancing-viewpoint/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jun 2015 23:46:26 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/06/10/revisiting-bachs-air-on-g-string-from-a-singing-and-dancing-viewpoint/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Three years ago, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/14/passion-of-bachs-air-on-the-g-string-three-different-interpretations/&#34;&gt;I wrote a post comparing three very different
performance styles&lt;/a&gt;
for Johann Sebastian Bach&amp;rsquo;s famous music,
&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Air_on_the_G_String&#34;&gt;Air on G String&lt;/a&gt;
and indicating which I preferred.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have received an unexpected number comments over the years, and
thought it was time to write an update of my thoughts in response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Primarily, I am responding to those who (correctly) criticized the
unfortunately chosen exemplar of the style that I preferred. I tried
to find better versions that might illustrate my perceptions. I also
integrated some thoughts based on how I perceive music as a singer and
as a dancer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;better-than-the-rushed-croatian-baroque-ensemble-s-performance&#34;&gt;Better than the rushed Croatian Baroque Ensemble&amp;rsquo;s performance?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I agreed quickly with the first commenters that the Croatian
ensemble&amp;rsquo;s performance was too perfunctory, even downright brutal and
unpleasant in various ways. I wish I had
chosen a better example of what I actually &lt;em&gt;like&lt;/em&gt; rather than &lt;em&gt;prefer
to the other two versions&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I searched YouTube for period-style performances that are
closer to what I envision than either the Croatian ensemble&amp;rsquo;s or
Koopman&amp;rsquo;s. It proved impossible for me to find a perfect performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-period-performance-i-like-more-christopher-hogwood&#34;&gt;A period performance I like more: Christopher Hogwood&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like this version by the late &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christopher_Hogwood&#34;&gt;Christopher Hogwood&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s Academy of
Ancient Music:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/nrtdhH8_47k&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a sweetness and &lt;em&gt;bouncy lightness&lt;/em&gt; to this version that I
like, but it is also somewhat anemic. Personally, I would play up more
contrast and fullness of sound and passion, but the overall tempo and
breathing to this version seems right to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;voices-of-music-richer-sound&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Voices of Music&amp;rdquo;: richer sound&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Voices of Music&amp;rdquo; here in a good performance:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/pzlw6fUux4o&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like the richness of sound in this performance. I miss the lighter,
more bouncy feeling that Hogwood brought out though. This performance
is a bit too legato for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;i-care-about-singing&#34;&gt;I care about singing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I approach this music from the viewpoint of singing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bouncy lightness is very important to me, along with the rhythmic
characterization. I feel this music as a song (it is an &amp;ldquo;air&amp;rdquo;, after
all), and I cannot help singing along when I hear it. Therefore, when
it&amp;rsquo;s taken too slow for me to sing and make it to natural breathing
points in phrases, that considerably lessens my pleasure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;yehudi-menuhin-solo-violin&#34;&gt;Yehudi Menuhin, solo violin&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s an interesting old black and white video of a performance by a young Yehudi Menuhin on violin with
accompaniment. It&amp;rsquo;s not a period performance, but moves along at a
decent &amp;ldquo;singing&amp;rdquo; tempo, as befits violin, that singing instrument.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34;
src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/08bDiKXW0gg&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;
allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I confess that I rather like this performance for its virtues,
although it distorts Bach&amp;rsquo;s music by so emphasizing just the musical
line, at the expense of the balance of the other voices and the
essential character of the dissonances among the voices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;more-menuhin-but-as-conductor&#34;&gt;More Menuhin, but as conductor&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s Yehudi Menuhin not as violin soloist but as conductor of the
Bath Festival Orchestra in 1960. Again, not a period performance, but
he takes the music briskly, and has the violins create sufficient
phrase delineations that I feel the music alertly as though it sings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s direct and clear, maybe not the most subtle and warm,
but I like it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/kaBAE4stNIo&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;dancing-is-possible-too&#34;&gt;Dancing is possible too&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also like to dance to expressive music. A pioneer of modern dance,
Doris Humphrey, famously choreographed a dance to a slowish
performance of this music:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/NjwJyaSIRqY&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not how I would dance to it, because I feel the music
differently. Surprisingly, I could find few examples on YouTube of
dancing to this music. I may consider choreographing a dance myself as
a project to express my own personal vision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing I would like to mention is that I feel that the &lt;em&gt;walking bass&lt;/em&gt;
is very important in this music and gives it the impetus. When played
too slow, the walking bass no longer feels like it&amp;rsquo;s walking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel this music in my legs, not just in my lungs. Yes, I have
actually hummed it to myself while walking in time to the bass
leisurely in the local park. There is a limit to how &amp;ldquo;leisurely&amp;rdquo; I can
walk without feeling frustrated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;ice-dancing&#34;&gt;Ice dancing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found this somewhat frenetic but nevertheless beautiful ice dancing
performance from the 1992 World Figure Skating Championships:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/1JjbwtM_E3g&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;recorder-quartet&#34;&gt;Recorder quartet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A final performance to enjoy: the Japanese &amp;ldquo;Sekishi Recorder Quartet&amp;rdquo;
playing their hearts out in 2009. I think it&amp;rsquo;s lovely: impeccable
phrasing, transparency,
and rich ensemble balance and tone. (As a twist, the melody line performer adds
his own ornamentations.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/pRRRK0UClNs&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was inspired by the accumulated comments on my previous post on
Bach&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Air on G String&amp;rdquo; that I decided to flesh out my thoughts by
using more example performances, as well as relate the orchestral
music to singing and dancing. I hope you have enjoyed these
explorations. There is no single &amp;ldquo;right&amp;rdquo; way to experience music, but
I wanted to share how I experience it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;ve read my previous post, does this one help clarify where
  I&amp;rsquo;m coming from with my musical values? Do you dance
  or sing? Does this affect how you perceive this piece of music and
  like to perform it or hear it performed?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The perfect music for Good Friday: some favorite interpretations of Bach&#39;s &#34;Erbarme dich&#34; from the St. Matthew Passion</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/04/18/the-perfect-music-for-good-friday-some-favorite-interpretations-of-bachs-erbarme-dich-from-the-st-matthew-passion/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Apr 2014 07:38:07 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/04/18/the-perfect-music-for-good-friday-some-favorite-interpretations-of-bachs-erbarme-dich-from-the-st-matthew-passion/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;You might assume, since I&amp;rsquo;m talking about &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Good_Friday&#34;&gt;Good Friday&lt;/a&gt;, that I&amp;rsquo;m Christian, and that I&amp;rsquo;m here to talk about my faith. Actually, I&amp;rsquo;m not Christian, but I also believe that Easter is not irrelevant. Here&amp;rsquo;s another non-Christian writing about &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rsablogs.org.uk/2014/socialbrain/meaning-easter-bunnies/&#34;&gt;why Easter matters&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve found it impossible to escape the fact that one of my favorite music composers, Johann Sebastian Bach, was not only Christian, but clearly imbued his music in some way or other with his deep faith. Two years ago, while listening to the opening chorus of his &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St_Matthew_Passion&#34;&gt;St. Matthew Passion&lt;/a&gt;, which was first performed on Good Friday in 1727, I also saw a thoughtful article by a Muslim, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.telegraph.co.uk/culture/music/opera/9206775/Can-non-Christians-appreciate-Bachs-St-Matthew-Passion.html&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Can non-Christians appreciate Bach&amp;rsquo;s St. Matthew Passion&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;m not here to add to that debate, but to share one of the most moving pieces in the entire history of Western music, the aria &amp;ldquo;Erbarme dich&amp;rdquo; from the St. Matthew Passion. I hope you will check it out, whether you are Christian or not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;erbarme-dich&#34;&gt;Erbarme dich&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The aria features a prominent violin solo part as well as a sung alto solo part. It represents the disciple Peter&amp;rsquo;s anguished and lonely weeping (&amp;ldquo;Have mercy, my Lord&amp;rdquo;) after &lt;a href=&#34;http://biblehub.com/matthew/26-75.htm&#34;&gt;he has three times denied knowing Jesus&lt;/a&gt;, guilty of the most shameful betrayal. The way Bach depicts Peter&amp;rsquo;s emotional state through music is astounding and gripping. You just have to hear it for yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;sophie-gent-damien-guillon&#34;&gt;Sophie Gent, Damien Guillon&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One performance I like features Sophie Gent on violin and Damien Guillon as countertenor. It is a very meditative, pure-sounding performance:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/nZb7FcP84CM&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;unknown-violinist-andreas-scholl&#34;&gt;Unknown violinist, Andreas Scholl&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I do prefer an edgier performance, and here is one that is more urgent and dramatic (audio only, no video of the performance) by Andreas Scholl as countertenor. Scholl really impresses here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/0WLedpz9a40&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can actually follow along in the score by a synchronized video score &lt;a href=&#34;http://musescore.com/rpbouman/scores/141997&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;fredrik-from-anne-sofie-von-otter&#34;&gt;Fredrik From, Anne Sofie von Otter&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An even more urgent performance that might be my favorite is by Fredrik From on violin, Anne Sofie von Otter as mezzo-soprano. I have to confess that I feel that the tempo is a bit fast, but that does, in conjunction with the impeccable articulation and ensemble unity of purpose and style, give a driving force to Peter&amp;rsquo;s anguish. For me, this is the most &lt;em&gt;expressive&lt;/em&gt; of the performances I&amp;rsquo;m listing here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few notes on this video:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This is a video of a recording session, so it is curious to see von Otter in everyday clothing and moving and gesturing while singing for the purpose of a recording, where the audience is not meant to know what she was wearing or how she was privately swaying to the music. I find watching her both mesmerizing and distracting, but I feel that somehow her being free to express herself any way she wanted, sight unseen, might have been a good thing, because hers is truly an emotionally raw performance. &lt;strong&gt;How do you feel about peeking into a recording session where conditions are optimal for the performer and not meant to be seen by the outside world?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The second half of the video is an interview with von Otter about the recording project.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/XR-DFZEBAic&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;unknown-violinist-nathalie-stutzmann&#34;&gt;Unknown violinist, Nathalie Stutzmann&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the topic of visually expressive performances, here is one of Nathalie Stutzmann as contralto and also as conductor. Both she and the violinist are totally into the music, holding nothing back physically as they express it. A rather unusual setting and view, but very powerful:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/Jeil9S2exIU&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;frederick-chiu-on-piano&#34;&gt;Frederick Chiu on piano&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pianist Frederick created his own transcription for piano of the aria. His performance is rather restrained for my taste, but it&amp;rsquo;s something different:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/U3nUvzApF2E&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve shared a few interesting performances of Bach&amp;rsquo;s aria &amp;ldquo;Erbarme dich&amp;rdquo; from his St. Matthew Passion. There are many other performances out there, of course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Which of the performances I linked to are your favorite, and why? Or which ones I did not link to do you prefer, and why? And do you feel you need to be a Christian to appreciate and enjoy this kind of sacred music?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I never expected my first wooden recorders to be Renaissance recorders</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/21/i-never-expected-my-first-wooden-recorders-to-be-renaissance-recorders/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2013 21:24:54 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/21/i-never-expected-my-first-wooden-recorders-to-be-renaissance-recorders/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/10/20/the-biggest-pittsburgh-recorder-society-meeting-i-have-attended-in-two-years/&#34;&gt;Yesterday, I noted&lt;/a&gt; that I picked up two recorders during the Pittsburgh Recorder Society meeting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They were these &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.vonhuene.com/Default.aspx?tabid=42&#34;&gt;Renaissance&lt;/a&gt; instruments:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mollenhauer-kynseker-recorders/boxed.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;In boxes&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mollenhauer-kynseker-recorders/assembled.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Assembled&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nice maple recorders, Mollenhauer Kynseker models:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mollenhauer.com/en/catalogue?page=shop.product_details&amp;amp;flypage=flypage.tpl&amp;amp;product_id=170&amp;amp;category_id=121&#34;&gt;Kynseker Soprano 4107&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mollenhauer.com/en/catalogue?page=shop.product_details&amp;amp;flypage=flypage.tpl&amp;amp;product_id=172&amp;amp;category_id=121&#34;&gt;Kynseker Alto 4217&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are my very first wooden recorders. All my other recorders are Yamaha plastic recorders, because they are inexpensive and easy to maintain. I&amp;rsquo;ve periodically considered buying wooden recorders, but to get some of clearly higher quality than the plastic ones is expensive!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-bother-with-renaissance&#34;&gt;Why bother with Renaissance?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I jumped at the opportunity to bid in the auction for these two Renaissance recorders to acquire them inexpensively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Up till recently, I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t have considered buying Renaissance recorders at all, because of the difference in construction and tonal quality from the Baroque-style recorders that I have and that we play in the Pittsburgh Recorder Society meetings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this summer at the Mideast early music workshop, I paid attention to people playing Renaissance recorders (for Renaissance music and other music too) and found the louder and &amp;ldquo;reedier&amp;rdquo; sound intriguing. I could see myself playing them in contexts in which this kind of sound quality would be advantageous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So now I have these two wooden recorders to play with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that the solo soprano recorder music by Jacob van Eyck from the Renaissance that &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/28/my-first-appearance-on-a-music-recital-program/&#34;&gt;I played last year&lt;/a&gt; would have entirely been suited to my new soprano Renaissance recorder! I may revisit that music to play it on the new instrument.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Chatham Baroque: The Pleasures of Purcell</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/05/12/chatham-baroque-the-pleasures-of-purcell/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 May 2013 23:55:23 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/05/12/chatham-baroque-the-pleasures-of-purcell/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;It was a little crazy, but right after I came home from a mega-long &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/05/12/my-rachel-carson-trail-hike-for-the-year/&#34;&gt;Rachel Carson Trail hike today&lt;/a&gt;, I rushed to shower and change and run over to a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.chathambaroque.org/events/pleasures-purcell&#34;&gt;special concert, &amp;ldquo;The Pleasures of Purcell&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; by the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.chathambaroque.org/&#34;&gt;Chatham Baroque&lt;/a&gt; at the local &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.redeemerpittsburgh.org/&#34;&gt;Church of the Redeemer&lt;/a&gt; in the Squirrel Hill neighborhood. Objectively, I should have just called it a day after the hike, but I love the Chatham Baroque and learning from Annie earlier that they were playing in the neighborhood just several blocks from where I live made me decide to hop over there. (The concert was free to the public, but welcomed donations, of course: please remember to contribute generously when you attend these kinds of community good will events!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I attended in part because the musical genre was basically new to me: choral music by Henry Purcell. This is not my kind of thing, but I&amp;rsquo;m old enough that I&amp;rsquo;ve gotten tired of only listening to &amp;ldquo;my kind of thing&amp;rdquo; rather than exploring what is new to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ran into Annie as I was limping my way toward the church with sore feet. I also noticed that Sam from the Pittsburgh Recorder Society was a guest performer for some of the music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-concert&#34;&gt;The concert&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Chatham Baroque was joined by a choir and solo vocalists and conductor to fill out the forces needed to perform the music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was completely wowed by the bass soloist. The depth and expression of his voice was amazing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for the music itself, I&amp;rsquo;ve already confessed that mostly sacred choral music from this time period is not really my thing. I didn&amp;rsquo;t change my mind, although I was glad to have given it a shot. I have enjoyed playing the instrumental music of Henry Purcell for recorder, but this music for the English court didn&amp;rsquo;t do much for me.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Another exciting concert at Bar Marco: Chris Norman and the Chatham Baroque playing a tasty assortment of dynamic music</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/02/28/another-exciting-concert-at-bar-marco-chris-norman-and-the-chatham-baroque-playing-a-tasty-assortment-of-dynamic-music/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Feb 2013 23:47:52 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/02/28/another-exciting-concert-at-bar-marco-chris-norman-and-the-chatham-baroque-playing-a-tasty-assortment-of-dynamic-music/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Just this week, Annie of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/PittsburghRecorderSociety&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Recorder Society&lt;/a&gt; sent out email reminding us of upcoming musical performances of interest, including some by the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.chathambaroque.org/&#34;&gt;Chatham Baroque&lt;/a&gt; joined by visiting &lt;a href=&#34;http://chrisnorman.com/&#34;&gt;Chris Norman&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://chrisnorman.com/images/home_feature.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Chris Norman&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When I heard that Chris Norman was coming, I frantically started rethinking my schedule for the week, because I really wanted to see him playing his wooden flutes. He has been one of my primary musical heroes since I first encountered him at a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/04/21/my-first-time-in-a-public-music-jam-intense-fun-with-chris-norman-and-david-greenberg/&#34;&gt;public music jam session last year&lt;/a&gt; sponsored by the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rbsp.org/&#34;&gt;Renaissance and Baroque of Pittsburgh&lt;/a&gt;. That day was one of the most important days of my life, which I will never forget, because not only did I see and hear a real master, but also was encouraged to participate myself in playing music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve always also been a big fan of Chatham Baroque, for their lively, alert performances of the standard repertoire as well as &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/10/04/chatham-baroque-thoughts-on-playing-new-non-baroque-music-on-baroque-instruments/&#34;&gt;new collaborations and projects&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I managed to attend one of this week&amp;rsquo;s concerts, and I was not disappointed!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-i-rarely-attend-concerts&#34;&gt;Why I rarely attend concerts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, a reminder: nowadays, I rarely attend concerts (or even listen to recorded music). &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/02/i-love-music-but-rarely-listen-to-it-now/&#34;&gt;I explained why over a year ago&lt;/a&gt;: time is limited (on weekdays and particularly on weekends). Furthermore, when I do attend concerts, I am much pickier about what I attend, because when I think about it, in the past I have often been disappointed by concerts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;bar-marco-and-nature-of-music-venues&#34;&gt;Bar Marco and nature of music venues&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing I came to realize is that the standard &amp;ldquo;classical music&amp;rdquo; concert is not to my taste. First of all, the programs tend to be very long, such as two hours with an intermission, which, frankly, taxes both my attention span as well as takes up an entire block of time in an evening. Second, and most important actually, is that there is a sense of &amp;ldquo;distance&amp;rdquo; and even formality in the standard concert. This is reinforced by certain choices of clothing and demeanor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: I&amp;rsquo;m speaking as one who did not grow up in &amp;ldquo;classical music&amp;rdquo; culture, but only really discovered and fell in love with Western art music upon &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/10/rip-charles-rosen/&#34;&gt;attending college&lt;/a&gt;. So there have always been things about the culture that initially struck me as strange, and are probably at least partially responsible for the relative lack of popularity of the music among younger people (just peek into the average classical music concert hall and you&amp;rsquo;ll see geezers and middle-aged people).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I rather enjoyed the use of Bar Marco last fall as non-traditional music venue, where &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/11/14/classical-revolution-pittsburghs-aquitango-delivers-passionate-traditional-tango/&#34;&gt;I saw AquiTango performing, and sat up close&lt;/a&gt; and enjoyed the relative intimacy and informality of the occasion. Not only that, but from a technical, performance point of view (now that I play music myself), it is extremely educational for me to be up front seeing what the musicians do and relating to it and learning from it, whether it&amp;rsquo;s cues and signals among them or details of physical technique. This is stuff you can&amp;rsquo;t get sitting far away in a big concert hall, and you certainly can&amp;rsquo;t get at all from audio recordings or even videos really. You have to be there, anticipating, thinking actively, hearing the breaths, seeing the faces, in real time. Music is not just sound, not just wave forms or digital bits. It&amp;rsquo;s a live, active creation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I jumped at the opportunity to see &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.showclix.com/event/3745641&#34;&gt;Chris Norman and Chatham Baroque also at Bar Marco&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This venue has its limitations, of course. Primarily, the bar downstairs is very noisy, and it would be nice if there were a barrier to avoid the noise and music blasting downstairs from so easily being heard upstairs. That said, for the most part I wasn&amp;rsquo;t too bothered by the noise, because I sat up front very near the musicians, and so when they were playing, I didn&amp;rsquo;t hear the noise. But in moments of dead silence the distraction was real. I would suggest putting up a temporary barrier at the stairway during performances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-music&#34;&gt;The music&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A single hour of musical selections was presented (a good length for me; as I mentioned earlier, two hours is a very long time).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;scottish-baroque-james-osvald&#34;&gt;Scottish Baroque: James Osvald&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The concert started out with a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scottish_Baroque_music&#34;&gt;Scottish Baroque&lt;/a&gt; sonata by &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_Oswald_%28composer%29&#34;&gt;James Osvald&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was interested to actually see Scottish Baroque music being performed live because up till now, I had only &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/08/finally-performing-some-sonatas-for-baroque-flute/&#34;&gt;played it without listening to it, through a &amp;ldquo;Baroque Around the World&amp;rdquo; series of books&lt;/a&gt;. And I had played it on flute, even though the music was clearly geared toward violin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;instruments&#34;&gt;Instruments&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chris played the same keyed wooden &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.oldflutes.com/classical.htm&#34;&gt;classical flute&lt;/a&gt; for the most part through the concert, although in the slow movement of just this sonata he switched to a deeper alto flute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout the concert, Andrew Fouts played Baroque violin, while Patrician Halverson played different sizes of viola da gamba, and Scott Pauley played theorbo as well as a banjo and a Baroque guitar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;no-program-notes&#34;&gt;No program notes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were no program notes for this concert, by the way: &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/11/on-not-reading-concert-program-notes/&#34;&gt;just how I like it&lt;/a&gt;! Instead, Chris introduced each piece before he and Chatham Baroque performed it. I liked how he added colorful and humorous touches to his brief introductions. &lt;em&gt;All concerts should work this way&lt;/em&gt;. Long program notes are as pointless, in my opinion, as voluminous printed slides at a lecture: they are only a distraction from the presentation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;american-old-time-music&#34;&gt;American old-time music&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then they switched things up and played some American &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Old-time_music&#34;&gt;old-time music&lt;/a&gt;, including &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Man_of_Constant_Sorrow&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Man of Constant Sorrow&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. It was interesting hearing Baroque instruments used for this kind of music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chris was really in his element playing this folk music. He became very expressive and walked around and stamped his feet. You can&amp;rsquo;t experience this kind of concentration and passion just sitting at home listening to some CD or music file: you had to be there, up front! This is what I want to live when I attend a concert.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;back-to-scottish-baroque-william-mcgibbon&#34;&gt;Back to Scottish Baroque: William McGibbon&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another name familiar to me (because of having played on flute one of his sonatas) came up, the Scottish Baroque composer &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/William_McGibbon&#34;&gt;William McGibbon&lt;/a&gt;. Apparently the composer was inspired by the Italian style and incorporated into his piece, a sonata in the style of Corelli. I think it&amp;rsquo;s important to remember that even back in the 18th century, musicians were eager to learn from their counterparts in remote places in the world. Think of how much effort it took to visit or get word of what was going on in Italy, from Scotland!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;maritime-canada&#34;&gt;Maritime Canada&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then we entered the world of Chris&amp;rsquo;s own heritage: he is from &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Music_of_the_Maritimes&#34;&gt;Maritime Canada&lt;/a&gt;. He did some singing in French as well as flute playing. It was the first time I had ever heard him sing, and it sounded similar to Cajun singing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;back-to-osvald&#34;&gt;Back to Osvald&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then we returned to Osvald, for the &amp;ldquo;Hawthorn&amp;rdquo; sonata. I was very curious to hear this because I had never heard it played, but had &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/08/finally-performing-some-sonatas-for-baroque-flute/&#34;&gt;played it myself on Baroque flute with Henry on piano&lt;/a&gt;, and run into problems because it was clearly meant for violin, given the crazy fast jig movement at the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that Chris took a break and sat out most of this sonata, ha! I enjoyed the opportunity to observe how Andrew on Baroque violin would play the first movement, to compare his style and choice of ornamentations with what I&amp;rsquo;ve done myself. He played it rather differently than how I play it. This is one of the fascinating things I like about Baroque music: there is a good deal of personal choice in how we feel and interpret it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To my amusement, Chris did come in for the brief but crazy fast jig that was the third movement, showing off his triple-tonguing chops on flute. Whew!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;scottish-smallpipes&#34;&gt;Scottish smallpipes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We ended with Chris pulling out his &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scottish_smallpipes&#34;&gt;Scottish smallpipes&lt;/a&gt; and playing on them. I had never seen this instrument before and was fascinated. In contrast to mouth-blown bagpipes, these are played with the arms only. A vigorous conclusion to the concert!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;afterwards&#34;&gt;Afterwards&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I chatted with Chris Norman a little afterwards. He seemed to recognize me from the jam session a year ago; that surprised me since I was just some quiet guy in the crowd who was still quite a beginner and didn&amp;rsquo;t play all that much. Anyway, I told him I was inspired by that jam session to not only play more traditional music of the kind that he plays (I got into Irish and French, buying myself an &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/irish-flute/&#34;&gt;Irish flute&lt;/a&gt;), but also improving my technique considerably on &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/baroque-flute/&#34;&gt;Baroque flute&lt;/a&gt;. I asked him about his new work on making wooden flutes; I thought it was really cool that he not only plays them, but now makes them too, and why not, if you&amp;rsquo;re interested in the engineering aspects of creating the kind of sounds you want? This utter physicality of (non-digital) music is something that I&amp;rsquo;ve come to particularly appreciate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a really great time at the concert at Bar Marco by Chris Norman and Chatham Baroque. I left inspired again to continue my own music-making and improve on it and incorporate my own personality into it, the way these fine musicians do. It was an hour well-spent.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Chatham Baroque: thoughts on playing new non-Baroque music on Baroque instruments</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/10/04/chatham-baroque-thoughts-on-playing-new-non-baroque-music-on-baroque-instruments/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Oct 2012 23:21:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/10/04/chatham-baroque-thoughts-on-playing-new-non-baroque-music-on-baroque-instruments/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.chathambaroque.org/sites/default/files/coverimages/DSC_0070.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Chatham Baroque press photo&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Today I went to the weekly CMU music convocation, which featured the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.chathambaroque.org/&#34;&gt;Chatham Baroque&lt;/a&gt;. They provided some interesting discussions and performances of musical excerpts of newly commissioned works as a preview before their &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.chathambaroque.org/events/baroque-reframed&#34;&gt;official premiere tomorrow&lt;/a&gt; in Pittsburgh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might be thinking, &amp;ldquo;Wait a second, &lt;em&gt;newly commissioned works&lt;/em&gt; for a Baroque ensemble playing Baroque instruments?&amp;rdquo; Does this mean some derivative, neo-Baroque stuff?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer is &lt;strong&gt;no&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-would-one-want-to-play-newly-composed-music-on-old-instruments&#34;&gt;Why would one want to play newly composed music on old instruments?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Superficially, one might wonder about the point of playing newly composed music on old instruments. But then one realizes that every instrument is an &amp;ldquo;old&amp;rdquo; instrument. The &amp;ldquo;modern&amp;rdquo; piano as we know it has been around for well over a century; it is an &amp;ldquo;old&amp;rdquo; instrument! By now, even the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Electric_guitar&#34;&gt;electric guitar&lt;/a&gt; is 81 years old. It&amp;rsquo;s an ancient instrument. Nobody thinks twice about writing new music for or playing music for the electric guitar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each instrument, no matter how old or new it is, presents unique sonorities and possibilities and technical challenges. There&amp;rsquo;s no reason not to explore new ways of exploiting and appreciating Baroque instruments in the service of fascinating new music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;three-composers&#34;&gt;Three composers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The three composers whose works we got a preview of were Moon Young Ha, Matthew McBane, and Lansing McLoskey. Each of them gave a brief introduction and talked about why they decided to write for the Chatham Baroque ensemble of violin, viola da gamba, and theorbo, and what they tried to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed the Andrew, Patricia, and Scott perform excerpts of the composers&amp;rsquo; pieces. None of them were imitative neo-Baroque pieces and they were intriguing, each in a completely different way, different harmonic and rhythmic languages and emphases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it&amp;rsquo;s great that Chatham Baroque is expanding beyond the Baroque in their musical explorations. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.chathambaroque.org/events&#34;&gt;Coming up in their concert season&lt;/a&gt;, they will be performing with some traditional Appalachian vocalists and instrumentalists. That should be interesting!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;one-limitation&#34;&gt;One limitation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While enjoying the previews of the new pieces, I couldn&amp;rsquo;t help thinking back to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburghmusicalliance.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Music Alliance&lt;/a&gt; season launch party that Abby and I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/20/my-first-bobblehead-doll-guess-who/&#34;&gt;attended recently&lt;/a&gt;. There, Chatham Baroque performed some music, but we could barely hear any of the instruments. At best, I could hear a bit of Andrew on Baroque violin, while the viola da gamba and theorbo were rather drowned out by the party noise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think a real limitation of the Baroque instruments is that they are relatively quiet and subtle. I found this a problem myself when trying to play Baroque flute in &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/28/another-french-music-jam-also-announcing-cats-dance/&#34;&gt;casual musical jam or party performance situations&lt;/a&gt;. In a quiet and intimate space, they work beautifully. But in a noisy, crowded world, they do not. That is my impression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just because you play a Baroque instrument doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean you have to be stuck only playing Baroque music or neo-Baroque music. The world is wide open, constrained only by taste and acoustic realities.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The passion of Bach&#39;s Air on the G String: three very different interpretations</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/09/14/passion-of-bachs-air-on-the-g-string-three-different-interpretations/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Sep 2012 06:45:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/09/14/passion-of-bachs-air-on-the-g-string-three-different-interpretations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, while driving home from work, I had my radio on, tuned to Pittsburgh&amp;rsquo;s classical music station, &lt;a href=&#34;http://wqed.org/fm&#34;&gt;WQED FM&lt;/a&gt;, as usual, and I immediately recognized the piece that was being performed. I listened with curiosity and then anger and disappointment as I made my way home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a movement from one of Johann Sebastian Bach&amp;rsquo;s orchestra suites
(Orchestral Suite No. 3 in D major, BWV 1068), the movement that has been popularized in the form of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Air_on_the_G_String&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Air on the G String&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think this piece is a good litmus test of how we perceive and appreciate Baroque music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2015-06-10&#34;&gt;(Update of 2015-06-10)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many readers have commented on this post, and therefore I have written
an &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2015/06/10/revisiting-bachs-air-on-g-string-from-a-singing-and-dancing-viewpoint/&#34;&gt;important sequel&lt;/a&gt; to this post, 3 years later!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-listening-test&#34;&gt;A listening test&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please click around on the YouTube videos to get a taste of different ways of performing the Air from Bach&amp;rsquo;s suite. I&amp;rsquo;ve embedded three very different interpretations, each with its own qualities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Which do you like most of the three?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Which do you dislike most of the three?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People can get very emotional about differences in musical taste, and I&amp;rsquo;m not here to start an argument (just look at any of the comment threads on YouTube videos and you see what I mean!), but rather a discussion. I recognize that your choices might be &lt;em&gt;completely different&lt;/em&gt; from mine, and I&amp;rsquo;m &lt;em&gt;completely OK&lt;/em&gt; with that, and hope that you might be &lt;em&gt;completely OK&lt;/em&gt; with my choices also!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/e2OoJamNLMQ&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/SZ6nS1wau0I&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/VEpCjxOJgms&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;objective-comparisons&#34;&gt;Objective comparisons&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;stokowski&#34;&gt;Stokowski&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first version is an arrangement by Leopold Stokowski, from maybe the 1950s. It is a very slow, richly scored, melodically oriented version with emphasis on a deep, swelling vibrato-filled string sound. Different lines are given emphasis, one after another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;croatian-baroque-ensemble&#34;&gt;Croatian Baroque Ensemble&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second version is a live performance from 2010 by the Croatian Baroque Ensemble. It is played on period instruments, very briskly, with a prominent harpsichord continuo, with minimal vibrato in the strings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;karajan&#34;&gt;Karajan&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third version is from a recording by Herbert von Karajan and the Berlin Philharmonic, from maybe the 1980s. It is marked by a blend of legato voices, with an emphasis on unified beautiful tone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-your-preference-means&#34;&gt;What your preference means&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, I would like to point out that of these three versions, although I have a clear personal ranking, there are many things I don&amp;rsquo;t like about my favorite version of the three. If I were setting up a performance of this piece, I would make many different interpretive choices. Therefore, my indication of my preference is not an endorsement of every element of my preferred version.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The style classification system I&amp;rsquo;m using here is directly taken from the fascinating book by &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bruce_Haynes&#34;&gt;Bruce Haynes&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.oup.com/us/catalog/general/subject/Music/MusicHistoryWestern/EarlyMusicMedievalRenaissance/~~/dmlldz11c2EmY2k9OTc4MDE5NTE4OTg3Mg==&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The End of Early Music&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. In fact, the Air from the G String is used as an example in his book. My observations and descriptions here, however, are my own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;stokowski-the-romantic-style&#34;&gt;Stokowski: the Romantic style&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you liked the Stokowski best, you favor the old-fashioned Romantic style, music played with a long heart-throbbing melodic line and rich accompaniment. Soulful cellos are your thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you dislike, you have a problem with odd composer-unintended arrangements, super-slow sentimentality, and personal idiosyncrasies such as slowing down to savor a particular romantic moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;croatian-baroque-ensemble-the-period-style&#34;&gt;Croatian Baroque Ensemble: the Period style&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you like the Croatian Baroque Ensemble best, you favor a quick rhythm and counterpoint, with an emphasis on dissonance, as the carrier of heightened emotion. You like music to be played as though spoken, with many separated phrases, as though question and answer pairs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you dislike, you don&amp;rsquo;t like the rougher sound of non-vibrato violins, the dissonant attacks, and most of all, the speed and detachment of phrases that removes the relaxing, romantic mood you prefer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;karajan-the-modern-style&#34;&gt;Karajan: the Modern style&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you like Karajan, you focus on clear, beautiful tone, and seamless integration of instruments, avoidance of roughness and imperfection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you dislike, you find the endless legato lifeless and missing the extra edge of passion, and you perceive that the emphasis on integration detracts from the clarity of individual voices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-preferences&#34;&gt;My preferences&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I prefer the Period approach of the Croatian Baroque Ensemble. I find it the most poignant and passionate of the three selections. I like the pauses of silence, the emphasis and swelling into the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bach.org/bach101/instrumental/3rd_suite_orch_bwv1068.html&#34;&gt;dissonant moments&lt;/a&gt;. The tempo is fast enough that the phrases feel like speaking and breathing. This is the Bach I have fallen in love with and have been enjoying playing myself in the past two years on &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/recorder/&#34;&gt;recorder&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/baroque-flute/&#34;&gt;Baroque flute&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, I have an honest, real emotional response to the Romantic approach of Stokowski, however perverse and bizarre it may be. It&amp;rsquo;s clearly nothing resembling what Bach would have expected in a performance. But on its own, it&amp;rsquo;s an ingenious product of Stokowski&amp;rsquo;s personal vision. You could say that Stokowski stole Bach&amp;rsquo;s notes and then composed his own thing using them as a starting point, changing everything else (from instrumentation to tempo to dynamics to articulation). I respect that. So even though part of me is horrified by this kind of plagiarism, part of me is also excited and wish that more of this perverse creativity would happen today. The Romantic approach went out of style decades ago, however, in favor of the Modern approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, the Modern approach basically leaves me cold. Yes, the Karajan version was the one I heard in my car while driving home from work. I felt angry and sad by how the performance did not really inspire me. It was boring and muddy to me. Karajan may have been playing the pitch values of the notes the way Bach wrote them down, and not &amp;ldquo;disrespectfully&amp;rdquo; messed with the elements that Stokowski eagerly transformed and added to, but to me, his performance was more of a boring lecture to sit through than something that made me sit up and engage with the music. &lt;em&gt;It was muzak to me.&lt;/em&gt; That was my reaction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;period-contrast-ton-koopman-with-amsterdam-baroque-orchestra&#34;&gt;Period contrast: Ton Koopman with Amsterdam Baroque Orchestra&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I mentioned earlier that there are many things I would do differently than the Croation Baroque Ensemble. The Period approach, like the Romantic and Modern ones, is not a single interpretation: it&amp;rsquo;s an entire approach with much diversity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a live performance in Period style that is noticeably different from the Croatian Baroque Ensemble performance. It is slower and sweeter, for example. But it also has more contrast between the long legato lines and the detached figures within them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/NlT8yeEYbMs&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;which-do-i-like-better&#34;&gt;Which do I like better?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of the two sample Period performances, which do I prefer?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Who knows??&lt;/em&gt; When there are things I like and dislike about both? At some point (I try to make this quick), I stop being a listener or critic, and feel the need to &lt;em&gt;stop listening&lt;/em&gt;, and go to work &lt;em&gt;myself&lt;/em&gt; on how I would do things very differently, from anyone else, as a performer, to express my personal feeling for the music. That is why I&amp;rsquo;ve switched in the past two years from being a listener to being a performer. I can&amp;rsquo;t sit around pining away waiting from someone to play something the way I really like it. I have to do the work myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope this little exercise is helpful in clarifying some of the differences in the approach to performing and enjoying Baroque era music. The question of how to best deal with music from the 1700s is one that everyone who plays or listens to it has to grapple with, whether implicitly or explicitly. I think Haynes&amp;rsquo; basic framework of three different styles is a useful one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Myself, in the past year or two during which I have suddenly fallen in love with Baroque music, after a lifetime of not really liking it at all, I have been persuaded by the Period approach, both as a listener and now also as a performer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2015-06-10-1&#34;&gt;(Update of 2015-06-10)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many readers have commented on this post, and therefore I have written
an &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2015/06/10/revisiting-bachs-air-on-g-string-from-a-singing-and-dancing-viewpoint/&#34;&gt;important sequel&lt;/a&gt; to this post, 3 years later!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My first appearance on a music recital program</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/07/28/my-first-appearance-on-a-music-recital-program/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Jul 2012 23:41:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/07/28/my-first-appearance-on-a-music-recital-program/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-ars-recital-summer-2012.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Pittsburgh Recorder Society spring 2012 recital program&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A month and a half ago, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/06/15/preparing-for-my-first-solo-flute-performance-notes-on-perfectionism-and-high-standards/&#34;&gt;I reported on an upcoming music recital I was going to perform in&lt;/a&gt;. In fact, I did perform, on Sunday, June 17, 2012. &lt;em&gt;It was my first appearance in my life on a musical recital program, and my first time solo on modern flute.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The event was an informal spring dinner party/recital at Helen&amp;rsquo;s home for the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.andrew.cmu.edu/user/lukas/pcars/Welcome.html&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh chapter of the American Recorder Society&lt;/a&gt;. (By the way, we also have a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/PittsburghRecorderSociety&#34;&gt;Facebook page&lt;/a&gt; now.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why did I put myself on the spot, by volunteering to play, and what did I choose to play?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-recital-program&#34;&gt;The recital program&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The program had several of us perform a dozen musical selections in a variety combinations (also performing at the end but not listed on the program were Mike and Fred).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(This year, Abby had submitted for the program a piece for Bulgarian tambura, &amp;ldquo;Ihtimansko Horo&amp;rdquo;, and this is on the printed program, but at the last minute, she had problems as a result of restringing her instrument during the week, and ended up not performing, unfortunately.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Myself, I had chosen three musical selections to play:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Doen Daphne D&amp;rsquo;over Schoone Maeght&amp;rdquo; from Jacob Van Eyck&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Der Fluyten Lust-Hof&amp;rdquo;; solo soprano recorder&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lachlann Dubh (Scottish slow air); Baroque flute&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;II. Allegro from C.P.E. Bach&amp;rsquo;s sonata in A minor for solo flute, Wq 132; modern flute&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;background-why-i-played&#34;&gt;Background: why I played&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;last-year-s-party-recital&#34;&gt;Last year&amp;rsquo;s party/recital&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I only started playing recorder and joining the Pittsburgh Recorder Society just over a year ago. After I had only spent a couple of months playing alto recorder (and therefore being at a total beginner level), Helen held her party/recital on June 19, 2011, and invited people to volunteer to play. I was, of course, not ready to prepare anything I felt interesting enough to perform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, it did not even occur to me at the time that I would perform at all any time soon. But in fact, in addition to the prepared performances by several of the people, we also ended up playing something in a large group that we had worked on at the monthly meeting of the Pittsburgh Recorder Society. Even in such casual circumstances, I found myself almost paralyzed with anxiety, sitting there while Abby and other people sat and watched us play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It should be noted that at this point in my life last year, &lt;em&gt;I had not played music in front of a sitting audience in decades&lt;/em&gt;, and never with any seriousness; I was thirteen when I was last stumbling around playing in marching band with no enthusiasm and just an anonymous figure in a crowd:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/lamphere-high-marching-band.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin in Lamphere High School marching band uniform&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I survived playing casually in the group, as Abby watched and took photos that day:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-ars-recital-summer-2011/group.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Pittsburgh Recorder Society group performing at summer 2011 recital&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I have to confess that I was actually shaking and hyperventilating at times, messing up my breathing. It all seems so silly now, but that&amp;rsquo;s how it was. We do what we need to do, eventually become less sensitive, and move on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;setting-a-goal-and-deadline&#34;&gt;Setting a goal and deadline&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t tell anyone that June day last year, but after going home, I made a solemn vow to myself: I was going to spend the entire following year practicing recorder seriously and effectively, in order to be able to prepare something to play at the next party/recital. I had no idea what I was going to play, because the first step was simply to continue improving using some recorder method books, before actually trying to learn a real piece. My goal was to have something substantial to play, to display how much I had learned and improved. (And not shake with anxiety.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-i-chose-the-selections-i-played-this-year&#34;&gt;Why I chose the selections I played this year&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;which-instrument-s&#34;&gt;Which instrument(s)?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that in a single year, I had not only improved at alto recorder, but had also learned soprano recorder. I had also bought a tenor recorder and begun playing it (same fingerings as soprano recorder). And by fall last year, I had also &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/03/my-new-bass-and-sopranino-recorders-and-having-fun/&#34;&gt;bought a bass recorder&lt;/a&gt; and begun playing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Completely unexpectedly, in November I had begun &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/09/taking-up-flute-again-after-decades/&#34;&gt;trying to play modern flute again&lt;/a&gt;. Even more unexpectedly, later I also &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/30/bought-a-baroque-flute/&#34;&gt;decided to take up the Baroque flute&lt;/a&gt;, after having explained &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/17/flute-versus-recorder/&#34;&gt;why I had no plan to try Baroque flute anytime soon&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I also started playing the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/11/learning-another-instrument-the-tin-whistle/&#34;&gt;Irish tin whistle&lt;/a&gt;. It has been quite a year of music for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what instruments and music was I going to play for the recital at Helen&amp;rsquo;s?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-answer-play-three-of-my-instruments&#34;&gt;The answer: play three of my instruments&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided that I would pick three fairly short music selections and play them on three different instruments as appropriate for the music&amp;rsquo;s style and period. Also, to simply my preparation, I looked for music I could play alone rather than, say, requiring a keyboard accompaniment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;late-renaissance-or-early-baroque-1650s&#34;&gt;Late Renaissance or early Baroque (1650s?)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I chose to play a selection from Van Eyck to show off the soprano recorder. Actually, I had played this selection for an audience before (a blog post about that life-changing experience, a &amp;ldquo;Baroque jam session&amp;rdquo;, on Friday, April 27, is still to be written). It was by pure accident that I came across Van Eyck&amp;rsquo;s music to play; I had found the score in the Carnegie Library of Pittsburgh&amp;rsquo;s catalog while looking for any recorder music at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A personal reason I wanted to play this was that I had not heard any interpretation that I really liked, from CDs or YouTube. Therefore, I wanted to fill a hole and try to play the music the way I felt it. This is the fundamental reason I have been playing music rather than just listening to others do it: self-expression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;update-of-2012-10-30&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-10-30)&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is the finally published post about the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/04/27/baroque-jam-session-at-cmu/&#34;&gt;Baroque jam session&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;traditional-scottish-air-1700s&#34;&gt;Traditional Scottish air (1700s?)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Baroque flute seemed appropriate to play this slow song. It could have used accompaniment, but I added it to the program too late to have someone accompany me on harp or mandolin or something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was a little hesitant to play the Baroque flute in public, because I had only really started playing it, and was clearly in need of serious improvement (in fact, it has been my main instrument of focus in the past month), but I thought I might as well put in a two-minute song for variety&amp;rsquo;s sake, and as a baseline since I had already decided that next year, I want to play the Baroque flute again at the 2013 party/recital, and much better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;late-baroque-or-pre-classical-1750s&#34;&gt;Late Baroque or pre-Classical (1750s?)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The CPE Bach sonata I had fallen in love with hearing it by accident on modern flute performed by &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/22/james-galway-made-me-hate-flute/&#34;&gt;Emmanuel Pahud&lt;/a&gt; when I was browsing YouTube one day for solo flute material. After hearing it, I vowed that one day I would play the whole thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I chose what seemed to be the easiest movement to focus on, and practiced it on modern flute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is, of course, a question of which flute is best suited for this music. Given the period, perhaps a simple system keyed wooden flute? But I don&amp;rsquo;t have one, and currently have no intention of getting one or learning to play it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would be possible to play it on a Baroque flute, but much more difficult. When I get better at Baroque flute, I just might consider playing CPE Bach on it, but I feel that the modern flute is not inappropriate for this music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-i-fared&#34;&gt;How I fared&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, I played. I got nervous, I made various errors I did not make in practice, I made errors that I made in practice, but I actually did manage to go up alone and play. I can&amp;rsquo;t pretend that I played very well (in fact, now, over a month later, I could play each of these selections noticeably better than I did), but I did what I could at the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, since Abby&amp;rsquo;s parents came to the party/recital this year, this was also the first time they ever saw me perform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was considerably less nervous than a year ago, but still more nervous than I really need to be. So next year, 2013, I expect to be more seasoned and more performance-ready.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After we all played, we enjoyed the potluck dinner and had a good time. What else could I ask for, an evening of music, food, and friends?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Sorry, I have no photos or videos of any of the activities. I was too busy experiencing rather than spectating, and I don&amp;rsquo;t think anyone actually took any photos or videos.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Pittsburgh Recorder Society spring potluck/recital means a lot to me because it was there last year that I continued to get to know the members, after having just joined, met new people, heard people play, and got the idea that I too could perform, if I worked at improving. I set some goals, was happy that Abby and her parents came along to see me perform, and the experience renewed my commitment to continuing to play and improve in the Pittsburgh Recorder Society group as well as on my own on Baroque flute and modern flute. I have every intention of having even more fun in my upcoming year of music!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Baroque jam session at CMU: first time my parents ever watched me perform music</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/04/27/baroque-jam-session-at-cmu/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Apr 2012 23:20:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/04/27/baroque-jam-session-at-cmu/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Three days ago, I suddenly saw this poster on a bulletin board in the hallway at work at CMU:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/baroque-jam-session/poster.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;CMU poster for Baroque jam session&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;
A night of music by some of these cool dead dudes.

A chance to hear CMU School of Music majors do their thing, 18th Century style.

An opportunity to bring your own instrument &amp; play along.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought to myself, I have to go to this event, even at short notice!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also experienced terror at the thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I went, and survived. It was a &lt;em&gt;life-changing&lt;/em&gt; experience for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;contact&#34;&gt;Contact&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I noticed that the contact person on the poster, Maria, was someone I had just recently seen a couple of days ago, at the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/04/21/my-first-time-in-a-public-music-jam-intense-fun-with-chris-norman-and-david-greenberg/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Renaissance and Baroque jam session by Chris Norman and David Greenberg&lt;/a&gt;. She was the Baroque oboist, student at CMU, who had been something of a center of attention during the session, because of her having a Baroque-tuned instrument rather than a modern-tuned one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I wrote Maria asking her if I could come play, and she said OK. She said the format was not a real jam session, but that it would be people bring stuff to play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;logistics&#34;&gt;Logistics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a complication: my parents were scheduled to drive in to visit me and Abby and stay for tonight. This meant that we had to clean up at home in preparation for their visit, make dinner, etc. If I was going to this Baroque music jam session, then it was going to be a hectic day. I figured that we could all attend together, and then my parents would actually finally see me play music in public, &lt;em&gt;for the first time in my life&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seriously: back when I was in elementary school and middle school and high school and piddled around without enthusiasm on the flute, they were similarly unenthusiastic and didn&amp;rsquo;t go around coming to my band concerts and applauding me or whatever. I don&amp;rsquo;t actually remember their presence at all; maybe my mother dropped me off or something and came back, when I needed any aid at all. I remember thinking the detachment odd because I had classmates whose parents hovered over their kids&amp;rsquo; music and sports involvement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;preparation&#34;&gt;Preparation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had to figure out what music to play. I couldn&amp;rsquo;t count necessarily on any accompanists. I quickly decided to work on something for solo recorder, and happened to recently have discovered a book of pieces for solo soprano recorder. I chose one set of theme and variations, &amp;ldquo;Doen Daphne D&amp;rsquo;over Schoone Maeght&amp;rdquo; from Jacob Van Eyck&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Der Fluyten Lust-Hof&amp;rdquo;, to work on. This music is earlier than Baroque, strictly, but hey, I thought maybe it would be good to provide contrast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also wanted to play some Baroque music, so my attention immediately turned to Henry Holcombe&amp;rsquo;s Air in E minor that I had &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/30/bought-a-baroque-flute/&#34;&gt;discovered in a volume of &amp;ldquo;English Airs and Dances&amp;rdquo; half a year ago&lt;/a&gt; and immediately fallen in love with. I was not prepared at all to play this on a Baroque flute, so I decided to risk embarrassment by playing on a modern flute instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-event&#34;&gt;The event&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So Abby and I took my parents to the Skibo Coffeehouse at CMU where the event was happening. A lot of familiar faces were there; I&amp;rsquo;ve been going to CMU student music recitals lately, primarily of flute students, and therefore have been seeing some of the same faces of graduating students and their friends. So I was feeling very intimidated because these students are &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt;. I had seen and heard them doing their thing. I wondered whether I had made a huge mistake by coming to play. I checked in with Maria, then decided to sit around and watch for a while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that a lot of what happened was random sight reading, and also some people playing an instrument that wasn&amp;rsquo;t their primary instrument. In any case, it was all pretty casual and in fun, and a lot of mistakes were being made, so I felt much better about the prospect of eventually taking my turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were also people who had come just watch, either because they had seen the poster earlier or because they happened to be in Skibo for a meal and decided to hang out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My parents seemed to be enjoying their evening of entertainment. I explained to them that it wasn&amp;rsquo;t a concert, that these students were just having fun sight reading. They were impressed with the sight reading skill, and the voices of the young men and women who sang.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;my-turn&#34;&gt;My turn&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It started getting late, and Abby was very tired. She left to take a little walk to get some air.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point, Maria asked me whether I wanted to play something. I felt I had to go now, so I couldn&amp;rsquo;t wait for Abby to come back. I offered to play the Holcombe piece for flute, and asked if someone could play continuo, since I had a score with the figured bass. A cellist stepped up. But as I got on stage and prepared to play, we suddenly realized that I was playing a modern flute at modern pitch, while the cello was at Baroque tuning. I felt so embarrassed. Someone I had seen in recitals playing clarinet volunteered to play continuo on the digital keyboard (which of course could be set for any tuning), so we proceeded. I was so nervous that I somehow botched up some passages, but I tried to play what I felt, even if my technique and mental condition were not entirely up to it. And so we did it, including my on-the-fly ornamentation during the repeats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apparently Abby had returned to see that I was in the middle of performing, and she was upset to have missed me. I told her that it was OK, not a big deal. There would be plenty of future opportunities for her to see me perform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We listened to some more student performances, then it really was getting late, and my parents wanted to leave, because they had to drive next morning to my sister in DC. So I announced that I had one more piece to perform and then had to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I played the solo soprano recorder piece. I think the audience liked that, because it was so different from what had gone on all evening. I didn&amp;rsquo;t play it perfectly, but I felt much more relaxed and capable on recorder than on flute, and I enjoyed hearing my ringing sound in the space of Skibo, with its very high ceilings. I thought I did pretty well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I packed up and we went home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was not only really my first time performing alone (in the recorder piece) in public, but also the first time my parents had seen me perform music, and the first time Abby had seen me do a solo. So it was a very special evening for me. I felt like, if I could accept myself playing among these much better musicians, despite my being nowhere as good (yet), I was going to continue to seek out all opportunities to share the music I love and feel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t know how to explain it, but working up the courage to participate in this Baroque jam session, and actually carrying through (despite almost chickening out by waiting until the evening was almost over), meant a lot to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2012-07-28&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-07-28)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three months later, I ended up playing the Van Eyck piece in the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/28/my-first-appearance-on-a-music-recital-program/&#34;&gt;summer recital of the Pittsburgh recorder group&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2012-09-08&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-09-08)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It took me four months from this Baroque jam session before I performed Holcombe&amp;rsquo;s Air in E minor again anywhere, and &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/08/finally-performing-some-sonatas-for-baroque-flute/&#34;&gt;that time I finally played it on a Baroque flute&lt;/a&gt; rather than a modern flute!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2012-11-01&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-11-01)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My parents were visiting me and Abby yesterday for the first time since this Baroque jam six months ago. Yes, they were stopping by for the night to break up the long drive to visit my sister in DC again to see their &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/05/31/some-pretty-attacking-chess-at-a-party-last-weekend/&#34;&gt;baby grandson&lt;/a&gt; again and help out with care again for two weeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did some flute playing for them last night (on Irish flute, modern flute, and Baroque flute) and they seemed to enjoy the diversion. They still remembered how totally nervous I had been six months ago at the Baroque jam session and have been supportive of my musical activities of the past year. I am very grateful for that.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>