<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Exercise on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/exercise/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Exercise on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/exercise/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Why I have never considered using a treadmill desk</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/06/10/why-i-have-never-considered-using-a-treadmill-desk/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jun 2015 21:34:04 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/06/10/why-i-have-never-considered-using-a-treadmill-desk/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Ten years ago, in 2005, a friend of mine sent me an article about a
trend among some people to use a treadmill desk in order to squeeze in
some exercise while working. He seemed to think it sounded like a cool
idea that wouldn&amp;rsquo;t interfere much with work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have never considered using a treadmill desk. Because of a recent
article that seems to confirm my thoughts from a decade ago, I&amp;rsquo;m
posting my reaction here, along with a link to the article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-response-in-january-2005&#34;&gt;My response in January 2005&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At one point years ago I was thinking about stuff like that, but a few
experiments showed how pointless and soulless it is, for me.  My
enjoyment of exercise is completely ruined if extraneous stuff is
brought in, like reading or listening to music.  I learned that the
whole profound pleasure and meaning of physical activity comes from
being completely engaged in it, with nothing else on the mind.  So the
former fantasies of multitasking are now completely antithetical to my
current life values.

&lt;p&gt;
It&#39;s not the quantity [of treadmill movement] that&#39;s the issue.
That&#39;s still one foot per second of continuous movement, requiring
irrelevant constant muscular pulses.  Note that I cannot read a simple
newspaper in a car or a bus or a plane.

&lt;p&gt;
I fidget all the time, especially when playing chess, but the
movements are not arbitrary and disembodied, but are connected with
feelings of comfort or with emotional states relevant to my mental
processes.  It&#39;s not like a treadmill commanding me to go a foot every
second.  It&#39;s my personal choice when to shake my leg or shift my foot
or whatever, and for how long.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;philosophy-and-practice&#34;&gt;Philosophy and practice&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may be wondering, from how I phrased my reasons, whether I have a
primarily theoretical, ideological opposition to a treadmill desk, or
simply a pragmatic one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t really make a distinction: I take what works and doesn&amp;rsquo;t work
and make my observations a basis for a possibly more general
philosophy, rather than adopt an ideology and make my practice fit it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically, I actually have &lt;em&gt;tried&lt;/em&gt; multitasking in various ways for
the purpose of &amp;ldquo;saving time&amp;rdquo; and it just doesn&amp;rsquo;t work for
me. Furthermore, sometimes I multitask &lt;em&gt;despite knowing it doesn&amp;rsquo;t
work&lt;/em&gt;, and I pay the price. For example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I have tripped or fallen on runs or hikes when I &amp;ldquo;zoned out&amp;rdquo; and
wasn&amp;rsquo;t paying attention to the terrain but was thinking of something!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I have listened to music while reading a news article and failed to
follow the music at all.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s not saving time if I try to do two things and end up not even
doing one of them well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-research&#34;&gt;The research&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The article I just read was a news article,
&lt;a href=&#34;http://well.blogs.nytimes.com/2015/06/10/the-downside-of-treadmill-desks/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The downside of treadmill desks&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. I
was pretty shocked and amused to read, &amp;ldquo;&amp;hellip; surprisingly little
research had examined whether treadmill desks affect someone’s ability
to get work done.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The results, when the researchers compared the treadmill walkers with the people sitting at their desks, substantially favored sitting. The people who had walked during the testing performed worse on almost all aspects of thinking, including the ability to concentrate and remember, compared with those who had been seated.

&lt;p&gt;
And they were much worse at typing, being substantially slower and
more error prone than the sitting group.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The irony is that the researcher interviewed still wants to believe in
benefits:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
But even with that caveat, he said, he believes that the health
benefits of a treadmill desk should outweigh any declines in
productivity and, in fact, he plans to buy one for himself.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;alternatives&#34;&gt;Alternatives?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My alternative to sitting all day, which indeed is by now known to be
terrible for health, is simple:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get up now and then and take a break from my task and walk around.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But doesn&amp;rsquo;t this take time and stop the flow of work? Actually,
no. There&amp;rsquo;s only so much focus I can have while working on something
continuously without a break anyway. So forcing myself to take a walk
is actually a win-win situation, not even just a mere tradeoff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Treadmill desks do not appeal to me at all, and I believe I have sound
scientific reasons based on what psychology has learned about the
working of the human mind. However, I understand that different
people&amp;rsquo;s minds may work differently from mine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Have you used a treadmill desk? Why or why not? Do you believe in
your ability to multitask without a performance hit?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Report on my final day of Stoic Week 2014: the view from above</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/30/report-on-my-final-day-of-stoic-week-2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2014 22:16:07 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/30/report-on-my-final-day-of-stoic-week-2014/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s the seventh and final day of Stoic Week 2014! I am very glad I participated in the daily readings and reflections. I&amp;rsquo;ve made so many positive changes in my life already. Now it&amp;rsquo;s time to stick to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;health&#34;&gt;Health&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been spending all of the Thanksgiving long holiday weekend catching up on sleep. I have a meditation habit now and today it was warm out and I went for a run and ended up doing five miles in Frick Park. This is the longest distance I&amp;rsquo;ve run in months!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;nature-providence-the-larger-whole&#34;&gt;Nature, providence, the larger whole&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is fitting that today&amp;rsquo;s theme is the Stoic view of humanity as being embedded in something bigger, call it &amp;ldquo;nature&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;providence&amp;rdquo;. Part of why I enjoy running in the trails of Frick Park is that in its own small way, the experience puts me in touch &lt;em&gt;directly&lt;/em&gt; with something bigger than us; I encounter dogs, chipmunks, trees, creeks, leaves, mud, and even deer (not today, but Abby and I saw one during our hike there yesterday).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I honestly feel more whole and alive when I see more of nature, and not in some self-conscious sentimental way. It&amp;rsquo;s more subtle than that. And there&amp;rsquo;s nothing sentimental about those steep hills that make me gasp for air when I climb them. But I sure appreciate the cleaner air in the park than on the main urban roads of Pittsburgh! And I remember where air comes from and how fragile its quality and composition is. The big picture matters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am grateful for the organizers of Stoic Week for putting it on again this year. Here is something I&amp;rsquo;ve decided to do, to keep its spirit alive indefinitely: I will continue to explore various interpretations of Stoicism (note that I don&amp;rsquo;t feel compelled to buy into any particular school or even call myself a Stoic at all), as well as other philosophy (for example, the Zen I had begun looking into years ago) on a daily basis, to keep my mind always focused on applying principles of practical living.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Did you hear about Stoic Week this year? If you did, why did you choose to participate in it, or more interestingly, choose not to?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Report on my sixth day of Stoic Week 2014: preparing for adversity</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/29/report-on-my-sixth-day-of-stoic-week-2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Nov 2014 18:37:25 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/29/report-on-my-sixth-day-of-stoic-week-2014/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I guess death is the ultimate adversity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;whose-death-and-how-and-what-next&#34;&gt;Whose death and how and what next?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I fear death. Not only for myself, but for Abby, for her parents, for my parents, for our friends. We knew older people who have died even this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today&amp;rsquo;s Stoic theme, &amp;ldquo;preparing for adversity&amp;rdquo;, is particularly relevant to us because not only are our parents aging and already actively preparing for &amp;ldquo;what next&amp;rdquo; if they were to die or get sick and incapacitated, and trying to talk to us about such things, but also because being married, we need to have clear plans and instructions in case one of us suddenly goes. We are not invincible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;decluttering&#34;&gt;Decluttering&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing that makes us anxious is that there&amp;rsquo;s too much clutter in the house, and also clutter in the form of many random online accounts that we need to keep track of. We&amp;rsquo;ve seen how deaths in our families have caused a lot of trouble to survivors because of unfinished business, stuff left behind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel that part of preparing &lt;em&gt;mentally&lt;/em&gt; for adversity is preparing &lt;em&gt;in reality&lt;/em&gt; for adversity. I would have much more peace of mind if I knew that everything would continue as smoothly as possible at home and at work if I suddenly died.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So today I continued on a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/19/really-taking-up-the-challenge-of-minimalism/&#34;&gt;long-interrupted project&lt;/a&gt; of decluttering at home. I dug up old college course notes, exercise log books from a decade ago, and other stuff I just don&amp;rsquo;t need. Dozens of books I no longer read. I filled boxes of stuff to recycle or have Abby donate to the library. I am committed to leaving nothing accidental behind if I die, only what is purposeful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, we don&amp;rsquo;t have wills or the like yet. Time to get cracking on that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;adversity-more-generally&#34;&gt;Adversity, more generally&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel that &amp;ldquo;negative thinking&amp;rdquo; is very useful and that I could do more of it. As a software developer, anticipating failure modes helps me write better and more confident code. Playing chess, I know firsthand that wishful thinking results in big crashes when things don&amp;rsquo;t go your way. Teaching chess, I like to set up unpleasant situations and have the student struggle (in a safe, low stakes environment) to defend, as practice for real tournament chess when the strength to deal with the unexpected is a key to success in competition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;daily-habits&#34;&gt;Daily habits&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, I did meditate and exercise (more dumbbell and body weight strength training) today. Recall that yesterday I had a setback. The advantage of having once had a successful exercise routine is that when I think clearly, I am prepared for adversity, having faced it before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I appreciate the curious technique of envisioning and simulating future catastrophe in order to enable acting more calmly today. Figuring out death seems the ultimate challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How do you feel about the technique of deliberately imagining bad things? Does this seem perverse to you? Or useful?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Report on my fifth day of Stoic Week 2014: action and the reserve clause</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/28/report-on-my-fifth-day-of-stoic-week-2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2014 23:20:43 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/28/report-on-my-fifth-day-of-stoic-week-2014/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I had some setbacks today, the fifth day of Stoic Week, but dealt with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-coconut-oil-accident-yesterday-at-thanksgiving-party&#34;&gt;A coconut oil accident yesterday at Thanksgiving party&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the time we left &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/11/27/report-on-my-fourth-day-of-stoic-week-2014/&#34;&gt;yesterday&amp;rsquo;s Thanksgiving party&lt;/a&gt; in the evening, I wasn&amp;rsquo;t feeling so well. I had blamed eating that one cookie and also drinking a bit of spicy warm cider, but as unpleasant symptoms developed (you don&amp;rsquo;t need to know the details), I immediately knew what must have happened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A bit of history, years ago I experimented with &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/01/26/improving-my-breakfast-and-other-meals/&#34;&gt;using coconut oil&lt;/a&gt; but found that I could tolerate only a little bit, and in fact quickly decided to just not use it any more in cooking, after some incidents in which I experienced very unpleasant symptoms after a meal and found out that Abby had used a good amount of coconut oil in cooking. We had her limit the use of coconut oil in cooking anything I was to eat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it had been quite some time since I experienced those symptoms, but unfortunately, I suffered for over twelve hours with poor sleep overnight, and can only conclude that a large mount of coconut oil was used in Thanksgiving dinner!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-system-temporarily-wrecked-illustrating-today-s-theme&#34;&gt;My system temporarily wrecked, illustrating today&amp;rsquo;s theme&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I not only woke up late in the morning today, but was also still suffering physically, was hungry nonetheless, and grouchy. Normally I try to start my day with meditation, but I just wanted to eat breakfast. Abby had gotten up hours before me and was annoyed I had gotten up late, and snapped at me while I was bleary-eyed and trying to start eating breakfast. I snapped back, and she got very upset and disappeared.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While eating, I recognized that I had gone totally non-Stoic, and so after I finished eating and reading today&amp;rsquo;s theme on &amp;ldquo;action and the reserve clause&amp;rdquo;, I immediately went to meditate for ten minutes before talking with her again, in a much calmer mood, explaining what had been happening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went back to napping, and then before lunch time, after my final visit to the toilet, I finally felt like my coconut oil disaster was truly over and I could start my day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I felt I had &amp;ldquo;failed&amp;rdquo; in that, contrary to Stoic teaching, I had let my physical distress take over my mind and everything I was doing. I could have dealt better with my situation, acting the best I could despite my circumstance rather than giving into my foul mood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &amp;ldquo;reserve clause&amp;rdquo; in Stoicism refers to how we &lt;em&gt;act&lt;/em&gt; even though we may not like what has happened or what might happen. I did not start the morning with this attitude.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;exercise&#34;&gt;Exercise&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I eventually made up, but it really bothered me that I had started off the day so badly. I was also feeling like my muscles were trashed from yesterday&amp;rsquo;s workout (and party play with the two sisters). Later in the afternoon, we went for a hike in Frick Park and both felt better. I considered that my &amp;ldquo;exercise&amp;rdquo; for the day, a lower-intensity day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a setback in my practice of Stoicism but recovered, with even more appreciation for daily reading and study to get back on track.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How do you deal with setbacks? Do you have a system, a philosophical principle, to keep you on track?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Report on my fourth day of Stoic Week 2014: virtue and relationships with others</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/27/report-on-my-fourth-day-of-stoic-week-2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2014 21:47:45 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/27/report-on-my-fourth-day-of-stoic-week-2014/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today was Thanksgiving in the US, a surprisingly appropriate day to be in the middle of observing Stoic Week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;thanksgiving-dinner&#34;&gt;Thanksgiving dinner&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/11/27/report-on-my-third-day-of-stoic-week-2014/&#34;&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve reported on yesterday&amp;rsquo;s theme&lt;/a&gt; of self-discipline and simplicity. At Thanksgiving dinner this year, I decided for the very first time to limit what I ate. I&amp;rsquo;ve always overeaten in the past, with poor results. It was just something I did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year, I did not eat any of the cake or pumpkin pie that was offered. For dessert (after the turkey etc.), I limited myself to one scoop of pistachio gelato and one cookie. Actually, I ended up regretting that cookie, because it was more substantial and sugary than I expected, so I&amp;rsquo;ve made a note to watch myself with the cookies. The gelato I may not have needed, but I enjoyed it all the more knowing it was the one main dessert I was allowing myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;fourth-day-of-health-habits&#34;&gt;Fourth day of health habits&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s my fourth day now of daily meditation and exercise. Actually, I overdid it on the exercise today, but not intentionally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been increasing the intensity of my short (seven-minute or so) daily workouts every day, lifting heavier weights and working more muscles. What I didn&amp;rsquo;t expect was that at the Thanksgiving party, two young sisters (of ages around five and two) were bored and wanted to play, and I rather exerted myself. The older one was the ringleader. We played at scaring each other and I pretended to be sitting on the couch sleeping and suddenly spring up and boo or growl, and I accidentally pulled something in my right arm during one of these explosive, sudden movements. I also pulled my left shoulder when the two challenged me to lift them repeatedly, and the older one (tall for her age) was heavier than I expected and not so easy to repeatedly lift, given that I&amp;rsquo;d already had a workout in the morning at home. All in good fun, but left me a bit overextended.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;on-today-s-theme&#34;&gt;On today&amp;rsquo;s theme&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find sensible the Stoic teaching of developing our &amp;ldquo;natural affection&amp;rdquo;, and expanding outward from ourselves. I feel I have been the beneficiary of much good from many people in my life and am grateful for this. The Thanksgiving dinner that Abby and I went to today is one we have attended for some years now. The hosts I met through Abby, who met them (and other dinner guests) through music and dance circles. I appreciate and deeply admire the generosity that they have shown us and to many others. I look up to them as role models for the kind of genuine affection that human beings can display and share, not only with immediate family or closest friends but outward to larger communities (such as local music communities) and beyond.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tragic shooting and death that happened this year in &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shooting_of_Michael_Brown&#34;&gt;Ferguson, Missouri&lt;/a&gt; has been in the news for some months now, and this week the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shooting_of_Michael_Brown#Announcement_of_no_bill&#34;&gt;grand jury decided not to indict&lt;/a&gt;. I haven&amp;rsquo;t commented in public or in private on any of these events, or on any of the commentary about them, but I do not dismiss what has happened as irrelevant to my life. In fact, I feel that what has happened has been so important, in the biggest possible picture of what has been going on in American history for a long time, that I cannot afford to lightly spew sound bites about it. I do ask myself, how can I best talk about what I am feeling? How can I make a positive difference, in the Stoic &amp;ldquo;cosmopolitan&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;love of all humanity&amp;rdquo;? I don&amp;rsquo;t know the answer yet, but I know what is not the answer: fanning the flames of passion. But simply being silent is also not the answer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2015-01-19&#34;&gt;(Update of 2015-01-19)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wrote something in &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2015/01/19/for-martin-luther-king-jr-day-some-black-american-voices-that-spoke-to-me-recently/&#34;&gt;observation of Martin Luther King, Jr. Day&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I take seriously the Stoic call that we are ethically responsible for more than just ourselves, that we are to develop ourselves outward (not just on inner virtues) and work to honestly consider all human beings our brothers and sisters. I see how I have been treated in such a way by others through my life and aspire to expand beyond myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How do you feel about cosmopolitanism? Do you feel it is naive, that it is best to just look out after family and clan? If you have been following the Ferguson tragedy, do you easily choose a simple &amp;ldquo;side&amp;rdquo;, an &amp;ldquo;us&amp;rdquo; versus &amp;ldquo;them&amp;rdquo;?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Report on my third day of Stoic Week 2014: self-discipline and Stoic simplicity</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/27/report-on-my-third-day-of-stoic-week-2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2014 11:03:44 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/27/report-on-my-third-day-of-stoic-week-2014/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There is a reason I&amp;rsquo;m a little late in reporting on my third day of Stoic Week 2014: the theme, self-discipline and simplicity, had me cut short my intended plan of writing and publishing my thoughts at the end of each day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;health-and-self-control&#34;&gt;Health and self-control&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today&amp;rsquo;s reading for Stoic Week 2014 had us reflect on the importance of physical health and self-control in our daily routine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the third day in a row, I did a morning ten-minute sitting meditation, and noticed that my posture and breathing have improved. It took three days to notice this. It will take weeks to notice even more improvements; I know this because I&amp;rsquo;m a backslider, rather than one completely new to meditation. I imagine it must be much harder for a newcomer to adopt a practice like this where patience is required in order to experience the benefits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also kicked it up a notch with exercise. I mentioned in &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/11/25/report-on-my-second-day-of-stoic-week-2014/&#34;&gt;yesterday&amp;rsquo;s report&lt;/a&gt; that I need to do more weight training. I&amp;rsquo;m on that now. I&amp;rsquo;m making exercise a priority for the next several months in my life, at least.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve still been pretty good about refraining from unhealthy snacks. On &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/11/24/report-on-my-first-day-of-stoic-week-2014/&#34;&gt;day one&lt;/a&gt;, I noted that my work colleague brought back snacks from his first trip to Asia and I chose not to eat any of them. I opened up the bag of chips, but ate only a couple of them (in the past I have given into temptations, when confronted with a bag of chips, to eat the whole bag) and stashed the rest away. (By the way, the chips were unexceptional, tasting not much different than ordinary American potato chips, and the ingredients list was scary, with many weird chemicals included.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;sleep&#34;&gt;Sleep&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I haven&amp;rsquo;t been good with my sleep habits. I tend to stay up too late on the computer, for example. Abby wants me to have a &amp;ldquo;computer off plan&amp;rdquo; for my daily routine, but I&amp;rsquo;ve found this difficult because I like to work on personal projects (such as writing) on the computer and I find the time in the evening. I know the benefits of the &amp;ldquo;natural&amp;rdquo; life, and I&amp;rsquo;m sure Stoics would promote being a morning person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the point of this report isn&amp;rsquo;t to talk about becoming a morning person, or even so much about sleep. It&amp;rsquo;s about self-control. The reality is, yesterday when I came home from work, I was very tired. &amp;ldquo;Sleep when sleepy&amp;rdquo; is so logical and natural, yet I find that American culture does not value sleep. It seems countercultural to sleep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, I decided to simplify the evening and choose to stay off the computer (hence not writing this article). Apart from Wednesday evening being designed &amp;ldquo;us night&amp;rdquo; for Abby and me anyway, I decided that before sleeping, I would read (physical books and paper printouts) instead of use the computer, until ready to sleep. I did end up sleeping earlier. I did miss having the use of the computer to look up stuff that would have been helpful in my reading, but for this evening, at least, it was a tradeoff in favor of simplicity rather than stimulation. I&amp;rsquo;ll have to think about how to arrange my life differently if I want to continue to be more targeted in using the computer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Self-discipline and simplicity are not popular in American culture, which prizes maximization and stimulation. I don&amp;rsquo;t find it easy to maintain self-discipline, and am grateful to Stoic Week to remind me of its benefits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Is your gut impression of Stoic teachings that they want to take the fun out of your life, or that they are a guide to the truly good life? What is the balance you purposefully adopt between self-indulgence and renunciation?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Report on my second day of Stoic Week 2014: mindfulness</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/25/report-on-my-second-day-of-stoic-week-2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2014 23:50:38 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/25/report-on-my-second-day-of-stoic-week-2014/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, I reported on my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/11/24/report-on-my-first-day-of-stoic-week-2014/&#34;&gt;first day of Stoic Week 2014&lt;/a&gt;. Today, the second day&amp;rsquo;s theme was &amp;ldquo;Stoic mindfulness&amp;rdquo;. This is similar to the Buddhist teaching on mindfulness, and is basically a sound psychological observation that &amp;ldquo;You are just an impression and not at all the thing you claim to represent&amp;rdquo;: our thoughts and feelings are one thing but what we do about them is another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found it particularly useful to remember this today, because Tuesdays present an interesting challenge for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;chess&#34;&gt;Chess&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Tuesday nights, I have been playing in the latest 6-round current Tuesday night &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburghcc.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Chess Club&lt;/a&gt; tournament, one round every Tuesday. Tonight was round 4. I had experienced an extremely painful loss last week in round 3 when I was &lt;em&gt;not mindful&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://chessimprover.com/blockading-to-defend-when-things-get-tough/&#34;&gt;got carried away by emotions&lt;/a&gt;: I had an overwhelming advantage during an attack on my opponent&amp;rsquo;s King, but I allowed my excitement to cloud my judgment, make poor moves, and then worse, after I managed to recover and had the opportunity to survive with a draw, &lt;em&gt;and saw this&lt;/em&gt;, I passed it up out of wishful thinking that I could continue an attack, so I ended up losing. In chess, I face the stark reality that most losses at my level in local competition (where I am typically the top-rated player) are due to faulty psychology, rather than lack of sufficient understanding and skill. A loss of &lt;em&gt;objectivity&lt;/em&gt; (which all athletes and other performers under high pressure) is the reason we fail. Mindfulness directly addresses this all-too-human flaw.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;continuing-habits-from-yesterday&#34;&gt;Continuing habits from yesterday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, I noted that I began meditating and exercising again, because it was in my power to do so. I have continued. It&amp;rsquo;s been tricky to get going again, because my body is out of whack, but I remember to do what I can, no more, with faith that incremental progress will pay off. Instead of running, I did a &lt;a href=&#34;http://well.blogs.nytimes.com/projects/workouts/&#34;&gt;7-minute workout&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;ve lost a lot of strength over the years and plan to regain it. I have dumbbells lying around the house from when I was using them a decade ago; it&amp;rsquo;s time to get back to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;tonight-s-chess-game&#34;&gt;Tonight&amp;rsquo;s chess game&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I won a decent game tonight at the chess tournament. It was the third last to finish, taking almost four hours. I&amp;rsquo;ve played against my opponent many times before over the years, mostly winning, but the last time I played him, he held me to a draw, despite a 500-rating-point difference (which is huge). One thing that sometimes happens in tournament chess is overconfidence when facing someone who is on paper much weaker, or fear because of a past bad result. Mindfulness teaches us that although historical facts are facts, we should distance ourselves from distracting feelings about them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As in many hard-fought chess games, I experienced a range of emotions during the game. First of all, in the opening, although I was doing OK, I was frustrated that I allowed a certain kind of position I ordinarily do not allow, because of an oversight. Instead of kicking myself, I focused to do what I could with what I had, assessing that even though I did not want that position, it was actually still OK for me. (Actually, computer analysis afterwards showed that I was more than OK, so I was still more pessimistic than warranted during the game.) In the middlegame, I emerged with an advantage, but then faced a curious choice. My opponent gave me an opportunity to win some material (a Rook for a Bishop and Pawn) at the expense of destroying my Pawn structure and therefore creating good chances for a draw. At the time, I saw no better winning try, so I went for it, deciding that, unlike last week, I was going to settle for a draw if my opponent could prove he could defend; I simply made sure to play soundly and not recklessly. It turned out that he cracked eventually and I won. I was pleased that I remained psychologically strong in the game and was rewarded accordingly. (For those of you interested in the technical details of the game, I will be annotating it in an upcoming article I will write for &lt;a href=&#34;http://chessimprover.com/category/franklin-chen/&#34;&gt;my weekly column in The Chess Improver&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;heavy-traffic&#34;&gt;Heavy traffic&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another thing: when driving home from work to eat dinner before the chess game, I noticed that the traffic was unusually bad. Mindfulness is always helpful when facing stressful situations like this. I was upset with myself for not anticipating apparent pre-Thanksgiving-holiday traffic and therefore being pressed for time to get home and eat dinner before playing chess. I decided to let go of my self-annoyance because it wasn&amp;rsquo;t going to help me get home any sooner and would just sap my mental energy I needed for my game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mindfulness is something I&amp;rsquo;ve had prior experience in trying to adopt well before I even read about Stoicism. But having a daily theme and reading during Stoic Week has been surprisingly helpful in keeping me aware.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Are you familiar with the concept of mindfulness and the scientific underpinnings of it? If so, do you deliberately practice it? Do you have misgivings about it?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Report on my first day of Stoic Week 2014</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/24/report-on-my-first-day-of-stoic-week-2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2014 22:30:51 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/24/report-on-my-first-day-of-stoic-week-2014/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Last year, I heard about the first Stoic Week, &lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.exeter.ac.uk/stoicismtoday/stoic-week-2013/&#34;&gt;Stoic Week 2013&lt;/a&gt;, but did not participate because I was distracted at the time and did not feel like focusing. This week, I decided it was time to sign up for &lt;a href=&#34;http://modernstoicism.com/course/view.php?id=5&#34;&gt;Stoic Week 2014&lt;/a&gt;, and I did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-my-interest-in-stoicism&#34;&gt;Why my interest in Stoicism?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve mentioned Stoicism only briefly in my blog: once in 2012 when &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/11/22/thanking-the-best-of-all-possible-worlds/&#34;&gt;thinking about Thanksgiving&lt;/a&gt; and once earlier this year after &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/01/17/hiroo-onoda-and-the-six-million-dollar-man/&#34;&gt;rewatching an old TV episode&lt;/a&gt;. As I mentioned, it was in 2011, upon reading a book on Stoicism, that I made some major changes in my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that a couple of weeks ago, I decided to make major changes in my life again, but not while thinking about Stoicism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over a year ago, my meditation practice fell apart, and I never really regained it. As a result, my thoughts and habits have become disordered, I have felt. For example, I stopped writing regularly for my blog. I spent too much time on Facebook and Twitter instead, being distracted, annoyed, and worse, behaving in ways that I later came to feel counterproductive. I did &amp;ldquo;quit&amp;rdquo; Facebook in July, and also &amp;ldquo;quit&amp;rdquo; Twitter some weeks ago (part of the big life changes I set in motion), but still, I have felt ungrounded. I decided Stoic Week 2014 would be a good opportunity for me to return to the contemplative life that Buddhism and Stoicism in their different ways aspire to and that I had forgotten.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-i-did-the-first-day-of-stoic-week-2014&#34;&gt;What I did the first day of Stoic Week 2014&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, as I started the first day of Stoic Week 2014, I began by meditating ten minutes, Zen style. &lt;em&gt;This was my first meditation session in weeks&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I read the assigned text for today in the Stoic Week handbook, on &amp;ldquo;What is in our power?&amp;rdquo; A basic principle of Stoicism is that we should know what is under our control and what is not, and summarily refuse to dwell on or resent what is not under our control, and focus on making good decisions about what is under our control. A very simple but powerful concept, especially in a world in which it is easy to get annoyed or angry about many things we hear about in the news or encounter in our daily lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My exercise habit has been very spotty for months now. Well, today I reflected that, what the hell, it is completely under my control whether I choose to exercise or not, so why am I wasting this precious freedom? Some people don&amp;rsquo;t have this freedom. Others, including prisoners in jail, have little freedom but make use of what they have, and &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/17/the-joys-of-convict-conditioning-bodyweight-exercising/&#34;&gt;they exercise&lt;/a&gt;! It happened to be warm outside today, so I really had no excuse. I went for a run in Frick Park. It was short, less than three miles long, but I went. &lt;em&gt;This was my first run in weeks&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was my turn to cook today at home, so I made a substantial beef casserole dish. Abby has (rightfully) complained in the past when I didn&amp;rsquo;t completely clean up after cooking. Well, today I thought to myself that it is completely within my control whether I choose to attend to the details of cleanup as much as I attend to the details of using our skillets and baking pans. So I cleaned up as well as I could.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have not been feeling very well physically for weeks now since an incident involving emergency dental work that somehow resulted in complications. I am still in recovery. OK, so it is not under my control that I am not in good health right now. But what is under my control? After lunch I took a nap, because I felt like I needed it. I have been skimping on naps, but this is stupid, because I know that sleep is the best restorative practice when ill. It is under my control whether I choose to set aside time to sleep as needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At work, a colleague just came back from his first trip in Asia. He gave me samples of some odd snacks: chips, cookies, and candy. In recent months, I would have opened them up and eaten them on the spot. Indeed, I have been having problems with eating too many snacks for no rational reason. Today, I decided that it is up to me whether I choose to give in to random cravings or temptations, and so I chose to put the snacks aside for later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After work, I went to a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/Pittsburgh-Code-Supply/events/210396972/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Code and Supply Build Night&lt;/a&gt;, where food was served. Apart from a Thanksgiving dinner (!), some kind of cake lurked around. I took one glance, and chose not to even look at it again until leaving (when it was already all eaten).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leaving Build Night, I found myself annoyed that it was taking forever for the pedestrian light to change, but caught myself and observed that, first of all, the cycle is as it is, beyond my control; and second, I had mistakenly assumed that someone had pressed the button, so it was my fault I had to wait so long. I pressed the button and eventually got to cross. Next, while driving home, I made the mistake of driving behind a bus, which kept stopping. I got annoyed, not by the bus, but by myself, for mistakenly driving on the wrong street rather than the other one that does not have this problem; I got annoyed that I was too lazy to make a U-turn on the street I was parked on in order to get to that other street. But I stopped myself when I realized that what was done was done, and I simply had to endure the rest of the drive home behind the bus because it was not going to save any more time if I detoured around it late in the game: the best I can do is to be more careful in the future when making choices while driving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I felt I improved my life today by keeping in mind the fundamental Stoic principle of observing what is not under my control and what is under my control. I look forward to continuing to adopt this outlook for the rest of the week, and beyond that.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Climbing the Cathedral of Learning to get to the Harvard Classics</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/10/22/climbing-the-cathedral-of-learning-to-get-to-the-harvard-classics/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Oct 2014 23:12:24 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/10/22/climbing-the-cathedral-of-learning-to-get-to-the-harvard-classics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I recently learned that the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Harvard_Classics&#34;&gt;Harvard Classics&lt;/a&gt;, a 51-volume set of classic writings first published in 1909, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.openculture.com/2014/03/the-harvard-classics-download-all-51-volumes-as-free-ebooks.html&#34;&gt;are now available for free download as ebooks&lt;/a&gt;. This isn&amp;rsquo;t really news, but was just something that appeared on my radar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What relevance such an ancient collection has today is an interesting question, especially in light of the fact that a century ago the concept of what was of interest in the history of the &amp;ldquo;world&amp;rdquo; was fairly narrow, but not something I&amp;rsquo;m discussing right now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a hunch where I could find a physical copy of the Harvard Classics. I tested my hunch:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/franklinmingchen/15415427937&#34; title=&#34;IMG_20141022_113213 by Franklin Chen, on Flickr&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5607/15415427937_62f9d10eae.jpg&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; height=&#34;375&#34; alt=&#34;IMG_20141022_113213&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;sightings&#34;&gt;Sightings&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have seen this type of material (including, of course sets of encyclopedias) in many places, including personal homes: dusty, hardly opened volumes handed down generation after generation, perhaps, or acquired at bargain prices from library or garage sales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But most interesting to me is seeing it in public places. In particularly, I suddenly had the suspicion (or unconscious memory) that the 36th floor of the Cathedral of Learning at Pitt, which has book shelves of many old books, might have the Harvard Classics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;climbing-the-cathedral&#34;&gt;Climbing the Cathedral&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/franklinmingchen/15601416745&#34; title=&#34;IMG_20141022_114120 by Franklin Chen, on Flickr&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3932/15601416745_5c49f2fbdf.jpg&#34; width=&#34;375&#34; height=&#34;500&#34; alt=&#34;IMG_20141022_114120&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I used my curiosity to stop by the Cathedral of Learning near lunch time and climb to the 36th floor, a curious form of exercise I hadn&amp;rsquo;t engaged in for quite some time, maybe almost a year by now. I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/04/i-had-no-choice-but-to-barefoot-climb-the-cathedral-of-learning/&#34;&gt;took off my shoes and socks&lt;/a&gt; and jacket, and stuffed them in my backpack before beginning the ascent. I am currently out of shape and started feeling nauseous probably around the 25th floor, but made it to the top:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/franklinmingchen/15415427937&#34; title=&#34;IMG_20141022_113213 by Franklin Chen, on Flickr&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5607/15415427937_62f9d10eae.jpg&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; height=&#34;375&#34; alt=&#34;IMG_20141022_113213&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There they were, the Harvard Classics!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/franklinmingchen/15601416115&#34; title=&#34;IMG_20141022_113305 by Franklin Chen, on Flickr&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3944/15601416115_470d900851.jpg&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; height=&#34;375&#34; alt=&#34;IMG_20141022_113305&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Physically old books have a durability and charm to them. Here&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;The Pilgrim&amp;rsquo;s Progress&amp;rdquo;, a book I actually acquired &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/12/22/a-favorite-poem-to-share-as-2013-comes-to-an-end&#34;&gt;by accident at age 9 along with many others&lt;/a&gt; but never really read (I tried but it was too confusing, despite the illustrations):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/franklinmingchen/15598756521&#34; title=&#34;IMG_20141022_113328 by Franklin Chen, on Flickr&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5615/15598756521_c5fe055973.jpg&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; height=&#34;375&#34; alt=&#34;IMG_20141022_113328&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-note-on-the-elevator-modernization-project&#34;&gt;A note on the &amp;ldquo;elevator modernization project&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After I climb to the top of the Cathedral of Learning, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/11/03/the-dilemma-of-how-to-descend-the-cathedral-of-learning-once-at-the-top/&#34;&gt;I have to choose whether to take an elevator down&lt;/a&gt;, and this time was no exception.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that an elevator appeared quickly before I had to decide whether to just walk down 36 floors, so I hopped in with some other people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I heard a lot of complaints about elevator waits thanks to elevators being out of service. People talked about waiting &lt;em&gt;fifteen to twenty minutes&lt;/em&gt; before giving up sometimes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I kept my mouth shut about the fact that it only takes far less time to either ascend or descend the entire Cathedral on the stairs; this is not a nation of walkers, and everyone has personal reasons not to take the stairs. There are many good reasons to improve accessibility between all the floors of the Cathedral for all people, and I have found the elevators unreliable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Getting back to the bottom, I saw a sign that explained the situation: there is an &amp;ldquo;elevator modernization project&amp;rdquo; in progress to try to considerably improve the elevator situation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/franklinmingchen/15577746826&#34; title=&#34;IMG_20141022_113740 by Franklin Chen, on Flickr&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3944/15577746826_4ee00263a0.jpg&#34; width=&#34;375&#34; height=&#34;500&#34; alt=&#34;IMG_20141022_113740&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found the Harvard Classics where I expected to find them! I will continue to climb the Cathedral in the future to see what other oldies exist up there. I am particularly interested in encyclopedias and &amp;ldquo;world history&amp;rdquo; books, having seen some really old ones in the past that were fascinating in either their short-sighted parochial nature or in their far-sighted prophetic correctness. I will report on what I find that might be particularly noteworthy.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The dilemma of how to descend the Cathedral of Learning once at the top</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/11/03/the-dilemma-of-how-to-descend-the-cathedral-of-learning-once-at-the-top/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Nov 2013 09:34:44 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/11/03/the-dilemma-of-how-to-descend-the-cathedral-of-learning-once-at-the-top/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, right after I left one of the sessions of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.music.pitt.edu/events/43rd-annual-jazz-seminar-concert130813&#34;&gt;annual Pittsburgh Jazz Seminar&lt;/a&gt; at the William Pitt Union, I immediately crossed the street to the Cathedral of Learning, in order to climb up to the 36th floor (I last climbed the Cathedral &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/10/29/an-early-start-on-cathedral-of-learning-stair-climbing/&#34;&gt;three days ago&lt;/a&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/cathedral-2013-11-02.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;View of Cathedral of Learning&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I took off my shoes, stuffed my jacket into my backpack, and went up at an &amp;ldquo;easy&amp;rdquo; pace, taking about nine minutes:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/cathedral-2013-11-02-at-top.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;View from 36th floor window of Cathedral of Learning&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Then I faced the usual dilemma of how to get back down, except this time, the dilemma was magnified because of my time constraints: I really needed to get down and out &lt;em&gt;quickly&lt;/em&gt;, in order to make it to an important appointment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;choices-and-tradeoffs&#34;&gt;Choices and tradeoffs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;elevator-down&#34;&gt;Elevator down&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One option is to take one of the elevators down. This is what I&amp;rsquo;ve almost always done ever since doing the Cathedral of Learning stair climb.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, whether this is time-effective depends a lot on various factors, such as whether Pitt classes are being held, Pitt students are roaming around, or tourists are roaming around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that Saturday afternoon is a bad time to be taking the elevator. There were hordes of students as well as tourists throughout the building, and especially the tourists at the top floor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, I had noticed on the ground floor earlier that some of the elevators were out of service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/10/29/an-early-start-on-cathedral-of-learning-stair-climbing/&#34;&gt;three days ago I had a bad experience with the elevator&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;taking-the-stairs-down&#34;&gt;Taking the stairs down&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other option is to take the stairs back down, all the way. This option is one I take so rarely that I don&amp;rsquo;t even remember when I last did it. I probably did it once earlier this year, but have no specific memory of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The drawback of taking the stairs down is the extra impact on the body.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But since I needed to descend as quickly as possible, I felt I had no choice but to take the stairs. In fact, I not only used the stairs, but ran down all the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It wasn&amp;rsquo;t hard (thank you, gravity!), although it got boring and weird after a while, because it feels like forever going down 36 floors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-day-after&#34;&gt;The day after&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought everything was OK, but this morning, the day after, I woke up with a serious case of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Delayed_onset_muscle_soreness&#34;&gt;DOMS&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My &lt;em&gt;calves&lt;/em&gt; were totally tight and trashed. Oops. Maybe I could have prevented this by stretching after running down yesterday, but I had no time, and had to make my appointment. Or maybe I just plain overdid things, not being conditioned at all to running down so many steps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I&amp;rsquo;m suffering, but no permanent damage done, of course: I will be OK after a day or two.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-next&#34;&gt;What next?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So does this mean that the next time I climb the Cathedral, I will stick to the elevator?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, &lt;em&gt;no&lt;/em&gt;. I take the experience as a challenge:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;First, I want to defeat my sense of boredom going down, just as I&amp;rsquo;ve managed to defeat it on the way up. I will find something meditative and aesthetic about the process of descending the steps.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Clearly my soreness showed that my calves were insufficiently conditioned. The solution to that is not to avoid running down the steps, but to &lt;em&gt;keep doing it&lt;/em&gt;, in a smarter way. Therefore, my plan now is that on any final repetition of the Cathedral stair climb, I will take the stairs back down, rather than the elevator, regardless of elevator congestion concerns.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An accidental case of trashed calves during a workout has led me to treat it as a learning experience and a challenge to overcome in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2014-10-22&#34;&gt;(Update of 2014-10-22)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/10/22/climbing-the-cathedral-of-learning-to-get-to-the-harvard-classics/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;elevator modernization project&amp;rdquo; started in September 2014 and makes it even more attractive to just walk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An early start on Cathedral of Learning stair climbing</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/29/an-early-start-on-cathedral-of-learning-stair-climbing/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Oct 2013 19:18:47 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/29/an-early-start-on-cathedral-of-learning-stair-climbing/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;After work today, I had gone to the Carnegie Library of Pittsburgh, main branch in Oakland, to pick up some books, when I looked across Forbes Avenue and saw the Pitt Cathedral of Learning. Primed by Becky&amp;rsquo;s message today about forming a team again for the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lung.org/pledge-events/pa/pittsburgh-climb-fy14/&#34;&gt;Fight for Air Climb at One Oxford Centre in downtown Pittsburgh, for next March&lt;/a&gt;, I suddenly decided to do the 36-floor stair climb of the Cathedral of Learning to &amp;ldquo;officially&amp;rdquo; begin my training for that event!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/cathedral-2013-10-29.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Cathedral of Learning&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m getting an early start this year on training for the Fight for Air Climb: last year, I didn&amp;rsquo;t even think about that event until I saw a poster for it during &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/28/meditations-on-climbing-the-36-floors-of-the-pitt-cathedral-of-learning/&#34;&gt;my first Cathedral climb in years, right after Christmas&lt;/a&gt;. So I&amp;rsquo;m going to have an additional two months of training.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;going-up&#34;&gt;Going up&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, in addition to my not having done the Cathedral climb in probably over half a year, I was wearing my work clothing and shoes and a backpack full of heavy books, so the climb was rather strenuous and sweaty. I even &amp;ldquo;forgot&amp;rdquo; to go to the 36th floor and got off at the 35th instead (no big deal).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/cathedral-2013-10-29-near-top.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;View out of 35th floor window&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;going-back-down&#34;&gt;Going back down&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once at the top, I didn&amp;rsquo;t stop to rest, because I wanted to get home quickly for dinner. Unfortunately, lots of people were already on the elevator when it came down from 36, and after I got on at 35, we kept on stopping to pick up others, and I felt very uncomfortable being sweaty and packed into the elevator near the back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-11-03&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-11-03)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/11/03/the-dilemma-of-how-to-descend-the-cathedral-of-learning-once-at-the-top/&#34;&gt;Three days later, I did the Cathedral climb again, and did take the stairs, but experienced a surprise.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My promise to prioritize my sleep</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/12/my-promise-to-prioritize-my-sleep/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Oct 2013 22:33:48 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/12/my-promise-to-prioritize-my-sleep/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Despite my knowledge (both firsthand and from reading research results) that sleep is important to healthy living, I have been failing to get my optimal sleep for a long time now. There are several reasons of this, but I am taking steps to address each one of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;too-many-activities&#34;&gt;Too many activities&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I began the process of catching up on sleep today by sleeping almost all day. Abby and I had yesterday decided to cancel our hiking plan for today because we both felt tired and decided it was a good time to just rest. We both have a bad habit of doing too many activities and not getting enough down time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I already mentioned some of the things I&amp;rsquo;m scaling down on: &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/10/04/final-rehearsal-for-my-first-ukulele-gig/&#34;&gt;musical activities&lt;/a&gt;. Today was the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.coolhanduke.com/&#34;&gt;Cool Hand Uke&lt;/a&gt; workshop and concert, both of which I had decided earlier to skip.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;night-time-distractions&#34;&gt;Night time distractions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not sleeping as early or deeply as I should, because of not turning down the lights and getting off the computer at night. I&amp;rsquo;m going to change that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In particular, social media at night are the worst. My decision today to &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/10/12/taking-a-break-from-twitter/&#34;&gt;take a break from Twitter, Facebook, and Google+&lt;/a&gt; will help a lot. Too much stimulation at night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;exercise&#34;&gt;Exercise&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a symbiotic relationship between sleep and exercise: the better the sleep, the more energy for stimulating exercise, and the more exercise, the more ready the body is to sleep in the evening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, after I slept almost all day, I found myself with energy to go for a run (I&amp;rsquo;ve barely been running in the past week). To my surprise, I effortlessly kept going and going, and ended up doing ten miles, no problem, in Frick Park and Summerset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was huge confirmation to me, that just catching up on sleep enabled me to enjoy a ten-mile run when I&amp;rsquo;ve barely been feeling like running at all in the past week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-2013-10-12/1.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-2013-10-12/2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-2013-10-12/3.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-2013-10-12/4.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-2013-10-12/5.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-2013-10-12/6.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m going to keep up good habits in order to improve my life. Sleep is the number one priority that I believe will benefit everything else.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why I was so happy to run 5 miles in 63 minutes today when I was doing it in 50 earlier this year</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/08/13/why-i-was-so-happy-to-run-5-miles-in-63-minutes-today-when-i-was-doing-it-in-50-earlier-this-year/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Aug 2013 21:18:29 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/08/13/why-i-was-so-happy-to-run-5-miles-in-63-minutes-today-when-i-was-doing-it-in-50-earlier-this-year/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I went for a run in Frick Park, my usual 5-mile route, which I haven&amp;rsquo;t done in a while. It took me 63 minutes. Earlier this year I was doing it in 50. My fitness is pretty low right now, as &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/08/10/emerging-from-my-three-months-of-illness-self-pitying-and-self-loathing/&#34;&gt;I explained three days ago&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I&amp;rsquo;m happy to be on the upswing. I&amp;rsquo;m getting out there, not pushing too hard, but challenging myself. I have faith that I will get back out of my slump. I have done this before. Other people have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you also have this experience of being happy to do something worse than you used to do it, because you&amp;rsquo;re doing it at all rather than doing nothing?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Emerging from my three months of illness, self-pitying, and self-loathing</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/08/10/emerging-from-my-three-months-of-illness-self-pitying-and-self-loathing/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Aug 2013 08:39:23 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/08/10/emerging-from-my-three-months-of-illness-self-pitying-and-self-loathing/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, I reported on my feelings after &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/08/09/getting-up-when-reality-punches-you-in-the-face-running-the-second-liberty-mile-in-pittsburgh/&#34;&gt;having a very painful and embarrassing performance in the Liberty Mile road race&lt;/a&gt;. I resolved to slowly return myself to health and fitness, starting &lt;em&gt;immediately&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, Leo Babauta wrote a great blog post that really spoke to me, &lt;a href=&#34;http://zenhabits.net/fraud/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Fear of Being Found a Fraud&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. Basically, he writes advice, but he&amp;rsquo;s not perfect, and doesn&amp;rsquo;t always successfully do what he preaches. I periodically have feelings like that, since I write about stuff too and also post &amp;ldquo;advice&amp;rdquo; links on Twitter, Facebook, and Google+. What would people think if they knew I have been failing myself in the past three months?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, I have to be honest. There&amp;rsquo;s no point lying. I sometimes &lt;em&gt;know&lt;/em&gt; what&amp;rsquo;s best and what has worked for me, but don&amp;rsquo;t take my own advice. This in itself is not the big problem. The real problem is the second-order problem, which is that of believing that I&amp;rsquo;m not only imperfect (we all are), but sometimes ending also deciding to give up on myself. That&amp;rsquo;s the worst thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, after health conditions disrupted my &amp;ldquo;normal&amp;rdquo; routines, I ended up not getting back on track when in fact I should and could have, through a gradual process. In a way, I was too proud to &lt;em&gt;adapt to reality&lt;/em&gt;. I was willing to operate under a different, better reality, but given the worse one, I chickened out, and entered a downward spiral of bad habits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;meditation-habit-destroyed&#34;&gt;Meditation habit, destroyed&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/02/01/a-report-on-one-month-of-daily-meditation/&#34;&gt;restarted a daily meditation practice for the new year&lt;/a&gt;, and entered into a 100-day meditation challenge. I encountered setbacks in my first month, but kept bouncing back. I even &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/01/dealing-with-setbacks-during-my-second-month-of-meditation/&#34;&gt;continued into a second month&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then things got worse, and as you can see in the archives to my blog, I &lt;em&gt;never wrote a report for the third month&lt;/em&gt;. According to my &lt;a href=&#34;http://insighttimer.com/&#34;&gt;Insight Timer&lt;/a&gt; journal, I actually did meditate in March almost every day, so I could have written a blog post on that, but I didn&amp;rsquo;t. &lt;em&gt;That was a mistake&lt;/em&gt;. I have found that public updates on progress keep me more accountable to myself; this is why I have written so much about my personal musical activities: not only to share my journey with those who are interested (because they are friends or because they are themselves on their own journeys), but also to keep myself honest about where I&amp;rsquo;ve been, what I still need to do, where I intend to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In April, my meditation practice started to fall apart. I missed April 10 and 11, then 13, 14, 15, then 18, 19, 20, 20, 23, and the rest of the month. In May I was erratic, till after May 13, &lt;em&gt;I completely stopped identifying myself as a &amp;ldquo;meditator&amp;rdquo; and quit&lt;/em&gt;. That&amp;rsquo;s right: I felt so ashamed of myself that I did not meditate between May 14 and August 9 this year. Big mistake, this pointless shame, especially given that I know, empirically, that &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/30/when-i-dont-have-time-to-sit-and-breathe-something-is-wrong-with-my-life/&#34;&gt;when I don&amp;rsquo;t &amp;ldquo;have time&amp;rdquo; to meditate, something is wrong with my life&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;exercise&#34;&gt;Exercise&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, my exercise schedule completely fell apart. &amp;ldquo;Normally&amp;rdquo;, I run every other day and do strength training the other days. None of this has to be a super-long session. Just enough to keep me mentally and physically alert. My strength training has generally been just a simple half-hour &amp;ldquo;core performance&amp;rdquo; type of workout at home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, I lost the habit, partially because marathon training caused me to cut back on strength training and because after the marathon, I took a break from running. The big lesson I learned here is that marathoning is very disruptive to my ordinary life, and I do not plan to ever do a marathon again in my life. But apart from that, I had non-marathon disruptions also, such as the skin rash after a hike that I&amp;rsquo;ve been dealing with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-i-did-today&#34;&gt;What I did today&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Today is the first day of the rest of my life.&lt;/strong&gt; Clean slate, forget the past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I meditated this morning. And I will continue to make this a high priority and do it daily. I must make sure that if I slip, I simply get back on track, rather than feel shame or whatever. It must simply be a habit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I ran yesterday, today was a non-running day. I decided that one way to prevent myself from completely slipping is to have a backup &amp;ldquo;very short&amp;rdquo; workout in case any kind of laziness or disruption causes me to think about just canceling a workout rather than do a longer one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So today was my first experiment with a &lt;a href=&#34;http://medium.com/editors-picks/e4975b151181&#34;&gt;7-minute workout&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s intense, but fast to get over with. I highly recommend checking it out!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are more links to this type of workout:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://journals.lww.com/acsm-healthfitness/Fulltext/2013/05000/HIGH_INTENSITY_CIRCUIT_TRAINING_USING_BODY_WEIGHT_.5.aspx&#34;&gt;Journal paper&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://7minworkoutapp.com/&#34;&gt;Online app&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lifehack.org/articles/lifestyle/master-the-7-minute-workout-with-this-video.html&#34;&gt;Lifehack article&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if you&amp;rsquo;re lazy, surely you have 7 minutes a day to squeeze in this little circuit. I did!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-future&#34;&gt;The future&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back to meditating every day, just 10 minutes a day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I&amp;rsquo;m going to take it easy to ramp back up to fitness. I know it&amp;rsquo;s going to take &lt;em&gt;months&lt;/em&gt; to get back to where I was earlier in the year. &lt;em&gt;Patience is a virtue&lt;/em&gt;. I will start small. A little bit of slow running every other day, and the 7-minute workout every other day, to get started, before extending further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was time to stop my descent into endless self-pitying and self-loathing over all the misfortunes that have come my way in the past months. I&amp;rsquo;m taking my life back.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Back to what running is really about for me</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/05/09/back-to-what-running-is-really-about-for-me/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 May 2013 08:32:41 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/05/09/back-to-what-running-is-really-about-for-me/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/cloudy-frick-park.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Cloudy day drizzling rain in Frick Park&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So, four days after my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/05/07/why-i-feel-sad-when-people-congratulate-me-for-finishing-the-pittsburgh-marathon/&#34;&gt;disappointing&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/05/06/2013-pittsburgh-marathon-my-135th-race-was-my-worst-i-finished/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Marathon&lt;/a&gt;, I&amp;rsquo;ve recovered enough to first walk, and now do some light running as well. I did a very slow, short 3-mile run in Frick Park.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m guessing it will take me another two or three weeks to be completely recovered physically, but I&amp;rsquo;m ecstatic to be out and about again. I&amp;rsquo;m also happy that I&amp;rsquo;m &lt;em&gt;emotionally&lt;/em&gt; recovered already; I was pretty unbalanced leading up to and after the ordeal. The big lesson I&amp;rsquo;ve learned yet again is that losing sight of what is important and focusing on narrow ideas of achievement backfired on me, self-destructively, just as it did when I played &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/04/round-4-of-pittsburgh-chess-club-tournament-the-agony-of-losing-a-won-game-against-the-difficult-opponent/&#34;&gt;bizarrely&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/11/round-5-of-pittsburgh-chess-club-tournament-psychology-of-losing-another-won-game/&#34;&gt;poorly&lt;/a&gt; in a chess tournament last fall before relaxing and then &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/02/20/pittsburgh-chess-club-championship-2013-round-6-winning-as-black-like-a-madman/&#34;&gt;winning the 2013 Pittsburgh Chess Club Championship&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-running-is-really-about&#34;&gt;What running is really about&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Running for me is really about enjoying the outdoors, feeling alive and expressive through rhythmic movement, and getting to know my body better and accept it while working with what nature has given me, to improve how I move and feel. Now that this whole marathon thing is over, I&amp;rsquo;m back to running on the trails instead of the hard roads, and I&amp;rsquo;m back to not timing myself. I&amp;rsquo;m back to being out there alone, not measuring myself against anyone or anything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;so-what-about-races&#34;&gt;So what about races?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, I do enjoy some element of competition, both against myself and against others, in the spirit of play and excellence. So, although I&amp;rsquo;ll take it easy for a couple of weeks just enjoying maintaining and rebuilding fitness (not just for running, but also getting back to some neglected strength training), I&amp;rsquo;m looking forward to doing some races this summer, with an intent to run them fast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first one coming up for me is the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.race360.com/running/races/detail.asp?eventid=16822&#34;&gt;Man Up Father&amp;rsquo;s Day 10K&lt;/a&gt; in June benefiting the &lt;a href=&#34;http://obcolefoundation.org/&#34;&gt;Obediah Cole Foundation for Prostate Cancer&lt;/a&gt;. I haven&amp;rsquo;t done any 10K other than the idiosyncratic Great Race 10K in 5 years, so I look forward to getting back to doing other 10K races. Also, I have done this Father&amp;rsquo;s Day 10k before, in 2004 and 2006. It would be nice if I could beat my 2006 time, getting back to my fitness level of 7 years ago, but ha, very unlikely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m ready to have a pleasant summer of outdoors activities. Abby and I already have hiking and kayaking plans. Meanwhile, I&amp;rsquo;ll continue running. The pain of the marathon season is already a dim memory.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>