<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Xero Shoes on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/xero-shoes/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Xero Shoes on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/xero-shoes/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Why and how I am going to run the 2013 Pittsburgh Marathon</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/01/30/why-and-how-i-am-going-to-run-the-2013-pittsburgh-marathon/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Jan 2013 20:31:41 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/01/30/why-and-how-i-am-going-to-run-the-2013-pittsburgh-marathon/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I surprised myself by deciding suddenly to run the &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburghmarathon.com/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Marathon&lt;/a&gt; this year, 2013. This was not part of the plan when I was &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/31/why-i-went-frick-park-trail-running-in-snowfall-for-the-first-time-in-a-decade/&#34;&gt;thinking about my running plans for 2013 a month ago&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will be my second Pittsburgh Marathon, because the last time I ran it was in 2003, and that was my first marathon ever. It was quite an ordeal to finish, because of a lot of rookie mistakes, but I made it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here I am in 2003 near the finish line (photo courtesy of my sister Linda):&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2003/P5040055.JPG&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin near finish line in 2003&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And here I am wearing my medal for finishing in 2003:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2003/P5040061.JPG&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin inside with medal&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So: why am I running the Pittsburgh Marathon again, &lt;em&gt;now&lt;/em&gt;, ten years later? What do I hope to accomplish? And how?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why&#34;&gt;Why?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;do-it-better&#34;&gt;Do it better&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2003, I ran my first marathon for a variety of reasons, and trained in certain ways, had certain expectations. I will write in depth later about that first marathon, because one reason I am running the Pittsburgh Marathon again now is to &lt;em&gt;do everything better&lt;/em&gt; this time, with the benefit of experience and new self-knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;maintain a smart pace&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;finish strong&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;avoid leg muscle cramping&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;avoid foot blistering&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;conquer the hills&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In sharp contrast to my first marathon, I do &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; plan to race this marathon as fast as I can. That blew up on me, and I do not have the time or desire to maximize my marathon performance at this point in my life. I do want to run strong, but not maximally. So I am not almost certainly not going to run faster than I did ten years ago; I am specifically expecting to run &lt;em&gt;slower&lt;/em&gt; but to have a &lt;em&gt;better&lt;/em&gt; overall experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will not be the second time I run a marathon distance; I have done that two or three times on my own while training for the &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/rachel-carson-trail-challenge/&#34;&gt;Rachel Carson Trail Challenge&lt;/a&gt; and have also run just over a marathon distance in the annual Sammy&amp;rsquo;s Birthday Run (a 6-hour ultra event) in 2006 and 2008. But those I did pretty slowly just for training and fun, in well over four hours. In the 2013 Pittsburgh Marathon, I&amp;rsquo;d like to finish close to the completely arbitrary magic number of 4:00:00. This is very low priority compared to the other goals, but it&amp;rsquo;s useful to have a little bit of ambition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;experiment&#34;&gt;Experiment&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides what I &lt;em&gt;know&lt;/em&gt; now that I didn&amp;rsquo;t, there are also things that I didn&amp;rsquo;t know then and still don&amp;rsquo;t know now, but have hypotheses about. So the experience will be an opportunity to test my hypotheses. In particular, the kind of exercise and diet I follow now different in various ways from ten years ago. I do a lot more core and strength training and less endurance training. So my main goal, in fact, is to run this marathon with relatively &lt;em&gt;low mileage&lt;/em&gt;. Instead of spending huge amounts of time and energy banging out the miles in training, I want to try ways of getting in really high-quality training that will enable me to handle the marathon distance better and gut it out through strength.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;social&#34;&gt;Social&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first Pittsburgh Marathon experience had me running all alone. I did have support as far as my sister coming to town and my friend Nathaniel watching me and cheering me on at certain points along the course, but out there, I was alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This time, I decided not to do the marathon unless I had at least a friend or two joining me. I got my office mate John to sign up (he also did the marathon over a decade ago). &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.runoverit.com/&#34;&gt;Chris&lt;/a&gt; is signed up for it, although he actually has yet to run his first marathon, which will be coming up in March. There are a bunch of others I also know who will be running. I guess when time comes, we&amp;rsquo;ll figure out how our likely paces might coincide (or not).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;it-will-be-on-my-birthday&#34;&gt;It will be on my birthday&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What can I say: it will be my very first race of any distance run &lt;em&gt;on my birthday&lt;/em&gt;. I thought it would be amusing and cool to celebrate my birthday by running the Pittsburgh Marathon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;discount&#34;&gt;Discount&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As staff at CMU, I (and my office mate John) get a &lt;a href=&#34;http://athletics.cmu.edu/fitness/fitkit2013&#34;&gt;special discount for the Pittsburgh Marathon&lt;/a&gt;. This explains why I registered today, right before the deadline!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the reduced registration fee, part of the deal is &amp;ldquo;Special access to private finish line tent with gourmet food, private massages, and more!&amp;rdquo; as well as 6 months free membership to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.steelcityrrc.org/&#34;&gt;Steel City Road Runners&lt;/a&gt;. Not bad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;update-of-2013-03-16&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-03-16)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I should note that the Steel City Road Runners was formed in 2011. John and I had in fact attended its &amp;ldquo;kick-off party&amp;rdquo; on Tuesday, September 13, 2011 where we did a free training run, but we ended up not joining the club or participating further, since we were not planning to do the Pittsburgh Marathon in 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;how&#34;&gt;How?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There isn&amp;rsquo;t actually much time before the marathon (three months), so I have to be smart about training and try to avoid setbacks. Some things I need to do:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;immediately start extending the distance of my runs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;continue core and strength training&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;keep up stair climbing and hill running&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;build up to some rigorous interval training&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;schedule long races to run in before the marathon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;cut back on various commitments in the next three months&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;removing-chess&#34;&gt;Removing chess&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve already decided on one major activity I am going to cut out: after I finish the current Tuesday night chess tournament, the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/02/04/pittsburgh-chess-club-championship-2013-round-3-attack-defense-and-sacrifices/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Chess Club Championship&lt;/a&gt;, I will take a break and not play in any more Tuesday night chess tournaments until possibly the fall (in summer I&amp;rsquo;d rather be playing outside in the sun rather than hunched over a chess board indoors!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Time and energy are limited. We can&amp;rsquo;t do everything all the time. In fact, as things are, I have not even been able to play in the monthly &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pitt.edu/~schach/ChessPA/ChessLeague/wpapcl.htm&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Chess League&lt;/a&gt; team matches since &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/11/11/pittsburgh-chess-league-round-3-back-to-chess-after-a-month-off/&#34;&gt;November&lt;/a&gt;: in December I was occupied with &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/02/oblivion-obsession-time-to-start-playing-melodica/&#34;&gt;music rehearsal&lt;/a&gt;, and just now in January I was coming off a hard week during which I was &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/25/notes-on-exercising-while-sick-or-tired/&#34;&gt;sick and overbooked&lt;/a&gt;. I do hope to make it to the February team match.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m doing well in the Pittsburgh Chess Club Championship so far, with a perfect score in my first three rounds, so I hope I&amp;rsquo;ll be able to say goodbye while winning it after another three rounds!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;footwear&#34;&gt;Footwear&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost certainly I will wear my &lt;em&gt;worn-out and holey&lt;/em&gt; pair of &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/08/28/five-reasons-we-just-stocked-up-on-vibram-fivefingers-kso-trek-shoes/&#34;&gt;Vibram FiveFingers KSO Trek shoes&lt;/a&gt;. The reason is that I have &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; been blistered wearing these shoes, no matter the distance. The leather is really comfortable for me. And I will wear the worn-out pair rather than a newer pair because on the roads, I don&amp;rsquo;t want the deeply lugged outsoles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other alternative I thought about was wearing huaraches such as my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/30/running-my-10th-great-race-10k-obscene-but-in-a-good-way/&#34;&gt;Xero Shoes that I wore in the Great Race 10K&lt;/a&gt;. I will do some experiments in the spring running much longer distances than 10K in huaraches, but I am currently very skeptical about running an entire marathon in them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m excited to be back for marathon running. I hope to have a stimulating adventure in the next three months as I train for and participate in the 2013 Pittsburgh Marathon!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-02-24&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-02-24)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/02/24/2013-pittsburgh-marathon-training-progress-since-signing-up-three-weeks-ago/&#34;&gt;A progress report describes setbacks to overcome.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thoughts on an unexpected winter barefoot run</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/01/20/thoughts-on-an-unexpected-winter-barefoot-run/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Jan 2013 08:14:12 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/01/20/thoughts-on-an-unexpected-winter-barefoot-run/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/barefoot-running-winter.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Barefoot running in winter&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, I went on my first ever &lt;em&gt;winter barefoot run&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; what you think; or maybe, it &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; what you think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;sunny-day&#34;&gt;Sunny day&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, there was still some snow on the ground. But it was purely residual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a sunny day. A &lt;em&gt;warm&lt;/em&gt; day, temperature of about 53 degrees F.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Originally I had planned to go for a run like I did a couple of days ago, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/17/winter-running-in-vibram-fivefingers-shoes-revisited/&#34;&gt;in Vibram FiveFingers shoes&lt;/a&gt;. But I changed my mind when I realized just how warm it was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Impulsively, I just hopped out the door in my short-sleeve T-shirt and shorts, and &lt;em&gt;barefoot&lt;/em&gt;, because it seemed that I could. What other winter have I had, during my lifetime spent in the northern United States, when I could go out running barefoot?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-run&#34;&gt;The run&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ended up running less than about three miles, because I faced some annoyances:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the roads and sidewalks were actually pretty cold&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;there was a lot of debris out there (ouch!), left behind after the snow melted; some of it was clearly salt crystals&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;putting-on-shoes&#34;&gt;Putting on shoes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ended up going back home and putting on my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/26/walking-and-running-in-invisible-shoes-a-review&#34;&gt;Xero Shoes (4mm Connect)&lt;/a&gt; that have become my favorite running footwear (when the weather allows; I stopped wearing them last fall shortly after the Great Race 10K, which was &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/30/running-my-10th-great-race-10k-obscene-but-in-a-good-way/&#34;&gt;my first race running in them&lt;/a&gt;). I felt much better wearing these huaraches and went back out to run another three miles.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/xero-shoes-winter.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Xero Shoes 4mm Connect&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;somber-thoughts&#34;&gt;Somber thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a good time running outside as though it were spring or fall, but actually, I get worried every time this winter I am able to do something like this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s not normal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it&amp;rsquo;s not good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wunderground.com/blog/weatherhistorian/comment.html?entrynum=112&#34;&gt;2012 was a record warm year for the continental United States&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s not pleasant contemplating &lt;a href=&#34;http://climate.nasa.gov/&#34;&gt;global climate change&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s been nice being able to run in winter here in Pittsburgh without being all bundled up. But that is a constant reminder to me that something weird has been happening to our planet.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Running my 10th Great Race 10K: &#34;obscene but in a good way&#34;</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/09/30/running-my-10th-great-race-10k-obscene-but-in-a-good-way/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Sep 2012 19:08:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/09/30/running-my-10th-great-race-10k-obscene-but-in-a-good-way/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/great-race-2012/great-race-expo.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Great Race quilt&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Today I ran in Pittsburgh&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://rungreatrace.com/&#34;&gt;Great Race 10K&lt;/a&gt; for the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/25/blistered-but-blissful-in-the-burgh/&#34;&gt;tenth time in my life&lt;/a&gt;. For various reasons, I performed a number of experiments for this tenth running of the race, doing things I&amp;rsquo;ve never done before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the race, I heard someone say, as I passed him:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
...obscene... but in a good way!
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It made my day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll explain what might have triggered this reaction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;preparation-and-uncertainty&#34;&gt;Preparation and uncertainty&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/07/running-my-8th-pretty-good-race-5k-dealing-with-disappointment/&#34;&gt;Pretty Good Race 5K&lt;/a&gt;, I was so tired out from my effort that I totally lost the desire to run. Plus my left foot was hurting more again. I ended up not running a single step for two weeks. This meant, of course, that there was no way I was going to go after the goal of beating last year&amp;rsquo;s time in the Great Race 10K.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, there was the question of whether I should even run the Great Race at all this year! Until almost the last minute, Abby and I agreed that if I did not feel up for running it at all, I would just sell my registration. Part of me felt bad about the possibility of breaking &amp;ldquo;tradition&amp;rdquo; and not running the race; I have stubbornly run it while horribly sick in some years! At the same time, it&amp;rsquo;s not really the end of the world if I miss a race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;change-of-purpose-and-plan-enter-the-invisible-shoes&#34;&gt;Change of purpose and plan: enter the Invisible Shoes!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eventually, after my two-week absence from running, my left foot injury resolved itself, and I started running again. The plan was to start road running (since I prefer to trail running) in preparation for the Great Race. The problem is that I actually don&amp;rsquo;t like wearing my road running Vibram FiveFingers shoes, my Bikila LS shoes. In fact, since my taste in footwear has become more and more minimalist over time, the Bikila LS shoes seem like a step totally in the wrong direction. I got them last year really only for the purpose of road racing, since the KSO blisters me and the KSO Trek is for the trails.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just to start running again, I began going out for 2-3 mile casual runs in my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/26/walking-and-running-in-invisible-shoes-a-review/&#34;&gt;Invisible Shoes&lt;/a&gt; that I&amp;rsquo;d been wearing all summer for walking, and sometimes for running. I enjoyed my short runs in these huaraches.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/great-race-2012/invisible-shoes-rolled.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Invisible Shoes rolled up&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Given that I was just getting back into running after such a long break, I never ran more than 3 miles during any of my runs leading up to the Great Race. And I never wore anything other than the Invisible Shoes. So that led me to the idea that since I wasn&amp;rsquo;t going to be able to achieve a goal of running super fast this year, I could set a &lt;em&gt;different goal&lt;/em&gt; for myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My new goal: &lt;em&gt;run the Great Race 10K in 4mm huaraches&lt;/em&gt;. More specifically, I wanted to see how my joints and muscles would hold up, as well as my feet and skin. Also, I&amp;rsquo;d never run fast in huaraches before, so this would also be an experiment in running fast in them. I had every intention of running pretty fast: I simply expected that I would not be able to run as fast as if I were running more protected shoes, because of many factors such as flopping soles and more pounding, resulting in my going more conservatively than if I had already experimented and knew what the limits were.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, originally I had planned to run a 5K race sometime in the huaraches; I had never planned to suddenly run a 10K in them without running a 5K first!! Also, I was going to run this 10K without having run more than 3 miles at a time in an entire month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;last-minute-panic-and-recovery&#34;&gt;Last minute panic and recovery&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Friday, I was coming down with a sore throat, and my boss said he and his son were both sick (they were both signed up for the Great Race this year). Now I was totally uncertain about whether I was going to run on Sunday. I tried to get healthy, and on Saturday, was feeling more stable, although a sore throat kept lingering, and picked up my race packet. Luckily, I was feeling great this morning, with no sign of a sore throat, so apparently my &amp;ldquo;placebos&amp;rdquo; worked (sleep, healthy food, various supplements). I canceled all my Saturday plans (such as going to a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/28/another-french-music-jam-also-announcing-cats-dance/&#34;&gt;French dance workshop&lt;/a&gt;) in order to rest up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other concern was the weather forecast. All week it seemed like it was going to rain sometime this morning. I&amp;rsquo;ve run in rain before, raced in rain before. I can do it. But the last time I ran in Invisible Shoes in the rain, I got into trouble. So now what? I simply decided I was going to deal with rain if it happened. Yet another variable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-race&#34;&gt;The race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;to-eat-or-not-to-eat&#34;&gt;To eat or not to eat?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One experiment I did today that I deem a big success: &lt;em&gt;I ate almost nothing before the race&lt;/em&gt;. I ate a bunch of almonds when I was leaving the house, but that was it. In the past, I always ate something more substantial before a race. Rationally, it does not make sense, but for some reason, I always felt that I should eat a mini-meal. This was completely irrational, a weird clinging behavior I engaged in: after all, when I casually go running in the morning, I do it before breakfast! So why should race day be any different? We human beings have enough fuel stored in our bodies. It&amp;rsquo;s true that when I go for a run of over, say, 8 miles, I get hungry, and like to either have a snack on me to eat, or have eaten right before going on the run, but when it comes to 5K and 10K races, clearly there is no need for me to eat before the race. Experience has shown that it only makes me feel sluggish. So from now on, &lt;em&gt;no more mini-meals before a race of 10K or shorter&lt;/em&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;shoes&#34;&gt;Shoes&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/great-race-2012/franklin-before.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin wearing Invisible Shoes and race number 1853&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/great-race-2012/feet-before.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin wearing Invisible Shoes&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As usual, I jogged a mile from home to the start line as my warmup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;beginning&#34;&gt;Beginning&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The temperature was in the low 50s F: ideal racing temperature, not too cold. Under 50, I would have worn a long-sleeve T-shirt instead of a short-sleeve one. As it was, since I anticipated rain, I did not wear my usual singlet but instead a standard short-sleeve T-shirt. It was not yet raining, thankfully!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some guy stepped on my right toes with his shoes as he wandered through the crowd. I was upset by this and hoped that my toes were OK. They were sore for a few minutes but then I forgot about them and was OK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within the first few minutes, I saw Don Slusser ahead of me; last year I had tracked him and then passed him at the end of the race. This year, he was obviously going much slower, thanks to his shot knees, so I passed him early on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I saw my boss standing on his street corner watching the race. I asked why he wasn&amp;rsquo;t running and he said he was too sick. It&amp;rsquo;s too bad he had to miss the race yet again, after missing it last year because of another commitment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My huaraches seemed to be working pretty well as I ran faster than I had ever run in them. I rather enjoyed being able to feel the ground, as though I were fully barefoot. At 4mm, running with these is pretty close to being barefoot, much closer than wearing Vibram FiveFingers shoes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wasn&amp;rsquo;t paying much attention to any glances or stares at my feet, or remarks people may have been making, although a few runners did directly ask me about my &amp;ldquo;flip flops&amp;rdquo;, with an attitude ranging from incredulity to amusement to admiration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;middle&#34;&gt;Middle&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Near halfway through the race, it started raining fairly steadily. I had to periodically wipe the water away from my eyes. Well, it was in the forecast. One thing I can say is that I was never in danger of overheating in this race! There have been instances of the Great Race in warm conditions under a sun, when even in a singlet I got very warm and had to dump water over my head: ha, today I got free water on my head constantly!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I started the race further back than I usually do, there were very few people running at exactly my pace. I was always either passing or being passed by people. This is one thing annoying about big races where people can cross the start mat at very different times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, at one point, a guy came to be in front of me who was running approximately my pace, so that I was almost a constant distance from him. On downhills I would tend to overtake him, but then he would come back. We would be mostly together for approximately the last two miles. At one point when I slowly passed him, I think I heard him say, &amp;ldquo;That&amp;rsquo;s obscene&amp;hellip; but in a good way!&amp;rdquo; I believe that comment was directed at me and my footwear, and I kind of took it as a compliment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;end&#34;&gt;End&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The water puddles were starting to get to me, as I had earlier feared. I did not feel confident about running any faster than I already was, given the road conditions and the way my huaraches were slipping around. And my toes were getting sore from the pounding. Normally, in the end of a race, I turn it on and try to use up the remaining energy I have, but today, I just did not feel confident in my footing. I continued going reasonably fast, but did not put in any finishing sprint at all. Even if I had wanted to, it would have been difficult, because of so many slower people in front of me. This is a direct consequence of my lining up at the start line far further back than I usually do: what happens is that slower people who started further up are in the way for the entirety of the race!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I did turn it on just enough to pass that guy I had been more or less with for two miles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;result&#34;&gt;Result&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My chip time was 48:23, not too bad given my footwear experimentation and lack of conditioning and failure to go all out in the final mile; last year&amp;rsquo;s time was 47:46. Next year, I would like to go under 47:00. I should be able to do that if I maintain a regular running regimen. 2006 was the last year that I went under 47:00.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;after-the-race&#34;&gt;After the race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got some water, was given two Smiley Cookies, and ate a bagel and a banana also. I hopped on the shuttle bus back to the start line (the ride took 30 minutes), then walked 25 minute (1.5 miles) back home in the cold. In the future, I don&amp;rsquo;t want to do this walk. I should park my car near the start line the night before, so that I can hop off the bus and drive home. It&amp;rsquo;s no fun to be walking so long in the cold when you&amp;rsquo;re tired and you&amp;rsquo;re not sure what the condition of your feet are, except that they hurt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are my feet after I got home:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/great-race-2012/feet-after.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin&amp;#39;s bare feet after race, at home&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It turns out that I got only one blister, and it was exactly where I got a blister last time I ran in the rain in the huaraches: between my first two toes. There was some roughing up of the callouses on the balls of my feet (from wearing the huaraches all summer), but otherwise, my feet were OK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After some more hours of recovery, I was feeling fine. No joint pain whatsoever, no muscle soreness whatsoever, none of that stuff. Even last year I had some stiffness when I got off the shuttle bus. My conclusion is that truly minimalist footwear trains me to land in such a way as to minimize problems to my body. No shin splints, no ankle soreness, no knee pain, no hip pain, no shot quads, no cramping calves, nothing. Just a blister, and toes and forefoot that were sore for a while but right now no longer are. It&amp;rsquo;s amazing what &lt;em&gt;no cushioning for the feet at all&lt;/em&gt; did to prevent the problems I used to face when running. I am so completely sold that I will look into running more races in huaraches, and in optimizing my lacing in order to prevent the flopping limitation and that one blister spot. I am consider going up to the 6mm sole from the 4mm sole, with the idea that 6mm would be more solid for racing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another thought: assuming a race with no rain or extreme cold or hot surfaces, I should run a race &lt;em&gt;barefoot&lt;/em&gt; sometime next year. I&amp;rsquo;ll think about this. I know people who have done this. Why not? Barefoot, one does not have to worry about blisters caused from laces, or sole flopping, or water slipping. One may have other worries instead, but knowing a course ahead of time can help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;photos&#34;&gt;Photos&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Official photos of me in action, including beating the guy I mentioned, are &lt;a href=&#34;http://orders.islandphoto.com/RACE/Proofs.aspx#26561404-00002-0026&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, but since they are copyrighted, I have not inserted them directly into my report here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The inaugural Liberty Mile: a review of Pittsburgh&#39;s first road mile race, a great community event</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/08/17/the-inaugural-liberty-mile-a-review-of-pittsburghs-first-road-mile-race/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Aug 2012 21:44:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/08/17/the-inaugural-liberty-mile-a-review-of-pittsburghs-first-road-mile-race/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/liberty-mile-2012.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin&amp;#39;s race number and Bikila LS shoes&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Tonight I was really excited to race in, and also watch, the inaugural &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.libertymile.org/&#34;&gt;GNC Live Well Liberty Mile&lt;/a&gt;, a road race that runs along Liberty Avenue in Pittsburgh, starting from the Strip District and ending downtown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s about time Pittsburgh had a road mile race! Pittsburgh already has the wonderful&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://rungreatrace.com/&#34;&gt;Great Race&lt;/a&gt;, which &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/25/blistered-but-blissful-in-the-burgh/&#34;&gt;I ran for my ninth time last year&lt;/a&gt; and will run for my tenth time this year (good think I pre-registered early, because today it &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburgh.cbslocal.com/2012/08/17/2012-great-race-officially-sold-out/&#34;&gt;already sold out!!&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pittsburghmarathon.com/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Marathon&lt;/a&gt;, which I&amp;rsquo;ve run once.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope this event is here to stay. Here&amp;rsquo;s my report on the event as both a runner and a spectator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-history-in-the-mile&#34;&gt;My history in the mile&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve run a mile race only twice before in my life, and that was on the track at Carnegie Mellon University. A decade ago, in June 2002, I ran in my first track mile, the Pittsylvania Mile on that track, and did it in 6:22. I could have run faster, but because of total inexperience, went out way too fast for the first quarter, doing it in 1:22, and paying the price in the other laps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following year, 2003, in probably my peak condition in my life, I improved, doing the Pittsylvania Mile in 6:10. I still went out too fast, in 1:26, had no sense of rhythm, slowed down a lot to try to compensate for going out too fast, then had too much energy at the end, which was wasted. Again, I had not trained for the mile distance at all, but happened to be in my peak condition anyway just because I was still conditioned from my intense training for the Pittsburgh Marathon that I had just done in May (my lifetime personal best in the 5K of 20:37 was achieved just two weeks after the Pittsburgh Marathon).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I never broke a 6-minute mile during my peak.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That was the last timed mile I ever ran, until tonight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;preparation&#34;&gt;Preparation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, I wasn&amp;rsquo;t prepared for the mile at all. Apart from not having run much because of a non-running injury to my left leg that happened a month ago (from which I have fully recovered), I have just come back from a week of unexpected travel and am still kind of recovering from that. And no speed work to speak of in the past month, other than a few random sprints (which I do for general physical conditioning when I don&amp;rsquo;t do much else).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had no idea what &amp;ldquo;mile pace&amp;rdquo; feels like. I just figured I would run a bit faster than 5K pace (which I always have a reasonable feel for).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hoped to finish somewhere near 6:30.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;dr-vonda-wright&#34;&gt;Dr. Vonda Wright&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://vondawright.com/images/stories/vonda-at-work.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Vonda Wright&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I bumped into &lt;a href=&#34;http://vondawright.com/&#34;&gt;Dr. Vonda Wright&lt;/a&gt; while heading toward the start line, and thanked her for her support of those of us who care about maintaining our health as we get older. I want to plug her great work in promoting lifetime fitness, especially for those over 40. She has written a book &lt;a href=&#34;http://vondawright.com/index.php?option=com_content&amp;amp;view=article&amp;amp;id=62&amp;amp;Itemid=83&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Fitness After 40&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; which is pretty good and has a lot of scientifically-backed tips on remaining strong and vital and even reversing what used to be considered &amp;ldquo;normal aging&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I heard about Dr. Wright from a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/01/20/cmu-fitness-challenge-keynote-lecture-by-vonda-wright-stay-strong-at-any-age/&#34;&gt;CMU &amp;ldquo;healthy campus week&amp;rdquo; talk she gave this January&lt;/a&gt;. Even though I had already known some of what she advocated, I was impressed that she summarized well the whole gamut of what we now know to be effective ways to increase strength and flexibility and avoid injury. Again, I recommend her books to anyone of any age who wants to be smart about diet and exercise and more than that, a whole philosophical approach to living in general.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-race-in-waves&#34;&gt;The race, in waves&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The race was held in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.libertymile.org/Race-Waves.asp&#34;&gt;waves separated by ten or twenty minutes&lt;/a&gt;. This is obviously necessary because of the variation in people&amp;rsquo;s speed. The slower, open waves were held first, and the elite racers were in the final waves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;early-waves&#34;&gt;Early waves&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I arrived to pick up my race number when the first wave was already in progress. There was a bit of confusion in the first two waves because a good number of people arrived late or were unclear about when to run, and therefore missed the first wave. Most of these seemed to be kids. By the way, it was great to see so many kids at the Liberty Mile. Running a 5K (3.1-mile) race can be daunting for a kid, but a single mile is surely a great introduction to many kids (and adults too!) to the joy of running. I think it is really great that the Liberty Mile is not just an elite race, but also a race anyone can participate in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;my-race-in-the-masters-wave&#34;&gt;My race, in the Masters wave&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Masters &amp;ldquo;Winning at 40+&amp;rdquo; wave was the first qualification-required wave.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ran in this serious, competitive wave, not one of the open waves, because I easily qualified to run in this wave, whose requirement was proof of ability to run an 8-minute mile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lining up, I saw a lot of really fit-looking people in this wave, many of whom were clearly well over 40. In any case, anyone who looked anywhere near my age (42) was obviously going to kick my butt all the way to the moon. There was no chance for an age-group prize for me today! No problem: as a non-elite racer, I don&amp;rsquo;t race for prizes, but just to do the best that I can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ended up running &lt;a href=&#34;http://runhigh.com/2012RESULTS/R081712AD.html&#34;&gt;6:38.8&lt;/a&gt;, good for 26th place out of 27 in my age group, ha! I was disappointed that I didn&amp;rsquo;t make 6:30 as I had originally hoped when I signed up a month ago, but that&amp;rsquo;s OK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the first quarter, I ran 1:29; oops, went out too fast yet again! &lt;strong&gt;I hereby pledge that before the next mile race I run, I will actually train and learn not to go out too fast.&lt;/strong&gt; There is no excuse for running three mile races going out too fast. I don&amp;rsquo;t go out too fast in 5K or longer distances, after all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the second and third quarters, 1:46 and 1:46 showed that I had gone out too fast. I did save something for the sprint finish, however, and did the final quarter in 1:38.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A serious and unexpected problem I had while running this race was that my mouth got very dry and I had trouble breathing as a result. It was pretty weird. I don&amp;rsquo;t exactly remember this in my mile races from a decade ago. I did hydrate considerably before the race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, of course, as I do in 5K races, I felt like puking during the final quarter, and my arms were getting tingly and losing sensation. It&amp;rsquo;s just what happens to me in the final push. I believe there is no way to avoid feeling like puking if I&amp;rsquo;m running as hard as I can, but I have a feeling that the problem with my arms has to do with my tightening up (rather than relaxing) and flailing around. I plan to try to fix that for my next races this month and next month; what is required, clearly, is disciplined speed work, which is something I have not done in years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;enjoying-being-a-spectator&#34;&gt;Enjoying being a spectator&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The really cool thing about a mile race held in waves is that you get to be a spectator for the remaining waves after you&amp;rsquo;re done. In a 5K race or longer, there aren&amp;rsquo;t any heats and you never get to be a spectator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was wowed watching the &amp;ldquo;Unstoppable&amp;rdquo; under-40 wave whose qualification time was running faster than 6:00. Watching good, fast running is a real pleasure to me, like watching skilled dancers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also a treat was getting to watch the female elite wave and male elite wave. These &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/27/why-i-do-not-watch-the-olympics-any-more/&#34;&gt;Olympic&lt;/a&gt;-caliber runners looked so elegant with their long, powerful strides.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-shoes&#34;&gt;My shoes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d been considering running a race soon wearing my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/26/walking-and-running-in-invisible-shoes-a-review/&#34;&gt;Invisible Shoes huaraches&lt;/a&gt;, but without testing them out with speed work, I&amp;rsquo;m not ready to go there yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I wore the shoes I&amp;rsquo;ve been &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/23/happiness-is-finishing-39th-of-43-men-in-a-race/&#34;&gt;road racing in for almost a full year now&lt;/a&gt;, the Vibram FiveFingers Bikila LS. They worked out just fine. I didn&amp;rsquo;t get blistered because it was cool and it was only a mile. Next month I&amp;rsquo;ll see whether I get blistered in the Great Race &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/25/blistered-but-blissful-in-the-burgh/&#34;&gt;the way I did last year&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;race-organization&#34;&gt;Race organization&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought the race was pretty well-organized, especially given that this was the first time such a race has been held in Pittsburgh. Thanks go to the sponsors, the timers, the announcers, the volunteers who handed out race numbers and stocked water and bagels at the finish line and handed out goodie bags and T-shirts, the police officers who closed the roads and lanes where necessary and directed traffic and kept Liberty Avenue clear, the spectators who cheered, the providers of the many port-a-johns near the start line, the &lt;a href=&#34;http://bringbackthemile.com/news/detail/Miller_and_Kampf_Win_GNC_Live_Well_Liberty_Mile&#34;&gt;elite runners who put on a display of amazing running&lt;/a&gt;. Everyone without question was helpful and friendly. The whole experience was just wonderful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The inaugural GNC Live Well Liberty Mile was a great event. I hope it is the beginning of a Pittsburgh tradition that, like the Great Race and the Pittsburgh Marathon, will continue for years and decades to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-08-09&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-08-09)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/08/09/getting-up-when-reality-punches-you-in-the-face-running-the-second-liberty-mile-in-pittsburgh/&#34;&gt;I ran the second Liberty Mile a year later.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>