<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Coriander India Grill on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/coriander-india-grill/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Coriander India Grill on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/coriander-india-grill/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>11 Pittsburgh bridge crossings in one 12-mile run</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/03/09/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings-in-one-12-mile-run/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Mar 2013 21:21:26 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/03/09/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings-in-one-12-mile-run/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://sphotos-b.xx.fbcdn.net/hphotos-ash3/602768_422297731198378_798317370_n.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;View from Mount Washington&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My first ever &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.steelcityrrc.org/scrrcevents?eventId=568739&amp;amp;EventViewMode=2&amp;amp;CalendarViewType=1&amp;amp;SelectedDate=3/16/2013&#34;&gt;Steel City Road Runners Saturday morning training run&lt;/a&gt; was a 12-mile run. My office mate John went with me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last time I ran as far as 12 miles &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/02/24/2013-pittsburgh-marathon-training-progress-since-signing-up-three-weeks-ago/&#34;&gt;was in February&lt;/a&gt;, so I expected to do OK. The important difference is that I have been increasing my weekly mileage. I had a monster training week last week, going up from 13 miles to 26 miles last week, the &lt;em&gt;largest&lt;/em&gt; training volume I have had in a single week in years. I&amp;rsquo;ll confess that this has taken a toll on me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result, I have backed off this week, such that including this 12-mile run (I will not run tomorrow), this week I will have 23 miles. In the long haul, &lt;em&gt;overtraining&lt;/em&gt; is a huge waste of time and energy. Unfortunately, in my attempt to &amp;ldquo;catch up&amp;rdquo; some because of the marathon coming in less than two months, I did in fact overtrain to an extent; last week I ran five out of seven days in order to reach that mileage of 26. This week, I tried to up the mileage but felt tired and wisely decided to rest when I needed to, even though that meant this week I ran only three days! Obviously, in retrospect, it would have been wiser to run four days last week and four this week, with better overall training.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I did enjoy today&amp;rsquo;s training run. It involved the most bridge crossings I have ever done in my life in a single day (by foot or otherwise): eleven!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is my report on the training run, including, of course, photos of bridge crossings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;sign-in&#34;&gt;Sign in&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;John and I signed in at 8 AM. It was going to be a beautiful, sunny day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We received printed maps of the route. I did have my smartphone with me, wearing it in my SPIbelt, so I felt pretty safe about knowing where I am or where to go in case I got lost.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings/sign-in.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Steel City Road Runners sign in&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There is indoor access to restrooms, water fountains, and warmth at these Steel City Road Runners training run meetings. Very nice for winter!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were designated pacers. I was uncertain about which pace group I should join, if any at all. I felt that probably the 10-minute pace group might be on the slow side, but definitely I did not expect to keep up with the 9-minute pace group for a long run. But we decided to start off with the 9-minute pace group and see what happens.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings/pace-groups.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Pacers&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I wore my Vibram FiveFingers Bikila LS shoes, which have been my main running shoes all winter (when there is no snow or water on the ground):&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings/vibram-fivefingers-bikila-ls.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin wearing Vibram FiveFingers Bikila LS&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-route&#34;&gt;The route&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is the route of the 12-mile training run:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe id=&#34;mapmyfitness_route&#34; src=&#34;http://snippets.mapmycdn.com/routes/view/embedded/178234904?width=560&amp;height=400&amp;elevation=true&amp;info=true&amp;line_color=E60f0bdb&amp;rgbhex=DB0B0E&amp;distance_markers=1&amp;unit_type=imperial&amp;map_mode=TERRAIN&amp;last_updated=2013-03-08T12:47:36-06:00&#34; height=&#34;590px&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: right; padding-right: 20px;&#34;&gt;&lt;a target=&#34;_blank&#34; href=&#34;http://mapmyrun.com/routes/create/&#34;&gt;Create Maps&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a target=&#34;_blank&#34; href=&#34;http://mapmyrun.com/routes/&#34;&gt;search&lt;/a&gt; from 80 million at &lt;a href=&#34;http://mapmyrun.com&#34;&gt;MapMyRun&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-bridge-crossings&#34;&gt;The bridge crossings&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 9-minute pace group was clearly going too fast for me. I hung off the back hoping to simply keep them in sight as they kept getting more ahead of me. To my surprise, John went with the group, even though he has not run in months. I was not sure it was wise of him not to have done any running before this training run, and am worried about his going too fast all of a sudden.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings/on-our-way.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;nine-minute pace group&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;rachel-carson-bridge-inbound-over-the-allegheny-river&#34;&gt;Rachel Carson Bridge, inbound over the Allegheny River&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings/rachel-carson-bridge.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;On Rachel Carson Bridge inbound&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We can see downtown Pittsburgh:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings/rachel-carson-bridge-see-downtown.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;On Rachel Carson Bridge, seeing downtown&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;7th-street-bridge-outbound&#34;&gt;7th Street Bridge, outbound&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings/7th-street-bridge.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;On 7th Street Bridge outbound&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;roberto-clemente-bridge-inbound&#34;&gt;Roberto Clemente Bridge, inbound&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings/roberto-clemente-bridge.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Approaching Roberto Clemente Bridge inbound&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;fort-duquesne-bridge-outbound&#34;&gt;Fort Duquesne Bridge, outbound&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings/fort-duquesne-bridge.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;On Fort Duquesne Bridge outbound&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;west-end-bridge-south-over-the-monongahela-river&#34;&gt;West End Bridge, south over the Monongahela River&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings/west-end-bridge.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;On West End Bridge south&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;first-water-stop-and-getting-lost&#34;&gt;First water stop and getting lost!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our first water stop was after 4 miles:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings/first-water-stop.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;First water stop&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;By the time I had reached this water stop, John and the rest of the 9-minute pace group were way ahead of me and barely visible. Unfortunately, after I drank some Gatorade, I noticed that I didn&amp;rsquo;t see them at all any more. So for almost the rest of the run, the following 8 miles, I was mostly alone! This was disconcerting because it meant that I&amp;rsquo;d have to try to follow the printed map and directions, and avoid getting lost. It would turn out that I would get lost a couple of times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;fort-pitt-bridge-inbound&#34;&gt;Fort Pitt Bridge, inbound&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings/fort-pitt-bridge.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;On Fort Pitt Bridge inbound&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;smithfield-street-bridge-outbound&#34;&gt;Smithfield Street Bridge, outbound&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings/smithfield-street-bridge.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;On Smithfield Street Bridge outbound&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Check out this view of bridges along the Monongahela River:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings/monongahela-river.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Monongahela River&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;10th-street-bridge-inbound&#34;&gt;10th Street Bridge, inbound&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leaving the South Side:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings/10th-street-bridge.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;On 10th Street Bridge inbound&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;liberty-bridge-outbound&#34;&gt;Liberty Bridge, outbound&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not having anyone to follow, I got confused about how to get onto the Liberty Bridge, missing the steps, and had to do some backtracking to find the way to get on.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings/liberty-bridge-outbound.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;On Liberty Bridge outbound&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;to-mount-washington&#34;&gt;To Mount Washington&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This training run featured a big, long uphill to Mount Washington, with a water stop at the very top!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings/to-mount-washington.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;To Mount Washington&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;After being alone for quite some time, I did encounter John and other runners coming back down Mount Washington when I was still going up. They were going really fast downhill!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings/up-to-mount-washington.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Uphill to Mount Washington&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;second-water-stop&#34;&gt;Second water stop&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My phone started acting funny when I got to the water stop at the top of Mount Washington, so I did not bother to try take any more photos after that. I was bummed that I didn&amp;rsquo;t get a photo of the view of Pittsburgh from the top, but someone did and posted it on Facebook, so here it is:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://sphotos-b.xx.fbcdn.net/hphotos-ash3/602768_422297731198378_798317370_n.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;View from Mount Washington&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At this water stop, at mile 9, I felt hungry, and saw some GU gels, and took one and ate it before continuing my run. It was &lt;a href=&#34;http://guenergy.com/products/products-roctane-gels&#34;&gt;GU Roctane&lt;/a&gt;. I didn&amp;rsquo;t look at the ingredients till after I got home and did a Web search on it. That explained a lot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While running down from Mount Washington, I felt a surge of energy and decided to run really, really fast, in hope of possibly catching sight of John at some point. In fact, I did not see any runner again for the next 3 miles until I reached the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;back-across-the-liberty-bridge-inbound&#34;&gt;Back across the Liberty Bridge, inbound&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then running through downtown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;16th-street-bridge-outbound&#34;&gt;16th Street Bridge outbound&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was kind of zoned out and missed the turn onto the bridge because I was just running fast, but luckily, I was off by just a block before I realized my mistake and backtracked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-end&#34;&gt;The end&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got back to the start in a bit less than two hours, so given my rest stops and getting lost, I definitely averaged under 10-minute pace. But I was definitely not running anywhere near 9-minute pace. I&amp;rsquo;ll keep that in my mind for the next training run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;John had finished well before me, but he himself had gotten lost near the end also.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We snacked on provided orange slices and chips:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings/after.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Steel City Road Runners snacks&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings/franklin.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Then I drove us back to our places. After both of us had showered and changed, we met up for lunch buffet at Coriander India Grill, a favorite place to eat &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/02/26/snowing-means-sambar-at-coriander-india-grill/&#34;&gt;after getting very hungry after a lot of exercise&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-next&#34;&gt;What next?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next week will be an 18-mile training run. As I have mentioned, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/02/24/2013-pittsburgh-marathon-training-progress-since-signing-up-three-weeks-ago/&#34;&gt;I do not intend to actually do such a long run&lt;/a&gt;, so I will think of a good way to run 16 miles instead: either I start walking earlier, or I walk near the end. And for sure, I will start with the 10-minute pace group rather than then 9-minute pace group. These training runs are not races. I don&amp;rsquo;t want to run too fast. In fact, I&amp;rsquo;m worried that I ran the last 3 miles today too fast, especially downhill from Mount Washington. My left knee is feeling a little funny. I hope it will recover after a day of rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve started to figure out the gel thing. I used eat gels a decade ago, but stopped because I had no reason to, but on these long runs, they do help, and I have to start planning what to use for fuel in the Pittsburgh Marathon, which will officially supply GU gel and Gatorade. I did learn, after the fact, that GU Roctane contains an insane amount of caffeine, and that&amp;rsquo;s probably what got me all hopped up to run super fast, but to my detriment today. So I need to be careful if I use Roctane in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a very instructive and tiring training run. I have a long way to go before being ready for the marathon in less than two months, but am happy to have finally joined a group training run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m very grateful for the opportunity to train with the Steel City Road Runners. Sometimes, it is much easier to commit to getting up early and going for a long run when you know that you&amp;rsquo;ll have company, that there will be support (in the form of a planned route and aid stations). Even for an introvert like me who usually prefers to run alone, the unique pains of marathon training cause me to value camaraderie for some tough runs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Snowing means sambar at Coriander India Grill</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/02/26/snowing-means-sambar-at-coriander-india-grill/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Feb 2012 12:10:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/02/26/snowing-means-sambar-at-coriander-india-grill/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/coriander-grill/store-front.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Coriander Grill&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, there was snow in Pittsburgh (almost all melted today, of course).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I had originally planned to be going on a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/pittsburghhikers/events/50162262/&#34;&gt;Meetup hike at Ohiopyle&lt;/a&gt;, carpooling with John, but on Friday we bailed out because of the weather forecast. We&amp;rsquo;ve done that hike a couple of times before, and will certainly do it again when it&amp;rsquo;s repeated in warmer weather anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Snow, however little there is of it, always makes me want to eat &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sambar_(dish)&#34;&gt;sambar&lt;/a&gt;. I love Indian food, and for some reason, I especially like sambar. Once every month or two, I crave going to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.coriandergrill.com/&#34;&gt;Coriander India Grill&lt;/a&gt; in Squirrel Hill, just a couple of blocks from where we live, to eat sambar and other good stuff. We&amp;rsquo;ve been to Coriander Grill several times, on different days and for lunch and dinner. There has been inconsistency, but I have reason to believe that lunch buffet on Saturday is a good time to go to Coriander.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/coriander-grill/sambar.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Sambar&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So the three of us went to Coriander for lunch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2014-01-13&#34;&gt;(Update of 2014-01-13)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I went to Coriander Grill for a Sunday dinner buffet yesterday, because we were hungry after a long hike, and I thought it would be a good idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We hadn&amp;rsquo;t been to Coriander for a while. They restricted their buffet days and increased the price. What we didn&amp;rsquo;t realize was that they also restricted the selection severely. Also, they kept on running out of food and not refilling frequently enough. Finally, we didn&amp;rsquo;t feel too well afterwards. I had a sleepless night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was very, very disappointed, and can no longer recommend Coriander Grill for their buffet. It is, of course, possible that their regular menu is still fine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;more-on-coriander-grill&#34;&gt;More on Coriander Grill&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The non-buffet menu at Coriander Grill is substantial. Abby and I have been there for dinner and sampled their &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Goa&#34;&gt;Goa&lt;/a&gt; Portuguese meat-based selections, for example. They also have Indian-Chinese dishes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lunch buffet is varied enough, and rotates, such that there is always something different there when we go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;preparation-for-lunch&#34;&gt;Preparation for lunch&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might be thinking, &amp;ldquo;Preparation for eating at a lunch buffet?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You bet. Eating at a buffet is &lt;em&gt;serious business&lt;/em&gt;, not to be undertaken lightly. It requires preparation of &lt;em&gt;mind, body, and spirit&lt;/em&gt;. (For amusement, check out this blog post on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://milkmiracle.net/2010/09/25/buffet/&#34;&gt;proper way to eat an an Indian buffet&lt;/a&gt;; please note that I am nowhere as &amp;ldquo;serious&amp;rdquo; as this guy, however.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;fasting&#34;&gt;Fasting&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The number one rule of eating at a buffet is, I plan to eat &lt;em&gt;a lot&lt;/em&gt;. A lot of &lt;em&gt;variety&lt;/em&gt;, and also a lot of volume. To do this effectively, fasting is necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe that &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.marksdailyapple.com/fasting/&#34;&gt;intermittent fasting&lt;/a&gt; is a good thing. I even believe that intermittent bingeing is a good thing. We are evolved to adapt to changes in food availability. Our bodies and minds are not designed to do the same thing over and over again, because then adaptation kicks in and we lose our physical and mental sharpness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that I didn&amp;rsquo;t eat very much on Friday (and had lost some weight during the week that I needed to make up), so on Saturday morning, when we decided to eat at Coriander, I was already partially prepared. Skipping breakfast was of course mandatory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;exercise&#34;&gt;Exercise&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did half an hour of intense exercise before lunch. I have learned from experience that exercise right before eating (whether for a buffet or just an ordinary meal) is effective in reducing gain of fat, redirecting toward muscle gain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, &lt;a href=&#34;http://ezinearticles.com/?Fasted-Cardio---Exercise-on-an-Empty-Stomach&amp;amp;id=4979785&#34;&gt;exercising on an empty stomach&lt;/a&gt; has additional benefits. Again, think about evolution. Our hunter-gatherer ancestors did not have &lt;sup&gt;24&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;7&lt;/sub&gt; access to junk food at all times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: usually, I do &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; exercise on a fully empty stomach, because there are drawbacks as well, as I learned from experience. Generally, I have found that eating a handful of nuts and possibly some dried fruit before exercising is optimal for me, in giving me some energy flow while keeping my head clear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;knowing-what-not-to-eat&#34;&gt;Knowing what not to eat&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no avoiding fatty, salty, starchy, sugary foods at a buffet. That&amp;rsquo;s part of the full experience. And that&amp;rsquo;s why I don&amp;rsquo;t eat at a buffet often, even a nice one like Coriander&amp;rsquo;s just blocks away from home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there are some guidelines that are very useful. The main thing is, I &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; eat rice or bread at a buffet. You don&amp;rsquo;t have to be &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/paleo/&#34;&gt;paleo&lt;/a&gt; or on some official low-carb diet to know that this is not worth the money, the bloat in your stomach, the wrecked blood sugar, and the fat gain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At an Indian buffet, I&amp;rsquo;m not really going to eat paleo-style. However, I&amp;rsquo;ll try to take it easy on breaded foods and especially the potatoes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;lunch-buffet&#34;&gt;Lunch buffet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lunch buffet offers two soups, a good selection of hot foods (including both meat/poultry/fish and vegetarian selections), and a cold section of salad, fruit, dessert.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/coriander-grill/two-soups.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Two soups provided&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/coriander-grill/buffet-left.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Left side of warm buffet&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/coriander-grill/buffet-right.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Right side of warm buffet&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/coriander-grill/buffet-cold.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Cold buffet&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-i-ate&#34;&gt;What I ate&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ate five rounds of food for lunch. (Yes, this was basically my meal for the entire day. In the evening yesterday, I did eat an apple and a snack, but no more than that.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first round (which I forgot to take a photo of), I ate a plate of hot food (Indian-Chinese chicken, fried veggie fritters, spinach, cauliflower/potatoes) and a full cup of sambar. I know the fried, breaded veggie fritters are not the healthiest food or buffet-optimal, but I enjoy having some.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For round 2, I had a bit of creamy chicken, vegetable korma, chickpeas, lentil dal, and more of the cauliflower/potatoes (I love that stuff). I am not a fan of creamy chicken or korma, but I always try a little bit of it because it&amp;rsquo;s there. I do very much like chickpeas and dal.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/coriander-grill/round-2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Round 2&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For round 3, I got more chickpeas, more dal, more spinach, more cauliflower/potatoes, my last veggie fritter, and a Tandoori-style chicken leg.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/coriander-grill/round-3.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Round 3&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For round 4, I got more Indian-Chinese chicken, more spinach, more chickpeas, more cauliflower/potatoes, and another cup of sambar! Halfway through this plate, I knew I was basically done eating.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/coriander-grill/round-4.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Round 4&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For my final round, I got a bit of salad (tomato, cucumber, lettuce, pickle, with some chutney), and a bit of cantaloupe and honeydew, and a wedge of lime. I like sucking lemon or lime at the end of a meal.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/coriander-grill/round-5.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Round 5&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;That was a lot of food! That was even more food than I normally eat at a buffet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and John ate some sugary desserts, but I had no room and no desire to have some myself. As I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/02/20/enjoying-more-french-dancing-in-pittsburgh/&#34;&gt;remembered recently&lt;/a&gt; at Gullifty&amp;rsquo;s, eating sugary desserts does not work well for me. I&amp;rsquo;ve resolved to do it only if something seems like it will be particularly tasty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;consequences&#34;&gt;Consequences&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I weighed myself when I got home. I had gained four pounds from the moment I left home to the point of return.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did end up getting sleepy in the afternoon and took a nap. I needed it anyway though, and I felt great the rest of the day, like I&amp;rsquo;d rebooted my body and satisfied some cravings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did gain quite a bit of extra weight, and pushed my fat percentage by one percent, but I know from experience this is temporary. My appetite today has been low, so I have naturally been eating less, and in a day or two I will have returned to my &amp;ldquo;normal&amp;rdquo; weight and fat percentage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like eating at buffets once every month or two. Having variety and knowing that I am giving my permission to eat all I want, rather than my usual policy of being much more moderate, adds a bit of excitement to my life, while probably also giving physical health benefits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-11-08&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-11-08)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year a new Indian restaurant opened in Pittsburgh, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.allindiapgh.com/&#34;&gt;All India&lt;/a&gt;. It is by far my favorite Indian restaurant in town now.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>