<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Randy Brecker on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/randy-brecker/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Randy Brecker on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/randy-brecker/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Attending the annual Pitt Jazz Seminar for the first time: day 2</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/11/03/attending-the-annual-pitt-jazz-seminar-for-the-first-time/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Nov 2012 20:52:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/11/03/attending-the-annual-pitt-jazz-seminar-for-the-first-time/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.music.pitt.edu/sites/default/files/jazz-2012-cropped.jpg?1350921512&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;42nd Pitt Jazz Seminar poster&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/11/02/attending-the-annual-pitt-jazz-seminar-for-the-first-time-day-1/&#34;&gt;Yesterday&lt;/a&gt;, I attended some morning sessions of the annual Pitt Jazz Seminar. I went back for more today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-tribute-to-miles&#34;&gt;A tribute to Miles&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;randy-brecker-http-randybrecker-com-trumpet&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://randybrecker.com/&#34;&gt;Randy Brecker&lt;/a&gt;, trumpet&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I liked how Randy Brecker talked about how he got into music. He listened to a lot of records as a kid, and at some point he started improvising during piano solos, by ear. He started with ballads (by Miles, Chet, etc.) and played with his brother &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.michaelbrecker.com/&#34;&gt;Michael&lt;/a&gt; (who sadly died some years ago).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;lew-soloff-http-www-lewsoloff-com-trumpet&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lewsoloff.com/&#34;&gt;Lew Soloff&lt;/a&gt;, trumpet&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lew Soloff came from a very different world. He stopped piano lessons at ten because his teachers did not emphasize &lt;em&gt;music&lt;/em&gt;, but &amp;ldquo;holding the hand a certain way&amp;rdquo;. He wanted trumpet because it was &lt;em&gt;shiny&lt;/em&gt;. Ha! Reminded me that it doesn&amp;rsquo;t matter why you start doing something; often you have a perhaps superficial reason, and find deeper reasons later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His uncle emphasized the importance of &lt;em&gt;practice&lt;/em&gt; and admonished him for being interested in too many things. Some tips on mental attitudes: never say &amp;ldquo;I can&amp;rsquo;t&amp;rdquo;, and also drop your &lt;em&gt;ego&lt;/em&gt;: learn from your peers. So in one summer, he went from last chair to first chair, practicing one and a half hours each day!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lew had a classical music training and therefore at first was scared to improvise. He had to overcome that fear. He also had to learn to articulate in &amp;ldquo;doodle tongue&amp;rdquo; rather than in the classical way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He said he eventually became open to all kinds of music, where in the past he was closed. He has a different take than Duke Ellington&amp;rsquo;s famous quote, &amp;ldquo;There are two kinds of music, good music and the other kind&amp;rdquo;: instead, Lew likes to think that the two kinds are the &lt;em&gt;honest&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;dishonest&lt;/em&gt;. I like this formulation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Randy piped in saying that he became musically open because that was just the way things were in Philadelphia, where there are so many styles.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Advice: when learning ballads, first play them &lt;em&gt;without&lt;/em&gt; improvisation, focusing on purity and honesty, and expressing emotion as though singing. Learn the lyrics and understand them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;artistry-in-rhythm-winard-harper-http-www-winardharper-com-drums&#34;&gt;Artistry in rhythm: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.winardharper.com/&#34;&gt;Winard Harper&lt;/a&gt;, drums&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Winard Harper spoke of coming from a musical family and playing at clubs by the time he was five years old. He emphasized the importance of relationships in making music come together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He&amp;rsquo;s really into an African instrument that I never heard of before called a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Balafon&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;balafon&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. More generally, he is interested in all kinds of world music, whether from Africa, Australia, Japan. He urged everyone to honor tradition, learn history, and do a lot of playing and listening. &amp;ldquo;The more you know, the more you can use&amp;rdquo;. He summed up with the message that as a drummer, when jamming, you have to face all kinds of situations, drums that are not yours, etc., and you have to learn to deal, because it&amp;rsquo;s not about you but about music. Sounds wise no matter what instrument we play!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-piano-in-jazz-george-cables-http-georgecables-com&#34;&gt;The piano in jazz: &lt;a href=&#34;http://georgecables.com/&#34;&gt;George Cables&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;George Cables emphasized that jazz is living music, through which everyone can become a &amp;ldquo;co-composer&amp;rdquo; through arranging and improvising.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a pianist, he didn&amp;rsquo;t want to be a soloist so much as a good side man. He was most inspired by Wynton Kelly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Musically, he emphasized that the piano is a percussion instrument. He also gave a history lesson on the piano in jazz, starting from Scott Joplin and moving forward from there. He said the progression was toward &amp;ldquo;freeing the bass&amp;rdquo;, allowing the left hand to do a lot more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(I had to leave this session a little early because I wanted to make it to a special recorder concert elsewhere in town.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found it very interesting and useful attending Pitt Jazz Seminar sessions these past two days, featuring very different musicians on different instruments, getting a broad perspective on how they operate and what they value and what they have to teach. I hope to continue attending this annual event!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>