<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Ukulele on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/ukulele/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Ukulele on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/ukulele/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Third year at July 3 music party and finally participated in jamming</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/07/03/third-year-at-july-3-music-party-and-finally-participated-in-jamming/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jul 2014 22:11:59 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/07/03/third-year-at-july-3-music-party-and-finally-participated-in-jamming/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;The past two years, Abby and I have gone to an annual July 3 music potluck/party, and we went again this year. Both &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/03/petrified-at-a-music-jam-session-so-i-didnt-play-but-watched-and-listened/&#34;&gt;in 2012&lt;/a&gt; as well as &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/07/03/second-year-at-july-3-music-party-still-only-listening-without-playing/&#34;&gt;in 2013&lt;/a&gt;, I was too intimidated to participate in music jamming, and only watched. This year I was determined to contribute, and I brought my ukulele (which I only started learning &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/08/23/another-unexpected-life-change-one-month-of-learning-to-play-ukulele/&#34;&gt;a month after last year&amp;rsquo;s party&lt;/a&gt;, actually) and my Irish flute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;piano&#34;&gt;Piano&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After my first round of food at the potluck, I went to Susan&amp;rsquo;s piano and played David Raksin&amp;rsquo;s theme from &amp;ldquo;Laura&amp;rdquo;, which I had so botched up last month at the annual Pittsburgh Recorder Society potluck/recital. I play it much better now, although I somehow messed up the final chords today. There were a few people sitting around listening, and they wanted to hear more, but I didn&amp;rsquo;t have any more, so I scurried away to eat more food.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;old-time&#34;&gt;Old time&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As dinner started winding down, the old time musicians started gathering outside to play. I saw fiddles, banjos, and other instruments make an appearance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;blues&#34;&gt;Blues&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inside, the main guy who plays guitar and ukulele unpacked his soprano ukulele, and so I took out my concert ukulele, and two other guys with guitars appeared. Eventually a woman who sang also appeared, as well as a guy on fiddle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I felt very intimidated, because although I&amp;rsquo;ve gotten some experience jamming while on recorder or flute or tin whistle, my ukulele experience &lt;em&gt;without written music&lt;/em&gt; is still very minimal. Nevertheless, I joined in. I fumbled around, and had to ask what key each song was being played in, and even then, I&amp;rsquo;m still quite shaky in anticipating and knowing chord changes beyond the simplest I, IV, V, and some dominant and major 7th chords. I strummed very softly.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/music-2014-07-04/jamming.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Music jamming&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;They&amp;rsquo;re a great bunch, improvising melodic lines at will and even making up lyrics right on the spot, just as they had at the last two years when I only watched. And the singing in harmony was fantastic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby got a little bit of video footage of us at one point:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/zYb1aBioAao&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For two years, I was afraid to join in the music jams at this annual July 3 party. This year I joined in a little bit. If we attend the party again next year, I hope to be in a position to contribute even more! Many thanks to Susan for hosting this annual party!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Steel City Ukuleles: navigating a challenging playlist</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/03/19/steel-city-ukuleles-navigating-a-challenging-playlist/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2014 21:32:31 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/03/19/steel-city-ukuleles-navigating-a-challenging-playlist/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/steel-city-ukuleles-2014-03-19.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Group photo&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Two weeks ago, I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/03/05/thoughts-on-returning-to-ukulele-after-almost-two-months-off/&#34;&gt;returned to attending Steel City Ukuleles meetings&lt;/a&gt; after almost two months off, and I &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/Steel-City-Ukuleles/events/158392572/&#34;&gt;attended again tonight&lt;/a&gt;; my habit since starting out last summer has been to attend the regular first and third Wednesday meetings in Regent Square. Although I have been thinking of cutting back to attending once a month instead of twice a month, I was intrigued by the rather ambitious playlist Adam created for this week, so I couldn&amp;rsquo;t resist going, even though it meant conflicting with a newly revived regular &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/french-dance/&#34;&gt;French dance music jam&lt;/a&gt; that I haven&amp;rsquo;t attended in half a year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adam started off with some easy blues, but soon we were launching into songs with pauses or other &amp;ldquo;irregularities&amp;rdquo;; these are always tricky because many of us don&amp;rsquo;t necessarily actually know the songs before we try to play and sing them and cannot guess right off the bat where they might be or follow along at the first attempt through. Also, there were songs that simply were very fast (meaning fast chord changes) or had complex chords and progressions. Very challenging, but I enjoy that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-to-handle-sight-reading-and-singing-harder-music&#34;&gt;How to handle sight reading and singing harder music&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the past half year since beginning on ukulele, I&amp;rsquo;ve figured out how to tackle hard music in Steel City Ukuleles readings. The thing to remember is that we always repeat a song at least once, and often more than once, and that within a song, there is usually a good deal of repetition as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trick is to never get held up on anything that you can&amp;rsquo;t do. &lt;em&gt;Never pause&lt;/em&gt;. Always keep going, even if means just keeping track of where everyone is (or getting back on track) while not playing or singing for a while. Strum the easy, important chords. Also, given that many songs I simply have not heard before, I usually don&amp;rsquo;t start singing until I&amp;rsquo;ve heard someone else do a section. And since I can never fully remember the exact pitches of a melody on first listening, I like to just go with the chords and make up a new inner (or lower, since there tend to be more women than men at meetings!) voice harmonically. That&amp;rsquo;s especially fun when the chords are more complex; I&amp;rsquo;ve decided that &lt;em&gt;singing in harmony&lt;/em&gt; is now actually my favorite thing to do as part of the group. This goes along with my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/03/16/pittsburgh-recorder-society-something-new-recently-recording-our-practice-sessions/&#34;&gt;recent focus on playing tenor and bass recorders with the Pittsburgh Pittsburgh Recorder group&lt;/a&gt; (rather than soprano and alto, which were my main focus during my first two years on recorder).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, there&amp;rsquo;s a benefit to going back home to really &amp;ldquo;master&amp;rdquo; a song. I don&amp;rsquo;t like operating in perpetual &amp;ldquo;sight reading&amp;rdquo; mode. That&amp;rsquo;s part of why I like to sign up for performances sometimes, to really work on getting something down better. But I don&amp;rsquo;t think I&amp;rsquo;ll have time to perform again for a couple more months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;nostalgia&#34;&gt;Nostalgia&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the songs triggered deep nostalgia in me. We did two songs by the great &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stevie_Wonder&#34;&gt;Stevie Wonder&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Isn%27t_She_Lovely&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Isn&amp;rsquo;t She Lovely?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/For_Once_in_My_Life&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;For Once in My Life&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. I totally love these classic songs: great melodies, rhythmic clarity, harmonic movement. It&amp;rsquo;s always a joy to revisit these songs. We also did &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/America_%28Simon_%26_Garfunkel_song%29&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;America&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; by Simon and Garfunkel: a much sadder, wistful song that has a special meaning to me because I listened to it in my childhood, without necessarily grasping the words and the narrative, but absorbing the story just from the harmonic changes and the tone of voice in the singing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we were all packing up to leave, Jack said we needed a group photo because it had been a while, so he got two in. Actually, I was sort of a de facto photographer for us since I joined last year, but I had disappeared for two months this year. (I did take photos two weeks ago when I returned, but Jack didn&amp;rsquo;t make it to that meeting.) I&amp;rsquo;ll continue taking photos as I attend Steel City Ukuleles events. I think it does encourage people to join when they see what a good time we&amp;rsquo;re having!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After I got home, I realized my left fingertips were so sore that I could barely type at the computer. I was OK, but that was a really intense two-hour meetup! I&amp;rsquo;m still getting all my callouses back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/steel-city-ukuleles-2014-03-19-fingers.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;My fingers&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thoughts on returning to ukulele after almost two months off: returning to piano was the reason</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/03/05/thoughts-on-returning-to-ukulele-after-almost-two-months-off/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2014 21:32:59 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/03/05/thoughts-on-returning-to-ukulele-after-almost-two-months-off/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I finally made it again to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/Steel-City-Ukuleles/events/158392272/&#34;&gt;latest Steel City Ukuleles meetup&lt;/a&gt;, after an absence of almost two months! What happened?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of what happened was that after the last meeting in mid-January, I had some battles with illness and fatigue and also got very busy. For whatever reason, I just plain lost interest in playing ukulele. It was like a switch flipped off. And each time a meetup came, I kind of intended to attend anyway, in hope of rekindling my interest, but it always turned out that something came up that was more important and so I missed two meetings in February that I otherwise did sign up for but canceled at the last minute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;piano&#34;&gt;Piano&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But on a deeper level, what happened was that in mid-January, right before the last meetup I attended, I learned that a boy I have been giving private chess lessons to was progressing rapidly in piano; his mother had sent me some video clips, and he played various pieces that were dear to me. This really shook my world, because I had &amp;ldquo;given up&amp;rdquo; on piano many times in my life, and never studied or practiced it seriously. &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/13/back-to-piano-too/&#34;&gt;Over two years ago, I wrote a little about this.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In particular, seeing a kid playing pieces that I never mastered made me feel deep regret that I had not stuck to teaching myself piano or getting professional instruction at some point in my life. So almost immediately upon learning about what he was up to, I decided to give piano a shot again. As a result, I completely dropped ukulele and flute, and focused my limited music time on recorder (in maintenance mode mostly) and piano.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got from the library not only the Alfred adult piano course again, but also the fantastic &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.carlhumphries.com/piano-books.html&#34;&gt;Carl Humphries &amp;ldquo;Piano Handbook&amp;rdquo; as well as &amp;ldquo;Piano Workbook&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. They are really good. I wish this kind of self-teaching material had existed two or three decades ago. I would have snapped it up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I have been making more progress on piano than I ever did twenty years ago when I last really tried. This has been exciting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;ukulele-influence-on-piano-playing&#34;&gt;Ukulele influence on piano playing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The interesting thing is that even before I started practice, I was already instantly better than ever before. I was initially surprised, but then realized that everything I&amp;rsquo;ve done on ukulele has magically helped me at piano even without my touching the instrument. In particular:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;left hand strength and coordination came simply from playing ukulele&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;awareness of harmonic changes and coordination with melody came from the multitasking and partial improvisation of singing and strumming simultaneously&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I&amp;rsquo;ve been delighted that once again, improving at one musical instrument is helping me with other instruments as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;piano-influence-on-ukulele-playing&#34;&gt;Piano influence on ukulele playing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All through February, I wasn&amp;rsquo;t in the mood to play ukulele at all. But by March, I suddenly felt the itch to pick up the instrument again, and I did, and magically found that I was playing &lt;em&gt;much better&lt;/em&gt; than I had ever before. Again, I was initially surprised. But maybe I should not have been:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;left hand precision and flexibility was considerably improved, leading to better chord changes (with less sight) as well as much better barring and also finally nailing certain hard chords such as the basic E chord&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;spatial awareness of moving up the fret board was improved&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;singing and sight-reading chord changes simultaneously became much easier&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;returning-to-the-meetup&#34;&gt;Returning to the meetup&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was having so much fun working on some songs for myself on ukulele while singing much better than ever, that I was happy to return to the Steel City Ukuleles meetup to do this with others. (Also, during the winter I confess to feeling somewhat antisocial and not excited about driving through cold, snow, and ice to meetups, frankly.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a great time! I especially enjoyed, in the final minutes of the session, when it was request time, that I requested &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/My_Favorite_Things_%28song%29&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;My Favorite Things&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; and we went through it. I love that song (and this was also when I noticed that I could play an E chord without much effort, actually).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/scu-2014-03-05/group.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Steel City Ukuleles&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;cookies&#34;&gt;Cookies&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Someone told me that in February, she had brought in Chinese cookies from Hong Kong that her son had given her, to share with me for Chinese New Year, but I had not showed up. It was touching that I was missed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apparently the New Year party featuring wine and snacks was so popular that every meeting since then has involved wine and snacks (including this time a bottle of wine brought by a guy whose father makes wine)!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was really hungry and ate some cookies, so here are photos according to &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/01/16/a-system-for-quitting-eating-cookies/&#34;&gt;my rule&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/scu-2014-03-05/cookie1.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/scu-2014-03-05/cookie2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following turned out not to really be a cookie, but was some kind of bread with cheese or something. It was not my thing, and if I had known, I would not have taken it, but once I bit into it, I had to finish it:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/scu-2014-03-05/cookie3.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s still going to hard to juggle practicing all the instruments I have, but it&amp;rsquo;s encouraging that working intensively on one seems to transfer benefits to playing another. So I&amp;rsquo;m going to keep working on piano while also maintaining ukulele. I have to confess it&amp;rsquo;s hard to do much with recorder or flute at the moment though. They&amp;rsquo;ve been put on the back burner.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Steel City Ukuleles: a nice session on playing by ear</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/11/06/steel-city-ukuleles-a-nice-session-on-playing-by-ear/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Nov 2013 21:20:29 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/11/06/steel-city-ukuleles-a-nice-session-on-playing-by-ear/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s been three (rather than the usual two, because of the nature of the twice-a-month scheduling) weeks since &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/10/16/steel-city-ukuleles-back-to-plain-good-fun/&#34;&gt;my last meeting of the Steel City Ukuleles&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was definitely starting to miss the group meeting, and was happy to attend &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/Steel-City-Ukuleles/events/132647952/&#34;&gt;tonight&lt;/a&gt;, although I have to confess I did enjoy having more time to work on my own ukulele musical projects (rather than practicing the meetup music).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;playing-by-ear&#34;&gt;Playing by ear&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Renee had volunteered to lead a session including basic practice for &lt;em&gt;playing by ear&lt;/em&gt;, a very important skill that many of us coming from the &amp;ldquo;written score&amp;rdquo; orientation of music need work on. That obviously includes me. I&amp;rsquo;m always astounded when going to jam sessions and seeing and hearing musicians do amazing things who barely read music, for example. The &lt;em&gt;freedom&lt;/em&gt; and flexible facility is just obvious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, we started easy, doing songs with only two chords, then moved to three, then four. We did this in four different keys. For me, amusingly, it was a good thing that I didn&amp;rsquo;t actually know most of the songs, so I had to pick them up in real time (or more accurately, partially in real time, then repair mistaken guesses after fumbling through the first repetition).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I very much appreciated the session on playing by ear. There is no reason I can&amp;rsquo;t work on this by myself at home, of course, using various techniques. I have done some of this, but not as systematically as I should, so after tonight, I decided to spend &lt;em&gt;every&lt;/em&gt; future musical practice session (regardless of instrument) doing something without any written music. I consider playing by ear to be a critical component of what I want to get out of music in my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;beatles&#34;&gt;Beatles&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rest of the time we had a Beatles-themed program of songs. I found these tricky because of the sometimes strange chord changes (&amp;ldquo;strange&amp;rdquo; relative to most of the stuff we play).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;ending-a-little-early&#34;&gt;Ending a little early&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We ended a little early because a subset of us were scheduled to use the time to rehearse for a recording session coming up. (I had not volunteered for this gig when it was announced along with the Ecofest gig that I did do.)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The biggest Pittsburgh Recorder Society meeting I have attended in two years!!</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/20/the-biggest-pittsburgh-recorder-society-meeting-i-have-attended-in-two-years/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Oct 2013 18:04:10 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/20/the-biggest-pittsburgh-recorder-society-meeting-i-have-attended-in-two-years/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;At the second meeting of this season of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/PittsburghRecorderSociety&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Recorder Society&lt;/a&gt;, I was amazed by the huge turnout. There were &lt;strong&gt;fourteen&lt;/strong&gt; of us, easily double the typical attendance in the past two seasons since &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/02/23/celebrating-two-years-of-playing-recorder/&#34;&gt;I first joined in 2011&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-recorder-society-2013-10-20/panorama.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Fred was very excited by the attendance and told us he would like for us to perform as an entire group sometime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/09/15/new-goals-for-a-new-season-of-the-pittsburgh-recorder-society/&#34;&gt;promised after last month&amp;rsquo;s meeting&lt;/a&gt;, I took the opportunity in this meeting to do some playing on my bass recorder. I also played tenor and soprano for some other pieces we worked on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;halloween-themed-desserts&#34;&gt;Halloween-themed desserts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since it is almost Halloween, Helen brought in some &amp;ldquo;scary&amp;rdquo; cupcakes that were, to me anyway, a sight to behold.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-recorder-society-2013-10-20/snacks.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-recorder-society-2013-10-20/scary-cupcake.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-recorder-society-2013-10-20/scary-cupcake-bottom.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;pittsburgh-s-rubber-duck&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh&amp;rsquo;s rubber duck&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People were talking about the planned departure later today of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/RubberDuckPittsburghPa&#34;&gt;our rubber duck&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, in the duck&amp;rsquo;s honor, I had brought my ukulele, and during the break I played &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/10/02/rubber-duckie-and-steel-city-ukuleles-rehearsal/&#34;&gt;Rubber Duckie on my ukulele&lt;/a&gt; while singing along, and Anita joined in the singing too. I had worked pretty hard to be able to passably play this song before our duck left. I still need more work on the song.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;more-recorders-for-me-to-play&#34;&gt;More recorders for me to play&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I picked up two recorders from Helen that I had bid on at the last meeting, when a large collection of recorders was given to us to be auctioned off. More on this later!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had another great time at the Pittsburgh Recorder Society monthly meeting. Every month, our Sunday afternoon meeting is something I truly look forward to.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Steel City Ukuleles: back to plain good fun, including the cups song</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/16/steel-city-ukuleles-back-to-plain-good-fun/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2013 22:06:02 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/16/steel-city-ukuleles-back-to-plain-good-fun/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s been over a week since I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/10/05/performing-with-the-steel-city-ukuleles-at-the-wilkins-school-community-center-ecofest-2013-with-videos/&#34;&gt;performed as part of the Steel City Ukuleles in the Wilkins School Community Center Ecofest&lt;/a&gt;. I was very relieved to have no more self-imposed performance obligations for a while, feeling burned out for a while, to tell the truth. But I was ready to get back into playing just for fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;members-choice&#34;&gt;Members&amp;rsquo; choice!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had a fun &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/Steel-City-Ukuleles/events/140097142/&#34;&gt;session this week&lt;/a&gt; in which all of us had earlier been invited to submit music we personally wanted to play. I had submitted &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mr._Sandman&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Mister Sandman&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, a song I&amp;rsquo;ve loved since (amusingly) first hearing it when watching &amp;ldquo;Back to the Future&amp;rdquo; way back. I was really excited to finally be singing it and playing it with others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We did various other member-contributed selections also, including a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cups_%28song%29&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Cups&amp;rdquo; song&lt;/a&gt; that apparently has become all the craze because of moving cups around as part of percussion! Three of us had practiced ahead of time to play the cups. I have to say I was impressed:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/cups.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Cups&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;rubber-duckie&#34;&gt;Rubber Duckie&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We went over &amp;ldquo;Rubber Duckie&amp;rdquo; again. I love this song. I&amp;rsquo;m getting better at singing and strumming it simultaneously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;kazoo&#34;&gt;Kazoo&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I finally bought a cheap kazoo for use in the future (several of us used kazoos in the Ecofest performance, but I did not have a kazoo at the time), as Jack got a whole bunch to sell to us:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/kazoo.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Kazoo&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed getting back to just plain fun with singing and playing ukulele, with no more performances in the near future that I&amp;rsquo;ve volunteered to be a part of.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Was that a ukulele I heard in Frick Park? No, a cavaquinho</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/06/was-that-a-ukulele-i-heard-in-frick-park-no-a-cavaquinho/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Oct 2013 14:19:09 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/06/was-that-a-ukulele-i-heard-in-frick-park-no-a-cavaquinho/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I had just run into Frick Park past the blue slide playground entrance when I thought I heard someone playing a ukulele! I looked around and saw a guy sitting on a park bench. I thought of approaching him, but decided not to interrupt my run, and kept going.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s what Frick Park looked today on a trail, with some fallen leaves. Bizarre that it&amp;rsquo;s still summer temperatures right now though.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/frick-park-2013-10-06.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Frick Park trail with fallen leaves&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When I came back around out of the trails, I saw the guy again and he was packing up to leave, so I approached him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out to be Ben, to whom &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/01/run-shadyside-5k-outrunning-mickey-mouse-and-lending-a-trumpet/&#34;&gt;I had lent a trumpet two years ago&lt;/a&gt; (since returned)! I asked him if the instrument in his case was a ukulele. He said no. I asked if it was a guitar. He said no. It was a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cavaquinho&#34;&gt;cavaquinho&lt;/a&gt;, the Portuguese ancestor of the Hawaiian ukulele! He pulled it out of the case and let me check it out. It&amp;rsquo;s tuned differently from the ukulele:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/cavaquinho.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Ben&amp;#39;s cavaquinho&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I had heard of this instrument, from reading something about the history of the ukulele (in particular, I had looked at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.coolhanduke.com/worldukehistory.html&#34;&gt;Cool Hand Uke&amp;rsquo;s booklet on ukulele history&lt;/a&gt; recently). Also, Handerson (who is from Brazil) had asked me if I knew where to buy a cavaquinho. Ben said he was looking for other cavaquinho players in Pittsburgh, so I sent him Handerson&amp;rsquo;s contact information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So no, I was not just hallucinating &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/10/05/performing-with-the-steel-city-ukuleles-at-the-wilkins-school-community-center-ecofest-2013-with-videos/&#34;&gt;post-ukulele-gig&lt;/a&gt; when I thought I heard a ukulele in Frick Park.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You never know what or who you might encounter in the park on a nice day.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Performing with the Steel City Ukuleles at the Wilkins School Community Center Ecofest 2013: with videos</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/05/performing-with-the-steel-city-ukuleles-at-the-wilkins-school-community-center-ecofest-2013-with-videos/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Oct 2013 19:38:08 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/05/performing-with-the-steel-city-ukuleles-at-the-wilkins-school-community-center-ecofest-2013-with-videos/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/ecofest-2013.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Ecofest 2013 poster&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/ecofest-2013/steel-city-ukuleles-banner.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It was a beautiful day outside at the Wilkins School Community Center Ecofest in Regent Square: warm and sunny, and &lt;em&gt;dry&lt;/em&gt;. It had been raining, and was even drizzling rain in the morning just before we performed at around 11:15 AM for an hour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were vendors, information booths, food, and families with children hanging out. Abby helped out with using our camera on a tripod to get footage of the Steel City Ukuleles performing, then went off to the clothing swap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, Marlene and others came out to listen to us and support us. That was great!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was happy to see parents with their children watching us, and some of them dancing a bit too. I silently thought to myself, &amp;ldquo;I am playing for the children standing in front of me&amp;rdquo;. Music is a beautiful thing to share with children; I remember how happy I was when I was young and encountered music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;videos&#34;&gt;Videos&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We managed to get about half of our program recorded on my camera. Unfortunately, the memory card ran out of space halfway through because we forgot to erase all the photos and videos that were still on the memory card from long ago. Still, we got quite a bit of footage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We missed recording the first two songs, because of a confusion with Abby about start time that resulted in her arriving in the middle of our second song, but then we got rolling and successfully recorded eight songs, before the memory card filled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;cindy&#34;&gt;Cindy&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/oOH7VEmncXk&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;shangri-la&#34;&gt;Shangri-La&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notice the mention of Pittsburgh in the verse!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/isKtJV1jlao&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;roxy-s-waltz&#34;&gt;Roxy&amp;rsquo;s Waltz&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was a trio, performed by Amber, Sunny, and Jon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/OgVtQ7m5ZNc&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;you-are-my-sunshine&#34;&gt;You Are My Sunshine&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/OdDBAMhUJDk&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;tonight-you-belong-to-me-and-by-the-light-of-the-silvery-moon&#34;&gt;Tonight You Belong To Me and By The Light Of The Silvery Moon&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of my favorite musical selection in our playlist, but also the trickiest for me to play, because of the key and the chord changes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/7pBKf4TfRLA&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;mountain-sound&#34;&gt;Mountain Sound&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adam had a solo intro in this one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/VAD4tzjkB80&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;stealin-stealin&#34;&gt;Stealin&amp;rsquo; Stealin&amp;rsquo;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/hkJvBfx9Ew0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;rough-on-rats&#34;&gt;Rough On Rats&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/j0nrKnfdf_0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then the camera memory card filled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sadly, we did not get footage of our concluding sing-along songs where we encouraged everyone to sing along!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;afterwards-at-the-ecofest&#34;&gt;Afterwards, at the Ecofest&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I packed up right after we were done performing, because I could only stay around several minutes longer to explore Ecofest with Abby before heading over to Point Park University downtown for the afternoon sessions of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.podcamppittsburgh.com/&#34;&gt;PodCamp Pittsburgh&lt;/a&gt;, whose morning sessions I missed because of the Ecofest gig.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But others of us hung around to do more jamming:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/ecofest-2013/after-jamming.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A view of Ecofest from front:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/ecofest-2013/front.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Panoramic view of Ecofest from the back dining area outside:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/ecofest-2013/panorama.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Some vendors and information booths:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/ecofest-2013/sample.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;reflections-on-our-performance&#34;&gt;Reflections on our performance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I felt fairly pleased with our performance. The three rehearsals we had in the past two weeks were crucial. We did flub some things that we didn&amp;rsquo;t flub in rehearsal, but that happens. But overall, we produced a fine unified sound. The videos don&amp;rsquo;t completely reflect that because of the distance and the background conversations at the event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I myself made more errors than in rehearsal and in private practice. There are a couple of reasons for this. I think the most interesting one is simply that I did not practice enough in a &lt;em&gt;performance&lt;/em&gt; mode. Most of the time, when I practice music, I am focused entirely on getting the words right, the melody, the rhythm, the harmonic changes, the fingerings, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in performance, there is the audience, and the point is to play for the audience, not for oneself. I had a hard time reallocating my scarce attentional resources toward engaging with the audience. When I did, such as by avoiding looking down so much at the fret board (actually, in the videos you can see that I could not entirely avoid this, because I don&amp;rsquo;t have a perfect feel yet for my finger positions, so I keep bobbing my head toward my instrument), I could feel myself miss nailing a chord.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having seen the footage, I will work more in the future toward specific practice oriented toward polishing up for performance. This means improving technique and memorizing as much as possible (chord changes, lyrics). It is &amp;ldquo;easy&amp;rdquo; to go out there with a music stand and run through stuff, but it is much harder to appear relaxed, confident, and attentive to the audience. I feel that this is quite important to a successful performance, whose aim is to truly touch the hearts and minds of those who are paying attention to us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is of course pointless to pay too much attention to aspects of presentation if your technique and intonation are poor, so I would say that performance presentation is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; the most important thing to work on, all things considered, but my aim is to master the musical basics enough that I can also reliably &lt;em&gt;add&lt;/em&gt; the presentation aspect as an integral part of complete musical development. I believe that a truly good musical performance must incorporate the spirit of those who are listening to us and feed it back into what we do in real time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed participating in my first ukulele gig. Now, I am exhausted, and will take a break from performance. It has been an amazing learning experience for me.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Final rehearsal for my first ukulele gig: and some hard decisions about music in my life</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/04/final-rehearsal-for-my-first-ukulele-gig/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2013 22:15:33 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/04/final-rehearsal-for-my-first-ukulele-gig/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;The night before our Ecofest gig, those of us in the Steel City Ukuleles who are performing in it had one final rehearsal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a very good rehearsal. We&amp;rsquo;re sounding more and more together as an ensemble, ending solidly on each song the way we agreed, and singing more in tune and balance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, Sunny reminded us that we are &lt;em&gt;performing&lt;/em&gt;, and so we should not just grimly look at our music booklets, but instead, when we can, we should look up and smile and engage with the audience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;singing&#34;&gt;Singing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still don&amp;rsquo;t have all the songs down as much as I would like, but by the end of the two-hour rehearsal, I was totally &lt;em&gt;hoarse&lt;/em&gt;. I am ready to sing out strong while simultaneously playing my ukulele.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I just realized that &lt;strong&gt;in the past three months, I have sung more than in the previous forty years of my life combined&lt;/strong&gt;. Wow. And I&amp;rsquo;m loving it. There&amp;rsquo;s nothing like singing, especially singing with others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;performance-is-time-and-energy-consuming&#34;&gt;Performance is time and energy consuming&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I almost didn&amp;rsquo;t make it to the rehearsal. I&amp;rsquo;ve completely exhausted myself this week with work and other activities, and badly need a break. There are times, such as earlier today, when I felt overwhelmed by everything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, yesterday, in discussing my musical plans for the coming months with Abby, I made some decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is my last ukulele gig for the year, for sure. I want to get back to basics and work on my technique and in really mastering some songs, rather than get back on the treadmill of more material for performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, this winter, I am not planning to participate in performing on recorder for the holiday gigs at Phipps Conservatory &amp;ldquo;candlelight evenings&amp;rdquo; that I&amp;rsquo;ve treasured &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/05/busy-evening-performing-at-phipps-followed-by-rehearsal-for-another-gig/&#34;&gt;in 2011&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/09/playing-music-on-recorders-at-a-phipps-conservatory-candlelight-evening/&#34;&gt;in 2012&lt;/a&gt;. That was always a huge amount of work for me. Unless I can participate in significantly reduced capacity, I don&amp;rsquo;t see how I can manage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will probably perform in the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/14/pittsburgh-contras-and-squares-holiday-ball-2012/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Contras and Squares Holiday Ball&lt;/a&gt; again, because it&amp;rsquo;s something I&amp;rsquo;ve been doing with Abby every year, and because after two years of doing it, I know the music, and therefore it will not require much work to participate in (if I want to do some Irish flute and tin whistle solos, of course, then I can add as much extra work for myself that I want, ha).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-is-the-best-use-of-my-limited-time-and-energy-for-music&#34;&gt;What is the best use of my limited time and energy for music?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, there have been announcements and reminders for some time about recorder and ukulele &lt;em&gt;workshops&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;concerts&lt;/em&gt; coming up soon. I have decided not to sign up for any of them, because I really need some rest time on &lt;em&gt;weekends&lt;/em&gt; that I have not been getting; weekends are also the time when I can do more household chores and spend time with Abby.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find that my main enjoyment and improvement in music comes form what I do daily, anyway, rather than what I can possibly do in a long, extended workshop format. I&amp;rsquo;ve always been frustrated that when I attend a one or two day conference or workshop on any subject (computer programming, salsa dance, etc.), I don&amp;rsquo;t actually retain or engage with as much as I would like. There are ways to optimize these experiences, but that requires a certain kind of immediate followup that I don&amp;rsquo;t have time for right now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I will sadly miss the fantastic &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flanders-recorder-quartet.be/en/home/&#34;&gt;Flanders Recorder Quartet&lt;/a&gt; when they come to Pittsburgh in November, and I will miss the workshop Annie has arranged for them to give here for the local recorder community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I am going to miss &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.coolhanduke.com/&#34;&gt;Cool Hand Uke&lt;/a&gt; when he comes to Pittsburgh to give a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/Steel-City-Ukuleles/events/135233932/&#34;&gt;workshop&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/Steel-City-Ukuleles/events/138577782/&#34;&gt;concert&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Life is full of choices, especially for those of us who have many interests, not just one. This week I made some decisions about my involvement with music in October, November, and December.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>9 things you could be doing in Pittsburgh on Saturday, October 5</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/04/9-things-you-could-be-doing-in-pittsburgh-on-saturday-october-5/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2013 00:46:44 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/04/9-things-you-could-be-doing-in-pittsburgh-on-saturday-october-5/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m always frustrated at this time of year because there are so many events of interest to me in Pittsburgh that seem to happen on the first weekend of October. Since I cannot attend all of them, I figured I might as well attempt a public service and mention some of them so that if you are in the Pittsburgh area, maybe you can go and enjoy what I can&amp;rsquo;t attend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So here are 9 of the probably dozens of cool things you could be doing tomorrow, Saturday, October 5, 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;free-concert-allegheny-city-ragtime-orchestra&#34;&gt;Free concert: Allegheny City Ragtime Orchestra&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re interested in ragtime or Latin music, check out &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.shadysideacademy.org/page.cfm?p=12541&#34;&gt;this concert by the Allegheny City Ragtime Orchestra&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some articles in anticipation of it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.post-gazette.com/stories/ae/music/preview-ragtime-orchestra-connects-with-history-705929/&#34;&gt;Post-Gazette&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://triblive.com/aande/music/4763900-74/ragtime-music-concert&#34;&gt;Trib&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I wanted to go, but finally decided that we have too many other activities earlier in the day and need to just stay home and unwind in the evening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;free-conference-podcamp-pittsburgh-8&#34;&gt;Free conference: PodCamp Pittsburgh 8&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 8th annual &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.podcamppittsburgh.com/&#34;&gt;PodCamp Pittsburgh&lt;/a&gt; should be good. If you have any interest in using social media for personal or professional purposes, you should check it out. Interesting talks, opportunities to just socialized and learn new things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I attended in 2010, 2011, 2012, and will attend again for the fourth year. Unfortunately, I will only be able to attend the afternoon sessions. But I didn&amp;rsquo;t want to completely miss it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that PodCamp completely changed my life. For example, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/21/one-month-anniversary-of-my-blog/&#34;&gt;I started this blog in 2011 because of my second PodCamp&lt;/a&gt;, and I became serious about using social media in general, and that led to a total transformation of my life as I learned about local activities and made new friends. (Unfortunately, I didn&amp;rsquo;t get around to finishing my draft reports about my experience at last year&amp;rsquo;s PodCamp 7.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;pittsburgh-south-side-slopes-step-trek&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh South Side Slopes Step Trek&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The annual &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.southsideslopes.org/steptrek/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh South Side Slopes Step Trek&lt;/a&gt; is another event you can attend tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/08/my-god-its-full-of-stairs-pittsburgh-step-trek-2011/&#34;&gt;blog coverage two years ago&lt;/a&gt; as well as my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/09/25/why-you-should-go-out-to-the-pittsburgh-south-side-slopes-step-trek/&#34;&gt;recent update&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, Abby and I will be missing it this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;run-shadyside-5k&#34;&gt;Run Shadyside 5K&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you like to run in races, a fine race is the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.runshadyside.com/&#34;&gt;Run Shadyside 5K&lt;/a&gt;. Fast and flat, with a pancake breakfast and festivities afterwards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not running in it this year, just because I have too many other things to do already for the rest of the day, but here&amp;rsquo;s my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/01/run-shadyside-5k-outrunning-mickey-mouse-and-lending-a-trumpet/&#34;&gt;report from two years ago&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;free-5th-annual-wilkins-school-community-center-ecofest-in-regent-square&#34;&gt;Free: 5th annual Wilkins School Community Center Ecofest in Regent Square&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/ecofest-2013.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;5th annual Wilkins School Community Center Ecofest in Regent Square&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Interested in green living? Check out the &lt;a href=&#34;http://foresthills-regentsquare.patch.com/groups/around-town/p/ecofest-encourages-recycling-green-living&#34;&gt;5th annual Wilkins School Community Center Ecofest in Regent Square&lt;/a&gt;. Abby has regularly attended for the clothing swap. There will also be food, information, and entertainment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that this year, I will also be attending, to perform as a new member of the Steel City Ukuleles. &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/08/23/another-unexpected-life-change-one-month-of-learning-to-play-ukulele/&#34;&gt;I just started playing the ukulele a bit over two months ago&lt;/a&gt;, and have been working hard to help put on an entertaining show!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;ll be performing around 11:30 AM to 12:30 PM. If you come, say hello!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;cmu-donut-dash-2-mile-race&#34;&gt;CMU Donut Dash 2 mile race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, if you are into weird running events, there is the &lt;a href=&#34;http://cmudonutdash.org/&#34;&gt;Carnegie Mellon University Donut Dash&lt;/a&gt;, a 2 mile event serving as a fundraiser for the Children&amp;rsquo;s Hospital of Pittsburgh of UPMC. This is not an event I have ever done, and not one I intend to do, but what the heck, some of you might love this sort of thing!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;national-chess-day-gateway-open-tournament-at-the-pittsburgh-chess-club&#34;&gt;National Chess Day: Gateway Open tournament at the Pittsburgh Chess Club&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did you know that it&amp;rsquo;s time for &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nationalchessday.com/&#34;&gt;National Chess Day&lt;/a&gt;? There will be a tournament at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburghcc.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Chess Club&lt;/a&gt;, the 56th annual Gateway Open. Yes, chess in Pittsburgh has a long and illustrious history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;pittsburgh-perl-workshop&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Perl Workshop&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are a Perl programmer, the &lt;a href=&#34;http://pghpw.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Perl Workshop&lt;/a&gt; is back &lt;a href=&#34;http://pghpw.org/ppw2013/&#34;&gt;this year&lt;/a&gt;. Registration is already closed, so it&amp;rsquo;s not so helpful right now for me to mention it, but in case you didn&amp;rsquo;t know it existed, watch for it next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;ninth-thing&#34;&gt;Ninth thing?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, I guess I miscounted. But there are a whole lot more than nine things to do in Pittsburgh tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, if you are interested in some free stuff to do, there&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.radworkshere.org/interior.php?pageID=64&#34;&gt;RADical Days&lt;/a&gt; listing a whole bunch of stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s no shortage of stuff to do in this great city of Pittsburgh at any time or day of year. I think it&amp;rsquo;s unfortunate that many things I like to do happen to repeatedly fall on the first Saturday of the year, but I&amp;rsquo;m not complaining about an embarrassment of riches. Go out and take advantage of what I can&amp;rsquo;t.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rubber Duckie and Steel City Ukuleles rehearsal</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/02/rubber-duckie-and-steel-city-ukuleles-rehearsal/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2013 21:43:30 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/02/rubber-duckie-and-steel-city-ukuleles-rehearsal/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/Steel-City-Ukuleles/events/132647852&#34;&gt;This week&amp;rsquo;s Wednesday meeting of the Steel City Ukuleles&lt;/a&gt; was an unusual one: it was split into two halves, the first half being our regular meeting (involving going through a new playlist), the second half being the second of three &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/09/26/first-rehearsal-for-my-first-ukulele-gig/&#34;&gt;rehearsals for the Ecofest gig&lt;/a&gt;. The deal was that everyone was open to stick around for the rehearsal if they wanted to, but with the caveat that it was serious rehearsal time, rather than the more casual regular meetup atmosphere. It turned out that a few people who were not performing in the Ecofest gig did stick around, although most others left.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sunny was not present, so Amber took charge of this meetup session.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/steel-city-ukuleles-2013-10-02.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;rubber-duckie&#34;&gt;Rubber Duckie&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed learning some new songs in the first half.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One slightly crazy thing we tried was running through &amp;ldquo;Rubber Duckie&amp;rdquo;, which I had actually suggested to Sunny in email for the playlist for the next meetup, but apparently others had also suggested, for obvious reasons here in Pittsburgh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/n-kHSXQ_wwk&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This song is hard, with a lot of chord changes. I would like to actually master it and play it solo for Abby before Pittsburgh&amp;rsquo;s rubber duck leaves.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/steel-city-ukuleles-2013-10-02-rubber-duckie.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;rehearsal&#34;&gt;Rehearsal&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rehearsal was intense, but we managed to cover the rest of the songs we are to play in the Ecofest gig three days (!!) from now. A lot of homework for me to do, just as I have been doing with the first half of the program.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An erhu player and a tuba player at a party said &#34;Let&#39;s jam&#34;</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/09/28/an-erhu-player-and-a-tuba-player-at-a-party-said-lets-jam/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Sep 2013 22:02:19 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/09/28/an-erhu-player-and-a-tuba-player-at-a-party-said-lets-jam/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I attended a music potluck party tonight. We had been unsure about whether to attend, since I do have the Great Race 10K to run tomorrow and need to avoid staying up too late. So we went with the understanding that we would leave early as needed, in order for me to wind down at home and go to bed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;food&#34;&gt;Food&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I whipped up a large batch of roasted vegetables to bring to the potluck:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/vegetables-2013-09-28.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Roasted vegetables&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;music&#34;&gt;Music&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a lot of eating and chatting, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.appalasia.com/Mimi.htm&#34;&gt;Mimi&lt;/a&gt; was ready to start jamming, and got out her &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Erhu&#34;&gt;erhu&lt;/a&gt;. A guy who had brought a tuba was ready to play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OK, who else was in?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I pulled out my flute. Abby took out her mandolin. It seemed like nobody else (yet) was interested in joining in. (But as we know, the party usually really gets going later in the evening when musicians are involved.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tuba player seemed really into jazz. He asked for requests and started his own rhythmic bass sometimes. I tried to join in with him and Mimi as they led the way. It was pretty hard for me, and frightening, but I did what I could to contribute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At one point, I volunteered to sing and play &amp;ldquo;Has Anybody Seen My Gal?&amp;rdquo; on ukulele, which I did (for the first time by myself outside home), and they followed along. I don&amp;rsquo;t know if that was the first time an erhu, tuba, and ukulele were in action simultaneously!?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;lending-my-flute-out&#34;&gt;Lending my flute out&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point, a guy arrived at the party who wanted to jam. He hadn&amp;rsquo;t yet brought in his trombone, but asked if he could borrow my flute. I recognized him from previous parties, and I had seen him play flute in at least one of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So he borrowed my flute and I sat back and watched and listened. He was a really good improviser. Actually, at the suggestion of the tuba player, who really liked totally free improvisation, the three of them did something I found amazing and beautiful. Starting with some long tones, they created an eerie sonic soundscape together, listening to one another while blending the erhu, tuba, and flute. I was really moved by this display of musicality and feeling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;leaving-early&#34;&gt;Leaving early&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby noted that it was getting &amp;ldquo;late&amp;rdquo; for us, and so we regrettably had to leave. Guests were still coming in and bringing food, even though those of us who had arrived early had filled our stomachs long ago. I got my flute back and packed up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is always a special treat for me when I get to hang around creative, accomplished musicians and get to see them make music spontaneously. I&amp;rsquo;m usually too intimidated in these kinds of situations to join in, but I did briefly tonight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-11-06&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-11-06)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was surprised and saddened to learn from Mimi that just a couple of days ago, the man who had borrowed my flute and played so beautifully, David Olson, &lt;a href=&#34;http://obituaries.triblive.com/listing/231895/David-E-Olson/&#34;&gt;died&lt;/a&gt;. Even in the brief time that I interacted with him at all, just in a handful of music parties, I was struck by his enthusiasm, humor, and graciousness. It is hard to believe that he is gone now, just a month since he was playing my flute. RIP, David.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>First rehearsal for my first ukulele gig: dealing with anxiety</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/09/26/first-rehearsal-for-my-first-ukulele-gig/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Sep 2013 23:09:23 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/09/26/first-rehearsal-for-my-first-ukulele-gig/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s now officially &lt;em&gt;two months&lt;/em&gt; since &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/08/23/another-unexpected-life-change-one-month-of-learning-to-play-ukulele/&#34;&gt;I started learning to play ukulele&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s hard to believe, but two months ago, I was still struggling to play three chords: I could play C, of course, but had trouble with G7, and had even worse trouble with F: I had no finger strength or dexterity and could not arch my fingers and everything was a painful buzz, and I could spend only five minutes a day practicing because of the pain on my uncalloused fingers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And after just over a month of playing, and joining the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/Steel-City-Ukuleles/&#34;&gt;Steel City Ukuleles&lt;/a&gt;, I had volunteered to &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/09/04/my-second-meeting-of-the-steel-city-ukuleles/&#34;&gt;perform in a gig for Ecofest in Regent Square&lt;/a&gt;, as a way to force myself to maintain momentum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this week, just in time, I got my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/09/23/finally-got-a-nice-new-ukulele-mainland-classic-mahogany-concert/&#34;&gt;brand new concert-sized ukulele&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/ecofest-2013-rehearsal-1.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;First Ecofest rehearsal&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The gig is in just over a week. I attended my first rehearsal with extreme anxiety. I was even thinking about bailing out instead of attending. Here&amp;rsquo;s why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;new-music-for-me&#34;&gt;New music for me&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/steel-city-ukuleles-bound-thing-1.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/steel-city-ukuleles-bound-thing-2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I went into rehearsal with basically &lt;em&gt;none&lt;/em&gt; of the songs we were going to perform. So it was basically a sight reading and singing session for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One reason is that I was waiting to get the official bound compilation of performance songs that we were to receive at the first rehearsal, which we did. I had not requested to get one ahead of time, because I was too busy all week anyway to make good use of it if I had possessed it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, it turns out that many of these songs are already familiar and played by most of the other members of the performance group; they are part of the general repertoire, for previous years&amp;rsquo; Ecofests as well as for other gigs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;new-performance-group-for-me&#34;&gt;New performance group for me&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that breaking into a performance group for the first time always involves an initial learning curve because there are those who already know everything inside and out. I still have very vivid memories of other times in my life when I have entered a performance group and felt lost for a while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was briefly in marching band, during the 9th grade in high school. As a new freshman, I was unfamiliar with the repertoire, the choreography, etc. It was a tricky experience for all us freshmen, of course, amidst the 10th, 11th, and 12th graders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, over a decade ago, for a couple of years I was a member of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://cmubdc.org/&#34;&gt;Carnegie Mellon University ballroom dance club&lt;/a&gt;, and I was on both the competition team as well as the formation team. I&amp;rsquo;d made ballroom dancing the main focus of my life, throwing myself into lessons and competition and being in performances with the formation team while still a beginner. I improved my dancing significantly and quickly as a result of jumping in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And more recently, I have been performing in a small &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/09/playing-music-on-recorders-at-a-phipps-conservatory-candlelight-evening/&#34;&gt;recorder quartet/quintet at winter holiday time&lt;/a&gt;. Practicing so that I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t totally flub everything always took a huge amount of work for me, but the side effect was that I really improved my recorder playing and musicianship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I know firsthand the benefits of just jumping in and being around very experienced team members who are inspirational to emulate and learn from, and to exert some healthy pressure on myself not to let the team down!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;listening-watching&#34;&gt;Listening, watching&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of what I did during rehearsal was listening and watching, while doing what I could to keep up and go and make dozens of mistakes everywhere. (It&amp;rsquo;s particularly important to boldly make those mistakes and write down what to work on for homework.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was no way I was going to be able to play everything at first sight. In fact, that&amp;rsquo;s not even the right way to think about the situation. This isn&amp;rsquo;t classical music where you really do &amp;ldquo;sight read&amp;rdquo;. This is music where almost everything is transmitted &lt;em&gt;by ear&lt;/em&gt;. Not knowing the melodies, and not having an actual score, I have to listen and figure out where the melodic lines roughly are, and where the chord changes are. I have to learn what the prevailing strum rhythms and breaks and mood the group has largely decided on. The goal is to learn how to blend in and contribute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t do much extended &lt;em&gt;singing&lt;/em&gt; during this rehearsal. But we have two more rehearsals after this one, so it was not necessary to get everything down right away. I would, of course, be doing my own homework, looking up YouTube videos, in between official rehearsals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For consistency, I found it very useful to focus my listening on one person at a time to emulate. Usually that person was Sunny, because she is leading us. Sometimes that was Adam, because I was sitting near him and because as a strong male voice, I could follow him especially in songs where we had male and female voices split.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fact that there were over a dozen of us in the group for this gig was very helpful to me, because it meant that there was much less pressure on me to get everything right. I don&amp;rsquo;t always have to sing, or sing everything. I don&amp;rsquo;t always have to play the tricky chord progressions that I&amp;rsquo;m not ready yet to get right. I can leave stuff out judiciously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;half-the-songs&#34;&gt;Half the songs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In two hours, we covered half the songs we planned to play at Ecofest. I felt there was still a huge amount of work for me to do in order to really contribute to the group, but no longer felt helpless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-cost-of-excellence&#34;&gt;The cost of excellence&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still think it&amp;rsquo;s a little crazy that I jumped into committing to performing when still a beginner at ukulele, but in the past couple of years, I have learned that shorter, tighter learning and creating cycles considerably speed up the improvement process, provided that one actually puts in the hard work on a daily basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s been a huge cost, unfortunately. I have let some things slide while focusing on ukulele in the past two months. For example, I have been playing chess very poorly. Last week, I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/09/26/the-chess-improver-the-psychology-of-not-winning-the-won-game/&#34;&gt;drew a game that I should have won&lt;/a&gt;. And just two days ago, disaster struck: in my fatigue, I lost a game I should have won. If I had known I was going to have ukulele take over my life outside of work, I would have chosen &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; to play in the current chess tournament.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now as in the past couple of years, I have chosen to sacrifice my chess performance when other things come up. This is why I rarely play chess tournaments any more: I hate playing worse than I am actually capable of playing. As I mentioned two weeks ago, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/09/15/saying-no-on-not-playing-in-the-pittsburgh-chess-league-this-season-for-the-cmu-tartans/&#34;&gt;I had anticipated becoming busy in November&lt;/a&gt;, but I had not anticipated being so busy now already, in September!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sunny led a great rehearsal for our Ecofest gig coming up. I really like some of these songs we&amp;rsquo;re working on, and left feeling that after more work, we can sound really good and have a lot of fun at the gig!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Finally got a nice new ukulele: Mainland Classic Mahogany Concert</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/09/23/finally-got-a-nice-new-ukulele-mainland-classic-mahogany-concert/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Sep 2013 23:10:46 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/09/23/finally-got-a-nice-new-ukulele-mainland-classic-mahogany-concert/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mainland-classic-mahogany-concert.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Mainland Classic Mahogany Concert ukulele&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Exactly two months after beginning to learn ukulele, I finally got a quality instrument for myself, ordered online from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mainlandukuleles.com/&#34;&gt;Mainland Ukes&lt;/a&gt; in Indiana (yes, there are good ukuleles made outside of Hawaii).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I first encountered Mainland because of an electric tenor that Linda lent me at &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/08/23/another-unexpected-life-change-one-month-of-learning-to-play-ukulele/&#34;&gt;my very first Steel City Ukuleles meeting&lt;/a&gt;. This instrument had some very nice qualities I appreciated: its construction, appearance, and sound.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-now&#34;&gt;Why now?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I delayed two months because I wanted to get sufficiently proficient that I could actually tell what was good and what I like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, Abby&amp;rsquo;s friend really wanted the banjolele back (I had been playing it mostly, amidst the other loaners), and having already &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/09/04/my-second-meeting-of-the-steel-city-ukuleles/&#34;&gt;signed up to perform in a gig soon&lt;/a&gt; (!), I really wanted to have my own instrument for that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-this-mainland-classic-mahogany-concert-http-shop-mainlandukuleles-com-product-sc-productid-9-categoryid-3&#34;&gt;Why this &lt;a href=&#34;http://shop.mainlandukuleles.com/product.sc?productId=9&amp;amp;categoryId=3&#34;&gt;Mainland Classic Mahogany Concert&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After trying various instruments, I concluded that I really did want a &lt;em&gt;solid wood&lt;/em&gt; ukulele, rather than a laminate, because of the fuller sound. Given that, there was the question of a reasonable price point. I figured that I did not want to spend more than $300 on an instrument.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another thing was that I wanted to make sure the &lt;em&gt;intonation&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;action&lt;/em&gt; were decent, and were set up with care. That meant ruling out buying from some random store without a specific person responsible for setting up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I looked up a lot of reviews and descriptions online, and also demonstration videos. Hawaii Music Supply was much mentioned, for example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I found information that made me think Mainland was the way to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some reviews of Mainland instruments that I paid attention to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ianchadwick.com/ukuleles/mainland.htm&#34;&gt;tenors&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.gotaukulele.com/2010/05/mainland-mahogany-concert-slotted.html&#34;&gt;mahogany concert&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Comparing the woods, I liked the deep mahogany sound. Although the bright spruce-topped instruments sound great too, I prefer deep to bright, even if the classic ukulele sound is on the bright side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sound of the mahogany just seemed gorgeous to me, and also the Mainland instruments are quite resonant:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/Z0j4lCNoba0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/xJ6uG1l4jtE&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;ordering&#34;&gt;Ordering&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I eventually contacted Mike of Mainland and asked him some questions, and then put in the order, and the instrument quickly arrived. I already love it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I felt I did a reasonable job in evaluating (in person or from online information) various instruments before finally ordering one. This was not an impulse purchase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that I have a beautiful instrument, I feel committed to play it every day! I expect to enjoy this investment for many, many years to come!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My third meeting of the Steel City Ukuleles: finally ordered a new instrument</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/09/18/my-third-meeting-of-the-steel-city-ukuleles/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Sep 2013 23:13:09 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/09/18/my-third-meeting-of-the-steel-city-ukuleles/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/steel-city-ukuleles-2013-09-18.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Steel City Ukuleles&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve entered my ninth week of playing ukulele: almost two months now!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two weeks ago, I wrote about my second meeting of the Steel City Ukuleles and &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/09/04/my-second-meeting-of-the-steel-city-ukuleles/&#34;&gt;why I decided to perform so quickly after joining and as a beginner to the ukulele&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a report on my &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/Steel-City-Ukuleles/events/132647892/&#34;&gt;third meeting&lt;/a&gt;, in which Sunny led a varied playlist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;musical-selection&#34;&gt;Musical selection&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sunny chose a variety of songs from various genres. Again, this stuff was basically new to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;fingerpicking&#34;&gt;Fingerpicking&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the songs had a short fingerpicking intro, so I was happy to try the easy pattern.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;singing&#34;&gt;Singing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am now mostly able to play through the chords and changes and improvise my own strumming pattern in most of the songs we go through, so I&amp;rsquo;ve been enjoying doing more and more singing in addition, although it still feels like talking and chewing gum at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s where the advantage of the repetitive structure of this kind of music becomes obvious: there are many opportunities to &amp;ldquo;correct&amp;rdquo; what you&amp;rsquo;re doing on the ukulele while learning a song, and then eventually switch the focus to the words.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;sight-reading-and-preparation&#34;&gt;Sight reading and preparation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because I&amp;rsquo;ve been busy with work and other things in the past several days, I only had time to briefly run over some of the songs on my own just before attending the meeting. I feel bad about not being maximally prepared, but sometimes that&amp;rsquo;s just what happens. When I was a perfectionist in the past, I would prefer to not do something at all if I was not &amp;ldquo;fully&amp;rdquo; prepared, but now, I see that sometimes, at least, home &amp;ldquo;preparation&amp;rdquo; is not actually optimal anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being completely unfamiliar with these songs, yes, I could ideally do the research and look up performances on YouTube, etc. (and I did in past weeks), but even then, how we play this music often differs anyway from what one might find. We might be in a different key, have simplified or different chords, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When playing in the Pittsburgh Recorder Society ensemble, I don&amp;rsquo;t leave things to chance, but do practice parts ahead of time, but this is a different kind of music that is hard to do exactly that kind of preparation. In particular, the sheets we get don&amp;rsquo;t have notes for the melodies, but just typically have text and then chord letters or tab symbols correlated loosely with the text, without any notation of duration. Basically, it&amp;rsquo;s a lot of guesswork to figure out what to do with the printed information we are given! It&amp;rsquo;s really best thought of as what music notation in the end is anyway: a lossy reminder of possible performance practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I&amp;rsquo;ve found that other than scanning the chords and working on getting them and the changes, as technical preparation, the best thing to do is to just show up and learn on the fly, by ear, and jot down notes, and then go home and really work on the songs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;ecofest-gig&#34;&gt;Ecofest gig&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sunny gave us more details about the logistics of our upcoming Ecofest gig that I signed up to take part in. We are going to receive nice little spiral-bound books containing the songs for performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;study&#34;&gt;Study&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the last meeting, I&amp;rsquo;ve invested in three technique books for ukulele. It is time to get truly serious and start working on technique.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;new-instrument&#34;&gt;New instrument&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, I finally just put in an order online for a new ukulele. I am going for high quality right off the bat, because I know that I am going to be serious about the instrument. It will not collect dust. I hope it will last me decades! I&amp;rsquo;ll report more when I get it. I hope it arrives soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m definitely getting serious about ukulele. I&amp;rsquo;ve invested not only in ukulele technique books, but also in a new instrument.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>