<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>St. Patricks Day on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/st.-patricks-day/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in St. Patricks Day on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/st.-patricks-day/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>18 miles in Vibram FiveFingers: training for the Pittsburgh Marathon through a St. Patrick&#39;s Day parade</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/03/16/18-miles-in-vibram-fivefingers-training-for-the-pittsburgh-marathon/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Mar 2013 18:22:34 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/03/16/18-miles-in-vibram-fivefingers-training-for-the-pittsburgh-marathon/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/18-miles/st-patricks-day-parade-prep.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Pittsburgh St. Patrick&amp;#39;s Day preparation&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My second &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.steelcityrrc.org/scrrcevents?eventId=619953&amp;amp;EventViewMode=2&amp;amp;CalendarViewType=1&amp;amp;SelectedDate=3/30/2013&#34;&gt;Saturday group training run with the Steel City Runners&lt;/a&gt; happened to be on St. Patrick&amp;rsquo;s Day weekend, and therefore took place just before the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pittsburghirish.org/parade/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh St. Patrick&amp;rsquo;s Day parade&lt;/a&gt;, which starts at 10 AM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;overtraining-and-knees&#34;&gt;Overtraining and knees&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/09/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings-in-one-12-mile-run/&#34;&gt;Last week I mentioned&lt;/a&gt; that I was having problems because of overtraining; I ran five days one week only to have to scale back to three the next. This week I consciously got in four days of running, with higher total mileage than either of the previous two weeks (when I did 26 and 23). This week, I got in 29. It wasn&amp;rsquo;t easy, especially given that I ran last week&amp;rsquo;s long run too hard and therefore had left knee oddness that actually lasted three days! It wasn&amp;rsquo;t so bad that I couldn&amp;rsquo;t run, but I clearly had to let it heal up, which it did in time for another long run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, both of John&amp;rsquo;s knees were in serious pain the day after last week&amp;rsquo;s training run, and a week later, he is still waiting for them to heal up, and therefore did not join me for today&amp;rsquo;s training run. Oops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;plan&#34;&gt;Plan&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For today&amp;rsquo;s run, I decided to run &lt;em&gt;only the first 16 miles&lt;/em&gt; and then walk the last 2 miles. Also, I joined the 10-minute pace group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that a lot of things went &amp;ldquo;wrong&amp;rdquo; on this run, but I got back to the start OK in the end!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;unknown-territory&#34;&gt;Unknown territory&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wore my Vibram FiveFingers Bikila LS shoes again. This is an important test, because I have &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; been on the road for 18 miles straight in these shoes before, run or walk! I need to know whether wearing these for the Pittsburgh Marathon will work out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;weather-conditions&#34;&gt;Weather conditions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had watched the forecast all week with concern that it might be pouring rain, but I was committed to do this run regardless of conditions, because if the Pittsburgh Marathon involves running in rain, I need to be ready to deal with that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that we lucked out; although it was cold, there was drizzling rain but no downpour!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/18-miles/start.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Start of run&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-route&#34;&gt;The route&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is the route of the 18-mile training run:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe id=&#34;mapmyfitness_route&#34; src=&#34;http://snippets.mapmycdn.com/routes/view/embedded/180281790?width=560&amp;height=400&amp;elevation=true&amp;info=true&amp;line_color=E60f0bdb&amp;rgbhex=DB0B0E&amp;distance_markers=1&amp;unit_type=imperial&amp;map_mode=TERRAIN&amp;last_updated=2013-03-11T10:51:41-04:00&#34; height=&#34;590px&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: right; padding-right: 20px;&#34;&gt;&lt;a target=&#34;_blank&#34; href=&#34;http://mapmyrun.com/routes/create/&#34;&gt;Create Maps&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a target=&#34;_blank&#34; href=&#34;http://mapmyrun.com/routes/&#34;&gt;search&lt;/a&gt; from 80 million at &lt;a href=&#34;http://mapmyrun.com&#34;&gt;MapMyRun&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-run&#34;&gt;The run&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started with the 10-minute pace group. I actually immediately fell back, wanting to start off running more slowly,  but was never too far from the pack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;st-patrick-s-day&#34;&gt;St. Patrick&amp;rsquo;s Day&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Immediately and throughout the run, I saw people in green who were a little loud and clearly had a bit to drink. I was amused that they were up and around already at 8 AM in the morning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We ended up running on Liberty Avenue through the setup for St. Patrick&amp;rsquo;s Day parade downtown (which begins at 10 AM). We got some cheers (many of us were wearing green) as well as some jeers. It was a strange experience, and I felt a bit embarrassed to be running through parade preparation.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/18-miles/st-patricks-day-parade-prep.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Pittsburgh St. Patrick&amp;#39;s Day preparation&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;first-water-stop&#34;&gt;First water stop&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the first water stop, I drank some water and grabbed a GU gel to go. I caught up to the 10-minute pace group at the first water stop, since a lot of people didn&amp;rsquo;t immediately keep going but waited for everyone to get water.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My new system with gels is to take one and then eat it some minutes after drinking water, rather than immediately with water. It saves time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;big-uphill-and-losing-my-map&#34;&gt;Big uphill and losing my map&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a big uphill going east on Liberty Ave during which I lost the 10-minute pace group because I prefer to go slower uphill to maintain an even &lt;em&gt;effort&lt;/em&gt; rather than &lt;em&gt;pace&lt;/em&gt;. I always make up the loss on the downhills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;second-water-stop&#34;&gt;Second water stop&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second water stop was near mile 8 in Shadyside. I caught up yet again to the 10-minute pace group at that point, and took another GU gel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, I realized that I must have lost my paper map while running up Liberty Avenue. This was bad, because although I roughly knew the route, I did not know all the details. I did have my smartphone on me, but the MapMyRun Web site did not display very well on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Worse, it appeared after the second water stop that the 10-minute pace group was either going much slower or I was all &amp;ldquo;warmed up&amp;rdquo; and going much faster, because I could not tolerate their pace, and I decided I had to forge ahead into Oakland, even though there was nobody ahead that I could follow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did find two other people who were willing to go at a faster pace along with me, so the three of us took off into Oakland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;birmingham-bridge&#34;&gt;Birmingham Bridge&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The three of us crossed the Birmingham Bridge together to the South Side. I remarked that the last time I did the Pittsburgh Marathon ten years ago, I was humbled by the uphill going &lt;em&gt;into&lt;/em&gt; Oakland (in the other direction) on the bridge.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/18-miles/birmingham-bridge.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Birmingham Bridge to South Side&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;south-side-and-falling-behind&#34;&gt;South Side and falling behind&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The South Side was a total party scene, as might be expected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Going east on Carson Street, I suddenly noticed at around mile 11 that I had lost one of my gloves. I had taken off my gloves earlier as it was getting warmer, and put them in my pockets, but just as I had lost my map because I hadn&amp;rsquo;t zipped my jacket pockets, I had now lost a glove. I apologized to my two companions and said I was turning back to find my glove if possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckily, my glove was just a block back, and a group of runners saw it and picked it up and gave it to me. But now my two companions were far away from me. I could still see them, but I didn&amp;rsquo;t want to run super fast just to catch them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;three-rivers-heritage-trail-and-getting-lost&#34;&gt;Three Rivers Heritage Trail and getting lost&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I saw my companions turn onto the Three Rivers Heritage Trail. At this point, I no longer knew exactly what the rest of the route was for the last 8 miles. I knew that there was a water/gel stop at some point in the next 7 miles before the West End Bridge, but had no idea where it was!! I really didn&amp;rsquo;t want to miss the final water/gel stop, since that would mean going 8 miles without any water or fuel. Of course, I did have some money on me, so I could stop somewhere to refuel, but I didn&amp;rsquo;t really want to stop if I didn&amp;rsquo;t have to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So now I&amp;rsquo;d run around 12 miles and my feet were definitely sore. It was a huge relief to be running on the trail, actually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then I made a mistake. I suddenly saw what seemed to be a water stop because a bunch of runners were gathering there. I approached and asked if it was the Steel City Road Runners water stop and they said no, it was Elite Runners and Walkers. They offered to give me some water anyway, but I declined, which was a mistake, because during the seconds I spent on this detour, I lost sight of my two companions!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I kept on running on the trail but they were just gone, and I never saw them again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;running-to-the-west-end-bridge&#34;&gt;Running to the West End Bridge&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I just kept on running west, figuring I would eventually get to the West End Bridge. I went through Station Square and made it across the West End Bridge. Now, I had planned ahead of time to stop running shortly after crossing the West End Bridge, because it was going to be 16 miles then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I started feeling cold, and so I did some run/walking east all the way back to the start. It was very lonely going the last 8 miles of the route alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;safe-and-warm&#34;&gt;Safe and warm&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I made it back OK. I grabbed two energy bars and went inside to get warm and stretch and devour the two energy bars. My feet were totally killing me, but I had survived 18 miles on them in Vibram FiveFingers Bikila LS shoes. I still have no idea whether I can last a whole marathon in them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;my-feet&#34;&gt;My feet&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although my feet are sore, everything seems to be OK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/18-miles/feet.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin&amp;#39;s feet&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/18-miles/shoes.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Vibram FiveFingers Bikila LS shoes&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/18-miles/soles.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin&amp;#39;s soles of feet&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;photos&#34;&gt;Photos&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/steelcityrrc&#34;&gt;Steel City Road Runners Facebook site&lt;/a&gt; is a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/media/set/?set=a.425827677512050.1073741827.391728257588659&amp;amp;type=1&#34;&gt;photo album of the St. Patrick&amp;rsquo;s Day run&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ran about 16 miles of the 18-mile route, as planned, but got lost, which I did not plan. I learned some lessons. In the future, I am zipping my jacket pockets, and I am also studying the printed map thoroughly before starting one of these runs. My super-sore feet have me worried about running the marathon in Vibram FiveFingers, so I will investigate alternatives. I&amp;rsquo;m still waiting for my order this week of &lt;a href=&#34;http://lunasandals.com/&#34;&gt;Luna Sandals&lt;/a&gt; to come in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, I&amp;rsquo;m thankful that Steel City Road Runners made it possible for me to do such a long run without feeling completely alone, and not having to haul all the water and fuel I needed during and after the run. Ten years ago when I was marathon training, I did carry along everything I needed, but it really is much nicer to simulate actual race conditions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am grateful that when I was done and called home, Abby baked a pizza for us to share when I got back. Fuel! Abby has been understanding and supportive during my training for the Pittsburgh Marathon. She thinks it&amp;rsquo;s a crazy thing to do, and it is, but I want to do it this once again while I have the opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A delayed St. Patrick&#39;s Day party: playing tin whistle and alto recorder</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/03/30/a-delayed-st-patricks-day-party-playing-tin-whistle-and-alto-recorder/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Mar 2012 22:58:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/03/30/a-delayed-st-patricks-day-party-playing-tin-whistle-and-alto-recorder/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Since so many people couldn&amp;rsquo;t make it to &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/17/st-patricks-day-party-playing-tin-whistle-and-flute/&#34;&gt;Henry&amp;rsquo;s St. Patrick&amp;rsquo;s Day party&lt;/a&gt;, Henry threw another party two weeks later, a second St. Patrick&amp;rsquo;s Day party! Abby and I attended this one too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was another huge milestone for me, musically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;chess&#34;&gt;Chess&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Henry has been playing chess very well lately in tournaments. In fact, last weekend in the big-money &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.chesstour.com/pit12.htm&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Open&lt;/a&gt;, he actually &lt;a href=&#34;http://chesstournamentservices.com/cca/tag/pittsburgh-open-2012-standings/&#34;&gt;tied for first in his section, winning $630&lt;/a&gt;, with a record of four wins and one draw, his best tournament in his life!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He sent me his games from the Pittsburgh Open, which I carefully analyzed and sent back to him with my annotations, just before the party. This was the first time I&amp;rsquo;ve analyzed games in well over a year. Doing it again sent the thrill of chess back into me. I thought I was done with chess, but now I&amp;rsquo;m vicariously living tournament chess through Henry. And I very much enjoying analyzing chess games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;music-preparation&#34;&gt;Music preparation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have learned by now that &amp;ldquo;preparation&amp;rdquo; when it comes to jamming does not amount to figuring out a few pieces. It means bringing a bunch of stuff and then figuring out what people want to hear or play with you, and then basically sight reading on the fly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So an important part of my music practice nowadays is &lt;em&gt;sight reading&lt;/em&gt;. I keep a big pile of music that I use simply to sight read.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because I felt still unready to play flute at a standard I found sufficiently acceptable to believe that people could take real pleasure in my playing, I decided not to bring my flute this time. I brought my tin whistle and recorders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;tin-whistle&#34;&gt;Tin whistle&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For tin whistle, I brought some big compilations of Irish music from the Carnegie Library, both fast and slow. I especially like slow Irish airs, not only because they&amp;rsquo;re slower and therefore &amp;ldquo;easier&amp;rdquo; to play, but because they are actually &amp;ldquo;hard&amp;rdquo; to play, in that you really have to pour yourself into expression and emotion; it&amp;rsquo;s actually easier to play fast music because you can cover up by just playing a lot of notes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;alto-recorder&#34;&gt;Alto recorder&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also brought a collection of Telemann minuets arranged for alto recorder and keyboard that I got out of the library as well. I have recently been getting a lot &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/21/flute-update-celebrating-bachs-birthday/&#34;&gt;into Baroque music&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;at-the-party&#34;&gt;At the party&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;chess-1&#34;&gt;Chess&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that David, a guy Henry knew from the Pittsburgh Chess Club tournaments, came to the party, so we spent a bit of time going over some recent games of theirs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;music-jamming&#34;&gt;Music jamming&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I felt much more comfortable than at the last party, since I was getting to know everyone, and I had not been &amp;ldquo;punished&amp;rdquo; in any way for my fumbling performances, but actually encouraged to keep playing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did soloing on tin whistle with slow Irish airs, and also did impromptu fast jigs and reels with Henry and Vassily.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what I enjoyed most was going through minuets with Henry at the piano while I played alto recorder. This being Baroque music, there was ample space for ornamentation on both parts. I have been working on the art of Baroque ornamentation, and was excited to let myself free during the repeats of the minuets we read through. At one point, Henry complimented me on my ornamentation, and I silently beamed. It&amp;rsquo;s a continual process, learning the art of ornamentation, because although there are some rules and guidelines, a lot is, as they say, a matter of having &amp;ldquo;good taste&amp;rdquo;. You want to do something interesting, but not too much, and not too distorting of the original. It&amp;rsquo;s tricky finding the right personal balance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby brought her various tamburas and mandolin to play and show Vassily.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a great time again at another of Henry&amp;rsquo;s parties. Great food, great company, fun playing music and talking chess.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>St. Patrick&#39;s Day party: playing tin whistle and flute</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/03/17/st-patricks-day-party-playing-tin-whistle-and-flute/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 Mar 2012 22:41:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/03/17/st-patricks-day-party-playing-tin-whistle-and-flute/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/st-patricks-2012/henry-franklin.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Henry and Franklin&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/st-patricks-2012/henry-franklin-abby.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Henry and Franklin and Abby&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Abby and I went to &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/01/27/a-new-friends-very-musical-birthday-party-changed-my-life/&#34;&gt;Henry&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/a&gt; place for a St. Patrick&amp;rsquo;s Day party, for which &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/12/quitting-the-cmu-all-university-orchestra-one-of-the-hardest-decisions-in-my-life/&#34;&gt;I had promised to play some music&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Today was one of the happiest days in my entire life!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;music-preparation&#34;&gt;Music preparation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All week, of course, I&amp;rsquo;ve been practicing &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/12/quitting-the-cmu-all-university-orchestra-one-of-the-hardest-decisions-in-my-life/&#34;&gt;tin whistle&lt;/a&gt;, and also some flute as well, in preparation for this party.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, I bought a brand new tin whistle just yesterday at the local music store down the street from home, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.acousticmusicworks.com/&#34;&gt;Acoustic Music Works&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/clarke-sweetone.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;My new Clarke Sweetone tin whistle&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It was a cheap &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.clarketinwhistle.com/&#34;&gt;Clarke&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.clarketinwhistle.com/products/sweetone-tin-whistle.aspx&#34;&gt;Sweetone&lt;/a&gt;. I got this to replace the Feadóg tin whistle that &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/11/learning-another-instrument-the-tin-whistle/&#34;&gt;I used initially to learn&lt;/a&gt; but was badly out of tune.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had picked up from the library a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lemccullough.com/Music-WhistleDVD.html&#34;&gt;nice little tutorial&lt;/a&gt; on tin whistle and learned a few tunes and some basics of ornamentation:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.lemccullough.com/Music-WhistleDVD_files/DVD%20cover-front-sm-filtered.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Learn to Play Irish Tinwhistle&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Completely unlike the classical orchestra world, here, the tunes are very easy, but all the interest is in the personal solo expression and ornamentation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;at-the-party&#34;&gt;At the party&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were, of course, fewer guests than at Henry&amp;rsquo;s birthday party. That was good, because it meant it was easier to get to know some people better (whom we had met at the earlier party) and also some new people we hadn&amp;rsquo;t met before. Actually, since Abby and I arrived very early, we got to know Henry better and vice versa before other guests arrived.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/st-patricks-2012/abby-franklin-st-patricks.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby and Franklin in green&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;chess&#34;&gt;Chess&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s always chess at Henry&amp;rsquo;s parties, because the kids like to play, and some adults too. I didn&amp;rsquo;t play this time; last time I did, but it was very time-consuming (Abby had to drag me away so we could go home), and I wasn&amp;rsquo;t playing any music then!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/st-patricks-2012/chess.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Boys playing chess&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;music-jamming&#34;&gt;Music jamming&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, there was jamming, before and after dinner. One of the young guys, Vassily, was eager to play accordion, and played waltzes and stuff from memory, and he had also brought a tin whistle and book, having heard I was coming with a tin whistle. (But he didn&amp;rsquo;t actually end up playing his!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that Vassily is interested in a wide variety of music, including Balkan, so Abby got all excited about meeting someone new who into the music she likes. Abby brought her tambourine and joined in a bunch of the jamming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;dancing&#34;&gt;Dancing&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any time I hear someone on accordion playing a waltz or polka, I just have to dance with Abby!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/st-patricks-2012/abby-franklin.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby and Franklin dancing&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h4 id=&#34;tin-whistle&#34;&gt;Tin whistle&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d only had a couple of days to work on tin whistle playing, so I&amp;rsquo;d only prepared to play a couple of tunes. But after I quickly ran out, people wanted more. And Henry wanted to accompany me with accordion or piano. I figured, what the heck, I&amp;rsquo;ll sight read some of the stuff I hadn&amp;rsquo;t even looked at in the tutor book. So I did, Henry figured out chords quickly, I stumbled around with lots of &amp;ldquo;wrong notes&amp;rdquo;, and it was all nevertheless OK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, not all of my notes were actually &amp;ldquo;wrong&amp;rdquo;: they just weren&amp;rsquo;t what was printed, but as long as stuff goes with the harmonies, there is no real sense in which the notes are wrong! That&amp;rsquo;s what&amp;rsquo;s so liberating about playing Irish music. I&amp;rsquo;m not following some orchestra score where every dynamic, every flurry of fast notes is carefully notated and is supposed to be followed exactly. And nevertheless, this freedom does not mean pure chaos. You still have to be aware of the stylistic conventions, of the implied shapes of phrases that you want to maintain or transform in some consistent way, etc. I really feel that playing this kind of music makes one much more connected with the role of &amp;ldquo;composer&amp;rdquo;, being very actively engaged and making short-term and long-term decisions about where to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vassily and I did some random jamming where he tried to accompany me as I read through some Irish music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;flute&#34;&gt;Flute&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also played flute for the first time in my life for people outside the context of school band and the CMU All-University orchestra I had just quit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I chose to play an arrangement of &amp;ldquo;Londonderry Air&amp;rdquo; for flute and piano, from &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/20/much-progress-playing-flute/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;I Used to Play Flute&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; so Henry accompanied me. I was standing as I played. I was so &lt;em&gt;nervous&lt;/em&gt; that my leg shook like crazy and I thought I was going to fall. I should have played sitting down. It was a huge deal for me, working up the courage to try to play flute while feeling like I was still a rank beginner (I still have terrible breath support and tone). I knew I didn&amp;rsquo;t play well, but I&amp;rsquo;d gone out there and done my best. I was proud of myself for that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed continuing to get to know Henry and his other guests better, and feeling more and more comfortable about playing music with them and for them. I felt like I was really coming out of my shell, both socially and musically. This is only the beginning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2012-03-30&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-03-30)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out my report on &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/30/a-delayed-st-patricks-day-party-playing-tin-whistle-and-alto-recorder/&#34;&gt;the next Henry party Abby and I attended&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>