<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Fight For Air Climb on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/fight-for-air-climb/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Fight For Air Climb on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/fight-for-air-climb/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>An early start on Cathedral of Learning stair climbing</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/29/an-early-start-on-cathedral-of-learning-stair-climbing/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Oct 2013 19:18:47 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/29/an-early-start-on-cathedral-of-learning-stair-climbing/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;After work today, I had gone to the Carnegie Library of Pittsburgh, main branch in Oakland, to pick up some books, when I looked across Forbes Avenue and saw the Pitt Cathedral of Learning. Primed by Becky&amp;rsquo;s message today about forming a team again for the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lung.org/pledge-events/pa/pittsburgh-climb-fy14/&#34;&gt;Fight for Air Climb at One Oxford Centre in downtown Pittsburgh, for next March&lt;/a&gt;, I suddenly decided to do the 36-floor stair climb of the Cathedral of Learning to &amp;ldquo;officially&amp;rdquo; begin my training for that event!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/cathedral-2013-10-29.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Cathedral of Learning&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m getting an early start this year on training for the Fight for Air Climb: last year, I didn&amp;rsquo;t even think about that event until I saw a poster for it during &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/28/meditations-on-climbing-the-36-floors-of-the-pitt-cathedral-of-learning/&#34;&gt;my first Cathedral climb in years, right after Christmas&lt;/a&gt;. So I&amp;rsquo;m going to have an additional two months of training.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;going-up&#34;&gt;Going up&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, in addition to my not having done the Cathedral climb in probably over half a year, I was wearing my work clothing and shoes and a backpack full of heavy books, so the climb was rather strenuous and sweaty. I even &amp;ldquo;forgot&amp;rdquo; to go to the 36th floor and got off at the 35th instead (no big deal).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/cathedral-2013-10-29-near-top.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;View out of 35th floor window&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;going-back-down&#34;&gt;Going back down&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once at the top, I didn&amp;rsquo;t stop to rest, because I wanted to get home quickly for dinner. Unfortunately, lots of people were already on the elevator when it came down from 36, and after I got on at 35, we kept on stopping to pick up others, and I felt very uncomfortable being sweaty and packed into the elevator near the back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-11-03&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-11-03)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/11/03/the-dilemma-of-how-to-descend-the-cathedral-of-learning-once-at-the-top/&#34;&gt;Three days later, I did the Cathedral climb again, and did take the stairs, but experienced a surprise.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The final Cathedral of Learning stair climb before the Fight for Air Climb</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/03/20/the-final-cathedral-of-learning-stair-climb-before-the-fight-for-air-climb/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Mar 2013 21:53:02 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/03/20/the-final-cathedral-of-learning-stair-climb-before-the-fight-for-air-climb/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Today, members of Team Ferlee met for a final stair climb at the Cathedral of Learning before we race in the Fight for Air Climb.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I originally had not planned to attend, because I am still in a state of recovery from all the running I&amp;rsquo;ve been doing, and had hoped to rest up till tomorrow before doing my own final stair climb. In fact, because I had not intended on a stair climb, I had done a run this morning already as my exercise for the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But circumstances made it most convenient for me to meet up with Becky in order to give her a final donation check as well as receive items to use for agreed-upon team costumes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-workout&#34;&gt;The workout&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out it was just Becky, Bill, and me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite starting from a condition of fatigue, I ended up doing four reps again. This was my most intense workout yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The three of us started with one rep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bill and I both did a crazy fast second rep: he did 6:49, which is a lot faster than the 7:26 he did &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/10/now-at-four-reps-of-the-cathedral-of-learning-stair-climb/&#34;&gt;ten days ago&lt;/a&gt;. I went close to all-out, but without knowing for sure when I could start my final sprint. Still, I finished in 7:06, a lot faster than the approximately 7:36 of ten days ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the third rep, I went at a fairly fast pace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my fourth rep, I did a series of intervals of sprints in order to figure out how long I could go into a full run. My conclusion was that I could not do more than five floors without my quads turning into jelly. That was good to find out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-next&#34;&gt;What next?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am completely beat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No more stair climbing tomorrow or Friday, because Saturday is the big day!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is unfortunate I left the fine-tuning of speed to the final week before the race, so I won&amp;rsquo;t get the full benefits of a serious training program, but optimizing the race was never of high priority to me, after all.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Only one easy rep of the Cathedral of Learning stair climb</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/03/17/only-one-easy-rep-of-the-cathedral-of-learning-stair-climb/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Mar 2013 23:55:52 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/03/17/only-one-easy-rep-of-the-cathedral-of-learning-stair-climb/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Team Ferlee met up yet again for a Cathedral of Learning stair climb workout.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I originally had not planned to even attend this time, for more than one reason:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;recovery from the crazy tough 18 mile Steel City Road Runners training run yesterday, of which I actually ran around 16 miles&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;having a Pittsburgh Recorder Society meeting to attend&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;having a St. Patrick&amp;rsquo;s Day party to attend after the recorder society meeting&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I missed not having seen the team since &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/10/now-at-four-reps-of-the-cathedral-of-learning-stair-climb/&#34;&gt;last week, when I crazily did four reps&lt;/a&gt;. I decided to show up briefly just to say hello before rushing off to the recorder society meeting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, I couldn&amp;rsquo;t help myself, and ended up doing one leisurely rep before leaving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That was actually probably a good thing to have done, because I left feeling less sore and tired. It&amp;rsquo;s definitely true in my experience that the day after a hard workout (as in my 16 mile run), one should resist the temptation to just be sedentary, and instead do something easy that increases circulation and warms the body in order to speed healing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s kind of funny to refer to an &amp;ldquo;easy&amp;rdquo; rep of doing a 36-floor stair climb, but in reality, after these months of gradual buildups, going up once at a leisurely pace is not actually hard for me at all any more. That&amp;rsquo;s encouraging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The team was amused I did this in my dress shirt and slacks (I did take off my socks and shoes and jacket and carried them in my hands while going up), but this is, after all, how I got started just before New Year!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;six-days-left&#34;&gt;Six days left&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are only six more days left till the Fight for Air Climb. I haven&amp;rsquo;t trained as much for this event as I would have liked, because my priority has been Pittsburgh Marathon training, but at some point this week I need to do some last-minute speed work in order to get at least some race sharpness for the Fight for Air Climb.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Now at four reps of the Cathedral of Learning stair climb!</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/03/10/now-at-four-reps-of-the-cathedral-of-learning-stair-climb/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Mar 2013 21:07:54 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/03/10/now-at-four-reps-of-the-cathedral-of-learning-stair-climb/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today I joined a Team Ferlee group stair climb workout at the Cathedral of Learning for the second time. &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/02/24/finally-doing-the-cathedral-of-learning-stair-climb-as-part-of-team-ferlee/&#34;&gt;Two weeks ago&lt;/a&gt; I did two reps and ten floors total.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am still in recovery from doing yesterday a really tough 12 mile Steel City Road Runners training run for the Pittsburgh Marathon, so I didn&amp;rsquo;t know what exactly I planned to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that thanks to Bill, with whom I finally climbed for the first time today, I did more than I had originally intended. In retrospect, I probably shouldn&amp;rsquo;t have, but I did, so what&amp;rsquo;s done is done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s what happened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-workout&#34;&gt;The workout&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The team did the first two reps sort of together, which meant not very fast for Bill or me. That was fine. I like socializing and going easy to warm up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the third rep, Bill decided he wanted to do a fast one, so he timed himself. I tried to follow him, but in my depleted condition had no plan to kill myself to overtake him. I just wanted to test an honest genuinely fast, but not all out, third rep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He ended up doing the third rep in 7:26, his new personal record. I did not time myself, but finished probably about ten seconds behind him, I gathered, so I did around 7:36. This was clearly the fastest I&amp;rsquo;ve also done one rep of the stair climb, not that I&amp;rsquo;ve been timing myself much in the past months (check out &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/19/why-ive-chosen-to-perform-only-two-repetitions-of-the-cathedral-of-learning-stair-climb/&#34;&gt;my reports from two months ago&lt;/a&gt;, when I timed myself just to get an idea of my baseline).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-fourth-rep&#34;&gt;My fourth rep&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone was done after the third rep, but I decided to hang around to do one last rep by myself, since I felt strangely OK even after the hard third rep; recovery from that seemed rather quick. The marathon training I&amp;rsquo;ve been doing has clearly helped with my endurance for stair climbing as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I did an untimed fourth rep just because I could.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having done four reps with good form is starting to give me confidence that in two weeks, I&amp;rsquo;ll be able to put in a good all-out effort in the Fight for Air Climb.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Finally doing the Cathedral of Learning stair climb as part of Team Ferlee</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/02/24/finally-doing-the-cathedral-of-learning-stair-climb-as-part-of-team-ferlee/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Feb 2013 18:01:42 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/02/24/finally-doing-the-cathedral-of-learning-stair-climb-as-part-of-team-ferlee/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have not been doing a lot of Cathedral of Learning stair climbing in the past month, because of life getting in the way. I did do a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/25/notes-on-exercising-while-sick-or-tired/&#34;&gt;fast single rep while tired&lt;/a&gt;, and then &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/31/doing-an-unexpected-workout/&#34;&gt;another single rep when short on time&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/02/02/an-unexpected-afternoon-tour-9-miles-of-running/&#34;&gt;a single rep in the middle of a long run&lt;/a&gt;, but that was it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, however, I started getting back into things. It&amp;rsquo;s been hard motivating myself to do the Cathedral of Learning stair climb, in part because I don&amp;rsquo;t inherently enjoy doing more than one rep. But now, I am part of an official &lt;em&gt;team&lt;/em&gt; for the Fight for Air Climb! This makes all the difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;team-ferlee&#34;&gt;Team Ferlee&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that a month ago, Chris, upon learning the Bill and I wanted to do the Fight for Air Climb, told us his coworker Becky had created a team and was looking for people to join it. So I joined it, but had been too busy, for a long time, to actually meet my fellow team members to train at the Cathedral.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But today, I finally carved out time to meet on a Sunday afternoon. I met Becky for the first time, as well as Natacha and the two Jennifers. (Bill was the only one who couldn&amp;rsquo;t make it.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have exactly a month before racing the actual Fight for Air Climb.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-workout&#34;&gt;The workout&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The plan was to do one rep and then an extra ten floors after going back down by elevator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have not been doing the stair climb for speed at all, so I was happy to do the first rep at my usual &amp;ldquo;comfortable&amp;rdquo; pace. Since each of us had a different pace, we regrouped at the top after everyone arrived. Then we took the elevator down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since we were to do just ten floors more, I decided to try to race up, to start some serious training finally. Up till now, I was just putting in a rep here or there, without doing any sprinting. I tried to &amp;ldquo;sprint&amp;rdquo; ten floors. It turns out that I can&amp;rsquo;t go all out (running two steps up a time) for ten entire floors. That&amp;rsquo;s good data to have, because in the actual race in a month, I want to know exactly how long a sprint I can actually sustain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;more-than-two-reps&#34;&gt;More than two reps!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other team members were done for the day for this workout and left.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But now that I was &amp;ldquo;warmed up&amp;rdquo;, I decided to stick around to do another full rep by myself, which I did. So this was actually the &lt;em&gt;first time in my life&lt;/em&gt; I did more than two reps: I did two reps and ten floors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over a month ago, I wrote about my deliberately &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/19/why-ive-chosen-to-perform-only-two-repetitions-of-the-cathedral-of-learning-stair-climb/&#34;&gt;limiting myself to just two repetitions of the Cathedral of Learning stair climb&lt;/a&gt;. The situation has changed now. It is time to not only add on more endurance, but also add more speed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was great to meet the team and socialize and get in some exercise also. I left feeling more motivated to continue training and meeting up. The sprint also changed things up and reminded me that it has always been part of the plan to sharpen up before race day.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why I&#39;ve chosen to perform only two repetitions of the Cathedral of Learning stair climb</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/01/19/why-ive-chosen-to-perform-only-two-repetitions-of-the-cathedral-of-learning-stair-climb/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Jan 2013 11:05:28 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/01/19/why-ive-chosen-to-perform-only-two-repetitions-of-the-cathedral-of-learning-stair-climb/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Four times now in the past two weeks, I have done exactly &lt;em&gt;two&lt;/em&gt; repetitions, no less and no more, of the 36-floor Cathedral of Learning stair climb.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A friend of mine who also started the stair climbing, inspired by my one-repetition initial climb before New Year, was very excited about immediately going to two, and then after that, going to three reps. I, on the other hand, have chosen to stay at exactly two. So yesterday I did two, as planned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s why I&amp;rsquo;ve chosen to stay at exactly two.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-question-of-goals&#34;&gt;The question of goals&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even before we begin an exercise program at all, we should be very clear and explicit about our goals. It is impossible to effectively and efficiently &lt;em&gt;achieve&lt;/em&gt; our goals if they are too vague or casual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes we expend all our &amp;ldquo;serious&amp;rdquo; energy on school or work or family, but do not carry out the same discipline when working on our goals outside the really big ones that in some sense are forced upon us. Typically, in these bigger, institutionalized realms, once we get involved at all, they have their own built-in feedback mechanisms to prevent us from totally slacking off (although of course there are workaholics who ignore their family as well as those whose highest priority is leaving the office at 5 PM sharp in order to get to the real business of having dinner with the family).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having specific goals enables we to break down into &lt;em&gt;action&lt;/em&gt; steps, supported by theory and practical experience and know-how.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Example questions we have to answer about our goals:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;short term or long term?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;appearance or function?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;specific or general?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, my overall goal in exercise is always &lt;em&gt;general&lt;/em&gt;, not tied to a specific event, but I always have secondary and tertiary increasingly specific goals, that I try to make as consistent as possible with the general goal, and exploit as rewards and milestones along the way for motivation and calibration. So for example, regarding my brand new stair-climbing component of my exercise regimen:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;primary: achieve and maintain lifelong functional core strength, power, vitality&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;secondary: get in better condition to enjoy tough, hilly runs and hikes here in Western Pennsylvania&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;tertiary: perform well in my very first &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lung.org/pledge-events/pa/pittsburgh-climb-fy13/&#34;&gt;Fight for Air Climb&lt;/a&gt; competitive event in March&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hill and stair climbing has always been a weakness of mine, so this is the year when I am going to systematically improve it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;analysis-of-goals&#34;&gt;Analysis of goals&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given my goals, we see that there is a mix of possible &amp;ldquo;zones&amp;rdquo; to target. I want both endurance and power. I&amp;rsquo;m not planning to do hilly ultramarathons, so maximizing endurance is not of interest. Therefore, I am not even thinking about building up to ten reps of the Cathedral of Learning stair climb.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I want to achieve a certain amount of endurance, for the long runs and hikes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But for the shorter term, I want to optimize for the Fight for Air Climb, which is only &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lung.org/pledge-events/pa/pittsburgh-climb-fy13/local/event-information.html&#34;&gt;45 floors (897 steps)&lt;/a&gt;. Given that, doing one fast rep of the Cathedral stair climb simulates best that particular event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-process-of-conditioning&#34;&gt;The process of conditioning&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then there&amp;rsquo;s the question of how to build up to where I want to be. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t happen all at once. Progress is gradual. The muscles need to grow and become efficient. How best to train?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve chosen to do two repetitions in order to simultaneously build up endurance and power, neither maximally, while in the early stages of training. My plan is to get enough endurance from this that I can then transition to more targeted training. In particular, I expect &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; to move up to three reps, but instead, to either drop &lt;em&gt;down&lt;/em&gt; to one rep, or instead change the parameters entirely, training anaerobically with sprints upward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-record-so-far&#34;&gt;The record so far&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s my history so far for the two-rep workout that I began this year:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/04/i-had-no-choice-but-to-barefoot-climb-the-cathedral-of-learning/&#34;&gt;2013-01-04&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;9:02&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;about 16:00 recovery&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;8:58&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/07/primantis-and-the-cathedral-of-learning/&#34;&gt;2013-01-07&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;9:07&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;10:42 recovery&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;8:54&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/14/three-questions-to-ask-yourself-when-you-dont-feel-like-doing-your-scheduled-workout/&#34;&gt;2013-01-14&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;8:47&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;8:39 recovery&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;8:21&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2013-01-18 (yesterday)

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;8:46&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;5:56 recovery&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;8:02&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In four workouts so far this month, I have made improvements while adhering to some deliberate constraints:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I have always taken it &amp;ldquo;easy&amp;rdquo; during the first rep.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I have focused on making the second rep not only faster than the first rep, but faster in absolute time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I have focused on shortening the recovery time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m going to stick to two repetitions until I reach an inflection point at which point I will make some big change. Staying with two allows me to gauge my progress along certain dimensions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is your preference when you work out? What variables do you change and monitor? Number of repetitions? Recovery time? Increase in distance? Increase in speed? Increase in weight load? And why? What are your goals?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-03-04&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-03-04)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over a month later, I finally moved up to &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/04/finally-moving-up-from-two-to-three-cathedral-of-learning-reps/&#34;&gt;three reps&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-03-10&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-03-10)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/10/now-at-four-reps-of-the-cathedral-of-learning-stair-climb/&#34;&gt;four reps&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A gradual progression made the improvement seem natural rather than painful and forced.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Primanti&#39;s and the Cathedral of Learning</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/01/07/primantis-and-the-cathedral-of-learning/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Jan 2013 21:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/01/07/primantis-and-the-cathedral-of-learning/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today I was scheduled to do the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/04/i-had-no-choice-but-to-barefoot-climb-the-cathedral-of-learning/&#34;&gt;Cathedral of Learning stair climb again, two repetitions like last time&lt;/a&gt;. Since I had stayed later at work than expected, I was hungry already, so I decided I would go do the two reps and then eat a lot of food.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;John was still around at work too and he was interested in doing two reps for the first time (years ago we&amp;rsquo;d periodically done one), so we went. We had a plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;two-reps&#34;&gt;Two reps&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did both reps barefoot this time, and with a fully stuffed backpack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided to lead the way with a slightly slow pace, in order to guarantee we would go faster during the second rep. We saw two people in shorts doing reps also. Both John and I were in street clothing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first rep we did in 9:07 (on Friday, alone, I had done 9:02).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This time I timed the break, because this is actually important information for the future when comparing improvement. We took a random break of 10:42 before doing the second rep, which we did in 8:54 (at some point before floor 31, we had an opportunity to overtake the other two people, who were on their third rep, and so I decided to just kick it up a notch for the rest of the way up).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-progression-plan&#34;&gt;My progression plan&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;John liked going two steps up at a time, but I am still on one by one, because it&amp;rsquo;s easier on my quads. My intuition tells me that a good cadence is important for efficiency, and until my quads are strong enough, I cannot keep a good cadence going up two steps at a time. Right now I&amp;rsquo;m focusing on simply getting some endurance and efficiency, and increasing the number of reps. After maybe two or three weeks of this, I will work on powering up two steps at a time over maybe no more than ten floors at a time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was amused to see the man wearing one of the old Rachel Carson Trail Challenge T-shirts that I also have, from 2008 (when I was a volunteer, not a participant as I was in 2005-2007). Also, the woman said she had done the Fight for Air Climb last year and placed third in the women&amp;rsquo;s division, I think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;primanti-s&#34;&gt;Primanti&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then we went to &lt;a href=&#34;http://primantibros.com/&#34;&gt;Primanti&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/a&gt; in Oakland, as planned. I stuffed myself with a huge roast beef sandwich, my usual order when I go there (just a couple of times a year).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I heard recently that Primanti&amp;rsquo;s may be &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wpxi.com/news/news/local/primanti-bros-receives-investment-hopes-expanding-/nTmGP/&#34;&gt;expanding nationwide&lt;/a&gt;. Cool! Why should the Pittsburgh area be the only one privileged to enjoy the huge &amp;ldquo;fully loaded&amp;rdquo; sandwiches with fries and cole slaw inside?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/primantis-roast-beef-oakland.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Primanti&amp;#39;s roast beef sandwich&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I had no choice but to barefoot climb the Cathedral of Learning</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/01/04/i-had-no-choice-but-to-barefoot-climb-the-cathedral-of-learning/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Jan 2013 18:28:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/01/04/i-had-no-choice-but-to-barefoot-climb-the-cathedral-of-learning/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/cathedral-of-learning-snow.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Cathedral of Learning in snow&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One week ago I reported on starting an exercise regimen including &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/28/meditations-on-climbing-the-36-floors-of-the-pitt-cathedral-of-learning/&#34;&gt;stair climbing 36 floors of the Cathedral of Learning&lt;/a&gt;. Since then, I&amp;rsquo;ve gone back three times to climb the Cathedral of Learning again. Part of the reason is that &lt;a href=&#34;http://billlaboon.com/&#34;&gt;Bill&lt;/a&gt; was inspired by the report and climbed it himself for the first time, and we decided we should do the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lung.org/pledge-events/pa/pittsburgh-climb-fy13/&#34;&gt;Fight for Air Climb&lt;/a&gt; this year. Therefore, he&amp;rsquo;s been going back for more climbing and so have I.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t expect to be regularly doing as much climbing as I happen to have been doing this past week. The other reason I did it was because it got colder and icier and I&amp;rsquo;m ramping up more slowly with my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/31/why-i-went-frick-park-trail-running-in-snowfall-for-the-first-time-in-a-decade/&#34;&gt;running&lt;/a&gt;, having run only twice in the past week while getting used to the impact again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, while chatting with Bill at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://pghrb.heroku.com/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Ruby&lt;/a&gt; users group, he mentioned he was planning today to do &lt;em&gt;two repetitions&lt;/em&gt; of the climb for the first time. So I decided to also do two reps for the first time as well, and committed to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things took an interesting turn during my Cathedral of Learning workout today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-plan&#34;&gt;The plan&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The original plan was simple. I&amp;rsquo;d head over in my work clothing with my backpack and stash my coat and scarf/hat/gloves into it and do the climb once, and then find a water fountain, hydrate, rest, and then take an elevator down to floor G, then do one more repetition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wanted to pace myself so that I would take the same amount of time for both reps. Based on my prior experience with endurance or strength training, I had no desire to use up my energy pointlessly in the first rep and then struggle in the second.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-first-rep&#34;&gt;The first rep&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I timed myself in order to be able to check my consistency over two reps. Of course, since I&amp;rsquo;m just starting to build a base, and I&amp;rsquo;m not going all out, the actual time doesn&amp;rsquo;t matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I encountered problems during the first rep. To tell the truth, these problems had appeared in milder form earlier through the week. The fundamental cause of the problems is that my street shoes I wear to walk in to work in the winter are not really suitable for athletic activity. My feet get sweaty, the non-zero height of the shoe just creates more distance I have to lift my legs, and there is more impact on my needs. Today the front of my right foot also got jammed such that by the time I ended my first rep, I was in actual pain! Plus, I had started blistering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As soon as I got to floor 36, I took off my shoes and socks and vowed &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; to wear this particular combination of footwear again for the stair climb.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My time was 9:02.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-rest-break&#34;&gt;The rest break&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I searched for nearby water. My quads were a bit weak as I walked back down from floor 36, one floor at a time, exploring all the open hallways for a water fountain. Curiously, I found one only when I reached floor 31. This was a bit of a surprise for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hit the elevator button to go down, but after minutes, the elevator still had not arrived. For all I knew, the buttons were broken. I walked down to floor 30. There, the elevator button seemed to work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-second-rep&#34;&gt;The second rep&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before the second rep, I stuffed my shoes and socks into my backpack. My right foot was still messed up from the first rep, but I hoped that it would fix itself now that I was shoeless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went up at what seemed a similar pace from the first rep. The experience was much easier for me than the first time. After a while, my right foot was completely OK. Also, I didn&amp;rsquo;t make noises for each step, but was able to land very lightly being barefoot. And my quads never felt sore, probably both because of the decreased leg lifting distance and because of the difference in impact angle. I felt more graceful and efficient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My time was 8:58, practically the same as for the first rep, so I was happy at my consistency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After my poor experience during my first rep climbing the Cathedral of Learning steps today, I decided to go barefoot, and solved all my problems. So I will continue to do this barefoot. I don&amp;rsquo;t even want to do this with minimalist shoes such as my &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/fivefingers/&#34;&gt;Vibram FiveFingers&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/xero-shoes/&#34;&gt;Xero Shoes&lt;/a&gt;; given the perfectly friendly nature of the stairways to bare feet, I will only ever again do the climb barefoot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The remaining question is whether it is permitted to do the Fight for Air Climb barefoot. I&amp;rsquo;ll have to find out.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>