<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Sick on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/sick/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Sick on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/sick/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Notes on exercising while sick or tired</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/01/25/notes-on-exercising-while-sick-or-tired/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Jan 2013 19:42:50 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/01/25/notes-on-exercising-while-sick-or-tired/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I was a bit sick this past week, a result of overexerting myself on various projects the previous week, and also Abby herself getting sick. We have been basically fine since Thursday, but I was feeling pretty bad Sunday through Tuesday in particular.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question always comes up, when I am sick or just plain tired, &amp;ldquo;What should I do to recover as efficiently as possible?&amp;rdquo; After trial and error over the years, I&amp;rsquo;ve come to realize I have to do a couple of things:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get more &lt;em&gt;sleep&lt;/em&gt;, whatever it takes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Eat only nutritious food, no junk.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Take some supplements such as vitamin C, B, zinc, fish oil (I don&amp;rsquo;t know if this is just a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.medscape.com/viewarticle/776832&#34;&gt;placebo effect&lt;/a&gt;, but it doesn&amp;rsquo;t matter because it seems to work, I end up believing, and therefore by the placebo effect it does work).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Start canceling lower-priority near-term engagements in order to free up rest time. (In retrospect, I should have bailed out of going to the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/21/attending-the-first-openhack-pittsburgh-meeting/&#34;&gt;first OpenHack Pittsburgh meeting&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get some kind of exercise.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s the exercise that gets tricky sometimes. When one is low on energy and weakened, what should one do, if anything at all? Here are some thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-even-exercise-at-all&#34;&gt;Why even exercise at all?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A long time ago, whenever I felt sick or tired, I would use that as a reason to just shut down and not get any exercise. I had the idea that I needed to &amp;ldquo;rest&amp;rdquo;, and any activity would only weaken me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that being completely sedentary is not actually &amp;ldquo;rest&amp;rdquo;. It is actually quite harmful. Lying around or sitting around all the time is, even for those of us who are healthy, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mayoclinic.com/health/sitting/AN02082&#34;&gt;unnatural and damaging&lt;/a&gt;. The way our bodies work actually changes when we are immobile. Granted, if we are seriously, seriously ill, and cannot move, then that is reality, but if we are ill but able to move, then there is a question of what we can do that helps rather than hinders recovery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;breaking-down&#34;&gt;Breaking down&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I take it for granted (and from experience) that when we&amp;rsquo;re sick, we shouldn&amp;rsquo;t just push through everything we would do if we were not. The reason is that normal levels of intense exercise deliberately does some controlled breaking down of the body in order for it to adapt and grow back stronger, but if we&amp;rsquo;re weak, we may not be strong enough to withstand the breaking down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I assume that we want to dial down the intensity in some way while retaining restorative effects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;walking-works-for-me&#34;&gt;Walking works for me&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find that walking (if you&amp;rsquo;re able to walk) is probably the ideal way of getting circulation when not feeling up to running or lifting weights. It&amp;rsquo;s low impact, you breathe more, and you can change the pace and intensity at very fine increments at will. So, if I do nothing else, I&amp;rsquo;ll get in a walk, even if it&amp;rsquo;s just around the block.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;running-sometimes-doesn-t-work-for-me&#34;&gt;Running sometimes doesn&amp;rsquo;t work for me&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find that it&amp;rsquo;s sometimes tricky to run when sick. The main problem is that there is a kind of threshold below which running feels inefficient to me. If you&amp;rsquo;re running a lot slower than usual, that is inefficient and increases pounding on the joints. I&amp;rsquo;d rather walk than run much slower than usual. So I haven&amp;rsquo;t run since &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/20/thoughts-on-an-unexpected-winter-barefoot-run/&#34;&gt;my barefoot run outside on Saturday&lt;/a&gt;. Now that I&amp;rsquo;m well again, I&amp;rsquo;m quite ready to resume running. I&amp;rsquo;d rather run when I&amp;rsquo;m excited to do it and feel that it will benefit me, instead of slogging through an inefficient and possibly form-disrupting run just because I&amp;rsquo;m &amp;ldquo;supposed&amp;rdquo; to run. As &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/14/i-love-medicine-balls-video-review-gaiam-fit-ball-workout/&#34;&gt;Tanja Djelevic&lt;/a&gt; recently wrote, &lt;a href=&#34;http://tanjadjelevic.com/blog/2013/01/22/for-the-purpose-of-living-loud/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;To be a slave to the work out regimen, and have hardcore guilt for missing a work out, is in every way detrimental.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, there are definitely times when I&amp;rsquo;ve run through a minor cold or something. It all depends. When the weather is really friendly (which it hasn&amp;rsquo;t been since real winter came immediately to Pittsburgh), it&amp;rsquo;s easy to just go out for a walk and have it turn into an easy run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;strength-training-partially&#34;&gt;Strength training, partially&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Usually, when I&amp;rsquo;m sick, I don&amp;rsquo;t feel like doing a whole lot of strength training. In fact, I&amp;rsquo;ve tested myself and when I&amp;rsquo;m sick, my pullups suffer considerably.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I&amp;rsquo;ve noticed that doing short bursts of &amp;ldquo;easier&amp;rdquo; exercises is quite helpful in getting the metabolism up and preventing the quick decline that happens if you just stop doing everything for too long. I do pushups every day (partially as a result of my 2013 decision to &amp;ldquo;earn&amp;rdquo; every square of chocolate I eat by first doing pushups just before eating it; as of today, I am earning my chocolate with 26 pushups). I don&amp;rsquo;t care how many I do: the point is to do something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-cathedral-of-learning-stair-climb-what-to-do-about-that&#34;&gt;My Cathedral of Learning stair climb: what to do about that?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been reporting regularly on my Cathedral of Learning 36-floor stair climb regimen &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/19/why-ive-chosen-to-perform-only-two-repetitions-of-the-cathedral-of-learning-stair-climb/&#34;&gt;lately&lt;/a&gt;. So what happened to my routine this week when I was not feeling well?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, I was supposed to do it Monday, and I was feeling queasy enough that I decided to completely bail out of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, Wednesday I was feeling much better, and decided that I wanted to do a reduced workout. I decided that after weeks of doing two repetitions, I was going to do &lt;em&gt;just one&lt;/em&gt;. But since I was feeling on the upswing, I felt that I was strong enough to gut out doing that one repetition relatively &lt;em&gt;fast&lt;/em&gt; (not all out fast, but pretty fast going one step at a time).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did it the fastest I&amp;rsquo;ve done so far this year, in 7:20. That&amp;rsquo;s 42 seconds faster than my fastest time yet in any of the stair climbs I&amp;rsquo;ve done so far this year. I was quite exhausted afterwards, and lay down panting for over three minutes (yes, I let the timer keep running to see when I would be able to breathe normally again). Doing the stair climb at this level of intensity to me feels considerably harder than &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/08/17/the-inaugural-liberty-mile-a-review-of-pittsburghs-first-road-mile-race/&#34;&gt;running an all-out mile race&lt;/a&gt;. Stair climbing is very different from (non-hilly) running, totally burning my quads and jacking up my heart rate way, way up (I didn&amp;rsquo;t measure it but I could feel it).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Afterwards, I felt pretty good and happy to have gotten myself out of my health slump.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;stair-racing-the-sport&#34;&gt;Stair racing, the sport?!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, here&amp;rsquo;s a great article a friend just sent me today about &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2013/01/27/magazine/stair-racing-a-sport-to-make-an-ironman-whimper.html&#34;&gt;stair racing, the sport&lt;/a&gt;. I had no idea there was actually a whole worldwide professional stair racing scene!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out the Empire State Building race:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/9iSGOUTz3QA&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;prevention&#34;&gt;Prevention&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, it&amp;rsquo;s better to prevent getting sick or tired in the first place. Here&amp;rsquo;s a great article on having &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sean-johnson.com/2013/01/22/why-you-need-more-margin-in-your-life/&#34;&gt;more &amp;ldquo;margin&amp;rdquo; in your life&lt;/a&gt; that I recently encountered. I plan to track and report on how I improve my margin in my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When my body is not functioning so well because of illness or fatigue, I try to figure out how to recover, and I&amp;rsquo;ve found that some types and levels of exercise are very helpful to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do you do to keep in shape when you are feeling sick or tired? Do you have your own specific plan B, or do you wing it, or do you follow the regular plan anyway?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Round 6 of Pittsburgh Chess Club tournament: playing pragmatically</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/12/18/round-6-of-pittsburgh-chess-club-tournament-playing-pragmatically/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Dec 2012 23:56:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/12/18/round-6-of-pittsburgh-chess-club-tournament-playing-pragmatically/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/chen-schreiber-2012-12-18_files/diag3FEF9E5EB4A16CC5.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Black Ne4 sacrifice&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Last week in &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/11/round-5-of-pittsburgh-chess-club-tournament-psychology-of-losing-another-won-game/&#34;&gt;round 5&lt;/a&gt;, I reported on a disastrous game I played in which I was mentally unbalanced and lost, for the second time in the current &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pittsburghcc.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Chess Club&lt;/a&gt; tournament, a game in which I was winning and went into an endgame one Pawn up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this week&amp;rsquo;s game, I also ended up in an endgame one Pawn up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I played pragmatically this time. I&amp;rsquo;ll explain what that means and why it is important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-complete-annotated-game&#34;&gt;The complete annotated game&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At your convenience, you can &lt;a href=&#34;../../chess/chen-schreiber-2012-12-18.htm&#34;&gt;enjoy playing over the game with my annotations, including diagrams.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;preparation&#34;&gt;Preparation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I had lost two games in a row, I was paired against an opponent, Jeff, of considerably lower rating than me, at his floor of 1900.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jeff had been much stronger in many years ago but after a visit to the hospital several years ago that resulted in his fighting for a year just to survive at all, he has never regained his former strength. I am very happy that he is back to stable health at all. He is a real asset to the Pittsburgh Chess Club, serving as a steward who opens and closes the club, answers the phone, etc: he was the very first person I met when I stopped by the club for the first time eight years ago, and he was so kind and helpful as I came back to chess after a two-decade absence that I decided to join the club and began playing in tournaments again in 2005. I owe Jeff for my return to chess play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for my record against Jeff, I had only played one game as White against him, in 2006, and lost when I failed to continue my attack properly against his Sicilian; I have won three games as Black against him in 2005, 2006, and 2008.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had no time or energy to devote to any special preparation for our game. In fact, I was so exhausted after the past couple of days (that included performing music at the annual &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/14/pittsburgh-contras-and-squares-holiday-ball-2012/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Contras and Squares Holiday Ball&lt;/a&gt; that I spent the weekend feeling as though I was going to get sick, slept a massive amount on both Saturday and Sunday, and on Sunday decided that I would take Monday (yesterday) off from work in order to continue to recover my health.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I did only two things to prepare for the final (whew) round of the chess tournament:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t do anything &lt;strong&gt;stupid&lt;/strong&gt; (the way I did in the last two tournament games).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As White, I had some control over the opening. I anticipated that he would play a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nimzo-Indian_Defence&#34;&gt;Nimzo-Indian&lt;/a&gt; against me if I let him, and I saw no reason to prevent him from doing so. I am very happy to play White against the Nimzo-Indian.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;overview-of-my-game&#34;&gt;Overview of my game&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-opening&#34;&gt;The opening&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I half-expected, Jeff played the Nimzo-Indian against me. We entered a variation that favors White.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/chen-schreiber-2012-12-18_files/diag3FEF9E591F75D725.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Nimzo-Indian&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-middle-game&#34;&gt;The middle game&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We ended up in a strange position in which Jeff for some reason chose to sacrifice his &lt;code&gt;g7&lt;/code&gt; Pawn for some activity.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/chen-schreiber-2012-12-18_files/diag3FEF9E5EB4A16CC5.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Black Ne4 sacrifice&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I took the Pawn, and then made a pragmatic decision to start simplifying to an endgame. This was not the strongest continuation, but I made this decision because frankly, I was very tired and my highest priority was to avoid a pointless loss caused by inability to calculate properly. So I wanted to simplify. In my last two games, I also deliberately chose to simplify, but then did not follow up consistently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My plan this time was to be consistent: play into a Pawn-up endgame where I had &lt;em&gt;no chance of losing&lt;/em&gt; and where I was the only one with &lt;em&gt;any chance of winning&lt;/em&gt;. Then I would sit and wait until my opponent made errors. If he didn&amp;rsquo;t and therefore held the draw, then so be it. I was tired of just plain losing out of time pressure and fatigue. I decided to stay ahead on the clock in a superior endgame.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-endgame&#34;&gt;The endgame&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I forced an exchange of Queens and even traded off Bishops.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/chen-schreiber-2012-12-18_files/diag3FEF9E61CFFEB075.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Drawn endgame?&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Objectively, this endgame should be a draw, of course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what is &amp;ldquo;objectivity&amp;rdquo; when I&amp;rsquo;m tired, and my opponent is over 200 rating points weaker than I am? In the end, chess is a human struggle of imperfection. My goal in this game was simply to avoid losing while preserving chances for a win, to close out this tournament with some honor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a single move, pushing &lt;code&gt;d5&lt;/code&gt;, Jeff finally blundered into a lost game.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/chen-schreiber-2012-12-18_files/diag3FEF9E6666666666.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Black loses&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Again, after this blunder, which loses a second Pawn (because Black ends up with too many weak isolated Pawns), I continued to play pragmatically. I didn&amp;rsquo;t look for the fastest win, the most elegant. I looked for what I felt to be the &lt;em&gt;safest&lt;/em&gt; win. I played to prevent Black from any chances at &lt;em&gt;counterplay&lt;/em&gt;. I slowly pushed my central Pawn mass, rather than go for some faster win that would rely on fewer of my forces but require more calculation. The last two weeks of playing in a tired physical and mental state showed that I could not trust my calculations. On the other hand, if I played relatively mindless but obviously good moves, rather than looking for the &amp;ldquo;best&amp;rdquo; moves, I could guarantee a win eventually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so I did.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/chen-schreiber-2012-12-18_files/diag3FEF9E712D51E931.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Black resigned&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;lessons-learned&#34;&gt;Lessons learned&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was nothing very exciting about this game. It was just a game in which I had an advantage straight out of the opening and &lt;em&gt;was never worse&lt;/em&gt; and also never played the best moves at interesting points in the game. I only played &amp;ldquo;good enough&amp;rdquo; moves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I only show this game to illustrate what it means to play pragmatically when outside forces dictate that this is the correct thing to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I am human; if I am tired, I must play differently than when I am fully rested and mentally sharp.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If the goal is to win, against a weaker opponent, it is often enough to just maintain an advantage, even in an objectively drawn endgame, because if he could always draw this kind of endgame, then he would have a higher rating.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-next&#34;&gt;What next?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m totally exhausted from the past two months of my life, and ready for the winter holidays, during which I expect to mostly just stay at home and recharge, and figure out my plans for the coming year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m absolutely certain now that next year I should not play again in this annual Tuesday night tournament that spans November and December. This is a bad time of year for me in terms of all the things that pile up on me at the end of the year. The historical record: I played terribly in this tournament also in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.uschess.org/msa/XtblMain.php?201012144091-12226800&#34;&gt;2010&lt;/a&gt; and in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.uschess.org/msa/XtblMain.php?200812165511-12226800&#34;&gt;2008&lt;/a&gt;. I should have thought about this trend before signing up this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will decide by New Year whether to play in the next Tuesday night tournament. Part of me clearly wants to continue with my chess explorations, but I really have to take into account what other commitments I&amp;rsquo;ll be making for January and February, to make sure I don&amp;rsquo;t play chess tired.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;followup-report-on-the-tournament&#34;&gt;Followup report on the tournament&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The two guys I lost to in rounds 4 and 5 played each other to decide first place in the tournament. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.uschess.org/msa/XtblMain.php?201212180392&#34;&gt;Ed ended up winning&lt;/a&gt;. I saw part of the game before I finished mine and left, and will comment on it in my next chess blog post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went into this final round of the chess tournament with a clear goal, and a clear method of achieving it, which was to play pragmatically and get the win. I accomplished this non-glamorous goal, and hope that in the future, I will be more deliberately pragmatic in my play in general.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Running my 10th Great Race 10K: &#34;obscene but in a good way&#34;</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/09/30/running-my-10th-great-race-10k-obscene-but-in-a-good-way/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Sep 2012 19:08:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/09/30/running-my-10th-great-race-10k-obscene-but-in-a-good-way/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/great-race-2012/great-race-expo.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Great Race quilt&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Today I ran in Pittsburgh&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://rungreatrace.com/&#34;&gt;Great Race 10K&lt;/a&gt; for the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/25/blistered-but-blissful-in-the-burgh/&#34;&gt;tenth time in my life&lt;/a&gt;. For various reasons, I performed a number of experiments for this tenth running of the race, doing things I&amp;rsquo;ve never done before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the race, I heard someone say, as I passed him:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
...obscene... but in a good way!
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It made my day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll explain what might have triggered this reaction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;preparation-and-uncertainty&#34;&gt;Preparation and uncertainty&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/07/running-my-8th-pretty-good-race-5k-dealing-with-disappointment/&#34;&gt;Pretty Good Race 5K&lt;/a&gt;, I was so tired out from my effort that I totally lost the desire to run. Plus my left foot was hurting more again. I ended up not running a single step for two weeks. This meant, of course, that there was no way I was going to go after the goal of beating last year&amp;rsquo;s time in the Great Race 10K.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, there was the question of whether I should even run the Great Race at all this year! Until almost the last minute, Abby and I agreed that if I did not feel up for running it at all, I would just sell my registration. Part of me felt bad about the possibility of breaking &amp;ldquo;tradition&amp;rdquo; and not running the race; I have stubbornly run it while horribly sick in some years! At the same time, it&amp;rsquo;s not really the end of the world if I miss a race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;change-of-purpose-and-plan-enter-the-invisible-shoes&#34;&gt;Change of purpose and plan: enter the Invisible Shoes!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eventually, after my two-week absence from running, my left foot injury resolved itself, and I started running again. The plan was to start road running (since I prefer to trail running) in preparation for the Great Race. The problem is that I actually don&amp;rsquo;t like wearing my road running Vibram FiveFingers shoes, my Bikila LS shoes. In fact, since my taste in footwear has become more and more minimalist over time, the Bikila LS shoes seem like a step totally in the wrong direction. I got them last year really only for the purpose of road racing, since the KSO blisters me and the KSO Trek is for the trails.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just to start running again, I began going out for 2-3 mile casual runs in my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/26/walking-and-running-in-invisible-shoes-a-review/&#34;&gt;Invisible Shoes&lt;/a&gt; that I&amp;rsquo;d been wearing all summer for walking, and sometimes for running. I enjoyed my short runs in these huaraches.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/great-race-2012/invisible-shoes-rolled.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Invisible Shoes rolled up&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Given that I was just getting back into running after such a long break, I never ran more than 3 miles during any of my runs leading up to the Great Race. And I never wore anything other than the Invisible Shoes. So that led me to the idea that since I wasn&amp;rsquo;t going to be able to achieve a goal of running super fast this year, I could set a &lt;em&gt;different goal&lt;/em&gt; for myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My new goal: &lt;em&gt;run the Great Race 10K in 4mm huaraches&lt;/em&gt;. More specifically, I wanted to see how my joints and muscles would hold up, as well as my feet and skin. Also, I&amp;rsquo;d never run fast in huaraches before, so this would also be an experiment in running fast in them. I had every intention of running pretty fast: I simply expected that I would not be able to run as fast as if I were running more protected shoes, because of many factors such as flopping soles and more pounding, resulting in my going more conservatively than if I had already experimented and knew what the limits were.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, originally I had planned to run a 5K race sometime in the huaraches; I had never planned to suddenly run a 10K in them without running a 5K first!! Also, I was going to run this 10K without having run more than 3 miles at a time in an entire month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;last-minute-panic-and-recovery&#34;&gt;Last minute panic and recovery&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Friday, I was coming down with a sore throat, and my boss said he and his son were both sick (they were both signed up for the Great Race this year). Now I was totally uncertain about whether I was going to run on Sunday. I tried to get healthy, and on Saturday, was feeling more stable, although a sore throat kept lingering, and picked up my race packet. Luckily, I was feeling great this morning, with no sign of a sore throat, so apparently my &amp;ldquo;placebos&amp;rdquo; worked (sleep, healthy food, various supplements). I canceled all my Saturday plans (such as going to a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/28/another-french-music-jam-also-announcing-cats-dance/&#34;&gt;French dance workshop&lt;/a&gt;) in order to rest up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other concern was the weather forecast. All week it seemed like it was going to rain sometime this morning. I&amp;rsquo;ve run in rain before, raced in rain before. I can do it. But the last time I ran in Invisible Shoes in the rain, I got into trouble. So now what? I simply decided I was going to deal with rain if it happened. Yet another variable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-race&#34;&gt;The race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;to-eat-or-not-to-eat&#34;&gt;To eat or not to eat?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One experiment I did today that I deem a big success: &lt;em&gt;I ate almost nothing before the race&lt;/em&gt;. I ate a bunch of almonds when I was leaving the house, but that was it. In the past, I always ate something more substantial before a race. Rationally, it does not make sense, but for some reason, I always felt that I should eat a mini-meal. This was completely irrational, a weird clinging behavior I engaged in: after all, when I casually go running in the morning, I do it before breakfast! So why should race day be any different? We human beings have enough fuel stored in our bodies. It&amp;rsquo;s true that when I go for a run of over, say, 8 miles, I get hungry, and like to either have a snack on me to eat, or have eaten right before going on the run, but when it comes to 5K and 10K races, clearly there is no need for me to eat before the race. Experience has shown that it only makes me feel sluggish. So from now on, &lt;em&gt;no more mini-meals before a race of 10K or shorter&lt;/em&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;shoes&#34;&gt;Shoes&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/great-race-2012/franklin-before.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin wearing Invisible Shoes and race number 1853&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/great-race-2012/feet-before.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin wearing Invisible Shoes&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As usual, I jogged a mile from home to the start line as my warmup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;beginning&#34;&gt;Beginning&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The temperature was in the low 50s F: ideal racing temperature, not too cold. Under 50, I would have worn a long-sleeve T-shirt instead of a short-sleeve one. As it was, since I anticipated rain, I did not wear my usual singlet but instead a standard short-sleeve T-shirt. It was not yet raining, thankfully!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some guy stepped on my right toes with his shoes as he wandered through the crowd. I was upset by this and hoped that my toes were OK. They were sore for a few minutes but then I forgot about them and was OK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within the first few minutes, I saw Don Slusser ahead of me; last year I had tracked him and then passed him at the end of the race. This year, he was obviously going much slower, thanks to his shot knees, so I passed him early on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I saw my boss standing on his street corner watching the race. I asked why he wasn&amp;rsquo;t running and he said he was too sick. It&amp;rsquo;s too bad he had to miss the race yet again, after missing it last year because of another commitment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My huaraches seemed to be working pretty well as I ran faster than I had ever run in them. I rather enjoyed being able to feel the ground, as though I were fully barefoot. At 4mm, running with these is pretty close to being barefoot, much closer than wearing Vibram FiveFingers shoes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wasn&amp;rsquo;t paying much attention to any glances or stares at my feet, or remarks people may have been making, although a few runners did directly ask me about my &amp;ldquo;flip flops&amp;rdquo;, with an attitude ranging from incredulity to amusement to admiration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;middle&#34;&gt;Middle&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Near halfway through the race, it started raining fairly steadily. I had to periodically wipe the water away from my eyes. Well, it was in the forecast. One thing I can say is that I was never in danger of overheating in this race! There have been instances of the Great Race in warm conditions under a sun, when even in a singlet I got very warm and had to dump water over my head: ha, today I got free water on my head constantly!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I started the race further back than I usually do, there were very few people running at exactly my pace. I was always either passing or being passed by people. This is one thing annoying about big races where people can cross the start mat at very different times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, at one point, a guy came to be in front of me who was running approximately my pace, so that I was almost a constant distance from him. On downhills I would tend to overtake him, but then he would come back. We would be mostly together for approximately the last two miles. At one point when I slowly passed him, I think I heard him say, &amp;ldquo;That&amp;rsquo;s obscene&amp;hellip; but in a good way!&amp;rdquo; I believe that comment was directed at me and my footwear, and I kind of took it as a compliment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;end&#34;&gt;End&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The water puddles were starting to get to me, as I had earlier feared. I did not feel confident about running any faster than I already was, given the road conditions and the way my huaraches were slipping around. And my toes were getting sore from the pounding. Normally, in the end of a race, I turn it on and try to use up the remaining energy I have, but today, I just did not feel confident in my footing. I continued going reasonably fast, but did not put in any finishing sprint at all. Even if I had wanted to, it would have been difficult, because of so many slower people in front of me. This is a direct consequence of my lining up at the start line far further back than I usually do: what happens is that slower people who started further up are in the way for the entirety of the race!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I did turn it on just enough to pass that guy I had been more or less with for two miles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;result&#34;&gt;Result&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My chip time was 48:23, not too bad given my footwear experimentation and lack of conditioning and failure to go all out in the final mile; last year&amp;rsquo;s time was 47:46. Next year, I would like to go under 47:00. I should be able to do that if I maintain a regular running regimen. 2006 was the last year that I went under 47:00.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;after-the-race&#34;&gt;After the race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got some water, was given two Smiley Cookies, and ate a bagel and a banana also. I hopped on the shuttle bus back to the start line (the ride took 30 minutes), then walked 25 minute (1.5 miles) back home in the cold. In the future, I don&amp;rsquo;t want to do this walk. I should park my car near the start line the night before, so that I can hop off the bus and drive home. It&amp;rsquo;s no fun to be walking so long in the cold when you&amp;rsquo;re tired and you&amp;rsquo;re not sure what the condition of your feet are, except that they hurt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are my feet after I got home:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/great-race-2012/feet-after.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin&amp;#39;s bare feet after race, at home&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It turns out that I got only one blister, and it was exactly where I got a blister last time I ran in the rain in the huaraches: between my first two toes. There was some roughing up of the callouses on the balls of my feet (from wearing the huaraches all summer), but otherwise, my feet were OK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After some more hours of recovery, I was feeling fine. No joint pain whatsoever, no muscle soreness whatsoever, none of that stuff. Even last year I had some stiffness when I got off the shuttle bus. My conclusion is that truly minimalist footwear trains me to land in such a way as to minimize problems to my body. No shin splints, no ankle soreness, no knee pain, no hip pain, no shot quads, no cramping calves, nothing. Just a blister, and toes and forefoot that were sore for a while but right now no longer are. It&amp;rsquo;s amazing what &lt;em&gt;no cushioning for the feet at all&lt;/em&gt; did to prevent the problems I used to face when running. I am so completely sold that I will look into running more races in huaraches, and in optimizing my lacing in order to prevent the flopping limitation and that one blister spot. I am consider going up to the 6mm sole from the 4mm sole, with the idea that 6mm would be more solid for racing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another thought: assuming a race with no rain or extreme cold or hot surfaces, I should run a race &lt;em&gt;barefoot&lt;/em&gt; sometime next year. I&amp;rsquo;ll think about this. I know people who have done this. Why not? Barefoot, one does not have to worry about blisters caused from laces, or sole flopping, or water slipping. One may have other worries instead, but knowing a course ahead of time can help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;photos&#34;&gt;Photos&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Official photos of me in action, including beating the guy I mentioned, are &lt;a href=&#34;http://orders.islandphoto.com/RACE/Proofs.aspx#26561404-00002-0026&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, but since they are copyrighted, I have not inserted them directly into my report here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why I missed the CMU intramural XC race this year</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/09/27/why-i-missed-the-cmu-intramural-xc-race-this-year/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Sep 2012 22:25:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/09/27/why-i-missed-the-cmu-intramural-xc-race-this-year/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;One thing interesting about having been writing in my blog for &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/22/celebrating-this-blogs-one-year-anniversary/&#34;&gt;just over a year now&lt;/a&gt; is the opportunity to look back one year and compare where I was then with where I am now when it comes to seasonal activities and goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, today I was originally planning to run in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://athletics.cmu.edu/intramurals/index&#34;&gt;CMU intramural&lt;/a&gt; men&amp;rsquo;s XC race this year, as &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/23/happiness-is-finishing-39th-of-43-men-in-a-race/&#34;&gt;I had enjoyed doing it last year&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ended up not running it for a couple of reasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been barely running since the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/07/running-my-8th-pretty-good-race-5k-dealing-with-disappointment/&#34;&gt;Pretty Good Race 5K&lt;/a&gt; and therefore untrained, and probably likely to finish dead last, given the very few number of guys preregistered.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It was raining pretty hard, making unpleasant the thought of running outside on the grass and mud.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I was feeling OK yesterday, but today was feeling unusually tired and almost sick, and I&amp;rsquo;m still trying to determine whether to run the Great Race on Sunday &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/25/blistered-but-blissful-in-the-burgh/&#34;&gt;for the tenth time as planned&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some interesting observations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If I had not been feeling sick, I think there was a 30% chance I would have run anyway.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If I had not been feeling sick, and it had not been raining, there was a 95% chance I would have run anyway (my only fear being forgetting the course and losing contact with the second-to-last place guy).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having a long-running blog enables me to remember what I did and what I hoped to do the following year, and compare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year, I didn&amp;rsquo;t manage to do what I planned a year ago. Well, there&amp;rsquo;s always next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2012-09-30&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-09-30)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/30/running-my-10th-great-race-10k-obscene-but-in-a-good-way/&#34;&gt;I did manage to run the Great Race 2012&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reflections on 2011</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/12/31/reflections-on-2011/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Dec 2011 18:52:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/12/31/reflections-on-2011/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I reflect on my year of 2011 as it ends. Since I did not start blogging until September, I go into more detail of what happened before then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;january&#34;&gt;January&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I continued our project of massively reorganizing our home, a project that began when she moved in during summer 2010. We were very grateful that Abby&amp;rsquo;s father helped out a lot.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I continued getting rid of a lot of stuff, including another eighteen boxes of my books, as I became an initially reluctant &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/minimalism/&#34;&gt;minimalist&lt;/a&gt;. We sold or gave away a &lt;em&gt;huge&lt;/em&gt; number of various of belongings.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby started cooking much more than in the past, and we enjoyed trying new dishes of her making.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I enjoyed some light cross-country skiing in the winter, using the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Schenley_Park_Golf_Course&#34;&gt;Bob O&amp;rsquo;Connor Golf Course at Schenley Park&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I began a weekly Zen &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/meditation/&#34;&gt;meditation&lt;/a&gt; session offered at Carnegie Mellon University.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started moving very gradually toward a &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/paleo/&#34;&gt;paleo&lt;/a&gt; diet and exercise routine, and immediately experienced benefits. &amp;ldquo;The Paleo Solution&amp;rdquo; by &lt;a href=&#34;http://robbwolf.com/&#34;&gt;Robb Wolf&lt;/a&gt; was very useful.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started learning modern &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/javascript/&#34;&gt;JavaScript&lt;/a&gt; for a new project at work, getting into client-side Web development. As part of that, I learned &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/jquery/&#34;&gt;jQuery&lt;/a&gt; through a free &lt;a href=&#34;http://p2pu.org/&#34;&gt;P2PU&lt;/a&gt; course and used it in the project.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started using &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/XQuery&#34;&gt;XQuery&lt;/a&gt; at work to process XML in a clear and concise way. I had used XSLT in the past, but it was very unpleasant.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I decided, for various reasons, to stop writing new &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/perl/&#34;&gt;Perl&lt;/a&gt; scripts and move to &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/python/&#34;&gt;Python&lt;/a&gt; instead.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started playing in my final (and disastrous) &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/chess/&#34;&gt;chess&lt;/a&gt; tournament, the Pittsburgh Chess Club Championship (which I had won in 2006 and 2007).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;february&#34;&gt;February&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pittsburgh was all about the Steelers, and I went to a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Super_Bowl_XLV&#34;&gt;Super Bowl&lt;/a&gt; party for the first time, but we lost!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I read &amp;ldquo;The Art of Non-Conformity&amp;rdquo; by &lt;a href=&#34;http://chrisguillebeau.com/&#34;&gt;Chris Guillebeau&lt;/a&gt; and found it so inspiring that I decided to take action and start making big changes to my life, in my own way.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;One big change: I quit playing chess, cold turkey, after having been unenthusiastic about it for months already (and playing correspondingly poorly). When the passion and enjoyment are gone, there is no point in hanging onto something just because it has been such an important part of my life for years.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;After years of not playing any music at all, I started playing &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/recorder/&#34;&gt;recorder&lt;/a&gt;, and vowed to play every single day if possible. Ten months later, I am still playing recorder.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I began attending a lot of &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/16/pittsburgh-software-developer-communities/&#34;&gt;local software developer group meetings&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started learning the &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/scala/&#34;&gt;Scala&lt;/a&gt; programming language and decided to use it on a small project.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;march&#34;&gt;March&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I continued our meditation practice at CMU, and went to our first mini-&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sesshin&#34;&gt;sesshin&lt;/a&gt; on a Saturday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I continued practicing recorder every single day, and joined the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.andrew.cmu.edu/user/lukas/pcars/Welcome.html&#34;&gt;local chapter of the American Recorder Society&lt;/a&gt;. It was very exciting to meet new people and to get into a wide range of music I had never really listened to or played.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I saw a video of &lt;a href=&#34;http://jakeshimabukuro.com/&#34;&gt;Jake Shimabukuro&lt;/a&gt; playing &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/ukulele/&#34;&gt;ukulele&lt;/a&gt; so beautifully that I was inspired to buy a ukulele and start learning to play it. (Unfortunately, it would turn out that time constraints caused me not to pursue ukulele far. This will change in 2012.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I got pulled into the Ruby programming language because it is well-supported on Mac OS and it is easy to install libraries and tools, of which there are many that are quite useful.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I went to &lt;a href=&#34;http://farmtotablepa.com/&#34;&gt;Farm to Table&lt;/a&gt; in Pittsburgh, and after that, Abby started moving toward paleo eating, with even better results than my smaller experiments earlier.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I started our &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/hiking/&#34;&gt;hiking&lt;/a&gt; season in the spring. Hiking is special to us; it was one of our first shared activities (after initially meeting during salsa dancing), and one we return to again and again. When there is no calendar conflict and the weather is acceptable, we like hiking almost every weekend from spring through fall.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;{% img /images/steves-soup-hike-2011-03-26.jpg Abby in front of me at Steve&amp;rsquo;s Soup Hike %}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;april&#34;&gt;April&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started wearing &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/fivefingers/&#34;&gt;Vibram FiveFingers shoes&lt;/a&gt; almost all the time, whether walking or running (but not yet for hiking).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I went to &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/yoga/&#34;&gt;yoga&lt;/a&gt; at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.clpgh.org/locations/squirrelhill/&#34;&gt;Squirrel Hill Library&lt;/a&gt; for the first time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;may&#34;&gt;May&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I began my experiment with barefoot running, in observation of &lt;a href=&#34;http://barefootrunners.org/ibrd&#34;&gt;International Barefoot Running Day&lt;/a&gt;. I started walking around barefoot at work, ignoring the confused looks or comments of colleagues. (I still go barefoot at work.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I bought a &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/melodica/&#34;&gt;melodica&lt;/a&gt;, inspired by the amazing performances of &lt;a href=&#34;http://jnote.org/&#34;&gt;James Howard Young&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I took a little vacation, spending some days in New York visiting Nathaniel and Yael and their baby. I finally fulfilled my dream (from before marriage) of taking Abby to Coney Island to walk on the boardwalk and at the beach, eating pizza, and riding the Wonder Wheel, just as I once did when I was six years old.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I started doing research into major home renovations for the summer.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I visited my parents, and my sister Linda and her husband Andre also visited, with my mother throwing a delayed reception at home for the both of us who had gotten married in the past two years. Abby got to meet my parents&amp;rsquo; friends, finally. And I went running with my brother-in-law for the first time! Also, I took Abby to the little park in Ann Arbor where as a too-shy teenager I used to go and sit on a particular bench and wish I were sitting with my dream girl. Mission accomplished!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;june&#34;&gt;June&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;John and I did a tough 19-mile training hike on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rachelcarsontrails.org/rct&#34;&gt;Rachel Carson Trail&lt;/a&gt; and decided we&amp;rsquo;d had enough of that trail, and I decided I was probably not going to do the 35-mile &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rachelcarsontrails.org/rct/challenge&#34;&gt;Rachel Carson Trail Challenge&lt;/a&gt; again (having completed it three times in the past).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;{% img /images/rachel-carson-trail-2011-06-05.jpg John on Rachel Carson Trail %}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby started wearing Vibram FiveFingers more and more for walking and running, and even walking barefoot on the streets (something I had not yet seriously done myself at the time).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I stupidly threw out my back during exercise, and my back took weeks to fully recover (I could still run and hike, but not lift weights). Never again, I hope. I felt like a 90-year-old when my back was hurting constantly.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;We started some home improvement projects.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;july&#34;&gt;July&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started gravitating to almost exclusively body weight &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/strength-training/&#34;&gt;strength training&lt;/a&gt;, as a reaction to my having injured my back earlier.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I went kayaking on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kiskiminetas_River&#34;&gt;Kiski River&lt;/a&gt; with &amp;ldquo;Fireman Steve&amp;rdquo; and the kayaking gang.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;On a longish hike, Abby surprised me by wearing Vibram FiveFingers shoes and they worked great for her, making her much faster and less sore, and I made a note to ditch my trail running shoes (which I had been using for years for hiking) in favor of FiveFingers for my next hike (which I did, and I have not gone back to regular shoes for hiking!).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I finally took Abby to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sandhillberries.com/&#34;&gt;Sand Hill Berries&lt;/a&gt; for tasty pie for the first time, always having intended to take her there when dating, but never having been in the vicinity with her then.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Major home renovation finally began, after much research, and we got electrical upgrade, insulation, and bathroom demolition and rebuilding. Very disruptive to our lives for weeks!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I did another mini-&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sesshin&#34;&gt;sesshin&lt;/a&gt; at CMU.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;After a lifetime of almost never drinking coffee (average of maybe three or four cups a year), I became an avid espresso fan (one small cup a day) as a result of my boss getting a machine at work.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started doing more barefoot running.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;august&#34;&gt;August&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bathroom renovation done at last.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I were regularly hiking in Vibram FiveFingers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;{% img /images/abby-franklin-soup-hike-vibram.jpg Abby and Franklin on Steve&amp;rsquo;s Soup Hike part 3 wearing Vibram FiveFingers %}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby joined me to run in her first ever 5K race, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.runaroundthesquare.com/&#34;&gt;Run Around the Square&lt;/a&gt; in Regent Square (mostly on the trails of Frick Park). What a special day! This race was my first ever 5K race when I started running in races in 2000.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started to learn &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/accordion/&#34;&gt;accordion&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;september&#34;&gt;September&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started running to work two or three times a week.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I ran in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~kalp/PGR/&#34;&gt;CMU SCS Pretty Good Race 5K&lt;/a&gt; together, her second 5K race.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I went to &lt;a href=&#34;http://podcamppittsburgh.com/&#34;&gt;PodCamp Pittsburgh&lt;/a&gt;, and after that, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/22/starting-a-new-web-site/&#34;&gt;I started this blog&lt;/a&gt; and proceeded to maintain a habit of posting every day (a routine that has been modified since then).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;october&#34;&gt;October&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started expanding beyond just writing for my blog, and began contributing to the Web through &lt;a href=&#34;http://twitter.com/franklinchen&#34;&gt;my Twitter account&lt;/a&gt; as well as writing comments on other people&amp;rsquo;s blog posts.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started taking Stanford online classes: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ml-class.org/&#34;&gt;Machine Learning&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.db-class.org/&#34;&gt;Introduction to Databases&lt;/a&gt;. (Blog posts on my experiences to appear soon.) Unfortunately, as a result of the extra time commitment, October through December were quite hectic for me.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I continued to move more toward a paleo diet.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;november&#34;&gt;November&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started playing &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/flute/&#34;&gt;flute&lt;/a&gt; again.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Probably because of fatigue and a compromised immune system, I came down with a skin ailment that I got serious treatment for, but it took almost two months to completely clear up and I spent over a month truly miserable &lt;sup&gt;24&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;7&lt;/sub&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;december&#34;&gt;December&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started playing Baroque flute.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started playing tin whistle.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I prepared for and made it through two music performances, playing recorder and flute (and almost tin whistle).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I ended the year completely exhausted, on the verge of getting sick, and took a long break from blogging.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The final week, Abby and I were on a hectic travel schedule that involved meeting up with her parents, my parents, her sister Carrie, Carrie&amp;rsquo;s boyfriend Alain, Alain&amp;rsquo;s parents, Alain&amp;rsquo;s extended family, my sister Linda, and her husband Andre. I am grateful that we got to meet up with so many people (and arranged for various of the individuals to meet up with various of the others!), but the trip was quite stressful to me, because I was not physically or emotionally prepared for it at all. (I will report later on what I learned from the experience.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2011 was quite a year for me and Abby. We had many changes and adventures in our lives: our home, our diet, our exercise, our outdoors activities, travel. For me, the biggest changes were quitting chess, starting music practice and performance, throwing myself into blogging and tweeting, getting more and more active in local software developer groups, applying new (to me) development tools at work, and in the fall, taking Stanford online courses in computer science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although I ended the year in poor shape, because of being overbooked, I am very excited by how many positive changes took place. I have an entirely new set of plans and priorities to formulate soon for 2012 in collaboration with Abby, in hope of learning from the lessons of my failures and omissions of 2011, and restoring balance.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I don&#39;t know whether to get a flu shot</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/11/02/i-dont-know-whether-to-get-a-flu-shot/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Nov 2011 21:33:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/11/02/i-dont-know-whether-to-get-a-flu-shot/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Every fall I am bombarded by reminders to get a flu shot. The reminders come from where I work, as well as from my health insurance provider. I never know whether I should really get one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, I got my flu shot after all. Why? And why my resistance?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/franklin-flu-shot-2011.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin getting flu shot at CMU in 2011&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-not-get-flu-vaccine&#34;&gt;Why not get flu vaccine?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are various reasons &amp;ldquo;why not&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;my-own-history&#34;&gt;My own history&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One is that in the short term, I find them painful and have had bad experiences in which my whole day was ruined because of the effects. Sometimes my arm hurts for two or three days straight. Sometimes I have trouble lifting my arm. Sometimes I feel really tired for some reason.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More annoyingly, some years I seem to have gotten downright sick after getting the shot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, there have been times when I got a flu vaccine in the fall but came down with some flu in February or March anyway. How effective is the vaccine anyway? Do we really know?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;other-people-s-history&#34;&gt;Other people&amp;rsquo;s history&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not the only one who has gotten sick or otherwise felt bad for a day or two after a flu vaccine. I personally know quite a few people have reported such side effects. In fact, my own mother got really ill once after a flu shot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;alternative-warnings&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Alternative&amp;rdquo; warnings&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as with &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MMR_vaccine_controversy&#34;&gt;childhood vaccines&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Water_fluoridation_controversy&#34;&gt;water fluoridation&lt;/a&gt; and any number of other public health measures, flu vaccines are a popular topic among some &amp;ldquo;alternative&amp;rdquo; circles that warn against how horrible these mandatory or recommended measures are. I never summarily dismiss alternative points of view in favor of automatic acceptance of mainstream wisdom, but it can be time-consuming and confusing to try to look into different points of view while not really being an expert in the area and therefore not necessarily being able to detect inaccuracies and falsehoods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-get-flu-vaccine&#34;&gt;Why get flu vaccine?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The short answer to &amp;ldquo;why follow the official recommendations&amp;rdquo; is that experts have presumably studied the pros and cons, the possible beneficial effects and negative effects, and a cost-benefit analysis for the public as a whole makes the treatment worthwhile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Opponents of vaccines and other public health measures often look just at the possible negatives without weighing the positives (assuming they do not straight away engage in conspiracy theories about the motives of government agencies). In particular, they often worry exclusively about their own health or that of their children rather than that of society as a whole. So opposition often takes a philosophical or political tone that is completely independent of the concrete issue at hand. Unfortunately, when it comes to matters such as vaccination, effectiveness depends on everyone making the same choice. If vaccination is effective, then by not getting vaccinated, I risk getting sick and spreading the illness to others. My decision does not affect just me, but other people also.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;today-s-experience&#34;&gt;Today&amp;rsquo;s experience&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CMU had been offering free flu shots for several weeks now, and each time I chose not to get one. But today was the CMU health and benefits fair, so I was going to that event anyway, and flu shots were being given there, and therefore there was a higher chance I would go for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that today was a nice, sunny day, and I was feeling pretty good, so I got the shot after all. If it had been a crappy day, I would not have. That&amp;rsquo;s what it came down to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tried an experiment, hoping to avoid feeling as bad as I have in the past. I exercised before and after shot, with the idea that better circulation would enable me to better deal with the shot. Nevertheless, by afternoon, I was strangely feeling pretty bad.  Very sleepy, and feverish.  That lasted an hour, then I was OK again. My arm is sore, but not horribly so. Hopefully I&amp;rsquo;ll be back to normal in a day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;ll see whether I get flu this winter. Either way, I can&amp;rsquo;t draw any conclusion from the result!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I Don&#39;t Feel Like Practicing; but I&#39;m Gonna Do It Anyway</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/09/26/i-dont-feel-like-practicing-but-im-gonna-do-it-anyway/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Sep 2011 19:07:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/09/26/i-dont-feel-like-practicing-but-im-gonna-do-it-anyway/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This morning I felt pretty tired, still recovering from yesterday&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/25/blistered-but-blissful-in-the-burgh/&#34;&gt;race&lt;/a&gt;, so the thought crossed my mind, &amp;ldquo;Maybe I should take a little break, and skip recorder practice today&amp;rdquo;. Also, I hadn&amp;rsquo;t improved as much during the past week as I had planned and felt frustrated.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/s-a-t-recorders.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin&amp;#39;s soprano, alto, and tenor recorders&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;No effing way!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to a lot of great web sites and books out there on &lt;a href=&#34;http://lifehacker.com/&#34;&gt;productivity&lt;/a&gt; and psychology, and advice from &lt;a href=&#34;http://zenhabits.net/&#34;&gt;wise people&lt;/a&gt; from all walks of life, I&amp;rsquo;ve learned to watch very carefully for signs of loss of self-discipline and direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jerry Seinfeld said, &lt;a href=&#34;http://lifehacker.com/281626/jerry-seinfelds-productivity-secret&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t break the chain&lt;/em&gt;&amp;ldquo;&lt;/a&gt;. If you want to get good at something and achieve a tough goal, you have to work at it every day, even if only a little bit a day. It is easy for our minds to wander and make up excuses to skip one day, to skip one practice. This applies to every aspect of life, not just matters such as music practice. It applies to whether to exercise every day, whether to write a blog post every day, whether to avoid eating cookies for a week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, I don&amp;rsquo;t necessarily kick myself if in fact I really have to alter my planned schedule. Sometimes I&amp;rsquo;m sick and it&amp;rsquo;s better to sleep than to try to go for a run, or I have a respiratory ailment and don&amp;rsquo;t want to blow into a wind instrument.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But too many times I&amp;rsquo;ve seen people (including myself) make up excuses to not do something, and become so creative as to put off a &amp;ldquo;plan&amp;rdquo; for years at a time. Maybe there&amp;rsquo;s that book I always meant to read, but it&amp;rsquo;s yellow now since college and somehow I have &amp;ldquo;no time&amp;rdquo; for it. Or maybe I wanted to learn to draw, but kept on &amp;ldquo;needing&amp;rdquo; fancy paper and pencils. Or maybe I wanted to lose weight, but every day I make an &amp;ldquo;exception&amp;rdquo; and eat a side of fries or cup of ice cream. Or maybe I always &amp;ldquo;wanted&amp;rdquo; to learn to dance the samba, but mysteriously, my leg seems to be &amp;ldquo;injured&amp;rdquo; remarkably often every time I&amp;rsquo;m not eating ice cream and looking for pencils to buy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What it comes down to is, you have to decide what is important, and act accordingly. What is important may not be what your friends think is important. It may not be what your spouse thinks is important. It may not be what your society thinks is important. But if you truly believe, then you have a stark choice: go ahead anyway, or quit. Do not go halfway. A &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yoda&#34;&gt;wise sage&lt;/a&gt; said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Do or do not. There is no try.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/9/96/CGIYoda.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Yoda with light saber&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Why waste time aimlessly practicing recorder only maybe once a week, and not getting anywhere at all, if I could spend that one hour doing something that I could find that I cared more about?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;applying-the-lessons-to-my-life&#34;&gt;Applying the lessons to my life&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, the day I really committed to playing recorder, March 7 of 2011 (after starting to play the alto recorder on February 19 and informally practicing every day until the initial excitement wore off), I printed out a music practice log/journal, and vowed to practice every single day, indefinitely (as far as this was reasonable). I had decided to join the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.andrew.cmu.edu/user/lukas/pcars/Welcome.html&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh chapter&lt;/a&gt; of the American Recorder Society, whose next meeting was March 20. I had two weeks to teach myself as much alto recorder as I could before the meeting. I attended, was warmly welcomed as a newcomer, and have continued to attend and participate in group playing, while getting lots of helpful advice from everyone there. The group is not too big, and is informal and friendly: I love how the communities for different hobbies of mine in Pittsburgh are so inviting. This city is just the right size for me. I&amp;rsquo;d feel lost living in New York or something, where there are a lot more things to do, more polish, more glamour, more hotshots, but also more distance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have missed probably an average of one day of recorder practice every two weeks. I can live with that. &lt;em&gt;The point of the planned schedule is not, paradoxically, to rigidly stick to it.&lt;/em&gt; The point is to set a personal standard, a mind set, a reference point, an &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/Anchoring&#34;&gt;anchor&lt;/a&gt;. When I was twelve years old, I was struck by this &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikiquote.org/wiki/Robert_Browning&#34;&gt;quote&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Ah, but a man&#39;s reach should exceed his grasp,
Or what&#39;s a heaven for?
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I immediately interpreted this as meaning, if I want to achieve something, I must aim beyond it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was learning &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.andrew.cmu.edu/user/shotokan/pska.org/CMU.shtml&#34;&gt;karate&lt;/a&gt; several years ago, I was taught that when punching someone, aim to punch through him, and not just to hit the surface.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of inevitable uncertainties and setbacks, it is necessary to aim beyond where one wants to go, in order to get there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I picked up my recorder and &lt;a href=&#34;http://musiciansway.com/&#34;&gt;practiced&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Namaste&#34;&gt;Namaste&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/alto-recorder-practice.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>