<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Regent Square on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/regent-square/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Regent Square on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/regent-square/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Performing with the Steel City Ukuleles at the Wilkins School Community Center Ecofest 2013: with videos</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/05/performing-with-the-steel-city-ukuleles-at-the-wilkins-school-community-center-ecofest-2013-with-videos/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Oct 2013 19:38:08 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/05/performing-with-the-steel-city-ukuleles-at-the-wilkins-school-community-center-ecofest-2013-with-videos/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/ecofest-2013.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Ecofest 2013 poster&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/ecofest-2013/steel-city-ukuleles-banner.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It was a beautiful day outside at the Wilkins School Community Center Ecofest in Regent Square: warm and sunny, and &lt;em&gt;dry&lt;/em&gt;. It had been raining, and was even drizzling rain in the morning just before we performed at around 11:15 AM for an hour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were vendors, information booths, food, and families with children hanging out. Abby helped out with using our camera on a tripod to get footage of the Steel City Ukuleles performing, then went off to the clothing swap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, Marlene and others came out to listen to us and support us. That was great!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was happy to see parents with their children watching us, and some of them dancing a bit too. I silently thought to myself, &amp;ldquo;I am playing for the children standing in front of me&amp;rdquo;. Music is a beautiful thing to share with children; I remember how happy I was when I was young and encountered music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;videos&#34;&gt;Videos&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We managed to get about half of our program recorded on my camera. Unfortunately, the memory card ran out of space halfway through because we forgot to erase all the photos and videos that were still on the memory card from long ago. Still, we got quite a bit of footage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We missed recording the first two songs, because of a confusion with Abby about start time that resulted in her arriving in the middle of our second song, but then we got rolling and successfully recorded eight songs, before the memory card filled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;cindy&#34;&gt;Cindy&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/oOH7VEmncXk&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;shangri-la&#34;&gt;Shangri-La&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notice the mention of Pittsburgh in the verse!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/isKtJV1jlao&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;roxy-s-waltz&#34;&gt;Roxy&amp;rsquo;s Waltz&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was a trio, performed by Amber, Sunny, and Jon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/OgVtQ7m5ZNc&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;you-are-my-sunshine&#34;&gt;You Are My Sunshine&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/OdDBAMhUJDk&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;tonight-you-belong-to-me-and-by-the-light-of-the-silvery-moon&#34;&gt;Tonight You Belong To Me and By The Light Of The Silvery Moon&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of my favorite musical selection in our playlist, but also the trickiest for me to play, because of the key and the chord changes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/7pBKf4TfRLA&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;mountain-sound&#34;&gt;Mountain Sound&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adam had a solo intro in this one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/VAD4tzjkB80&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;stealin-stealin&#34;&gt;Stealin&amp;rsquo; Stealin&amp;rsquo;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/hkJvBfx9Ew0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;rough-on-rats&#34;&gt;Rough On Rats&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/j0nrKnfdf_0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then the camera memory card filled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sadly, we did not get footage of our concluding sing-along songs where we encouraged everyone to sing along!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;afterwards-at-the-ecofest&#34;&gt;Afterwards, at the Ecofest&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I packed up right after we were done performing, because I could only stay around several minutes longer to explore Ecofest with Abby before heading over to Point Park University downtown for the afternoon sessions of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.podcamppittsburgh.com/&#34;&gt;PodCamp Pittsburgh&lt;/a&gt;, whose morning sessions I missed because of the Ecofest gig.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But others of us hung around to do more jamming:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/ecofest-2013/after-jamming.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A view of Ecofest from front:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/ecofest-2013/front.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Panoramic view of Ecofest from the back dining area outside:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/ecofest-2013/panorama.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Some vendors and information booths:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/ecofest-2013/sample.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;reflections-on-our-performance&#34;&gt;Reflections on our performance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I felt fairly pleased with our performance. The three rehearsals we had in the past two weeks were crucial. We did flub some things that we didn&amp;rsquo;t flub in rehearsal, but that happens. But overall, we produced a fine unified sound. The videos don&amp;rsquo;t completely reflect that because of the distance and the background conversations at the event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I myself made more errors than in rehearsal and in private practice. There are a couple of reasons for this. I think the most interesting one is simply that I did not practice enough in a &lt;em&gt;performance&lt;/em&gt; mode. Most of the time, when I practice music, I am focused entirely on getting the words right, the melody, the rhythm, the harmonic changes, the fingerings, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in performance, there is the audience, and the point is to play for the audience, not for oneself. I had a hard time reallocating my scarce attentional resources toward engaging with the audience. When I did, such as by avoiding looking down so much at the fret board (actually, in the videos you can see that I could not entirely avoid this, because I don&amp;rsquo;t have a perfect feel yet for my finger positions, so I keep bobbing my head toward my instrument), I could feel myself miss nailing a chord.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having seen the footage, I will work more in the future toward specific practice oriented toward polishing up for performance. This means improving technique and memorizing as much as possible (chord changes, lyrics). It is &amp;ldquo;easy&amp;rdquo; to go out there with a music stand and run through stuff, but it is much harder to appear relaxed, confident, and attentive to the audience. I feel that this is quite important to a successful performance, whose aim is to truly touch the hearts and minds of those who are paying attention to us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is of course pointless to pay too much attention to aspects of presentation if your technique and intonation are poor, so I would say that performance presentation is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; the most important thing to work on, all things considered, but my aim is to master the musical basics enough that I can also reliably &lt;em&gt;add&lt;/em&gt; the presentation aspect as an integral part of complete musical development. I believe that a truly good musical performance must incorporate the spirit of those who are listening to us and feed it back into what we do in real time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed participating in my first ukulele gig. Now, I am exhausted, and will take a break from performance. It has been an amazing learning experience for me.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Final rehearsal for my first ukulele gig: and some hard decisions about music in my life</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/04/final-rehearsal-for-my-first-ukulele-gig/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2013 22:15:33 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/04/final-rehearsal-for-my-first-ukulele-gig/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;The night before our Ecofest gig, those of us in the Steel City Ukuleles who are performing in it had one final rehearsal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a very good rehearsal. We&amp;rsquo;re sounding more and more together as an ensemble, ending solidly on each song the way we agreed, and singing more in tune and balance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, Sunny reminded us that we are &lt;em&gt;performing&lt;/em&gt;, and so we should not just grimly look at our music booklets, but instead, when we can, we should look up and smile and engage with the audience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;singing&#34;&gt;Singing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still don&amp;rsquo;t have all the songs down as much as I would like, but by the end of the two-hour rehearsal, I was totally &lt;em&gt;hoarse&lt;/em&gt;. I am ready to sing out strong while simultaneously playing my ukulele.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I just realized that &lt;strong&gt;in the past three months, I have sung more than in the previous forty years of my life combined&lt;/strong&gt;. Wow. And I&amp;rsquo;m loving it. There&amp;rsquo;s nothing like singing, especially singing with others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;performance-is-time-and-energy-consuming&#34;&gt;Performance is time and energy consuming&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I almost didn&amp;rsquo;t make it to the rehearsal. I&amp;rsquo;ve completely exhausted myself this week with work and other activities, and badly need a break. There are times, such as earlier today, when I felt overwhelmed by everything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, yesterday, in discussing my musical plans for the coming months with Abby, I made some decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is my last ukulele gig for the year, for sure. I want to get back to basics and work on my technique and in really mastering some songs, rather than get back on the treadmill of more material for performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, this winter, I am not planning to participate in performing on recorder for the holiday gigs at Phipps Conservatory &amp;ldquo;candlelight evenings&amp;rdquo; that I&amp;rsquo;ve treasured &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/05/busy-evening-performing-at-phipps-followed-by-rehearsal-for-another-gig/&#34;&gt;in 2011&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/09/playing-music-on-recorders-at-a-phipps-conservatory-candlelight-evening/&#34;&gt;in 2012&lt;/a&gt;. That was always a huge amount of work for me. Unless I can participate in significantly reduced capacity, I don&amp;rsquo;t see how I can manage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will probably perform in the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/14/pittsburgh-contras-and-squares-holiday-ball-2012/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Contras and Squares Holiday Ball&lt;/a&gt; again, because it&amp;rsquo;s something I&amp;rsquo;ve been doing with Abby every year, and because after two years of doing it, I know the music, and therefore it will not require much work to participate in (if I want to do some Irish flute and tin whistle solos, of course, then I can add as much extra work for myself that I want, ha).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-is-the-best-use-of-my-limited-time-and-energy-for-music&#34;&gt;What is the best use of my limited time and energy for music?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, there have been announcements and reminders for some time about recorder and ukulele &lt;em&gt;workshops&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;concerts&lt;/em&gt; coming up soon. I have decided not to sign up for any of them, because I really need some rest time on &lt;em&gt;weekends&lt;/em&gt; that I have not been getting; weekends are also the time when I can do more household chores and spend time with Abby.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find that my main enjoyment and improvement in music comes form what I do daily, anyway, rather than what I can possibly do in a long, extended workshop format. I&amp;rsquo;ve always been frustrated that when I attend a one or two day conference or workshop on any subject (computer programming, salsa dance, etc.), I don&amp;rsquo;t actually retain or engage with as much as I would like. There are ways to optimize these experiences, but that requires a certain kind of immediate followup that I don&amp;rsquo;t have time for right now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I will sadly miss the fantastic &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flanders-recorder-quartet.be/en/home/&#34;&gt;Flanders Recorder Quartet&lt;/a&gt; when they come to Pittsburgh in November, and I will miss the workshop Annie has arranged for them to give here for the local recorder community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I am going to miss &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.coolhanduke.com/&#34;&gt;Cool Hand Uke&lt;/a&gt; when he comes to Pittsburgh to give a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/Steel-City-Ukuleles/events/135233932/&#34;&gt;workshop&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/Steel-City-Ukuleles/events/138577782/&#34;&gt;concert&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Life is full of choices, especially for those of us who have many interests, not just one. This week I made some decisions about my involvement with music in October, November, and December.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>9 things you could be doing in Pittsburgh on Saturday, October 5</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/04/9-things-you-could-be-doing-in-pittsburgh-on-saturday-october-5/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2013 00:46:44 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/04/9-things-you-could-be-doing-in-pittsburgh-on-saturday-october-5/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m always frustrated at this time of year because there are so many events of interest to me in Pittsburgh that seem to happen on the first weekend of October. Since I cannot attend all of them, I figured I might as well attempt a public service and mention some of them so that if you are in the Pittsburgh area, maybe you can go and enjoy what I can&amp;rsquo;t attend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So here are 9 of the probably dozens of cool things you could be doing tomorrow, Saturday, October 5, 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;free-concert-allegheny-city-ragtime-orchestra&#34;&gt;Free concert: Allegheny City Ragtime Orchestra&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re interested in ragtime or Latin music, check out &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.shadysideacademy.org/page.cfm?p=12541&#34;&gt;this concert by the Allegheny City Ragtime Orchestra&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some articles in anticipation of it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.post-gazette.com/stories/ae/music/preview-ragtime-orchestra-connects-with-history-705929/&#34;&gt;Post-Gazette&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://triblive.com/aande/music/4763900-74/ragtime-music-concert&#34;&gt;Trib&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I wanted to go, but finally decided that we have too many other activities earlier in the day and need to just stay home and unwind in the evening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;free-conference-podcamp-pittsburgh-8&#34;&gt;Free conference: PodCamp Pittsburgh 8&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 8th annual &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.podcamppittsburgh.com/&#34;&gt;PodCamp Pittsburgh&lt;/a&gt; should be good. If you have any interest in using social media for personal or professional purposes, you should check it out. Interesting talks, opportunities to just socialized and learn new things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I attended in 2010, 2011, 2012, and will attend again for the fourth year. Unfortunately, I will only be able to attend the afternoon sessions. But I didn&amp;rsquo;t want to completely miss it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that PodCamp completely changed my life. For example, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/21/one-month-anniversary-of-my-blog/&#34;&gt;I started this blog in 2011 because of my second PodCamp&lt;/a&gt;, and I became serious about using social media in general, and that led to a total transformation of my life as I learned about local activities and made new friends. (Unfortunately, I didn&amp;rsquo;t get around to finishing my draft reports about my experience at last year&amp;rsquo;s PodCamp 7.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;pittsburgh-south-side-slopes-step-trek&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh South Side Slopes Step Trek&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The annual &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.southsideslopes.org/steptrek/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh South Side Slopes Step Trek&lt;/a&gt; is another event you can attend tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/08/my-god-its-full-of-stairs-pittsburgh-step-trek-2011/&#34;&gt;blog coverage two years ago&lt;/a&gt; as well as my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/09/25/why-you-should-go-out-to-the-pittsburgh-south-side-slopes-step-trek/&#34;&gt;recent update&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, Abby and I will be missing it this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;run-shadyside-5k&#34;&gt;Run Shadyside 5K&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you like to run in races, a fine race is the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.runshadyside.com/&#34;&gt;Run Shadyside 5K&lt;/a&gt;. Fast and flat, with a pancake breakfast and festivities afterwards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not running in it this year, just because I have too many other things to do already for the rest of the day, but here&amp;rsquo;s my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/01/run-shadyside-5k-outrunning-mickey-mouse-and-lending-a-trumpet/&#34;&gt;report from two years ago&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;free-5th-annual-wilkins-school-community-center-ecofest-in-regent-square&#34;&gt;Free: 5th annual Wilkins School Community Center Ecofest in Regent Square&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/ecofest-2013.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;5th annual Wilkins School Community Center Ecofest in Regent Square&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Interested in green living? Check out the &lt;a href=&#34;http://foresthills-regentsquare.patch.com/groups/around-town/p/ecofest-encourages-recycling-green-living&#34;&gt;5th annual Wilkins School Community Center Ecofest in Regent Square&lt;/a&gt;. Abby has regularly attended for the clothing swap. There will also be food, information, and entertainment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that this year, I will also be attending, to perform as a new member of the Steel City Ukuleles. &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/08/23/another-unexpected-life-change-one-month-of-learning-to-play-ukulele/&#34;&gt;I just started playing the ukulele a bit over two months ago&lt;/a&gt;, and have been working hard to help put on an entertaining show!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;ll be performing around 11:30 AM to 12:30 PM. If you come, say hello!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;cmu-donut-dash-2-mile-race&#34;&gt;CMU Donut Dash 2 mile race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, if you are into weird running events, there is the &lt;a href=&#34;http://cmudonutdash.org/&#34;&gt;Carnegie Mellon University Donut Dash&lt;/a&gt;, a 2 mile event serving as a fundraiser for the Children&amp;rsquo;s Hospital of Pittsburgh of UPMC. This is not an event I have ever done, and not one I intend to do, but what the heck, some of you might love this sort of thing!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;national-chess-day-gateway-open-tournament-at-the-pittsburgh-chess-club&#34;&gt;National Chess Day: Gateway Open tournament at the Pittsburgh Chess Club&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did you know that it&amp;rsquo;s time for &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nationalchessday.com/&#34;&gt;National Chess Day&lt;/a&gt;? There will be a tournament at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburghcc.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Chess Club&lt;/a&gt;, the 56th annual Gateway Open. Yes, chess in Pittsburgh has a long and illustrious history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;pittsburgh-perl-workshop&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Perl Workshop&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are a Perl programmer, the &lt;a href=&#34;http://pghpw.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Perl Workshop&lt;/a&gt; is back &lt;a href=&#34;http://pghpw.org/ppw2013/&#34;&gt;this year&lt;/a&gt;. Registration is already closed, so it&amp;rsquo;s not so helpful right now for me to mention it, but in case you didn&amp;rsquo;t know it existed, watch for it next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;ninth-thing&#34;&gt;Ninth thing?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, I guess I miscounted. But there are a whole lot more than nine things to do in Pittsburgh tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, if you are interested in some free stuff to do, there&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.radworkshere.org/interior.php?pageID=64&#34;&gt;RADical Days&lt;/a&gt; listing a whole bunch of stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s no shortage of stuff to do in this great city of Pittsburgh at any time or day of year. I think it&amp;rsquo;s unfortunate that many things I like to do happen to repeatedly fall on the first Saturday of the year, but I&amp;rsquo;m not complaining about an embarrassment of riches. Go out and take advantage of what I can&amp;rsquo;t.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rubber Duckie and Steel City Ukuleles rehearsal</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/02/rubber-duckie-and-steel-city-ukuleles-rehearsal/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2013 21:43:30 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/02/rubber-duckie-and-steel-city-ukuleles-rehearsal/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/Steel-City-Ukuleles/events/132647852&#34;&gt;This week&amp;rsquo;s Wednesday meeting of the Steel City Ukuleles&lt;/a&gt; was an unusual one: it was split into two halves, the first half being our regular meeting (involving going through a new playlist), the second half being the second of three &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/09/26/first-rehearsal-for-my-first-ukulele-gig/&#34;&gt;rehearsals for the Ecofest gig&lt;/a&gt;. The deal was that everyone was open to stick around for the rehearsal if they wanted to, but with the caveat that it was serious rehearsal time, rather than the more casual regular meetup atmosphere. It turned out that a few people who were not performing in the Ecofest gig did stick around, although most others left.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sunny was not present, so Amber took charge of this meetup session.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/steel-city-ukuleles-2013-10-02.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;rubber-duckie&#34;&gt;Rubber Duckie&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed learning some new songs in the first half.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One slightly crazy thing we tried was running through &amp;ldquo;Rubber Duckie&amp;rdquo;, which I had actually suggested to Sunny in email for the playlist for the next meetup, but apparently others had also suggested, for obvious reasons here in Pittsburgh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/n-kHSXQ_wwk&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This song is hard, with a lot of chord changes. I would like to actually master it and play it solo for Abby before Pittsburgh&amp;rsquo;s rubber duck leaves.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/steel-city-ukuleles-2013-10-02-rubber-duckie.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;rehearsal&#34;&gt;Rehearsal&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rehearsal was intense, but we managed to cover the rest of the songs we are to play in the Ecofest gig three days (!!) from now. A lot of homework for me to do, just as I have been doing with the first half of the program.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>First rehearsal for my first ukulele gig: dealing with anxiety</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/09/26/first-rehearsal-for-my-first-ukulele-gig/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Sep 2013 23:09:23 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/09/26/first-rehearsal-for-my-first-ukulele-gig/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s now officially &lt;em&gt;two months&lt;/em&gt; since &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/08/23/another-unexpected-life-change-one-month-of-learning-to-play-ukulele/&#34;&gt;I started learning to play ukulele&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s hard to believe, but two months ago, I was still struggling to play three chords: I could play C, of course, but had trouble with G7, and had even worse trouble with F: I had no finger strength or dexterity and could not arch my fingers and everything was a painful buzz, and I could spend only five minutes a day practicing because of the pain on my uncalloused fingers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And after just over a month of playing, and joining the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/Steel-City-Ukuleles/&#34;&gt;Steel City Ukuleles&lt;/a&gt;, I had volunteered to &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/09/04/my-second-meeting-of-the-steel-city-ukuleles/&#34;&gt;perform in a gig for Ecofest in Regent Square&lt;/a&gt;, as a way to force myself to maintain momentum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this week, just in time, I got my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/09/23/finally-got-a-nice-new-ukulele-mainland-classic-mahogany-concert/&#34;&gt;brand new concert-sized ukulele&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/ecofest-2013-rehearsal-1.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;First Ecofest rehearsal&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The gig is in just over a week. I attended my first rehearsal with extreme anxiety. I was even thinking about bailing out instead of attending. Here&amp;rsquo;s why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;new-music-for-me&#34;&gt;New music for me&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/steel-city-ukuleles-bound-thing-1.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/steel-city-ukuleles-bound-thing-2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I went into rehearsal with basically &lt;em&gt;none&lt;/em&gt; of the songs we were going to perform. So it was basically a sight reading and singing session for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One reason is that I was waiting to get the official bound compilation of performance songs that we were to receive at the first rehearsal, which we did. I had not requested to get one ahead of time, because I was too busy all week anyway to make good use of it if I had possessed it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, it turns out that many of these songs are already familiar and played by most of the other members of the performance group; they are part of the general repertoire, for previous years&amp;rsquo; Ecofests as well as for other gigs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;new-performance-group-for-me&#34;&gt;New performance group for me&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that breaking into a performance group for the first time always involves an initial learning curve because there are those who already know everything inside and out. I still have very vivid memories of other times in my life when I have entered a performance group and felt lost for a while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was briefly in marching band, during the 9th grade in high school. As a new freshman, I was unfamiliar with the repertoire, the choreography, etc. It was a tricky experience for all us freshmen, of course, amidst the 10th, 11th, and 12th graders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, over a decade ago, for a couple of years I was a member of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://cmubdc.org/&#34;&gt;Carnegie Mellon University ballroom dance club&lt;/a&gt;, and I was on both the competition team as well as the formation team. I&amp;rsquo;d made ballroom dancing the main focus of my life, throwing myself into lessons and competition and being in performances with the formation team while still a beginner. I improved my dancing significantly and quickly as a result of jumping in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And more recently, I have been performing in a small &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/09/playing-music-on-recorders-at-a-phipps-conservatory-candlelight-evening/&#34;&gt;recorder quartet/quintet at winter holiday time&lt;/a&gt;. Practicing so that I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t totally flub everything always took a huge amount of work for me, but the side effect was that I really improved my recorder playing and musicianship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I know firsthand the benefits of just jumping in and being around very experienced team members who are inspirational to emulate and learn from, and to exert some healthy pressure on myself not to let the team down!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;listening-watching&#34;&gt;Listening, watching&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of what I did during rehearsal was listening and watching, while doing what I could to keep up and go and make dozens of mistakes everywhere. (It&amp;rsquo;s particularly important to boldly make those mistakes and write down what to work on for homework.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was no way I was going to be able to play everything at first sight. In fact, that&amp;rsquo;s not even the right way to think about the situation. This isn&amp;rsquo;t classical music where you really do &amp;ldquo;sight read&amp;rdquo;. This is music where almost everything is transmitted &lt;em&gt;by ear&lt;/em&gt;. Not knowing the melodies, and not having an actual score, I have to listen and figure out where the melodic lines roughly are, and where the chord changes are. I have to learn what the prevailing strum rhythms and breaks and mood the group has largely decided on. The goal is to learn how to blend in and contribute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t do much extended &lt;em&gt;singing&lt;/em&gt; during this rehearsal. But we have two more rehearsals after this one, so it was not necessary to get everything down right away. I would, of course, be doing my own homework, looking up YouTube videos, in between official rehearsals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For consistency, I found it very useful to focus my listening on one person at a time to emulate. Usually that person was Sunny, because she is leading us. Sometimes that was Adam, because I was sitting near him and because as a strong male voice, I could follow him especially in songs where we had male and female voices split.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fact that there were over a dozen of us in the group for this gig was very helpful to me, because it meant that there was much less pressure on me to get everything right. I don&amp;rsquo;t always have to sing, or sing everything. I don&amp;rsquo;t always have to play the tricky chord progressions that I&amp;rsquo;m not ready yet to get right. I can leave stuff out judiciously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;half-the-songs&#34;&gt;Half the songs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In two hours, we covered half the songs we planned to play at Ecofest. I felt there was still a huge amount of work for me to do in order to really contribute to the group, but no longer felt helpless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-cost-of-excellence&#34;&gt;The cost of excellence&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still think it&amp;rsquo;s a little crazy that I jumped into committing to performing when still a beginner at ukulele, but in the past couple of years, I have learned that shorter, tighter learning and creating cycles considerably speed up the improvement process, provided that one actually puts in the hard work on a daily basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s been a huge cost, unfortunately. I have let some things slide while focusing on ukulele in the past two months. For example, I have been playing chess very poorly. Last week, I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/09/26/the-chess-improver-the-psychology-of-not-winning-the-won-game/&#34;&gt;drew a game that I should have won&lt;/a&gt;. And just two days ago, disaster struck: in my fatigue, I lost a game I should have won. If I had known I was going to have ukulele take over my life outside of work, I would have chosen &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; to play in the current chess tournament.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now as in the past couple of years, I have chosen to sacrifice my chess performance when other things come up. This is why I rarely play chess tournaments any more: I hate playing worse than I am actually capable of playing. As I mentioned two weeks ago, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/09/15/saying-no-on-not-playing-in-the-pittsburgh-chess-league-this-season-for-the-cmu-tartans/&#34;&gt;I had anticipated becoming busy in November&lt;/a&gt;, but I had not anticipated being so busy now already, in September!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sunny led a great rehearsal for our Ecofest gig coming up. I really like some of these songs we&amp;rsquo;re working on, and left feeling that after more work, we can sound really good and have a lot of fun at the gig!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My third meeting of the Steel City Ukuleles: finally ordered a new instrument</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/09/18/my-third-meeting-of-the-steel-city-ukuleles/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Sep 2013 23:13:09 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/09/18/my-third-meeting-of-the-steel-city-ukuleles/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/steel-city-ukuleles-2013-09-18.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Steel City Ukuleles&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve entered my ninth week of playing ukulele: almost two months now!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two weeks ago, I wrote about my second meeting of the Steel City Ukuleles and &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/09/04/my-second-meeting-of-the-steel-city-ukuleles/&#34;&gt;why I decided to perform so quickly after joining and as a beginner to the ukulele&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a report on my &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/Steel-City-Ukuleles/events/132647892/&#34;&gt;third meeting&lt;/a&gt;, in which Sunny led a varied playlist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;musical-selection&#34;&gt;Musical selection&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sunny chose a variety of songs from various genres. Again, this stuff was basically new to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;fingerpicking&#34;&gt;Fingerpicking&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the songs had a short fingerpicking intro, so I was happy to try the easy pattern.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;singing&#34;&gt;Singing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am now mostly able to play through the chords and changes and improvise my own strumming pattern in most of the songs we go through, so I&amp;rsquo;ve been enjoying doing more and more singing in addition, although it still feels like talking and chewing gum at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s where the advantage of the repetitive structure of this kind of music becomes obvious: there are many opportunities to &amp;ldquo;correct&amp;rdquo; what you&amp;rsquo;re doing on the ukulele while learning a song, and then eventually switch the focus to the words.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;sight-reading-and-preparation&#34;&gt;Sight reading and preparation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because I&amp;rsquo;ve been busy with work and other things in the past several days, I only had time to briefly run over some of the songs on my own just before attending the meeting. I feel bad about not being maximally prepared, but sometimes that&amp;rsquo;s just what happens. When I was a perfectionist in the past, I would prefer to not do something at all if I was not &amp;ldquo;fully&amp;rdquo; prepared, but now, I see that sometimes, at least, home &amp;ldquo;preparation&amp;rdquo; is not actually optimal anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being completely unfamiliar with these songs, yes, I could ideally do the research and look up performances on YouTube, etc. (and I did in past weeks), but even then, how we play this music often differs anyway from what one might find. We might be in a different key, have simplified or different chords, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When playing in the Pittsburgh Recorder Society ensemble, I don&amp;rsquo;t leave things to chance, but do practice parts ahead of time, but this is a different kind of music that is hard to do exactly that kind of preparation. In particular, the sheets we get don&amp;rsquo;t have notes for the melodies, but just typically have text and then chord letters or tab symbols correlated loosely with the text, without any notation of duration. Basically, it&amp;rsquo;s a lot of guesswork to figure out what to do with the printed information we are given! It&amp;rsquo;s really best thought of as what music notation in the end is anyway: a lossy reminder of possible performance practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I&amp;rsquo;ve found that other than scanning the chords and working on getting them and the changes, as technical preparation, the best thing to do is to just show up and learn on the fly, by ear, and jot down notes, and then go home and really work on the songs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;ecofest-gig&#34;&gt;Ecofest gig&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sunny gave us more details about the logistics of our upcoming Ecofest gig that I signed up to take part in. We are going to receive nice little spiral-bound books containing the songs for performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;study&#34;&gt;Study&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the last meeting, I&amp;rsquo;ve invested in three technique books for ukulele. It is time to get truly serious and start working on technique.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;new-instrument&#34;&gt;New instrument&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, I finally just put in an order online for a new ukulele. I am going for high quality right off the bat, because I know that I am going to be serious about the instrument. It will not collect dust. I hope it will last me decades! I&amp;rsquo;ll report more when I get it. I hope it arrives soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m definitely getting serious about ukulele. I&amp;rsquo;ve invested not only in ukulele technique books, but also in a new instrument.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My second meeting of the Steel City Ukuleles: why I already signed up to perform before being ready</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/09/04/my-second-meeting-of-the-steel-city-ukuleles/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Sep 2013 22:40:45 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/09/04/my-second-meeting-of-the-steel-city-ukuleles/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve entered my seventh week of playing ukulele.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last month, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/08/23/another-unexpected-life-change-one-month-of-learning-to-play-ukulele/&#34;&gt;I wrote about&lt;/a&gt; finally starting to learn to play ukulele and then attending my first meeting of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/Steel-City-Ukuleles/&#34;&gt;Steel City Ukuleles&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I just attended &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/Steel-City-Ukuleles/events/117972052/&#34;&gt;my second meeting&lt;/a&gt; after having improved a huge amount in two weeks (oh, the joy of being a beginner).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adam led a great playlist of songs for us to go through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;steel-city-ukuleles-t-shirt&#34;&gt;Steel City Ukuleles T-shirt&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/steel-city-ukuleles-shirt.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin wearing Steel City Ukuleles shirt&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The first thing I did upon arrival at the session was to pay for and put on the Steel City Ukuleles T-shirt that Sunny said was for sale at my last meeting. I picked the blue one (there is also a red one). Very nice, and I&amp;rsquo;m proud to be wearing it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;singing&#34;&gt;Singing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two weeks ago, at my first meeting, I was only on my fifth week of playing the ukulele at all, and struggled to keep up with chords and their changes in real time while also strumming, much less singing, so I did very little singing (especially since I barely knew most of the songs).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This week, having some of the finger work more under control, I started trying to start singing along sometimes. One thing I forgot to emphasize about why I&amp;rsquo;ve always been attracted to the prospect of playing guitar or ukulele is that I like to sing, and the drawback of playing wind instruments (as I have spent the last two years playing recorders and flutes) is that I can&amp;rsquo;t do that while also singing. And I love the idea of being able to accompany myself while singing, being my own harmonic and rhythmic support. (This is also a great thing about piano, but I have barely any piano competence, unfortunately.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;music-new-to-me-and-the-transformation-of-taste&#34;&gt;Music new to me and the transformation of taste&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m learning all kinds of songs of all kinds of genres. This is a totally different world from what I&amp;rsquo;m used to. I feel myself undergoing a transformation the same way I did when I started playing recorder. Before playing recorder, I had relatively little interest in Baroque or Renaissance music. It was, frankly, &amp;ldquo;boring&amp;rdquo;. But when forced to actually play it, I began to understand and feel it and enjoy the subtleties of expression, from the point of view of the performer (and even the composer). In fact, I would admit that as a result, I have come to enjoy playing music rather than passively listening to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m experiencing the same transformation of my perception and taste and enjoyment now. There&amp;rsquo;s all this stuff that I haven&amp;rsquo;t much listened to, much less played or sung, whether blues, soul, rock, indie pop, country. Not all of the songs we go through are exciting to me, but I&amp;rsquo;ve been impressed by how many have &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt; that is catchy that I can enjoy and express. These are songs that in many cases, if I didn&amp;rsquo;t actively strum or sing, would be boring to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;still-need-my-own-instrument&#34;&gt;Still need my own instrument&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m still using the loaner banjolele, because the intonation of my Lanikai soprano ukulele is too far off (eventually I should figure out how to fix it).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I returned Linda&amp;rsquo;s electric tenor and she lent me another instrument, an inexpensive concert ukulele (pictured):&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/steel-city-ukuleles-shirt.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin wearing Steel City Ukuleles shirt&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s been a good thing for me to try out different instruments, before I buy a concert sized ukulele of my own, which I should do soon, because just a week ago, I signed up to perform in a gig!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;small-group-and-solo-playing&#34;&gt;Small group and solo playing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What has been really inspiring and was seeing some of the members of the group volunteer to sing and play something they wanted to share with the rest of us. I enjoy appreciating the vulnerability and individuality of soloing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, Heidi, Amber, and Sunny performed a song as a trio, with beautiful ukulele playing and singing in harmony.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/heidi-amber-sunny.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Heidi, Amber, and Sunny&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;i-decided-to-perform-before-i-was-ready&#34;&gt;I decided to perform before I was ready&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/ecofest-2013.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Wilkins Center Community Center Ecofest 2013&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Last week, Sunny put out a call for volunteers to perform for a gig in a month, at the second annual &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wsccpgh.org/&#34;&gt;Wilkins Center Community Center&lt;/a&gt; Ecofest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remembered something that has changed my life in the past couple of years: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.stevenpressfield.com/2010/07/start-before-youre-ready/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;start before you&amp;rsquo;re ready&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. In this case, it meant that since there was an opportunity to perform in a low-key, low-stress environment, I should seize it even though I don&amp;rsquo;t at all feel &amp;ldquo;ready&amp;rdquo;. In the past two years, I have done dozens of things before feeling &amp;ldquo;ready&amp;rdquo;, while in the last three decades, I accomplished very little in my life because I never felt &amp;ldquo;ready&amp;rdquo;. I learned in two years that perfectionism is the enemy, and that you have to just go out there and do stuff, and ideally as early as possible, to get early feedback (external or internal) for rapid improvement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I signed up to perform in the Ecofest on October 5. If you live in the Pittsburgh area, I invite you to come see some subset of us from the Steel City Ukuleles perform at the Ecofest in Regent Square! I&amp;rsquo;ll write up more details later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deciding to perform means committing to getting a lot better in a month, of course. It also means not slacking on getting my own quality instrument. Finally, it means devoting time to official rehearsals, time that will have to come out of somewhere. (The rehearsal dates have not yet been set.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m starting to settle in on playing ukulele. In my seventh week now, I&amp;rsquo;ve gotten far enough to know for sure that I want to continue playing and get serious. To prove that I am serious, I am planning to perform already in a month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-09-18&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-09-18)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two weeks later: a report on &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/09/18/my-third-meeting-of-the-steel-city-ukuleles/&#34;&gt;my third Steel City Ukuleles meeting&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>