<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Pierre Hantaï on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/pierre-hanta%C3%AF/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Pierre Hantaï on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/pierre-hanta%C3%AF/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>The single greatest performance of Bach&#39;s Goldberg Variations: Pierre Hantaï with rhythmic drive and life</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/05/the-single-greatest-performance-of-bachs-goldberg-variations-pierre-hantai/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2014 22:32:07 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/05/the-single-greatest-performance-of-bachs-goldberg-variations-pierre-hantai/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been listening to JS Bach&amp;rsquo;s Goldberg Variations for a quarter of a century now. I haven&amp;rsquo;t actually said much about this piece on this blog, although I did mention attending a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/11/19/chamber-music-concert-at-cmu-featured-bachs-goldberg-variations-arranged-for-string-trio/&#34;&gt;concert featuring a string trio arrangement of it a year ago&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a favorite recording, out of probably a dozen recordings I have heard since a college friend introduced me to the piece performed by Glenn Gould on piano . Several years ago I discovered my true favorite, upon encountering &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pierre_Hanta%C3%AF&#34;&gt;Pierre Hantaï&lt;/a&gt; on harpsichord in a CD recording.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-hantaï-stands-out-for-me&#34;&gt;Why Hantaï stands out for me&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given that there are plenty of other performances that I consider worthy, why is Hantaï&amp;rsquo;s by far my favorite?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;sustained intensity (many performances have me getting bored and sleepy)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;rhythmic&lt;/em&gt; drive is always there; the music never droops&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;subtlety and shape to all phrasing and contrast&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;no distractions of self-absorption (many performances have certain kinds of oddities that are magnified when spread out over an hour or more)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;nice harpsichord sound&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: I once didn&amp;rsquo;t like harpsichord, and always preferred a piano when possible, but now I actually prefer Bach&amp;rsquo;s music on harpsichord, because of the nature of articulation and decay and how dissonances are more delicious on this instrument.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a treat I just found by accident: a video of Hantaï performing the Goldberg Variations. Watch it if you care about the Goldberg Variations at all!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/9NYqiKm3gng&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you are already a fan of the Goldberg Variations, what is your favorite performance, and why? Also, does it matter to you whether piano or harpsichord is used?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>