<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>French Dance on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/french-dance/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in French Dance on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/french-dance/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Life: cooking, eating with friends, music jamming, dancing</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/03/29/life-cooking-eating-with-friends-music-jamming-dancing/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Mar 2014 23:38:31 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/03/29/life-cooking-eating-with-friends-music-jamming-dancing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Abby and I went to a French potluck dance party at Lisa&amp;rsquo;s, the first one we&amp;rsquo;ve attended together in &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/05/25/learning-the-congo-de-captieux-traditional-french-dance/&#34;&gt;ten months&lt;/a&gt; (although I went to one without Abby &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/09/14/back-to-french-dance-potluck-and-party/&#34;&gt;half a year ago&lt;/a&gt; when she was out of town).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a wonderful experience, one that we&amp;rsquo;ve missed for two months, since we have not gone out to a party with friends since Abby got a new job and we&amp;rsquo;ve had to adapt to that big change in our lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although we still had to leave early, I was reminded of what I really enjoy in life, deep down: nothing fancy, just getting together and having fun and being creative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;music-jamming&#34;&gt;Music jamming&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hadn&amp;rsquo;t done French music jamming in months, so when Abby and I arrived, and dinner was still being prepared, and John said &amp;ldquo;hey, let&amp;rsquo;s play&amp;rdquo;, I pulled out my flutes (both my standard Boehm flute and my wooden Irish flute) and went at it with him on melodeon. We hadn&amp;rsquo;t played together in half a year! Susan joined in at some point, also on melodeon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We played mazurka and Schottische and other music for about half an hour, from John&amp;rsquo;s memory, as I tried to follow along by ear. I realized how much I miss French music jamming. Lisa&amp;rsquo;s been hosting it again recently, but there have been schedule conflicts for me, but it looks like we&amp;rsquo;ll be getting on a schedule that works for me. I&amp;rsquo;m coming back!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I was taking a break, John played a multi-section hanter dro that Fabien and Lisa started dancing to, and I joined them in their line and picked it up. Again, something I hadn&amp;rsquo;t done in a while, and almost forgotten the unique pleasure of!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;potluck&#34;&gt;Potluck&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This seemed to me the biggest French potluck party yet, with almost twenty people present, I believe. We met some new people as well as old friends.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/french-potluck-2014-03-29/dinner.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;At dinner&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I baked a butternut squash to bring. I only very, very lightly seasoned it, to not detract from the natural flavor of the squash:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;butternut squash, sliced in half, placed in roasting pan&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;salt&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;pepper&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;cayenne pepper&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;butter&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;extra virgin olive oil&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;brown sugar&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/french-potluck-2014-03-29/squash.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Butternut squash&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Abby made a kale and mushroom dish:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/french-potluck-2014-03-29/kale.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Kale&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The other guests all brought a lot of great homemade food, and Lisa and Alex provided tasty and filling entrees and desserts. A fantastic meal!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/french-potluck-2014-03-29/food1.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Food&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/french-potluck-2014-03-29/food2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Food&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/french-potluck-2014-03-29/food3.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Food&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, there were &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/03/21/time-to-taste-the-world-thoughts-on-expanding-my-food-tastes-as-an-adult/&#34;&gt;Brussels sprouts, and I enjoyed them&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/french-potluck-2014-03-29/brussels-sprouts.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Brussels sprouts&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;cookies-and-other-desserts&#34;&gt;Cookies (and other desserts)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In accordance with &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/01/16/a-system-for-quitting-eating-cookies/&#34;&gt;my rule&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Music-themed cookies homemade from molds:

&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/french-potluck-2014-03-29/musical-cookies.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Musical cookies&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ate one, of a dancing couple:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/french-potluck-2014-03-29/dance-cookie.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A slice of yummy chocolatey thing:

&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/french-potluck-2014-03-29/chocolatey.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Chocolatey&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A slice of chocolate cake:

&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/french-potluck-2014-03-29/chocolate-cake.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Chocolate cake&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Unfortunately, I think I should have cut myself a smaller slice, instead of accepting a precut slice.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A tiny piece of a very rich, buttery thing:

&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/french-potluck-2014-03-29/another-dessert.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A non-homemade cookie from a box (I didn&amp;rsquo;t need to eat this):

&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/french-potluck-2014-03-29/box-cookie.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;dancing&#34;&gt;Dancing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After dinner, Lisa and Fabien started off the dancing portion of the evening, by re-teaching the &amp;ldquo;Congo de Captieux&amp;rdquo; set dance that Lisa and Lynn had taught &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/05/25/learning-the-congo-de-captieux-traditional-french-dance/&#34;&gt;ten months ago&lt;/a&gt;. It had been so long that Abby and I barely remembered it and were practically learning it from scratch again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of eventually got through it! I got sweaty again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After that, there was a break, and since it was already &amp;ldquo;late&amp;rdquo; (for Abby and me on our current schedule), we had to say goodbye, just as the &amp;ldquo;regular&amp;rdquo; French dance portion of the evening was about to begin (bourrées, waltzes, mazurkas, hanter dro, more music jamming, etc.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some photos of dancing that I took before we left early:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/french-potluck-2014-03-29/dancing1.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/french-potluck-2014-03-29/dancing2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/french-potluck-2014-03-29/dancing3.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a beautiful evening that filled my belly and soul. It&amp;rsquo;s been such a blessing to have been brought into this world of French traditional dance and music through the enthusiasm and generosity of Lisa &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/01/23/discovering-french-traditional-dance-in-pittsburgh/&#34;&gt;two years ago&lt;/a&gt; and many others. I feel like my life has been immeasurably enriched.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re in the Pittsburgh area and want to join in, we always welcome more dancers and musicians. (Or even if you&amp;rsquo;re not in the Pittsburgh area, as we&amp;rsquo;ve had visitors from further away.)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Back to French dance: potluck and party</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/09/14/back-to-french-dance-potluck-and-party/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Sep 2013 23:40:51 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/09/14/back-to-french-dance-potluck-and-party/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I went to a French potluck dance party at Lisa&amp;rsquo;s. For the first time, I attended without Abby, because she was up at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.snpjrec.com/&#34;&gt;SNPJ&lt;/a&gt; for an international folk dance camp; actually, we had a fairly low turnout (I counted fourteen people) because some others who would have come to the potluck are at the camp with her!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s been months since I was involved with French dance or music, because I gave all that up temporarily in order to focus on &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/08/23/another-unexpected-life-change-one-month-of-learning-to-play-ukulele/&#34;&gt;learning ukulele starting less than two months ago&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last French potluck dance party I attended was &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/05/25/learning-the-congo-de-captieux-traditional-french-dance/&#34;&gt;almost four months ago&lt;/a&gt;. I really love this informal&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;potluck&#34;&gt;Potluck&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I made a huge batch of vegetables for the potluck.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/french-potluck-2013-09-14/broccoli.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My simple recipe:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;three bunches of broccoli with florets and stems (sliced thinly)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;extra virgin olive oil&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.traderjoes.com/fearless-flyer/article.asp?article_id=149&#34;&gt;Trader Joe&amp;rsquo;s South African smoke seasoning&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;two tomatoes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;one onion&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;one clove of garlic&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;dancing&#34;&gt;Dancing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a photo of some dancing in action.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/french-potluck-2013-09-14/dancing.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I did not actually do much dancing this evening at all, because of my slow recovery from a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/09/06/was-it-worth-sprinting-to-a-terrible-fall-to-finish-25th-in-the-cmu-pretty-good-race-5k/&#34;&gt;really bad injury from a week ago&lt;/a&gt;. I only did one dance. My left arm, left hip, and right knee are in constant pain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did join John by playing flute along with him on button accordion. By the way, he&amp;rsquo;s planning to order a new one with more rows and more keys to play in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were not enough women tonight for pairing up. It was joked that this is a &amp;ldquo;Pittsburgh problem&amp;rdquo;, because usually when it comes to dancing, there are not enough men!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although I could not really dance tonight, I appreciated the opportunity to socialize and make music, and not feel so lonely at home alone while Abby was out of town!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Learning the Congo de Captieux traditional French dance</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/05/25/learning-the-congo-de-captieux-traditional-french-dance/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 May 2013 23:29:20 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/05/25/learning-the-congo-de-captieux-traditional-french-dance/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Abby and I went to a French dance potluck party hosted by Lisa that included a special dance workshop on &amp;ldquo;Congo de Captieux&amp;rdquo; taught by her and a visitor, Lynn. This is a set dance for groups of four dancers (two couples) that really moves along and gets you sweaty! Here is a sample of what it looks like (&lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; of us):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/ZHovppdfZBk&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We haven&amp;rsquo;t been doing French dance or music lately because of lots of things going on (including Abby&amp;rsquo;s breaking her foot in February; she can finally do a bit of dancing again), so it was good to be back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dance was pretty complex to learn, but it was fun to finally be able to get through the steps, because the coordinating the interleaving continuous motion was strangely satisfying and thrilling!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Stepping it up at the French and blues jam</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/02/25/stepping-it-up-at-the-french-and-blues-jam/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Feb 2013 23:09:11 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/02/25/stepping-it-up-at-the-french-and-blues-jam/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Last month, I reported on &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/28/my-first-blues-music-jam-happened-after-the-regular-french-music-jam/&#34;&gt;exciting new developments in the local French/blues music jam&lt;/a&gt; that happens approximately once a month. We continued with the excitement this month, playing more complex and difficult tunes that Lisa, John, Donna, and others have been transcribing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, if you are interested in checking out some of our growing French repertoire, take a look at our &lt;a href=&#34;http://drawthedots.com/&#34;&gt;transcriptions&lt;/a&gt;, choosing tunebook &amp;ldquo;Campanule by Gregory Dyke&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Tunes for Mondays by Lisa Tamres&amp;rdquo;. These tunebooks are always in progress, so not everything we know or are working on has been put up yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And if you live in the Pittsburgh area and would like to join in playing with us in the future, contact me!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;french-jam&#34;&gt;French jam&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I arrived somewhat late because I was coming from leaving the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/02/25/openhack-pittsburgh-studying-scala/&#34;&gt;second OpenHack Pittsburgh&lt;/a&gt; early (regrettably); in retrospect, I was trying to squeeze in too much on a Monday evening and should have skipped attending OpenHack Pittsburgh, but I had too much enjoyed &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/21/attending-the-first-openhack-pittsburgh-meeting/&#34;&gt;the first one&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I arrived, Lisa, John, and Allison were already playing together (on fiddle, accordion, piano), and I joined them for two hours of jamming and playing for the dancers who arrived later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was excited to be learning new (to me) music, in various different keys and modes and rhythms, while all still falling in the categories of waltz, mazurka, bourrée, Schottisch. Because of all the different keys, I ended up only playing my modern flute, not ever switching to my Irish flute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We took turns looking through some transcriptions and deciding what to work on, and one song I chose was something called &amp;ldquo;Les Ormeaux&amp;rdquo;. It&amp;rsquo;s a lovely song. Here is a performance of it on accordion I found:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/MxuXoaH5L2k&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;upcoming-french-dance-workshop&#34;&gt;Upcoming French dance workshop&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another French dance workshop is &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.facebook.com/events/161251944027578/&#34;&gt;being held at CMU on Saturday, March 9&lt;/a&gt;. There was discussion of getting a group of us together to play live music for the workshop. This reminded me that it was a year ago that I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/01/23/discovering-french-traditional-dance-in-pittsburgh/&#34;&gt;first became involved in French dance&lt;/a&gt; and also hoped to eventually play music at a workshop. Normally, I would jump at the opportunity to play for the next French dance workshop, taking up the main melody role on flute, but I simply anticipated being too busy to be involved in the next one coming up so soon, so I had to decline to join in. I hope that for the April workshop I&amp;rsquo;ll have more time to commit to joining in, rehearsing, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;blues-jam&#34;&gt;Blues jam&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was exhausted after two hours of the French jam and dance, plus I needed to get home as I promised Abby I would be home before she got back from being driven home from her mandolin practice, so I don&amp;rsquo;t know how the blues jam went. Maybe next month I&amp;rsquo;ll be able to check it out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a great time further exploring French music and continuing to play with Lisa, John, and Allison, whom I&amp;rsquo;ve played with several times now, getting to feel like a solid core group.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My first blues music jam happened after the regular French music jam</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/01/28/my-first-blues-music-jam-happened-after-the-regular-french-music-jam/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jan 2013 23:26:28 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/01/28/my-first-blues-music-jam-happened-after-the-regular-french-music-jam/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s been over two months since the last French music jam, which was in November. I didn&amp;rsquo;t write about it because there was nothing particularly remarkable about it compared to the whole past year of French music jams: there was Lisa, John, Allison, a new fiddler Liz, and Leslie joining us on banjo again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tonight, an addition was made to the program. For some time I had suggested to Lisa that for French/blues dance night, maybe there should be a blues jam in addition to the French jam. She liked that idea, got hold of people she knew who were interested, and so tonight was the first blues jam!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was actually &lt;em&gt;my first full participation in a blues jam&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was very anxious, but I&amp;rsquo;ve grown somewhat used to feeling anxious at least once a month in the past two years pushing myself into unfamiliar territory repeatedly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, there were some changes for the French jam. Here&amp;rsquo;s how the evening went.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;french-jam&#34;&gt;French jam&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this new year of French music jamming, John, Lisa, and others have kicked things off by transcribing some of their favorite tunes by listening to recordings, watching YouTube, or from memory, in order to share so that we can learn and play them. John couldn&amp;rsquo;t make it tonight, ironically, because he was sick, but I was very exciting that we started exploring a lot of new tunes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I showed up, it was just Lisa on fiddle, Allison on piano (she also brought her button accordion), and me. Enough to get going. (I switched between Irish flute and modern flute as needed depending on the key.) Later, Donna also showed up, on fiddle, and Jess showed up, on clarinet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We played for quite some time, including old favorites we already knew, for the dancers, and learning some new tunes. I think we were at it for two hours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;blues-jam&#34;&gt;Blues jam&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As some of the French dance crowd went home and the blues dance crowd came in, the blues jam began. There was Anders on piano, whom I recognized from his having played blues indoors at a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/03/petrified-at-a-music-jam-session-so-i-didnt-play-but-watched-and-listened/&#34;&gt;summer party&lt;/a&gt;; I may have seen him elsewhere also at &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/10/07/my-first-contra-dance-workshop-unexpected-fun./&#34;&gt;contra dance&lt;/a&gt; or something. I met Michael and Billy, who both had guitars and harmonicas. And all three of them were apparently willing to sing!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was really intimidated. I&amp;rsquo;m still totally, utterly a novice at blues, although I started working on that last year. I wasn&amp;rsquo;t even sure whether I shouldn&amp;rsquo;t pack up my flute and go home. After all, I&amp;rsquo;d already spent a lot of time on music this evening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But something happened that made me stay! Allison seemed like she was about to pack up too, but was curious, and stayed. No longer on piano, she was on her button accordion. We both confessed to never having done this before, but stayed on. I thought she was doing quite well. I wasn&amp;rsquo;t doing so well, but I participated in bits. (But no, I did not sing.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for playing for dancers, I think the dancers were sometimes confused by the experiment, because they didn&amp;rsquo;t have their usual iTunes playlist to dance to. Not everything we did was really suitable to the dancing they wanted to do. We&amp;rsquo;ll have to eventually figure out what works for the dancers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically, when it came to my first blues jam experience, I felt sort of the way I did when I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/05/14/playing-french-music-for-first-time-and-dancing-blues-for-first-time/&#34;&gt;first got into playing French music eight months ago&lt;/a&gt;: anxious, uncertain, embarrassed. But if I work at this and get more comfortable and better, the feeling will pass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d like to do more blues jamming. There is a bit of a problem in that this has made for a very long and late evening. I think that&amp;rsquo;s just the nature of the blues music/dance world. I&amp;rsquo;ll have to plan my schedule accordingly if I want to integrate a regular blues jam into my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And of course, I should continue my studies of the blues.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dan Possumato and friends playing Irish, Scottish, French music</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/11/25/dan-possumato-and-friends-playing-irish-scottish-french-music/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Nov 2012 21:42:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/11/25/dan-possumato-and-friends-playing-irish-scottish-french-music/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/dan-possumato/flyer.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;World Kaleidoscope Flyer&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Abby and I checked out a musical performance at the Carnegie Library of Pittsburgh, main branch. They have a regular Sunday afternoon &amp;ldquo;World Kaleidoscope&amp;rdquo; series featuring world sounds from local musicians: two months ago I reported on some delightful &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/23/living-appalachian-music-of-southwestern-pennsylvania/&#34;&gt;local Appalachian music&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.carnegielibrary.org/events/details.cfm?event_id=69116&#34;&gt;Today&amp;rsquo;s performance&lt;/a&gt; was by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.danpossumato.com&#34;&gt;Dan Possumato&lt;/a&gt; and friends, featuring mostly Irish music, with Dan on button accordion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had a good time. Among the selections:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Scottish music&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Irish jigs and reels&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Irish waltz &amp;ldquo;Planxty Irwin&amp;rdquo; that Abby and I danced to&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a French &lt;a href=&#34;http://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hanter-dro&#34;&gt;hanter dro&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/dan-possumato/back.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;View from back&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/dan-possumato/right.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;View from right&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/dan-possumato/dan-possumato.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Dan Possumato&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>French music jam with unexpected new musicians</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/10/15/french-music-jam-with-unexpected-new-musicians/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Oct 2012 23:45:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/10/15/french-music-jam-with-unexpected-new-musicians/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Tonight was my fourth participation in &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/28/another-french-music-jam-also-announcing-cats-dance/&#34;&gt;Lisa&amp;rsquo;s French traditional dance music jam&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The evening started quietly, because only Lisa and John and I were present at first, and nobody else. Apparently people were either in classes or had other engagements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We always love having more people join us in making music, so it was great that unexpectedly, we got two people into playing with us before I had to leave after two hours! So where did they come from?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;three-of-us&#34;&gt;Three of us&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it was just the three of us, Lisa and John played over some new tunes they had worked on earlier, so that I could pick them up. I&amp;rsquo;m much better now at learning music by ear. I&amp;rsquo;m still not very fast at picking up tunes, but I&amp;rsquo;m definitely better. Furthermore, although they had scribbled down some scores on paper to keep track of the different new songs, I found the handwritten attempts sufficiently difficult to decipher that I chose to completely ignore them. This is a new attitude for me: in the past, I would have scrambled to get a written score if possible. Now, I&amp;rsquo;ve grown used to doing without, and not worrying about making mistakes or learning more slowly than if I had a score. It took me &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/05/14/playing-french-music-for-first-time-and-dancing-blues-for-first-time/&#34;&gt;five months&lt;/a&gt; to reach this point of relative comfort with uncertainty, confusion, and imperfection, ha!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;dancers&#34;&gt;Dancers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Very few dancers showed up at all during the evening. As a result, the ones that did show up expecting to dance started watching us continue to play music instead. But then John started saying, &amp;ldquo;Hey, grab an instrument and join us!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Someone I hadn&amp;rsquo;t met before, Georgia, had started learning some chords on mandolin recently, and she got sucked into joining us as John handed her his mandolin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later, Leslie arrived. She regularly attends to dance. Since there were hardly any dancers around, we said, hey, want to play? John pointed to two banjo cases he had on the floor, so she went and tried one banjo and then switched to the other, and the next thing we knew, we were all playing together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Georgia and Leslie do play other musical instruments and sing, but they just happen not to &amp;ldquo;really&amp;rdquo; play mandolin or banjo. I thought it was pretty cool that the unfortunate lack of dancers led to their unexpectedly joining us as musicians. I guess we&amp;rsquo;ll see whether they start playing more with us!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The small number of musicians and dancers might have made the evening less interesting than past sessions, but it was great that we spontaneously added to our musical group for the evening.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My first contra dance workshop: unexpected fun!</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/10/07/my-first-contra-dance-workshop-unexpected-fun/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Oct 2012 21:19:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/10/07/my-first-contra-dance-workshop-unexpected-fun/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/first-contra-dance/motion.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Dancers in motion&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Today Abby and I attended the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/events/374623475947550/&#34;&gt;first CMU contra dance workshop&lt;/a&gt; put on by the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/catsdancepgh&#34;&gt;Carnegie Alliance of Traditional and Social Dance&lt;/a&gt;, as I mentioned we might when I wrote about the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/28/another-french-music-jam-also-announcing-cats-dance/&#34;&gt;formation of CATS Dance&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have to understand that for years I &lt;em&gt;resisted&lt;/em&gt; the idea of ever doing contra dancing. I had some bad memories of being forced to do a bit of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Square_dance&#34;&gt;square dancing&lt;/a&gt; in elementary school, I have a tendency to resist choreographed patterns, and frankly, I associated contra dancing with old, maybe clumsy people. In the past year, having met plenty of people who mentioned doing contra dancing, and who clearly are not old and clumsy (some are old but far from clumsy), I&amp;rsquo;d gotten interested in giving it a try.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The seed was first planted just from happening to get pulled into &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/11/learning-another-instrument-the-tin-whistle/&#34;&gt;playing music for contra dancing ten months ago&lt;/a&gt;. But I didn&amp;rsquo;t act on it, other than participating a little bit impromptu &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/31/my-first-sampling-of-english-country-dance-and-contra-dance/&#34;&gt;at a birthday party&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I finally went for a full four-hour workshop, held at CMU.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a great time, way beyond my expectations!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;turnout&#34;&gt;Turnout&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The turnout was great. I estimate there were about thirty to forty participants. Most of them appeared to be undergrad or grad students; others were older people, many of whom Abby and I already knew from elsewhere, including the &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/french-dance/&#34;&gt;French dance workshops we&amp;rsquo;ve attended in the past several months&lt;/a&gt;. The predominance of young people was a good sign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;caller&#34;&gt;Caller&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.cdss.org/system/html/gayefifer-579cfde1.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Gaye Fifer&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We were really blessed today to have a great caller, &lt;a href=&#34;http://wa64.com/Waltz.html&#34;&gt;Gaye Fifer&lt;/a&gt;, who is not only clear in her instruction and calling, but also was always very observant and helpful to anyone who was in her line of sight. Whenever I was near her and messing up, she noticed and efficiently got me back on track. She did that for everyone, not just me. Given the size of the crowd, I found that care and attention to detail really impressive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gaye made the whole learning experience effective, friendly, and joyful!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;band&#34;&gt;Band&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/first-contra-dance/gallimaufry.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Gallimaufry&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We also had a fantastic live band, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/gallimaufryband&#34;&gt;Gallimaufry&lt;/a&gt;, from Oberlin. This is a group of five youthful and very skilled musicians playing a whole bunch of instruments. I saw fiddle, cello, electric guitar, accordion, piano, drums.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They played with great rhythm and sheer exuberance and expression, and seamless ensemble work. Wow. They were rocking out. They knew how to ramp it up to get the dancers moving and smiling!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;participants&#34;&gt;Participants&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The energy level and enthusiasm of the dancers today was great. I have been in dance situations in which some of the dancers were not fully engaged, not really getting into the music or the movement, or choosing to remain distant with those they rotated around to dance with. I think it&amp;rsquo;s really important, for this kind of dance to work, for everyone to be fully present and open to the experience, and open to dancing with everyone else. It&amp;rsquo;s a communal experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a mix of beginners (like myself) as well as those who clearly already knew what they were doing. This was actually very helpful because those who knew what they were doing kept the rest of us on the right track, both through personal example and through verbal and physical reminders of what to do. As a result, typically after repeating a pattern ten times (down one end of the room to the next and then back) while the music went on and on, I was able to improve during each iteration to the point that by the end of each dance we learned, I more or less knew what to do and how to do it (not that I necessarily remembered it exactly or executed it smoothly).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, I got pretty sweaty during the four-hour workshop. It was intense. This isn&amp;rsquo;t just shuffling around: it&amp;rsquo;s real exercise, with the music being lively and everyone being in constant motion. I was starving and dehydrated after the first two hours!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;watching&#34;&gt;Watching&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/first-contra-dance/abby-david.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby partnering with David&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There was a snack break halfway through, but I took other breaks to catch my breath and rest my mind, since the dances got progressively more complicated and faster (counting in four rather than eight, for example, and traveling more). It was fun to take a break and watch people dance, because the more experienced dancers added their own ornaments and spins and looked so smooth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the caller pointed out, the subtlety and the fun in contra dancing comes from making all the &lt;em&gt;transitions&lt;/em&gt; smooth and coordinated. I have a lot of work to do to continue improving, but during the hours of the workshop as I learned to be more aware of my immediate circle and relative positions and movements, I got a real sense of how I could really improve my experience of and enjoyment of contra dance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;french-dance-during-break&#34;&gt;French dance during break&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, during the break, Lisa taught some basic French dance to those who just couldn&amp;rsquo;t get too much dancing. Hopefully this will translate into increased participation in the upcoming French dance workshops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;waltzes&#34;&gt;Waltzes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a nice typical touch, each of the two sets were concluded with a waltz. Abby and I enjoyed the opportunity to dance together, just the two of us, during the waltzes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-next&#34;&gt;What next?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I have known for a while, of course, about the regular &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburghcontra.org/&#34;&gt;Friday night contra dance by the Pittsburgh Contras and Squares&lt;/a&gt;. That&amp;rsquo;s not a great time and day, unfortunately, because going out late on a Friday night does not appeal to me. I like the weekend afternoon schedule of the CMU French and contra dance workshops, currently held 4-7 PM. Being held at CMU also has the large advantages of being very close to home as well as encouraging a good turnout of young people to keep the energy up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the current CMU schedule continues, that makes it much more likely that we&amp;rsquo;ll continue to do French and contra dancing regularly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, I expect to play music at the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/16/playing-recorder-and-flute-at-the-holiday-ball/&#34;&gt;annual holiday ball&lt;/a&gt; again this year. This time, I am sure I will have no fear about maybe taking part in the dancing!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had an unforgettable dance experience today. I never expected to enjoy contra dancing so much, but because of how friendly all of the workshop participants were, and the caller, and the amazing band, I feel like I now have a taste of why people do this, and I hope to do more!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Another French music jam; also, announcing CATS Dance</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/09/28/another-french-music-jam-also-announcing-cats-dance/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Sep 2012 20:55:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/09/28/another-french-music-jam-also-announcing-cats-dance/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://thebridge.cmu.edu/images/W170xL170/0/noshadow/Organization/603b06cbdc7847018dce159a5ed99543.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;CATS Dance photo&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;On Monday I participated for my third time in Lisa&amp;rsquo;s French traditional dance music jam.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/08/27/my-second-french-music-jam-playing-my-irish-flute-in-public-for-the-first-time/&#34;&gt;Last time&lt;/a&gt;, I started playing my &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/irish-flute/&#34;&gt;Irish flute&lt;/a&gt; at the jam, continued playing my &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/baroque-flute/&#34;&gt;Baroque flute&lt;/a&gt;, and left my modern flute at home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This time, I changed things up. Also, we got a new musician playing a new instrument!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;instruments-and-musicians&#34;&gt;Instruments and musicians&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lisa was on fiddle as usual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we had John, who brought and used various kinds of accordions and his mandolin. (He had also brought recorders, in case I wanted to play with him, but I did not bring my recorders.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Allison was on piano.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Donna was on fiddle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most exciting to me was that Cindy came and played &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Autoharp&#34;&gt;autoharp&lt;/a&gt;. I think the addition of the harmonic accompaniment and countermelodies she provided was really nice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-instruments&#34;&gt;My instruments&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; bring my Baroque flute this time. I made a decision this week that I was no longer going to try to play my Baroque flute in most public situations. I have been frustrated that its soft sound gets drowned out by other instruments and just by people talking and socializing at parties. Therefore, when playing the Baroque flute in public, I will reserve it for very quiet performance situations only.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did bring my Irish flute, which served well when we were playing in appropriate keys.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have begun caving in and bringing my modern flute. It can be played more easily in all kinds of keys, and has the power to actually be heard. Maybe one day I&amp;rsquo;ll have a keyed wooden flute to play traditional music on, but that day is not near at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So after some experimentation, I believe I&amp;rsquo;m come to the right instrument(s) for different situations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;carnegie-alliance-of-traditional-and-social-dance-cats-dance&#34;&gt;Carnegie Alliance of Traditional and Social Dance (CATS Dance)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d like to take this opportunity to promote the new CMU-based dance group, the &lt;a href=&#34;http://thebridge.cmu.edu/organization/catsdance&#34;&gt;Carnegie Alliance of Traditional and Social Dance&lt;/a&gt;. Check out also their &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/catsdancepgh&#34;&gt;Facebook page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This group has been formed in order to grow a local community of people interested in all kinds of traditional and social dance, French dance being just one example; contra dancing and other folk dancing are also being explored.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In particular, this group exists because there is increasing interest among young people in these kinds of dances and music. The Pittsburgh dance scene has sometimes been dominated by older people, and it&amp;rsquo;s good to get younger people involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last week CATS Dance organized an outing to the regular &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburghcontra.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Contras and Squares&lt;/a&gt; Friday dance. Tomorrow there will be a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/events/105195582969170/&#34;&gt;French dance workshop and social dance&lt;/a&gt; held directly on CMU campus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These workshops and dances are, of course, open to everyone, not just CMU students. Abby and I are not CMU students, but &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/01/23/discovering-french-traditional-dance-in-pittsburgh/&#34;&gt;started attending&lt;/a&gt; these workshops at CMU in January. All ages and levels of dancers are always welcome! If you&amp;rsquo;re curious, drop by and check it out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first contra dance workshop to be hosted at CMU has also already been scheduled, for Sunday, October 7. Since I&amp;rsquo;ve never been to a contra dance workshop (although I had a sampling of contra dance at a birthday party &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/31/my-first-sampling-of-english-country-dance-and-contra-dance&#34;&gt;six months ago&lt;/a&gt;; I was very confused by it then), I hope Abby and I will make it to this workshop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2012-10-07&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-10-07)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/10/07/my-first-contra-dance-workshop-unexpected-fun/&#34;&gt;Abby and I did make it to the contra dance workshop&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I continue to greatly enjoy the regular French music jam and meeting and playing with more musicians. Meanwhile, although I have not done much dancing lately, I am excited about the creation of CATS Dance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2012-10-15&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-10-15)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out the latest update on the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/10/15/french-music-jam-with-unexpected-new-musicians/&#34;&gt;French music jam&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My second French music jam: playing my Irish flute in public for the first time</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/08/27/my-second-french-music-jam-playing-my-irish-flute-in-public-for-the-first-time/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Aug 2012 22:37:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/08/27/my-second-french-music-jam-playing-my-irish-flute-in-public-for-the-first-time/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Tonight I participated for the second time in a new little &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/groups/182324948478861/&#34;&gt;French traditional dance&lt;/a&gt; music jam session that &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/02/my-first-french-music-jam-anxious-but-excited/&#34;&gt;started up in July&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This time, I played not only my &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/baroque-flute/&#34;&gt;Baroque flute&lt;/a&gt; (which happens to be the instrument I&amp;rsquo;ve mostly been playing for the past two months), but also my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/30/got-my-new-casey-burns-small-handed-irish-flute/&#34;&gt;new Irish flute I got a month ago&lt;/a&gt;. I did &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; bring my modern flute at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we did the last time, after we played around for an hour or so, we then played for dancers for another hour. I enjoyed the experience a lot, and was less nervous than I was the first time. I am slowly improving at learning a tune, without a score, while someone is playing it, and then imitating the melodic line or filling in a harmonically sensible line on the fly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;instruments-and-musicians&#34;&gt;Instruments and musicians&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I finally received my Irish flute a month ago and have spent some minutes every day breaking it in at home. Tonight was its &amp;ldquo;debut&amp;rdquo; in public. I enjoyed the louder, stronger sound.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still used the Baroque flute, for key signatures that my keyless Irish flute does not work well for (half-holing is a pain).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also had fiddles, melodeon, guitar, mandolin (not all at the same time, since John was switching between melodeon and mandolin depending on the key of the song, given the limitations of the melodeon), and I felt that the Irish flute was balanced pretty well with the other instruments, better than the Baroque flute did in the first session in July (when it was often drowned out).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We lost some musicians from last time, because one of them left town, and the clarinetist has a class in the evening and therefore cannot arrive till later, when she comes to dance. But we had two new people!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our little French music group is gaining momentum. I&amp;rsquo;m very excited! Also, as the CMU fall semester starts, there are plans to really promote French and other traditional music and dance in the form of an official CMU student organization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2012-09-28&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-09-28)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/28/another-french-music-jam-also-announcing-cats-dance/&#34;&gt;CATS Dance successfully launched in September&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My first French music jam: anxious but excited</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/07/02/my-first-french-music-jam-anxious-but-excited/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jul 2012 23:45:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/07/02/my-first-french-music-jam-anxious-but-excited/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Tonight I participated for the first time in a new local &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/groups/182324948478861/&#34;&gt;French traditional dance&lt;/a&gt; music jam session that is getting off the ground, organized by Lisa. I was really excited about the formation of our group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How did this come about?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;inspired-by-gregory&#34;&gt;Inspired by Gregory&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What happened was that after &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/05/14/playing-french-music-for-first-time-and-dancing-blues-for-first-time/&#34;&gt;Gregory left us this summer&lt;/a&gt;, I told Lisa that I really wanted to do the kind of thing Gregory had been doing, playing French music for dancers. Lisa was excited about this and thought it would be cool for herself to start playing fiddle again. She found some other people who were interested in playing French music together, and so we met up!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;instruments&#34;&gt;Instruments&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tonight, I played both my &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/baroque-flute/&#34;&gt;Baroque flute&lt;/a&gt; and my modern flute. I didn&amp;rsquo;t really want to play the modern flute, but there were times when we played some music in keys I wasn&amp;rsquo;t comfortable with on Baroque flute. Meanwhile, it will take a long time for the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/06/12/ordered-the-casey-burns-small-handed-irish-flute/&#34;&gt;Irish flute I ordered&lt;/a&gt; to be made and shipped. I really want to use the louder Irish flute when feasible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lisa had her fiddle, and someone else also had a fiddle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A guy brought his melodeon (button accordion), which unfortunately is limited in the keys it can play in. He sometimes used the old upright piano also. There was someone else who also used the piano.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there was someone on clarinet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-it-went&#34;&gt;How it went&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was quite nervous, because much of what we did was not from printed scores, but from people&amp;rsquo;s memories of their favorite tunes. I in fact ended up using my phone to send Lisa a PDF of Gregory&amp;rsquo;s French music score compilation so that she could print it out for some of us!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I quickly noticed that my Baroque flute was being drowned out by the other instruments. So I pulled out my modern flute sometimes in order to be heard more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We went on for quite some time as the dancers arrived and became restless, and then we played for them for about an hour. Actually, I was heard better then, because Lisa and some other musicians gave introductory lessons or themselves wanted to dance. The result was that after a while, it was just Donna on fiddle, John on melodeon, and me on Baroque flute playing for the dancers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s really a joy playing music for people to dance to. I feel like I&amp;rsquo;m starting to fulfill my dream that &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/10/flute-loving-it-again/&#34;&gt;I dared to mention in March: that of being the musician rather than the dancer at a dance&lt;/a&gt;. During his time here in Pittsburgh, I was really inspired by the example of Gregory (who has finished his stay in the country and gone back to Europe) to start learning tunes by ear, ornamenting, and improvising. I&amp;rsquo;m still quite a beginner at this approach to music, but this is what I&amp;rsquo;ve always wanted to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first French music jam and new format for the French dance (live music instead of iTunes) was a great start of something new. We were all so excited that we definitely want to continue doing this. I look forward to continuing to play together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2012-08-27&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-08-27)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And less than two months later, I am &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/08/27/my-second-french-music-jam-playing-my-irish-flute-in-public-for-the-first-time/&#34;&gt;still involved in the new French music jam&lt;/a&gt;, and finally with my own Irish flute!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Playing French music for the first time, and dancing blues for the first time</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/05/14/playing-french-music-for-first-time-and-dancing-blues-for-first-time/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 May 2012 23:44:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/05/14/playing-french-music-for-first-time-and-dancing-blues-for-first-time/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Although I have stopped writing about it, Abby and I have continued to do &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/02/20/enjoying-more-french-dancing-in-pittsburgh/&#34;&gt;French dancing here in Pittsburgh&lt;/a&gt;. Tonight, for the first time, we finally attended the regular Monday night French and blues dance hosted by Lisa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was quite an intense evening for me, both playing French music &lt;em&gt;for the first time&lt;/em&gt; and dancing blues &lt;em&gt;for the first time&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;french-and-blues-social-dance&#34;&gt;French and blues social dance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;French &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; blues night?! What&amp;rsquo;s the connection?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, the story is simply that Lisa and Gregory (and some other dancers) enjoy both French music/dance and blues music/dance, so both types of music and dance are combined into one evening of dancing. Of course, there are people who show up who are only interested in the French or only interested in the blues. The iTunes playlists have a mix of both.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-i-wanted-to-go&#34;&gt;Why I wanted to go&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d never done blues dancing before, and was curious to see it, and maybe learn some and try it with Abby, who is also completely unfamiliar with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also: since Gregory is going back back to Europe soon, I wanted to have an opportunity to see him again before he left, and finally play French music with him. I&amp;rsquo;d never played French music before. When I told him I wanted to come and play with him for the first time, he helpfully sent me a link to his compilation of French tunes, &lt;a href=&#34;http://drawthedots.com/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Campanule&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. I feverishly tried to learn some of them before showing up. That was tricky because I wanted to play the music on my Baroque flute, an instrument that I&amp;rsquo;m &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/04/21/my-first-time-in-a-public-music-jam-intense-fun-with-chris-norman-and-david-greenberg/&#34;&gt;still quite a beginner at&lt;/a&gt;. But I didn&amp;rsquo;t want to use the modern flute for this music; it doesn&amp;rsquo;t produce the kind of sound I like for traditional music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;playing-music-with-gregory&#34;&gt;Playing music with Gregory&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gregory and I spent maybe ten minutes playing some of his compiled music sort of together. This was very hard for me for a number of reasons:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m still pretty bad at Baroque flute, having trouble with fingerings and intonation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t know the tunes very well, and was trying to find them in my printouts of his scores.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;He doesn&amp;rsquo;t even look at the scores, but just plays from memory.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;He doesn&amp;rsquo;t play exactly what was in the scores anyway, but improvises at will.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We were not coordinated, because he repeated sections or measures at will, and we didn&amp;rsquo;t really take turns or something.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t know how to come up with a secondary line or accompaniment on the fly to blend in with Gregory.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As dancers started arriving and Gregory kept on playing, I stopped my feeble attempts at contributing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a way, my attempt to get into playing French music tonight was a &lt;em&gt;failure&lt;/em&gt;, but on the other hand, I actually learned a lot from observing Gregory, and knew what I had to do to be able to function as an actual musician for dancing. I had to memorize tunes, learn them by ear, get myself off the tyranny of printed scores, watch dancers, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;dancing-blues&#34;&gt;Dancing blues&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point, the French dance part of the evening started to end, as the demand for blues rose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There wasn&amp;rsquo;t going to be any blues dance instruction, so Abby and I had a choice. We could just watch, or we could leave. We did do some watching, but I decided I wanted to dance, and so I just started making stuff up. I got the impression that people were basically just leading and following through improvisation similar to what I&amp;rsquo;ve experienced before when I did some Argentine tango (and a bit of Lindy hop and West Coast swing). I rather enjoy that kind of improvisational dancing, but have had little opportunity to participate in it because Abby is not used to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We did do a bit of blues dancing tonight, but it&amp;rsquo;s not clear to me whether we will continue. I&amp;rsquo;m very interested in exploring blues dance further, but Abby seems less interested. People are interested in different activities; that&amp;rsquo;s just a fact of life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This evening highlighted the contrast between my lack of ability to function as a practical musician for dancers and my comfort with improvisation as a dancer. I plan to work toward merging these two worlds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel sad that Gregory is leaving us, because I wanted to start working with him on French music, but his example has inspired me to want to continue playing French music after he is gone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2012-07-02&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-07-02)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And less than two months later, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/02/my-first-french-music-jam-anxious-but-excited/&#34;&gt;I joined Lisa and others in playing French music together, inspired by Gregory&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Flute: loving it again, remembering why I dance, and how I met my wife!</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/03/10/flute-loving-it-again/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Mar 2012 21:28:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/03/10/flute-loving-it-again/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, after four days of &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/07/flute-taking-a-break-while-clarifying-my-goals&#34;&gt;not even touching my (modern) flute&lt;/a&gt; and having spent the time having fun with my Baroque flute instead, I felt the urge to return to the modern flute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still have not regained the inclination to continue working on the orchestra music I still have to improve a lot on in the coming week, but I rediscovered the joy of simply playing my instrument.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;sound-intonation&#34;&gt;Sound, intonation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The perpetual challenges of getting clean sounds and accurate pitches on the Baroque flute in the past four days have given me an increased appreciation for the modern flute. I picked it up and spent time just trying to make beautiful sounds. Freed from the stress of orchestra practice, I felt much more relaxed on the instrument than I have for a while now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To my surprise (but not really), I have improved considerably on the flute after not playing it for four days. I really needed a break, a consolidation of lessons learned. My production of tones is much improved, and high notes are squeaking less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;music-for-dance&#34;&gt;Music for dance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing I&amp;rsquo;ve truly come to realize is that I particularly enjoy playing rhythmic music suitable for dancing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, every time I attend a dance, and there is live music, I experience a strange internal conflict: I do like to dance, but sometimes, I&amp;rsquo;d rather be on the other side of the dance floor, being the musical performer! The &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; time I&amp;rsquo;ve been on the other side has been at last year&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburghcontra.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Contras and Squares&lt;/a&gt; Holiday Ball.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most recent instance of my wishing I could sometimes stop dancing and just join the musicians has been at the local &lt;a href=&#34;http://coalcountry.org/frenchdance.html&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh French dance workshop and social&lt;/a&gt;, where we&amp;rsquo;ve had live piano, fiddle, and of course, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~gdyke/&#34;&gt;Gregory&lt;/a&gt; on his Irish flute. I wonder whether at some point I might be qualified to play for the event, using either my modern flute or Baroque flute. (By the way, it was held again today, but unfortunately, Abby and I chose not to go because we had too many things to do this weekend.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;remembering-dancing&#34;&gt;Remembering dancing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday I spent time playing along to a score/CD set I&amp;rsquo;ve mentioned before, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/World-Music-Cuba-Flute-play-along/dp/3702465804&#34;&gt;World Music Cuba&lt;/a&gt;. While playing the bolero, cha cha, and mambo pieces in particular, I felt I was returning &amp;ldquo;home&amp;rdquo; in many ways. This was among the first music I heard and saw people dancing to when I was curious and visited the &lt;a href=&#34;http://cmubdc.org/&#34;&gt;CMU Ballroom Dance Club&lt;/a&gt; in 2000, and fell in love with, and learned to dance to. I also played along to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Play-along-Argentina-Flute-World-Music/dp/3702465871&#34;&gt;World Music Argentina&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;some-photos-of-my-ballroom-dance-days&#34;&gt;Some photos of my ballroom dance days&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some photos of me dancing in 2002 with my last dance partner, Amy, before I quit competitive ballroom dancing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here we are at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dcdancesportinferno.com/&#34;&gt;DC DanceSport Inferno&lt;/a&gt; in 2002 doing a hockey stick in international rumba:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/ballroom/dcdi-2002-hockey-stick.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Amy and Franklin at DCDI 2002 in rumba&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And here were are at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://comp.cornelldancesport.org/&#34;&gt;Cornell DanceSport Classic&lt;/a&gt; in 2002 in cha cha, rumba, and tango:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/ballroom/cornell-2002-new-yorker.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Amy and Franklin at Cornell 2002 in cha cha&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/ballroom/cornell-2002-hockey-stick.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Amy and Franklin at Cornell 2002 in rumba&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/ballroom/cornell-2002-tango-promenade.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Amy and Franklin at Cornell 2002 in tango&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;dancing-with-abby&#34;&gt;Dancing with Abby&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But never mind the ballroom dance days. It was through salsa dancing that I met my wife!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;how-i-met-abby&#34;&gt;How I met Abby&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was through dancing that I met Abby in the first place. After quitting dancing in 2003, I never danced again until late 2006, when my friend Jon told me he had recently started salsa dancing (because of a girlfriend who got him into it) and invited me to join him at a free outdoors dance, and I went. Then as I re-entered the Pittsburgh salsa dance scene, I kept running into Abby.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;some-photos-of-us-dancing-salsa&#34;&gt;Some photos of us dancing salsa&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are not many photos of Abby dancing with me, because when I&amp;rsquo;m dancing, I&amp;rsquo;m not holding my camera, but here are some photos a friend took at a big salsa dance weekend at the Palisades in McKeesport in April 2008, a year after we started dating in 2007.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/palisades-2008/abby-franklin.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby and Franklin dancing salsa at Palisades&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/palisades-2008/abby-franklin-hair.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby and Franklin dancing salsa at Palisades, hair flying&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;expression-and-improvisation-in-dance-and-in-music&#34;&gt;Expression and improvisation in dance and in music&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;dance&#34;&gt;Dance&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One reason I gave up ballroom dancing was that I felt there was an overemphasis on &amp;ldquo;syllabus steps&amp;rdquo; (I realize this is an oversimplification of the ballroom dance culture; all very good ballroom dancers go beyond the syllabus mindset). After quitting ballroom dancing, I explored Argentine tango, which is all about improvisation, but I left it because (at the time) it seemed that most of the women in the local scene were very tall, which made dancing awkward for me. I got into salsa because freed from the closed embrace, there was clearly a lot of room for personal improvisation. Ironically, I first got into making stuff up as a result of my imperfect memory: I could never memorize long choreography of step patterns, whether I was doing ballroom dancing or anything else. So I would always make a &amp;ldquo;mistake&amp;rdquo;, then I would make something out of the mistake. I learned that as long as you get back in time with the music, and keep the lead and follow communication strong, there is no such thing really as a mistake. You just keep going, with whatever is happening at the present moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I now have a long-term goal of developing my technique and releasing my inhibitions so that I can improvise musically at will. Yesterday, I played with improvising when playing bolero, cha cha, and tango. It was a lot of fun and profoundly satisfying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;music&#34;&gt;Music&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I actually credit my study of the recorder and the Baroque flute for reawakening me to my dream of free expression and improvisation. Baroque music leaves room for a lot of interpretation of trills and ornamentation and articulation (subject, of course, to &amp;ldquo;good taste&amp;rdquo;). I want to go beyond that, but it has been a great starting point. For some reason, too much exposure to later music (such as Beethoven) had turned me into a score-reader, since such later music has so much already marked up for the performer to simply &lt;em&gt;obey&lt;/em&gt;. The sparse annotations in Renaissance and Baroque music give one much more freedom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am enjoying playing the flute again, now that I know what I really want to do with it. And I would like to merge my dance and music lives, just as Abby has always played the Balkan music she also dances to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2012-03-12&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-03-12)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ended up &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/12/quitting-the-cmu-all-university-orchestra-one-of-the-hardest-decisions-in-my-life/&#34;&gt;quitting the CMU AUO&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2013-01-26&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-01-26)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost a year later, I finally played tangos on flute &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/26/music-i-just-played-for-the-first-time-recorder-sonata-tangos/&#34;&gt;at a party&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2013-03-17&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-03-17)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost exactly a year later, I ended up playing selections from the World Music Cuba book &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/17/finally-doing-some-latin-music-jamming-on-flute/&#34;&gt;at a party&lt;/a&gt;, and improvising freely with two other guys!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Enjoying more French dancing in Pittsburgh</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/02/20/enjoying-more-french-dancing-in-pittsburgh/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Feb 2012 01:03:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/02/20/enjoying-more-french-dancing-in-pittsburgh/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A month ago I reported on how Abby and I had our &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/01/23/discovering-french-traditional-dance-in-pittsburgh&#34;&gt;first experience of French traditional dance&lt;/a&gt;. On Saturday, we went again to Skibo Gym at Carnegie Mellon University for another fun session of French dancing from 4:00 to 7:00 PM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had a great time again, and afterwards joined the instructors and some other people in having dinner at &lt;a href=&#34;http://gulliftys.us/&#34;&gt;Gullifty&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;attendance&#34;&gt;Attendance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to some familiar faces, there were many new people we hadn&amp;rsquo;t met before, and I got my office mate John to go too. Abby and I learned some dances that were not taught the last time, and we got to do more of the dances we had learned the last time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The male-female ratio was not so great this time: it would be nice to have more men attend these workshops and dances! If you are male and interested in learning French dance, come next month!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;3-count-bourrée&#34;&gt;3-count bourrée&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last month, we had learned the 2-count bourrée, but this month we also added the 3-count. That&amp;rsquo;s really fast and was a real workout!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;dances-from-last-time&#34;&gt;Dances from last time&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We went over the dances from last time also. Since they were no longer new to me, I felt freer to feel the music more and make the most of enjoying the dances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, in a very simple circle dance, I felt like lifting my body up when we swung our arms upward, and letting my body bend naturally to the &amp;ldquo;1-2-3, down&amp;rdquo; movement. Otherwise, just stepping endlessly like a rigid robot was getting quite boring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last time, I was rather stiff and clumsy at the Schottische, waltz, and mazurka, because I was out of practice in these turning dances. This time I got more into the swing of things and remembered the fun I had doing ballroom dancing over ten years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were two other circle dances from last time that we did again. I really enjoy these partner switching dances. Again, since I knew the moves already, I felt freer to improve my technique and personal expression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;social-dancing&#34;&gt;Social dancing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A familiar musician, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/16/playing-recorder-and-flute-at-the-holiday-ball/&#34;&gt;Donna Isaac&lt;/a&gt;, played fiddle for us, with Gregory on his Irish flute again. I liked the different texture from last month&amp;rsquo;s piano and flute, but I have to confess that missing a bass line made the music harder to dance to. In fact, I ended up starting to hum my own bass line to fill in the harmonies to feel less of a musical omission and help my rhythm while dancing!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again I thank everyone who was at the workshop and dance. It was a great group. I am so happy to be dancing again. I had put it aside for a couple of years after Abby and I got married, but now I envision our making it a regular part of our lives again!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Sorry, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/02/19/why-i-have-not-posted-many-photos-or-videos-recently-exploitation/&#34;&gt;I took no photos or videos this time&lt;/a&gt;. I spent the whole time immersed in dancing!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;dinner-at-gullifty-s&#34;&gt;Dinner at Gullifty&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since people were talking about going to dinner afterwards, and this time Abby and I did not leave the dance early before it ended, we ended up joining six others for dinner. We helped pack stuff up and drove home and walked to Gullifty&amp;rsquo;s. I hadn&amp;rsquo;t been there in at least ten years. It&amp;rsquo;s not my favorite idea of food, but I made the most of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ordered a &amp;ldquo;pierogie burger&amp;rdquo; for dinner. Only in Pittsburgh, ha! It was actually pretty good. It was a burger that had pierogies on top, all encased in a bun. It came with a pickle and fries. Not the kind of food I usually eat, but &amp;ldquo;cheating&amp;rdquo; once in a while is fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, we &amp;ldquo;had&amp;rdquo; to have dessert. Gullifty&amp;rsquo;s is &amp;ldquo;famous&amp;rdquo; for desserts. Abby and I had reservations about continuing our &amp;ldquo;cheating&amp;rdquo; to desserts, but what the heck, we shared a triple chocolate cake. Unfortunately, we got a huge chunk of cake, as the waitress explained that it was the end of the cake so we got probably twice as much as we would ordinarily have received. We ate the whole thing, but I ended up feeling quite sugared out and bloated. That&amp;rsquo;s the punishment for &amp;ldquo;cheating&amp;rdquo; way too much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;blues-and-other-dancing&#34;&gt;Blues and other dancing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People at dinner were talking about needing to take a nap afterwards and then going to a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pittsburghdancecenter.com/&#34;&gt;blues dance&lt;/a&gt; at midnight. That&amp;rsquo;s very late for Abby and me to be dancing! We&amp;rsquo;ve never done blues dancing before but are interested in trying it out sometime (but not if it&amp;rsquo;s too late at night).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dinner gang was also into Lindy hop. I did a little bit of Lindy and swing a decade ago, but never got much into it. Maybe Abby and I should check that out too. I know there&amp;rsquo;s a lot of it here in Pittsburgh. In the past, I&amp;rsquo;ve gone to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.swingpgh.com&#34;&gt;Swing City&lt;/a&gt;. There&amp;rsquo;s the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.coalcountry.org/swingdances.html&#34;&gt;Edgewood Club&lt;/a&gt; also.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m kind of interested in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.chickenswing.com/&#34;&gt;Chicken Swing&lt;/a&gt; because it meets right at Carnegie Mellon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there&amp;rsquo;s West Coast swing in town too, at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pghwcs.com/&#34;&gt;Absolute Ballroom&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a lot of fun dancing with Abby more again, and also with other people, and hanging out at dinner. I am not a dance maniac any more, and time is limited, but I am excited about continuing with Abby to further explore dances we haven&amp;rsquo;t done much of before. It&amp;rsquo;s great exercise and great socializing!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2012-05-14&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-05-14)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three months later, I ended up beginning to &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/05/14/playing-french-music-for-first-time-and-dancing-blues-for-first-time/&#34;&gt;play French music on flutes&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Discovering French traditional social dance in Pittsburgh</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/01/23/discovering-french-traditional-dance-in-pittsburgh/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jan 2012 21:53:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/01/23/discovering-french-traditional-dance-in-pittsburgh/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/bourree.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Dancing to bourree&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/LwyH1viCibo&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Saturday, Abby and I went for the first time to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/events/344055168957638/&#34;&gt;latest meeting&lt;/a&gt; of a &lt;a href=&#34;http://coalcountry.org/frenchdance.html&#34;&gt;local French traditional social dance&lt;/a&gt; workshop and dance here in Pittsburgh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a lot of fun!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;attendance&#34;&gt;Attendance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the recently fallen snow at the time (now all but melted!), around twelve of us eventually showed up, and the male-female ratio happened to be very good. For most of us, it was our first time trying out French dancing, but some of us just happened to have had prior some experience with other dancing, such as ballroom and swing and Cajun. The workshop was very friendly to beginners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;dances-we-learned&#34;&gt;Dances we learned&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We spent an hour or so learning various dances, taught by Gregory Dyke and Lisa Tamres.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We warmed up by learning a simple &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Circle_dance&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;circle dance&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; to a waltz rhythm, and Gregory made it more challenging by having us sing along in French (which not all of us knew, but that was OK; I know some French but half the time I just hummed rather than try to sing French while doing dance steps).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then we went to the partnered &lt;em&gt;waltz&lt;/em&gt;, which we did at various tempos, but all pretty fast. There was discussion of toning down the long gliding and lifting actions that some of us reflexively use from having experience with the slow waltz from ballroom dancing, because there is not enough time to use those actions for every step. (I immediately remembered being constantly reminded not to perform these actions when I was dancing &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Viennese_Waltz&#34;&gt;Viennese waltz&lt;/a&gt; in my ballroom dance days. The tempo range for French waltz seems basically the same.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then we learned the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Schottische&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Schottische&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, in a variant that had a triple step, followed by a triple step, and then four single steps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then we changed things up to a variant of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bourrée&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;bourrée&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, in double time, in which there are two lines formed, and the partners facing each other alternate dancing toward each other and past each other, leaving room for personal expression as they do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We returned to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mazurka&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;mazurka&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which was very tricky for many of us because of the asymmetric step pattern: 1-2-hold, 1-2-3, followed by the same starting with the other foot. I still don&amp;rsquo;t completely have the hang of it, but I could feel how it could be pretty exciting because of the holding and building momentum for the second half of the pattern, on which I like to turn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, we learned a really fun circle dance, the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mts.net/~jinks/fd/circassi.htm&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Circassian Circle&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;social-dancing&#34;&gt;Social dancing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the workshop instruction, the pianist, Ellen Gozian, had arrived, and the social dance began to live music performed by her and also by Gregory on his wooden flute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About another hour of dancing followed, till it was time for Ellen to leave. Abby and I decided to leave shortly afterwards, but social dancing was going to continue with recorded music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a lot of fun exploring new dances, and would like to attend future workshops and social dances. It&amp;rsquo;s great that so many different dance and music groups exist here in Pittsburgh!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am grateful to Gregory and Lisa for the instruction, Ellen for the piano playing, and every person who was on the dance floor. I think I can safely claim that everyone was smiling and laughing and having a great time at this event!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;invitation&#34;&gt;Invitation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re in the Pittsburgh area and interested in French traditional social dance, check out the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/groups/182324948478861/&#34;&gt;Facebook group&lt;/a&gt; for announcements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2012-02-20&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-02-20)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I have &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/02/20/enjoying-more-french-dancing-in-pittsburgh/&#34;&gt;continued enjoying French dancing&lt;/a&gt; over the year.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>