<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Performance on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/performance/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Performance on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/performance/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Playing music on recorders at a Phipps Conservatory &#34;candlelight evening&#34;</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/12/09/playing-music-on-recorders-at-a-phipps-conservatory-candlelight-evening/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Dec 2012 20:46:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/12/09/playing-music-on-recorders-at-a-phipps-conservatory-candlelight-evening/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/recorders-at-phipps-2012/group-photo.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Sam, Franklin, Annie, Helen, Mike&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/recorders-at-phipps-2012/phipps-outside.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Entrance to Phipps&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;After almost two months of weekly music rehearsals, we (Annie, Helen, Mike, Sam, and I) finally performed as planned in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/events/136074939878556/&#34;&gt;Phipps Conservatory&lt;/a&gt;. It was a lot of fun. We came up with a huge batch of music that we hadn&amp;rsquo;t played &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/05/busy-evening-performing-at-phipps-followed-by-rehearsal-for-another-gig/&#34;&gt;at Phipps last year&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As people wandered around in the garden, sometimes they gathered to sit for a while to enjoy our music before moving on. We had our largest audiences earlier rather than later in the evening.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/recorders-at-phipps-2012/audience.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Audience at one point&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A sample photo and video, which I took while Sam, Helen, and Mike were playing in a trio, while Annie and I took a break. (Since there were five of us, we took turns playing either as a quartet or trio or as a quartet with a part doubled.)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/recorders-at-phipps-2012/trio.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Trio&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/1ExrZyU5cAU&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My full report on the event:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;several-weeks-of-preparation&#34;&gt;Several weeks of preparation&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/recorders-at-phipps-2012/music-scores.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;My music score binder&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We spent something like 16 hours in rehearsal, spread out over almost two months, before we performed. We first sight read a huge amount of music, nearly half of which we ended up deciding not to play this time, and worked on what we chose. I also spent time at home working on some trickier passages in some of the music. It was a pretty big time commitment, and at one point, the week before Thanksgiving, when I was really low on time and energy because of other commitments, I was feeling overwhelmed and suggested to the group that I might bail out this year because I was too tired to make it to one of the rehearsals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then I reconsidered, after realizing that missing one rehearsal was not the end of the world (since everyone else but Annie had missed at least one rehearsal already by then!), and that I didn&amp;rsquo;t have to play all the music, but could take turns with others if needed. (In the end, we each did take turns, since as five, we never needed all five of us when playing three or four part music.) After surviving that one week, I returned to rehearsal and was &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/11/19/preparing-for-december-9-recorder-performance-in-phipps-conservatory/&#34;&gt;re-energized to go through with the plan to perform again this year&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;at-phipps&#34;&gt;At Phipps&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We ended up playing for two hours, which was longer than the hour and a half of last year. We did have a lot more music, so that it took over an hour to run through all our music, before we took a break, and then started from the beginning again, choosing a subset of selections to repeat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As usual, I made various mistakes in performance that I simply never made in practice. I guess we all did, at one point or another. It happens. I am not as anxious about mistakes as I used to be. I&amp;rsquo;m a lot better at &lt;em&gt;recovery&lt;/em&gt; from a mistake than I used to be, and I&amp;rsquo;ve learned over my past year of music that recovery is far more important than never making a mistake. People can hear a little blip here, but as long as you get back on track quickly, without breaking the flow, it&amp;rsquo;s not the biggest deal in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I am a lot more comfortable now with the mechanics of playing recorder, I have been focusing on contributing to ensemble unity of dynamics, articulation, etc. That&amp;rsquo;s the really fun part of playing together, after moving beyond the initial focus on getting the notes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing nice about having an audience, and a space in which to play all out, is that I felt inspired to play as beautifully as I could, getting the harmonies clean and ringing out. I just said that I made more mistakes in performance than in practice; but it is also true that I felt that I never played recorder more beautifully than tonight in some of the pieces. A paradox, perhaps, but one I can live with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sam&amp;rsquo;s wife came along to watch us. That was really nice, because there were times when the audience was otherwise very thin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am truly grateful to have had the opportunity to play in a little recorder ensemble again this year. Life is always kind of hectic at this time of year, but I am already looking forward to playing with the recorder gang again next year!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you to Annie, Helen, Mike, and Sam for having me be part of the holiday-themed music gig!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Preparing for December 9 recorder performance in Phipps Conservatory</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/11/19/preparing-for-december-9-recorder-performance-in-phipps-conservatory/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Nov 2012 23:40:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/11/19/preparing-for-december-9-recorder-performance-in-phipps-conservatory/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; time of year.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/phipps-candlelight.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Phipps Conservatory candlelight evening&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I just came back from another two-hour rehearsal (we&amp;rsquo;ve been having one every week) for an upcoming music gig.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll be performing with five other recorder players in one of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://phipps.conservatory.org/&#34;&gt;Phipps Conservatory&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ldquo;candlelight evenings&amp;rdquo;, Sunday, December 9, from 6 PM to 8 PM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Candlelight Evenings

Nov. 25, 2012 - Jan. 6, 2013

Extended Hours: Open until 10 p.m.

Winter Flower Show is even more enchanting at night - a time when glowing candles light the walkways and live music fills the air.

Experience the magic for yourself as we remain open until 10 p.m. daily from Nov. 23 - Jan. 6.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-this-event-is-special-to-me&#34;&gt;Why this event is special to me&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I reflect on having performed at Phipps last year as part of this recorder group, as the &lt;em&gt;first time&lt;/em&gt; I ever performed music in public since I was a kid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;last-year&#34;&gt;Last year&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year I wrote at length about my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/01/im-going-to-perform-music-much-sooner-than-i-expected-monday/&#34;&gt;anxiety and gratitude&lt;/a&gt; in anticipation of performing music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also wrote about the actual experience, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/05/busy-evening-performing-at-phipps-followed-by-rehearsal-for-another-gig/&#34;&gt;after it happened&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;grateful&#34;&gt;Grateful&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year I was very grateful for the opportunity to play with Annie, Helen, Mike, and Karen of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/PittsburghRecorderSociety&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Recorder Society&lt;/a&gt;. I practiced diligently outside of our rehearsals to try to get my parts down as well as I could, knowing that I was still prone to various slips. I also chose to not participate in some of the pieces that I felt I could not handle yet at my skill level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A year later, I&amp;rsquo;m far better a recorder player and musician. There&amp;rsquo;s no comparison between how I was a year ago and how I am now. Of course, I still have a &lt;em&gt;huge&lt;/em&gt; amount of further improvement as I continue to play music; I plan to continue to make large improvements year after year, decade after decade! My attitude is: &lt;strong&gt;I have only just begun&lt;/strong&gt;, after really just two years of practicing music seriously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year, Sam will join us also in performance, making six of us total. He&amp;rsquo;ll play not only recorder, but also bells and tambourines. This is going to be fun!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2012-12-09&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-12-09)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It quickly turned out that we were only five, because Karen was not going to be available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;anxiety&#34;&gt;Anxiety&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a year of playing a lot of music, both in private and in public, my anxiety has decreased considerably, and each time I perform in public, in particular, I become less self-conscious. What I&amp;rsquo;ve learned is to let go of my ego, and remember that I am playing so that people will enjoy the music: this is not about me, not about my mistakes, not about my brilliance, not about any of that stuff at all. It&amp;rsquo;s about conveying emotion and beauty, however imperfectly, and people sense that and respond to that. With this attitude, the only thing that can truly go wrong is &lt;em&gt;failing to connect to the audience&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, I&amp;rsquo;m &lt;em&gt;orders of magnitude&lt;/em&gt; less &lt;em&gt;shy&lt;/em&gt; now as a musician, and more generally, as a human being, after a year of putting myself out there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I look forward to playing again for a Phipps Conservatory &amp;ldquo;candlelight evening&amp;rdquo;. We have a lot of interesting new selections to play, with almost none of it being standard overdone Christmas carols.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re in Pittsburgh on Sunday, December 9, consider stopping by for a candlelit evening in Phipps Conservatory and hearing us play!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2012-12-09-1&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-12-09)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/09/playing-music-on-recorders-at-a-phipps-conservatory-candlelight-evening/&#34;&gt;A report on the performance&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My first appearance on a music recital program</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/07/28/my-first-appearance-on-a-music-recital-program/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Jul 2012 23:41:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/07/28/my-first-appearance-on-a-music-recital-program/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-ars-recital-summer-2012.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Pittsburgh Recorder Society spring 2012 recital program&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A month and a half ago, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/06/15/preparing-for-my-first-solo-flute-performance-notes-on-perfectionism-and-high-standards/&#34;&gt;I reported on an upcoming music recital I was going to perform in&lt;/a&gt;. In fact, I did perform, on Sunday, June 17, 2012. &lt;em&gt;It was my first appearance in my life on a musical recital program, and my first time solo on modern flute.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The event was an informal spring dinner party/recital at Helen&amp;rsquo;s home for the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.andrew.cmu.edu/user/lukas/pcars/Welcome.html&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh chapter of the American Recorder Society&lt;/a&gt;. (By the way, we also have a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/PittsburghRecorderSociety&#34;&gt;Facebook page&lt;/a&gt; now.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why did I put myself on the spot, by volunteering to play, and what did I choose to play?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-recital-program&#34;&gt;The recital program&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The program had several of us perform a dozen musical selections in a variety combinations (also performing at the end but not listed on the program were Mike and Fred).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(This year, Abby had submitted for the program a piece for Bulgarian tambura, &amp;ldquo;Ihtimansko Horo&amp;rdquo;, and this is on the printed program, but at the last minute, she had problems as a result of restringing her instrument during the week, and ended up not performing, unfortunately.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Myself, I had chosen three musical selections to play:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Doen Daphne D&amp;rsquo;over Schoone Maeght&amp;rdquo; from Jacob Van Eyck&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Der Fluyten Lust-Hof&amp;rdquo;; solo soprano recorder&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lachlann Dubh (Scottish slow air); Baroque flute&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;II. Allegro from C.P.E. Bach&amp;rsquo;s sonata in A minor for solo flute, Wq 132; modern flute&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;background-why-i-played&#34;&gt;Background: why I played&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;last-year-s-party-recital&#34;&gt;Last year&amp;rsquo;s party/recital&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I only started playing recorder and joining the Pittsburgh Recorder Society just over a year ago. After I had only spent a couple of months playing alto recorder (and therefore being at a total beginner level), Helen held her party/recital on June 19, 2011, and invited people to volunteer to play. I was, of course, not ready to prepare anything I felt interesting enough to perform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, it did not even occur to me at the time that I would perform at all any time soon. But in fact, in addition to the prepared performances by several of the people, we also ended up playing something in a large group that we had worked on at the monthly meeting of the Pittsburgh Recorder Society. Even in such casual circumstances, I found myself almost paralyzed with anxiety, sitting there while Abby and other people sat and watched us play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It should be noted that at this point in my life last year, &lt;em&gt;I had not played music in front of a sitting audience in decades&lt;/em&gt;, and never with any seriousness; I was thirteen when I was last stumbling around playing in marching band with no enthusiasm and just an anonymous figure in a crowd:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/lamphere-high-marching-band.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin in Lamphere High School marching band uniform&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I survived playing casually in the group, as Abby watched and took photos that day:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-ars-recital-summer-2011/group.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Pittsburgh Recorder Society group performing at summer 2011 recital&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I have to confess that I was actually shaking and hyperventilating at times, messing up my breathing. It all seems so silly now, but that&amp;rsquo;s how it was. We do what we need to do, eventually become less sensitive, and move on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;setting-a-goal-and-deadline&#34;&gt;Setting a goal and deadline&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t tell anyone that June day last year, but after going home, I made a solemn vow to myself: I was going to spend the entire following year practicing recorder seriously and effectively, in order to be able to prepare something to play at the next party/recital. I had no idea what I was going to play, because the first step was simply to continue improving using some recorder method books, before actually trying to learn a real piece. My goal was to have something substantial to play, to display how much I had learned and improved. (And not shake with anxiety.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-i-chose-the-selections-i-played-this-year&#34;&gt;Why I chose the selections I played this year&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;which-instrument-s&#34;&gt;Which instrument(s)?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that in a single year, I had not only improved at alto recorder, but had also learned soprano recorder. I had also bought a tenor recorder and begun playing it (same fingerings as soprano recorder). And by fall last year, I had also &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/03/my-new-bass-and-sopranino-recorders-and-having-fun/&#34;&gt;bought a bass recorder&lt;/a&gt; and begun playing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Completely unexpectedly, in November I had begun &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/09/taking-up-flute-again-after-decades/&#34;&gt;trying to play modern flute again&lt;/a&gt;. Even more unexpectedly, later I also &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/30/bought-a-baroque-flute/&#34;&gt;decided to take up the Baroque flute&lt;/a&gt;, after having explained &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/17/flute-versus-recorder/&#34;&gt;why I had no plan to try Baroque flute anytime soon&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I also started playing the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/11/learning-another-instrument-the-tin-whistle/&#34;&gt;Irish tin whistle&lt;/a&gt;. It has been quite a year of music for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what instruments and music was I going to play for the recital at Helen&amp;rsquo;s?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-answer-play-three-of-my-instruments&#34;&gt;The answer: play three of my instruments&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided that I would pick three fairly short music selections and play them on three different instruments as appropriate for the music&amp;rsquo;s style and period. Also, to simply my preparation, I looked for music I could play alone rather than, say, requiring a keyboard accompaniment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;late-renaissance-or-early-baroque-1650s&#34;&gt;Late Renaissance or early Baroque (1650s?)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I chose to play a selection from Van Eyck to show off the soprano recorder. Actually, I had played this selection for an audience before (a blog post about that life-changing experience, a &amp;ldquo;Baroque jam session&amp;rdquo;, on Friday, April 27, is still to be written). It was by pure accident that I came across Van Eyck&amp;rsquo;s music to play; I had found the score in the Carnegie Library of Pittsburgh&amp;rsquo;s catalog while looking for any recorder music at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A personal reason I wanted to play this was that I had not heard any interpretation that I really liked, from CDs or YouTube. Therefore, I wanted to fill a hole and try to play the music the way I felt it. This is the fundamental reason I have been playing music rather than just listening to others do it: self-expression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;update-of-2012-10-30&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-10-30)&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is the finally published post about the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/04/27/baroque-jam-session-at-cmu/&#34;&gt;Baroque jam session&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;traditional-scottish-air-1700s&#34;&gt;Traditional Scottish air (1700s?)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Baroque flute seemed appropriate to play this slow song. It could have used accompaniment, but I added it to the program too late to have someone accompany me on harp or mandolin or something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was a little hesitant to play the Baroque flute in public, because I had only really started playing it, and was clearly in need of serious improvement (in fact, it has been my main instrument of focus in the past month), but I thought I might as well put in a two-minute song for variety&amp;rsquo;s sake, and as a baseline since I had already decided that next year, I want to play the Baroque flute again at the 2013 party/recital, and much better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;late-baroque-or-pre-classical-1750s&#34;&gt;Late Baroque or pre-Classical (1750s?)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The CPE Bach sonata I had fallen in love with hearing it by accident on modern flute performed by &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/22/james-galway-made-me-hate-flute/&#34;&gt;Emmanuel Pahud&lt;/a&gt; when I was browsing YouTube one day for solo flute material. After hearing it, I vowed that one day I would play the whole thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I chose what seemed to be the easiest movement to focus on, and practiced it on modern flute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is, of course, a question of which flute is best suited for this music. Given the period, perhaps a simple system keyed wooden flute? But I don&amp;rsquo;t have one, and currently have no intention of getting one or learning to play it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would be possible to play it on a Baroque flute, but much more difficult. When I get better at Baroque flute, I just might consider playing CPE Bach on it, but I feel that the modern flute is not inappropriate for this music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-i-fared&#34;&gt;How I fared&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, I played. I got nervous, I made various errors I did not make in practice, I made errors that I made in practice, but I actually did manage to go up alone and play. I can&amp;rsquo;t pretend that I played very well (in fact, now, over a month later, I could play each of these selections noticeably better than I did), but I did what I could at the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, since Abby&amp;rsquo;s parents came to the party/recital this year, this was also the first time they ever saw me perform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was considerably less nervous than a year ago, but still more nervous than I really need to be. So next year, 2013, I expect to be more seasoned and more performance-ready.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After we all played, we enjoyed the potluck dinner and had a good time. What else could I ask for, an evening of music, food, and friends?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Sorry, I have no photos or videos of any of the activities. I was too busy experiencing rather than spectating, and I don&amp;rsquo;t think anyone actually took any photos or videos.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Pittsburgh Recorder Society spring potluck/recital means a lot to me because it was there last year that I continued to get to know the members, after having just joined, met new people, heard people play, and got the idea that I too could perform, if I worked at improving. I set some goals, was happy that Abby and her parents came along to see me perform, and the experience renewed my commitment to continuing to play and improve in the Pittsburgh Recorder Society group as well as on my own on Baroque flute and modern flute. I have every intention of having even more fun in my upcoming year of music!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why go to concerts by amateur music groups?</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/12/12/why-go-to-concerts-by-amateur-music-groups/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Dec 2011 21:13:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/12/12/why-go-to-concerts-by-amateur-music-groups/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-historical-music-society-concert/program.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Program&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;On Sunday, Abby and I carpooled with Helen and Mike (of the &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/recorder/&#34;&gt;recorder&lt;/a&gt; gang) to Ambridge for a free concert given by the &lt;a href=&#34;http://pghhistoricalmusicsociety.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Historical Music Society&lt;/a&gt; as part of a Christmas-themed event in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.oldeconomyvillage.org/&#34;&gt;Old Economy Village&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That was a long way to drive to see an amateur group give a concert. So why did we pile into the car?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main draw was that there was going to be a performance of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brandenburg_concertos#Brandenburg_Concerto_No._4_in_G_major.2C_BWV_1049&#34;&gt;Bach&amp;rsquo;s Brandenburg concerto 4&lt;/a&gt;, including as soloists the local &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/baroque-flute/&#34;&gt;Baroque flute&lt;/a&gt; players Karen Parsons and Laura Lockard, and violinist and conductor William Lockard. I was very curious to see some Baroque flutists in action, since I had only recently &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/30/bought-a-baroque-flute/&#34;&gt;bought a Baroque flute&lt;/a&gt;. Also, I love Bach&amp;rsquo;s Brandenburg concerto 4 (which I tried to sight read for alto recorder a while ago but is still too hard for me).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The concert featured a variety of early music, including some music specifically written for the original orchestra of historic Old Economy Village back in the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-historical-music-society-concert/orchestra-left.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Left view of orchestra&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-historical-music-society-concert/orchestra-right.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Right view of orchestra&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-historical-music-society-concert/harp-viol-flute.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Harp, viola da gamba, and flute&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below are the soloists in the Brandenburg 4:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-historical-music-society-concert/brandenburg-4.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Soloists for the Brandenburg 4&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;concert-review&#34;&gt;Concert review&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Going to an event like this, my expectations are not very high. In fact, once upon a time, I would not really bother to attend a concert of amateur performers because of high standards programmed into my mind as a result of easy access to any number of current or classic music recordings by professionals. And no, I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t have bothered to attend this particular concert if not for the draw of the Baroque flutists and the personal connections as well as expectations that they would be decent (which they were).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the concert, some of the violins were perpetually out of tune, and there were constant glitches everywhere, whether in the cello, horns, whatever. One has to simply be patient and decide to enjoy the performances as they are. Sometimes the struggle even adds to the excitement. The Brandenburg 4 is not easy, and even at the slow tempos chosen, the imperfections in execution combined with honest enthusiasm made me appreciate even more how special it was that Bach wrote such brilliant and passionate music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;in-praise-of-amateurism-and-imperfection&#34;&gt;In praise of amateurism and imperfection&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am an amateur musician, and not yet a very skilled one, so I recognize my limitations. I can miss notes, create uneven and ragged phrasing, fall apart at high speed, play out of tune, and make all kinds of other errors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think that being out there myself playing now, I am more appreciative than I used to be of other amateurs who love music and put themselves out there also in all their imperfection. And interestingly, I learn from that also. By hearing someone play less than perfectly, I better see that in myself and have a basis for becoming more self-aware and improving. Paradoxically, it is less useful to see someone perform at professional perfection, because that&amp;rsquo;s too far away from where I am. I consider this true whatever the field: music, chess, computer programming. Just being around perfection does not help one&amp;rsquo;s own practice and appreciation. It helps also to be around those of a somewhat higher level. That makes it easier to think, &amp;ldquo;I could be up at that level also, with work&amp;rdquo;, which is much easier to think than, &amp;ldquo;I could be Einstein or Beethoven&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;you-too-can-participate&#34;&gt;You too can participate!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Especially today, when some people are fearful and avoid doing anything that they don&amp;rsquo;t think they will be immediately expert at, I think there is a powerful message to spread. If you love music, please consider joining us amateurs who go around playing it and sharing it and helping each other improve! You don&amp;rsquo;t have to be perfect to enjoy performing. You can sing, or pick up that instrument you haven&amp;rsquo;t touched since childhood, and start up again! The media would have us believe that we are unworthy and that the best we can do is choose not to be an active music maker and instead just buy and consume recordings from the pros. There is certainly nothing wrong with appreciating the pros and supporting their beautiful performances, but we too can dance and sing, with enthusiasm and without shame!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;personal-connections&#34;&gt;Personal connections&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The recorder gang knows Laura Lockard from her involvement with a music workshop held in the summer (which I may attend next summer). They also seemed to know the other solo flutist, Karen Parsons. Also, Abby and I have our own connection to Karen Parsons: it&amp;rsquo;s her farm that we sometimes get &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/28/thankful-for-the-free-range-orange-yolked-eggs&#34;&gt;eggs&lt;/a&gt; from! Very small world, this Pittsburgh or western PA region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;postscript&#34;&gt;Postscript&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you love the Brandenburg 4, check out this amazing melodica rendition of the last movement by James Howard Young, all by himself on multiple tracks:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/_YE3akDmw9Q&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I&#39;m going to perform music much sooner than I expected: Monday</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/12/01/im-going-to-perform-music-much-sooner-than-i-expected-monday/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Dec 2011 23:19:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/12/01/im-going-to-perform-music-much-sooner-than-i-expected-monday/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/s-a-t-recorders.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;My soprano, alto, tenor recorders&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Next week on Monday, I am to join a handful of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.andrew.cmu.edu/user/lukas/pcars/Welcome.html&#34;&gt;local recorder players&lt;/a&gt; in playing holiday-themed music at a &lt;a href=&#34;http://phipps.conservatory.org/exhibits-and-events/featured-event.aspx?eventid=259&#34;&gt;Candlelit Evening at Phipps Conservatory&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will be my first time in public since I was a kid in band, and also my first time performing as part of such a small ensemble. It will be quite a new experience for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;grateful&#34;&gt;Grateful&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel very grateful for the opportunity to contribute to the performance group. I only started playing recorder &lt;em&gt;nine months ago&lt;/em&gt;, and never had any intention to start performing before at least a year of hard work to get sufficiently decent, but they think I&amp;rsquo;ve been improving a lot and invited me to join them for some holiday music that they say is &amp;ldquo;easy&amp;rdquo;. (I have not seen the music yet and will see it for the first time tomorrow evening at rehearsal. I will try to get there early!) It does mean a lot to me that they trust I can do my share playing a part in a quintet or sextet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;anxiety&#34;&gt;Anxiety&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I definitely feel anxiety at the thought of performing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the anxiety has to do with unknowns: I have not even seen the music and sight read it yet!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also have anxieties about playing wrong notes, totally losing my place, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But my anxiety is lessened when I think about how bad it would be if I made various errors. First of all, this is not some kind of formal concert where people are sitting silently watching your every move; we are playing incidental music while people check out the sights in Phipps Conservatory. Second, I trust those I am playing with: I have played with them (in a non-performance setting) for months, and know what kind of supportive people they are, and feel a rapport with them, such that I know they wouldn&amp;rsquo;t scream at me if I made a few mistakes here and there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;even-more-performance-opportunities&#34;&gt;Even more performance opportunities&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;pittsburgh-contras-and-squares-holiday-ball&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Contras and Squares Holiday Ball&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, I&amp;rsquo;m expecting to play in another holiday-oriented gig that Abby is playing in and wants me to join: the annual Holiday Ball of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburghcontra.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Contras and Squares&lt;/a&gt;. I still don&amp;rsquo;t know whether I&amp;rsquo;ll choose to play recorder or flute or whatever other instrument in this (I do have a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/01/run-shadyside-5k-outrunning-mickey-mouse-and-lending-a-trumpet/&#34;&gt;melodica&lt;/a&gt; too)! The first rehearsal is next week and I plan to attend.  I have been assured that this is a pretty informal affair, where musicians have fun contributing as they can and dancers appreciate the live music and get to have their fun also.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(No, I&amp;rsquo;m not going to play at the Holiday Ball the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/30/bought-a-baroque-flute/&#34;&gt;Baroque flute I just got yesterday and started to learn&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;update-of-2011-12-16&#34;&gt;(Update of 2011-12-16)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I reported on &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/16/playing-recorder-and-flute-at-the-holiday-ball/&#34;&gt;playing in the Holiday Ball&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;carnegie-mellon-all-university-orchestra&#34;&gt;Carnegie Mellon All-University Orchestra&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I am considering joining, in January after winter break, the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.andrew.cmu.edu/user/auo/&#34;&gt;Carnegie Mellon All-University Orchestra&lt;/a&gt;, playing (modern) flute. This is a non-audition orchestra, so I don&amp;rsquo;t have to be super good to be a part of it. Nevertheless, I have a month or so to continue improving a lot on the flute before I can judge whether I should join it. If I do, then that will be the first time ever in an orchestra!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being non-audition, the CMU AUO is not a very good orchestra. And I know firsthand, because I went to one of their free concerts many years ago because I knew someone who was in it. But life would be tragic if only super good musicians could play music together, just as life would be tragic if only elite individuals in society were allowed or encouraged to read or write or do arithmetic or cook or garden or run or write computer programs. (That&amp;rsquo;s my social commentary for today; I will expand on this theme in later writings.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;update-of-2012-03-12&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-03-12)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/02/01/joining-an-orchestra-learning-in-the-face-of-terror/&#34;&gt;I did join the CMU AUO in January&lt;/a&gt;, but &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/12/quitting-the-cmu-all-university-orchestra-one-of-the-hardest-decisions-in-my-life/&#34;&gt;quit in March&lt;/a&gt;, one of my hardest but best decisions in my life!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am excited to start performing music in public for this holiday season. I have been quite content to just play music informally without an audience, or playing it for myself, but I have to admit that even for an introvert like me, part of the entire pleasure of playing music at all is that of connecting to the minds, hearts, bodies of people who appreciate what you communicate and express to them. Even when I play alone, I imagine connecting somehow with the universe in some strange way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2012-11-19&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-11-19)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A year later, I reported on &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/11/19/preparing-for-december-9-recorder-performance-in-phipps-conservatory/&#34;&gt;preparing for the 2012 holiday gig at Phipps&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>