<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Phipps Conservatory on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/phipps-conservatory/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Phipps Conservatory on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/phipps-conservatory/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Final rehearsal for my first ukulele gig: and some hard decisions about music in my life</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/04/final-rehearsal-for-my-first-ukulele-gig/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2013 22:15:33 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/04/final-rehearsal-for-my-first-ukulele-gig/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;The night before our Ecofest gig, those of us in the Steel City Ukuleles who are performing in it had one final rehearsal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a very good rehearsal. We&amp;rsquo;re sounding more and more together as an ensemble, ending solidly on each song the way we agreed, and singing more in tune and balance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, Sunny reminded us that we are &lt;em&gt;performing&lt;/em&gt;, and so we should not just grimly look at our music booklets, but instead, when we can, we should look up and smile and engage with the audience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;singing&#34;&gt;Singing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still don&amp;rsquo;t have all the songs down as much as I would like, but by the end of the two-hour rehearsal, I was totally &lt;em&gt;hoarse&lt;/em&gt;. I am ready to sing out strong while simultaneously playing my ukulele.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I just realized that &lt;strong&gt;in the past three months, I have sung more than in the previous forty years of my life combined&lt;/strong&gt;. Wow. And I&amp;rsquo;m loving it. There&amp;rsquo;s nothing like singing, especially singing with others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;performance-is-time-and-energy-consuming&#34;&gt;Performance is time and energy consuming&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I almost didn&amp;rsquo;t make it to the rehearsal. I&amp;rsquo;ve completely exhausted myself this week with work and other activities, and badly need a break. There are times, such as earlier today, when I felt overwhelmed by everything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, yesterday, in discussing my musical plans for the coming months with Abby, I made some decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is my last ukulele gig for the year, for sure. I want to get back to basics and work on my technique and in really mastering some songs, rather than get back on the treadmill of more material for performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, this winter, I am not planning to participate in performing on recorder for the holiday gigs at Phipps Conservatory &amp;ldquo;candlelight evenings&amp;rdquo; that I&amp;rsquo;ve treasured &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/05/busy-evening-performing-at-phipps-followed-by-rehearsal-for-another-gig/&#34;&gt;in 2011&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/09/playing-music-on-recorders-at-a-phipps-conservatory-candlelight-evening/&#34;&gt;in 2012&lt;/a&gt;. That was always a huge amount of work for me. Unless I can participate in significantly reduced capacity, I don&amp;rsquo;t see how I can manage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will probably perform in the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/14/pittsburgh-contras-and-squares-holiday-ball-2012/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Contras and Squares Holiday Ball&lt;/a&gt; again, because it&amp;rsquo;s something I&amp;rsquo;ve been doing with Abby every year, and because after two years of doing it, I know the music, and therefore it will not require much work to participate in (if I want to do some Irish flute and tin whistle solos, of course, then I can add as much extra work for myself that I want, ha).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-is-the-best-use-of-my-limited-time-and-energy-for-music&#34;&gt;What is the best use of my limited time and energy for music?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, there have been announcements and reminders for some time about recorder and ukulele &lt;em&gt;workshops&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;concerts&lt;/em&gt; coming up soon. I have decided not to sign up for any of them, because I really need some rest time on &lt;em&gt;weekends&lt;/em&gt; that I have not been getting; weekends are also the time when I can do more household chores and spend time with Abby.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find that my main enjoyment and improvement in music comes form what I do daily, anyway, rather than what I can possibly do in a long, extended workshop format. I&amp;rsquo;ve always been frustrated that when I attend a one or two day conference or workshop on any subject (computer programming, salsa dance, etc.), I don&amp;rsquo;t actually retain or engage with as much as I would like. There are ways to optimize these experiences, but that requires a certain kind of immediate followup that I don&amp;rsquo;t have time for right now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I will sadly miss the fantastic &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flanders-recorder-quartet.be/en/home/&#34;&gt;Flanders Recorder Quartet&lt;/a&gt; when they come to Pittsburgh in November, and I will miss the workshop Annie has arranged for them to give here for the local recorder community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I am going to miss &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.coolhanduke.com/&#34;&gt;Cool Hand Uke&lt;/a&gt; when he comes to Pittsburgh to give a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/Steel-City-Ukuleles/events/135233932/&#34;&gt;workshop&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/Steel-City-Ukuleles/events/138577782/&#34;&gt;concert&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Life is full of choices, especially for those of us who have many interests, not just one. This week I made some decisions about my involvement with music in October, November, and December.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Playing music on recorders at a Phipps Conservatory &#34;candlelight evening&#34;</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/12/09/playing-music-on-recorders-at-a-phipps-conservatory-candlelight-evening/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Dec 2012 20:46:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/12/09/playing-music-on-recorders-at-a-phipps-conservatory-candlelight-evening/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/recorders-at-phipps-2012/group-photo.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Sam, Franklin, Annie, Helen, Mike&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/recorders-at-phipps-2012/phipps-outside.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Entrance to Phipps&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;After almost two months of weekly music rehearsals, we (Annie, Helen, Mike, Sam, and I) finally performed as planned in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/events/136074939878556/&#34;&gt;Phipps Conservatory&lt;/a&gt;. It was a lot of fun. We came up with a huge batch of music that we hadn&amp;rsquo;t played &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/05/busy-evening-performing-at-phipps-followed-by-rehearsal-for-another-gig/&#34;&gt;at Phipps last year&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As people wandered around in the garden, sometimes they gathered to sit for a while to enjoy our music before moving on. We had our largest audiences earlier rather than later in the evening.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/recorders-at-phipps-2012/audience.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Audience at one point&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A sample photo and video, which I took while Sam, Helen, and Mike were playing in a trio, while Annie and I took a break. (Since there were five of us, we took turns playing either as a quartet or trio or as a quartet with a part doubled.)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/recorders-at-phipps-2012/trio.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Trio&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/1ExrZyU5cAU&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My full report on the event:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;several-weeks-of-preparation&#34;&gt;Several weeks of preparation&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/recorders-at-phipps-2012/music-scores.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;My music score binder&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We spent something like 16 hours in rehearsal, spread out over almost two months, before we performed. We first sight read a huge amount of music, nearly half of which we ended up deciding not to play this time, and worked on what we chose. I also spent time at home working on some trickier passages in some of the music. It was a pretty big time commitment, and at one point, the week before Thanksgiving, when I was really low on time and energy because of other commitments, I was feeling overwhelmed and suggested to the group that I might bail out this year because I was too tired to make it to one of the rehearsals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then I reconsidered, after realizing that missing one rehearsal was not the end of the world (since everyone else but Annie had missed at least one rehearsal already by then!), and that I didn&amp;rsquo;t have to play all the music, but could take turns with others if needed. (In the end, we each did take turns, since as five, we never needed all five of us when playing three or four part music.) After surviving that one week, I returned to rehearsal and was &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/11/19/preparing-for-december-9-recorder-performance-in-phipps-conservatory/&#34;&gt;re-energized to go through with the plan to perform again this year&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;at-phipps&#34;&gt;At Phipps&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We ended up playing for two hours, which was longer than the hour and a half of last year. We did have a lot more music, so that it took over an hour to run through all our music, before we took a break, and then started from the beginning again, choosing a subset of selections to repeat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As usual, I made various mistakes in performance that I simply never made in practice. I guess we all did, at one point or another. It happens. I am not as anxious about mistakes as I used to be. I&amp;rsquo;m a lot better at &lt;em&gt;recovery&lt;/em&gt; from a mistake than I used to be, and I&amp;rsquo;ve learned over my past year of music that recovery is far more important than never making a mistake. People can hear a little blip here, but as long as you get back on track quickly, without breaking the flow, it&amp;rsquo;s not the biggest deal in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I am a lot more comfortable now with the mechanics of playing recorder, I have been focusing on contributing to ensemble unity of dynamics, articulation, etc. That&amp;rsquo;s the really fun part of playing together, after moving beyond the initial focus on getting the notes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing nice about having an audience, and a space in which to play all out, is that I felt inspired to play as beautifully as I could, getting the harmonies clean and ringing out. I just said that I made more mistakes in performance than in practice; but it is also true that I felt that I never played recorder more beautifully than tonight in some of the pieces. A paradox, perhaps, but one I can live with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sam&amp;rsquo;s wife came along to watch us. That was really nice, because there were times when the audience was otherwise very thin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am truly grateful to have had the opportunity to play in a little recorder ensemble again this year. Life is always kind of hectic at this time of year, but I am already looking forward to playing with the recorder gang again next year!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you to Annie, Helen, Mike, and Sam for having me be part of the holiday-themed music gig!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Preparing for December 9 recorder performance in Phipps Conservatory</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/11/19/preparing-for-december-9-recorder-performance-in-phipps-conservatory/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Nov 2012 23:40:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/11/19/preparing-for-december-9-recorder-performance-in-phipps-conservatory/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; time of year.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/phipps-candlelight.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Phipps Conservatory candlelight evening&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I just came back from another two-hour rehearsal (we&amp;rsquo;ve been having one every week) for an upcoming music gig.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll be performing with five other recorder players in one of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://phipps.conservatory.org/&#34;&gt;Phipps Conservatory&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ldquo;candlelight evenings&amp;rdquo;, Sunday, December 9, from 6 PM to 8 PM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Candlelight Evenings

Nov. 25, 2012 - Jan. 6, 2013

Extended Hours: Open until 10 p.m.

Winter Flower Show is even more enchanting at night - a time when glowing candles light the walkways and live music fills the air.

Experience the magic for yourself as we remain open until 10 p.m. daily from Nov. 23 - Jan. 6.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-this-event-is-special-to-me&#34;&gt;Why this event is special to me&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I reflect on having performed at Phipps last year as part of this recorder group, as the &lt;em&gt;first time&lt;/em&gt; I ever performed music in public since I was a kid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;last-year&#34;&gt;Last year&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year I wrote at length about my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/01/im-going-to-perform-music-much-sooner-than-i-expected-monday/&#34;&gt;anxiety and gratitude&lt;/a&gt; in anticipation of performing music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also wrote about the actual experience, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/05/busy-evening-performing-at-phipps-followed-by-rehearsal-for-another-gig/&#34;&gt;after it happened&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;grateful&#34;&gt;Grateful&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year I was very grateful for the opportunity to play with Annie, Helen, Mike, and Karen of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/PittsburghRecorderSociety&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Recorder Society&lt;/a&gt;. I practiced diligently outside of our rehearsals to try to get my parts down as well as I could, knowing that I was still prone to various slips. I also chose to not participate in some of the pieces that I felt I could not handle yet at my skill level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A year later, I&amp;rsquo;m far better a recorder player and musician. There&amp;rsquo;s no comparison between how I was a year ago and how I am now. Of course, I still have a &lt;em&gt;huge&lt;/em&gt; amount of further improvement as I continue to play music; I plan to continue to make large improvements year after year, decade after decade! My attitude is: &lt;strong&gt;I have only just begun&lt;/strong&gt;, after really just two years of practicing music seriously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year, Sam will join us also in performance, making six of us total. He&amp;rsquo;ll play not only recorder, but also bells and tambourines. This is going to be fun!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2012-12-09&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-12-09)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It quickly turned out that we were only five, because Karen was not going to be available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;anxiety&#34;&gt;Anxiety&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a year of playing a lot of music, both in private and in public, my anxiety has decreased considerably, and each time I perform in public, in particular, I become less self-conscious. What I&amp;rsquo;ve learned is to let go of my ego, and remember that I am playing so that people will enjoy the music: this is not about me, not about my mistakes, not about my brilliance, not about any of that stuff at all. It&amp;rsquo;s about conveying emotion and beauty, however imperfectly, and people sense that and respond to that. With this attitude, the only thing that can truly go wrong is &lt;em&gt;failing to connect to the audience&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, I&amp;rsquo;m &lt;em&gt;orders of magnitude&lt;/em&gt; less &lt;em&gt;shy&lt;/em&gt; now as a musician, and more generally, as a human being, after a year of putting myself out there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I look forward to playing again for a Phipps Conservatory &amp;ldquo;candlelight evening&amp;rdquo;. We have a lot of interesting new selections to play, with almost none of it being standard overdone Christmas carols.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re in Pittsburgh on Sunday, December 9, consider stopping by for a candlelit evening in Phipps Conservatory and hearing us play!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2012-12-09-1&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-12-09)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/09/playing-music-on-recorders-at-a-phipps-conservatory-candlelight-evening/&#34;&gt;A report on the performance&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Walking the scenic route through Schenley Park to work</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/06/18/walking-the-scenic-route-through-schenley-park-to-work/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Jun 2012 22:08:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/06/18/walking-the-scenic-route-through-schenley-park-to-work/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Two months ago, I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/04/16/one-week-of-commuting-on-foot-because-of-cmu-carnival/&#34;&gt;spent a whole week&lt;/a&gt; commuting to work at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cmu.edu/&#34;&gt;Carnegie Mellon University&lt;/a&gt; by walking instead of driving, because of the annoyances of parking during Carnival week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because I enjoyed that experience so much, since then, I have walked to/from work at least once a week! Usually my route has included either Forbes Avenue or Schenley Drive, but once I went on other roads through Schenley Park.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last week I started making the trails of Schenley Park part of my walk. This adds probably half a mile to the walk (for a total of just less than 2.5 miles from home to work); time efficiency was why I had not taken this indirect route before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some photos of my walk to CMU last week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;going-barefoot-to-schenley-park&#34;&gt;Going barefoot to Schenley Park&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went barefoot the entire way from home to Schenley Park.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/commute-schenley-park/barefoot.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Barefoot&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Reaching the Schenley Park sign on Hobart Street:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/commute-schenley-park/hobart.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Schenley Park sign on Hobart Street&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;About to enjoy barefoot running on the grass to cross Beacon Street and Bartlett Street to reach the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.examiner.com/article/schenley-park-bartlett-street-playground&#34;&gt;Bartlett Playground&lt;/a&gt;. Note that the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.tour.pitt.edu/tour-080.html&#34;&gt;Cathedral of Learning&lt;/a&gt; is visible in the background.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/commute-schenley-park/beacon-bartlett-grass.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Grass at Hobart Street and Beacon Street&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Arriving at the Bartlett Shelter sign:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/commute-schenley-park/bartlett-shelter.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Sign for Bartlett Shelter&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Right behind the playground is the entrance to the Panther Hollow Trail:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/commute-schenley-park/bartlett-panther-hollow-trail.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Sign for Panther Hollow Trail&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;panther-hollow-trail-to-schenley-park-cafe-and-visitor-center&#34;&gt;Panther Hollow Trail to Schenley Park Cafe and Visitor Center&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This section of the Panther Hollow Trail that I followed all the way to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pittsburghparks.org/schenleyparkcafe&#34;&gt;Schenley Park Cafe and Visitor Center&lt;/a&gt; is the all-downhill section of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~kalp/PGR/&#34;&gt;Pretty Good Race 5K&lt;/a&gt; course that I ran on to &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/06/06/i-celebrated-national-running-day-in-schenley-park-remembering-how-i-began-to-run-13-year-ago/&#34;&gt;celebrate National Running Day on June 6&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My apologies to the barefoot purists, but I immediately found the trail too rough for my bare feet and put on my Vibram FiveFingers KSO shoes:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/commute-schenley-park/vibram-fivefingers-kso.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Vibram FiveFingers KSO shoes on Panther Hollow Trail&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A typical view while running downhill on the Panther Hollow Trail for about 0.9 mile:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/commute-schenley-park/panther-hollow-trail-downhill.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Panther Hollow Trail going downhill&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A sign at the base of the steps that lead up to the Schenley Park Cafe and Visitor Center. I appreciate the renovations in the Pittsburgh parks in the past several years that include such features as the new signs that I think help visitors a lot.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/commute-schenley-park/steps-sign.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Schenley Park sign at base of steps&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Finally out of the trail:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/commute-schenley-park/schenley-park-cafe-and-visitor-center.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Schenley Park Cafe and Visitor Center&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;across-flagstaff-hill-to-my-office-at-carnegie-mellon-university&#34;&gt;Across Flagstaff Hill to my office at Carnegie Mellon University&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A view of Phipps Conservatory as well as the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.tour.pitt.edu/tour-080.html&#34;&gt;Cathedral of Learning&lt;/a&gt; in the distance:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/commute-schenley-park/phipps-cathedral.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Phipps Conservatory&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One is probably not supposed to do so, but I climbed up the stone border (about four feet high) to enter Flagstaff Hill. The more circuitous route to my office would be to take Schenley Drive, which curves around, but it&amp;rsquo;s shorter (and also more scenic and strenuous) to go up the hill directly and steeply, and then descend.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/commute-schenley-park/flagstaff-hill.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Flagstaff Hill&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Taking in the view of the Cathedral of Learning against the lovely blue sky, while running through the grass on Flagstaff Hill:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/commute-schenley-park/cathedral-of-learning-from-flagstaff-hill.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Cathedral of Learning visible from Flagstaff Hill&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My office is barely visible through the trees as I descend:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/commute-schenley-park/office-through-trees.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Office visible through trees&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A convenient path to Frew Street:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/commute-schenley-park/path-to-frew-street.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Path to Frew Street&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At my office building:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/commute-schenley-park/office-building.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;My office building&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a lot of fun on a nice day to walk to work the &amp;ldquo;long&amp;rdquo; way that goes through the trails of Schenley Park and also Flagstaff Hill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am so grateful that Pittsburgh is friendly and stimulating for walking in. And, of course, I am grateful that &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mary_Schenley&#34;&gt;Mary Schenley&lt;/a&gt; donated the land to Pittsburgh way back that became Schenley Park.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Busy evening: performing at Phipps followed by rehearsal for another gig!</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/12/05/busy-evening-performing-at-phipps-followed-by-rehearsal-for-another-gig/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Dec 2011 23:11:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/12/05/busy-evening-performing-at-phipps-followed-by-rehearsal-for-another-gig/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Tonight I left my office and walked across Flagstaff Hill to Phipps Conservatory to &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/01/im-going-to-perform-music-much-sooner-than-i-expected-monday/&#34;&gt;play some music&lt;/a&gt; with four other recorder players.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/recorders-at-phipps/phipps-monday-evening.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Phipps in evening from Flagstaff Hill&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;at-phipps&#34;&gt;At Phipps&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sorry, no photos or videos of me playing, because I didn&amp;rsquo;t want to bother or confuse any Phipps visitors on how to use my camera! I did take a photo of the rest of us playing a piece that I did not participate in:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/recorders-at-phipps/deck-the-halls.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Recorder quartet playing Deck the Halls&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We played for about an hour and a half.  It was a slow Monday night at Phipps, with not many people around. On average there may have been up to ten people standing or sitting around somewhere in sight, in addition to people roaming around. A good number of young children seemed to come and go, sometimes making noises.
That was OK; it was nice to see them around enjoying our playing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was happy to finally have the opportunity to play recorder for an audience, after nine months on the instrument. Since the setting was so informal, and with so few people, I did not feel very anxious, and treated the experience as similar to rehearsal, except for a desire to sound as good as I knew how.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;rehearsal-for-holiday-ball&#34;&gt;Rehearsal for Holiday Ball&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the Phipps gig, I rushed to walk half a mile back to my car to drive over to the first rehearsal for the &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburghcontra.org/&#34;&gt;Holiday Ball&lt;/a&gt;. I arrived an hour and fifteen minutes late, with forty-five minutes left. There, I switched to flute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a large group of people, maybe twenty, with all kinds of instruments: accordions, violins, flutes, clarinet, ukuleles, harmonica, tambura, and others I didn&amp;rsquo;t even see (since I arrived late and sat in the back and side).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had only started looking at the music a day or two ago, and sight read some of it at home with Abby. More than half the music is manageable for me now, but I hadn&amp;rsquo;t realized that the jigs go at breakneck speed. I may need to sit out of those, because I cannot play all the notes on either recorder or flute at this time. In any case, at least I have a concrete challenge to work on for the rest of the week before the second (and final) rehearsal on Sunday!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did try to play recorder for some of the pieces, but I think my intuition was correct: the recorder gets drowned out in the sea of more powerful instruments. But I will bring my recorders to the next rehearsal anyway, in case some of the pieces I missed this time (because of arriving late) would work acoustically and stylistically with a soprano or alto recorder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2011-12-16&#34;&gt;(Update of 2011-12-16)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I reported on playing at the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/16/playing-recorder-and-flute-at-the-holiday-ball/&#34;&gt;Holiday Ball&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m excited to have played recorder at Phipps, and I&amp;rsquo;m excited about the prospect of another new musical experience: playing for dancers at the upcoming Holiday Ball. I remember many times in the past decade wondering about being on the other side of the dance floor, since I used to do a lot of dancing (ballroom, swing, tango, salsa).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2012-05-14&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-05-14)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Half a year later, I did &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/05/14/playing-french-music-for-first-time-and-dancing-blues-for-first-time/&#34;&gt;start playing music regularly for dancers&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2012-12-09&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-12-09)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/09/playing-music-on-recorders-at-a-phipps-conservatory-candlelight-evening/&#34;&gt;A report on performing again at Phipps the following year, 2012&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I&#39;m going to perform music much sooner than I expected: Monday</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/12/01/im-going-to-perform-music-much-sooner-than-i-expected-monday/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Dec 2011 23:19:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/12/01/im-going-to-perform-music-much-sooner-than-i-expected-monday/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/s-a-t-recorders.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;My soprano, alto, tenor recorders&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Next week on Monday, I am to join a handful of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.andrew.cmu.edu/user/lukas/pcars/Welcome.html&#34;&gt;local recorder players&lt;/a&gt; in playing holiday-themed music at a &lt;a href=&#34;http://phipps.conservatory.org/exhibits-and-events/featured-event.aspx?eventid=259&#34;&gt;Candlelit Evening at Phipps Conservatory&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will be my first time in public since I was a kid in band, and also my first time performing as part of such a small ensemble. It will be quite a new experience for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;grateful&#34;&gt;Grateful&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel very grateful for the opportunity to contribute to the performance group. I only started playing recorder &lt;em&gt;nine months ago&lt;/em&gt;, and never had any intention to start performing before at least a year of hard work to get sufficiently decent, but they think I&amp;rsquo;ve been improving a lot and invited me to join them for some holiday music that they say is &amp;ldquo;easy&amp;rdquo;. (I have not seen the music yet and will see it for the first time tomorrow evening at rehearsal. I will try to get there early!) It does mean a lot to me that they trust I can do my share playing a part in a quintet or sextet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;anxiety&#34;&gt;Anxiety&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I definitely feel anxiety at the thought of performing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the anxiety has to do with unknowns: I have not even seen the music and sight read it yet!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also have anxieties about playing wrong notes, totally losing my place, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But my anxiety is lessened when I think about how bad it would be if I made various errors. First of all, this is not some kind of formal concert where people are sitting silently watching your every move; we are playing incidental music while people check out the sights in Phipps Conservatory. Second, I trust those I am playing with: I have played with them (in a non-performance setting) for months, and know what kind of supportive people they are, and feel a rapport with them, such that I know they wouldn&amp;rsquo;t scream at me if I made a few mistakes here and there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;even-more-performance-opportunities&#34;&gt;Even more performance opportunities&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;pittsburgh-contras-and-squares-holiday-ball&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Contras and Squares Holiday Ball&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, I&amp;rsquo;m expecting to play in another holiday-oriented gig that Abby is playing in and wants me to join: the annual Holiday Ball of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburghcontra.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Contras and Squares&lt;/a&gt;. I still don&amp;rsquo;t know whether I&amp;rsquo;ll choose to play recorder or flute or whatever other instrument in this (I do have a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/01/run-shadyside-5k-outrunning-mickey-mouse-and-lending-a-trumpet/&#34;&gt;melodica&lt;/a&gt; too)! The first rehearsal is next week and I plan to attend.  I have been assured that this is a pretty informal affair, where musicians have fun contributing as they can and dancers appreciate the live music and get to have their fun also.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(No, I&amp;rsquo;m not going to play at the Holiday Ball the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/30/bought-a-baroque-flute/&#34;&gt;Baroque flute I just got yesterday and started to learn&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;update-of-2011-12-16&#34;&gt;(Update of 2011-12-16)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I reported on &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/16/playing-recorder-and-flute-at-the-holiday-ball/&#34;&gt;playing in the Holiday Ball&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;carnegie-mellon-all-university-orchestra&#34;&gt;Carnegie Mellon All-University Orchestra&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I am considering joining, in January after winter break, the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.andrew.cmu.edu/user/auo/&#34;&gt;Carnegie Mellon All-University Orchestra&lt;/a&gt;, playing (modern) flute. This is a non-audition orchestra, so I don&amp;rsquo;t have to be super good to be a part of it. Nevertheless, I have a month or so to continue improving a lot on the flute before I can judge whether I should join it. If I do, then that will be the first time ever in an orchestra!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being non-audition, the CMU AUO is not a very good orchestra. And I know firsthand, because I went to one of their free concerts many years ago because I knew someone who was in it. But life would be tragic if only super good musicians could play music together, just as life would be tragic if only elite individuals in society were allowed or encouraged to read or write or do arithmetic or cook or garden or run or write computer programs. (That&amp;rsquo;s my social commentary for today; I will expand on this theme in later writings.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;update-of-2012-03-12&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-03-12)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/02/01/joining-an-orchestra-learning-in-the-face-of-terror/&#34;&gt;I did join the CMU AUO in January&lt;/a&gt;, but &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/12/quitting-the-cmu-all-university-orchestra-one-of-the-hardest-decisions-in-my-life/&#34;&gt;quit in March&lt;/a&gt;, one of my hardest but best decisions in my life!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am excited to start performing music in public for this holiday season. I have been quite content to just play music informally without an audience, or playing it for myself, but I have to admit that even for an introvert like me, part of the entire pleasure of playing music at all is that of connecting to the minds, hearts, bodies of people who appreciate what you communicate and express to them. Even when I play alone, I imagine connecting somehow with the universe in some strange way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2012-11-19&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-11-19)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A year later, I reported on &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/11/19/preparing-for-december-9-recorder-performance-in-phipps-conservatory/&#34;&gt;preparing for the 2012 holiday gig at Phipps&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>