<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>English Muffins on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/english-muffins/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in English Muffins on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/english-muffins/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Thoughts on learning that I have eaten English muffins wrong all my life</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/06/28/thoughts-on-learning-that-i-have-eaten-english-muffins-wrong-all-my-life/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Jun 2015 18:25:34 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/06/28/thoughts-on-learning-that-i-have-eaten-english-muffins-wrong-all-my-life/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today, I found out I had been eating
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/English_muffin&#34;&gt;English muffins&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;em&gt;wrong&lt;/em&gt; my whole life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-story&#34;&gt;The story&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This morning, while at breakfast in a hotel before Abby and I were
checking out before returning home, I suddenly decided I might as well
change things up and eat my egg and sausage patties inside the halves
of an English muffin (yesterday I had eaten them alone, and an
uninspiring crappy plain bagel on the side).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I was about to bite into my sandwich, Abby interrupted me and said,
&amp;ldquo;You need to toast the English muffin.&amp;rdquo; I said, &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;ve never toasted an
English muffin.&amp;rdquo; She made a face of disgust and said, &amp;ldquo;Eww, that&amp;rsquo;s
&lt;em&gt;wrong&lt;/em&gt;, English muffins are designed to be eaten toasted! They are
disgusting raw.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I disputed that there was a &amp;ldquo;right&amp;rdquo; way to eat English muffins, but
allowed her to toast the muffin halves for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The resulting sandwich tasted pretty good. I then realized that I had
been eating English muffins wrong my entire life. How could this be?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-breakfast-growing-up-in-america&#34;&gt;My breakfast growing up in America&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have to understand that I spent the first couple of years of my
remembered childhood, as the first child of immigrant parents to
America, eating a breakfast that often consisted of
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Congee&#34;&gt;congee&lt;/a&gt; (rice porridge) with
toppings (I particularly liked pickled cucumbers and
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rousong&#34;&gt;rousong&lt;/a&gt;, a dried pork product).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bread was not part of my usual diet until I went to Kindergarten in
New York City, where I ate free lunches and was introduced to such
bizarre concepts as the grilled
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cheese_sandwich&#34;&gt;cheese sandwich&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did increasingly eat &amp;ldquo;American&amp;rdquo; foods as I grew up, but still, I was
never introduced to the full variety of breakfast foods for a long
time. It wasn&amp;rsquo;t until I was over ten years old, for example, that I
took the initiative and convinced my mother that we should try out
pancakes and waffles and cinnamon toast. Jellies, jams, syrup, butter
really came into my life then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But English muffins were somehow left out. My mother bought them but
apparently &lt;em&gt;we ate them wrong&lt;/em&gt;. We didn&amp;rsquo;t toast them. And because &lt;em&gt;they
didn&amp;rsquo;t taste so good&lt;/em&gt; to me, I never really ate them again. For the
next decades of my life, given a choice, I never took an English
muffin if I could instead eat a donut, cupcake, bagel, or ordinary
sliced bread. I had come to associate English muffins with &amp;ldquo;not
tasty&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;lessons-learned-from-my-conversion-today&#34;&gt;Lessons learned from my conversion today&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, this morning I learned that toasted English muffins are actually
pretty good. They have a particular texture, form factor, aroma,
crispness when toasted. Although I currently try to limit my intake of
bread in general, in the future if I am confronted with the usual free
hotel breakfast, I will definitely choose English muffins!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After we returned home, I actually looked online to find out the
&amp;ldquo;truth&amp;rdquo; about English muffins. Well, it turns out that a lot of people
online do note that raw English muffins don&amp;rsquo;t taste so good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What broader lessons have I learned?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is possible for an immigrant to live in a country for decades and
yet not fully understand what a native does, simply because of early
choices or misleading experiences in some aspect of life.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Just because something tastes bad in one form doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean it has to
taste bad in &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; its possible forms (I am always learning this; I only
recently learned to &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/03/21/time-to-taste-the-world-thoughts-on-expanding-my-food-tastes-as-an-adult&#34;&gt;enjoy Brussels sprouts&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Although there is no such thing, objectively, as preparing or eating
something the &amp;ldquo;wrong&amp;rdquo; way, you might find some ways (including
generally accepted traditional practices) to have merit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;People don&amp;rsquo;t always tell you when you&amp;rsquo;re doing something
&amp;ldquo;wrong&amp;rdquo;. Some might just be polite and remain silent. Others might
let the oddity slip because they think you are just being weird and
truly enjoy raw English muffins. Don&amp;rsquo;t make the assumption that
people are doing what they really like; they could just be operating
out of habit and not knowing or having explored an alternative.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed learning that English muffins are actually edible after
all. I don&amp;rsquo;t really expect to ever eat a raw English muffin again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Has anyone ever pointed out something to you that you weren&amp;rsquo;t aware
  of even though maybe you &amp;ldquo;should&amp;rdquo; have known? Did you feel
  embarrassed or argue, or did you try out the new suggestion? When
  you see someone doing something weird, do you ever step in and offer
  a suggestion, or do you prefer to be polite and not be nosy?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;postscript&#34;&gt;Postscript&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This evening when discussing the breakfast incident with Abby, somehow
the subject of bagels came up and she said something about toasting
bagels, and I recoiled in horror, because I was pretty sure that
&lt;em&gt;bagels are not supposed to be toasted&lt;/em&gt;. Again, I had to consult the
Internet to find out the &amp;ldquo;truth&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you might expect, the truth is that I grew up with bagels living in
New York City and the East Coast in general, before moving to the
Midwest. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.thedailymeal.com/real-new-yorkers-dont-toast-their-bagels&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Real New Yorkers don&amp;rsquo;t toast their bagels&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;.
If you have access to a fresh, good bagel, it&amp;rsquo;s pretty wrong to toast
it, right? Well, as the article points out, there are differing
opinions, admittedly, and nobody argues that a crappy stale bagel or a
frozen one shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be toasted. Still, out of sheer habit, I have
never toasted a bagel, even if it might deserve toasting. Interesting,
huh? It&amp;rsquo;s just a habit. I see the logic of reviving a bagel as
needed. So I will consider toasting crappy bagels in the future if
they need that treatment.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>