<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Chess on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/chess/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Chess on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/chess/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>The powerful e5 Pawn break against the Benoni: using it as White, neutralizing it as Black</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2016/07/29/the-powerful-e5-pawn-break-against-the-benoni-using-it-as-white-neutralizing-it-as-black/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Jul 2016 07:50:37 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2016/07/29/the-powerful-e5-pawn-break-against-the-benoni-using-it-as-white-neutralizing-it-as-black/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been very busy coaching chess and therefore haven&amp;rsquo;t published any chess writing lately, but I was inspired by a discussion about a chess position with Isaac, the creator of &lt;a href=&#34;https://chesssummit.com/&#34;&gt;Chess Summit&lt;/a&gt;, to write a guest &lt;a href=&#34;https://chesssummit.com/2016/07/28/the-powerful-e5-pawn-break-against-the-benoni-using-it-as-white-neutralizing-it-as-black/&#34;&gt;blog post there&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you love chess and want to follow the journeys of chess players who are working hard to improve their game and share their stories along the way, check out the Chess Summit site!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On finally achieving the US National Master chess title at age 45: part 1</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2016/01/22/on-finally-achieving-the-us-national-master-chess-title-at-age-45-part-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Jan 2016 20:49:11 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2016/01/22/on-finally-achieving-the-us-national-master-chess-title-at-age-45-part-1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&#34;true&#34;  href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/franklinmingchen/24441379882/in/album-72157661509446593/&#34; title=&#34;National Master certificate&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://c3.staticflickr.com/2/1560/24441379882_36a8f817c7.jpg&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; height=&#34;375&#34; alt=&#34;National Master certificate&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async src=&#34;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On December 18, 2015, I finally achieved the
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chess_title#Master&#34;&gt;United States National Master&lt;/a&gt;
chess title, at the relatively late age of 45 (I don&amp;rsquo;t have
statistics, but I suspect the vast majority of chess players who reach
National Master do so in their teens and twenties). I plan to
eventually write about how I significantly improved my chess when I
returned after a twenty-year break to start playing again ten years
ago at age 35, and how I now teach and coach chess based on my
experience in self-improvement. I will also write more about how I
continue to work on self-improvement outside of chess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For now, below is an interview that was published in the June 2016
issue of the
&lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburghcc.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Chess Club&lt;/a&gt; publication, &amp;ldquo;En
Passant&amp;rdquo;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&#34;true&#34;  href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/franklinmingchen/28474055921&#34; title=&#34;Untitled&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://c2.staticflickr.com/9/8194/28474055921_0e62aa5380.jpg&#34; width=&#34;375&#34; height=&#34;500&#34; alt=&#34;Untitled&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async src=&#34;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;when-did-you-learn-chess-how-old-were-you-who-taught-you-what-did-you-think-or-feel-during-that-first-experience&#34;&gt;When did you learn chess? How old were you? Who taught you? What did you think or feel during that first experience?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t actually remember a moment in my life when I didn&amp;rsquo;t know the
basic rules of chess!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s what I mean: my first life memories are from shortly before I
was 3 years old (I remember celebrating my 3rd birthday), when I was
already playing chess with my father. The story is that when I was 2
years old, the 1972 Fischer-Spassky match was happening and the result
was that during the summer of 1972, my father and his grad school
classmates decided to teach themselves chess. According to him, at
some point I watched and deduced some of the movements, and he noticed
my interest. I don&amp;rsquo;t remember any of that, but I remember that at some
point he bought &amp;ldquo;Bobby Fischer Teaches Chess&amp;rdquo; (he may still have this
in his library) and he led me through it after he had finished it
himself. So that was my first chess book, and we did it before I was 4
years old, because life changed for me after my sister was born before
I turned 4, and my father no longer had much attention for me for a
while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I remember is simply the joy of seeing the geometry of the
different piece movements fitting together. I was also extremely
particular about setting up the board: I always wanted my Knights to
face each other, and I still am, and at the beginning of every game,
you will note that I always adjust my Knights accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-was-the-next-big-step-in-your-chess-life-as-a-child&#34;&gt;What was the next big step in your chess life as a child?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After my father finished graduate school, he was very busy finding
jobs, etc., and chess was put aside for a while, but finding chess
sets lying around in school led me to find in the libraries some chess
books written for children, and I enjoyed them very much. When I was
7, he found his first stable job in Morristown, New Jersey, so we
moved yet again. We discovered that the Morris County Free Library had
a huge chess book collection, and we started reading through it
together. In the process, we finally realized that we had gotten some
of the rules wrong when playing with each other at home!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I must have read through 30 or 40 chess books from that library
between age 7 and 9 before we moved again. During that time, I had
nobody to play with, because the one time in school recess I tried to
play with a classmate who claimed he knew how to play, he captured my
King after I overlooked a pin, and claimed victory, and would not
listen to me when I said I could not make an illegal make and Kings
cannot be captured! I did have one &lt;a href=&#34;http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/05/30/life-lessons-i-learned-from-a-lunch-recess-chess-game-at-age-seven/&#34;&gt;interesting experience with a chess
computer&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also started teaching my younger sister chess during this time
period (at around age 4), because I had no one else to play with other
than my father. And I lost every single game I played with my father,
because he would not let me win; he would give me chances when I was
losing, but &lt;a href=&#34;http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/06/03/why-i-am-grateful-that-my-father-never-let-me-win-a-chess-game-against-him/&#34;&gt;never let me actually win&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-did-you-get-into-playing-in-chess-tournaments&#34;&gt;How did you get into playing in chess tournaments?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, my father had to learn that there was such a thing as chess
tournaments for amateurs. This happened when he accidentally
discovered a chess club.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shortly before I turned 10, my parents and my sister and I were at the
local community center (for a new job, my father had moved the family
again, to Madison Heights, Michigan) when my father heard strange
noises in the basement and wondered what was going on. He went down
and came back up all excited. My sister and I went back down with him,
and I still remember the thick cigar smoke and the men loudly banging
on ticking chess clocks while swearing and trash-talking during
blitz. My father and I joined the club and began playing in casual
blitz as well as in unrated club tournaments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone said we should also join the Michigan Chess Association and
the US Chess Federation and play in official rated tournaments. My
father said &amp;ldquo;wait, we just paid for one membership and you want us to
pay for two others already?&amp;ldquo;, but signed us up for MCA membership,
so that we could get the newsletter and stay informed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;when-was-your-first-tournament-do-you-remember-what-you-felt-when-you-won-your-first-official-game&#34;&gt;When was your first tournament? Do you remember what you felt when you won your first official game?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By summer, everyone was excited about the upcoming annual Michigan
Open over Labor Day weekend, so we went, signed up with USCF, and
played in our first USCF rated tournament, the under-1800 Reserve
Section of the 1980 Michigan Open. I lost my first round game, but
in the second round, I won a very long, 88-move game as White (I
still have the original scoresheet and just looked over the game
again) against a 1400-rated opponent. My opponent made the final
blunder in an endgame, allowing me to trade into a King and Pawn
ending I knew was a win. I took the opposition, won the Pawn Queening
race, and knew how to win with a Queen against Knight Pawn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It felt great to bounce back so quickly from a first round loss to
winning my first tournament game. I ended up scoring 3.&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;7&lt;/sub&gt;.0 and
winning a 2nd place Unrated trophy, while my father won the 1st
place Unrated trophy. I achieved my first provisional rating of
1591, while his was 1574, lower than mine despite his higher score.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My father was so excited by our success that we continued playing
in tournaments for a while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-happened-after-your-first-tournament&#34;&gt;What happened after your first tournament?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After our first tournament, my father and I were excited to continue
playing. He decided to continue playing in the Reserve Section while I
never played in the Reserve Section again after the first tournament,
because unlike him, I was not in it for the prizes but for the
challenge of playing against stronger opponents and getting better
myself. I did well in the Open Section of my second tournament three
months after my first, and my rating went up from 1591 to 1659, so
that was exciting. I won no prize, while my father got what he wanted
and won prizes for a fine performance in the Reserve Section. After
this second tournament, everyone was taking note of my progress, and
said I had talent. I didn&amp;rsquo;t think so highly of myself, because by
then, I had met Ben Finegold, who was a year younger than me, but
already much better than me in the tournament scene.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In January 1981, my father applied for a chess scholarship from the
American Chess Foundation in order for fund some chess instruction for
me, and we got funding for ten lessons in May from the winner of
the 1980 Michigan Open, Master David Whitehouse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before the lessons even began, I had continued to do well in
tournaments, beat my first Expert, and gotten my rating up to 1741.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I very much enjoyed the lessons, and still remember a great deal from
them in retrospect. Mr. Whitehouse showed me some endgames, openings,
and illustrative games of his, but most of all, gave me a tremendously
useful book list, and I would even today recommend the study of many
of the classics that he listed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-was-your-first-setback&#34;&gt;What was your first setback?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, despite the ten weeks of instruction, it turned out
that I was stuck at a plateau for an entire year of tournament play,
not having gone higher than 1765. In fact, during my second year of
tournament play (age 11), I had my first loss against a lower-rated
opponent, my first draw against a lower-rated opponent, and my first
loss to an unrated opponent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, my father himself had topped out at a rating of around
1774, I had finally beaten him at home (after which he never played a
game of chess again for another 20 years), family life was in disarray
as he looked for another job, and I was becoming a teenager and not
getting along with my parents or my teachers in school. So my father
let our USCF memberships expire, in July 1982, and my parents worried
that I was too obsessed with chess (my mother never approved of it in
the first place) and took away my chess set. I didn&amp;rsquo;t protest too
much, because I had my own life problems at the time, plus had no idea
how to continue to improve in chess. So that&amp;rsquo;s how I retired from
chess at age 12. Life was in disarray for everyone, and I almost
failed my classes in the fall during the 7th grade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;when-did-you-return-to-chess-after-this-setback&#34;&gt;When did you return to chess after this setback?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within the following year, some things had improved: my father had a
new job lined up, and he renewed my lapsed USCF membership and gave me
my chess set back. It was clear, though, that chess was only to be a
hobby and he would not be supporting me in any substantial way. In
1983-1985, I concluded my chess career of my youth by playing two
tournaments each of those years (during which my father had one more
job change, the final one of his career, and we had moved a couple
more times).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through introspection, I did make a conscious effort to improve my
play and broke through my 1700 plateau quickly during my return to
chess at age 13, having missed age 12. I got up to 2050 when I was
15. All the while, though, I felt more and more that I still didn&amp;rsquo;t
really understand chess, and Ben Finegold had long since made Master,
and would drop out of high school to move to Europe for a professional
chess career. I did still think enough about chess that I wrote my
college application on how chess is simultaneously an art, sport, and
science, and informed how I think about human endeavors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then chess ended for me for 20 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;as-your-rating-was-rising-say-after-it-past-1200-1500-1800-what-types-of-thoughts-did-you-have-did-you-think-you-would-one-day-become-a-chess-master-or-grandmaster-can-you-share-the-emotions-of-reaching-higher-ratings&#34;&gt;As your rating was rising, say after it past 1200, 1500, 1800, what types of thoughts did you have? Did you think you would one day become a Chess Master or Grandmaster? Can you share the emotions of reaching higher ratings?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my youth, I never believed I was going to become a Master, and I
never acted as though I wanted to give it a try.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I liked to play, hoped I was improving, but didn&amp;rsquo;t have the internal
drive or family support to do anything really serious with chess. I
didn&amp;rsquo;t really play that much chess as a youth: in 1980-1985, I played
16 rated tournaments, for a total of 83 rated games that took me from
unrated to an initial rating of 1591 to a peak rating of 2050. Compare
with my adult tournament career so far from 2005-2015, which consisted
of 436 rated games: the vast majority of my chess playing has occurred
in my adulthood, with rating range from 2057 up finally to 2201.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My plateau at age 11, during which I received no encouragement or
support from anyone, made me pessimistic even when I recovered from
it. To be honest, during the entire time I played from 1983-1985, I
was afraid to have any serious expectations or goals. My own lack of
confidence combined with my fear of family disapproval caused me to
actually be relieved when I no longer had time for chess. In fact, I
considered myself rather lucky to have made it to past 2000 and had a
lingering fear that if I continued, I would just lose that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-made-you-return-to-chess-after-a-20-year-absence&#34;&gt;What made you return to chess after a 20 year absence?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did play a little bit of casual chess in my freshman year in
college, but then never played a game again for 17 years, nor did I
follow any chess world news during that time. Chess was dead to me
during those years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in the early 2000s, a friend mentioned that there were strong free
chess engines that were worth trying out. I was skeptical at first,
because in my youth I could beat chess computers. But I started
playing with some engines to see how much they had improved since my
childhood. They were still not so strong, but were definitely much
stronger!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I became very interested in whether the engines were strong enough to
resolve some analytical questions I had about complicated games in my
childhood in which I didn&amp;rsquo;t know if I played something correctly (in
particular, some sacrifices). So my renewed interest in chess was not
as a competitor but as an analyst. I started reading chess books
again, and rejoining USCF, although not yet playing. In particular,
around 2003, my life was changed when a chess book showed up in the
public library, John Watson&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Chess Strategy in Action&amp;rdquo;. I checked it
out and it completely altered my perception of and understanding of
chess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, at this point in my life in my mid-30s, I was noticing
small but clear signs of physical and mental decline (I had peaked in
my 5K race speed) and thought to myself that I had unfinished business
in my life, dreams I gave up or did not allow myself in childhood,
that I should return to soon if I wanted to accomplish them at all
before it was too late. One of those dreams was to actually see how
well I can play chess if I committed to improvement, since I believed
deep in my heart that I had stopped before reaching my full potential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I discovered the existence of the Pittsburgh Chess Club in 2004,
played a game of chess with my father while visiting him for
Christmas, our first game in over 20 years, and in 2005, started
playing in tournaments again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-did-you-do-to-move-your-rating-up-did-you-study-a-lot-play-a-lot-what-types-of-exercises-did-you-do-did-you-have-chess-boards-set-up-at-places-in-the-house-was-there-anything-unique-you-could-share-that-readers-will-enjoy-knowing-or-reading&#34;&gt;What did you do to move your rating up? Did you study a lot? play a lot? What types of exercises did you do? Did you have chess boards set up at places in the house? Was there anything unique you could share that readers will enjoy knowing or reading?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my youth, there were no chess engines or computers really worth
using, so progress was much harder for someone like me who was on his
own and did not have access to strong coaches (other than the ten free
lessons I received at age 11). So, I initially just learned from
playing blitz often at the club, playing in tournaments and reading
books and magazines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To break my 1700 plateau, I studied specific opening systems that had
clear strategic goals for the middlegame. That made a huge difference
moving forward because I was no longer playing just randomly, but with
purpose. That worked to get me up to 2000+, but it was at that point
when I realized that I was holding myself back by playing only these
weird offbeat openings that I had studied. I had to go back to the
classics in order to rebuild myself to go beyond 2000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had another plateau during my entire first year back to chess in
adulthood, I was stuck at a plateau of the low 2000s and despaired of
ever improving beyond my childhood level. I realized that I had to
rebuild my chess understanding from scratch. I had never studied chess
systematically before, had a really spotty understanding of every
aspect of the game, from openings to middlegames to endgames. So in my
second year back, in 2006, I started rebuilding myself, gradually
transforming how I play. That paid off as I finally cracked 2100 and
then 2150, during 2006 and 2007. It was not until I passed 2100 that
for the first time in my life, I decided to set myself a goal of
making Master!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The single most helpful tool to me in recent years has been analyzing
my own games in detail with use of strong chess engines. I would say
this is more important than anything else. Being confronted with
reliable evidence of ideas or tactics that you missed (or your
opponent missed) must be the single most useful tool for improvement
available today that wasn&amp;rsquo;t available in the pre-computer era. In
particular, computers make it easy to try &amp;ldquo;what if&amp;rdquo; by experimenting
with different continuations, setups, and see how they measure up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;were-there-times-you-were-disappointed-with-yourself-and-thought-about-quitting-were-there-other-factors-like-friend-family-girlfriend-who-led-you-or-tried-to-dissuade-you-to-continue-playing-chess-is-there-any-story-you-would-like-to-share-on-this-topic&#34;&gt;Were there times you were disappointed with yourself and thought about quitting? Were there other factors like friend, family, girlfriend who led you or tried to dissuade you to continue playing chess? Is there any story you would like to share on this topic?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have often been disappointed in my chess play, but interestingly,
never seriously thought about quitting except in one situation: I only
thought about quitting once I came close to reaching Master and kept
failing, which coincided chronologically with my meeting a young
woman.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every loss or draw that set me back as I approached 2200 had a
tendency of making me feel like I didn&amp;rsquo;t have what it takes. And
starting to date again in 2007 definitely began to take a toll on my
chess, both because Abby actively opposed my chess activities at the
time and because of my whole schedule and routine was disrupted,
making tournament play difficult logistically. By the time we got
married in 2009, I had basically quit chess, and I thought for good,
and not willingly but as a concession. I periodically tried to come
back and play, but always less well than I was capable, because of
being rusty, unsupported, and tired. It wasn&amp;rsquo;t until the second half
of 2015 that I was ready to try again to play the best I could, this
time finally with complete emotional support from Abby, who had
finally come to understand how much chess meant to me. I also canceled
a lot of my usual activities in the second half of 2015 in order to
focus my energy outside of work on chess, and all this paid off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-is-the-single-most-important-factor-a-chess-player-must-consider-to-move-up-his-her-rating&#34;&gt;What is the single, most important factor a chess player must consider to move up his/her rating?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We all hit a plateau at some point, at which we are apparently making
the same kinds of errors that stronger players are not making, so
somehow we have to change the kinds of errors that we make.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the most powerful tool available is analysis of your own
games. Each game you play has the fingerprints of your personal
weaknesses all over it. Using a chess engine, and ideally a strong
human guide who can explain concepts and variations that lie behind
the engine&amp;rsquo;s numerical evaluations, you can learn to gradually remove
errors. For example, if you lost an otherwise good game only because
of one misconception during an endgame, avoiding that single error in
the future could pay off in any number of similar situations. Or if
you misplayed an opening, rebuilding your thought process that led to
a strategic misunderstanding can help in all future games using that
opening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;have-you-been-close-to-2200-several-times-and-then-fell-therefore-postponing-the-master-level-can-you-give-details-of-how-you-felt&#34;&gt;Have you been close to 2200 several times and then fell? (therefore postponing the Master level)? Can you give details of how you felt?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, I have been close several times! In fact, a couple of times I had
2200 locked up, in the sense that if I had withdrawn from a tournament
in progress, I would have guaranteed going over 2200 based on the wins
I had already racked up in the tournament.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first time was in the 2007 PA State Action Championship. I went in
at 2171 and had won the first three rounds. In the fourth round, I had
a totally won game against a Master and nerves got to me and I fell
apart and lost. In the final round, I had a totally won game against
an 1800 and fell apart and lost. This was my first experience of
completely choking under the pressure of knowing I was very close to
2200.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then in January 2008, I had a rating of 2197 from a Pittsburgh Chess
League round. The thing you have to understand is that in
January-February, I was simultaneously playing in the PCC Championship
held on Tuesday nights, and had won my first three rounds by February,
which meant that if I had withdrawn, I would have secured far more
than the 3 rating points necessary to go over 2200. But I had never
withdrawn from a tournament in my life, and didn&amp;rsquo;t want to achieve
Master through calculated cowardice. So I played on. But I choked, and
proceeded to draw the fourth game and lose the fifth. I continued to
play worse as I got engaged to be married, and quit chess the year of
my marriage in 2009.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I periodically came back in 2010-2012 but just played worse and worse,
unforced errors. In 2013, I started recovering, and in 2014, I again
almost made Master. At 2195, I choked, losing a won game against a
much lower-rated player while a Rook up! All I needed was to win that
game to make Master. And I kept on choking in tournaments after that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fall of 2015, I more or less stopped choking. I still played badly
sometimes, but I distinguish between poor quality of play and just
plain choking. How did I stop choking? I stopped paying attention to
my rating. In fact, in my final tournament games of 2015 that led me
to go over 2200, I did not do any calculations to determine whether I
would or would not go over. I knew it could be close, but did not want
to calculate. I tried to focus on my games and nothing else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m still proud that I made Master without the trick of withdrawing
from any tournaments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;can-you-discuss-which-is-more-important-for-chess-improvement-studying-the-opening-middlegame-or-endgame-explain-why&#34;&gt;Can you discuss which is more important for chess improvement: studying the opening, middlegame, or endgame? Explain why.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The short answer is that everything is actually interconnected, and I
wish I had known this earlier. A quality game will have a story behind
it that connects all phases of chess. Because of this, I think the
study of complete, annotated games (including annotating your own
games) is the single most useful technique for improvement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, opening study is popular, but studying the opening in
isolation, apart from understanding fundamental principles and knowing
not to fall into tricky traps, is almost irrelevant at under-2000
level, where games will mostly be decided not by opening subtleties,
but by later parts of the game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My main improvements have come from understanding the middlegame
better, learning how to assess positions and create plans based on
features of the positions, especially through considering Pawn
structure. If you think of an opening as a way to try to get to a
certain kind of middlegame, and think of the middlegame as a way to
get to a certain kind of endgame, then everything starts to fit
together. The middlegame is the core.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Improving in the endgame is important at all levels.  When I look at
my first tournament games at a 1500-1600 level, I see that the vast
majority of them went into endgames where anything could happen
because none of us really knew what we were doing, but I managed draws
and wins because I was a bit better there than opponents who otherwise
matched me in the opening and middlegame.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With my young students, I go over the opening phase with them only
enough for them to survive it (by playing classically and avoiding
needlessly complex and subtle variations), but focus my instruction
primarily on how to get to a desired middlegame by means of opening
choice. I also add endgame instruction incrementally as it becomes a
bottleneck in overall performance: when they get good enough to get a
dominating middlegame and then fail to win in the endgame, that&amp;rsquo;s when
we work on the endgame. But I feel like spending a lot of time on the
endgame up front is not realistic if one is not even surviving the
middlegame.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;were-there-any-special-small-or-large-celebration-when-you-became-a-master&#34;&gt;Were there any special, small or large celebration when you became a Master?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No, there was no celebration. I have to confess I&amp;rsquo;m not really a
celebration kind of person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-are-your-plans-now&#34;&gt;What are your plans now?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will continue what I&amp;rsquo;ve already been doing in chess since 2012:
writing and teaching.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started writing about chess on my personal blog around 2012. I
really enjoy sharing my analysis and thoughts with others, and this
eventually led to my writing for GM Nigel Davies&amp;rsquo; &lt;a href=&#34;http://ChessImprover.com/author/FranklinC/&#34;&gt;The Chess Improver&lt;/a&gt;
site and giving private chess lessons since 2013. I am still teaching
now and very much enjoy helping others improve their chess. So
teaching has been my main focus in chess for a while now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will continue to play in local tournaments as time permits. I am not
done improving yet! Also, I enjoy being a role model for my students,
to walk the walk as I give them advice about how to study, improve,
and compete. I have even been inspired to try to play model games to
illustrate specific themes I teach. For example, last year when the
subject was isolated Pawns, I played a game in which I chose an
opening aimed specifically against an isolated Pawn structure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2016-06-25&#34;&gt;(Update of 2016-06-25)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still play chess with my father whenever I see him. He&amp;rsquo;s still
playing pretty well at age 78. I feel he is possibly even better than
when he was in his 40s, probably because he has all the time in the
world to play casual games regularly at his local community center
since retirement. It&amp;rsquo;s actually harder for me to beat him now than
when I was a kid. Here&amp;rsquo;s a photo from the last visit to my parents&amp;rsquo; in
May 2016; I barely managed to win this game, where I took advantage of
the weakness of his isolated Pawn in the endgame:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&#34;true&#34;  href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/franklinmingchen/27597310106/in/album-72157671558553835/&#34; title=&#34;Untitled&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://c3.staticflickr.com/8/7317/27597310106_994a1df764.jpg&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; height=&#34;375&#34; alt=&#34;Untitled&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async src=&#34;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>If you were this old man playing chess against a young boy, what would you have done?</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2016/01/09/if-you-were-this-old-man-playing-chess-against-a-young-boy-what-would-you-have-done/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Jan 2016 12:08:32 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2016/01/09/if-you-were-this-old-man-playing-chess-against-a-young-boy-what-would-you-have-done/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m going to tell you a true story about an old man and a young boy
(age under 10) who played a game of chess in a competitive tournament
where prize money was at stake. I&amp;rsquo;d like you to think about the odd
situation that occurred, while looking at it, with &lt;em&gt;empathy&lt;/em&gt;, from
different points of view:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the old man&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the young boy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the boy&amp;rsquo;s parent&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the tournament director, whose job is to enforce the official
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.uschess.org/content/view/7864/221/&#34;&gt;US Chess Federation rules of tournament chess&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the bigger picture of the chess community&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the biggest picture of life lessons&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the whole story, do you think that what happened was right?
Is there something you would have done differently if you had been one
of the actors in the story? In particular, what would you have done as
the old man?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;prelude&#34;&gt;Prelude&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s call the old man Mr. M, the boy B, the tournament director T.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the beginning of the second half of a long tournament, Mr. M and B
were paired against each other. Neither had been doing too well in the
tournament up till that point, but there was the rest of the
tournament to go, and anything can happen in a long tournament. Mr. M
on paper had the highest US chess rating of their shared class
division going into the tournament and so was the favorite to win. B
was a young newcomer to chess who had only been playing for half a
year but was improving rapidly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out during the game that B played extremely well, outplaying
Mr. M. The position was complicated but B had an advantage. B thought
he spotted a winning move, and carelessly (still being young and
impulsive, unfortunately) &lt;em&gt;picked up one of his pieces&lt;/em&gt; in order to
make the winning move, but in mid-air realized it was not going to
win.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;touch-move&#34;&gt;Touch-move&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Touch-move_rule&#34;&gt;touch-move&lt;/a&gt; rule
in chess is one of the most important rules that exists in serious
tournament chess. If you touch your own piece with &lt;em&gt;intent&lt;/em&gt; to move
it, or touch an opponent&amp;rsquo;s piece with &lt;em&gt;intent&lt;/em&gt; to capture it, then you
have to complete your move using the touched piece one way or another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Violating touch-move is very common among young chess players in a
casual setting, and therefore a critical bad habit to break, as B
learned the hard way in this game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;where-to-move-it&#34;&gt;Where to move it?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, since B was still in mid-air, he did not have to complete the
move he was going to play. He did have to complete some legal move
using his touched piece, which he still held. At this point, he
&lt;em&gt;intended&lt;/em&gt; to put the piece back on its &lt;em&gt;original&lt;/em&gt; square, as is legal
to do so, to think of what move to make with the piece.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, in confusion, B accidentally released the piece on a
random other square rather than the original square. This was really
bad luck because the move that was thereby &lt;em&gt;determined&lt;/em&gt; by the
release.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-old-man-s-decision&#34;&gt;The old man&amp;rsquo;s decision&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since Mr. M knew as well as B did that B did not intend to release the
piece on the absurd square it was released at, he decided to allow B
to return the piece to the original square in order to make a
different legal move. Very charitable!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then Mr. M suddenly changed his mind and said the accidentally
determined move had to stand. The tournament director was called and
ruled that according to the rules, indeed the move had to stand: the
piece was released on a legal square.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;B&amp;rsquo;s parent did not contest the ruling, because it was by the book, and
the result was that Mr. M captured B&amp;rsquo;s piece and quickly won the game,
because the rest of the game was nonsensical given the nonsensical
move B was forced to play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;your-reaction&#34;&gt;Your reaction?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Given this information, how do you feel about what happened? Rules
  are rules, but Mr. M had the power to insist on strict enforcement
  or to overlook the unintended violation, and originally intended to
  let it go.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first reaction when learning about this story was anger that Mr. M
had changed his mind like that. If Mr. M had taken one course of
action or the other, &lt;em&gt;without suddenly changing his mind&lt;/em&gt;, I would
have been OK with that. Either be forgiving or play by the book, but
be consistent!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My second reaction, was from the point of view of what this
incident meant for B in the long run. I had some conflicting feelings:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I felt bad about B being forced to lose an important game in which
he was playing some of the best chess he had ever played in his
life.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I was annoyed that B still hadn&amp;rsquo;t mastered &amp;ldquo;touch-move&amp;rdquo;, and felt
that he needed to &lt;em&gt;learn a lesson&lt;/em&gt; that would help him avoid such
carelessness in his future chess tournaments, and this was a
legitimate case of his learning an important lesson.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I worried about how B would feel about this loss, given that he had
started off the tournament pretty badly and was just getting his
momentum back by the second half.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;complications&#34;&gt;Complications&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this wasn&amp;rsquo;t the whole story. The other thing Mr. M did when
explaining why he changed his mind was that he wanted to win the game
and the tournament (recall that he was in a worse position against B,
and hadn&amp;rsquo;t been doing so well in the tournament despite being the
highest rated player in the section). So his concern wasn&amp;rsquo;t about
strictly enforcing the rules; presumably if he already had a
tournament win locked up and this game didn&amp;rsquo;t &amp;ldquo;matter&amp;rdquo;, he would have
been &amp;ldquo;charitable&amp;rdquo; and allowed B to continue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Does this change how you feel about what happened?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, Mr. M&amp;rsquo;s justification made me actively dislike him. At the
same time, maybe B learned an additional life lesson in this
tournament, that adults will do whatever is in their own interest and
any generosity offered may be contingent on whether it impacts their
own interest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-end-result&#34;&gt;The end result&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some rounds later, the tournament was complete. It turned out that
Mr. M won all subsequent games he played in the tournament, and
therefore won the tournament, along with the prize money for first
place, $500. He achieved his goal, fulfilling his justification for
being firm in his game against B. So from his point of view, he made
the right decision and got his moment of glory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;B bounced back from his disaster and also won his remaining games, and
ended up with a pretty successful tournament overall. You could say
that although it was unfortunate that his touch-move slip might have
cost him first place, he learned a lot about taking touch-move
seriously and about recovering from unfortunate incidents during a
chess tournament. So from B&amp;rsquo;s point of view, he probably learned a lot
more from Mr. M&amp;rsquo;s adherence to the rules than if Mr. M had been too
nice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although I don&amp;rsquo;t like how Mr. M went about what he did, the end result
seems actually optimal for everyone involved. Or was it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;appendix&#34;&gt;Appendix&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve written in the past about some life lessons I learned from chess
as a child. I&amp;rsquo;m curious how B will look back at his incident later in
life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/05/30/life-lessons-i-learned-from-a-lunch-recess-chess-game-at-age-seven&#34;&gt;Life lessons I learned from a lunch recess chess game at age seven&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/06/03/why-i-am-grateful-that-my-father-never-let-me-win-a-chess-game-against-him&#34;&gt;Why I am grateful that my father never let me win a chess game against him&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Clever chess tactics that were not what they seemed</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/11/30/clever-chess-tactics-that-were-not-what-they-seemed/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Nov 2015 02:25:52 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/11/30/clever-chess-tactics-that-were-not-what-they-seemed/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In round 3 of the current 6-round Pittsburgh Chess Club Tuesday night
tournament, I played a very tense game that led to an unusual position
with beautiful tactical possibilities. My opponent, Melih, is a strong
player who is a winner of the 2015 Pittsburgh Chess Club Championship earlier
this year, and had won the last two tournament games we have played,
so I came into this game anxious and also thirsty for revenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The game proved to be very challenging for both of us. I achieved a
better position out of the opening as Black but was too cautious to
press more aggressively. After more than 3 hours (!) of play, we ended
up in a simplified late middlegame in which I had only a small but
clear advantage. We were both clearly physically and mentally
exhausted, and starting to run out of time (these tournament games
have a time control of 2 hours per person with a 5-second delay per
move). It was up to me to try to find a way to win by inducing errors
in his play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;get-ready-to-be-quizzed&#34;&gt;Get ready to be quizzed!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What ended up happening was in retrospect both remarkable and
comic. To maximize your entertainment as well as challenge your
tactical skills, I recommend pausing at each diagrammed position below
in order to ask yourself what move you would play, and why, before
gradually uncovering the whole story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: an interactive chess board with all variations is provided at
the end of this article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;first-assess-a-quiet-looking-starting-position&#34;&gt;First, assess a quiet-looking starting position&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For context, here is the position after 21 moves, after Black played
21&amp;hellip;Qc6.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/ozbek-chen-2015-11-17/22w.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;21...Qc6; White to move&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;questions&#34;&gt;Questions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What opening do you think this middlegame came from?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Who stands better and why?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is White&amp;rsquo;s best plan, and what is Black&amp;rsquo;s best plan?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;answers&#34;&gt;Answers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Congratulations if you guessed this was a
  &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/French_Defence#Advance_Variation:_3.e5&#34;&gt;French Defense, Advance Variation&lt;/a&gt;,
  gone totally wrong for White!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Black stands better and has a simple plan:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;attack White&amp;rsquo;s backward Pawn on c3 on the half-open file, and
perhaps also the e5 Pawn as well; and the a2 Pawn and b4 Pawn are
also potential targets&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;use the half-open c-file for the Rooks, and the dark-squared Bishop
against White&amp;rsquo;s Pawns, and get the Queen involved as well&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;using these attacks, overload White&amp;rsquo;s defenses somehow in order to
win at least one of those Pawns to enter a probably winning endgame&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;White&amp;rsquo;s only possible counter-plan:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;defend the weak Queen side Pawns&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;maybe plant the Knight on a good outpost such as d4&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;defend the Pawn on e5 with maybe an f4 advance, and hope to attack
Black&amp;rsquo;s King side with perhaps an f5 break&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;progress-after-seven-moves&#34;&gt;Progress after seven moves?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Black has just played 28&amp;hellip;Rc4.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/ozbek-chen-2015-11-17/29w.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;28...Rc4; White to move&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;questions-1&#34;&gt;Questions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Who has made more progress in the last seven moves: White or Black?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is the nature of the progress made?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;answers-1&#34;&gt;Answers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;White has played to wait to see what Black is up to; meanwhile, Black
has made some progress on the Queen side by:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;doubling Rooks on the half-open c-file&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;using the Queen to bear down on White&amp;rsquo;s a-Pawn, which White has
(mistakenly) advanced to a3.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;white-played-a-surprising-move&#34;&gt;White played a surprising move&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;White has just played 29 Rac2.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/ozbek-chen-2015-11-17/29b.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;29 Rac2; Black to move&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;questions-2&#34;&gt;Questions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the 29th move, White moved the Rook from a2 to c2, leaving the
defense of the a3 Pawn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is the meaning of this strange move?!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can Black just take the Pawn with the Queen?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;answers-2&#34;&gt;Answers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may be thinking &amp;ldquo;White is provocatively setting a trap for Black
to fall into&amp;rdquo;. You get credit if you can see the trap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;black-fell-into-a-trap&#34;&gt;Black fell into a trap?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I played 29&amp;hellip;Qxa3.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/ozbek-chen-2015-11-17/30w.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;29...Qxa3; White to move&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But wait, I took the Pawn! Did I fall into a trap?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;questions-3&#34;&gt;Questions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is the trap you saw earlier, if you saw it?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is it really a trap?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;white-closed-the-trap&#34;&gt;White closed the trap?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;White has played 30 Ra2.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/ozbek-chen-2015-11-17/30b.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;30 Ra2; Black to move&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;answers-3&#34;&gt;Answers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the Rook moved back to a2, apparently trapping Black&amp;rsquo;s Queen. But
again, was it really a trap?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;black-refuted-the-trap&#34;&gt;Black refuted the trap?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Black played 30&amp;hellip;Rxd4.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/ozbek-chen-2015-11-17/31w.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;30...Rxd4; White to move&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You get credit if you saw this move taking White&amp;rsquo;s Knight on d4, and
saw that White&amp;rsquo;s Queen is overloaded such that retaking the Rook in
either one of two ways leads to losing back the Rook on c1 and
therefore losing a piece overall and the game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was very proud of seeing this tactic. (If you saw a different move
for Black, we&amp;rsquo;ll discuss that further down below.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;white-refuted-the-refutation&#34;&gt;White refuted the refutation?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;White played 31 Qc2.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/ozbek-chen-2015-11-17/31b.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;31 Qc2; Black to move&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When Melih moved his Queen to c2, I was in shock and disgust at
myself: in my fatigue near the end of this game, and overexcitement at
believing I had &amp;ldquo;refuted&amp;rdquo; a &amp;ldquo;trap&amp;rdquo;, I had completely failed to take
into account that White was not actually required to take my Rook on d4!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amusingly, it turns out that Melih, after playing 29 Rac2 setting the
&amp;ldquo;trap&amp;rdquo;, saw to his horror the resource 30&amp;hellip;Rxd4, and thought he was
lost, but then saw 31 Qc2. So neither of us had originally seen this
saving resource for White.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;questions-4&#34;&gt;Questions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is Black&amp;rsquo;s Queen trapped for real now?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What should Black do? Is Black lost? Or is Black still winning? Or
should Black start looking for a draw?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;black-panicked-trying-to-draw&#34;&gt;Black panicked, trying to draw&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, Black&amp;rsquo;s Queen is trapped for real. You get credit if you saw
that Black&amp;rsquo;s flashy 30&amp;hellip;Rxd4 had this flaw.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only question for me was how best to give up my Queen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I chose poorly. In a daze, I could not think straight. I chose to give
back a Rook with 31&amp;hellip;Qxc3, in order to force a trade Queens on c3 and
go into an endgame an exchange down for two Pawns, and hope for a draw.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/ozbek-chen-2015-11-17/36w.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;31...Qxc3; White to move&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I was correct that the resulting position was objectively equal and
drawable, but in a time scramble, it&amp;rsquo;s obviously easier to play White,
and for the rest of the game, both sides made major errors (with White
botching up winning positions and Black botching up drawn positions)
until a simplified position was reached (Rook and two Pawns for each
side) with only seconds left on the clock, and a draw agreed. I
consider myself lucky to have drawn. The final position was:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/ozbek-chen-2015-11-17/draw.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Agreed drawn&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;but-black-could-have-played-to-win&#34;&gt;But Black could have played to win&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You get credit if you chose instead to sacrifice the Queen with
31&amp;hellip;Qxc1+ to get the Rook and Bishop and Pawns against White&amp;rsquo;s Queen,
with advantage and a good chance of winning. After 32 Qxc1 Bxb4, Black
is about to win White&amp;rsquo;s c3 Pawn:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/ozbek-chen-2015-11-17/33rooksw.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;32...Bxb4; White to move&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In fact, if you saw all this when thinking about whether to take the
Pawn on a3 in the first place, then you get bonus points for seeing a
way to an advantage through the sequence of tactical blows. Neither
Melih nor I saw any of this up front, unfortunately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I chickened out and did not take this continuation because after being
shocked that my Queen was disappearing, I experienced a visceral fear
that I needed to bring down White&amp;rsquo;s Queen also, else it with White&amp;rsquo;s
Rook might be dangerous to my King.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that my fear was objectively unwarranted, as Black&amp;rsquo;s
defenses are sufficient because of the power of the dark-squared
Bishop to hit White&amp;rsquo;s e5 Pawn and even the f2 Pawn, but I was not
thinking straight any more as time was running out for the four-hour
game and it was already around 11 PM at night on a weekday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;one-possible-position&#34;&gt;One possible position&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a position that might have arisen if I had gone into this
variation:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/ozbek-chen-2015-11-17/35rooksw.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;White to move&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The thing is, even though the computer says Black has an advantage, it
could be scary playing against White&amp;rsquo;s Queen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;another-possible-position&#34;&gt;Another possible position&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But analysis also shows that White has to be very careful. For
example, if White is greedy and wastes time taking Black&amp;rsquo;s a7 Pawn
above, Black quickly gets a winning attack:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/ozbek-chen-2015-11-17/37rooksw.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;White to move&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In time pressure, anything can happen, and I think it would have been
very likely that White would have grabbed the a7 Pawn, after which
Black&amp;rsquo;s position play itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;finally-black-s-real-refutation&#34;&gt;Finally: Black&amp;rsquo;s real refutation!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I said you get extra credit for seeing everything to the point of
sacrificing Black&amp;rsquo;s Queen for an advantage. But you only get full
credit if you saw the real refutation of White&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;trap&amp;rdquo; earlier in the
game! I kicked myself for not having seen it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;questions-5&#34;&gt;Questions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Was there a point at which Black could have deviated and won the
game outright?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hint: which of Black&amp;rsquo;s pieces have we not focused on in the
variations covered so far?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;answers-4&#34;&gt;Answers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Black could, after White &amp;ldquo;trapped&amp;rdquo; the Queen with 30 Ra2, used a
different and better deflection of White&amp;rsquo;s overloaded Queen than
30&amp;hellip;Rxd4, which was OK but not best.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We haven&amp;rsquo;t looked at Black&amp;rsquo;s Bishop enough. I only saw this upon
recovering from the draw and analyzing the game later at home: the
winning shot is 30&amp;hellip;Bg5!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/ozbek-chen-2015-11-17/31varw.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;White to move&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If White blocks the threat to the Queen with 31 f4,
then Black just lops off the Pawn with 31&amp;hellip;Bxf4 and now:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;if White takes the Bishop or otherwise moves the Queen, Black will
win either the Rook on a2 or the Rook on c1&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;if White takes Black&amp;rsquo;s Queen, then Black takes White&amp;rsquo;s Queen on d2
with tempo and will eventually win all three of White&amp;rsquo;s weak
Pawns on dark squares (c3 followed by e5 and b4)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Either way, the endgame is an easy win for Black.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neither Melih nor I saw this winning resource for Black during the
game. We just weren&amp;rsquo;t looking at that quiet Bishop because it hadn&amp;rsquo;t
participated in anything up till that point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chess never ceases to surprise me. Tactical possibilities are
everywhere, and in this game, both Melih and I missed various
possible continuations, playing moves thinking we knew what had to
follow. I hope you enjoyed this story of missed opportunities and
incomplete calculations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My thanks to Melih for a challenging and fascinating game, and sharing
his thoughts with me afterwards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&#34;true&#34;  href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/franklinmingchen/23445261516/in/datetaken/&#34; title=&#34;Melih and Franklin at the Pittsburgh Chess Club&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm1.staticflickr.com/589/23445261516_25ee07e170_z.jpg&#34; width=&#34;640&#34; height=&#34;480&#34; alt=&#34;Franklin and Melih at the Pittsburgh Chess Club&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async src=&#34;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;appendix-interactive-playable-board&#34;&gt;Appendix: interactive playable board&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;
        src=&#34;http://chesstempo.com/js/pgnyui.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;
        src=&#34;http://chesstempo.com/js/pgnviewer.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;link
     type=&#34;text/css&#34;
     rel=&#34;stylesheet&#34;
     href=&#34;http://chesstempo.com/css/board-min.css&#34;&gt;
&lt;/link&gt;

&lt;script&gt;
    new PgnViewer(
      { boardName: &#34;demo&#34;,
        pgnFile: &#39;/chess/ozbek-chen-2015-11-17/ozbek-chen.pgn&#39;,
        pieceSet: &#39;merida&#39;,
        pieceSize: 46
      }
    );
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;style&gt;
#demo-stuff {
    display: flex;
}

#demo-moves {
    overflow-y: auto;
}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;div id=&#34;demo-stuff&#34;&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;demo-container&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;demo-moves&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The importance of stalemate in chess: how chess is completely different from life</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/06/16/the-importance-of-stalemate-in-chess-how-chess-is-completely-different-from-life/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Jun 2015 22:16:19 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/06/16/the-importance-of-stalemate-in-chess-how-chess-is-completely-different-from-life/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I just saw a cute end to a top-level chess game that ended in a forced
draw because the would-be losing side &lt;a href=&#34;http://dejanbojkov.blogspot.com/2015/06/jakovenko-and-stalemate.html&#34;&gt;managed a swindle&lt;/a&gt; by giving away
all his pieces by force in order to create a
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stalemate&#34;&gt;stalemate&lt;/a&gt;. If you don&amp;rsquo;t
play chess, a stalemate is what happens when it&amp;rsquo;s your turn to move
and you have no legal moves. You can claim a draw when you are &lt;em&gt;totally
trapped&lt;/em&gt; in this way. So one way of saving an otherwise losing game,
when you are outnumbered and about to be checkmated (losing when your
King comes under attack and it&amp;rsquo;s your move and you cannot stop the
check), is to find a brilliant way to be &lt;em&gt;unable to move&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/stalemate.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Black forced a draw through being stalemated!&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Is this a totally bizarre concept or what? Why was this rule of chess
invented anyway? Wouldn&amp;rsquo;t it make more sense if being trapped meant
&lt;em&gt;losing&lt;/em&gt;, like it does in real life conflicts?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;history-of-stalemate&#34;&gt;History of stalemate&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stalemate was apparently
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stalemate#History_of_the_stalemate_rule&#34;&gt;standardized to be a draw in the 19th century&lt;/a&gt;. Before
that, conventions differed on what the outcome of the game was
supposed to be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now and then, notable chess players have called for the abolishment of
his rule, to replace the stalemate with a win for the side that
trapped the other side, because this is &amp;ldquo;logical&amp;rdquo; and corresponds to
what you would expect in war or in some other &amp;ldquo;real life&amp;rdquo; situation in
which you have pressed hard for a long time, accumulated a lot of
force, and can cause your opponent to not be able to move at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;i-like-that-stalemate-is-illogical&#34;&gt;I like that stalemate is illogical&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m going to be blunt: I like that stalemate is &amp;ldquo;illogical&amp;rdquo;! It
creates tremendous difficulty for the side with more material to win
in endgames. I like that it gives the underdog a chance to avoid
losing by being clever. If stalemate were not a draw, then it would be
trivial to win many games in which one side has made a mistake and
lost a Pawn, because then all that has to be done is trade everything
off until all that remains is a King and Pawn versus King, and declare
victory. Stalemate means that the side with the extra Pawn has to work
super hard to avoid trading everything off, to avoid just mechanically
fighting battles with equal losses on both sides until one Pawn is
left.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like stalemate because in real life, often it is too easy for one
side to win just because of an early error by the loser. &lt;em&gt;Chess is not
real life&lt;/em&gt;, and I like it that way. Stalemate and other rules of chess
add bizarre whimsy and creativity to the game, just as the rule of
checkmate at all is counter to real life. In real life, you can kill
the general of an army and still lose the war. In chess, it&amp;rsquo;s always
like in the movies, on the other hand: you can have a lone hero defy
all odds to get at the enemy King and sacrifice everything else for
this objective, and have a happy ending. There is something &lt;em&gt;romantic&lt;/em&gt;
about chess that is part of its appeal to me. Chess is a game of logic
but according to weird heroic rules, where sheer &lt;em&gt;material wealth&lt;/em&gt; is
not enough to guarantee a win.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is unfortunate that many top-level chess games end in a draw, but
to abolish stalemate would change the capricious character of the
game in a way that ruins its appeal to me (on a lower level of play).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you are not a chess player, what do you think of the stalemate
  rule? If you are a chess player, what do you think of it?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thoughts on giving up an old project to make room for the new</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/12/15/thoughts-on-giving-up-an-old-project-to-make-room-for-the-new/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2014 20:10:34 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/12/15/thoughts-on-giving-up-an-old-project-to-make-room-for-the-new/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Today I made a difficult decision to give up doing something that I have enjoyed for well &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/09/12/my-first-post-on-the-chess-improver-the-value-of-thematic-complete-games-against-a-weaker-opponent/&#34;&gt;over a year now&lt;/a&gt;: writing a &lt;a href=&#34;http://chessimprover.com/category/franklin-chen/&#34;&gt;weekly chess column&lt;/a&gt; at &lt;a href=&#34;http://chessimprover.com/&#34;&gt;The Chess Improver&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;writing&#34;&gt;Writing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s been a major commitment coming up with something to write about every week for such a long time. There have been times when I was overflowing with ideas; there have been times when I struggled to come up with something to write about that I could stand behind. Sometimes I have published something I felt was particularly good; sometimes I felt uninspired; sometimes I just dashed something out of uneven quality. But through it all, I learned a lot from my attempt to convey &lt;em&gt;something specific and concrete&lt;/em&gt; that I hoped readers would enjoy and ideally even use to their practical advantage in their own chess play. The best way to verify whether you actually understand something is to write about it! I definitely had to do homework in many cases in order to make sure I really understood what I was talking about, in order to be as accurate and correct as I could.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I even kept on writing about chess during very dry spells in my writing in general, when I wasn&amp;rsquo;t writing anything for my other two blogs, this personal blog and my &lt;a href=&#34;http://ConscientiousProgrammer.com/&#34;&gt;programming blog&lt;/a&gt;. I admit to being rather embarrassed that during these dry spells, I kept on posting links to my chess blog from this blog. I will never again waste readers&amp;rsquo; time by posting links from one blog to another except when relevant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-law-of-conservation-of-time-and-energy&#34;&gt;The law of conservation of time and energy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our lives, we can&amp;rsquo;t do it all. For 2015, recent circumstances have led me to commit to a bunch of personal projects that have nothing to do with chess, so I knew, as 2014 comes to a close, that I would have to give up something &lt;em&gt;old&lt;/em&gt; in order to free up time and energy for the &lt;em&gt;new&lt;/em&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;m going to writing up a retrospective on 2014 before 2015 comes, in order to plan out how to go about 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;it-s-not-really-giving-up&#34;&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s not really giving up&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I lied in my title. I&amp;rsquo;m not really &amp;ldquo;giving up&amp;rdquo; chess writing; I&amp;rsquo;m just putting it aside. If a time comes when I feel it is worthwhile to do it again, I may well return. However, for now, I&amp;rsquo;m shutting it down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All things come to an end, or at least, an adjournment. I look forward to tackling new challenges as I free myself from the responsibility of writing a weekly chess column.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How do you rearrange your life when you decide to start new demanding projects? Do you try to squeeze them in and cut out &amp;ldquo;non-essentials&amp;rdquo; or optimize your efficiency? Or do you decide that you have to cut out significant old projects? Or do you feel that you are already stretched to the limit with essentials (such as young children) and cannot possibly take on anything new?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Report on my second day of Stoic Week 2014: mindfulness</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/25/report-on-my-second-day-of-stoic-week-2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2014 23:50:38 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/25/report-on-my-second-day-of-stoic-week-2014/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, I reported on my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/11/24/report-on-my-first-day-of-stoic-week-2014/&#34;&gt;first day of Stoic Week 2014&lt;/a&gt;. Today, the second day&amp;rsquo;s theme was &amp;ldquo;Stoic mindfulness&amp;rdquo;. This is similar to the Buddhist teaching on mindfulness, and is basically a sound psychological observation that &amp;ldquo;You are just an impression and not at all the thing you claim to represent&amp;rdquo;: our thoughts and feelings are one thing but what we do about them is another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found it particularly useful to remember this today, because Tuesdays present an interesting challenge for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;chess&#34;&gt;Chess&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Tuesday nights, I have been playing in the latest 6-round current Tuesday night &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburghcc.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Chess Club&lt;/a&gt; tournament, one round every Tuesday. Tonight was round 4. I had experienced an extremely painful loss last week in round 3 when I was &lt;em&gt;not mindful&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://chessimprover.com/blockading-to-defend-when-things-get-tough/&#34;&gt;got carried away by emotions&lt;/a&gt;: I had an overwhelming advantage during an attack on my opponent&amp;rsquo;s King, but I allowed my excitement to cloud my judgment, make poor moves, and then worse, after I managed to recover and had the opportunity to survive with a draw, &lt;em&gt;and saw this&lt;/em&gt;, I passed it up out of wishful thinking that I could continue an attack, so I ended up losing. In chess, I face the stark reality that most losses at my level in local competition (where I am typically the top-rated player) are due to faulty psychology, rather than lack of sufficient understanding and skill. A loss of &lt;em&gt;objectivity&lt;/em&gt; (which all athletes and other performers under high pressure) is the reason we fail. Mindfulness directly addresses this all-too-human flaw.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;continuing-habits-from-yesterday&#34;&gt;Continuing habits from yesterday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, I noted that I began meditating and exercising again, because it was in my power to do so. I have continued. It&amp;rsquo;s been tricky to get going again, because my body is out of whack, but I remember to do what I can, no more, with faith that incremental progress will pay off. Instead of running, I did a &lt;a href=&#34;http://well.blogs.nytimes.com/projects/workouts/&#34;&gt;7-minute workout&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;ve lost a lot of strength over the years and plan to regain it. I have dumbbells lying around the house from when I was using them a decade ago; it&amp;rsquo;s time to get back to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;tonight-s-chess-game&#34;&gt;Tonight&amp;rsquo;s chess game&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I won a decent game tonight at the chess tournament. It was the third last to finish, taking almost four hours. I&amp;rsquo;ve played against my opponent many times before over the years, mostly winning, but the last time I played him, he held me to a draw, despite a 500-rating-point difference (which is huge). One thing that sometimes happens in tournament chess is overconfidence when facing someone who is on paper much weaker, or fear because of a past bad result. Mindfulness teaches us that although historical facts are facts, we should distance ourselves from distracting feelings about them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As in many hard-fought chess games, I experienced a range of emotions during the game. First of all, in the opening, although I was doing OK, I was frustrated that I allowed a certain kind of position I ordinarily do not allow, because of an oversight. Instead of kicking myself, I focused to do what I could with what I had, assessing that even though I did not want that position, it was actually still OK for me. (Actually, computer analysis afterwards showed that I was more than OK, so I was still more pessimistic than warranted during the game.) In the middlegame, I emerged with an advantage, but then faced a curious choice. My opponent gave me an opportunity to win some material (a Rook for a Bishop and Pawn) at the expense of destroying my Pawn structure and therefore creating good chances for a draw. At the time, I saw no better winning try, so I went for it, deciding that, unlike last week, I was going to settle for a draw if my opponent could prove he could defend; I simply made sure to play soundly and not recklessly. It turned out that he cracked eventually and I won. I was pleased that I remained psychologically strong in the game and was rewarded accordingly. (For those of you interested in the technical details of the game, I will be annotating it in an upcoming article I will write for &lt;a href=&#34;http://chessimprover.com/category/franklin-chen/&#34;&gt;my weekly column in The Chess Improver&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;heavy-traffic&#34;&gt;Heavy traffic&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another thing: when driving home from work to eat dinner before the chess game, I noticed that the traffic was unusually bad. Mindfulness is always helpful when facing stressful situations like this. I was upset with myself for not anticipating apparent pre-Thanksgiving-holiday traffic and therefore being pressed for time to get home and eat dinner before playing chess. I decided to let go of my self-annoyance because it wasn&amp;rsquo;t going to help me get home any sooner and would just sap my mental energy I needed for my game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mindfulness is something I&amp;rsquo;ve had prior experience in trying to adopt well before I even read about Stoicism. But having a daily theme and reading during Stoic Week has been surprisingly helpful in keeping me aware.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Are you familiar with the concept of mindfulness and the scientific underpinnings of it? If so, do you deliberately practice it? Do you have misgivings about it?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My predictions after Carlsen and Anand are tied after round 4 of the World Chess Championship</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/12/my-predictions-after-carlsen-and-anand-are-tied-after-round-4-of-the-world-chess-championship/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2014 23:01:25 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/12/my-predictions-after-carlsen-and-anand-are-tied-after-round-4-of-the-world-chess-championship/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/11/06/my-predictions-and-hopes-for-the-2014-carlsen-anand-world-chess-championship-rematch/&#34;&gt;Last week I made some predictions&lt;/a&gt; about the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sochi2014.fide.com/&#34;&gt;2014 Carlsen-Anand World Chess Championship&lt;/a&gt; match before it began. Now, four rounds later, there have been two draws and a win for each player. What next? Since I correctly predicted some things already, I thought I&amp;rsquo;d speculate about the next couple of rounds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;anand&#34;&gt;Anand&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;as-white&#34;&gt;As White&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I expected, Anand opened with d4 with a view to aggressive, sharp lines based on home preparation. In round 1, he lost his nerve and lost his initiative, but in round 3, he won convincingly, first inviting a Queen&amp;rsquo;s Indian (as I expected he would) but then defeating the Queen&amp;rsquo;s Gambit Declined. I do not see why he would vary from d4 as White in the future unless he ends up ahead in the match and has psychological reasons to mix things up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;as-black&#34;&gt;As Black&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far, Anand has only faced 1 e4 as Black. In round 2, Anand made what seems like a stupid decision to try to go into the Berlin Defense, and got punished by a loss. I see no reason for him to play the Berlin Defense again; playing 1&amp;hellip;e5 just seems to be playing into Carlsen&amp;rsquo;s strengths. In round 4, Anand went for the Sicilian, as I expected; he used an &amp;hellip;e6 move order to avoid the Moscow and Rossolimo, causing Carlsen to vary with a g3 anti-Sicilian, resulting in a draw. My suspicion is still that Anand might be aiming for a &amp;hellip;Nc6 Sicilian through transposition, perhaps a Taimanov. I expect him to try this again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m most curious about how Anand would face the English. I think it would depend on his situation. 1&amp;hellip;e5 would be an ambitious, unbalancing choice, while transposition to a Slav structure is also possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;carlsen&#34;&gt;Carlsen&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;as-white-1&#34;&gt;As White&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I made no specific prediction about how Carlsen would open as White. He has played 1 e4 twice, once with success but once leading to a draw. Psychologically, his inability or unwillingness to engage Anand in an Open Sicilian does not make continuing with 1 e4 right now seem plausible. I expect him to vary, possibly using the English. I certainly hope he doesn&amp;rsquo;t try the Reti again as he did last year, even though it worked then; he is facing a different Anand this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;as-black-1&#34;&gt;As Black&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Grnfeld in round 1 was a surprise, but exactly true to my expectation that &amp;ldquo;he will do whatever might confuse Anand&amp;rdquo;. That he varied in round 3 with the Queen&amp;rsquo;s Gambit Declined suggests that the Grnfeld may not appear again soon, but he lost with the Queen&amp;rsquo;s Gambit Declined, so will he play it again? It is possible. Another possibility is to resort to the Queen&amp;rsquo;s Indian, making sure to avoid sacrificial lines (which means possibly playing a traditional &amp;hellip;Bb7 instead of &amp;hellip;Ba6). Or he could play a Ragozin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right now I think Anand is actually in good shape in the match, having a certain momentum. It appears Carlsen is mainly winging it, in the last two rounds. I expect him to change things up.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My predictions and hopes for the 2014 Carlsen-Anand world chess championship rematch</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/06/my-predictions-and-hopes-for-the-2014-carlsen-anand-world-chess-championship-rematch/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Nov 2014 21:09:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/06/my-predictions-and-hopes-for-the-2014-carlsen-anand-world-chess-championship-rematch/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sochi2014.fide.com/&#34;&gt;2014 World Chess Championship&lt;/a&gt; is about to begin, featuring Anand and Carlsen again, this time with Anand as challenger and Carlsen as defending champion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year when I followed the World Chess Championship match, I wrote several blog posts looking at each game that was played. This year I&amp;rsquo;m not planning to do the same, but instead, I would like to offer some predictions and hopes for the rematch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recall that I made one prediction that was eerily correct last year:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-correct-prediction-last-year&#34;&gt;My correct prediction last year&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before round 9 began, I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/11/21/world-chess-championship-2013-round-9-i-correctly-predicted-anands-aggressively-opening-choice-but-he-blundered-horribly-again-to-lose/&#34;&gt;predicted correctly&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
It came to me in a dream: Anand playing d4 in the next round, then going for an f3, e4 Pawn storm against Carlsen #FWCM2013
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was a critical game in the match, in which Anand blundered horribly to lose a game that he had very good chances of winning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;for-this-year&#34;&gt;For this year&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;anand&#34;&gt;Anand&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anand&amp;rsquo;s play last year was very disappointing: he did not win a single game in the match, as he was psychologically unprepared to play aggressively enough when he had good positions against Carlsen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I expect that this year, being the challenger instead of the defending champion, he will play in a more forceful way, because he has no choice and nothing to lose. What does this mean?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year I was surprised Anand played e4 as White inviting the Berlin Defense. This was a big mistake. I cannot imagine why he would play e4 again. He surely must play d4, or at least the English Opening with c4. What could he possibly have against the Nimzo-Indian, however, now that the f3 weapon is well-known? There&amp;rsquo;s always the Rubinstein e3 variation but Carlsen, like Karpov of old, should be happy with Black there. The other option is to avoid the Nimzo-Indian and use one of the Pawn sacrifice lines in the Queen&amp;rsquo;s Indian or Catalan. But Carlsen must be prepared against such. So there remains the option of trying for a tiny first-move advantage using the English. I guess we&amp;rsquo;ll see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Black, Anand could stick with the Grunfeld setup from last year, or return to a Slav setup. But what about against e4? There&amp;rsquo;s always the Najdorf, but that allowed the Moscow last year, so maybe a Nc6 Sicilian? In any case, I hope we see fewer Berlin Defense games this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;carlsen&#34;&gt;Carlsen&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Carlsen is still the favorite to win this year, but is not invincible. He can either play like he did last year, or play differently. Because he is versatile, he can change his plans depending on what happens. I suspect that because he is champion now, he may want to prove his dominance, and play more sharply than last year, but he can always fall back on his wait-for-opponent-to-self-destruct style. Since Anand is simply not going to last forever, Carlsen needs to already start preparing to play against his younger rivals such as Caruana and might want to send a message to them in this match.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I expect that his aim will be to psychologically destroy Anand one way or another, so he will do whatever might confuse Anand. I cannot really predict how he will play. I suspect his use of the Reti as White is over, however; there are plenty of ways to still control the situation as White while playing d4 or c4. Playing the English might be smart, actually, especially if Anand is also thinking of playing it. We could see one of those matches where both players decide to enter openings as both colors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have no idea if any of my &amp;ldquo;predictions&amp;rdquo; will actually come true, but thought it would be fun to get them on record in case they do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Are you going to follow this year&amp;rsquo;s World Chess Championship? What do you expect to see in the 2014 match in Sochi?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Things look different from the perspective of the professional and the spectator</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/05/things-look-different-from-the-perspective-of-the-professional-and-the-spectator/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2014 22:10:35 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/05/things-look-different-from-the-perspective-of-the-professional-and-the-spectator/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I saw an interesting &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.uschess.org/content/view/12843/785/&#34;&gt;article by young American chess Grandmaster Sam Shankland on his recent successful tournament in Brazil&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His goal was to qualify for the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chess_World_Cup&#34;&gt;Chess World Cup&lt;/a&gt;, the tournament that feeds into the final candidates for the World Championship match.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;I knew before going that Id be unlikely to face any of the top seeds
until the end of the tournament, and that it would largely be about
taking care of business against guys 100-200 points lower than
me. While normally I would avoid such a tournament, it all goes back
to that one goal: the World Cup. I did not care about playing good
chess, challenging myself, raising my rating, playing with strong
players &amp;ndash; all things I normally prioritize &amp;ndash; all I wanted was one of
the four coveted spots. As such, I played very differently than
normal.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;short-draws&#34;&gt;Short draws&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing about high level chess that often seems to confuse and frustrate spectators is the high percentage of short draws. Spectators find it easy to make fun of the elite competitors for being cowards or the like, not trying harder to win when it seems possible to do so in chess positions that are not yet dead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But if you put yourself in the professional&amp;rsquo;s shoes, you should be able to understand the strategic decision-making that happens on the board and off the board. I&amp;rsquo;m happy that players such as GM Sam Shankland are writing in a personal way about their choices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;I made more short draws in this event than I have in all my other
tournaments combined in the past year and a half. I love chess and I
have a well deserved reputation for being a fighting player, which is
largely due to my priorities.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.samshankland.com/&#34;&gt;GM Sam Shankland&lt;/a&gt; is a fine American chess player and writer. I appreciate his candor in explaining not only his chess moves but also his approach to his games and tournaments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How do you perceive and judge professional behavior in the world that often seems at odds with the interests of other people than themselves: by chess players, teachers, politicians, physicians, musicians, writers, athletes, etc?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Chess Improver: The common problem of following a pattern without understanding it</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/10/30/the-chess-improver-the-common-problem-of-following-a-pattern-without-understanding-it/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2014 20:14:40 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/10/30/the-chess-improver-the-common-problem-of-following-a-pattern-without-understanding-it/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;For &lt;a href=&#34;http://chessimprover.com/&#34;&gt;The Chess Improver&lt;/a&gt;, I wrote &lt;a href=&#34;http://chessimprover.com/the-common-problem-of-following-a-pattern-without-understanding-it/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The common problem of following a pattern without understanding it&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Chess Improver: Learning through comparing similar but different situations</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/10/23/the-chess-improver-learning-through-comparing-similar-but-different-situations/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2014 07:13:51 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/10/23/the-chess-improver-learning-through-comparing-similar-but-different-situations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;For &lt;a href=&#34;http://chessimprover.com/&#34;&gt;The Chess Improver&lt;/a&gt;, I wrote &lt;a href=&#34;http://chessimprover.com/learning-through-comparing-similar-but-different-situations/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Learning through comparing similar but different situations&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Chess Improver: Basic endgames teach how to tie together mathematics and logic</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/10/16/the-chess-improver-basic-endgames-teach-how-to-tie-together-mathematics-and-logic/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Oct 2014 07:10:54 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/10/16/the-chess-improver-basic-endgames-teach-how-to-tie-together-mathematics-and-logic/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;For &lt;a href=&#34;http://chessimprover.com/&#34;&gt;The Chess Improver&lt;/a&gt;, I wrote &lt;a href=&#34;http://chessimprover.com/basic-endgames-teach-how-to-tie-together-mathematics-and-logic/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Basic endgames teach how to tie together mathematics and logic&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Chess Improver: The temptation to play safe can prevent improvement</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/10/09/the-chess-improver-the-temptation-to-play-safe-can-prevent-improvement/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2014 07:02:49 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/10/09/the-chess-improver-the-temptation-to-play-safe-can-prevent-improvement/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;For &lt;a href=&#34;http://chessimprover.com/&#34;&gt;The Chess Improver&lt;/a&gt;, I wrote &lt;a href=&#34;http://chessimprover.com/the-temptation-to-play-safe-can-prevent-improvement/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The temptation to play safe can prevent improvement&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Chess Improver: Your Pawn is threatened: do you defend, advance, or trade?</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/10/02/the-chess-improver-your-pawn-is-threatened-do-you-defend/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2014 07:02:40 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/10/02/the-chess-improver-your-pawn-is-threatened-do-you-defend/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;For &lt;a href=&#34;http://chessimprover.com/&#34;&gt;The Chess Improver&lt;/a&gt;, I wrote &lt;a href=&#34;http://chessimprover.com/your-pawn-is-threatened-do-you-defend-advance-or-trade/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Your Pawn is threatened: do you defend, advance, or trade?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>