<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Tin Whistle on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/tin-whistle/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Tin Whistle on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/tin-whistle/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Finally doing some Latin music jamming on flute; also Irish and French</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/03/17/finally-doing-some-latin-music-jamming-on-flute/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Mar 2013 23:36:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/03/17/finally-doing-some-latin-music-jamming-on-flute/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;St. Patrick&amp;rsquo;s Day weekend means, of course, a party at Henry&amp;rsquo;s. Last year Abby and I even went to two of his St. Patrick&amp;rsquo;s Day parties! At the first, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/17/st-patricks-day-party-playing-tin-whistle-and-flute/&#34;&gt;I played tin whistle for the first time&lt;/a&gt;, and I played some easy recorder music &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/30/a-delayed-st-patricks-day-party-playing-tin-whistle-and-alto-recorder/&#34;&gt;at the second&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year, I reflected on how far I&amp;rsquo;ve come musically, and as usual, wanted to do something new and challenging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;irish-music&#34;&gt;Irish music&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I brought my tin whistle and Irish flute ready to jam. It turned out that Barbara had come with violin ready for some Irish jamming also. When she went at it with Henry on piano, she ended up playing &amp;ldquo;Danny Boy&amp;rdquo; (&amp;ldquo;Londonderry Air&amp;rdquo;) as one selection. Unfortunately, I had planned on playing it on flute, &amp;ldquo;redeeming&amp;rdquo; myself after being terrible on flute a year ago &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/17/st-patricks-day-party-playing-tin-whistle-and-flute/&#34;&gt;when I tried it&lt;/a&gt;, so since she had already done it, I quietly scrapped my original plan. No problem: there were many other things to play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Barbara joined me and Henry in some jigs, reels, and waltzes that I pulled out, some of which I did on tin whistle and some of which I did on Irish flute. That was fun, if pretty exhausting: lots and lots of notes, not so easy to just plain sight read. But of course, nobody has to play all the notes. That&amp;rsquo;s the beauty of this music. There never were official notes anyway; these are traditional tunes with a certain recognizable rhythm and shape and harmonic movement, but everyone does the notes differently anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;french-music&#34;&gt;French music&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d asked Vasili to learn on accordion &amp;ldquo;Les Ormeaux&amp;rdquo;, which I had learned just recently &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/02/25/stepping-it-up-at-the-french-and-blues-jam/&#34;&gt;at a French jam&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s not actually a traditional tune, but it&amp;rsquo;s a great one. Unfortunately, it turned out that Vasili had learned it in a different key from the one I was using on modern flute, so one of us (him) transposed on the fly to try to match, and the result therefore wasn&amp;rsquo;t as good as it could have been. Next time! Anyway, Abby and I jammed with Vasili on stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;latin-music&#34;&gt;Latin music&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;bolero&#34;&gt;Bolero&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The musical highlight for me was my debut in playing Latin, or more specifically, Cuban music. I fell in love with this music when I was &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/10/flute-loving-it-again/&#34;&gt;introduced to Latin ballroom dance back in 2000&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started off with an unnamed bolero from a World Music Cuba book I had first encountered &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/02/22/flute-progress-still-hanging-in-there/&#34;&gt;a year ago when I was just barely playing flute&lt;/a&gt;. I got on flute and Henry enthusiastically improvised along on piano and we took a couple of turns. That was great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I pulled out &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pbs.org/buenavista/music/songs/dos_gardenias.html&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Dos Gardenias&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, one of my favorite boleros of all time (and the bolero is one of my favorite musical genres). (By the way, I am working on being ready to sing this and other boleros before too long, making my debut as a bolero singer.) Again, more fun opportunities for inventiveness for Henry and me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;buena-vista-social-club&#34;&gt;Buena Vista Social Club&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, I first encountered &amp;ldquo;Dos Gardenias&amp;rdquo; through Ibrahim Ferrer of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Buena_Vista_Social_Club_%28album%29&#34;&gt;Buena Vista Social Club&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/5pKW7qvYSHU&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Buena Vista Social Club&amp;rdquo; was a very important music recording to me. At a time in my life around thirteen years ago when I was trying to explore Latin music and asked around for suggestions, my grad school classmate Andrej recommended this CD to me and my musical world was changed forever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;cha-cha&#34;&gt;Cha cha&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I pulled out an unnamed cha cha from the World Music Cuba book. We really went wild for this one, especially since Chad, one of Henry&amp;rsquo;s piano students (and a fine improviser) decided to join us and sat at the piano with Henry as both of them played with me and we kept going and going and I became very excited and inspired along with them. Wow. That was one of the most intense musical experiences I&amp;rsquo;ve ever had. It was frightening (didn&amp;rsquo;t know when I&amp;rsquo;d hit the limits of my technique or inventiveness) and exhilarating at the same time. When I was done, I was sweating from all the effort. Abby said she&amp;rsquo;d never seen me so animated before playing music, since she&amp;rsquo;s only ever seen me play Baroque and other such music mainly, or Irish and French. Well, Latin jazz is different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;chess&#34;&gt;Chess&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point in the evening, I needed a break from playing music and from socializing and decided to rest. However, it turned out that my &amp;ldquo;rest&amp;rdquo; consisted of relaxing in a chair while closing my eyes and&amp;hellip; &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/17/my-second-ever-blindfold-chess-game/&#34;&gt;playing blindfold chess&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2014-03-16&#34;&gt;(Update of 2014-03-16)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I couldn&amp;rsquo;t make it to Henry&amp;rsquo;s St. Patrick Day party in 2014. I felt sad about this, but our other plans made earlier made it impractical to try to attend.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pittsburgh Contras and Squares Holiday Ball 2012</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/12/14/pittsburgh-contras-and-squares-holiday-ball-2012/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Dec 2012 23:50:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/12/14/pittsburgh-contras-and-squares-holiday-ball-2012/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/holiday-ball-2012/grand-march.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Grand March&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So this year I joined Abby again to play in the &amp;ldquo;Holiday Ball Orchestra&amp;rdquo; as I had &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/16/playing-recorder-and-flute-at-the-holiday-ball/&#34;&gt;done for the first time last year&lt;/a&gt;, for the annual &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/pages/Pittsburgh-Holiday-Ball/283731778337030&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Contras and Squares Holiday Ball&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My experience at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/events/383908395031216/&#34;&gt;this year&amp;rsquo;s event&lt;/a&gt; compared to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/events/308706299154491/&#34;&gt;last year&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/a&gt;, and thoughts about the future:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;preparation&#34;&gt;Preparation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, I was much more &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/11/24/preparing-to-play-irish-flute-in-the-holiday-ball/&#34;&gt;prepared&lt;/a&gt; this second time than the first time. Not only have I been playing any music at all for an entire extra year, but also, I had prior knowledge of and access to most of the music that is played every year, so I could start my practice well before the event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;costumes&#34;&gt;Costumes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby wanted me to dress up again. Since people enjoyed my wearing red pants last year, I wore them again this year. I was tired of the whole green thing, however, and so I wore a pink shirt and red vest to go all out on the red theme. I added a sport jacket also, one that had been too big for me my whole life till now; it turns out that my blazer that I wore last year is too small now, as my chest has noticeably expanded in the past year (probably because of weight lifting, posture changes, and playing wind instruments). I added a beret that I&amp;rsquo;d never worn before.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/holiday-ball-2012/franklin.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Abby came up with her own colorful outfit.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/holiday-ball-2012/abby-octave-mandolin.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;venue&#34;&gt;Venue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was afraid that Swisshelm Park Community Center would be super cold again like last year, but I did bring my Handeze fingerless gloves just in case. It turned out that the place was warm (it&amp;rsquo;s been a very warm &amp;ldquo;winter&amp;rdquo;), and so I did not have any problems feeling cold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;on-stage&#34;&gt;On stage&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year I think there were somewhat fewer musicians in the Holiday Ball Orchestra than last year. I thought this was actually a good thing. Last year there were some real problems with space and also with ensemble balance (there were a whole lot of violins last year, for example).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;instruments&#34;&gt;Instruments&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I brought my modern flute, wooden keyless Irish flute, and tin whistle. Last year I had played primarily recorder, but this year I chose not to play recorder at all: the Irish flute was what I wanted to use as much as possible for this music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also brought my melodica! I had practiced playing the Hallelujah Chorus part of the Grand March using it and was excited to make my melodica debut. I also planned to use it in some of the Christmas songs, such as &amp;ldquo;Frosty the Snowman&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby brought an &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Octave_mandolin&#34;&gt;octave mandolin&lt;/a&gt; she had been borrowing. She started playing mandolin just this year, and octave mandolin just in the past couple of weeks, I think. This instrument is so much better suited to the music, she says, than her tamburitza she played last year.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/holiday-ball-2012/instruments.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Our instruments&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Several &amp;ldquo;kazumpets&amp;rdquo; (kazoo trumpets) were also provided by Lynette and Jim, and passed out to whoever wanted to play them during certain songs. Abby took one.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/holiday-ball-2012/abby-kazumpet.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby with kazumpet&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;dancing&#34;&gt;Dancing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since Abby and I have now actually done some &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/10/07/my-first-contra-dance-workshop-unexpected-fun/&#34;&gt;contra dancing together&lt;/a&gt;, there was a question of whether we would do any dancing. Abby and I discussed this before the event; Abby was very excited to play music on octave mandolin, and so she did not want to dance, so we did no dancing. Like I said last year: &amp;ldquo;We can always dance some other time.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the other musicians were very excited about dancing and pre-arranged to spend one half or the other of the time dancing instead of playing music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I saw a lot of familiar faces among the dancers, thanks to having met some of them when doing French and contra dances at CMU, and others I met from non-dance contexts elsewhere in the past year in Pittsburgh. It was nice to see my friend Henry and his girlfriend Gina at the dance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;off-and-running&#34;&gt;Off and running&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marlin was the caller again as usual and the evening proceeded with the Grand March and then the whole big assortment of jigs, reels, waltzes, Christmas songs, and a couple of interesting new pieces for this year.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/holiday-ball-2012/grand-march.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Grand March&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t have additional interesting photos or videos to share from during the event, because I took none: after the initial Grand March, I was entirely focused just on playing music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;overall-experience&#34;&gt;Overall experience&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was far less nervous than I was last year. Also, I positioned myself near, rather than deliberately far away from, a microphone, in order to be more audible. I don&amp;rsquo;t actually know what I sounded like, but some dancers during intermission commented that they liked the sound of the wooden Irish flute, so I guess it must have been audible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Playing music for hours is tiring, especially when it is so fast and there are so many notes. Of course, nobody is required to play all the notes all the time. I picked and chose when to take breaks, typically alternating repeats or entire sections. And there is definitely a limit to how long I can play flutes before my mouth gives up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the second half, a guy who had danced during the first half played a keyed Irish flute and tin whistle with us. I hadn&amp;rsquo;t seen him at the two of three rehearsals I had attended, so I hadn&amp;rsquo;t known someone else would be playing those instruments. As a result, I changed some things up in the second half, by playing the tin whistle sometimes when he was playing the flute, and vice versa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did play the melodica as planned, but noticed that the intonation was poor in the lower notes, so I backed off. I&amp;rsquo;ll have to fix this problem before I do more melodica playing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I chose not to force myself to &amp;ldquo;achieve&amp;rdquo; some of the &amp;ldquo;goals&amp;rdquo; I set last year, which were to do some solos and nontrivial ornamentation/improvisation. I felt that because of the natural of my musical focus all this year, I hadn&amp;rsquo;t had time to devote to getting good enough to really justify taking the spotlight for some tunes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The music is still crazy fast: I am still not able to play everything quite properly at the appropriate tempo. Frustrating, but that&amp;rsquo;s OK. I expect to continue to improve my technique; I&amp;rsquo;m already so much better than I was last year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I very much enjoyed performing for the Holiday Ball this year. And I feel like the Holiday Ball Orchestra sounded better this year than we did last year, and some dancers remarked on this also. I think there are several reasons for this. One is that we had some people coming back for the second time (like me), much improved. Another is that there were slightly fewer people, which I think creates a tighter ensemble.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;goals-for-the-future&#34;&gt;Goals for the future&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right now, I&amp;rsquo;m just totally exhausted and happy to be done with music performance of any kind this year. It&amp;rsquo;s been a very tough week, a very tough month, and a very tough two months in my life, with all the things that piled up on me since the end of October.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because December always ends up being so frantic for me, for next year I need to better plan what activities I pursue during this time of year. Last year, I was totally set on playing again this year in the Holiday Ball. Now, I am not sure whether I will continue for next year. It&amp;rsquo;s a question of priorities, and I need to plan what I will be doing next year in December. If I do it again next year, then clearly I want to be doing some solos!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;thank-yous&#34;&gt;Thank yous&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, I have to thank Lynette for organizing the music scores and putting it into booklets for everyone. Jim made the kazumpets. Donna, Allison, and Maro led the rehearsals as well as conducted and played their instruments with enthusiasm; I&amp;rsquo;ve been really happy to have met them a year ago, because I&amp;rsquo;ve been encountering them in other musical contexts in Pittsburgh in the past year too!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We play for the dancers, and so I really appreciate it when they take note of our playing and respond to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And none of this would happened without Abby, who got me into the whole scene in the first place. I&amp;rsquo;ve met so many musicians and dancers, and tried out different instruments and musical styles and dances in the past year, thanks to Abby!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Preparing to play Irish flute in the Holiday Ball</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/11/24/preparing-to-play-irish-flute-in-the-holiday-ball/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Nov 2012 20:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/11/24/preparing-to-play-irish-flute-in-the-holiday-ball/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://pittsburghcontra.org/wp-content/uploads/2011/12/contra_header21.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Pittsburgh Contras and Squares&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A very important event for me last year was joining Abby in playing music at the annual &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburghcontra.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Contras and Squares&lt;/a&gt; Holiday Ball at the Swisshelm Park Community Center as part of the &amp;ldquo;Holiday Ball Orchestra&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I started to prepare to play music for the Holiday Ball (Friday, December 14) again: I have three weeks to practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What progress have I made in the past year on the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/16/playing-recorder-and-flute-at-the-holiday-ball/&#34;&gt;goals I listed after last year&amp;rsquo;s event&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;improvement-at-instruments&#34;&gt;Improvement at instruments&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, I wrote: &amp;ldquo;I want to be much better at all the instruments I would play in it (recorder, flute, tin whistle)&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My status this year:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m better at &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/recorder/&#34;&gt;recorder&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m much better at &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/flute/&#34;&gt;flute&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve only barely worked on &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/tin-whistle/&#34;&gt;tin whistle&lt;/a&gt;, but am automatically better at it because of getting better at other instruments.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I unexpectedly got an &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/irish-flute/&#34;&gt;Irish flute&lt;/a&gt;, which I have mostly been playing for &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/french-dance/&#34;&gt;French dance&lt;/a&gt;, but which &lt;strong&gt;I intend to be my main instrument for the Holiday Ball&lt;/strong&gt;!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From a sound and style point of view, the Irish flute is clearly the best of my instruments to use for the Holiday Ball. So I read through my copies of the Holiday Ball music (lots of jigs, reels, waltzes) tonight at speed, to see where I stand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, I could play (on any instrument) barely any of the music at speed, even on my best instrument at the time, which was soprano recorder. I was reduced to sitting out some tunes or playing just a single note each measure, when I otherwise would have been unable to continue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, I found that I could get through most of the selections OK at speed, but somewhat sloppily and inaccurately. I would &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; be happy to have to perform this music at speed tonight; I would rather sit out or simplify rather than try to play something beyond me. But I have three weeks to improve significantly, and I believe I can improve enough that when the time comes, I won&amp;rsquo;t be sitting out most of the tunes the way I kind of did last year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the fingering of the tin whistle is the same as for my keyless Irish flute, I can also choose to use the tin whistle where I feel appropriate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;microphone&#34;&gt;Microphone&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, I wrote: &amp;ldquo;I want to be proficient and confident enough to sit by a microphone&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea of being in the foreground is still a bit daunting to me, but I think after I get in some good practice over the next week or so, I&amp;rsquo;ll feel confident about not just being in the background the way I was last year. I do think it would be nice to have an audible Irish flute in our performance for the dancers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;solos&#34;&gt;Solos&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, I wrote: &amp;ldquo;I want to do some solos, with stylistically appropriate improvisations&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even scarier. I&amp;rsquo;ve been working through &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/_posts/2012/06/12/ordered-the-casey-burns-small-handed-irish-flute/&#34;&gt;Grey Larsen&amp;rsquo;s book&lt;/a&gt;, which is amazingly detailed and good, but as Irish music has &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; at all been my focus during this year of music for me, I&amp;rsquo;m nowhere at the level of passing for a traditional Irish musician. Still, there is time to work up a sound basic practical level of ornamentation, I think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll have to evaluate, after a week or two, what I feel comfortable doing on stage. The basic rule is: better to play an melody simply and beautifully, unornamented, rather than do something badly and in poor taste and technique!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;dance&#34;&gt;Dance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, I wrote: &amp;ldquo;Maybe I should learn some of the dances and perform some too&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that in fact, I did learn some &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/10/07/my-first-contra-dance-workshop-unexpected-fun/&#34;&gt;contra dance&lt;/a&gt;, so depending on how Abby would like to split up playing music and dancing, I would be, unlike last year, totally up for participating as a dancer as well as a musician.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a lot of fun playing music at the Holiday Ball last year and hope to enjoy it again, and this time with a higher level of musicality and a higher level of contribution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re in the Pittsburgh area and like contra dancing, make sure to put Friday, December 14 on your calendar already, and come to the Holiday Ball!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My first time in a public music jam: intense fun with Chris Norman and David Greenberg</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/04/21/my-first-time-in-a-public-music-jam-intense-fun-with-chris-norman-and-david-greenberg/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Apr 2012 13:44:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/04/21/my-first-time-in-a-public-music-jam-intense-fun-with-chris-norman-and-david-greenberg/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://fbcdn-sphotos-a.akamaihd.net/hphotos-ak-ash3/544714_10150682065771513_55075526512_9775036_876594193_n.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;David Greenberg and Chris Norman and the rest of us&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Friday evening, Abby and I packed up various musical instruments of ours, and attended an event that I had been eagerly awaiting for over three weeks since I first found out about it from Annie of the local &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.andrew.cmu.edu/user/lukas/pcars/Welcome.html&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh recorder gang&lt;/a&gt;: a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rbsp.org/Jam%20Session%20Flyer.pdf&#34;&gt;jam session open to the public&lt;/a&gt; being offered by &lt;a href=&#34;http://chrisnorman.com/&#34;&gt;Chris Norman&lt;/a&gt;, flutist, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.davidgreenberg.ca/&#34;&gt;David Greenberg&lt;/a&gt;, violinist the day before &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rbsp.org/11-12c6.aspx&#34;&gt;their concert&lt;/a&gt; the next evening to close the current season of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rbsp.org/&#34;&gt;Renaissance and Baroque of Pittsburgh&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was so excited by this opportunity to jam with such esteemed musicians. Norman and Greenberg specialize in playing Irish, Scottish, Cape Breton and Baroque music. I&amp;rsquo;ve come to love playing the rhythmic, danceable music of the old days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I learned a lot from the experience, and would like to share what I learned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;some-photos-of-the-event&#34;&gt;Some photos of the event&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/pages/Pittsburgh-Renaissance-and-Baroque/55075526512&#34;&gt;Facebook page of the Pittsburgh Renaissance and Baroque&lt;/a&gt; has a bunch of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/media/set/?set=a.10150682065546513.394216.55075526512&amp;amp;type=3&#34;&gt;photos of the event&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;ve used a couple of these here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;preparation&#34;&gt;Preparation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;my-instruments&#34;&gt;My instruments&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been spending most of my daily music practice all year working on the modern &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/flute/&#34;&gt;flute&lt;/a&gt;; I have not reported on my progress in over a month because I&amp;rsquo;ve been too busy &lt;em&gt;doing&lt;/em&gt; rather than &lt;em&gt;writing&lt;/em&gt;, but will catch up with the writing sometime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But for this jam session, I had decided very quickly that I was &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; going to be bringing my modern flute to play, because I do prefer to play older music on other instruments; I planned to bring the following instruments instead:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;my &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/tin-whistle/&#34;&gt;tin whistle&lt;/a&gt;, which I bought the week of St. Patrick&amp;rsquo;s Day in March (for a party I haven&amp;rsquo;t written about yet but which radically changed my life)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;an assortment of &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/recorder/&#34;&gt;recorders&lt;/a&gt;: I decided to just bring my soprano and alto&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;my &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/baroque-flute/&#34;&gt;Baroque flute&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, interspersed with my continuing work on the modern flute, I have also done some maintenance practice of tin whistle and recorders. The most difficult challenge was trying to get serious about Baroque flute: the one-keyed flute is &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.oldflutes.com/charts/onekey/index.htm&#34;&gt;very, very, very tricky to play in tune&lt;/a&gt;. Sometimes I wonder whether it&amp;rsquo;s worth the bother. But I tend to be inspired by quirky challenges whose benefit I don&amp;rsquo;t fully understand immediately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ideally, I would own an &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.caseyburnsflutes.com/cat_d.php&#34;&gt;Irish flute&lt;/a&gt;, preferably with a number of keys to aid with intonation and fingering, but given that I don&amp;rsquo;t currently intend to specialize in Irish music, and am still working with the tin whistle anyway, I cannot at all justify buying an Irish flute at this time. So I&amp;rsquo;ve been working on using the related Baroque flute instead, for traditional Irish or Scottish music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;abby-s-instruments&#34;&gt;Abby&amp;rsquo;s instruments&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby started learning mandolin just this year, joining the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pittsburghmandolinsociety.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Mandolin Orchestra&lt;/a&gt;, so I was excited that she decided early on to bring it to the jam session. (And I look forward to seeing her play for the first time in the orchestra&amp;rsquo;s concert on Mother&amp;rsquo;s Day coming up in three weeks!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She also brought a frame drum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-event&#34;&gt;The event!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;arrival&#34;&gt;Arrival&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I arrived a little late, so I scrambled to get ready while a whole bunch of people were already gathered. Many people were sitting in back just to watch and listen, while maybe twenty of us were armed with instruments of all kinds, ready to have some fun!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://fbcdn-sphotos-a.akamaihd.net/hphotos-ak-prn1/541085_10150682067126513_55075526512_9775042_292845062_n.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;We played lots of different instruments&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We ran into half a dozen people we knew from various of our musical circles, including Annie from recorder, a guy Abby knew from mandolin, and some fellow &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/16/playing-recorder-and-flute-at-the-holiday-ball/&#34;&gt;Holiday Ball&lt;/a&gt; musicians.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was intrigued by the couple of people who had actual keyed Irish flutes and eager to hear them play (it would turn out, of course, that they were very, very good).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;music-scores&#34;&gt;Music scores&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So each of us got a packet of around twenty pages of music. We didn&amp;rsquo;t play all of it, of course, but it was a good basis for sight reading along with Chris and David leading the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much of the music went at breakneck pace that I&amp;rsquo;m still not proficient enough to sight reading perfectly, but my (yet unreported) musical adventures in the past month have made me far less self-conscious about perfection and figure out ways to cope:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it&amp;rsquo;s not necessary to play all the notes; in fast music, you can contribute just fine playing only one main note per measure or harmony change&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;you can also substitute a different, easier melodic line that is compatible with the chords&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;since sections are repeated many times, you can add more during repetitions as you feel ready to&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it&amp;rsquo;s not the end of the world to miscalculate sometimes and squeak out a harsh dissonant error; the music just keeps going, so don&amp;rsquo;t look back, only forward&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;learning-by-ear-improvisation&#34;&gt;Learning by ear, improvisation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I expected, much of the time we didn&amp;rsquo;t play music from the handed out scores at all. This was the fun I was anticipating all along (I had not really expected music scores at all, actually).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost half the time, Chris would ask us for music suggestions to offer up &lt;em&gt;by example&lt;/em&gt;, so that the volunteer would play (or sing) the melody, then the rest of us would start &amp;ldquo;learning&amp;rdquo; it by ear and join in and continue with repetitions. I had not anticipated the call for volunteers, else I would have come prepared with some favorite tunes to offer!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some people were more familiar with various tunes being offered up than I was, since they had a lot more experience with Irish, Scottish and other such music than me, so I felt awkward and lost trying to learn and play on the spot, without written music, but it was part of the whole fun, really stretching what I have usually been doing with music (very oriented toward following a written score).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve mentioned before my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/10/flute-loving-it-again/&#34;&gt;poor memory&lt;/a&gt; having a considerable impact on my life, and I worked around it again, given that I could not quickly learn the details of a melody, by just giving up and improvising around the harmony changes instead. I would like to find ways to improve my memory, but for now, I work around my limitations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;a-charming-tangent-involving-an-oboe&#34;&gt;A charming tangent involving an oboe&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it turned out that a young woman among us had come with a Baroque oboe tuned to A415 instead of the modern A440 tuning. This caused confusion, of course, when she tried to play from written scores. I&amp;rsquo;m not sure what she ended up doing: the only choices were to mentally transpose from the written scores (when we were playing music from them) or just ignore the scores and learn by ear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, Chris and David repeatedly wanted to play with her and asked her what music she had on her, and she had a variety of Baroque music scores with her (she said she was actually giving a recital the next day), and so they tried to play some stuff just with her while doing their own mental transposition so that she would get to play without mental transposition! Check out Chris hovering over the score trying to do the really hard work of transposing on the fly:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://fbcdn-sphotos-a.akamaihd.net/hphotos-ak-ash4/s720x720/295215_10150682067841513_395463764_n.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Baroque oboist with Chris and David&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;dancing&#34;&gt;Dancing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Periodically, a number of people got up to dance in the space at the side, especially when we played waltzes. It was nice to see people moving.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://fbcdn-sphotos-a.akamaihd.net/hphotos-ak-ash3/529154_10150682066471513_55075526512_9775039_758574985_n.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;A couple dancing&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;i-m-caught-on-a-photo-playing-baroque-flute&#34;&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m caught on a photo playing Baroque flute&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spent a fair amount of time playing the tin whistle, and some time on my recorders, but in the end gravitated toward the Baroque flute because it was mellower and I could draw less attention to my mistakes by playing it instead!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that a photo was taken that included me when I was playing my Baroque flute. In this photo, you can also see a guy playing tin whistle (this guy also at one point volunteered to sing a tune, and did so with quite a powerful voice, a great rendition).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://fbcdn-sphotos-a.akamaihd.net/hphotos-ak-ash2/35507_10150682067581513_55075526512_9775044_1738151368_n.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;A fellow tin whistle player, and me on Baroque flute&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My posture is really bad here. I need to sit up straight and keep my head over my body rather than straining over my neck. My only excuse is that this photo was probably taken two hours into the jam session when it was almost over, and I was having energy issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-note-on-energy-requirements&#34;&gt;A note on energy requirements&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was totally exhausted after the jam session. After Abby and I drove back home, we both had to eat something. We were starving. We should have taken a snack break at the jam session.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I weighed myself and I had lost weight. The mental demands on me were considerable, and I had really spent myself. Given that I have lost weight before when taking exams in school, or playing in chess tournaments, or doing similar activities that combine both mental demands and personal anxiety, I should have been better prepared with fuel at the event. I get the impression that I burn more energy by thinking hard than by running.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was my first time ever at a public music jam session, and I quite enjoyed it. I am grateful to Chris Norman and David Greenberg, and the Pittsburgh Renaissance and Baroque, for providing it to the community. I am always very happy for opportunities to play music with Abby, and keep remembering how she got me into this particular early traditional dance music world, through our first musical time together at the Holiday Ball.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got self-feedback about musical shortcomings for me to keep working on in order to enjoy future jam sessions, and I learned that I really need food to keep me fueled for optimal musicality!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A delayed St. Patrick&#39;s Day party: playing tin whistle and alto recorder</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/03/30/a-delayed-st-patricks-day-party-playing-tin-whistle-and-alto-recorder/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Mar 2012 22:58:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/03/30/a-delayed-st-patricks-day-party-playing-tin-whistle-and-alto-recorder/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Since so many people couldn&amp;rsquo;t make it to &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/17/st-patricks-day-party-playing-tin-whistle-and-flute/&#34;&gt;Henry&amp;rsquo;s St. Patrick&amp;rsquo;s Day party&lt;/a&gt;, Henry threw another party two weeks later, a second St. Patrick&amp;rsquo;s Day party! Abby and I attended this one too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was another huge milestone for me, musically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;chess&#34;&gt;Chess&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Henry has been playing chess very well lately in tournaments. In fact, last weekend in the big-money &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.chesstour.com/pit12.htm&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Open&lt;/a&gt;, he actually &lt;a href=&#34;http://chesstournamentservices.com/cca/tag/pittsburgh-open-2012-standings/&#34;&gt;tied for first in his section, winning $630&lt;/a&gt;, with a record of four wins and one draw, his best tournament in his life!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He sent me his games from the Pittsburgh Open, which I carefully analyzed and sent back to him with my annotations, just before the party. This was the first time I&amp;rsquo;ve analyzed games in well over a year. Doing it again sent the thrill of chess back into me. I thought I was done with chess, but now I&amp;rsquo;m vicariously living tournament chess through Henry. And I very much enjoying analyzing chess games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;music-preparation&#34;&gt;Music preparation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have learned by now that &amp;ldquo;preparation&amp;rdquo; when it comes to jamming does not amount to figuring out a few pieces. It means bringing a bunch of stuff and then figuring out what people want to hear or play with you, and then basically sight reading on the fly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So an important part of my music practice nowadays is &lt;em&gt;sight reading&lt;/em&gt;. I keep a big pile of music that I use simply to sight read.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because I felt still unready to play flute at a standard I found sufficiently acceptable to believe that people could take real pleasure in my playing, I decided not to bring my flute this time. I brought my tin whistle and recorders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;tin-whistle&#34;&gt;Tin whistle&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For tin whistle, I brought some big compilations of Irish music from the Carnegie Library, both fast and slow. I especially like slow Irish airs, not only because they&amp;rsquo;re slower and therefore &amp;ldquo;easier&amp;rdquo; to play, but because they are actually &amp;ldquo;hard&amp;rdquo; to play, in that you really have to pour yourself into expression and emotion; it&amp;rsquo;s actually easier to play fast music because you can cover up by just playing a lot of notes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;alto-recorder&#34;&gt;Alto recorder&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also brought a collection of Telemann minuets arranged for alto recorder and keyboard that I got out of the library as well. I have recently been getting a lot &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/21/flute-update-celebrating-bachs-birthday/&#34;&gt;into Baroque music&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;at-the-party&#34;&gt;At the party&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;chess-1&#34;&gt;Chess&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that David, a guy Henry knew from the Pittsburgh Chess Club tournaments, came to the party, so we spent a bit of time going over some recent games of theirs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;music-jamming&#34;&gt;Music jamming&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I felt much more comfortable than at the last party, since I was getting to know everyone, and I had not been &amp;ldquo;punished&amp;rdquo; in any way for my fumbling performances, but actually encouraged to keep playing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did soloing on tin whistle with slow Irish airs, and also did impromptu fast jigs and reels with Henry and Vassily.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what I enjoyed most was going through minuets with Henry at the piano while I played alto recorder. This being Baroque music, there was ample space for ornamentation on both parts. I have been working on the art of Baroque ornamentation, and was excited to let myself free during the repeats of the minuets we read through. At one point, Henry complimented me on my ornamentation, and I silently beamed. It&amp;rsquo;s a continual process, learning the art of ornamentation, because although there are some rules and guidelines, a lot is, as they say, a matter of having &amp;ldquo;good taste&amp;rdquo;. You want to do something interesting, but not too much, and not too distorting of the original. It&amp;rsquo;s tricky finding the right personal balance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby brought her various tamburas and mandolin to play and show Vassily.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a great time again at another of Henry&amp;rsquo;s parties. Great food, great company, fun playing music and talking chess.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>St. Patrick&#39;s Day party: playing tin whistle and flute</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/03/17/st-patricks-day-party-playing-tin-whistle-and-flute/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 Mar 2012 22:41:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/03/17/st-patricks-day-party-playing-tin-whistle-and-flute/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/st-patricks-2012/henry-franklin.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Henry and Franklin&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/st-patricks-2012/henry-franklin-abby.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Henry and Franklin and Abby&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Abby and I went to &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/01/27/a-new-friends-very-musical-birthday-party-changed-my-life/&#34;&gt;Henry&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/a&gt; place for a St. Patrick&amp;rsquo;s Day party, for which &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/12/quitting-the-cmu-all-university-orchestra-one-of-the-hardest-decisions-in-my-life/&#34;&gt;I had promised to play some music&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Today was one of the happiest days in my entire life!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;music-preparation&#34;&gt;Music preparation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All week, of course, I&amp;rsquo;ve been practicing &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/12/quitting-the-cmu-all-university-orchestra-one-of-the-hardest-decisions-in-my-life/&#34;&gt;tin whistle&lt;/a&gt;, and also some flute as well, in preparation for this party.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, I bought a brand new tin whistle just yesterday at the local music store down the street from home, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.acousticmusicworks.com/&#34;&gt;Acoustic Music Works&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/clarke-sweetone.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;My new Clarke Sweetone tin whistle&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It was a cheap &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.clarketinwhistle.com/&#34;&gt;Clarke&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.clarketinwhistle.com/products/sweetone-tin-whistle.aspx&#34;&gt;Sweetone&lt;/a&gt;. I got this to replace the Feadóg tin whistle that &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/11/learning-another-instrument-the-tin-whistle/&#34;&gt;I used initially to learn&lt;/a&gt; but was badly out of tune.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had picked up from the library a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lemccullough.com/Music-WhistleDVD.html&#34;&gt;nice little tutorial&lt;/a&gt; on tin whistle and learned a few tunes and some basics of ornamentation:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.lemccullough.com/Music-WhistleDVD_files/DVD%20cover-front-sm-filtered.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Learn to Play Irish Tinwhistle&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Completely unlike the classical orchestra world, here, the tunes are very easy, but all the interest is in the personal solo expression and ornamentation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;at-the-party&#34;&gt;At the party&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were, of course, fewer guests than at Henry&amp;rsquo;s birthday party. That was good, because it meant it was easier to get to know some people better (whom we had met at the earlier party) and also some new people we hadn&amp;rsquo;t met before. Actually, since Abby and I arrived very early, we got to know Henry better and vice versa before other guests arrived.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/st-patricks-2012/abby-franklin-st-patricks.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby and Franklin in green&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;chess&#34;&gt;Chess&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s always chess at Henry&amp;rsquo;s parties, because the kids like to play, and some adults too. I didn&amp;rsquo;t play this time; last time I did, but it was very time-consuming (Abby had to drag me away so we could go home), and I wasn&amp;rsquo;t playing any music then!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/st-patricks-2012/chess.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Boys playing chess&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;music-jamming&#34;&gt;Music jamming&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, there was jamming, before and after dinner. One of the young guys, Vassily, was eager to play accordion, and played waltzes and stuff from memory, and he had also brought a tin whistle and book, having heard I was coming with a tin whistle. (But he didn&amp;rsquo;t actually end up playing his!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that Vassily is interested in a wide variety of music, including Balkan, so Abby got all excited about meeting someone new who into the music she likes. Abby brought her tambourine and joined in a bunch of the jamming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;dancing&#34;&gt;Dancing&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any time I hear someone on accordion playing a waltz or polka, I just have to dance with Abby!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/st-patricks-2012/abby-franklin.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby and Franklin dancing&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h4 id=&#34;tin-whistle&#34;&gt;Tin whistle&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d only had a couple of days to work on tin whistle playing, so I&amp;rsquo;d only prepared to play a couple of tunes. But after I quickly ran out, people wanted more. And Henry wanted to accompany me with accordion or piano. I figured, what the heck, I&amp;rsquo;ll sight read some of the stuff I hadn&amp;rsquo;t even looked at in the tutor book. So I did, Henry figured out chords quickly, I stumbled around with lots of &amp;ldquo;wrong notes&amp;rdquo;, and it was all nevertheless OK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, not all of my notes were actually &amp;ldquo;wrong&amp;rdquo;: they just weren&amp;rsquo;t what was printed, but as long as stuff goes with the harmonies, there is no real sense in which the notes are wrong! That&amp;rsquo;s what&amp;rsquo;s so liberating about playing Irish music. I&amp;rsquo;m not following some orchestra score where every dynamic, every flurry of fast notes is carefully notated and is supposed to be followed exactly. And nevertheless, this freedom does not mean pure chaos. You still have to be aware of the stylistic conventions, of the implied shapes of phrases that you want to maintain or transform in some consistent way, etc. I really feel that playing this kind of music makes one much more connected with the role of &amp;ldquo;composer&amp;rdquo;, being very actively engaged and making short-term and long-term decisions about where to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vassily and I did some random jamming where he tried to accompany me as I read through some Irish music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;flute&#34;&gt;Flute&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also played flute for the first time in my life for people outside the context of school band and the CMU All-University orchestra I had just quit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I chose to play an arrangement of &amp;ldquo;Londonderry Air&amp;rdquo; for flute and piano, from &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/20/much-progress-playing-flute/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;I Used to Play Flute&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; so Henry accompanied me. I was standing as I played. I was so &lt;em&gt;nervous&lt;/em&gt; that my leg shook like crazy and I thought I was going to fall. I should have played sitting down. It was a huge deal for me, working up the courage to try to play flute while feeling like I was still a rank beginner (I still have terrible breath support and tone). I knew I didn&amp;rsquo;t play well, but I&amp;rsquo;d gone out there and done my best. I was proud of myself for that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed continuing to get to know Henry and his other guests better, and feeling more and more comfortable about playing music with them and for them. I felt like I was really coming out of my shell, both socially and musically. This is only the beginning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2012-03-30&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-03-30)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out my report on &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/30/a-delayed-st-patricks-day-party-playing-tin-whistle-and-alto-recorder/&#34;&gt;the next Henry party Abby and I attended&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quitting the CMU All-University Orchestra: one of the hardest decisions in my life</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/03/12/quitting-the-cmu-all-university-orchestra-one-of-the-hardest-decisions-in-my-life/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Mar 2012 22:45:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/03/12/quitting-the-cmu-all-university-orchestra-one-of-the-hardest-decisions-in-my-life/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s the Monday after what would have been the regular Sunday evening CMU All-University Orchestra rehearsal, except that there was no rehearsal because of Spring Break.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surprise (or not)!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have decided to immediately &lt;em&gt;quit&lt;/em&gt; the CMU AUO that I had &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/02/01/joining-an-orchestra-learning-in-the-face-of-terror/&#34;&gt;just joined less than two months ago&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have already told everyone that I&amp;rsquo;m quitting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t like quitting. I don&amp;rsquo;t like being a quitter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what&amp;rsquo;s the story? And what next?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;orchestra-morale-problems&#34;&gt;Orchestra morale problems&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Five days ago, I reported on &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/07/flute-taking-a-break-while-clarifying-my-goals/&#34;&gt;problems in the orchestra&lt;/a&gt; and deciding that I would probably quit the orchestra after the spring term is over. The memories of that have lingered in my mind. And my relief yesterday at not having rehearsal was a real message to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2012-03-21&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-03-21)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maria just sent the mailing list (which I&amp;rsquo;m still on despite having quit the orchestra) an email saying, &amp;ldquo;It seems that over spring break we may have lost much of what we did in the first portion of the semester.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No kidding. As I had observed earlier, people clearly just weren&amp;rsquo;t taking practice seriously. They probably didn&amp;rsquo;t touch their instruments when they went on spring break. I&amp;rsquo;m so glad I quit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;personal-musical-goals&#34;&gt;Personal musical goals&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past couple of days while off the hook on orchestral practice, I had an opportunity to think about &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/10/flute-loving-it-again/&#34;&gt;what I actually love about music, and what role I want it to play in my life&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;a-chance-opportunity&#34;&gt;A chance opportunity&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that Abby and I have just been invited to a St. Patrick&amp;rsquo;s Day party by Henry, whose &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/01/27/a-new-friends-very-musical-birthday-party-changed-my-life/&#34;&gt;birthday party less than two months ago&lt;/a&gt; had so moved me musically (and right after I had joined the AUO). I was so eager to attend that I asked Henry whether I should bring a tin whistle and play some Irish music, and he said, sure! I had promised myself after his birthday party that if we were ever invited to a party by him, I would play music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;brute-reality&#34;&gt;Brute reality&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, I can no longer deny the reality: being in an orchestra is &lt;em&gt;completely contrary&lt;/em&gt; to the kind of musical life I actually enjoy and want. I need to play music of my choice, I want to improvise, I want to play in small groups. The task of mastering some difficult flute parts in a big orchestral work and being a tiny part of a performance, &lt;em&gt;does not appeal to me at all&lt;/em&gt;, even if I could do it well (which I currently cannot at all).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a concrete example: I could spend my time this week slogging away at AUO music practice, or I could be learning some tunes on tin whistle so that I can play them on Saturday at Henry&amp;rsquo;s party and have a blast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s no comparison, whether in the short term or in the long term.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But emotionally, it&amp;rsquo;s just tough to quit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-did-i-really-ever-hope-to-get-out-of-orchestra&#34;&gt;What did I really ever hope to get out of orchestra?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think part of me hoped that somehow, being in an orchestra was a standard rite of passage that a &amp;ldquo;serious&amp;rdquo; musician should do. When I was a kid, I was kind of envious that classmates joined the school orchestra, while I remained out of music entirely. My younger sister played violin in various orchestras in middle school and in high school and college.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But now it occurs to me that not much of what I could get out of orchestra would help me with my real musical goals anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-art-of-quitting&#34;&gt;The art of quitting&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a policy of never just &lt;em&gt;quitting&lt;/em&gt; something, but &lt;em&gt;replacing&lt;/em&gt; the void instead. &lt;em&gt;Quitting&lt;/em&gt; is negative. &lt;em&gt;Replacing&lt;/em&gt; is positive. In my case, quitting orchestra frees up a considerable amount of time to work toward my real musical goals. Instead of fruitlessly working on difficult flute parts that are currently beyond my capabilities, and beyond my interests, I can focus on gradually improving at the music I do want to play, and building the technique necessary, without arbitrary deadlines like some big concert.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;resources&#34;&gt;Resources&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the United States, we are constantly bombarded with messages in the media and general culture not to be a &amp;ldquo;quitter&amp;rdquo;. And I got that a lot from my parents (who came from Taiwan) when I was a kid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My current point of view: &lt;em&gt;not learning to be an effective quitter was the single worst mistake of my first decades in life&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some articles that really resonated with me about the benefits of quitting correctly:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.projecthappilyeverafter.com/2009/03/sometimes-its-better-to-be-a-quitter/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Sometimes it&amp;rsquo;s better to be a quitter&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cormackcarr.com/2009/12/05/how-to-be-a-quitter/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;How to be a quitter&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s never easy for me to quit something. Part of me always feels like I failed, wasn&amp;rsquo;t good enough, wasn&amp;rsquo;t courageous enough, or something like that. Maybe sometimes that is actually true. But other times, it clearly is not. All signs point to quitting orchestra as the best thing I can do now for my flute playing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-is-your-own-relationship-to-quitting&#34;&gt;What is your own relationship to quitting?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is your gut reaction when hearing about someone quitting (like me just now), or when considering quitting something yourself? Is your &lt;em&gt;gut reaction&lt;/em&gt; one of disdain and shame, or of liberation? Is this a result of your upbringing, or the nature of your relationships with peers? Is it a deliberate rational philosophical position? Or is primarily emotional, based on either moral sentiment or ego?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When was the last time you quit and felt &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt; about it? When was the last time you quit and felt &lt;em&gt;bad&lt;/em&gt; about it? When was the last time you quit and &lt;em&gt;at the time&lt;/em&gt; felt one way, but later felt you had made the wrong decision?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fun at the East End Food Co-op Winterfest</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/12/18/fun-at-the-east-end-food-co-op-winterfest/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Dec 2011 18:52:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/12/18/fun-at-the-east-end-food-co-op-winterfest/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Saturday, Abby and I went to the annual &lt;a href=&#34;http://eastendfoodcoop.com/&#34;&gt;East End Food Co-op&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/events/144638855639374/&#34;&gt;Winterfest&lt;/a&gt; with John, as we did last year, and were joined by Mark, Jin, and their daughter Julia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This family-friendly annual event serves as a fund raiser, and features a variety of vegetarian and vegan food as well as live music. This year, the draw was &lt;a href=&#34;http://davidshelow.com/guitar/performance/ensemble.php&#34;&gt;Bury the Cabbage&lt;/a&gt;, a group playing Irish traditional music.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/eefc-winterfest-2011/bury-the-cabbage.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Bury the Cabbage&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Every year, I&amp;rsquo;ve bumped into a good number of people here that I haven&amp;rsquo;t seen for a while, and this year was no exception.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;young-children&#34;&gt;Young children&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The little kids quickly and spontaneously found one another other and started running around and playing, so Julia had her fun. They all seemed to like the balloon man.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/eefc-winterfest-2011/balloons.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Young children love balloons&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;food&#34;&gt;Food&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was plenty of food available at the Winterfest. It was all vegetarian and vegan. I stuffed myself silly, especially enjoying the roasted peppers, eggplant, zucchini, and sweet potato pancakes. There was pasta with tofu, falafel, mushroom, salad, fruit, and other selection. I sampled them all.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/eefc-winterfest-2011/getting-food.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;People getting food&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There was a wide selection of cookies, carefully classified. Some were vegan, others were gluten-free. There were too many varieties for me to even try one of each.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/eefc-winterfest-2011/cookies.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Wide selection of cookies&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;people-in-pittsburgh&#34;&gt;People in Pittsburgh&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I recognized one person in the Irish band, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lesgetchell.com/&#34;&gt;Les&lt;/a&gt;. We had met him at a party at one point but not known much about him. It&amp;rsquo;s funny how in Pittsburgh it is easy to run into the same person in different contexts!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We saw &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cleanlink.com/sm/article/Endurance-Running-Takes-Will-Desire--550&#34;&gt;Sam Bertenthal&lt;/a&gt; again with his son Fernando. Sam is a local ultrarunner whom I first met in &lt;a href=&#34;../../images/franklin-finishing-sammys-birthday-run-2006.jpg&#34;&gt;2006&lt;/a&gt; when I ran in his annual &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.runnersworld.com/community/forums/runner-communities/masters/sammys-6-hour-birthday-run-race-report-new-twists?plckFindPostKey=Cat:Runner%20CommunitiesForum:648106477Discussion:926106577Post:836106577&#34;&gt;Sammy&amp;rsquo;s Birthday Run&lt;/a&gt; for the first time. I ran just 27.5 miles that year (long enough to go beyond the marathon distance of 26.2 for my own pride), and went back to do the same in &lt;a href=&#34;../../images/franklin-finishing-sammys-birthday-run-2008.jpg&#34;&gt;2008&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sam said hello and reminded me that next year he will be holding his race on July 14. We&amp;rsquo;ll see whether I&amp;rsquo;m up for it again. I haven&amp;rsquo;t been running long distances in recent years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also saw some other people we recognized as regulars to the Winterfest, such as Linda of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.salsaritmodance.org/&#34;&gt;Salsa Ritmo&lt;/a&gt;, a salsa dance instructor through whom Abby and I actually first got together at a party of hers (and Linda&amp;rsquo;s dance partner is Mark Fuhs, who was my classmate at CMU when I got him into ballroom dancing, then he discovered salsa and got serious about it and became an instructor).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.myspace.com/kimberleefaught&#34;&gt;Kimberlee Faught&lt;/a&gt; is a regular at the annual Winterfest also. If you live in the city of Pittsburgh, you&amp;rsquo;ve probably seen her around playing violin in Squirrel Hill on Murray or Forbes (or elsewhere) when the weather is nice. I bump into her running in 5K races also!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I mention all this only because I really want to highlight how much I love that in Pittsburgh, I never feel alone. Wherever I go, I&amp;rsquo;ll run into someone I know or have met from somewhere. This feel is very important to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;music-and-dancing&#34;&gt;Music and dancing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We enjoyed listening to the music, and Abby and I got up to dance a couple of waltzes (last year . There were some people who attempted to do Irish step dancing. Unfortunately, Abby and I don&amp;rsquo;t know it, so we didn&amp;rsquo;t try it. Maybe that&amp;rsquo;s something else worth learning!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sorry, no videos this year of Abby and me dancing! Last year John did get video of us &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SKWXpkHF20g&#34;&gt;dancing waltz to Zydeco Dogz&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I noticed that &lt;a href=&#34;http://brucefoley.com/&#34;&gt;Bruce Foley&lt;/a&gt; of Bury the Cabbage was playing what looked like an oversized tin whistle, so during a break I asked him about the instrument. Indeed, it was a whistle in D an octave lower than the little tin whistle I had started playing. He said the best place to get these whistles is &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.burkewhistles.com/&#34;&gt;Burke&lt;/a&gt;. I have to confess I&amp;rsquo;m not currently in the market for a low whistle, much less any professional-grade whistle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;interviews-about-the-east-end-food-co-op-updated-2012-12-04&#34;&gt;Interviews about the East End Food Co-op (updated 2012-12-04)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the party, there was a call for volunteers to be interviewed about the East End Food Co-op, how they use it, and what it means to them. Here&amp;rsquo;s a video that was made from the interviews.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe src=&#34;http://player.vimeo.com/video/37628327?badge=0&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; height=&#34;281&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen allowFullScreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://vimeo.com/37628327&#34;&gt;Winterfest with the East End Food Co-op&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href=&#34;http://vimeo.com/user10547223&#34;&gt;East End Food Co-op&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&#34;http://vimeo.com&#34;&gt;Vimeo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was getting to be bedtime for Julia, so Mark and Jin prepared to go home, and John, Abby, and I also packed up (we were all told to take leftover food, of which there was plenty) and went home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With filling our bellies, hearing a variety of music on different instruments and, dancing, hanging out with friends, people-watching, it was a fun evening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am grateful to the East End Food Co-op for organizing this annual event and providing the food, and the Jewish Community Center for hosting its location again. I am grateful that Mark, Jin, Julia, and John were able to join Abby and me for the evening. I am grateful for the opportunity to listen to excellent live music and dance to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2012-15-15&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-15-15)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following year, we attended the annual Winterfest &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/15/east-end-food-co-op-winterfest-2012/&#34;&gt;again&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Playing recorder and flute at the Holiday Ball!</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/12/17/playing-recorder-and-flute-at-the-holiday-ball/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 Dec 2011 23:17:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/12/17/playing-recorder-and-flute-at-the-holiday-ball/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;So on Friday, after &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/01/im-going-to-perform-music-much-sooner-than-i-expected-monday/&#34;&gt;just two weeks&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/05/busy-evening-performing-at-phipps-followed-by-rehearsal-for-another-gig/&#34;&gt;practicing music&lt;/a&gt; for the &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburghcontra.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Contras and Squares&lt;/a&gt; Holiday Ball, the moment of truth finally arrived.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The event went pretty well! Here is a report, with some photos and videos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;costumes&#34;&gt;Costumes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby had said that we were supposed to show up dressed &amp;ldquo;festively&amp;rdquo;, so I thought, OK, I&amp;rsquo;ll wear something green and something red, for the holiday season. I immediately thought of a green shirt and red pants I have. Abby came up with the idea that I should wear a hat, and so I picked out one of my hats (which I only wear for costume parties) and she put a green band around it. I feared being cold (and rightfully so, it turned out), and so I added a blazer and a tie to the outfit. A good number of people seemed to like this colorful outfit!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/holiday-ball-2011/abby-franklin-holiday-ball.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby and Franklin posing before event&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;venue&#34;&gt;Venue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had never been to the Swisshelm Park Community Center before, but since Abby had, she had warned me that it was cold on stage at this time last year. Indeed it was. I was very, very happy to be wearing a hat and my blazer. In the future, I&amp;rsquo;ll remember to bring my Handeze fingerless gloves to gigs anywhere (and pack a hat and layers of clothing), to keep my hands warm when not performing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;on-stage&#34;&gt;On stage&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Around twenty-five musicians eventually gathered on stage. There was just enough space for all of us, although it was crowded. I got put in the &amp;ldquo;wind section&amp;rdquo;, armed with my main instrument I had finally decided on for this gig, soprano recorder (which I had started practicing the music for only a couple of days before!!), along with my secondary instrument, flute, which I planned to use only on the Hallelujah Chorus and some waltzes, and finally, the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/11/learning-another-instrument-the-tin-whistle/&#34;&gt;tin whistle&lt;/a&gt;, which I did not have enough time to play well enough for most of the music, and therefore planned to possibly use on only one piece.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/holiday-ball-2011/franklin-soprano-recorder.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin posing with soprano recorder&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/holiday-ball-2011/franklin-flute.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin posing with flute&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby sat to my right with her tamburitza. This was the first time we have ever played music together at an event!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/holiday-ball-2011/abby-tamburitza.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby posing with tamburitza&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;off-and-running&#34;&gt;Off and running&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marlin, the caller, kicked things off and the bagpiper led the Grand March and after he played for a while, we started playing. Before each group of dances, Marlin gave a brief lesson to the dancers.  We had jigs, reels, waltzes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout, Donna and Allison split the conducting, with Maro at the keyboard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;some-videos&#34;&gt;Some videos&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I managed to get some videos with my digital camera while on stage, because I didn&amp;rsquo;t play continuously. We often did three or four or even more repeats, such that I would sit out and rest and have an opportunity to switch instruments or take photos. With twenty-five of us playing, there wasn&amp;rsquo;t a need for any one individual to be playing lots of notes all the time (except for Maro at the keyboard!). We also changed things up so that we&amp;rsquo;d alternate among the &amp;ldquo;reeds&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;winds&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;fiddles&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;strings&amp;rdquo;, etc. for variety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a clip of me playing soprano recorder during Coleraine:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/JZqMmpwQwZE&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a view of some of the others during Coleraine:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/CgVVxWq1hLE&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is dancing to Whalen&amp;rsquo;s Breakdown:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/LNiUdN_4-44&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;something-unexpected&#34;&gt;Something unexpected&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I mentioned earlier that I had planned to possibly play tin whistle in one piece, which was the fourth in a medley, of which we had been told we would not be playing the third. Since we were not supposed to play the third, I had crossed it out and not even sight read it once (given that I had less than two weeks to try to learn thirty pieces we were going to play).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Guess what? Somehow, after the second piece in the medley ended, I got completely confused, because we went into the third one that we weren&amp;rsquo;t supposed to play. This third one was Whalen&amp;rsquo;s Breakdown, which I got video of above. Eventually I joined in and started playing it, but not on tin whistle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;overall-experience&#34;&gt;Overall experience&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Time went by surprisingly quickly. Getting set up and ready on stage, the time passed quickly (I was glad we arrived quite early). I was surprisingly hungry after we took a break after the first hour, and was grateful to enjoy a plate of cookies I gathered from the table near the entrance, where dancers and musicians had brought in food to share.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Originally there had been talk of some of us musicians sitting out the first or second half because of space constraints, but since it turned out that there was enough space for all of us who ended up participating, Abby and I did not need to leave. She asked me if I wanted to stop playing and dance instead for the second half, but I was all excited about playing (and had worked so hard to practice the music) that I said I&amp;rsquo;d like to continue playing. We can always dance some other time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although I knew from my practice that I couldn&amp;rsquo;t play all the pieces (at the speed required) or all the notes, I was happy to contribute in my own small way where I could (and I was not seated very near any of the microphones, ha!). There was safety in numbers, definitely. I did the best I could.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;goals-for-the-future&#34;&gt;Goals for the future&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next year, I&amp;rsquo;d like to play in this event again, but I have a couple of specific goals for next year already if I do:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I want to be much better at all the instruments I would play in it (recorder, flute, tin whistle).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I want to be proficient and confident enough to sit by a microphone.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I want to do some solos, with stylistically appropriate improvisations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Maybe I should learn some of the dances and perform some too.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I think tin whistle is particularly suitable for the music in question, I&amp;rsquo;d like to get a better one and work on playing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, right now I am bushed, and am taking a rest from this music, but I&amp;rsquo;ll think about it again after a month or two.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;thank-yous&#34;&gt;Thank yous&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would like to thank Lynette, Donna, Allison, and Maro for all they&amp;rsquo;ve done for this annual Holiday Ball Orchestra over the years, and their openness and friendliness to new participants like me. I had a lot of fun exploring music new to me, and learning to play it and feel it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would like to thank the dancers for enjoying and showing appreciation for our playing for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And of course, I would like to thank my wife Abby for encouraging me to join her in playing for the Holiday Ball!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2012-12-14&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-12-14)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following year, I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/14/pittsburgh-contras-and-squares-holiday-ball-2012/&#34;&gt;played music again in the annual Holiday Ball&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Learning another instrument: the tin whistle</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/12/11/learning-another-instrument-the-tin-whistle/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Dec 2011 21:33:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/12/11/learning-another-instrument-the-tin-whistle/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;So on this blog I&amp;rsquo;ve already written about &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/recorder/&#34;&gt;starting to play recorder&lt;/a&gt; earlier this year, then taking up &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/flute/&#34;&gt;flute again&lt;/a&gt;, and even just barely getting started with &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/baroque-flute/&#34;&gt;Baroque flute&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday I started playing the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tin_whistle&#34;&gt;tin whistle&lt;/a&gt; for the first time ever!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This basic cheap &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.feadog.ie/&#34;&gt;Feadóg&lt;/a&gt; tin whistle is the one I am currently using (Abby picked it up at some point years ago while in Ireland, and I dug it out of a box in the basement yesterday).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/feadog-tin-whistle.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Feadóg tin whistle&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Why on earth am I playing this thing, which looks like a toy?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;upcoming-performance-at-the-holiday-ball&#34;&gt;Upcoming performance at the Holiday Ball&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve mentioned in an earlier blog post that I am going to be &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/01/im-going-to-perform-music-much-sooner-than-i-expected-monday/&#34;&gt;performing music&lt;/a&gt; in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburghcontra.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Contras and Squares&lt;/a&gt; annual Holiday Ball (coming up Friday). I have been &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/05/busy-evening-performing-at-phipps-followed-by-rehearsal-for-another-gig/&#34;&gt;practicing hard&lt;/a&gt;, trying to get up to speed on playing the music on either recorder or flute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;practical-considerations&#34;&gt;Practical considerations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had early on decided that I wanted to try to play the flute instead of the recorder in order to get a bigger sound than I would with a recorder (since there will be around thirty musicians total playing, including a whole lot of loud fiddles, accordions, brass). I also wanted to use this goal as a nudge to get better at flute generally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But as a beginner, frankly, at flute (I played only aimlessly in the past as a pre-teen), I&amp;rsquo;ve been finding it quite difficult to play all these Irish &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jig&#34;&gt;jigs&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reel_(dance)&#34;&gt;reels&lt;/a&gt; at full speed. OK, after one week of practice I can say that I find it &lt;em&gt;impossible&lt;/em&gt; at this point to play these at full speed on flute. Part of the reason is that the music is almost all in keys with sharps, and I find it much easier to play music on the flute with flats (which is all I did as a child).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I use the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/29/a-musicians-best-friend/&#34;&gt;metronome method&lt;/a&gt; of gradually improving my speed while working on getting things right at a slower speed, but even after a week, for example, I progressed on the Chorus Jig (check out the video of sample &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=69BzrCkEvdU&#34;&gt;fiddle rendition&lt;/a&gt;) from metronome marking 78 to 80 to 90 and to 100, but I can&amp;rsquo;t go any faster than yet, for just this one of around &lt;em&gt;thirty&lt;/em&gt; pieces on the program! (I&amp;rsquo;m guessing from our rehearsals that we will be playing at 110 or faster.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tried switching back to soprano recorder but it is all still pretty difficult.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;enter-the-tin-whistle&#34;&gt;Enter the tin whistle&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also became dissatisfied with the &amp;ldquo;heaviness&amp;rdquo; of the flute in playing this kind of music (music I have never been familiar with, actually). When I discovered that the soprano recorder sounded pretty good in one of the pieces I tried it on, I wondered what the &amp;ldquo;authentic&amp;rdquo; ways to play this kind of music were. I looked on YouTube, of course, and found no shortage of professional and (mostly) amateur performances of jigs and reels on recorders, Irish flutes, and tin whistles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tin whistle is an authentic instrument for this Irish dance music!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the first rehearsal, Jim had suggested I play tin whistle, and I had thought he was joking, but Abby said she had one, and I vaguely remembered her showing it to me once. So yesterday I dug up the tin whistle, and Abby even found a two-volume instructional method for it of Irish tunes. I didn&amp;rsquo;t use the method, since I already have Irish tunes to play, but I spent an hour learning the fingering (which turns out to be pretty similar to the Baroque flute&amp;rsquo;s, both based on D major) and watching and trying to follow along with some &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.whistletutor.com/&#34;&gt;good videos online&lt;/a&gt; I found through a Web search.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, what I really wanted to learn was the authentic style, involving various forms of embellishment and articulation. I learned about &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.whistletutor.com/lessons/intermediate&#34;&gt;taps, cuts, rolls, slides, etc.&lt;/a&gt; and started trying to experiment with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a lot of fun spending an hour on that yesterday, but one single hour on a new instrument and new musical style isn&amp;rsquo;t enough. If I played a tune slowly, I could add some appropriate embellishments, but I had a hard time playing anything fast at all. I know I could be much better after two weeks, but I don&amp;rsquo;t have two weeks. I have till Friday. I will see what I can do in four days of practice on the tin whistle!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;today-s-final-rehearsal&#34;&gt;Today&amp;rsquo;s final rehearsal&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This afternoon, Abby and I went to the final rehearsal for the Holiday Ball. I brought my various instruments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a tough time because there was music I hadn&amp;rsquo;t even seen yet, much less sight read, that will be on the program. This music goes at breakneck speed, and I felt pretty helpless. I figure I will sit out of what I can&amp;rsquo;t play, or just contribute with some notes to provide support to the chords. Tomorrow I will map out a plan, to figure out what I can play, on what instrument, and what to sit out of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;dancing-at-the-holiday-ball&#34;&gt;Dancing at the Holiday Ball&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since so many musicians are expected to gather to play on Friday, and seating space is limited, we were asked whether any of us were interested in only playing for the first or second half of the program. Abby and I volunteered to play just the first half. So I&amp;rsquo;ll have less music to try to go over before Friday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby is interested in dancing with me during the second half. I&amp;rsquo;ve never done contra dancing in my life. I suppose I should be a good sport and give it a try.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2012-10-07&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-10-07)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that at the holiday ball, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/16/playing-recorder-and-flute-at-the-holiday-ball/&#34;&gt;I ended up deciding not to dance at all, but just played music&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But 10 months later, Abby and I did do a full contra dance workshop for my first time! &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/10/07/my-first-contra-dance-workshop-unexpected-fun/&#34;&gt;And it was a lot of fun&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-future&#34;&gt;The future&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am amused and grateful that by accident I have come to yet another musical instrument of interest, the tin whistle. I will try to get better at it this week for the Holiday Ball, but I have to confess that I don&amp;rsquo;t know what I&amp;rsquo;ll do with it outside of that context. I don&amp;rsquo;t exactly go around playing Irish dance music. As far as my musical goals are concerned: I&amp;rsquo;d like to return to my long-term project of improving a lot on the modern flute in the coming months, and continuing my recorder improvement as well. I will put Baroque flute on hold for a while, till maybe spring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are other instruments also, but time is so limited. Some time ago, I only barely got started on &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/accordion/&#34;&gt;accordion&lt;/a&gt; and have no idea when I&amp;rsquo;ll return to that. Also I started up on piano again, but have put that aside again. I have a ukulele that I have barely started on, but Abby and I seem to be meeting people who are getting into it lately, so at least I know that if I wanted to take it up, there would be a local community to tap into.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I figure that to get good eventually and rapidly at any instrument, I need to spend at least half an hour a day on average of practice, and I cannot really spend more than an hour a day total on music right now, so that means working on no more than two instruments at a time.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>