<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Cookies on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/cookies/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Cookies on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/cookies/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Report on my fourth day of Stoic Week 2014: virtue and relationships with others</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/27/report-on-my-fourth-day-of-stoic-week-2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2014 21:47:45 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/27/report-on-my-fourth-day-of-stoic-week-2014/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today was Thanksgiving in the US, a surprisingly appropriate day to be in the middle of observing Stoic Week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;thanksgiving-dinner&#34;&gt;Thanksgiving dinner&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/11/27/report-on-my-third-day-of-stoic-week-2014/&#34;&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve reported on yesterday&amp;rsquo;s theme&lt;/a&gt; of self-discipline and simplicity. At Thanksgiving dinner this year, I decided for the very first time to limit what I ate. I&amp;rsquo;ve always overeaten in the past, with poor results. It was just something I did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year, I did not eat any of the cake or pumpkin pie that was offered. For dessert (after the turkey etc.), I limited myself to one scoop of pistachio gelato and one cookie. Actually, I ended up regretting that cookie, because it was more substantial and sugary than I expected, so I&amp;rsquo;ve made a note to watch myself with the cookies. The gelato I may not have needed, but I enjoyed it all the more knowing it was the one main dessert I was allowing myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;fourth-day-of-health-habits&#34;&gt;Fourth day of health habits&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s my fourth day now of daily meditation and exercise. Actually, I overdid it on the exercise today, but not intentionally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been increasing the intensity of my short (seven-minute or so) daily workouts every day, lifting heavier weights and working more muscles. What I didn&amp;rsquo;t expect was that at the Thanksgiving party, two young sisters (of ages around five and two) were bored and wanted to play, and I rather exerted myself. The older one was the ringleader. We played at scaring each other and I pretended to be sitting on the couch sleeping and suddenly spring up and boo or growl, and I accidentally pulled something in my right arm during one of these explosive, sudden movements. I also pulled my left shoulder when the two challenged me to lift them repeatedly, and the older one (tall for her age) was heavier than I expected and not so easy to repeatedly lift, given that I&amp;rsquo;d already had a workout in the morning at home. All in good fun, but left me a bit overextended.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;on-today-s-theme&#34;&gt;On today&amp;rsquo;s theme&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find sensible the Stoic teaching of developing our &amp;ldquo;natural affection&amp;rdquo;, and expanding outward from ourselves. I feel I have been the beneficiary of much good from many people in my life and am grateful for this. The Thanksgiving dinner that Abby and I went to today is one we have attended for some years now. The hosts I met through Abby, who met them (and other dinner guests) through music and dance circles. I appreciate and deeply admire the generosity that they have shown us and to many others. I look up to them as role models for the kind of genuine affection that human beings can display and share, not only with immediate family or closest friends but outward to larger communities (such as local music communities) and beyond.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tragic shooting and death that happened this year in &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shooting_of_Michael_Brown&#34;&gt;Ferguson, Missouri&lt;/a&gt; has been in the news for some months now, and this week the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shooting_of_Michael_Brown#Announcement_of_no_bill&#34;&gt;grand jury decided not to indict&lt;/a&gt;. I haven&amp;rsquo;t commented in public or in private on any of these events, or on any of the commentary about them, but I do not dismiss what has happened as irrelevant to my life. In fact, I feel that what has happened has been so important, in the biggest possible picture of what has been going on in American history for a long time, that I cannot afford to lightly spew sound bites about it. I do ask myself, how can I best talk about what I am feeling? How can I make a positive difference, in the Stoic &amp;ldquo;cosmopolitan&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;love of all humanity&amp;rdquo;? I don&amp;rsquo;t know the answer yet, but I know what is not the answer: fanning the flames of passion. But simply being silent is also not the answer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2015-01-19&#34;&gt;(Update of 2015-01-19)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wrote something in &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2015/01/19/for-martin-luther-king-jr-day-some-black-american-voices-that-spoke-to-me-recently/&#34;&gt;observation of Martin Luther King, Jr. Day&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I take seriously the Stoic call that we are ethically responsible for more than just ourselves, that we are to develop ourselves outward (not just on inner virtues) and work to honestly consider all human beings our brothers and sisters. I see how I have been treated in such a way by others through my life and aspire to expand beyond myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How do you feel about cosmopolitanism? Do you feel it is naive, that it is best to just look out after family and clan? If you have been following the Ferguson tragedy, do you easily choose a simple &amp;ldquo;side&amp;rdquo;, an &amp;ldquo;us&amp;rdquo; versus &amp;ldquo;them&amp;rdquo;?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Report on my first day of Stoic Week 2014</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/24/report-on-my-first-day-of-stoic-week-2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2014 22:30:51 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/24/report-on-my-first-day-of-stoic-week-2014/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Last year, I heard about the first Stoic Week, &lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.exeter.ac.uk/stoicismtoday/stoic-week-2013/&#34;&gt;Stoic Week 2013&lt;/a&gt;, but did not participate because I was distracted at the time and did not feel like focusing. This week, I decided it was time to sign up for &lt;a href=&#34;http://modernstoicism.com/course/view.php?id=5&#34;&gt;Stoic Week 2014&lt;/a&gt;, and I did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-my-interest-in-stoicism&#34;&gt;Why my interest in Stoicism?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve mentioned Stoicism only briefly in my blog: once in 2012 when &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/11/22/thanking-the-best-of-all-possible-worlds/&#34;&gt;thinking about Thanksgiving&lt;/a&gt; and once earlier this year after &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/01/17/hiroo-onoda-and-the-six-million-dollar-man/&#34;&gt;rewatching an old TV episode&lt;/a&gt;. As I mentioned, it was in 2011, upon reading a book on Stoicism, that I made some major changes in my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that a couple of weeks ago, I decided to make major changes in my life again, but not while thinking about Stoicism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over a year ago, my meditation practice fell apart, and I never really regained it. As a result, my thoughts and habits have become disordered, I have felt. For example, I stopped writing regularly for my blog. I spent too much time on Facebook and Twitter instead, being distracted, annoyed, and worse, behaving in ways that I later came to feel counterproductive. I did &amp;ldquo;quit&amp;rdquo; Facebook in July, and also &amp;ldquo;quit&amp;rdquo; Twitter some weeks ago (part of the big life changes I set in motion), but still, I have felt ungrounded. I decided Stoic Week 2014 would be a good opportunity for me to return to the contemplative life that Buddhism and Stoicism in their different ways aspire to and that I had forgotten.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-i-did-the-first-day-of-stoic-week-2014&#34;&gt;What I did the first day of Stoic Week 2014&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, as I started the first day of Stoic Week 2014, I began by meditating ten minutes, Zen style. &lt;em&gt;This was my first meditation session in weeks&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I read the assigned text for today in the Stoic Week handbook, on &amp;ldquo;What is in our power?&amp;rdquo; A basic principle of Stoicism is that we should know what is under our control and what is not, and summarily refuse to dwell on or resent what is not under our control, and focus on making good decisions about what is under our control. A very simple but powerful concept, especially in a world in which it is easy to get annoyed or angry about many things we hear about in the news or encounter in our daily lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My exercise habit has been very spotty for months now. Well, today I reflected that, what the hell, it is completely under my control whether I choose to exercise or not, so why am I wasting this precious freedom? Some people don&amp;rsquo;t have this freedom. Others, including prisoners in jail, have little freedom but make use of what they have, and &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/17/the-joys-of-convict-conditioning-bodyweight-exercising/&#34;&gt;they exercise&lt;/a&gt;! It happened to be warm outside today, so I really had no excuse. I went for a run in Frick Park. It was short, less than three miles long, but I went. &lt;em&gt;This was my first run in weeks&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was my turn to cook today at home, so I made a substantial beef casserole dish. Abby has (rightfully) complained in the past when I didn&amp;rsquo;t completely clean up after cooking. Well, today I thought to myself that it is completely within my control whether I choose to attend to the details of cleanup as much as I attend to the details of using our skillets and baking pans. So I cleaned up as well as I could.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have not been feeling very well physically for weeks now since an incident involving emergency dental work that somehow resulted in complications. I am still in recovery. OK, so it is not under my control that I am not in good health right now. But what is under my control? After lunch I took a nap, because I felt like I needed it. I have been skimping on naps, but this is stupid, because I know that sleep is the best restorative practice when ill. It is under my control whether I choose to set aside time to sleep as needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At work, a colleague just came back from his first trip in Asia. He gave me samples of some odd snacks: chips, cookies, and candy. In recent months, I would have opened them up and eaten them on the spot. Indeed, I have been having problems with eating too many snacks for no rational reason. Today, I decided that it is up to me whether I choose to give in to random cravings or temptations, and so I chose to put the snacks aside for later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After work, I went to a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/Pittsburgh-Code-Supply/events/210396972/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Code and Supply Build Night&lt;/a&gt;, where food was served. Apart from a Thanksgiving dinner (!), some kind of cake lurked around. I took one glance, and chose not to even look at it again until leaving (when it was already all eaten).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leaving Build Night, I found myself annoyed that it was taking forever for the pedestrian light to change, but caught myself and observed that, first of all, the cycle is as it is, beyond my control; and second, I had mistakenly assumed that someone had pressed the button, so it was my fault I had to wait so long. I pressed the button and eventually got to cross. Next, while driving home, I made the mistake of driving behind a bus, which kept stopping. I got annoyed, not by the bus, but by myself, for mistakenly driving on the wrong street rather than the other one that does not have this problem; I got annoyed that I was too lazy to make a U-turn on the street I was parked on in order to get to that other street. But I stopped myself when I realized that what was done was done, and I simply had to endure the rest of the drive home behind the bus because it was not going to save any more time if I detoured around it late in the game: the best I can do is to be more careful in the future when making choices while driving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I felt I improved my life today by keeping in mind the fundamental Stoic principle of observing what is not under my control and what is under my control. I look forward to continuing to adopt this outlook for the rest of the week, and beyond that.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sometimes the best speech is the one you didn&#39;t have time to prepare</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/05/29/sometimes-the-best-speech-is-the-one-you-didnt-have-time-to-prepare/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 May 2014 21:57:45 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/05/29/sometimes-the-best-speech-is-the-one-you-didnt-have-time-to-prepare/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I went to something like my twelfth &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.hss.cmu.edu/&#34;&gt;CMU Dietrich College of Humanities and Social Sciences&lt;/a&gt; staff appreciation lunch (I&amp;rsquo;ve lost track). Basically, they feed you, recognize people who have worked some multiple of five years, and hold a raffle for ten cash prizes topping out at $100 (I won $75 last year). It&amp;rsquo;s a pleasant annual social event, but one whose details I don&amp;rsquo;t really remember from one year to the next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this year was different. I will not forget this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;where-s-the-dean&#34;&gt;Where&amp;rsquo;s the dean?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The current dean, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.stat.cmu.edu/GSS/lehoczky.html&#34;&gt;John Lehoczky&lt;/a&gt;, who always gives out the awards during the staff appreciation lunch, was nowhere to be found. This was especially mysterious because he was to be honored with a gift today, since he is stepping down as dean after fourteen years, to return to his duties as professor of statistics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;food&#34;&gt;Food&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lunch was pretty good, for me anyway. I had steak, potatoes, steamed vegetables, and salad, and topped off with some coffee and cake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/dietrich-appreciation-lunch-2014-05-29/lunch.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Lunch&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/dietrich-appreciation-lunch-2014-05-29/cake.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Coffee and cake&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I was surprised by the absence of vegetarian entrees. I myself am not vegetarian, but I know many people who are, or are almost-vegetarian, and I enjoy vegetarian options, so I am always sensitive to the variety of food options at events. Vegetarians at this lunch today had to make do by loading up on only simple salad and steamed vegetables.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;dean-lehoczky-appears&#34;&gt;Dean Lehoczky appears&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, after everyone was done eating, Dean Lehoczky appeared.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He explained that last night he had been working on some fancy speech for us, but then his wife had an accident and he took her to the hospital and they had some adventures there. After they finally returned home, he decided to scrap his plans for his speech.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, he gave a little talk that is the only one of his that I expect to remember in the past decade of this annual event (I have no memory of what he even said last year, for example). It was hilarious, and it was just him telling a story highlighting the humor in all the situations that arose after the accident last night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I guarantee you that I will &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; forget this story he told, as long as I live, it was so funny and personal. I will remember this story for decades. Up till this moment, John Lehoczky was to me just some guy I saw around at events. I don&amp;rsquo;t remember anything he might have said at any ceremonial speech I may have attended by him. But after yesterday, I saw a really funny guy who shared a personal story at his last staff appreciation lunch. The first thing when I got home from work was to tell Abby the story.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/dietrich-appreciation-lunch-2014-05-29/lehoczky.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;John Lehoczky&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re going to give a speech, why not make it unique and interesting, rather than formal and boilerplate? It worked, by accident, for John Lehoczky in his final moments as dean of the CMU Dietrich College of Humanities and Social Sciences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When you have to speak in public, how do you feel about your obligation? Do you fall back on some impersonal formula based on some template, since nobody really cares anyway? Or do you tell a story, and make it interesting? Do you care if anyone cares?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How a homemade ice cream cookie sandwich touched my heart seven years ago</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/05/21/how-a-homemade-ice-cream-cookie-sandwich-touched-my-heart-seven-years-ago/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2014 20:09:43 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/05/21/how-a-homemade-ice-cream-cookie-sandwich-touched-my-heart-seven-years-ago/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Today&amp;rsquo;s was Carnegie Mellon University&amp;rsquo;s annual &amp;ldquo;staff picnic&amp;rdquo;. Basically, they provide some reasonable food in the University Center, including a variety of sandwiches and wraps (with many good vegetarian selections, by the way), and salads, and ice cream billed as &amp;ldquo;homemade ice cream sandwiches&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The menu in recent years has been pretty good, and stayed the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ate a single one of the ice cream cookie sandwiches, which was plenty! There were several different configurations: this time, I chose the chocolate ice cream sandwiched by chocolate chip cookies:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/cmu-staff-picnic-ice-cream-top.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Top view&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/cmu-staff-picnic-ice-cream-side.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Side view&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-big-disappointment-seven-years-ago-then-an-unexpected-surprise&#34;&gt;A big disappointment seven years ago, then an unexpected surprise&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The funny thing is that even as I enjoyed the staff appreciation lunch, my colleagues and I still remember a disappointment from seven years ago, when because of budget cuts and/or bad judgment, CMU put on a staff picnic that went horrifically wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically, they barely had enough food for everyone, there was no potato salad, and there was no ice cream at all! It was an insult to be &amp;ldquo;appreciated&amp;rdquo; in this manner: it would have been better to cancel the event than hold one that everyone would grumble about for seven years. I think only since last year did people really start forgetting about that one incident. Time heals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, however, I still remember the incident if only because of a counterbalancing incident that happened just a few hours later, after work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seven years ago, when I had only recently started dating Abby, she had invited me to come after work to her friend&amp;rsquo;s place for a little party the same day as the CMU staff picnic, so I went. I arrived complaining to her that I had not received my annual ice cream sandwich (in previous years of the CMU staff picnic, they always provided standard-brand ice cream sandwiches, nothing special, but at least something). It turned out that there was ice cream present at the party, and also cookies, so Abby just combined a pat of ice cream with two cookies and presented it to me! Although the ice cream melted quickly and so the &amp;ldquo;sandwich&amp;rdquo; didn&amp;rsquo;t work so well after all, the gesture was funny and kind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know it&amp;rsquo;s a tiny little thing to do, but it really touched my heart seven years ago. It was a surprise, unexpected, and just very sweet. It&amp;rsquo;s one of those memories that, when it pops up (spontaneously or because Abby reminds me, as she did tonight when I told her about eating a chocolate one this year rather than a vanilla one), makes me smile. There I was, disappointed by how CMU apparently didn&amp;rsquo;t care enough to truly &amp;ldquo;appreciate&amp;rdquo; its staff, and then there was Abby, making a little treat for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our fifth anniversary of marriage is coming up soon. It&amp;rsquo;s been easy to start forgetting the early moments from when we first met, but I&amp;rsquo;ve decided that it&amp;rsquo;s important to keep remembering and remain grateful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CMU must have gotten a lot of feedback from the debacle seven years ago, because the staff picnic went back to normal, and then eventually even improved further. In the past couple of years, they got away from the boring burgers and hot dogs entirely, and went to a much more healthy and interesting menu. Meanwhile, Abby still surprises me sometimes with a treat of some kind, such as when packing lunch for us when we got for a day of hiking. Life is the little things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How do you react to either negative or positive surprises? Which do you remember more, after the passage of time?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pittsburgh Recorder Society: discovering the beauty of Alonso Lobo</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/05/18/pittsburgh-recorder-society-discovering-the-beauty-of-alonso-lobo/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 May 2014 17:48:23 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/05/18/pittsburgh-recorder-society-discovering-the-beauty-of-alonso-lobo/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We had another great turnout for the monthly meeting of the Pittsburgh Recorder Society. We got another new member, Joanna. I counted fifteen of us, total.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-recorder-society-2014-05-18/group.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Today, the highlight for me was discovering some music I don&amp;rsquo;t remember encountering before, by &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alonso_Lobo&#34;&gt;Alonso Lobo&lt;/a&gt;, who lived roughly 1555-1617. Fred passed out parts for his &amp;ldquo;Versa est in luctum&amp;rdquo;, a sacred motet for voice (which we are playing as a recorder ensemble instead).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This music is beautiful and new to me, and Fred provided instructive interpretive guidance I will discuss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d never heard of Lobo before (outside of recorder playing, I simply have very little knowledge of early pre-Baroque music) and had to look up Lobo after the meeting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;versa-est-in-luctum-by-alonso-lobo&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Versa est in luctum&amp;rdquo; by Alonso Lobo&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is passionate funeral music, written for a Spanish king&amp;rsquo;s funeral. I found an interesting &lt;a href=&#34;http://luiscfhenriques.com/alonso-lobos-versa-est-in-luctum/&#34;&gt;musicologist&amp;rsquo;s blog post about the work&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;English translation printed on our recorder arrangement parts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
My harp is turned to mourning and my music into the voice of those that weep.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fred put me on the alto 1 part. After some work on the piece, he called for those of us on alto 1 (there was at least one other person, but possibly no more, of us fifteen) to play louder, with more emotion, to really ring out. I had held back in part because I was afraid of going sharp if I blowed harder, but also in part because for other music we&amp;rsquo;ve been playing, I&amp;rsquo;ve been focusing on blending in playing tenor parts. I sometimes somehow get into a rut and &amp;ldquo;forget&amp;rdquo; the importance or impact of carrying the top line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fred was actually singing along quite expressively as he conducted us. It&amp;rsquo;s inspirational to me that we have a leader who so believes in the music he has us play, and seeks to help us bring out its essence. The interesting thing about this piece is that there are phrases of longer notes as well as those that are more agitated, with faster movement. So there is a lot of beautiful interplay and contrast among the voices as well as within their own span throughout the piece. Fred advised on providing separation at the end of phrases so that they can be heard better in contrast against other voices as they enter and leave in different places.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, the other first alto(s) and I did play more confidently and louder, as did the rest of the ensemble, and when we did that, it was an amazing feeling, the sense of filling the air and resonating. I live for experiences like this! Let&amp;rsquo;s keep it up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;a-performance-for-choir-you-should-check-out&#34;&gt;A performance for choir you should check out&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For reference, here is a fine performance by the Gabrieli Consort I discovered:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/yZe16Mpsmg8&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;group-recording-from-before&#34;&gt;Group recording from before&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fred brought in a little boombox so we could hear the recording he had made earlier of us playing &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/03/16/pittsburgh-recorder-society-something-new-recently-recording-our-practice-sessions/&#34;&gt;two months ago&lt;/a&gt;. We didn&amp;rsquo;t sound terrible, actually!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-recorder-society-2014-05-18/recording.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;snacks&#34;&gt;Snacks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ate three cookies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-recorder-society-2014-05-18/cookie1.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-recorder-society-2014-05-18/cookie2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-recorder-society-2014-05-18/cookie3.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In retrospect, I should not have eaten three cookies. Maybe two, or maybe one. I know, I made this observation &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/04/27/pittsburgh-recorder-society-palestrina-gombert-and-dolly-parton-cookies/&#34;&gt;last month&lt;/a&gt;. This time, I&amp;rsquo;m serious. Next meeting, I will eat no more than &lt;em&gt;two&lt;/em&gt; cookies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed being shown yet another beautiful piece of music and getting the opportunity to play it with others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How often do you discover beautiful music you have never heard before, through being given it to play? Is this experience different than just hearing it without playing it?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pittsburgh Recorder Society: Palestrina, Gombert, and Dolly Parton cookies</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/04/27/pittsburgh-recorder-society-palestrina-gombert-and-dolly-parton-cookies/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Apr 2014 17:47:27 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/04/27/pittsburgh-recorder-society-palestrina-gombert-and-dolly-parton-cookies/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We had a great turnout again for the monthly meeting of the Pittsburgh Recorder Society. We even got an enthusiastic new member, Andriy. There were around fifteen of us, total; we really filled the room!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our director Fred was inspirational again, encouraging and helping us to continue to refine our sound, our unity, our expression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every month, attending the Sunday recorder meeting is truly one of the things I look forward to most in life! Sometimes I feel emotionally naked and a bit anxious in our meetings, but I know that this is a safe place to grow and to contribute. Today was one of those days in which I really felt challenged to do my very best to make music together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;kyrie-of-the-missa-papae-marcelli-by-palestrina-revisited&#34;&gt;Kyrie of the &amp;ldquo;Missa Papae Marcelli&amp;rdquo; by Palestrina, revisited&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/16/excited-by-the-new-season-of-the-pittsburgh-recorder-society/&#34;&gt;Well over a year ago&lt;/a&gt;, we had begun work on a recorder ensemble arrangement of Palestrina&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Kyrie de la &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Missa_Papae_Marcelli&#34;&gt;Missa Papae Marcelli&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;, but had actually not picked up much on that, so I was delighted that Fred decided (especially now that we have more members) to start on this piece again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got a tenor 2 part and was happy to do my best to produce a rich inner voice blending it into the ensemble&amp;rsquo;s tapestry of sound. Fred emphasized that the original music did not have bar lines, and that each &amp;ldquo;Kyrie&amp;rdquo; phrase can and does begin on any beat of a &amp;ldquo;measure&amp;rdquo;, so we should focus on keeping the flow going. Of course, this being originally vocal music, I tried to &amp;ldquo;sing&amp;rdquo; on recorder, paying attention to entrances and breath control (I am still unable to last an entire breath in some of these phrases).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;mille-regres-by-nicolas-gombert-http-en-wikipedia-org-wiki-nicolas-gombert&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Mille Regres&amp;rdquo; by &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nicolas_Gombert&#34;&gt;Nicolas Gombert&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also started work on a recorder arrangement of &amp;ldquo;Mille Regres&amp;rdquo; by Nicolas Gombert, originally for voice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fred put me on the alto part and after we started playing, I realized I was the only one on the part, and felt anxious! There was nowhere to hide. It&amp;rsquo;s very different from playing on a tenor or bass part with a bunch of other people, or even when playing a part with just one other person. On the one hand, there is much more freedom, because when a voice is doubled, you have to work with someone to sound like one. Of course, you always have to blend with the rest of the ensemble, regardless, but when you&amp;rsquo;re alone, you realize that you do not have backup for your voice, that you are it. Strong entrances, making the high notes clear and rich, are totally up to you now. It&amp;rsquo;s a great responsibility and opportunity, and I felt myself focusing as deep as I could into every element of the music. After today&amp;rsquo;s first cut, I hope to continue to improve on bringing my part fully to life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a performance of the original music for voice:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/J_2kRgCxeHk&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;mille-regretz-by-josquin-des-prez&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Mille Regretz&amp;rdquo; by Josquin des Prez&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that elements of this music sounded familiar to me, because in fact it is based on the French chanson &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mille_Regretz&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Mille Regretz&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Josquin_des_Prez&#34;&gt;Josquin des Prez&lt;/a&gt;, which I was familiar with because in last year&amp;rsquo;s Mideast early music workshop, I took a voice class in which we performed it. I really enjoyed singing it (as tenor; sorry, I don&amp;rsquo;t know if anyone has a video of our performance at the final student concert).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a nice performance of &amp;ldquo;Mille Regretz&amp;rdquo; with just one singer per part:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/S0TNPoDYHFY&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;another-alto-solo&#34;&gt;Another alto solo&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was another piece we started (but there were not enough scores, so I had to share with Kristel; I need to ask for a copy to be emailed to me, but for now I don&amp;rsquo;t remember the name or composer) in which Fred again put me on a solo part, which was originally marked &amp;ldquo;soprano&amp;rdquo; but after a run through, he told me to read it on alto up an octave.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This assignment made me even more anxious because I actually start out with a full statement of the melody without any accompaniment, before everyone else starts to come in. I&amp;rsquo;m not used to be put on the spot like this. But again, it&amp;rsquo;s a great opportunity to really work on refining my technique and expression, and being aware that I am setting the stage for the whole piece to succeed. Also, it&amp;rsquo;s an upbeat, rhythmic piece rather than a melancholy, lyrical one, so it was great to have the opportunity to portray different moods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;snacks&#34;&gt;Snacks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As usual, people brought in snacks to share for the mid-meeting break.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Helen not only brought in the recipe for her delicious brownies from &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/03/16/pittsburgh-recorder-society-something-new-recently-recording-our-practice-sessions/&#34;&gt;last month&amp;rsquo;s meeting&lt;/a&gt;, but also a new batch of what she called &amp;ldquo;Dolly Parton&amp;rdquo; cookies, incorporating a lot of apple in them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The recipe for last month&amp;rsquo;s brownies:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-recorder-society-2014-04-27/recipe.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I ate three of this month&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Dolly Parton&amp;rdquo; squares:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-recorder-society-2014-04-27/cookie1.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-recorder-society-2014-04-27/cookie2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-recorder-society-2014-04-27/cookie3.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although setting a limit on three was better than no limit at all, after I got home, I did wonder whether maybe I should have limited myself to two; these were quite substantial and filling!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had another intense and joyful musical afternoon with a great group of friendly and fun recorder enthusiasts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is your favorite role when you are on a team? Do you like being a prominent soloist, or do you prefer to blend into the background? Or do you like to switch up your roles? What do you adjust when you switch?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My progress so far on my cookie quota system</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/04/20/my-progress-so-far-on-my-cookie-quota-system/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Apr 2014 19:27:37 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/04/20/my-progress-so-far-on-my-cookie-quota-system/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Abby and I went to an annual (secular) Easter party hosted by Lynette and Jim. In the past, I&amp;rsquo;ve often ended up all sleepy and sluggish at these parties. My experience this time was a bit different different. OK, we were all still quite well-fed, and I got tired, but far less so this time. I definitely believe it is because of my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/01/16/a-system-for-quitting-eating-cookies/&#34;&gt;cookie quota system&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I limited myself to just three &amp;ldquo;cookies&amp;rdquo; (Jim repeatedly teased me for my explanation that &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/02/22/cake-is-the-same-as-cookie-in-my-book-so-here-is-a-photo-of-birthday-cake/&#34;&gt;cake counts as cookie&lt;/a&gt;). This meant skipping out on trying a couple of desserts, because there were far more than three options. In the past, I would try a bit of everything, and that always ended up being too much, even if I took what I considered to be a small portion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some kind of tart:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/easter-2014/cookie1.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Birthday cake:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/easter-2014/cookie2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Tiramisu:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/easter-2014/cookie3.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I also did not eat any bread rolls, and limited my potato intake at Easter dinner. And I drank no wine. All this helped me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe it&amp;rsquo;s time for me to go down from three to two &amp;ldquo;cookies&amp;rdquo;. I will consider this. Also, maybe I should start counting ice cream and candy as &amp;ldquo;cookies&amp;rdquo; as well. I do regret eating one &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lindtusa.com/shop/chocolate-carrot-gift-bag&#34;&gt;Lindt &amp;ldquo;chocolate carrot&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; that in retrospect I did not really need to eat. (I did not eat any ice cream at this party, however.)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://cdn.lindtusa.com/wcsstore/ExtendedSitesCatalogAssetStore/images/catalog/products/main/450x/chocolate-carrot-gift-bag_main_450x_8325-M.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Lindt chocolate carrot&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Other than quitting something cold turkey, do you have a working system for reducing your consumption of desserts that you know are not so healthy for you? What makes your system work? Do you have an incremental reduction plan like mine, and self-punishment such as promising to post individual photos online of what you eat?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A note on running in warm weather</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/04/13/a-note-on-running-in-warm-weather/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Apr 2014 21:43:14 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/04/13/a-note-on-running-in-warm-weather/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I haven&amp;rsquo;t been running much at all in recent months; actually, I barely ran all winter, in contrast to last winter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since it&amp;rsquo;s warmer now, I no longer have an excuse. I went out for a short run in Frick Park late in the afternoon, when it was warm and sunny, probably around 80 degrees F.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a really tough time out there, going less than three miles before I turned around and started walking home. I know from prior experience that after not running much, I have to ramp up slowly, but in this case, the suddenly warm weather (after months of a seemingly endless winter) took a toll on me. So I&amp;rsquo;d like to remind anyone else coming out of &amp;ldquo;hibernation&amp;rdquo; not to feel discouraged if feeling unfit: just do a little bit of running at a time, &lt;em&gt;hydrate&lt;/em&gt; (I was grateful that the water fountains in the park are operational), and &lt;em&gt;be patient&lt;/em&gt;! If I didn&amp;rsquo;t know any better, I would be feeling quite discouraged after my excursion today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I treated myself to some cookies after my run. These are cookies I saved from an event at work last week, specifically for only after hiking or running. &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/01/16/a-system-for-quitting-eating-cookies/&#34;&gt;I would not eat&lt;/a&gt; these unremarkable cookies otherwise!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/frick-park-2014-04-13/cookie1.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Cookie 1&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/frick-park-2014-04-13/cookie2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Cookie 2&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/frick-park-2014-04-13/franklin.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>&#34;Time to Taste the World&#34;: thoughts on expanding my food tastes as an adult</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/03/21/time-to-taste-the-world-thoughts-on-expanding-my-food-tastes-as-an-adult/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Mar 2014 21:37:07 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/03/21/time-to-taste-the-world-thoughts-on-expanding-my-food-tastes-as-an-adult/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This evening, right after work, I attended an event called &amp;ldquo;Time to Taste the World&amp;rdquo;, organized by Carnegie Mellon University&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cmu.edu/dietrich/modlang/student-organizations/mlsac.html&#34;&gt;Modern Languages Student Advisory Council&lt;/a&gt; for the Department of Modern Languages. It was an informal event featuring some food selections followed by a German film that I opted not to watch, since I needed to go home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were three tables of food, one for &amp;ldquo;Asian&amp;rdquo;, another for &amp;ldquo;Mediterranean&amp;rdquo;, and another for &amp;ldquo;European&amp;rdquo;. Obviously, only a very tiny fraction of the world was actually represented in this event, and the selections were mostly not very exciting, but it was interesting and even jarring going from one table to another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/time-to-taste-the-world-2014/mediterranean.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Mediterranean&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/time-to-taste-the-world-2014/asian.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Asian&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/time-to-taste-the-world-2014/european.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;European&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that standard CMU catering cookies were also provided.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did try a bit of everything, including stuff I less frequently encounter. Unexpectedly, the experience of hopping from one table to another, and sampling every single item, led me to reflect on how unfamiliar some of these items were to me until later in life, and how my taste in food has expanded considerably in my &lt;em&gt;30s and 40s&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;linking-my-history-of-eating-to-time-to-taste-the-world&#34;&gt;Linking my history of eating to &amp;ldquo;Time to Taste the World&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Most of what I like to eat now is what I never ate or knew existed before I was 30 years old&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This probably goes against &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.theguardian.com/lifeandstyle/wordofmouth/2013/jan/29/changing-tastes-food-and-aging&#34;&gt;most people&amp;rsquo;s eating histories&lt;/a&gt;, but heck, I&amp;rsquo;m a late bloomer, because for various reasons, I had very limited life experiences until my 30s and even more so, my 40s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For fun, I decided to think back about when it was that I first ate or even encountered, each of the items I sampled in &amp;ldquo;Time to Taste the World&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;mediterranean-table&#34;&gt;Mediterranean table&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pita bread: OK, I suppose I probably encountered this first in college, when the dorm cafeteria provided it and I used it to eat with tuna fish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grape leaves stuffed with rice: first time encountered and eaten was as a grad student at CMU in 1997, age 27, from Sree&amp;rsquo;s food truck, actually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hummus: also discovered in Pittsburgh upon arrival in 1997.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Baba ghanoush: also discovered in Pittsburgh upon arrival in 1997.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, I still love grape leaves and hummus. Baba ghanoush I still find a bit harsh and biting, but happily eat it in small quantities at a time. By the way, I should note that I discovered olive oil in 1997 also. At first its strong taste and appearance were confusing to me, but I got used to them, and have been using olive oil since as part of my everyday cooking, in fact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;asian-table&#34;&gt;Asian table&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OK, my parents were immigrants from Taiwan, so these foods have never been unfamiliar to me!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spring rolls: my mother makes them sometimes, and of course much better than the commercial frozen ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chicken wings: some of my favorite childhood food memories involve my mother&amp;rsquo;s chicken wings with soy sauce and ginger. Still my favorite flavor of wings!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Noodle dishes: again, my mother makes this stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.npr.org/2011/08/08/139033757/babys-palate-and-food-memories-shaped-before-birth&#34;&gt;our initial food tastes are actually formed in the womb&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;european-table&#34;&gt;European table&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OK, this is the stuff that I&amp;rsquo;m least familiar with, find overall least appealing, and still encounter surprises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was some &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gorgonzola&#34;&gt;gorgonzola&lt;/a&gt; cheese appetizer thing that I&amp;rsquo;ve had before, and I had some here, but it&amp;rsquo;s not really my thing. I don&amp;rsquo;t think I ever ate something like this until my 30s. The taste and texture is interesting. Not my favorite thing to eat, but I could have a little bit now and then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was also &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prosciutto&#34;&gt;prosciutto&lt;/a&gt; wrapped around some cheesy stuff, something I think I never tried until my 40s. Again, it still tastes weird to me, but I can eat it if I have to. It&amp;rsquo;s not revolting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main thing is that I have historically &lt;em&gt;fundamentally&lt;/em&gt; disliked all dairy. I emerged into the world seemingly hating milk: I don&amp;rsquo;t like the taste, I don&amp;rsquo;t like the smell. I was forced to drink milk as a toddler and basically accepted that I was supposed to drink it, and that it was the only thing to go with cereal, so I tolerated it all the way till I went to college. Then in freshman year in college, I came down with severe puzzling health problems, and finally found out by accident (upon missing breakfast for a couple of days) that cutting out my usual breakfast cereal with milk completely solved my problems: I was simply &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lactose_intolerance&#34;&gt;lactose intolerant&lt;/a&gt;. I cut down significantly on dairy consumption (which for me was only milk for cereal, and cheese on pizza).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point in my late 30s, I found that my lactose intolerance had let up, and with care I could eat some forms of dairy without having problems. Cheese on pizza is OK, if it&amp;rsquo;s not &amp;ldquo;extra thick&amp;rdquo;. Cheese in a serving of lasagna is typically not OK, in the quantities provided. Also, in my late 30s I began developing a taste for hard cheeses, which smell less bad to me, and happen to also have far less lactose, and so I do enjoy eating some hard cheeses occasionally: my favorite is &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gruy%C3%A8re_cheese&#34;&gt;Gruyre&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is some food awkwardness at home, because I&amp;rsquo;m married to Abby, who comes from the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nature.com/news/archaeology-the-milk-revolution-1.13471&#34;&gt;dairy-loving peoples&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;m perpetually having to tolerate the odor of dairy of all kinds at home. This is &lt;em&gt;quite difficult&lt;/em&gt; for me, but such is life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;notes-on-more-recent-food-adventures&#34;&gt;Notes on more recent food adventures&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I explored a tremendous amount of new food when I went vegetarian (for several months) at age 29, and got serious for the first time in my life, about cooking for myself. All kinds of bean, lentils, unfamiliar nuts, spices, herbs, vegetables such as kale, etc. Although I didn&amp;rsquo;t stay vegetarian long, that phase of my life resulted in the biggest explosion in my food taste diversity ever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I didn&amp;rsquo;t even touch beets until my mid-30s, when I was &amp;ldquo;forced&amp;rdquo; to because they came in my &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.kretschmannfarm.com/&#34;&gt;farm subscription box&lt;/a&gt;. A whole bunch of other unfamiliar vegetables have come my way through my annual subscription since I began it. The latest was celeriac, which I had never even heard of until it started showing up in our farm box last year. I figured out stuff to do with it, and I like it! It&amp;rsquo;s fantastic continuing to discover new stuff to cook and eat. Life is not boring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m even learning to eat &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brussels_sprout&#34;&gt;Brussels sprouts&lt;/a&gt;. My initial experiences in my 30s made me want to vomit, but there are ways to cook these to make them much more palatable, and in the past couple of years, I have enough tolerable experiences that I can see myself trying them more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;cookies&#34;&gt;Cookies&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did eat some cookies at the event, but only three, in accordance with &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/03/16/pittsburgh-recorder-society-something-new-recently-recording-our-practice-sessions/&#34;&gt;my recent findings about how many I should eat at a time&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/time-to-taste-the-world-2014/cookie1.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Cookie 1&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/time-to-taste-the-world-2014/cookie2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Cookie 2&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/time-to-taste-the-world-2014/cookie3.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Cookie 3&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s never too late to try new foods. You might be surprised and enjoy something new. And if you don&amp;rsquo;t like it, you don&amp;rsquo;t have to keep eating it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m very grateful to have had the opportunity to try new foods now and then, and add to my enjoyment of life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many thanks to the Modern Languages Department at CMU for sponsoring this little event! I hope many of the students attending it got some exposure to new foods that they will remember for the rest of their lives.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pittsburgh Recorder Society: Something new recently: recording our practice sessions</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/03/16/pittsburgh-recorder-society-something-new-recently-recording-our-practice-sessions/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Mar 2014 18:39:46 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/03/16/pittsburgh-recorder-society-something-new-recently-recording-our-practice-sessions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-recorder-society-2014-03-16/group.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Pittsburgh Recorder Society&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I forgot to mention in my post about &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/02/16/pittsburgh-recorder-society-7-part-gabrieli-and-coconut-chocolate-cookies/&#34;&gt;last month&amp;rsquo;s Pittsburgh Recorder Society&amp;rsquo;s meeting&lt;/a&gt; that Fred has started recording our sessions; he&amp;rsquo;s set up a tripod and an audio recorder. I kind of didn&amp;rsquo;t pay attention because it was not emphasized and nobody talked much about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today was a different story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;recording&#34;&gt;Recording&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was more mention of recording than in the past, and Fred made jokes about checking out what we did and how it would be useful for us to listen and see how we progress. Interestingly, this seemed to have quite an effect on what we did. I definitely felt a lot more serious and alert. Although I already always do take our meetings seriously, I will confess right now that whenever Fred said, &amp;ldquo;OK, now let&amp;rsquo;s do this again, and with recording&amp;rdquo;, I really perked up and gave it my all, trying to play as musically as possible, paying attention to intonation, articulation, ensemble balance, and even that terrible habit many of us have of sucking our recorders after the end of a piece.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fred is right: it doesn&amp;rsquo;t really make sense, &lt;em&gt;logically&lt;/em&gt;, to goof off during rehearsal and then expect to play well in actual performance. In practice, we should do the reverse: play it as well as we can in rehearsal, so that when we perform, which is usually in less than ideal circumstances (anxiety, unusual location or acoustics, or being hectic in getting somewhere, or any number of other unexpected glitches), our performance might be &lt;em&gt;worse&lt;/em&gt; than what we did, but it will still be good. On the other hand, if we don&amp;rsquo;t give it our all in practice, then what miracle can get us even better in performance?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, the recording of our work was not at all some kind of grim task. I enjoyed the additional seriousness and care, and I think we&amp;rsquo;re sounding better and better every month. Amusingly, the most noticeable thing is that when we know we are being recorded, we end pieces much better, and then &lt;em&gt;dead silence&lt;/em&gt;. No rustling, no recorder sucking. Wow. I really enjoy that unity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;tenor-and-bass&#34;&gt;Tenor and bass&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the first recorder meeting in my three years in which I did not play soprano or alto recorder once! I have been much preferring to play tenor and bass, to provide inner or bottom voices, and letting the newer members of the group play the soprano and alto voices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;snacks&#34;&gt;Snacks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People brought in snacks to share, as usual, for the mid-meeting break.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-recorder-society-2014-03-16/snacks.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Snacks&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And of course, this being St. Patrick&amp;rsquo;s Day weekend, Helen had to bring special Irish-themed snacks to share. In addition to Irish cheese, she also brought homemade brownies that she said were from an actual Irish recipe! These were &lt;em&gt;fantastic brownies&lt;/em&gt;: chocolate, cocoa, good stuff. I had to eat them, again and again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In accordance with my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/01/16/a-system-for-quitting-eating-cookies/&#34;&gt;promise about &amp;ldquo;cookies&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, here is a photo of each individual one I ate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-recorder-society-2014-03-16/brownie1.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Brownie 1&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-recorder-society-2014-03-16/brownie2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Brownie 2&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Someone brought in a box of castle cookies. I ate one:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-recorder-society-2014-03-16/castle-cookie.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;While I was packing up to leave, I couldn&amp;rsquo;t resist temptation and ate my third Helen brownie:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-recorder-society-2014-03-16/brownie3.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Brownie 3&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In retrospect, &lt;strong&gt;this was a big mistake&lt;/strong&gt;. After getting home, I felt burdened by this third brownie. I would have been fine just eating the first two and the one cookie (along with some cheese and nuts that I also had).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve noticed that I have a problem when I eat a &amp;ldquo;one more for the road&amp;rdquo; cookie at events. I&amp;rsquo;ve decided to consciously watch out and &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; do that in the future. I should only eat as much as I can handle, and leave it at that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2014-04-27&#34;&gt;(Update of 2014-04-27)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By popular demand, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/04/27/pittsburgh-recorder-society-palestrina-gombert-and-dolly-parton-cookies/&#34;&gt;the following month, Helen brought in the recipe for these brownies&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thoughts on attending the Duquesne Young Artist Performance Awards Winners Showcase</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/03/08/thoughts-on-attending-the-duquesne-young-artist-performance-awards-winners-showcase/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Mar 2014 17:01:35 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/03/08/thoughts-on-attending-the-duquesne-young-artist-performance-awards-winners-showcase/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that a ten-year-old boy I currently give private chess lessons to is also passionate about music, and his piano teacher had him submit a recording for the annual &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cmcpgh.org/competitions/performanceAwards.aspx&#34;&gt;Duquesne Young Artist Performance Awards&lt;/a&gt; competition, and his entry happened to be one of the around thirty chosen, ranging from ages 7-16, so he gave a performance at the Winners Showcase at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.duq.edu/academics/schools/music/facilities/pnc-recital-hall&#34;&gt;PNC Recital Hall&lt;/a&gt; of the Mary Papper School of Music of Duquesne University.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d seen him perform informally before, but was curious to see him on stage, and also to see other kids and where they were in their musical development and personal style, so I told his parents that I was going to attend to watch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d never been to an event like this before, a gathering of kids who had proven at least some level of ability by winning an award. I&amp;rsquo;m a latecomer to classical music, not having had much to do with it until I went to college. My younger sister did take up violin in junior high school and I went one or two of her performances with my parents, but to be frank, I was not very interested in or understanding of classical music then, so I remember almost nothing of what happened and must have snored through; all I really remember is &amp;ldquo;Please let this be over&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The young performers collectively actually played a decent variety of music of different eras and styles. The selections were mostly quite short, as they had to be of course because there were about thirty performers to go through in the space of less than two hours. One came up after another, with no break. It was pretty intense, actually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed getting a taste of what all these different kids had to offer musically, and I hope it was a positive experience for all of them. There was a lot of nervousness on display, but also some really touching resolve and mature calmness as well. I was happy to see my chess student get up there and play that grand piano with flair.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;reception&#34;&gt;Reception&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Afterwards, cookies at a reception. I was hungry. I could not &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/01/16/a-system-for-quitting-eating-cookies/&#34;&gt;resist&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/cookies-2014-03-08/cupcake.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/cookies-2014-03-08/cookie.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thoughts on returning to ukulele after almost two months off: returning to piano was the reason</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/03/05/thoughts-on-returning-to-ukulele-after-almost-two-months-off/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2014 21:32:59 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/03/05/thoughts-on-returning-to-ukulele-after-almost-two-months-off/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I finally made it again to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/Steel-City-Ukuleles/events/158392272/&#34;&gt;latest Steel City Ukuleles meetup&lt;/a&gt;, after an absence of almost two months! What happened?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of what happened was that after the last meeting in mid-January, I had some battles with illness and fatigue and also got very busy. For whatever reason, I just plain lost interest in playing ukulele. It was like a switch flipped off. And each time a meetup came, I kind of intended to attend anyway, in hope of rekindling my interest, but it always turned out that something came up that was more important and so I missed two meetings in February that I otherwise did sign up for but canceled at the last minute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;piano&#34;&gt;Piano&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But on a deeper level, what happened was that in mid-January, right before the last meetup I attended, I learned that a boy I have been giving private chess lessons to was progressing rapidly in piano; his mother had sent me some video clips, and he played various pieces that were dear to me. This really shook my world, because I had &amp;ldquo;given up&amp;rdquo; on piano many times in my life, and never studied or practiced it seriously. &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/13/back-to-piano-too/&#34;&gt;Over two years ago, I wrote a little about this.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In particular, seeing a kid playing pieces that I never mastered made me feel deep regret that I had not stuck to teaching myself piano or getting professional instruction at some point in my life. So almost immediately upon learning about what he was up to, I decided to give piano a shot again. As a result, I completely dropped ukulele and flute, and focused my limited music time on recorder (in maintenance mode mostly) and piano.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got from the library not only the Alfred adult piano course again, but also the fantastic &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.carlhumphries.com/piano-books.html&#34;&gt;Carl Humphries &amp;ldquo;Piano Handbook&amp;rdquo; as well as &amp;ldquo;Piano Workbook&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. They are really good. I wish this kind of self-teaching material had existed two or three decades ago. I would have snapped it up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I have been making more progress on piano than I ever did twenty years ago when I last really tried. This has been exciting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;ukulele-influence-on-piano-playing&#34;&gt;Ukulele influence on piano playing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The interesting thing is that even before I started practice, I was already instantly better than ever before. I was initially surprised, but then realized that everything I&amp;rsquo;ve done on ukulele has magically helped me at piano even without my touching the instrument. In particular:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;left hand strength and coordination came simply from playing ukulele&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;awareness of harmonic changes and coordination with melody came from the multitasking and partial improvisation of singing and strumming simultaneously&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I&amp;rsquo;ve been delighted that once again, improving at one musical instrument is helping me with other instruments as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;piano-influence-on-ukulele-playing&#34;&gt;Piano influence on ukulele playing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All through February, I wasn&amp;rsquo;t in the mood to play ukulele at all. But by March, I suddenly felt the itch to pick up the instrument again, and I did, and magically found that I was playing &lt;em&gt;much better&lt;/em&gt; than I had ever before. Again, I was initially surprised. But maybe I should not have been:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;left hand precision and flexibility was considerably improved, leading to better chord changes (with less sight) as well as much better barring and also finally nailing certain hard chords such as the basic E chord&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;spatial awareness of moving up the fret board was improved&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;singing and sight-reading chord changes simultaneously became much easier&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;returning-to-the-meetup&#34;&gt;Returning to the meetup&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was having so much fun working on some songs for myself on ukulele while singing much better than ever, that I was happy to return to the Steel City Ukuleles meetup to do this with others. (Also, during the winter I confess to feeling somewhat antisocial and not excited about driving through cold, snow, and ice to meetups, frankly.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a great time! I especially enjoyed, in the final minutes of the session, when it was request time, that I requested &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/My_Favorite_Things_%28song%29&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;My Favorite Things&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; and we went through it. I love that song (and this was also when I noticed that I could play an E chord without much effort, actually).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/scu-2014-03-05/group.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Steel City Ukuleles&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;cookies&#34;&gt;Cookies&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Someone told me that in February, she had brought in Chinese cookies from Hong Kong that her son had given her, to share with me for Chinese New Year, but I had not showed up. It was touching that I was missed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apparently the New Year party featuring wine and snacks was so popular that every meeting since then has involved wine and snacks (including this time a bottle of wine brought by a guy whose father makes wine)!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was really hungry and ate some cookies, so here are photos according to &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/01/16/a-system-for-quitting-eating-cookies/&#34;&gt;my rule&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/scu-2014-03-05/cookie1.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/scu-2014-03-05/cookie2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following turned out not to really be a cookie, but was some kind of bread with cheese or something. It was not my thing, and if I had known, I would not have taken it, but once I bit into it, I had to finish it:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/scu-2014-03-05/cookie3.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s still going to hard to juggle practicing all the instruments I have, but it&amp;rsquo;s encouraging that working intensively on one seems to transfer benefits to playing another. So I&amp;rsquo;m going to keep working on piano while also maintaining ukulele. I have to confess it&amp;rsquo;s hard to do much with recorder or flute at the moment though. They&amp;rsquo;ve been put on the back burner.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cake is the same as cookie in my book so here is a photo of birthday cake</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/02/22/cake-is-the-same-as-cookie-in-my-book-so-here-is-a-photo-of-birthday-cake/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Feb 2014 20:44:59 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/02/22/cake-is-the-same-as-cookie-in-my-book-so-here-is-a-photo-of-birthday-cake/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Since I consider cake to be in the same category as cookies for &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/01/16/a-system-for-quitting-eating-cookies/&#34;&gt;my rule&lt;/a&gt;, I had to take a photo of this slice of birthday cake.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/birthday-cake-2014-02-22.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Slice of birthday cake&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It was difficult for me to say no to a bit of cake mainly because Abby&amp;rsquo;s parents had us over for dinner and this cake was for a delayed joint celebration of Abby&amp;rsquo;s birthday and her father&amp;rsquo;s birthday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on how I felt when we got home, I still think that it&amp;rsquo;s best for me to avoid cake in general.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pittsburgh Recorder Society: 7-part Gabrieli and coconut chocolate cookies</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/02/16/pittsburgh-recorder-society-7-part-gabrieli-and-coconut-chocolate-cookies/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Feb 2014 17:41:04 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/02/16/pittsburgh-recorder-society-7-part-gabrieli-and-coconut-chocolate-cookies/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Because so many people are now regularly attending the Pittsburgh Recorder Society monthly meetings, we have enough critical mass to work on larger ensemble pieces. Fred pulled out a 7-part &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Giovanni_Gabrieli&#34;&gt;Gabrieli&lt;/a&gt; piece for us from the 16th century. Fun! I look forward to continuing working on this in March.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also continued work on other pieces we started earlier in the season. Fred&amp;rsquo;s guidance is as inspiring as ever. I feel that every meeting of our group is a wonderful opportunity to grow as a musician.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After going home I found a trumpet ensemble performance of the Gabrieli online:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/PlfvhJPNuTE&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;snacks&#34;&gt;Snacks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People brought in snacks to share, as usual, for break time.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/recorder-2014-02-16/snacks.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Helen made super-tasty-looking &amp;ldquo;cookies&amp;rdquo; (I asked if they counted as cookies, and she said yes). Coconut plus coconut plus homemade equals &lt;em&gt;difficult to resist&lt;/em&gt;!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/01/16/a-system-for-quitting-eating-cookies/&#34;&gt;my new rule&lt;/a&gt;, here are the three cookies I ate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/recorder-2014-02-16/cookie1.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;My first cookie&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/recorder-2014-02-16/cookie2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;My second cookie&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/recorder-2014-02-16/cookie3.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;My third cookie&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I stopped at three, which was a good thing, because after I went home, I did feel a little bloated. I should really have eaten only two, I think. I did take one home for Abby to enjoy.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>First time in my life not eating cookies or cake at a party</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/01/31/first-time-in-my-life-not-eating-cookies-or-cake-at-a-party/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Jan 2014 23:11:21 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/01/31/first-time-in-my-life-not-eating-cookies-or-cake-at-a-party/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I was at a birthday party. There were cookies of various varieties around. Also, there was a birthday cake. I did not eat the cookies or the cake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have to say this was a first for me. Usually, my rule at parties is &amp;ldquo;anything goes&amp;rdquo;. But it was time to admit that this rule caused many problems. If I load up on junk food at a party, I end up feeling crappy afterwards: maybe bloated, maybe sleepy, but in any case, I end up being a &lt;em&gt;worse guest&lt;/em&gt; to be around. And after going home I don&amp;rsquo;t feel well either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is exactly what happened to me just two days ago at a party where &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/01/29/my-no-cookie-rule-a-photo-update/&#34;&gt;I ate two cookies unnecessarily&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;good-food-to-drive-out-the-bad&#34;&gt;Good food to drive out the bad&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was plenty of good, healthy food at the party: the hosts provided great appetizers and entrees, and guests made and brought in delicious contributions also. There was no reason to pig out on the junk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, a salad Abby assembled when we arrived at the party:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/abby-salad.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;future&#34;&gt;Future&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My job is not yet done. It turns out that at the party, although I mostly ate healthy food, I also ate pita chips and similar bready items along with hummus that left me not feeling optimal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I&amp;rsquo;m extending my rule to these bready chip things also. Note that I have not yet banned potato chips or corn tortilla chips!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>