<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Twitter on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/twitter/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Twitter on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/twitter/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Smart versus unpredictable people: whom do you prefer?</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/08/smart-versus-unpredictable-people/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Nov 2014 11:10:13 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/08/smart-versus-unpredictable-people/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I saw an excellent &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ribbonfarm.com/2014/11/05/dont-surround-yourself-with-smarter-people/&#34;&gt;Ribbonfarm blog post&lt;/a&gt;, &amp;ldquo;Don&amp;rsquo;t surround yourself with smarter people&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should read this post; in fact, you should follow the blog in general, as it is one of the deepest-thinking blogs out there. Furthermore, it is an &lt;em&gt;unpredictable&lt;/em&gt; blog. I never know what will be discussed there, but whatever it is, I always find that it is new to me, not something following a standard school of thought or template.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, I follow this blog precisely for the reasons the post advocates learning not only from &amp;ldquo;smart&amp;rdquo; people but specifically from unpredictable people:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
I am only interested in people as long as they are unpredictable to me. If I can predict what you’ll do or say, I’ll lose interest in you rapidly. If you can keep regularly surprising me in some way, forcing me to actually think in unscripted ways in order to respond, I’ll stay interested.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-experience&#34;&gt;My experience&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is how I feel about whom I follow online through blogs (RSS) or through Twitter. I&amp;rsquo;m always looking for something different. People have different reasons for reading what they read, or following whom they follow. Personally, my goal is to &lt;em&gt;better understand the world&lt;/em&gt;. Sometimes, this comes from following people who offer useful news and information that I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t otherwise know. Other times, I learn from being offered a perspective that is completely contrary to or foreign to mine; in fact, I have changed my mind about a lot of things through deliberately following people who make me uncomfortable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I can predict everything you might say, or you can predict everything I might say, then there seems not much point in communicating; we might as well just fire up computer programs to spit out &amp;ldquo;virtual&amp;rdquo; conversations that add no new information. So I like to hear about your weird ideas, or stuff that goes against the dominant scripts of your tribe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Do you value independence of mind or do you think it is overrated? Why? What sort of balance do you try to achieve?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What can you quit today? I&#39;m taking a break from Twitter, Facebook, and Google&#43;</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/12/taking-a-break-from-twitter/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Oct 2013 22:30:37 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/12/taking-a-break-from-twitter/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Tonight, I officially announced through my accounts on &lt;a href=&#34;http://twitter.com/franklinchen&#34;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/franklin.chen&#34;&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://gplus.to/FranklinChen&#34;&gt;Google+&lt;/a&gt; that I was leaving social media for a while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;reasons&#34;&gt;Reasons?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right now, I don&amp;rsquo;t feel like explaining in detail all the many reasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason for leaving is not just one isolated event, although blocks of certain series of events and actions on Twitter have been particularly discouraging to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most recent seed for quitting actually came just a couple of days ago, from a blog I follow, where I was challenged to ask myself, &lt;a href=&#34;http://clairediazortiz.com/what-can-you-quit-today/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;what can you quit today?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
The idea, of course, is that we’re all doing things we don’t need to be doing. Things that zap our energy and passion and crowd our lives so much that we can’t do the amazing things we should be putting all our passions into.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the many thoughts I had was that my blogs have been stagnant for quite some time now. There is a clear inverse relationship between my participating on Twitter and Facebook (I never did do much on Google+) and my writing long form articles. So I am going to return to regular blogging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;rss&#34;&gt;RSS&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past, whenever I published a blog post, I would post a link to the social networks I&amp;rsquo;m on. Well, as part of my experiment, I am going to stop that. I realize that this means many fewer people will keep up with my blog. I have had people tell me that they don&amp;rsquo;t use RSS feeds any more. I would like to encourage them to get back to RSS so that they can receive updates on blogs such as mine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I am fine with having fewer regular readers. It turns out that most feedback I get on my blog is from people who don&amp;rsquo;t actually regularly follow it anyway, but find something useful from its archives because a Web search led them to my blog. So I feel no need to be &lt;em&gt;timely&lt;/em&gt;. Enough people are doing that. I will try more to be &lt;em&gt;timeless&lt;/em&gt; instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I cannot exaggerate how beneficial I have found social media to be since I got involved two years ago. But there have been severe down sides as well. Meanwhile, I will experiment with taking a break from my biggest sources of distraction and alienation.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What I did immediately after the National Day of Unplugging</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/03/24/what-i-did-immediately-after-the-national-day-of-unplugging/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Mar 2012 19:40:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/03/24/what-i-did-immediately-after-the-national-day-of-unplugging/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/22/paradox-i-will-observe-the-national-day-of-unplugging-but-just-bought-my-first-smartphone-this-week/&#34;&gt;The past 24 hours&lt;/a&gt;, I observed the &lt;a href=&#34;http://nationaldayofunplugging.org/&#34;&gt;National Day of Unplugging&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not a report on what I learned during that experience. I will be working on that report, which will probably be spread out over multiple posts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a report of what I did, &amp;ldquo;plugged in&amp;rdquo;, right after the event ended.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-i-immediately-did-after-finishing-the-national-day-of-unplugging&#34;&gt;What I immediately did after finishing the National Day of Unplugging&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Made a phone call to Abby, who has been in North Carolina since yesterday.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Turned on my home computer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Announced on Facebook and Twitter that I was back from unplugging! (Funny that this is the first thing I did online.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Checked my emails: I have around 30 to deal with. That&amp;rsquo;s not bad, but I know that usually, I receive the least email on Saturdays.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Started to &amp;ldquo;catch up&amp;rdquo; on my RSS feeds, Facebook, Twitter, Google+.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;emails-i-missed&#34;&gt;Emails I missed&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Notification about a Meetup event for tomorrow morning. If I had known about it earlier, I might have planned today differently. It is &amp;ldquo;too late&amp;rdquo; now to change tomorrow&amp;rsquo;s plans, so I will not be attending that event. (There is a different Meetup event I&amp;rsquo;m going to in the afternoon.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Notification about multiple Meetup events further in the future I may be interested in attending; need to look at the details and add to my online calendar if I decide to go.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Party invitation on Facebook. &lt;strong&gt;This is why I can&amp;rsquo;t quit Facebook; people actually use it.&lt;/strong&gt; Need to look at my online calendar and discuss with Abby.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Continuing old and new email threads involving various friends; I need to catch up and participate.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Notifications about new comments in my blog&amp;rsquo;s threads and other people&amp;rsquo;s blogs&amp;rsquo; threads where I&amp;rsquo;d indicated I want to be notified; sometimes this is useful, but other times less so. I will respond promptly to the comment on my old blog post.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Never-ending emails about new bills and statements I need to inspect and deal with.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Notifications about a bunch of new people following me on Twitter. I&amp;rsquo;ve long since given up on looking up every single new follower (or unfollower). I do like to make note of Pittsburgh locals I may have met in person or should meet, however.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Various mailing lists and other notifications.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;facebook&#34;&gt;Facebook&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OK, so it took about 15 minutes to catch up on browsing Facebook. That&amp;rsquo;s actually longer than I expected. Typically I check Facebook once or twice a day, and I&amp;rsquo;ve imagined that I don&amp;rsquo;t spend more than 5 minutes a day on Facebook, but apparently I&amp;rsquo;m wrong. Interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe I should spend less time on Facebook, because in reality, most of what I see there is not really necessary for me to see; it&amp;rsquo;s just idle people-watching for me, and the value of that is unclear to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;google&#34;&gt;Google+&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll be honest: I spend very little time on Google+. It&amp;rsquo;s just not where most people I know (as in &amp;ldquo;non-geeks&amp;rdquo;) are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;rss-feeds&#34;&gt;RSS feeds&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lots of articles to sort through. For fun, as I go through them to save those I cannot just skim in 15 seconds, but want to read in depth later, I am listing the topics of the saved ones here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Eclipse plugin for automatic Javadoc comments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Improvised Persian music for Nowruz&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Claims that Twitter Bootstrap is the way to go for web site design&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Privacy and how to pay for it&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Formal mathematical model of film success or failure&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to fix local issues: government or not?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The stresses on women in today&amp;rsquo;s world&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Plight of the introvert&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Calibre and freedom for ebooks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Guido and callbacks in Python&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A new blogging platform called Svbtle (sic)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Collection of historical chess footage on YouTube&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saturday is a slow day. On a weekday I typically find more new stuff to read.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;twitter&#34;&gt;Twitter&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I hit Twitter, to scroll down and see what I missed. I get tremendous value from Twitter, actually, that I cannot get from other sources. Perhaps that is the subject for a future blog post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-new-smartphone&#34;&gt;My new smartphone&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still need to get going on setting up and really using my new smartphone. This task may need to wait until Monday or Tuesday, since I have a lot of stuff I need to get done tonight and tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve talked about the first things I&amp;rsquo;ve done after getting back online. I&amp;rsquo;ll continue monitoring my online activities as they happen. One thing &amp;ldquo;unplugging&amp;rdquo; has done for me is give me (at least temporarily) a more conscious than usual awareness of what I do online. This will be a step toward streamlining my online activities.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>