<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Pittsburgh Contras And Squares on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/pittsburgh-contras-and-squares/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Pittsburgh Contras And Squares on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/pittsburgh-contras-and-squares/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Pittsburgh Contras and Squares Holiday Ball 2012</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/12/14/pittsburgh-contras-and-squares-holiday-ball-2012/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Dec 2012 23:50:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/12/14/pittsburgh-contras-and-squares-holiday-ball-2012/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/holiday-ball-2012/grand-march.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Grand March&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So this year I joined Abby again to play in the &amp;ldquo;Holiday Ball Orchestra&amp;rdquo; as I had &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/16/playing-recorder-and-flute-at-the-holiday-ball/&#34;&gt;done for the first time last year&lt;/a&gt;, for the annual &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/pages/Pittsburgh-Holiday-Ball/283731778337030&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Contras and Squares Holiday Ball&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My experience at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/events/383908395031216/&#34;&gt;this year&amp;rsquo;s event&lt;/a&gt; compared to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/events/308706299154491/&#34;&gt;last year&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/a&gt;, and thoughts about the future:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;preparation&#34;&gt;Preparation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, I was much more &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/11/24/preparing-to-play-irish-flute-in-the-holiday-ball/&#34;&gt;prepared&lt;/a&gt; this second time than the first time. Not only have I been playing any music at all for an entire extra year, but also, I had prior knowledge of and access to most of the music that is played every year, so I could start my practice well before the event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;costumes&#34;&gt;Costumes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby wanted me to dress up again. Since people enjoyed my wearing red pants last year, I wore them again this year. I was tired of the whole green thing, however, and so I wore a pink shirt and red vest to go all out on the red theme. I added a sport jacket also, one that had been too big for me my whole life till now; it turns out that my blazer that I wore last year is too small now, as my chest has noticeably expanded in the past year (probably because of weight lifting, posture changes, and playing wind instruments). I added a beret that I&amp;rsquo;d never worn before.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/holiday-ball-2012/franklin.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Abby came up with her own colorful outfit.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/holiday-ball-2012/abby-octave-mandolin.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;venue&#34;&gt;Venue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was afraid that Swisshelm Park Community Center would be super cold again like last year, but I did bring my Handeze fingerless gloves just in case. It turned out that the place was warm (it&amp;rsquo;s been a very warm &amp;ldquo;winter&amp;rdquo;), and so I did not have any problems feeling cold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;on-stage&#34;&gt;On stage&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year I think there were somewhat fewer musicians in the Holiday Ball Orchestra than last year. I thought this was actually a good thing. Last year there were some real problems with space and also with ensemble balance (there were a whole lot of violins last year, for example).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;instruments&#34;&gt;Instruments&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I brought my modern flute, wooden keyless Irish flute, and tin whistle. Last year I had played primarily recorder, but this year I chose not to play recorder at all: the Irish flute was what I wanted to use as much as possible for this music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also brought my melodica! I had practiced playing the Hallelujah Chorus part of the Grand March using it and was excited to make my melodica debut. I also planned to use it in some of the Christmas songs, such as &amp;ldquo;Frosty the Snowman&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby brought an &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Octave_mandolin&#34;&gt;octave mandolin&lt;/a&gt; she had been borrowing. She started playing mandolin just this year, and octave mandolin just in the past couple of weeks, I think. This instrument is so much better suited to the music, she says, than her tamburitza she played last year.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/holiday-ball-2012/instruments.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Our instruments&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Several &amp;ldquo;kazumpets&amp;rdquo; (kazoo trumpets) were also provided by Lynette and Jim, and passed out to whoever wanted to play them during certain songs. Abby took one.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/holiday-ball-2012/abby-kazumpet.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby with kazumpet&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;dancing&#34;&gt;Dancing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since Abby and I have now actually done some &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/10/07/my-first-contra-dance-workshop-unexpected-fun/&#34;&gt;contra dancing together&lt;/a&gt;, there was a question of whether we would do any dancing. Abby and I discussed this before the event; Abby was very excited to play music on octave mandolin, and so she did not want to dance, so we did no dancing. Like I said last year: &amp;ldquo;We can always dance some other time.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the other musicians were very excited about dancing and pre-arranged to spend one half or the other of the time dancing instead of playing music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I saw a lot of familiar faces among the dancers, thanks to having met some of them when doing French and contra dances at CMU, and others I met from non-dance contexts elsewhere in the past year in Pittsburgh. It was nice to see my friend Henry and his girlfriend Gina at the dance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;off-and-running&#34;&gt;Off and running&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marlin was the caller again as usual and the evening proceeded with the Grand March and then the whole big assortment of jigs, reels, waltzes, Christmas songs, and a couple of interesting new pieces for this year.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/holiday-ball-2012/grand-march.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Grand March&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t have additional interesting photos or videos to share from during the event, because I took none: after the initial Grand March, I was entirely focused just on playing music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;overall-experience&#34;&gt;Overall experience&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was far less nervous than I was last year. Also, I positioned myself near, rather than deliberately far away from, a microphone, in order to be more audible. I don&amp;rsquo;t actually know what I sounded like, but some dancers during intermission commented that they liked the sound of the wooden Irish flute, so I guess it must have been audible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Playing music for hours is tiring, especially when it is so fast and there are so many notes. Of course, nobody is required to play all the notes all the time. I picked and chose when to take breaks, typically alternating repeats or entire sections. And there is definitely a limit to how long I can play flutes before my mouth gives up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the second half, a guy who had danced during the first half played a keyed Irish flute and tin whistle with us. I hadn&amp;rsquo;t seen him at the two of three rehearsals I had attended, so I hadn&amp;rsquo;t known someone else would be playing those instruments. As a result, I changed some things up in the second half, by playing the tin whistle sometimes when he was playing the flute, and vice versa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did play the melodica as planned, but noticed that the intonation was poor in the lower notes, so I backed off. I&amp;rsquo;ll have to fix this problem before I do more melodica playing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I chose not to force myself to &amp;ldquo;achieve&amp;rdquo; some of the &amp;ldquo;goals&amp;rdquo; I set last year, which were to do some solos and nontrivial ornamentation/improvisation. I felt that because of the natural of my musical focus all this year, I hadn&amp;rsquo;t had time to devote to getting good enough to really justify taking the spotlight for some tunes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The music is still crazy fast: I am still not able to play everything quite properly at the appropriate tempo. Frustrating, but that&amp;rsquo;s OK. I expect to continue to improve my technique; I&amp;rsquo;m already so much better than I was last year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I very much enjoyed performing for the Holiday Ball this year. And I feel like the Holiday Ball Orchestra sounded better this year than we did last year, and some dancers remarked on this also. I think there are several reasons for this. One is that we had some people coming back for the second time (like me), much improved. Another is that there were slightly fewer people, which I think creates a tighter ensemble.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;goals-for-the-future&#34;&gt;Goals for the future&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right now, I&amp;rsquo;m just totally exhausted and happy to be done with music performance of any kind this year. It&amp;rsquo;s been a very tough week, a very tough month, and a very tough two months in my life, with all the things that piled up on me since the end of October.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because December always ends up being so frantic for me, for next year I need to better plan what activities I pursue during this time of year. Last year, I was totally set on playing again this year in the Holiday Ball. Now, I am not sure whether I will continue for next year. It&amp;rsquo;s a question of priorities, and I need to plan what I will be doing next year in December. If I do it again next year, then clearly I want to be doing some solos!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;thank-yous&#34;&gt;Thank yous&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, I have to thank Lynette for organizing the music scores and putting it into booklets for everyone. Jim made the kazumpets. Donna, Allison, and Maro led the rehearsals as well as conducted and played their instruments with enthusiasm; I&amp;rsquo;ve been really happy to have met them a year ago, because I&amp;rsquo;ve been encountering them in other musical contexts in Pittsburgh in the past year too!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We play for the dancers, and so I really appreciate it when they take note of our playing and respond to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And none of this would happened without Abby, who got me into the whole scene in the first place. I&amp;rsquo;ve met so many musicians and dancers, and tried out different instruments and musical styles and dances in the past year, thanks to Abby!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Preparing to play Irish flute in the Holiday Ball</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/11/24/preparing-to-play-irish-flute-in-the-holiday-ball/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Nov 2012 20:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/11/24/preparing-to-play-irish-flute-in-the-holiday-ball/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://pittsburghcontra.org/wp-content/uploads/2011/12/contra_header21.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Pittsburgh Contras and Squares&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A very important event for me last year was joining Abby in playing music at the annual &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburghcontra.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Contras and Squares&lt;/a&gt; Holiday Ball at the Swisshelm Park Community Center as part of the &amp;ldquo;Holiday Ball Orchestra&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I started to prepare to play music for the Holiday Ball (Friday, December 14) again: I have three weeks to practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What progress have I made in the past year on the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/16/playing-recorder-and-flute-at-the-holiday-ball/&#34;&gt;goals I listed after last year&amp;rsquo;s event&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;improvement-at-instruments&#34;&gt;Improvement at instruments&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, I wrote: &amp;ldquo;I want to be much better at all the instruments I would play in it (recorder, flute, tin whistle)&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My status this year:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m better at &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/recorder/&#34;&gt;recorder&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m much better at &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/flute/&#34;&gt;flute&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve only barely worked on &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/tin-whistle/&#34;&gt;tin whistle&lt;/a&gt;, but am automatically better at it because of getting better at other instruments.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I unexpectedly got an &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/irish-flute/&#34;&gt;Irish flute&lt;/a&gt;, which I have mostly been playing for &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/french-dance/&#34;&gt;French dance&lt;/a&gt;, but which &lt;strong&gt;I intend to be my main instrument for the Holiday Ball&lt;/strong&gt;!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From a sound and style point of view, the Irish flute is clearly the best of my instruments to use for the Holiday Ball. So I read through my copies of the Holiday Ball music (lots of jigs, reels, waltzes) tonight at speed, to see where I stand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, I could play (on any instrument) barely any of the music at speed, even on my best instrument at the time, which was soprano recorder. I was reduced to sitting out some tunes or playing just a single note each measure, when I otherwise would have been unable to continue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, I found that I could get through most of the selections OK at speed, but somewhat sloppily and inaccurately. I would &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; be happy to have to perform this music at speed tonight; I would rather sit out or simplify rather than try to play something beyond me. But I have three weeks to improve significantly, and I believe I can improve enough that when the time comes, I won&amp;rsquo;t be sitting out most of the tunes the way I kind of did last year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the fingering of the tin whistle is the same as for my keyless Irish flute, I can also choose to use the tin whistle where I feel appropriate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;microphone&#34;&gt;Microphone&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, I wrote: &amp;ldquo;I want to be proficient and confident enough to sit by a microphone&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea of being in the foreground is still a bit daunting to me, but I think after I get in some good practice over the next week or so, I&amp;rsquo;ll feel confident about not just being in the background the way I was last year. I do think it would be nice to have an audible Irish flute in our performance for the dancers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;solos&#34;&gt;Solos&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, I wrote: &amp;ldquo;I want to do some solos, with stylistically appropriate improvisations&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even scarier. I&amp;rsquo;ve been working through &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/_posts/2012/06/12/ordered-the-casey-burns-small-handed-irish-flute/&#34;&gt;Grey Larsen&amp;rsquo;s book&lt;/a&gt;, which is amazingly detailed and good, but as Irish music has &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; at all been my focus during this year of music for me, I&amp;rsquo;m nowhere at the level of passing for a traditional Irish musician. Still, there is time to work up a sound basic practical level of ornamentation, I think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll have to evaluate, after a week or two, what I feel comfortable doing on stage. The basic rule is: better to play an melody simply and beautifully, unornamented, rather than do something badly and in poor taste and technique!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;dance&#34;&gt;Dance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, I wrote: &amp;ldquo;Maybe I should learn some of the dances and perform some too&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that in fact, I did learn some &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/10/07/my-first-contra-dance-workshop-unexpected-fun/&#34;&gt;contra dance&lt;/a&gt;, so depending on how Abby would like to split up playing music and dancing, I would be, unlike last year, totally up for participating as a dancer as well as a musician.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a lot of fun playing music at the Holiday Ball last year and hope to enjoy it again, and this time with a higher level of musicality and a higher level of contribution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re in the Pittsburgh area and like contra dancing, make sure to put Friday, December 14 on your calendar already, and come to the Holiday Ball!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Playing recorder and flute at the Holiday Ball!</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/12/17/playing-recorder-and-flute-at-the-holiday-ball/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 Dec 2011 23:17:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/12/17/playing-recorder-and-flute-at-the-holiday-ball/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;So on Friday, after &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/01/im-going-to-perform-music-much-sooner-than-i-expected-monday/&#34;&gt;just two weeks&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/05/busy-evening-performing-at-phipps-followed-by-rehearsal-for-another-gig/&#34;&gt;practicing music&lt;/a&gt; for the &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburghcontra.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Contras and Squares&lt;/a&gt; Holiday Ball, the moment of truth finally arrived.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The event went pretty well! Here is a report, with some photos and videos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;costumes&#34;&gt;Costumes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby had said that we were supposed to show up dressed &amp;ldquo;festively&amp;rdquo;, so I thought, OK, I&amp;rsquo;ll wear something green and something red, for the holiday season. I immediately thought of a green shirt and red pants I have. Abby came up with the idea that I should wear a hat, and so I picked out one of my hats (which I only wear for costume parties) and she put a green band around it. I feared being cold (and rightfully so, it turned out), and so I added a blazer and a tie to the outfit. A good number of people seemed to like this colorful outfit!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/holiday-ball-2011/abby-franklin-holiday-ball.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby and Franklin posing before event&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;venue&#34;&gt;Venue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had never been to the Swisshelm Park Community Center before, but since Abby had, she had warned me that it was cold on stage at this time last year. Indeed it was. I was very, very happy to be wearing a hat and my blazer. In the future, I&amp;rsquo;ll remember to bring my Handeze fingerless gloves to gigs anywhere (and pack a hat and layers of clothing), to keep my hands warm when not performing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;on-stage&#34;&gt;On stage&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Around twenty-five musicians eventually gathered on stage. There was just enough space for all of us, although it was crowded. I got put in the &amp;ldquo;wind section&amp;rdquo;, armed with my main instrument I had finally decided on for this gig, soprano recorder (which I had started practicing the music for only a couple of days before!!), along with my secondary instrument, flute, which I planned to use only on the Hallelujah Chorus and some waltzes, and finally, the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/11/learning-another-instrument-the-tin-whistle/&#34;&gt;tin whistle&lt;/a&gt;, which I did not have enough time to play well enough for most of the music, and therefore planned to possibly use on only one piece.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/holiday-ball-2011/franklin-soprano-recorder.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin posing with soprano recorder&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/holiday-ball-2011/franklin-flute.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin posing with flute&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby sat to my right with her tamburitza. This was the first time we have ever played music together at an event!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/holiday-ball-2011/abby-tamburitza.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby posing with tamburitza&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;off-and-running&#34;&gt;Off and running&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marlin, the caller, kicked things off and the bagpiper led the Grand March and after he played for a while, we started playing. Before each group of dances, Marlin gave a brief lesson to the dancers.  We had jigs, reels, waltzes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout, Donna and Allison split the conducting, with Maro at the keyboard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;some-videos&#34;&gt;Some videos&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I managed to get some videos with my digital camera while on stage, because I didn&amp;rsquo;t play continuously. We often did three or four or even more repeats, such that I would sit out and rest and have an opportunity to switch instruments or take photos. With twenty-five of us playing, there wasn&amp;rsquo;t a need for any one individual to be playing lots of notes all the time (except for Maro at the keyboard!). We also changed things up so that we&amp;rsquo;d alternate among the &amp;ldquo;reeds&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;winds&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;fiddles&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;strings&amp;rdquo;, etc. for variety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a clip of me playing soprano recorder during Coleraine:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/JZqMmpwQwZE&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a view of some of the others during Coleraine:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/CgVVxWq1hLE&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is dancing to Whalen&amp;rsquo;s Breakdown:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/LNiUdN_4-44&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;something-unexpected&#34;&gt;Something unexpected&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I mentioned earlier that I had planned to possibly play tin whistle in one piece, which was the fourth in a medley, of which we had been told we would not be playing the third. Since we were not supposed to play the third, I had crossed it out and not even sight read it once (given that I had less than two weeks to try to learn thirty pieces we were going to play).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Guess what? Somehow, after the second piece in the medley ended, I got completely confused, because we went into the third one that we weren&amp;rsquo;t supposed to play. This third one was Whalen&amp;rsquo;s Breakdown, which I got video of above. Eventually I joined in and started playing it, but not on tin whistle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;overall-experience&#34;&gt;Overall experience&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Time went by surprisingly quickly. Getting set up and ready on stage, the time passed quickly (I was glad we arrived quite early). I was surprisingly hungry after we took a break after the first hour, and was grateful to enjoy a plate of cookies I gathered from the table near the entrance, where dancers and musicians had brought in food to share.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Originally there had been talk of some of us musicians sitting out the first or second half because of space constraints, but since it turned out that there was enough space for all of us who ended up participating, Abby and I did not need to leave. She asked me if I wanted to stop playing and dance instead for the second half, but I was all excited about playing (and had worked so hard to practice the music) that I said I&amp;rsquo;d like to continue playing. We can always dance some other time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although I knew from my practice that I couldn&amp;rsquo;t play all the pieces (at the speed required) or all the notes, I was happy to contribute in my own small way where I could (and I was not seated very near any of the microphones, ha!). There was safety in numbers, definitely. I did the best I could.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;goals-for-the-future&#34;&gt;Goals for the future&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next year, I&amp;rsquo;d like to play in this event again, but I have a couple of specific goals for next year already if I do:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I want to be much better at all the instruments I would play in it (recorder, flute, tin whistle).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I want to be proficient and confident enough to sit by a microphone.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I want to do some solos, with stylistically appropriate improvisations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Maybe I should learn some of the dances and perform some too.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I think tin whistle is particularly suitable for the music in question, I&amp;rsquo;d like to get a better one and work on playing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, right now I am bushed, and am taking a rest from this music, but I&amp;rsquo;ll think about it again after a month or two.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;thank-yous&#34;&gt;Thank yous&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would like to thank Lynette, Donna, Allison, and Maro for all they&amp;rsquo;ve done for this annual Holiday Ball Orchestra over the years, and their openness and friendliness to new participants like me. I had a lot of fun exploring music new to me, and learning to play it and feel it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would like to thank the dancers for enjoying and showing appreciation for our playing for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And of course, I would like to thank my wife Abby for encouraging me to join her in playing for the Holiday Ball!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2012-12-14&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-12-14)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following year, I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/14/pittsburgh-contras-and-squares-holiday-ball-2012/&#34;&gt;played music again in the annual Holiday Ball&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>