<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Creativity on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/creativity/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Creativity on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/creativity/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>The importance of stalemate in chess: how chess is completely different from life</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/06/16/the-importance-of-stalemate-in-chess-how-chess-is-completely-different-from-life/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Jun 2015 22:16:19 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/06/16/the-importance-of-stalemate-in-chess-how-chess-is-completely-different-from-life/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I just saw a cute end to a top-level chess game that ended in a forced
draw because the would-be losing side &lt;a href=&#34;http://dejanbojkov.blogspot.com/2015/06/jakovenko-and-stalemate.html&#34;&gt;managed a swindle&lt;/a&gt; by giving away
all his pieces by force in order to create a
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stalemate&#34;&gt;stalemate&lt;/a&gt;. If you don&amp;rsquo;t
play chess, a stalemate is what happens when it&amp;rsquo;s your turn to move
and you have no legal moves. You can claim a draw when you are &lt;em&gt;totally
trapped&lt;/em&gt; in this way. So one way of saving an otherwise losing game,
when you are outnumbered and about to be checkmated (losing when your
King comes under attack and it&amp;rsquo;s your move and you cannot stop the
check), is to find a brilliant way to be &lt;em&gt;unable to move&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/stalemate.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Black forced a draw through being stalemated!&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Is this a totally bizarre concept or what? Why was this rule of chess
invented anyway? Wouldn&amp;rsquo;t it make more sense if being trapped meant
&lt;em&gt;losing&lt;/em&gt;, like it does in real life conflicts?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;history-of-stalemate&#34;&gt;History of stalemate&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stalemate was apparently
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stalemate#History_of_the_stalemate_rule&#34;&gt;standardized to be a draw in the 19th century&lt;/a&gt;. Before
that, conventions differed on what the outcome of the game was
supposed to be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now and then, notable chess players have called for the abolishment of
his rule, to replace the stalemate with a win for the side that
trapped the other side, because this is &amp;ldquo;logical&amp;rdquo; and corresponds to
what you would expect in war or in some other &amp;ldquo;real life&amp;rdquo; situation in
which you have pressed hard for a long time, accumulated a lot of
force, and can cause your opponent to not be able to move at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;i-like-that-stalemate-is-illogical&#34;&gt;I like that stalemate is illogical&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m going to be blunt: I like that stalemate is &amp;ldquo;illogical&amp;rdquo;! It
creates tremendous difficulty for the side with more material to win
in endgames. I like that it gives the underdog a chance to avoid
losing by being clever. If stalemate were not a draw, then it would be
trivial to win many games in which one side has made a mistake and
lost a Pawn, because then all that has to be done is trade everything
off until all that remains is a King and Pawn versus King, and declare
victory. Stalemate means that the side with the extra Pawn has to work
super hard to avoid trading everything off, to avoid just mechanically
fighting battles with equal losses on both sides until one Pawn is
left.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like stalemate because in real life, often it is too easy for one
side to win just because of an early error by the loser. &lt;em&gt;Chess is not
real life&lt;/em&gt;, and I like it that way. Stalemate and other rules of chess
add bizarre whimsy and creativity to the game, just as the rule of
checkmate at all is counter to real life. In real life, you can kill
the general of an army and still lose the war. In chess, it&amp;rsquo;s always
like in the movies, on the other hand: you can have a lone hero defy
all odds to get at the enemy King and sacrifice everything else for
this objective, and have a happy ending. There is something &lt;em&gt;romantic&lt;/em&gt;
about chess that is part of its appeal to me. Chess is a game of logic
but according to weird heroic rules, where sheer &lt;em&gt;material wealth&lt;/em&gt; is
not enough to guarantee a win.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is unfortunate that many top-level chess games end in a draw, but
to abolish stalemate would change the capricious character of the
game in a way that ruins its appeal to me (on a lower level of play).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you are not a chess player, what do you think of the stalemate
  rule? If you are a chess player, what do you think of it?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>They published my brilliant chess game, hinting it was not so original, but was it?</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/06/02/they-published-my-brilliant-chess-game/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Jun 2012 12:19:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/06/02/they-published-my-brilliant-chess-game/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The past couple of days, I have been writing about what I learned through playing chess as a kid. I continue today by discussion a game I played right before retiring from chess at age fifteen. This game came to my mind when I was writing about the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/05/30/life-lessons-i-learned-from-a-lunch-recess-chess-game-at-age-seven/&#34;&gt;chess computer game I played at age seven&lt;/a&gt;, because I played against the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sicilian_Defence,_Accelerated_Dragon&#34;&gt;Accelerated Dragon of the Sicilian Defense&lt;/a&gt; in that game, and in my retirement tournament I also played a game against that opening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My final tournament before I started the 11th grade and became fully absorbed in academic study was kind of special because I played reasonably well, achieving an Expert rating just as I retired, jumping from a rating of 1934 to over 2000, and because it was one of those tournaments held in East Lansing, which meant visiting and staying with my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/16/remembering-my-uncle-steve/&#34;&gt;aunt and uncle and cousins&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The game I played in the Michigan Open was the second to last chess game I played in a serious tournament before returning to chess over twenty years later. It ended up being published in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.michess.org/interim/magazine/1980s/MC8510.pdf&#34;&gt;following Michigan Chess magazine issue&lt;/a&gt;, warranting a short note that it was reminiscent of a &amp;ldquo;famous Fischer-Reshevsky debacle&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;pride-or-shame-creative-or-original&#34;&gt;Pride or shame? Creative or original?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was playing my game, I was feeling pretty proud of my winning combination, even though I knew it was not completely original; I in fact had been inspired by a theme in the Fischer-Reshevsky game that I had remembered when first encountering it in a book with my father back when I was eight years old. When I read the Michigan Chess magazine column and saw that, of course, the editor saw the resemblance, I felt deflated. As a result, I never showed my father the mention of my game in the magazine, nor did I show the game to him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But today, I am going to display this game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-game&#34;&gt;My game&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my game, I embarked on a double sacrifice combination that, if one had never seen the theme before, looks spectacular. If one had seen the theme before, it might look boring. But actually, it required accurate calculation to make the concrete variation of the theme actually work: playing simply by analogy is disastrous in chess because any small difference in a position can radically change its evaluation. So although I cannot take credit for spotting the theme, I think I can take credit for making sure that it actually applies in context.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is the critical position of my game, with White to play and win:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/accelerated-dragon-trap_files/diag3FDFE53F3ECA481F.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Chen-Winfield, Michigan Open 1985&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here is the critical position of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.chessgames.com/perl/chessgame?gid=1008376&#34;&gt;Fischer-Reshevsky, US Championship 1958&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/accelerated-dragon-trap_files/diag3FDFE554B3C66396.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Fischer-Reshevsky, US Championship 1958&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you have not seen either game before, do you see the similarities? Can you spot the forced wins?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-full-annotations&#34;&gt;The full annotations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out my annotations of both &lt;a href=&#34;../../chess/accelerated-dragon-trap.htm&#34;&gt;my game and Bobby Fischer&amp;rsquo;s game&lt;/a&gt;. My annotations go further into what I was thinking during the game. (The game page pops up defaulting to showing my game; use the upper-right corner selection menu to switch view to Fischer&amp;rsquo;s game.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-discussion-of-the-theme-and-variations&#34;&gt;A discussion of the theme and variations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So if you have looked through the games now, you can see that the basic theme is of trying to trap Black&amp;rsquo;s Queen and win it, and in order to avoid losing the Queen immediately, Black has to move the King out and risk being checkmated. And the key moves for White are to play Bxf7+ to remove the f Pawn that defends e6, and then Ne6 attacking the Queen. What is critical is evaluating whether Black can just take the Knight on e6 with the King and survive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are some real differences in how the theme plays out in my game and Fischer&amp;rsquo;s game:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In Fischer&amp;rsquo;s game, the Queen really is trapped; and taking the Knight on e6 with the King leads to a quick forced checkmate&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In my game, the Queen is not actually trapped, because the Queen can always go to e8, but in that case, I win the rook on c7 instead; finally, in my game, Black can in fact take the Knight on e6 with the King, and this does not lead to a forced checkmate, because Black has Bxc3+ freeing up the g7 square for the King to possibly escape to.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In retrospect, I should not have been too ashamed by the resemblance to Fischer&amp;rsquo;s game, because there were real differences that lead to completely different calculations and variations in winning the game. I did have to use my own mind. The calculations are not so hard for a strong player, but I was not even at an Expert rating yet at the time, so my game was pretty good for a Class A rated player.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-i-have-learned&#34;&gt;What I have learned&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some useful lessons I have learned upon revisiting this game:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Having a deep background in already existing knowledge (such as already played games) helps one spot a theme and apply it in a new situation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is no shame in stealing and using someone&amp;rsquo;s good idea.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Even when stealing an idea, it requires one&amp;rsquo;s own ingenuity to make sure it works in a new context.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do not let your own honest judgment of your work be swayed too much by what is said about it in a publication.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I could have been more proud of myself in front of my parents when I was a kid and shared my excitement at my personal accomplishments.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Exploring creativity</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/12/02/exploring-creativity/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Dec 2011 23:37:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/12/02/exploring-creativity/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday at work, I participated in a brown bag seminar &amp;ldquo;Fostering Team Creativity&amp;rdquo; offered by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cmu.edu/hr/learning/&#34;&gt;CMU&lt;/a&gt;, taught by Ron Placone, whose seminar &amp;ldquo;Communicating Through Dialogue&amp;rdquo; back in October that &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/11/communicating-through-dialogue/&#34;&gt;I had found so useful&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Often, when we think of creativity, we think of creative individuals.
There is growing interest, however, in the importance of team creativity
to the overall success of organizations. This brown bag session will
explore ways managers and team leaders can stimulate innovative work
teams.

We will discuss the following:

The importance of debunking myths about creativity.
Ways to design supportive physical and psychological environments.
The relationship between dialogue and team creativity.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-is-creativity&#34;&gt;What is creativity?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Creativity&lt;/em&gt; is, in our (American) culture, a fuzzy and loaded term, with all kinds of unfortunate connotations. Throughout my life, I have heard rather &lt;em&gt;emotional&lt;/em&gt; reactions to the very idea of creativity. One is that it&amp;rsquo;s something some people are just born with. Another is that it&amp;rsquo;s artsy nonsense. Another is that &amp;ldquo;everyone is creative&amp;rdquo;. So it may be useful to undertake a more objective examination of creativity, what it is, why it is important, who has it, etc. I attended the seminar to get some interesting starting points for thinking about this topic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t yet have any special insights or comments to offer; I have not had the time since yesterday to at least read all the handouts and excerpts in the packet we received. But I plan to explore the topic of creativity on this blog in the future, as I learn more about what researchers have found and as I reflect on my own experiences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;online-resources&#34;&gt;Online resources&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I happened to find a audio-recorded version, with accompanying slides, of an older instance of this seminar online! So if you are curious, you can go through Ron Placone&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cmu.edu/hr/learning/ld_online_assets/rp_fosteringcreativity/fostering_team_creativity.htm&#34;&gt;presentation&lt;/a&gt; and pick up a some ideas from it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am grateful for CMU&amp;rsquo;s commitment to offering these free seminars to staff, and Ron is really an effective and fun speaker and facilitator of discussions at all his seminars I&amp;rsquo;ve been to in the past years.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>