<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Pittsburgh Chess Club on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/pittsburgh-chess-club/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Pittsburgh Chess Club on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/pittsburgh-chess-club/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>On finally achieving the US National Master chess title at age 45: part 1</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2016/01/22/on-finally-achieving-the-us-national-master-chess-title-at-age-45-part-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Jan 2016 20:49:11 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2016/01/22/on-finally-achieving-the-us-national-master-chess-title-at-age-45-part-1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&#34;true&#34;  href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/franklinmingchen/24441379882/in/album-72157661509446593/&#34; title=&#34;National Master certificate&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://c3.staticflickr.com/2/1560/24441379882_36a8f817c7.jpg&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; height=&#34;375&#34; alt=&#34;National Master certificate&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async src=&#34;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On December 18, 2015, I finally achieved the
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chess_title#Master&#34;&gt;United States National Master&lt;/a&gt;
chess title, at the relatively late age of 45 (I don&amp;rsquo;t have
statistics, but I suspect the vast majority of chess players who reach
National Master do so in their teens and twenties). I plan to
eventually write about how I significantly improved my chess when I
returned after a twenty-year break to start playing again ten years
ago at age 35, and how I now teach and coach chess based on my
experience in self-improvement. I will also write more about how I
continue to work on self-improvement outside of chess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For now, below is an interview that was published in the June 2016
issue of the
&lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburghcc.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Chess Club&lt;/a&gt; publication, &amp;ldquo;En
Passant&amp;rdquo;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&#34;true&#34;  href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/franklinmingchen/28474055921&#34; title=&#34;Untitled&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://c2.staticflickr.com/9/8194/28474055921_0e62aa5380.jpg&#34; width=&#34;375&#34; height=&#34;500&#34; alt=&#34;Untitled&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async src=&#34;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;when-did-you-learn-chess-how-old-were-you-who-taught-you-what-did-you-think-or-feel-during-that-first-experience&#34;&gt;When did you learn chess? How old were you? Who taught you? What did you think or feel during that first experience?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t actually remember a moment in my life when I didn&amp;rsquo;t know the
basic rules of chess!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s what I mean: my first life memories are from shortly before I
was 3 years old (I remember celebrating my 3rd birthday), when I was
already playing chess with my father. The story is that when I was 2
years old, the 1972 Fischer-Spassky match was happening and the result
was that during the summer of 1972, my father and his grad school
classmates decided to teach themselves chess. According to him, at
some point I watched and deduced some of the movements, and he noticed
my interest. I don&amp;rsquo;t remember any of that, but I remember that at some
point he bought &amp;ldquo;Bobby Fischer Teaches Chess&amp;rdquo; (he may still have this
in his library) and he led me through it after he had finished it
himself. So that was my first chess book, and we did it before I was 4
years old, because life changed for me after my sister was born before
I turned 4, and my father no longer had much attention for me for a
while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I remember is simply the joy of seeing the geometry of the
different piece movements fitting together. I was also extremely
particular about setting up the board: I always wanted my Knights to
face each other, and I still am, and at the beginning of every game,
you will note that I always adjust my Knights accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-was-the-next-big-step-in-your-chess-life-as-a-child&#34;&gt;What was the next big step in your chess life as a child?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After my father finished graduate school, he was very busy finding
jobs, etc., and chess was put aside for a while, but finding chess
sets lying around in school led me to find in the libraries some chess
books written for children, and I enjoyed them very much. When I was
7, he found his first stable job in Morristown, New Jersey, so we
moved yet again. We discovered that the Morris County Free Library had
a huge chess book collection, and we started reading through it
together. In the process, we finally realized that we had gotten some
of the rules wrong when playing with each other at home!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I must have read through 30 or 40 chess books from that library
between age 7 and 9 before we moved again. During that time, I had
nobody to play with, because the one time in school recess I tried to
play with a classmate who claimed he knew how to play, he captured my
King after I overlooked a pin, and claimed victory, and would not
listen to me when I said I could not make an illegal make and Kings
cannot be captured! I did have one &lt;a href=&#34;http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/05/30/life-lessons-i-learned-from-a-lunch-recess-chess-game-at-age-seven/&#34;&gt;interesting experience with a chess
computer&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also started teaching my younger sister chess during this time
period (at around age 4), because I had no one else to play with other
than my father. And I lost every single game I played with my father,
because he would not let me win; he would give me chances when I was
losing, but &lt;a href=&#34;http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/06/03/why-i-am-grateful-that-my-father-never-let-me-win-a-chess-game-against-him/&#34;&gt;never let me actually win&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-did-you-get-into-playing-in-chess-tournaments&#34;&gt;How did you get into playing in chess tournaments?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, my father had to learn that there was such a thing as chess
tournaments for amateurs. This happened when he accidentally
discovered a chess club.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shortly before I turned 10, my parents and my sister and I were at the
local community center (for a new job, my father had moved the family
again, to Madison Heights, Michigan) when my father heard strange
noises in the basement and wondered what was going on. He went down
and came back up all excited. My sister and I went back down with him,
and I still remember the thick cigar smoke and the men loudly banging
on ticking chess clocks while swearing and trash-talking during
blitz. My father and I joined the club and began playing in casual
blitz as well as in unrated club tournaments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone said we should also join the Michigan Chess Association and
the US Chess Federation and play in official rated tournaments. My
father said &amp;ldquo;wait, we just paid for one membership and you want us to
pay for two others already?&amp;ldquo;, but signed us up for MCA membership,
so that we could get the newsletter and stay informed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;when-was-your-first-tournament-do-you-remember-what-you-felt-when-you-won-your-first-official-game&#34;&gt;When was your first tournament? Do you remember what you felt when you won your first official game?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By summer, everyone was excited about the upcoming annual Michigan
Open over Labor Day weekend, so we went, signed up with USCF, and
played in our first USCF rated tournament, the under-1800 Reserve
Section of the 1980 Michigan Open. I lost my first round game, but
in the second round, I won a very long, 88-move game as White (I
still have the original scoresheet and just looked over the game
again) against a 1400-rated opponent. My opponent made the final
blunder in an endgame, allowing me to trade into a King and Pawn
ending I knew was a win. I took the opposition, won the Pawn Queening
race, and knew how to win with a Queen against Knight Pawn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It felt great to bounce back so quickly from a first round loss to
winning my first tournament game. I ended up scoring 3.&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;7&lt;/sub&gt;.0 and
winning a 2nd place Unrated trophy, while my father won the 1st
place Unrated trophy. I achieved my first provisional rating of
1591, while his was 1574, lower than mine despite his higher score.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My father was so excited by our success that we continued playing
in tournaments for a while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-happened-after-your-first-tournament&#34;&gt;What happened after your first tournament?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After our first tournament, my father and I were excited to continue
playing. He decided to continue playing in the Reserve Section while I
never played in the Reserve Section again after the first tournament,
because unlike him, I was not in it for the prizes but for the
challenge of playing against stronger opponents and getting better
myself. I did well in the Open Section of my second tournament three
months after my first, and my rating went up from 1591 to 1659, so
that was exciting. I won no prize, while my father got what he wanted
and won prizes for a fine performance in the Reserve Section. After
this second tournament, everyone was taking note of my progress, and
said I had talent. I didn&amp;rsquo;t think so highly of myself, because by
then, I had met Ben Finegold, who was a year younger than me, but
already much better than me in the tournament scene.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In January 1981, my father applied for a chess scholarship from the
American Chess Foundation in order for fund some chess instruction for
me, and we got funding for ten lessons in May from the winner of
the 1980 Michigan Open, Master David Whitehouse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before the lessons even began, I had continued to do well in
tournaments, beat my first Expert, and gotten my rating up to 1741.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I very much enjoyed the lessons, and still remember a great deal from
them in retrospect. Mr. Whitehouse showed me some endgames, openings,
and illustrative games of his, but most of all, gave me a tremendously
useful book list, and I would even today recommend the study of many
of the classics that he listed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-was-your-first-setback&#34;&gt;What was your first setback?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, despite the ten weeks of instruction, it turned out
that I was stuck at a plateau for an entire year of tournament play,
not having gone higher than 1765. In fact, during my second year of
tournament play (age 11), I had my first loss against a lower-rated
opponent, my first draw against a lower-rated opponent, and my first
loss to an unrated opponent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, my father himself had topped out at a rating of around
1774, I had finally beaten him at home (after which he never played a
game of chess again for another 20 years), family life was in disarray
as he looked for another job, and I was becoming a teenager and not
getting along with my parents or my teachers in school. So my father
let our USCF memberships expire, in July 1982, and my parents worried
that I was too obsessed with chess (my mother never approved of it in
the first place) and took away my chess set. I didn&amp;rsquo;t protest too
much, because I had my own life problems at the time, plus had no idea
how to continue to improve in chess. So that&amp;rsquo;s how I retired from
chess at age 12. Life was in disarray for everyone, and I almost
failed my classes in the fall during the 7th grade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;when-did-you-return-to-chess-after-this-setback&#34;&gt;When did you return to chess after this setback?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within the following year, some things had improved: my father had a
new job lined up, and he renewed my lapsed USCF membership and gave me
my chess set back. It was clear, though, that chess was only to be a
hobby and he would not be supporting me in any substantial way. In
1983-1985, I concluded my chess career of my youth by playing two
tournaments each of those years (during which my father had one more
job change, the final one of his career, and we had moved a couple
more times).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through introspection, I did make a conscious effort to improve my
play and broke through my 1700 plateau quickly during my return to
chess at age 13, having missed age 12. I got up to 2050 when I was
15. All the while, though, I felt more and more that I still didn&amp;rsquo;t
really understand chess, and Ben Finegold had long since made Master,
and would drop out of high school to move to Europe for a professional
chess career. I did still think enough about chess that I wrote my
college application on how chess is simultaneously an art, sport, and
science, and informed how I think about human endeavors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then chess ended for me for 20 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;as-your-rating-was-rising-say-after-it-past-1200-1500-1800-what-types-of-thoughts-did-you-have-did-you-think-you-would-one-day-become-a-chess-master-or-grandmaster-can-you-share-the-emotions-of-reaching-higher-ratings&#34;&gt;As your rating was rising, say after it past 1200, 1500, 1800, what types of thoughts did you have? Did you think you would one day become a Chess Master or Grandmaster? Can you share the emotions of reaching higher ratings?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my youth, I never believed I was going to become a Master, and I
never acted as though I wanted to give it a try.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I liked to play, hoped I was improving, but didn&amp;rsquo;t have the internal
drive or family support to do anything really serious with chess. I
didn&amp;rsquo;t really play that much chess as a youth: in 1980-1985, I played
16 rated tournaments, for a total of 83 rated games that took me from
unrated to an initial rating of 1591 to a peak rating of 2050. Compare
with my adult tournament career so far from 2005-2015, which consisted
of 436 rated games: the vast majority of my chess playing has occurred
in my adulthood, with rating range from 2057 up finally to 2201.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My plateau at age 11, during which I received no encouragement or
support from anyone, made me pessimistic even when I recovered from
it. To be honest, during the entire time I played from 1983-1985, I
was afraid to have any serious expectations or goals. My own lack of
confidence combined with my fear of family disapproval caused me to
actually be relieved when I no longer had time for chess. In fact, I
considered myself rather lucky to have made it to past 2000 and had a
lingering fear that if I continued, I would just lose that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-made-you-return-to-chess-after-a-20-year-absence&#34;&gt;What made you return to chess after a 20 year absence?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did play a little bit of casual chess in my freshman year in
college, but then never played a game again for 17 years, nor did I
follow any chess world news during that time. Chess was dead to me
during those years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in the early 2000s, a friend mentioned that there were strong free
chess engines that were worth trying out. I was skeptical at first,
because in my youth I could beat chess computers. But I started
playing with some engines to see how much they had improved since my
childhood. They were still not so strong, but were definitely much
stronger!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I became very interested in whether the engines were strong enough to
resolve some analytical questions I had about complicated games in my
childhood in which I didn&amp;rsquo;t know if I played something correctly (in
particular, some sacrifices). So my renewed interest in chess was not
as a competitor but as an analyst. I started reading chess books
again, and rejoining USCF, although not yet playing. In particular,
around 2003, my life was changed when a chess book showed up in the
public library, John Watson&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Chess Strategy in Action&amp;rdquo;. I checked it
out and it completely altered my perception of and understanding of
chess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, at this point in my life in my mid-30s, I was noticing
small but clear signs of physical and mental decline (I had peaked in
my 5K race speed) and thought to myself that I had unfinished business
in my life, dreams I gave up or did not allow myself in childhood,
that I should return to soon if I wanted to accomplish them at all
before it was too late. One of those dreams was to actually see how
well I can play chess if I committed to improvement, since I believed
deep in my heart that I had stopped before reaching my full potential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I discovered the existence of the Pittsburgh Chess Club in 2004,
played a game of chess with my father while visiting him for
Christmas, our first game in over 20 years, and in 2005, started
playing in tournaments again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-did-you-do-to-move-your-rating-up-did-you-study-a-lot-play-a-lot-what-types-of-exercises-did-you-do-did-you-have-chess-boards-set-up-at-places-in-the-house-was-there-anything-unique-you-could-share-that-readers-will-enjoy-knowing-or-reading&#34;&gt;What did you do to move your rating up? Did you study a lot? play a lot? What types of exercises did you do? Did you have chess boards set up at places in the house? Was there anything unique you could share that readers will enjoy knowing or reading?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my youth, there were no chess engines or computers really worth
using, so progress was much harder for someone like me who was on his
own and did not have access to strong coaches (other than the ten free
lessons I received at age 11). So, I initially just learned from
playing blitz often at the club, playing in tournaments and reading
books and magazines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To break my 1700 plateau, I studied specific opening systems that had
clear strategic goals for the middlegame. That made a huge difference
moving forward because I was no longer playing just randomly, but with
purpose. That worked to get me up to 2000+, but it was at that point
when I realized that I was holding myself back by playing only these
weird offbeat openings that I had studied. I had to go back to the
classics in order to rebuild myself to go beyond 2000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had another plateau during my entire first year back to chess in
adulthood, I was stuck at a plateau of the low 2000s and despaired of
ever improving beyond my childhood level. I realized that I had to
rebuild my chess understanding from scratch. I had never studied chess
systematically before, had a really spotty understanding of every
aspect of the game, from openings to middlegames to endgames. So in my
second year back, in 2006, I started rebuilding myself, gradually
transforming how I play. That paid off as I finally cracked 2100 and
then 2150, during 2006 and 2007. It was not until I passed 2100 that
for the first time in my life, I decided to set myself a goal of
making Master!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The single most helpful tool to me in recent years has been analyzing
my own games in detail with use of strong chess engines. I would say
this is more important than anything else. Being confronted with
reliable evidence of ideas or tactics that you missed (or your
opponent missed) must be the single most useful tool for improvement
available today that wasn&amp;rsquo;t available in the pre-computer era. In
particular, computers make it easy to try &amp;ldquo;what if&amp;rdquo; by experimenting
with different continuations, setups, and see how they measure up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;were-there-times-you-were-disappointed-with-yourself-and-thought-about-quitting-were-there-other-factors-like-friend-family-girlfriend-who-led-you-or-tried-to-dissuade-you-to-continue-playing-chess-is-there-any-story-you-would-like-to-share-on-this-topic&#34;&gt;Were there times you were disappointed with yourself and thought about quitting? Were there other factors like friend, family, girlfriend who led you or tried to dissuade you to continue playing chess? Is there any story you would like to share on this topic?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have often been disappointed in my chess play, but interestingly,
never seriously thought about quitting except in one situation: I only
thought about quitting once I came close to reaching Master and kept
failing, which coincided chronologically with my meeting a young
woman.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every loss or draw that set me back as I approached 2200 had a
tendency of making me feel like I didn&amp;rsquo;t have what it takes. And
starting to date again in 2007 definitely began to take a toll on my
chess, both because Abby actively opposed my chess activities at the
time and because of my whole schedule and routine was disrupted,
making tournament play difficult logistically. By the time we got
married in 2009, I had basically quit chess, and I thought for good,
and not willingly but as a concession. I periodically tried to come
back and play, but always less well than I was capable, because of
being rusty, unsupported, and tired. It wasn&amp;rsquo;t until the second half
of 2015 that I was ready to try again to play the best I could, this
time finally with complete emotional support from Abby, who had
finally come to understand how much chess meant to me. I also canceled
a lot of my usual activities in the second half of 2015 in order to
focus my energy outside of work on chess, and all this paid off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-is-the-single-most-important-factor-a-chess-player-must-consider-to-move-up-his-her-rating&#34;&gt;What is the single, most important factor a chess player must consider to move up his/her rating?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We all hit a plateau at some point, at which we are apparently making
the same kinds of errors that stronger players are not making, so
somehow we have to change the kinds of errors that we make.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the most powerful tool available is analysis of your own
games. Each game you play has the fingerprints of your personal
weaknesses all over it. Using a chess engine, and ideally a strong
human guide who can explain concepts and variations that lie behind
the engine&amp;rsquo;s numerical evaluations, you can learn to gradually remove
errors. For example, if you lost an otherwise good game only because
of one misconception during an endgame, avoiding that single error in
the future could pay off in any number of similar situations. Or if
you misplayed an opening, rebuilding your thought process that led to
a strategic misunderstanding can help in all future games using that
opening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;have-you-been-close-to-2200-several-times-and-then-fell-therefore-postponing-the-master-level-can-you-give-details-of-how-you-felt&#34;&gt;Have you been close to 2200 several times and then fell? (therefore postponing the Master level)? Can you give details of how you felt?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, I have been close several times! In fact, a couple of times I had
2200 locked up, in the sense that if I had withdrawn from a tournament
in progress, I would have guaranteed going over 2200 based on the wins
I had already racked up in the tournament.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first time was in the 2007 PA State Action Championship. I went in
at 2171 and had won the first three rounds. In the fourth round, I had
a totally won game against a Master and nerves got to me and I fell
apart and lost. In the final round, I had a totally won game against
an 1800 and fell apart and lost. This was my first experience of
completely choking under the pressure of knowing I was very close to
2200.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then in January 2008, I had a rating of 2197 from a Pittsburgh Chess
League round. The thing you have to understand is that in
January-February, I was simultaneously playing in the PCC Championship
held on Tuesday nights, and had won my first three rounds by February,
which meant that if I had withdrawn, I would have secured far more
than the 3 rating points necessary to go over 2200. But I had never
withdrawn from a tournament in my life, and didn&amp;rsquo;t want to achieve
Master through calculated cowardice. So I played on. But I choked, and
proceeded to draw the fourth game and lose the fifth. I continued to
play worse as I got engaged to be married, and quit chess the year of
my marriage in 2009.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I periodically came back in 2010-2012 but just played worse and worse,
unforced errors. In 2013, I started recovering, and in 2014, I again
almost made Master. At 2195, I choked, losing a won game against a
much lower-rated player while a Rook up! All I needed was to win that
game to make Master. And I kept on choking in tournaments after that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fall of 2015, I more or less stopped choking. I still played badly
sometimes, but I distinguish between poor quality of play and just
plain choking. How did I stop choking? I stopped paying attention to
my rating. In fact, in my final tournament games of 2015 that led me
to go over 2200, I did not do any calculations to determine whether I
would or would not go over. I knew it could be close, but did not want
to calculate. I tried to focus on my games and nothing else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m still proud that I made Master without the trick of withdrawing
from any tournaments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;can-you-discuss-which-is-more-important-for-chess-improvement-studying-the-opening-middlegame-or-endgame-explain-why&#34;&gt;Can you discuss which is more important for chess improvement: studying the opening, middlegame, or endgame? Explain why.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The short answer is that everything is actually interconnected, and I
wish I had known this earlier. A quality game will have a story behind
it that connects all phases of chess. Because of this, I think the
study of complete, annotated games (including annotating your own
games) is the single most useful technique for improvement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, opening study is popular, but studying the opening in
isolation, apart from understanding fundamental principles and knowing
not to fall into tricky traps, is almost irrelevant at under-2000
level, where games will mostly be decided not by opening subtleties,
but by later parts of the game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My main improvements have come from understanding the middlegame
better, learning how to assess positions and create plans based on
features of the positions, especially through considering Pawn
structure. If you think of an opening as a way to try to get to a
certain kind of middlegame, and think of the middlegame as a way to
get to a certain kind of endgame, then everything starts to fit
together. The middlegame is the core.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Improving in the endgame is important at all levels.  When I look at
my first tournament games at a 1500-1600 level, I see that the vast
majority of them went into endgames where anything could happen
because none of us really knew what we were doing, but I managed draws
and wins because I was a bit better there than opponents who otherwise
matched me in the opening and middlegame.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With my young students, I go over the opening phase with them only
enough for them to survive it (by playing classically and avoiding
needlessly complex and subtle variations), but focus my instruction
primarily on how to get to a desired middlegame by means of opening
choice. I also add endgame instruction incrementally as it becomes a
bottleneck in overall performance: when they get good enough to get a
dominating middlegame and then fail to win in the endgame, that&amp;rsquo;s when
we work on the endgame. But I feel like spending a lot of time on the
endgame up front is not realistic if one is not even surviving the
middlegame.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;were-there-any-special-small-or-large-celebration-when-you-became-a-master&#34;&gt;Were there any special, small or large celebration when you became a Master?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No, there was no celebration. I have to confess I&amp;rsquo;m not really a
celebration kind of person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-are-your-plans-now&#34;&gt;What are your plans now?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will continue what I&amp;rsquo;ve already been doing in chess since 2012:
writing and teaching.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started writing about chess on my personal blog around 2012. I
really enjoy sharing my analysis and thoughts with others, and this
eventually led to my writing for GM Nigel Davies&amp;rsquo; &lt;a href=&#34;http://ChessImprover.com/author/FranklinC/&#34;&gt;The Chess Improver&lt;/a&gt;
site and giving private chess lessons since 2013. I am still teaching
now and very much enjoy helping others improve their chess. So
teaching has been my main focus in chess for a while now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will continue to play in local tournaments as time permits. I am not
done improving yet! Also, I enjoy being a role model for my students,
to walk the walk as I give them advice about how to study, improve,
and compete. I have even been inspired to try to play model games to
illustrate specific themes I teach. For example, last year when the
subject was isolated Pawns, I played a game in which I chose an
opening aimed specifically against an isolated Pawn structure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2016-06-25&#34;&gt;(Update of 2016-06-25)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still play chess with my father whenever I see him. He&amp;rsquo;s still
playing pretty well at age 78. I feel he is possibly even better than
when he was in his 40s, probably because he has all the time in the
world to play casual games regularly at his local community center
since retirement. It&amp;rsquo;s actually harder for me to beat him now than
when I was a kid. Here&amp;rsquo;s a photo from the last visit to my parents&amp;rsquo; in
May 2016; I barely managed to win this game, where I took advantage of
the weakness of his isolated Pawn in the endgame:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&#34;true&#34;  href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/franklinmingchen/27597310106/in/album-72157671558553835/&#34; title=&#34;Untitled&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://c3.staticflickr.com/8/7317/27597310106_994a1df764.jpg&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; height=&#34;375&#34; alt=&#34;Untitled&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async src=&#34;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Clever chess tactics that were not what they seemed</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/11/30/clever-chess-tactics-that-were-not-what-they-seemed/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Nov 2015 02:25:52 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/11/30/clever-chess-tactics-that-were-not-what-they-seemed/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In round 3 of the current 6-round Pittsburgh Chess Club Tuesday night
tournament, I played a very tense game that led to an unusual position
with beautiful tactical possibilities. My opponent, Melih, is a strong
player who is a winner of the 2015 Pittsburgh Chess Club Championship earlier
this year, and had won the last two tournament games we have played,
so I came into this game anxious and also thirsty for revenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The game proved to be very challenging for both of us. I achieved a
better position out of the opening as Black but was too cautious to
press more aggressively. After more than 3 hours (!) of play, we ended
up in a simplified late middlegame in which I had only a small but
clear advantage. We were both clearly physically and mentally
exhausted, and starting to run out of time (these tournament games
have a time control of 2 hours per person with a 5-second delay per
move). It was up to me to try to find a way to win by inducing errors
in his play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;get-ready-to-be-quizzed&#34;&gt;Get ready to be quizzed!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What ended up happening was in retrospect both remarkable and
comic. To maximize your entertainment as well as challenge your
tactical skills, I recommend pausing at each diagrammed position below
in order to ask yourself what move you would play, and why, before
gradually uncovering the whole story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: an interactive chess board with all variations is provided at
the end of this article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;first-assess-a-quiet-looking-starting-position&#34;&gt;First, assess a quiet-looking starting position&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For context, here is the position after 21 moves, after Black played
21&amp;hellip;Qc6.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/ozbek-chen-2015-11-17/22w.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;21...Qc6; White to move&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;questions&#34;&gt;Questions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What opening do you think this middlegame came from?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Who stands better and why?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is White&amp;rsquo;s best plan, and what is Black&amp;rsquo;s best plan?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;answers&#34;&gt;Answers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Congratulations if you guessed this was a
  &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/French_Defence#Advance_Variation:_3.e5&#34;&gt;French Defense, Advance Variation&lt;/a&gt;,
  gone totally wrong for White!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Black stands better and has a simple plan:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;attack White&amp;rsquo;s backward Pawn on c3 on the half-open file, and
perhaps also the e5 Pawn as well; and the a2 Pawn and b4 Pawn are
also potential targets&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;use the half-open c-file for the Rooks, and the dark-squared Bishop
against White&amp;rsquo;s Pawns, and get the Queen involved as well&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;using these attacks, overload White&amp;rsquo;s defenses somehow in order to
win at least one of those Pawns to enter a probably winning endgame&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;White&amp;rsquo;s only possible counter-plan:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;defend the weak Queen side Pawns&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;maybe plant the Knight on a good outpost such as d4&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;defend the Pawn on e5 with maybe an f4 advance, and hope to attack
Black&amp;rsquo;s King side with perhaps an f5 break&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;progress-after-seven-moves&#34;&gt;Progress after seven moves?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Black has just played 28&amp;hellip;Rc4.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/ozbek-chen-2015-11-17/29w.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;28...Rc4; White to move&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;questions-1&#34;&gt;Questions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Who has made more progress in the last seven moves: White or Black?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is the nature of the progress made?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;answers-1&#34;&gt;Answers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;White has played to wait to see what Black is up to; meanwhile, Black
has made some progress on the Queen side by:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;doubling Rooks on the half-open c-file&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;using the Queen to bear down on White&amp;rsquo;s a-Pawn, which White has
(mistakenly) advanced to a3.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;white-played-a-surprising-move&#34;&gt;White played a surprising move&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;White has just played 29 Rac2.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/ozbek-chen-2015-11-17/29b.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;29 Rac2; Black to move&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;questions-2&#34;&gt;Questions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the 29th move, White moved the Rook from a2 to c2, leaving the
defense of the a3 Pawn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is the meaning of this strange move?!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can Black just take the Pawn with the Queen?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;answers-2&#34;&gt;Answers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may be thinking &amp;ldquo;White is provocatively setting a trap for Black
to fall into&amp;rdquo;. You get credit if you can see the trap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;black-fell-into-a-trap&#34;&gt;Black fell into a trap?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I played 29&amp;hellip;Qxa3.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/ozbek-chen-2015-11-17/30w.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;29...Qxa3; White to move&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But wait, I took the Pawn! Did I fall into a trap?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;questions-3&#34;&gt;Questions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is the trap you saw earlier, if you saw it?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is it really a trap?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;white-closed-the-trap&#34;&gt;White closed the trap?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;White has played 30 Ra2.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/ozbek-chen-2015-11-17/30b.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;30 Ra2; Black to move&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;answers-3&#34;&gt;Answers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the Rook moved back to a2, apparently trapping Black&amp;rsquo;s Queen. But
again, was it really a trap?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;black-refuted-the-trap&#34;&gt;Black refuted the trap?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Black played 30&amp;hellip;Rxd4.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/ozbek-chen-2015-11-17/31w.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;30...Rxd4; White to move&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You get credit if you saw this move taking White&amp;rsquo;s Knight on d4, and
saw that White&amp;rsquo;s Queen is overloaded such that retaking the Rook in
either one of two ways leads to losing back the Rook on c1 and
therefore losing a piece overall and the game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was very proud of seeing this tactic. (If you saw a different move
for Black, we&amp;rsquo;ll discuss that further down below.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;white-refuted-the-refutation&#34;&gt;White refuted the refutation?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;White played 31 Qc2.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/ozbek-chen-2015-11-17/31b.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;31 Qc2; Black to move&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When Melih moved his Queen to c2, I was in shock and disgust at
myself: in my fatigue near the end of this game, and overexcitement at
believing I had &amp;ldquo;refuted&amp;rdquo; a &amp;ldquo;trap&amp;rdquo;, I had completely failed to take
into account that White was not actually required to take my Rook on d4!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amusingly, it turns out that Melih, after playing 29 Rac2 setting the
&amp;ldquo;trap&amp;rdquo;, saw to his horror the resource 30&amp;hellip;Rxd4, and thought he was
lost, but then saw 31 Qc2. So neither of us had originally seen this
saving resource for White.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;questions-4&#34;&gt;Questions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is Black&amp;rsquo;s Queen trapped for real now?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What should Black do? Is Black lost? Or is Black still winning? Or
should Black start looking for a draw?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;black-panicked-trying-to-draw&#34;&gt;Black panicked, trying to draw&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, Black&amp;rsquo;s Queen is trapped for real. You get credit if you saw
that Black&amp;rsquo;s flashy 30&amp;hellip;Rxd4 had this flaw.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only question for me was how best to give up my Queen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I chose poorly. In a daze, I could not think straight. I chose to give
back a Rook with 31&amp;hellip;Qxc3, in order to force a trade Queens on c3 and
go into an endgame an exchange down for two Pawns, and hope for a draw.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/ozbek-chen-2015-11-17/36w.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;31...Qxc3; White to move&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I was correct that the resulting position was objectively equal and
drawable, but in a time scramble, it&amp;rsquo;s obviously easier to play White,
and for the rest of the game, both sides made major errors (with White
botching up winning positions and Black botching up drawn positions)
until a simplified position was reached (Rook and two Pawns for each
side) with only seconds left on the clock, and a draw agreed. I
consider myself lucky to have drawn. The final position was:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/ozbek-chen-2015-11-17/draw.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Agreed drawn&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;but-black-could-have-played-to-win&#34;&gt;But Black could have played to win&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You get credit if you chose instead to sacrifice the Queen with
31&amp;hellip;Qxc1+ to get the Rook and Bishop and Pawns against White&amp;rsquo;s Queen,
with advantage and a good chance of winning. After 32 Qxc1 Bxb4, Black
is about to win White&amp;rsquo;s c3 Pawn:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/ozbek-chen-2015-11-17/33rooksw.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;32...Bxb4; White to move&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In fact, if you saw all this when thinking about whether to take the
Pawn on a3 in the first place, then you get bonus points for seeing a
way to an advantage through the sequence of tactical blows. Neither
Melih nor I saw any of this up front, unfortunately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I chickened out and did not take this continuation because after being
shocked that my Queen was disappearing, I experienced a visceral fear
that I needed to bring down White&amp;rsquo;s Queen also, else it with White&amp;rsquo;s
Rook might be dangerous to my King.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that my fear was objectively unwarranted, as Black&amp;rsquo;s
defenses are sufficient because of the power of the dark-squared
Bishop to hit White&amp;rsquo;s e5 Pawn and even the f2 Pawn, but I was not
thinking straight any more as time was running out for the four-hour
game and it was already around 11 PM at night on a weekday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;one-possible-position&#34;&gt;One possible position&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a position that might have arisen if I had gone into this
variation:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/ozbek-chen-2015-11-17/35rooksw.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;White to move&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The thing is, even though the computer says Black has an advantage, it
could be scary playing against White&amp;rsquo;s Queen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;another-possible-position&#34;&gt;Another possible position&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But analysis also shows that White has to be very careful. For
example, if White is greedy and wastes time taking Black&amp;rsquo;s a7 Pawn
above, Black quickly gets a winning attack:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/ozbek-chen-2015-11-17/37rooksw.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;White to move&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In time pressure, anything can happen, and I think it would have been
very likely that White would have grabbed the a7 Pawn, after which
Black&amp;rsquo;s position play itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;finally-black-s-real-refutation&#34;&gt;Finally: Black&amp;rsquo;s real refutation!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I said you get extra credit for seeing everything to the point of
sacrificing Black&amp;rsquo;s Queen for an advantage. But you only get full
credit if you saw the real refutation of White&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;trap&amp;rdquo; earlier in the
game! I kicked myself for not having seen it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;questions-5&#34;&gt;Questions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Was there a point at which Black could have deviated and won the
game outright?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hint: which of Black&amp;rsquo;s pieces have we not focused on in the
variations covered so far?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;answers-4&#34;&gt;Answers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Black could, after White &amp;ldquo;trapped&amp;rdquo; the Queen with 30 Ra2, used a
different and better deflection of White&amp;rsquo;s overloaded Queen than
30&amp;hellip;Rxd4, which was OK but not best.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We haven&amp;rsquo;t looked at Black&amp;rsquo;s Bishop enough. I only saw this upon
recovering from the draw and analyzing the game later at home: the
winning shot is 30&amp;hellip;Bg5!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/ozbek-chen-2015-11-17/31varw.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;White to move&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If White blocks the threat to the Queen with 31 f4,
then Black just lops off the Pawn with 31&amp;hellip;Bxf4 and now:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;if White takes the Bishop or otherwise moves the Queen, Black will
win either the Rook on a2 or the Rook on c1&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;if White takes Black&amp;rsquo;s Queen, then Black takes White&amp;rsquo;s Queen on d2
with tempo and will eventually win all three of White&amp;rsquo;s weak
Pawns on dark squares (c3 followed by e5 and b4)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Either way, the endgame is an easy win for Black.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neither Melih nor I saw this winning resource for Black during the
game. We just weren&amp;rsquo;t looking at that quiet Bishop because it hadn&amp;rsquo;t
participated in anything up till that point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chess never ceases to surprise me. Tactical possibilities are
everywhere, and in this game, both Melih and I missed various
possible continuations, playing moves thinking we knew what had to
follow. I hope you enjoyed this story of missed opportunities and
incomplete calculations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My thanks to Melih for a challenging and fascinating game, and sharing
his thoughts with me afterwards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a data-flickr-embed=&#34;true&#34;  href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/franklinmingchen/23445261516/in/datetaken/&#34; title=&#34;Melih and Franklin at the Pittsburgh Chess Club&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm1.staticflickr.com/589/23445261516_25ee07e170_z.jpg&#34; width=&#34;640&#34; height=&#34;480&#34; alt=&#34;Franklin and Melih at the Pittsburgh Chess Club&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;script async src=&#34;//embedr.flickr.com/assets/client-code.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;appendix-interactive-playable-board&#34;&gt;Appendix: interactive playable board&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;
        src=&#34;http://chesstempo.com/js/pgnyui.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;
        src=&#34;http://chesstempo.com/js/pgnviewer.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;link
     type=&#34;text/css&#34;
     rel=&#34;stylesheet&#34;
     href=&#34;http://chesstempo.com/css/board-min.css&#34;&gt;
&lt;/link&gt;

&lt;script&gt;
    new PgnViewer(
      { boardName: &#34;demo&#34;,
        pgnFile: &#39;/chess/ozbek-chen-2015-11-17/ozbek-chen.pgn&#39;,
        pieceSet: &#39;merida&#39;,
        pieceSize: 46
      }
    );
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;style&gt;
#demo-stuff {
    display: flex;
}

#demo-moves {
    overflow-y: auto;
}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;div id=&#34;demo-stuff&#34;&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;demo-container&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;demo-moves&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Report on my second day of Stoic Week 2014: mindfulness</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/25/report-on-my-second-day-of-stoic-week-2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2014 23:50:38 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/25/report-on-my-second-day-of-stoic-week-2014/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, I reported on my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/11/24/report-on-my-first-day-of-stoic-week-2014/&#34;&gt;first day of Stoic Week 2014&lt;/a&gt;. Today, the second day&amp;rsquo;s theme was &amp;ldquo;Stoic mindfulness&amp;rdquo;. This is similar to the Buddhist teaching on mindfulness, and is basically a sound psychological observation that &amp;ldquo;You are just an impression and not at all the thing you claim to represent&amp;rdquo;: our thoughts and feelings are one thing but what we do about them is another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found it particularly useful to remember this today, because Tuesdays present an interesting challenge for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;chess&#34;&gt;Chess&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Tuesday nights, I have been playing in the latest 6-round current Tuesday night &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburghcc.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Chess Club&lt;/a&gt; tournament, one round every Tuesday. Tonight was round 4. I had experienced an extremely painful loss last week in round 3 when I was &lt;em&gt;not mindful&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://chessimprover.com/blockading-to-defend-when-things-get-tough/&#34;&gt;got carried away by emotions&lt;/a&gt;: I had an overwhelming advantage during an attack on my opponent&amp;rsquo;s King, but I allowed my excitement to cloud my judgment, make poor moves, and then worse, after I managed to recover and had the opportunity to survive with a draw, &lt;em&gt;and saw this&lt;/em&gt;, I passed it up out of wishful thinking that I could continue an attack, so I ended up losing. In chess, I face the stark reality that most losses at my level in local competition (where I am typically the top-rated player) are due to faulty psychology, rather than lack of sufficient understanding and skill. A loss of &lt;em&gt;objectivity&lt;/em&gt; (which all athletes and other performers under high pressure) is the reason we fail. Mindfulness directly addresses this all-too-human flaw.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;continuing-habits-from-yesterday&#34;&gt;Continuing habits from yesterday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, I noted that I began meditating and exercising again, because it was in my power to do so. I have continued. It&amp;rsquo;s been tricky to get going again, because my body is out of whack, but I remember to do what I can, no more, with faith that incremental progress will pay off. Instead of running, I did a &lt;a href=&#34;http://well.blogs.nytimes.com/projects/workouts/&#34;&gt;7-minute workout&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;ve lost a lot of strength over the years and plan to regain it. I have dumbbells lying around the house from when I was using them a decade ago; it&amp;rsquo;s time to get back to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;tonight-s-chess-game&#34;&gt;Tonight&amp;rsquo;s chess game&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I won a decent game tonight at the chess tournament. It was the third last to finish, taking almost four hours. I&amp;rsquo;ve played against my opponent many times before over the years, mostly winning, but the last time I played him, he held me to a draw, despite a 500-rating-point difference (which is huge). One thing that sometimes happens in tournament chess is overconfidence when facing someone who is on paper much weaker, or fear because of a past bad result. Mindfulness teaches us that although historical facts are facts, we should distance ourselves from distracting feelings about them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As in many hard-fought chess games, I experienced a range of emotions during the game. First of all, in the opening, although I was doing OK, I was frustrated that I allowed a certain kind of position I ordinarily do not allow, because of an oversight. Instead of kicking myself, I focused to do what I could with what I had, assessing that even though I did not want that position, it was actually still OK for me. (Actually, computer analysis afterwards showed that I was more than OK, so I was still more pessimistic than warranted during the game.) In the middlegame, I emerged with an advantage, but then faced a curious choice. My opponent gave me an opportunity to win some material (a Rook for a Bishop and Pawn) at the expense of destroying my Pawn structure and therefore creating good chances for a draw. At the time, I saw no better winning try, so I went for it, deciding that, unlike last week, I was going to settle for a draw if my opponent could prove he could defend; I simply made sure to play soundly and not recklessly. It turned out that he cracked eventually and I won. I was pleased that I remained psychologically strong in the game and was rewarded accordingly. (For those of you interested in the technical details of the game, I will be annotating it in an upcoming article I will write for &lt;a href=&#34;http://chessimprover.com/category/franklin-chen/&#34;&gt;my weekly column in The Chess Improver&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;heavy-traffic&#34;&gt;Heavy traffic&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another thing: when driving home from work to eat dinner before the chess game, I noticed that the traffic was unusually bad. Mindfulness is always helpful when facing stressful situations like this. I was upset with myself for not anticipating apparent pre-Thanksgiving-holiday traffic and therefore being pressed for time to get home and eat dinner before playing chess. I decided to let go of my self-annoyance because it wasn&amp;rsquo;t going to help me get home any sooner and would just sap my mental energy I needed for my game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mindfulness is something I&amp;rsquo;ve had prior experience in trying to adopt well before I even read about Stoicism. But having a daily theme and reading during Stoic Week has been surprisingly helpful in keeping me aware.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Are you familiar with the concept of mindfulness and the scientific underpinnings of it? If so, do you deliberately practice it? Do you have misgivings about it?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Chess Improver: The strange pleasure of drawing a lost game</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/18/the-chess-improver-the-strange-pleasure-of-drawing-a-lost-game/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Oct 2013 07:40:02 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/18/the-chess-improver-the-strange-pleasure-of-drawing-a-lost-game/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I concluded my series of posts about the Pittsburgh Chess Club six-round Tuesday night tournament that I just completed with an article about managing to draw my final round game: &lt;a href=&#34;http://chessimprover.com/the-strange-pleasure-of-drawing-a-lost-game/&#34;&gt;The strange pleasure of drawing a lost game&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that my tournament is over, I will use other material for my weekly blog posts on &lt;a href=&#34;http://chessimprover.com/&#34;&gt;The Chess Improver&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Chess Improver: the difference between accepting reality and making excuses</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/10/the-chess-improver-the-difference-between-accepting-reality-and-making-excuses/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2013 08:04:02 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/10/the-chess-improver-the-difference-between-accepting-reality-and-making-excuses/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Last week, I wrote on &lt;a href=&#34;http://chessimprover.com/&#34;&gt;The Chess Improver&lt;/a&gt; about &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/10/03/the-chess-improver-the-psychology-of-losing-a-drawn-game/&#34;&gt;my fourth round game in the current Pittsburgh Chess Club Tuesday night tournament, in which I lost a game that should have been drawn&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This week, I wrote about my fifth round game, in which I won, but played poorly at a critical point: &lt;a href=&#34;http://chessimprover.com/the-difference-between-accepting-reality-and-making-excuses/&#34;&gt;The difference between accepting reality and making excuses&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>9 things you could be doing in Pittsburgh on Saturday, October 5</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/04/9-things-you-could-be-doing-in-pittsburgh-on-saturday-october-5/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2013 00:46:44 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/04/9-things-you-could-be-doing-in-pittsburgh-on-saturday-october-5/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m always frustrated at this time of year because there are so many events of interest to me in Pittsburgh that seem to happen on the first weekend of October. Since I cannot attend all of them, I figured I might as well attempt a public service and mention some of them so that if you are in the Pittsburgh area, maybe you can go and enjoy what I can&amp;rsquo;t attend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So here are 9 of the probably dozens of cool things you could be doing tomorrow, Saturday, October 5, 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;free-concert-allegheny-city-ragtime-orchestra&#34;&gt;Free concert: Allegheny City Ragtime Orchestra&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re interested in ragtime or Latin music, check out &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.shadysideacademy.org/page.cfm?p=12541&#34;&gt;this concert by the Allegheny City Ragtime Orchestra&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some articles in anticipation of it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.post-gazette.com/stories/ae/music/preview-ragtime-orchestra-connects-with-history-705929/&#34;&gt;Post-Gazette&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://triblive.com/aande/music/4763900-74/ragtime-music-concert&#34;&gt;Trib&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I wanted to go, but finally decided that we have too many other activities earlier in the day and need to just stay home and unwind in the evening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;free-conference-podcamp-pittsburgh-8&#34;&gt;Free conference: PodCamp Pittsburgh 8&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 8th annual &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.podcamppittsburgh.com/&#34;&gt;PodCamp Pittsburgh&lt;/a&gt; should be good. If you have any interest in using social media for personal or professional purposes, you should check it out. Interesting talks, opportunities to just socialized and learn new things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I attended in 2010, 2011, 2012, and will attend again for the fourth year. Unfortunately, I will only be able to attend the afternoon sessions. But I didn&amp;rsquo;t want to completely miss it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that PodCamp completely changed my life. For example, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/21/one-month-anniversary-of-my-blog/&#34;&gt;I started this blog in 2011 because of my second PodCamp&lt;/a&gt;, and I became serious about using social media in general, and that led to a total transformation of my life as I learned about local activities and made new friends. (Unfortunately, I didn&amp;rsquo;t get around to finishing my draft reports about my experience at last year&amp;rsquo;s PodCamp 7.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;pittsburgh-south-side-slopes-step-trek&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh South Side Slopes Step Trek&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The annual &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.southsideslopes.org/steptrek/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh South Side Slopes Step Trek&lt;/a&gt; is another event you can attend tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/08/my-god-its-full-of-stairs-pittsburgh-step-trek-2011/&#34;&gt;blog coverage two years ago&lt;/a&gt; as well as my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/09/25/why-you-should-go-out-to-the-pittsburgh-south-side-slopes-step-trek/&#34;&gt;recent update&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, Abby and I will be missing it this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;run-shadyside-5k&#34;&gt;Run Shadyside 5K&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you like to run in races, a fine race is the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.runshadyside.com/&#34;&gt;Run Shadyside 5K&lt;/a&gt;. Fast and flat, with a pancake breakfast and festivities afterwards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not running in it this year, just because I have too many other things to do already for the rest of the day, but here&amp;rsquo;s my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/01/run-shadyside-5k-outrunning-mickey-mouse-and-lending-a-trumpet/&#34;&gt;report from two years ago&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;free-5th-annual-wilkins-school-community-center-ecofest-in-regent-square&#34;&gt;Free: 5th annual Wilkins School Community Center Ecofest in Regent Square&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/ecofest-2013.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;5th annual Wilkins School Community Center Ecofest in Regent Square&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Interested in green living? Check out the &lt;a href=&#34;http://foresthills-regentsquare.patch.com/groups/around-town/p/ecofest-encourages-recycling-green-living&#34;&gt;5th annual Wilkins School Community Center Ecofest in Regent Square&lt;/a&gt;. Abby has regularly attended for the clothing swap. There will also be food, information, and entertainment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that this year, I will also be attending, to perform as a new member of the Steel City Ukuleles. &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/08/23/another-unexpected-life-change-one-month-of-learning-to-play-ukulele/&#34;&gt;I just started playing the ukulele a bit over two months ago&lt;/a&gt;, and have been working hard to help put on an entertaining show!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;ll be performing around 11:30 AM to 12:30 PM. If you come, say hello!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;cmu-donut-dash-2-mile-race&#34;&gt;CMU Donut Dash 2 mile race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, if you are into weird running events, there is the &lt;a href=&#34;http://cmudonutdash.org/&#34;&gt;Carnegie Mellon University Donut Dash&lt;/a&gt;, a 2 mile event serving as a fundraiser for the Children&amp;rsquo;s Hospital of Pittsburgh of UPMC. This is not an event I have ever done, and not one I intend to do, but what the heck, some of you might love this sort of thing!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;national-chess-day-gateway-open-tournament-at-the-pittsburgh-chess-club&#34;&gt;National Chess Day: Gateway Open tournament at the Pittsburgh Chess Club&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did you know that it&amp;rsquo;s time for &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nationalchessday.com/&#34;&gt;National Chess Day&lt;/a&gt;? There will be a tournament at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburghcc.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Chess Club&lt;/a&gt;, the 56th annual Gateway Open. Yes, chess in Pittsburgh has a long and illustrious history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;pittsburgh-perl-workshop&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Perl Workshop&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are a Perl programmer, the &lt;a href=&#34;http://pghpw.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Perl Workshop&lt;/a&gt; is back &lt;a href=&#34;http://pghpw.org/ppw2013/&#34;&gt;this year&lt;/a&gt;. Registration is already closed, so it&amp;rsquo;s not so helpful right now for me to mention it, but in case you didn&amp;rsquo;t know it existed, watch for it next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;ninth-thing&#34;&gt;Ninth thing?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, I guess I miscounted. But there are a whole lot more than nine things to do in Pittsburgh tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, if you are interested in some free stuff to do, there&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.radworkshere.org/interior.php?pageID=64&#34;&gt;RADical Days&lt;/a&gt; listing a whole bunch of stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s no shortage of stuff to do in this great city of Pittsburgh at any time or day of year. I think it&amp;rsquo;s unfortunate that many things I like to do happen to repeatedly fall on the first Saturday of the year, but I&amp;rsquo;m not complaining about an embarrassment of riches. Go out and take advantage of what I can&amp;rsquo;t.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Chess Improver: the psychology of losing a drawn game</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/03/the-chess-improver-the-psychology-of-losing-a-drawn-game/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Oct 2013 07:29:14 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/03/the-chess-improver-the-psychology-of-losing-a-drawn-game/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/15th-fred-sorensen-memorial/round-4.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Round 4&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Last week, I wrote on &lt;a href=&#34;http://chessimprover.com/&#34;&gt;The Chess Improver&lt;/a&gt; about &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/09/26/the-chess-improver-the-psychology-of-not-winning-the-won-game/&#34;&gt;my third round game in the current Pittsburgh Chess Club Tuesday night tournament, in which I had a won game but did not win&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This week, I wrote about my fourth round game, in which I did even worse, hence my new post: &lt;a href=&#34;http://chessimprover.com/the-psychology-of-losing-a-drawn-game/&#34;&gt;The psychology of losing a drawn game&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Chess Improver: the psychology of not winning the won game</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/09/26/the-chess-improver-the-psychology-of-not-winning-the-won-game/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Sep 2013 08:13:50 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/09/26/the-chess-improver-the-psychology-of-not-winning-the-won-game/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/15th-fred-sorensen-memorial/round-3.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Round 3&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I published my third post on the blog &lt;a href=&#34;http://chessimprover.com/&#34;&gt;The Chess Improver&lt;/a&gt;. It covers my third round game in the current Pittsburgh Chess Club Tuesday night tournament, in which I was very disappointed because I had a won game but failed to actually win the game!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://chessimprover.com/the-psychology-of-not-winning-the-won-game/&#34;&gt;The psychology of not winning the won game.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Chess Improver: remember the importance of development</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/09/19/the-chess-improver-remember-the-importance-of-development/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Sep 2013 08:34:10 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/09/19/the-chess-improver-remember-the-importance-of-development/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I published my second post on the blog &lt;a href=&#34;http://chessimprover.com/&#34;&gt;The Chess Improver&lt;/a&gt;. It covers my second round game in the current Pittsburgh Chess Club Tuesday night tournament, in which I won, but suffered for a bit because I neglected a basic principle in chess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://chessimprover.com/remember-the-importance-of-development/&#34;&gt;Remember the importance of development!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Saying No: on not playing in the Pittsburgh Chess League this season for the CMU Tartans</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/09/15/saying-no-on-not-playing-in-the-pittsburgh-chess-league-this-season-for-the-cmu-tartans/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Sep 2013 00:14:55 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/09/15/saying-no-on-not-playing-in-the-pittsburgh-chess-league-this-season-for-the-cmu-tartans/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://twitchfilm.com/assets/2011/07/120889.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Chess&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Later today, the first round of the 2013-14 season of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pitt.edu/~schach/ChessPA/ChessLeague/wpapcl.htm&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Chess League&lt;/a&gt; will start, and I will not be there to play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;last-season&#34;&gt;Last season&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last season, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/04/29/celebrating-the-victory-of-the-cmu-tartans-in-the-2012-13-pittsburgh-chess-league-season/&#34;&gt;I played in the Pittsburgh Chess League as a member of the CMU Tartans and we won&lt;/a&gt;. As I mentioned, out of the six rounds our team played in (one round was a bye for each team), I ended up playing only in the first two of those rounds, the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/10/14/pittsburgh-chess-league-round-2-natural-moves-are-often-bad/&#34;&gt;October&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/11/11/pittsburgh-chess-league-round-3-back-to-chess-after-a-month-off/&#34;&gt;November&lt;/a&gt;. After that, I simply kept running into trouble:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;having &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/02/oblivion-obsession-time-to-start-playing-melodica/&#34;&gt;schedule conflicts&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/0130/why-and-how-i-am-going-to-run-the-2013-pittsburgh-marathon&#34;&gt;getting sick&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/02/20/pittsburgh-chess-club-championship-2013-round-6-winning-as-black-like-a-madman/&#34;&gt;having to take care of Abby after an accident&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/04/06/comeback-from-pittsburgh-marathon-overtraining/&#34;&gt;being exhausted from marathon training&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One way or another, I kept on not being up to the prospect of spending up to &lt;em&gt;five hours&lt;/em&gt; on a single chess game on a Sunday afternoon from 2 PM to 7 PM. Repeatedly, when asked whether I could play in an upcoming round, I felt guilty about saying that I would play only in case of an emergency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;saying-no&#34;&gt;Saying &amp;ldquo;No&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This fall, I made the tough decision to leave the Pittsburgh Chess League, telling CMU Tartans team captain Jeff some weeks ago that I preferred not to be on the roster this year at all, even as an alternate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve had a lifelong difficulty with saying &amp;ldquo;No&amp;rdquo;, not only &lt;a href=&#34;http://zenhabits.net/say-no/&#34;&gt;to others&lt;/a&gt; but also to myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heck, I even wrote a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/02/23/saying-no-in-order-to-say-yes/&#34;&gt;blog post well over two years ago about saying &amp;ldquo;No&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, but I don&amp;rsquo;t also optimally apply to myself my own advice!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve had a habit of taking on all kinds of obligations or activities that stretched myself thin, resulting in subpar performance and dependability, and meanwhile, anxiety, guilt, and shame. People deserve better than this from me. I deserve better than this from me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;chess&#34;&gt;Chess&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love chess, but it can be very time and energy-consuming, so I have to be careful about how much time I spend on it at all. This year, it turns out that I completely stopped playing chess in February, and &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/09/12/my-first-post-on-the-chess-improver-the-value-of-thematic-complete-games-against-a-weaker-opponent/&#34;&gt;just came back now in September, along with becoming a new contributor to the Chess Improver blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually looking at my calendar and my overall plans for the next half year, I decided that if I cannot be a dependable team member for the CMU Tartans (in terms of regularly showing up to play for the team as well as playing well for the team), then it is better not to be on the team at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, I also decided that after the current Pittsburgh Chess Club Tuesday night tournament concludes in October (I just finished the first two of six rounds in the 15th Fred Sorensen Memorial), I will, unlike last year, &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; continue on in the following Tuesday night tournament (November-December), because based on how my schedule went in the past two years, those two months are very busy for me, and the last two years I barely stumbled to winter break alive, and performed terribly in the tournament last year, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/11/round-5-of-pittsburgh-chess-club-tournament-psychology-of-losing-another-won-game/&#34;&gt;ridiculously losing two won games&lt;/a&gt;, and also performed suboptimally in other projects I was doing. I&amp;rsquo;m not going to let that happen this year. It is not only chess I am cutting out for November-December, but most likely some musical activities as well (yet to be finalized).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was better for the CMU Tartans to find a reliable replacement for me than for me to be undependable for them. Luka has left town, and I have dropped out, but the team has managed to get Joe Mucerino on board, so I hope all will go well for the team in the new season of the Pittsburgh Chess League with the reduced number of members.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saying &amp;ldquo;No&amp;rdquo; to others and to myself is very difficult. I enjoy new projects and challenges. But if doing too much means not doing everything optimally well, then what&amp;rsquo;s the point? So I&amp;rsquo;ve taken a big step toward reclaiming my sanity by choosing not to be a part of the Pittsburgh Chess League this year.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My first post on The Chess Improver: The Value of Thematic Complete Games Against a Weaker Opponent</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/09/12/my-first-post-on-the-chess-improver-the-value-of-thematic-complete-games-against-a-weaker-opponent/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Sep 2013 05:04:25 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/09/12/my-first-post-on-the-chess-improver-the-value-of-thematic-complete-games-against-a-weaker-opponent/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Today is my debut as a contributor to the blog &lt;a href=&#34;http://chessimprover.com/&#34;&gt;The Chess Improver&lt;/a&gt;, thanks to the invitation of GM Nigel Davies to join in the sharing of ideas and observations about improving at chess (and even more generally, other endeavors as well). I will be regularly writing about chess there instead of here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that although the blog does not support comments, Nigel Davies hosts lively discussions about each blog post on Facebook through &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/nigel.davies1&#34;&gt;his account&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;both-participant-and-observer&#34;&gt;Both participant and observer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since it turns out that I have just finished two of the six rounds in the current Pittsburgh Chess Club Tuesday night tournament, the 15th Fred Sorensen Memorial, I began my debut by using my first round game as material for a post to beginn a discussion about &lt;a href=&#34;http://chessimprover.com/the-value-of-thematic-complete-games-against-a-weaker-opponent/&#34;&gt;learning from imperfectly played games that, however, illustrate chess themes well&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/15th-fred-sorensen-memorial/round-1.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Round 1&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/15th-fred-sorensen-memorial/round-1-in-progress.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Round 1 in progress&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I will have a post up next week about my second round game of this week, which was quite interesting. I will not always be writing about my own games on the blog, of course. They just happen to be, right now, a timely source of relevant material, since I am in the middle of a tournament.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;previous-chess-writings&#34;&gt;Previous chess writings&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I have not played tournament chess since &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/02/20/pittsburgh-chess-club-championship-2013-round-6-winning-as-black-like-a-madman/&#34;&gt;winning the 2013 Pittsburgh Chess Club Championship in February&lt;/a&gt;, if you have discovered this blog only recently, you may be interested in exploring my previous &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/chess/&#34;&gt;chess writings&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pittsburgh Chess Club Championship 2013, Round 6: Winning as Black like a madman!</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/02/20/pittsburgh-chess-club-championship-2013-round-6-winning-as-black-like-a-madman/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Feb 2013 01:15:56 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/02/20/pittsburgh-chess-club-championship-2013-round-6-winning-as-black-like-a-madman/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/wallnau-chen-2013-02-19_files/round-6.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Round 6 panorama&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/wallnau-chen-2013-02-19_files/round-6-game.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Round 6 Wallnau-Chen&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In the 6th and final round of the Pittsburgh Chess Club Championship of 2013, I was Black against Kurt Wallnau, as I mentioned I would be in &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/02/14/pittsburgh-chess-club-championship-2013-round-5-surprised-at-move-4-of-the-opening/&#34;&gt;my report on round 5&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;d promised him before the game that I was going to &lt;em&gt;play for a win as Black&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.gmsquare.com/BlackisOKAdorjan.html&#34;&gt;Black is OK!&lt;/a&gt;), even though I only needed a draw to secure undisputed first place in the tournament, since I went into the final round one full point ahead of him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I played aggressively like a madman and brought home the full point, thereby becoming the Pittsburgh Chess Club Champion of 2013!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have to admit that objectively, my opening choice was risky, but I&amp;rsquo;ll explain why I played so wildly as Black.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/wallnau-chen-2013-02-19_files/final-position.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Final position&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-complete-annotated-game&#34;&gt;My complete annotated game&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At your convenience, you can &lt;a href=&#34;../../chess/wallnau-chen-2013-02-19.htm&#34;&gt;enjoy playing over the game with my annotations, including diagrams&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;preparation&#34;&gt;Preparation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/02/14/pittsburgh-chess-club-championship-2013-round-5-surprised-at-move-4-of-the-opening/&#34;&gt;I mentioned last week&lt;/a&gt;, I have played one tournament game against Kurt before, and I lost &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/11/round-5-of-pittsburgh-chess-club-tournament-psychology-of-losing-another-won-game/&#34;&gt;that game&lt;/a&gt;. So yes, I was out for revenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had no time to prepare any particular opening surprise against Kurt, because of the personal emergency that Abby and I have been dealing with for over a week now (her fracturing a foot last Monday), the consequence of which our lives have (temporarily, we hope) turned upside down!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was very happy that only one game remained in this tournament. Immediately after the accident, I had informed the captain of the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/11/11/pittsburgh-chess-league-round-3-back-to-chess-after-a-month-off/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Chess League&lt;/a&gt; team I&amp;rsquo;m on that yet again, I was not going to be able to play in the month&amp;rsquo;s round (which is next Sunday). That means I&amp;rsquo;ll have missed the December, January, and February rounds because of unforeseen circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All I can say is that the only preparation I&amp;rsquo;ve had in the past two rounds has been doing a ten-minute meditation at home half an hour before the round began, in order to calm myself after a very stressful and tiring day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;overview-of-my-game&#34;&gt;Overview of my game&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-opening&#34;&gt;The opening&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amusingly, it did not matter that I did not prepare anything against any of what I remembered Kurt&amp;rsquo;s opening repertoire to be, because he played something I&amp;rsquo;d never seen him play before, &lt;code&gt;Nf3&lt;/code&gt;, going for a Reti! So he was the one who &amp;ldquo;surprised&amp;rdquo; me, rather than vice versa. Or so he thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I &amp;ldquo;threatened&amp;rdquo; to go into an ultra-aggressive reversed &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/King%27s_Indian_Defence&#34;&gt;King&amp;rsquo;s Indian&lt;/a&gt; against him (normally Black does not play the White side of a King&amp;rsquo;s Indian one tempo down), and he allowed me to do so, and so I did!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/wallnau-chen-2013-02-19_files/diag3FA2AF509B32EED9.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Reversed King&amp;#39;s Indian&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h4 id=&#34;subtleties-of-playing-black&#34;&gt;Subtleties of playing Black&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What was really crazy of me, however, was playing a provocative and surely not quite sound wing attack &lt;code&gt;g5&lt;/code&gt; against him:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/wallnau-chen-2013-02-19_files/diag3FA2AF68AF45BB6D.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I was inspired to do this by profoundly technical as well as philosophical thoughts both by &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andr%C3%A1s_Adorj%C3%A1n&#34;&gt;Andrs Adorjn&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_L._Watson&#34;&gt;John Watson&lt;/a&gt; about the nature of playing Black in &amp;ldquo;reversed&amp;rdquo; openings. The idea is that in many variations, being one tempo down is not necessarily a disadvantage, because White&amp;rsquo;s extra tempo means having committed to something, and therefore &amp;ldquo;giving&amp;rdquo; Black some &lt;em&gt;information&lt;/em&gt; that can be useful. In this particular case, for example, I started off with a reversed &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/King%27s_Indian_Defence#Averbakh_Variation&#34;&gt;Averbakh variation&lt;/a&gt;, but then because I had not yet committed to putting a Bishop on &lt;code&gt;g4&lt;/code&gt; or on &lt;code&gt;e6&lt;/code&gt;, and White has committed to castling already, the flank attack &lt;code&gt;g5&lt;/code&gt; looks interesting, because of ideas Black might have of not only getting in &lt;code&gt;g4&lt;/code&gt;, but maybe also prying open the &lt;code&gt;h&lt;/code&gt; file while lifting the Queen possibly to &lt;code&gt;d6&lt;/code&gt; and to &lt;code&gt;g6&lt;/code&gt;. The point is that there are very &lt;em&gt;concrete&lt;/em&gt; reasons to justify this bizarre attack. This is not to say that it is entirely sound (I don&amp;rsquo;t believe it is!), but at least this attack has some real basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I should note that John Watson&amp;rsquo;s book &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Secrets-Modern-Chess-Strategy-Watson/dp/1901983072&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Secrets of Modern Chess Strategy&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; was the single primary reason for my returning to serious chess play in 2005 after twenty years of absence: I had accidentally come across this book in a book store and been so profoundly captivated by it that I bought it (and also &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Chess-Strategy-Action-John-Watson/dp/1901983692&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Chess Strategy in Action&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;) and completely altered my perception of the concrete beauty and excitement of chess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, I also played &lt;code&gt;g5&lt;/code&gt; because I was sure that Kurt would be completely surprised by it: he may have surprised me first, but I was going to surprise him in return!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;white-playing-the-reverse-also&#34;&gt;White playing the reverse also&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I expected, Kurt went into a reversed &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Benko_Gambit&#34;&gt;Benko Gambit&lt;/a&gt; sacrificial attack against me (and it is completely sound here for White):&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/wallnau-chen-2013-02-19_files/diag3FA2AF75802672A2.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Reversed Benko&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h4 id=&#34;i-fell-into-a-bad-position&#34;&gt;I fell into a bad position&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At an important point, after some not entirely accurate play on both sides, I could have engaged in a consistent and good &lt;code&gt;h4&lt;/code&gt; attack as follows:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/wallnau-chen-2013-02-19_files/diag3FA2AFA162ABCEB7.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;h4 was best&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But I got cold feet and decided to try to castle. This was actually a serious mistake and led to very frightening positions in which I was not confident that I would be able to defend against White&amp;rsquo;s initiative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even after I managed to get in a thematic Rook lift to &lt;code&gt;a6&lt;/code&gt;, I was not confident in my position:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/wallnau-chen-2013-02-19_files/diag3FA2AFC8FF90EDBA.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Black Rook lift&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-middlegame&#34;&gt;The middlegame&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After much complex play, we arrived at an important position in which the question is, how can White continue to press?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/wallnau-chen-2013-02-19_files/diag3FA2AFEF0EC76AE5.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Tense&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;White erred by moving his Bishop to &lt;code&gt;c7&lt;/code&gt; to chase the Black Queen to &lt;code&gt;d7&lt;/code&gt;, which is not really a problem for Black at all:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/wallnau-chen-2013-02-19_files/diag3FA2AFF7FD738D7E.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Bishop at c7 is useless&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Then White allowed Black to develop both &lt;code&gt;Ba6&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;Rc8&lt;/code&gt; led to a decent position for Black at last:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/wallnau-chen-2013-02-19_files/diag3FA2B0021662A97A.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Black is OK&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I was finally feeling safe in the game.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/wallnau-chen-2013-02-19_files/white-thinking.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Kurt thinking&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h4 id=&#34;white-s-first-blunder-was-a-terrible-one&#34;&gt;White&amp;rsquo;s first blunder was a terrible one&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;White then blundered away two pieces (the Knight on &lt;code&gt;b5&lt;/code&gt; and the Bishop on &lt;code&gt;d5&lt;/code&gt; for a Rook. After this, I was finally happy, knowing I had a completely won game. The only question was, how to consolidate?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/wallnau-chen-2013-02-19_files/diag3FA2B025D11333E1.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;White blundered&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It turned out that we both started running low on time, and also I started playing less than perfectly. I was obsessed with winning the &lt;code&gt;d5&lt;/code&gt; Pawn, but it was not really necessary to go for that in order to win the game. Focusing on the passed Pawns on the Queen side was best, because White could not break through on the King side anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I allowed White some counterplay, but still had a won position anyway. Then White tried an idea with &lt;code&gt;h4&lt;/code&gt; to get the Queen to &lt;code&gt;g5&lt;/code&gt;, but this was too slow:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/wallnau-chen-2013-02-19_files/diag3FA2B078263AB597.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;h4&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Black&amp;rsquo;s &lt;code&gt;Rd6&lt;/code&gt; guaranteed winning the &lt;code&gt;d5&lt;/code&gt; Pawn and therefore the game along the long diagonal to &lt;code&gt;h1&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/wallnau-chen-2013-02-19_files/diag3FA2B07F87383659.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;White is lost&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The final position when White resigned:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/wallnau-chen-2013-02-19_files/diag3FA2B0DA043489BC.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Final position&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;lessons-learned-from-my-game&#34;&gt;Lessons learned from my game&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s not much use &amp;ldquo;preparing&amp;rdquo; anyway against an opponent who plays all kinds of openings, not just a narrow set.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When playing a &amp;ldquo;reversed&amp;rdquo; opening, Black may have subtle additional opportunities to complicate the game.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When on the attack out of the opening, getting cold feet and not continuing it can result in much pain.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;White lost a long-held advantage and then quickly blundered badly; this flow of &amp;ldquo;momentum&amp;rdquo; is a common feature of chess games between humans.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Black also lost some momentum after achieving a won game, but managed to keep the winning advantage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;statistics&#34;&gt;Statistics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is the final rated &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.uschess.org/msa/XtblMain.php?201302193592&#34;&gt;crosstable for the Pittsburgh Chess Club Championship&lt;/a&gt;. As a result of my winning all six games, my rating has finally bounced back upward, from 2126 to 2164: I defeated opponents rated 1728, 1947, 2050, 1999, 2072, 2077. My lifetime peak was in 2008 when &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.uschess.org/msa/XtblMain.php?200801273991.1-12226800&#34;&gt;I reached 2197&lt;/a&gt; (3 points short of getting a US Chess National &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chess_master&#34;&gt;Master&lt;/a&gt; title).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-next&#34;&gt;What next?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I felt proud of myself for playing hard for the win and not for a draw as Black when I did not need to for tournament purposes. I am of course ecstatic that I finally won the Pittsburgh Chess Club Championship again, and that I played fairly well in this tournament, after so many years of not really performing anywhere near how I used to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In August I wrote about my goals in returning to &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/08/21/returning-to-chess/&#34;&gt;tournament play again&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/08/29/returning-to-chess/&#34;&gt;Tuesday night tournaments in particular&lt;/a&gt;. Despite not playing as well as I knew I could in the first two tournaments, because of poor time/energy/psychology management, I finally got my act together and played reasonably well in this one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wish I could say that I look forward to continuing my &amp;ldquo;streak&amp;rdquo; soon, but the reality is that in January, I had already decided, well before the conclusion of this tournament, and before Abby&amp;rsquo;s fractured foot, to &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/30/why-and-how-i-am-going-to-run-the-2013-pittsburgh-marathon/&#34;&gt;stop playing in Tuesday night tournaments for several months, until possibly fall&lt;/a&gt;. At the time, I had already concluded that I have many projects to work on in the coming months, and it&amp;rsquo;s really been quite difficult to squeeze in the time and energy to play in Tuesday night tournaments, especially given how my games seem to always last past 11 PM, and that messes up my ideal sleep schedule.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As explained in my August posts, I no longer have any particular rating or title goals; I found that having them backfired badly on me. I will never again play competitive chess with any goals other than to play logically and creatively to the best of my abilities given my real life constraints.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2015-12-21&#34;&gt;(Update of 2015-12-21)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So much for giving up competitive goals: two years later, I made a
focused push, temporarily putting many things aside in my life, in the
fall of 2015 to &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2016/01/22/on-finally-achieving-the-us-national-master-chess-title-at-age-45-part-1&#34;&gt;achieve my US Chess National Master&lt;/a&gt; title, and finally
made it, a dream come true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, during all this time, my real passion for chess has always
been the teaching that I started in 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;thanks&#34;&gt;Thanks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would like to thank tournament director Mike Holsinger for doing a fine job running yet another Tuesday night tournament, handling pairings and attending to players&amp;rsquo; questions during rounds. It is quite a commitment to direct a tournament for six straight weeks!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would like to thank all of my opponents, as co-creators of these fascinating games that we have played together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would also like to thank everyone who follows my chess postings on my blog and has encouraged me to do chess writing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I dedicate the win of this tournament to Abby, who has never seen me win a Pittsburgh Chess Club Championship since we&amp;rsquo;ve known each other, and supported my effort this year to finally win it again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed the really tense game with Kurt in the final round, in which he applied considerable pressure that forced me to think very hard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a great time playing in the Pittsburgh Chess Club Championship of 2013, and managing to win it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although I&amp;rsquo;m taking a break from tournament chess, &lt;strong&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll be back!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pittsburgh Chess Club Championship 2013, Round 5: Surprised at move 4 of the opening!</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/02/14/pittsburgh-chess-club-championship-2013-round-5-surprised-at-move-4-of-the-opening/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Feb 2013 22:06:16 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/02/14/pittsburgh-chess-club-championship-2013-round-5-surprised-at-move-4-of-the-opening/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/chen-edahl-2013-02-12_files/after-move-4.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin in deep throught after move 4&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Round 5 of the annual &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburghcc.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Chess Club&lt;/a&gt; Championship involved a very unusual (for me) situation: being surprised at move 4 out of the opening! (Amusingly, Kurt was taking a bunch of photos at the time and happened to get a photo of me being surprised, and later sent it to me.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I coped well and played what I thought to be perhaps my cleanest game yet in this tournament.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I report on the psychology of how to deal with opening surprises, and other turning points in the game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-complete-annotated-game&#34;&gt;My complete annotated game&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At your convenience, you can &lt;a href=&#34;../../chess/chen-edahl-2013-02-12.htm&#34;&gt;enjoy playing over the game with my annotations, including diagrams&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;preparation&#34;&gt;Preparation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/02/05/pittsburgh-chess-club-championship-2013-round-4-fascinating-attacking-defending-game/&#34;&gt;mentioned after last week&amp;rsquo;s game&lt;/a&gt;, for this week I was paired against Expert Richard Edahl, whom I had never played against before, so I had nothing special prepared against him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, I was occupied with a personal emergency (Abby broke her foot late last night, so we spent two hours at the emergency room) that had me taking the day off work and not knowing for sure whether I was going to even make it to the game (we spent another two hours in the morning at the hospital for more X-rays and a plan for recovery). I managed to get done what I needed to do and arrive at the club for the game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;overview-of-my-game&#34;&gt;Overview of my game&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-opening&#34;&gt;The opening&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Richard as Black played the first moves in the opening very quickly, then spent two minutes on his fourth move, playing a move, &lt;code&gt;e5&lt;/code&gt;, that I had &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; seen before or considered in this opening, and rose and walked away from the board:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/chen-edahl-2013-02-12_files/diag3F920BBB96735C8F.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;e5&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So what should one do when encountering a totally unexpected move in the opening? There are only a few possible explanations for an unexpected move:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it is a known good move, and I just have a bad memory or incomplete theoretical study of the opening&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it is a theoretical novelty that improves on previous play&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it is a bad move, and that&amp;rsquo;s why I have never seen it before&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this case, since the &amp;ldquo;new&amp;rdquo; move was at move 4, not deep in some obscure variation, I was sure that the move was a &lt;em&gt;bad&lt;/em&gt; one. So then the question was, how to &lt;em&gt;punish&lt;/em&gt; it? I spent 16 minutes calculating a whole series of lines in depth until I convinced myself of why the move was bad and how I could prove it no matter what my opponent&amp;rsquo;s followup moves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;does-black-lose-a-pawn&#34;&gt;Does Black lose a Pawn?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing to note is that Black does not lose the unprotected &lt;code&gt;e5&lt;/code&gt; Pawn to &lt;code&gt;Nxe5&lt;/code&gt;, because there is, at least, the discovered attack &lt;code&gt;Nxe4&lt;/code&gt; that regains the Pawn. However, just because Black regains a Pawn does not mean that the position is then equal. I quickly concluded that if Black played &lt;code&gt;Nxe4&lt;/code&gt;, I could force Black to accept a clearly inferior position by blocking up his Bishop and weakening his King side. (This is in fact what happened in the game.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I had to consider the possibility that Black could try to regain the Pawn a different way, with &lt;code&gt;Qe7&lt;/code&gt;. Here, I had to find out why this move &lt;em&gt;had&lt;/em&gt; to be bad (given my assumption that &lt;code&gt;e5&lt;/code&gt; in the first place was bad). Surely, if Black can regain the Pawn by chasing White&amp;rsquo;s Knight away, the position would be equal?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It took a while for me to find and verify the refutation of &lt;code&gt;Qe7&lt;/code&gt;, which in fact does &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; regain the Pawn. The trick is the sacrificial pin &lt;code&gt;Bg5&lt;/code&gt; threatening &lt;code&gt;Nd5&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/chen-edahl-2013-02-12_files/diag3F920E33D716AAE6.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So I offer this as an example of thinking a long time about a possible game continuation that did &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; take place, but &lt;em&gt;could have&lt;/em&gt;, and therefore had to be considered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;the-game-continuation&#34;&gt;The game continuation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After Black played &lt;code&gt;Nxe4&lt;/code&gt;, I forced the following position, clearly favorable to White:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/chen-edahl-2013-02-12_files/diag3F92125B2C8668D4.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Forced line after Nxe4&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What next? I decided to keep my options open and possibly aim to attack on the King side. Things were helped when my opponent moved his Queen away from the King side:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/chen-edahl-2013-02-12_files/diag3F92156C70DAFCC2.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-middlegame&#34;&gt;The middlegame&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, I had a choice: either safely castle King side with a huge positional advantage in the center and in development, or continue my King side attack plan, while setting a diabolical trap. I opted to set the trap with &lt;code&gt;h4&lt;/code&gt;; my opponent fell into the trap by playing &lt;code&gt;h5&lt;/code&gt;, after which my &lt;code&gt;Nd5&lt;/code&gt; won a Pawn, at the cost of a Queen trade and my giving up a Bishop for a Knight:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/chen-edahl-2013-02-12_files/diag3F92164A95676463.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Win a Pawn&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-endgame&#34;&gt;The endgame&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After I grabbed the Pawn on &lt;code&gt;c7&lt;/code&gt;, we arrived at this position:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/chen-edahl-2013-02-12_files/diag3F9217CA48E58BC1.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;White a Pawn up&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Then after some inaccurate play by Black, we arrived at an important position:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/chen-edahl-2013-02-12_files/diag3F92182DB48E01BE.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Black in trouble&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here, &lt;code&gt;Nd5&lt;/code&gt; was best, but instead I passively defended against &lt;code&gt;Bd3+&lt;/code&gt; with &lt;code&gt;R1c3&lt;/code&gt;, after which Black could have played actively with &lt;code&gt;Ba5&lt;/code&gt; and caused trouble, equalizing into a drawn position. Instead, he immediately lost with &lt;code&gt;Rd7??&lt;/code&gt;, which fell victim to &lt;code&gt;Be5+&lt;/code&gt; followed by &lt;code&gt;Nd5&lt;/code&gt; winning an exchange:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/chen-edahl-2013-02-12_files/diag3F9218981DC85007.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;White wins the exchange&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Black could have resigned, but did not; the rest of the game was anticlimactic, with Black blundering further and hanging a piece on &lt;code&gt;h4&lt;/code&gt; and immediately resigning:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/chen-edahl-2013-02-12_files/diag3F9218DF932964D5.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Final position&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;lessons-learned-from-my-game&#34;&gt;Lessons learned from my game&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do not panic when surprised in the opening; if you have prepared well, chances are the surprising move is a bad one, so just calculate out why it is bad.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Even in a completely winning position, one small passive move could lead to the losing side having enough active counterplay to equalize.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-next&#34;&gt;What next?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So after round 5, I am leading the tournament by an entire point, with a score of 5.0/6.0 going into round 6, and nobody else having 5.0 or even 4.5 points. This means that &lt;em&gt;no matter what happens in round 6&lt;/em&gt;, I am already tied for first for the title of Pittsburgh Chess Club Champion of 2013. I could lose and tie for first; if I draw or win, I get clear first, no tie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For round 6, I am paired against Kurt Wallnau, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/11/round-5-of-pittsburgh-chess-club-tournament-psychology-of-losing-another-won-game/&#34;&gt;who won a game against me in the last Tuesday night tournament&lt;/a&gt;. I get Black again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There will be some interesting psychology for our game, because &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/15/how-the-best-player-won-the-last-pittsburgh-chess-club-tuesday-night-tournament/&#34;&gt;just as in the last tournament, he needs to win in order to tie for first place&lt;/a&gt;: a draw leaves me the sole champion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Needless to say, I am playing in round 6 for the &lt;em&gt;win&lt;/em&gt;, not for the &lt;em&gt;draw&lt;/em&gt;. Although I would be very happy to become the clear Pittsburgh Chess Club Champion, prizes and titles don&amp;rsquo;t actually mean that much to me. My goal remains to play the best chess I can: a correct and creative game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a corollary, of course, if I manage to do that, I should also &lt;em&gt;as a side effect&lt;/em&gt; totally &lt;em&gt;destroy and crush&lt;/em&gt; my opponent, which also happens to be fun, I have to confess. There&amp;rsquo;s no way to euphemize this fundamentally warlike nature of chess. I&amp;rsquo;m a bit uneasy about it, but part of me enjoys releasing my aggression through chess. Check out this interview with current world number one Magnus Carlsen:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/Qc_v9mTfhC8&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Click in the video to 4:10, where he answers the interview question, &amp;ldquo;But you enjoy it when you see you opponents squirm?&amp;rdquo; He answers candidly, for all of us serious chess players:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Yes, I do. I enjoy it when I see my opponent, you know, really suffering, when he knows that I&#39;ve outsmarted him. If I lose just one game, then usually, you know, I just really want to [gestures violently and angrily] get revenge.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can&amp;rsquo;t deny this part of chess. I lost to Kurt in the last tournament, so what can I say? I&amp;rsquo;m itching to win.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, check out &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jamesrachels.org/stuart/stuchess.htm&#34;&gt;former American prodigy Stuart Rachels&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo; fascinating essay on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jamesrachels.org/stuart/Chessay.pdf&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Reviled Art&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed thinking for myself, outside of &amp;ldquo;book&amp;rdquo;, after move 4 in the opening in this game. I feel like I&amp;rsquo;ve been playing reasonably well in this tournament, and hope to conclude it with a good game next week.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pittsburgh Chess Club Championship 2013, Round 4: fascinating attacking-defending game!!</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/02/05/pittsburgh-chess-club-championship-2013-round-4-fascinating-attacking-defending-game/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Feb 2013 23:48:21 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/02/05/pittsburgh-chess-club-championship-2013-round-4-fascinating-attacking-defending-game/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/jansen-chen-2013-02-05_files/round-4.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Round 4 of the annual &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburghcc.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Chess Club&lt;/a&gt; Championship had me playing one of the most &lt;em&gt;fascinating&lt;/em&gt; games I have played in my entire life. My opponent tried to wipe me off the board with a brute-force attack in the early moves of the opening and I managed to defend, but there were various subtleties involved. He engaged in &lt;em&gt;sacrifice&lt;/em&gt; after sacrifice, not all sound, but all interesting.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/jansen-chen-2013-02-05_files/final-position.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-complete-annotated-game&#34;&gt;My complete annotated game&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At your convenience, you can &lt;a href=&#34;../../chess/jansen-chen-2013-02-05.htm&#34;&gt;enjoy playing over the game with my annotations, including diagrams&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In fact, it is necessary to read the detailed annotations to get a full picture of all the best moves that neither player saw but existed.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;preparation&#34;&gt;Preparation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned in &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/02/03/pittsburgh-chess-club-championship-2013-round-3-attack-defense-and-sacrifices/&#34;&gt;my report on the previous round&lt;/a&gt;, I knew that for today, I would face Peter Jansen (currently rated 1999), and that I know how he plays the openings. I knew that he tries to play solidly for a draw against stronger players, so I had to figure out a way to maximize my winning chances. I planned a particular &lt;em&gt;ultra-aggressive&lt;/em&gt; opening as Black against him, the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dutch_Defence&#34;&gt;Dutch Defense&lt;/a&gt;, the goal of which is avoid early contact while preparing to stake out a claim in the center as well as on the King side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In particular, I remembered that some years ago, Peter had been White against Grandmaster &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alexander_Shabalov&#34;&gt;Alexander Shabalov&lt;/a&gt; (who is a four-time winner of the US Chess Championship, and also happens to live in Squirrel Hill in Pittsburgh) and Shabalov had used the Dutch as Black against him. (Actually, I had misremembered the occasion as a simultaneous exhibition; after our game, when I told Peter about my preparation, he said that the game had been an actual tournament game. I looked and verified that it was a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.uschess.org/assets/msa_joomla/XtblMain.php?200710142921.1-12533530&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Chess League game in 2007&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;overview-of-my-game&#34;&gt;Overview of my game&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-opening&#34;&gt;The opening&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Peter played &lt;em&gt;exactly&lt;/em&gt; as I predicted he would, and we reached a position that I had concluded was fine for Black. After playing &lt;code&gt;h6&lt;/code&gt; to kick White&amp;rsquo;s Bishop, I fully expected a retreat and then a slow progression to an interesting middlegame:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/jansen-chen-2013-02-05_files/diag3FA63606B7AA25D9.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Dutch after h6&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Instead, Peter uncorked a series of remarkable disruptive sacrificial ideas!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, he did not retreat the Bishop, but instead played &lt;code&gt;Qb3&lt;/code&gt; exploiting the weakness of Black&amp;rsquo;s &lt;code&gt;e6&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;f7&lt;/code&gt; squares:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/jansen-chen-2013-02-05_files/diag3FA6361ECBBCF26C.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Qb3&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;White&amp;rsquo;s Bishop cannot be captured by Black. (See the annotations for details.) So I calmly developed with &lt;code&gt;Bg7&lt;/code&gt;. Then Peter went totally wild with &lt;code&gt;h5&lt;/code&gt;, which is not really sound, but is definitely &lt;em&gt;interesting&lt;/em&gt;. Not only did he leave the Bishop unprotected, but he was sacrificing the &lt;code&gt;h&lt;/code&gt; Pawn.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/jansen-chen-2013-02-05_files/diag3FA636625EE9729E.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;h5&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I calmly took the Pawn. He followed up with the wild &lt;code&gt;Nh4&lt;/code&gt; that continued to offer the Bishop as a sacrifice while attacking Black&amp;rsquo;s &lt;code&gt;g6&lt;/code&gt; Pawn:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/jansen-chen-2013-02-05_files/diag3FA6366A23529BD6.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I did not take, but defended &lt;code&gt;g6&lt;/code&gt; while also opening up a defense of the &lt;code&gt;e6&lt;/code&gt; square. He then continued by sacrificing his Knight on &lt;code&gt;g6&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/jansen-chen-2013-02-05_files/diag3FA6368FCF1D708B.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Nxg6&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This is not a true sacrifice, because he gets the Knight on &lt;code&gt;h5&lt;/code&gt; in return. But the Bishop on &lt;code&gt;g5&lt;/code&gt; is still being offered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that this whole series of blows by White was unsound, and could have been refuted calmly by &lt;code&gt;Kf8&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/jansen-chen-2013-02-05_files/diag3FA636A01EC713E7.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Kf8 refutes attack&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But I saw a related idea and did not play the correct refutation, so the game continued to be interesting rather than ending quickly. I played &lt;code&gt;d5&lt;/code&gt;, which has a similar idea but has the drawback of allowing a good tactical save by White.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/jansen-chen-2013-02-05_files/diag3FA63697F6F24239.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;d5&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;White could have used a tactic to win the Pawn on &lt;code&gt;d5&lt;/code&gt; while saving his Bishop from being trapped by attacking Black&amp;rsquo;s Knight on &lt;code&gt;g6&lt;/code&gt;. Oops! But neither Peter nor I saw this resource, and he did not play it.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/jansen-chen-2013-02-05_files/diag3FA636D4EFF89295.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Instead, he played a completely unsound sacrifice &lt;code&gt;e4&lt;/code&gt; that I could have punished by taking the Bishop on &lt;code&gt;g5&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/jansen-chen-2013-02-05_files/diag3FA636DCB461BBCD.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Black wins a piece for real&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But in a collective hallucination, neither of us saw that the Bishop was in danger, because for so many moves up till &lt;code&gt;d5&lt;/code&gt;, it was &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; in danger!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, I opted to take the Pawn on &lt;code&gt;e4&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-middlegame&#34;&gt;The middlegame&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So White&amp;rsquo;s opening attack finally came to an end, and we reached a middlegame in which Black has to get his King to safety but is one Pawn up. Objectively, the game is actually quite equal. I was happy to have reached this middlegame, after all the turmoil, not having seen the big refutations earlier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After some natural moves, after which both sides were castled Queen side, I expected some kind of struggle on the King side in which White had pressure against Black&amp;rsquo;s &lt;code&gt;h6&lt;/code&gt; Pawn and possibly could regain it at some point.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/jansen-chen-2013-02-05_files/diag3FA6371A10D3B49F.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Both castled&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Instead, Peter &lt;em&gt;blundered&lt;/em&gt; with another sacrifice, or &lt;em&gt;so I thought&lt;/em&gt;. It turns out from extensive computer analysis that the sacrifice was actually &lt;em&gt;sound&lt;/em&gt; and should have led to an equal position through some extremely fascinating play. Let me explain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Peter played &lt;code&gt;Nxe4&lt;/code&gt;, with the idea of regaining the piece after &lt;code&gt;Qf7&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/jansen-chen-2013-02-05_files/diag3FA6372171D13561.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Nxe4 sacrifice&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/jansen-chen-2013-02-05_files/diag3FA6372A607D57FB.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Qf7&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It turns out that White does &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; regain the piece, after Black defends (as I did) with &lt;code&gt;Qd6&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/jansen-chen-2013-02-05_files/diag3FA637315E0F3046.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It turns out that White has a miraculously deep move &lt;code&gt;Ra5&lt;/code&gt; that equalizes through threats on Black&amp;rsquo;s King!! But neither of us saw this.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/jansen-chen-2013-02-05_files/diag3FA6373985E401F4.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Ra5&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Instead, Peter blundered straight into having his Queen trapped:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/jansen-chen-2013-02-05_files/diag3FA6378607BCA4C0.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Queen trapped&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The game was effectively over at this point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-endgame&#34;&gt;The endgame&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, Peter kept playing, and we ended up going into an endgame that was clearly lost for him (being a piece down):&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/jansen-chen-2013-02-05_files/diag3FA6379E1BCF7153.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Lost endgame for White&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The rest of the game is only worth looking at for its efficient technique.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Peter finally resigned after losing more and more material:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/jansen-chen-2013-02-05_files/diag3FA6CCA14DB3192E.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;White resigned&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;lessons-learned-from-my-game&#34;&gt;Lessons learned from my game&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t take for granted that your opponent will play in exactly the same style you&amp;rsquo;ve seen for years.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t think I have ever &lt;em&gt;in my entire life&lt;/em&gt; played a game in which I have been offered so many sacrifices. It is important to keep one&amp;rsquo;s cool and try to figure out the truth of each one.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A sacrifice could be &lt;em&gt;sound&lt;/em&gt;, yet not work because it is not followed up properly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A sacrifice could be &lt;em&gt;unsound&lt;/em&gt;, yet work because the defender fails to respond correctly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It takes careful calculation to determine which sacrifices are sound and which are unsound, and we humans do not always see the full truth, but &lt;em&gt;computers&lt;/em&gt; do.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-next&#34;&gt;What next?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For round 5 next week, I have White against fellow Expert Richard Edahl. He is doing pretty well in the tournament, considering that, as he mentioned when he entered the tournament, he has not played in a single chess tournament in &lt;a href=&#34;http://main.uschess.org/msa/MbrDtlTnmtHst.php?10333784&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;over twenty years&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;! So I expect an interesting fight. I have no idea how idea how he plays, so this will be new and exciting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I give credit to Peter for completely surprising me by attacking and sacrificing aggressively for a win, totally contrary to how I&amp;rsquo;ve usually seen him play. The result was a fascinating game.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pittsburgh Chess Club Championship 2013, Round 3: attack, defense, and sacrifices</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/02/03/pittsburgh-chess-club-championship-2013-round-3-attack-defense-and-sacrifices/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Feb 2013 20:30:41 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/02/03/pittsburgh-chess-club-championship-2013-round-3-attack-defense-and-sacrifices/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/chen-ahlborg-2013-01-29_files/round-3.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;PCC Championship Round 3&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Round 3 of the annual &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburghcc.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Chess Club&lt;/a&gt; Championship had me playing another very long game, the last game to finish (which it did after four hours, when nobody else was around any more except the tournament director).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For once, I am actually fairly proud of my game, in which I pressed hard with an attack and won. I have submitted the score for consideration in the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/16/pittsburgh-chess-club-championship-2013-round-1-the-art-of-swindling/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Best Attack&amp;rdquo; special prize category for the tournament&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/chen-ahlborg-2013-01-29_files/final-position.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Our final position&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This week&amp;rsquo;s chess theme is &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sacrifice_(chess)&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;sacrifice&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in chess. The reason is that in my game, there were many possible points of sacrifice on my end (the attacker), but also, ironically, my opponent was the one who twice sacrificed material for a &lt;em&gt;defensive&lt;/em&gt; purpose. Although the sacrifices were not sound, they had some practical merit that I will discuss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-complete-annotated-game&#34;&gt;My complete annotated game&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At your convenience, you can &lt;a href=&#34;../../chess/chen-ahlborg-2013-01-29.htm&#34;&gt;enjoy playing over the game with my annotations, including diagrams&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;preparation&#34;&gt;Preparation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I knew ahead of time that my opponent was going to be John Ahlborg, whom I have played once before &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/19/round-3-of-pittsburgh-chess-club-tournament-another-approach-against-the-sicilian-squeezing-with-the-bind/&#34;&gt;in a game that I won&lt;/a&gt;, also as White.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So my &amp;ldquo;preparation&amp;rdquo; consisted of nothing other than deciding to play a different opening against him. I should note that I inherently enjoy exploring different ways of playing, so avoidance is not really the purpose, but is actually my &lt;em&gt;excuse&lt;/em&gt; to play differently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;overview-of-my-game&#34;&gt;Overview of my game&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-opening&#34;&gt;The opening&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;John reacted to my English Opening surprise in an unexpectedly passive if solid way, allowing me permanent pressure against his &lt;code&gt;d&lt;/code&gt; Pawn:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/chen-ahlborg-2013-01-29_files/diag3FA43B22549ECDAE.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Black d Pawn weak&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We both played a bit stereotypically in the opening, missing chances for an aggressive advantage or counterplay, but instead reached a completely thematic position:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/chen-ahlborg-2013-01-29_files/diag3FA43B3240DCC894.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Thematic position&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Black has a passive but actually very solid position. The only way White can possibly make progress is reorganize and find a way to launch a King side attack with &lt;code&gt;f4&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;g4&lt;/code&gt; eventually, while Black should obtain counterplay on the Queen side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-middlegame&#34;&gt;The middlegame&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, my opponent faltered by not playing on the Queen side but instead trying to get counterplay by redeploying the King Knight to &lt;code&gt;e5&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/chen-ahlborg-2013-01-29_files/diag3FA43B50283E7411.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Knight maneuver to g4&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I correctly punished this error by bringing my Knight to &lt;code&gt;h4&lt;/code&gt; aiming to go to &lt;code&gt;f5&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We reached a position that is beautiful for White:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/chen-ahlborg-2013-01-29_files/diag3FA43B72B8AC0516.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;White not only has the two Bishops, but also has the &lt;code&gt;f5&lt;/code&gt; Pawn controlling &lt;code&gt;e5&lt;/code&gt; as well as ready to participate in a Pawn storm involving &lt;code&gt;g4&lt;/code&gt; and then either &lt;code&gt;f6&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;g6&lt;/code&gt;. Black&amp;rsquo;s two Knights optically look active but have no real threats at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-first-sacrifice-was-for-counterplay&#34;&gt;The first sacrifice was for counterplay&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, my opponent decided to engage in an unsound sacrifice but one he felt could give him activity and open lines, playing &lt;code&gt;b5&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, after I took the Pawn and returned my Knight to &lt;code&gt;c3&lt;/code&gt;, it became clear that the only open lines were for my Bishop pair, and Black is objectively lost.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/chen-ahlborg-2013-01-29_files/diag3FA43B979D9F88DF.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The only question was, how to conduct the winning attack on Black&amp;rsquo;s King?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got in &lt;code&gt;g4&lt;/code&gt;, and then hesitated to play &lt;code&gt;g5&lt;/code&gt; immediately. I decided to &amp;ldquo;prepare&amp;rdquo; for the inevitable attack more slowly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;potential-attacking-sacrifices&#34;&gt;Potential attacking sacrifices&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out from computer analysis that the quickest wins involve immediately pushing forth with &lt;code&gt;g5&lt;/code&gt; and having ideas of throwing everything at Black&amp;rsquo;s King, possibly sacrificing a Knight or Bishop here or there in order to tighten the net around the King while swinging the Queen and Rook over to the &lt;code&gt;h&lt;/code&gt; file. See the &lt;a href=&#34;../../chess/chen-ahlborg-2013-01-29.htm&#34;&gt;annotated game&lt;/a&gt; for some sample lines. Here is an example position involving a &lt;code&gt;g6&lt;/code&gt; sacrifice and a possible sacrifice on &lt;code&gt;d5&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/chen-ahlborg-2013-01-29_files/diag3FA43BC50DD386CB.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Possible sacrifice&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;critical-position&#34;&gt;Critical position&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The actual game continuation led to a critical position:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/chen-ahlborg-2013-01-29_files/diag3FA43BEB1D0A03F6.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Black&amp;#39;s King exposed&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;An opened up position like this tends to be critical because&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the attacker has made a commitment to the attack and therefore has made some concessions, possibly overreaching, possibly inadvertently freeing the defender by opening up lines&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the defender was formerly cramped but now has some space, ironically, and perhaps can use the space to bring in more defenses&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that while I did not continue most precisely, my opponent also did not choose the best defense, so we reached a position that is very bad for Black because a piece will soon be lost:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/chen-ahlborg-2013-01-29_files/diag3FA43C0522371AD8.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-second-defensive-sacrifice&#34;&gt;The second defensive sacrifice&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My opponent chose an interesting practical try, sacrificing the Knight for an attempt to block White&amp;rsquo;s dark Bishop and advance some Pawns and lock out White&amp;rsquo;s stray Knight:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/chen-ahlborg-2013-01-29_files/diag3FA43C112C408121.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Black&amp;#39;s sacrifice of a piece&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Objectively, White has a totally won game. But at this point, time was running low for both sides.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under time pressure, I missed a quick win at one point. I also somehow walked into a less and less winning position, eventually hanging an exchange inadvertently!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/chen-ahlborg-2013-01-29_files/diag3FA43C2A6A964717.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;White can lose an exchange&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But under worse time pressure, my opponent did not see the win of an exchange (after which White is luckily still winning because he was a piece up originally) and &lt;em&gt;completely collapsed&lt;/em&gt;, playing into this lost position:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/chen-ahlborg-2013-01-29_files/diag3FA43C36749FAD60.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Black is lost&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Checkmate followed:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/chen-ahlborg-2013-01-29_files/diag3FA43C4FB2F57356.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Checkmate&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;lessons-learned-from-my-game&#34;&gt;Lessons learned from my game&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Being passive right out of the opening can be very challenging for a human player because it requires playing very precisely in order to maintain the balance&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Defensive sacrifices may be unsound but may disrupt things sufficiently that your opponent could make an error (after the first one I did not but after the second one I did)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Time pressure, as usual, drastically lowers the quality of chess play&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-next&#34;&gt;What next?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For round 5, I will be Black against Peter Jansen, who ended up winning his &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/02/02/an-unexpected-afternoon-tour-9-miles-of-running/&#34;&gt;game against Kurt Wallnau on Saturday&lt;/a&gt;. I have played a tournament game with him only once before, six years ago, when I was White. I was not at all happy with how I played that game, even though I won (although on time in a drawn position), so I consider our game Tuesday to be my chance to finally actually play well against Peter. I have seen how he plays in the opening, so there&amp;rsquo;s not going to be an opening surprise coming from him, I think, as White. We will take the battle to the middlegame.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite some inaccuracies on my part, I played more consistently in this game than I have recently, so I felt fairly happy about this game. Of course, I had cooperation from my opponent.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>