<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>History on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/history/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in History on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/history/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>How learning about the Magna Carta in high school changed my life</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/06/13/how-learning-about-the-magna-carta-in-high-school-changed-my-life/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Jun 2015 15:35:30 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/06/13/how-learning-about-the-magna-carta-in-high-school-changed-my-life/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I couldn&amp;rsquo;t help noticing the headlines in the news lately about the
800th anniversary of the
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Magna_Carta&#34;&gt;Magna Carta&lt;/a&gt;, that
historical document from 1215 in England. As I write, apparently there
is a
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bbc.com/news/uk-england-33116579&#34;&gt;celebration being held on the River Thames&lt;/a&gt;,
even. And I just found a Web site devoted entirely to this
&lt;a href=&#34;http://magnacarta800th.com/&#34;&gt;800th anniversary&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Magna Carta has not been on my mind for over thirty years since I
first learned about it in a social studies class in the ninth grade high
school in the early 1980s. But when I think about it, the surprising
truth is that learning about the Magna Carta was a &lt;em&gt;turning point&lt;/em&gt; in
my life as a new teenager (age twelve or thirteen), and the lessons I
learned have informed me throughout my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-is-the-magna-carta-associated-with&#34;&gt;What is the Magna Carta associated with?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Magna Carta in popular imagination is associated with &amp;ldquo;liberty&amp;rdquo;,
with &amp;ldquo;the people&amp;rdquo; rising up in revolt against arbitrary monarchy and
making King John sign a document guaranteeing basic rights, such as
the right to a fair trail and no taxation without representation; and
&amp;ldquo;equality&amp;rdquo;, putting the king himself under the scope of law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Magna Carta is thought of as an inspiration for
subsequent milestones in history such as the United States Declaration
of Independence and the &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/constitution/&#34;&gt;Constitution&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-truth-as-i-learned-it&#34;&gt;The truth as I learned it&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I took a required &amp;ldquo;social studies&amp;rdquo; class in the ninth grade in high
school. It was one of the most interesting and life-changing classes I
ever took. I remember more from that class than probably any other in
all of high school. I loved the class because it was a small honors
class, didn&amp;rsquo;t follow a standard textbook, the teacher had us engage in
discussions, and we did many interesting activities such as watch
films and play games and do simulations. She used a kind of &amp;ldquo;Socratic
method&amp;rdquo; to direct us and get us thinking and offering our opinions
with reasons. &lt;em&gt;This was the one of the first (and few) times in school
in which I felt I was being treated as an independent adult-to-be, not
as a child.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is what I learned in ninth grade social studies class from the
coverage of the Magna Carta:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John,_King_of_England&#34;&gt;King John&lt;/a&gt; was
just one of a line of random kings in history who gained their power
from accident of birth rather than anything else.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Our teacher made fun of an artist&amp;rsquo;s fictional depiction of King
John&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;signing&amp;rdquo; the Magna Carta, arguing that since King John was
illiterate, he could not have signed it, and usual practice was to
press his seal on documents. (Amusingly, there is still
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bbc.com/news/blogs-magazine-monitor-30879124&#34;&gt;online discussion of this detail&lt;/a&gt;
decades after my class.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The whole Magna Carta thing came out of a civil war. It wasn&amp;rsquo;t like
one side was really right and the king was particularly evil as far
as kings went back in the day.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A bunch of &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Landed_gentry&#34;&gt;landed nobility&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Collusion&#34;&gt;colluded&lt;/a&gt; to protect their
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Collective_bargaining&#34;&gt;collective interests&lt;/a&gt;.
Basically, they tried to form the first &amp;ldquo;union&amp;rdquo; against royal
interests.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This document did not have anything to do with &amp;ldquo;the people&amp;rdquo; as such
(who in those days lived in abject misery whether under the nobility
or the king). The Magna Carta was not for the &amp;ldquo;little people&amp;rdquo;. Its
clauses were specific about whom they applied to, i.e., &amp;ldquo;free men&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Magna Carta was the product of a power struggle among those who
already had power. It was about power and money. A bunch of
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rent-seeking&#34;&gt;rent-seeking&lt;/a&gt; nobility
didn&amp;rsquo;t like that the king was arbitrarily cutting in on them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Magna Carta was originally a flop: civil war continued, King
John ignored its rules. But it proved useful later symbolically when
conditions changed, proved to be something to rally around and
reinterpret for a new age.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;no-untarnished-heroes&#34;&gt;No untarnished heroes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest question that arose in discussion was, should we be
cynical about the Magna Carta because of what it was originally for,
as opposed to what it later became to stand for or how it inspired
more far-reaching change? I think we can ask that of anything,
especially, for those of us in the United States, of our own
perception of our Founding Fathers and the nature of the American
Revolution, which all occurred five hundred years after the Magna
Carta.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I learned from the study of history (which I enjoyed so much I
took two non-required world history courses in the tenth grade before
the required American history sequence in the eleventh grade) that
there are no easy answers, and that it is important to be skeptical of
mythologizing the past. I have remembered these lessons long after not
thinking about the Magna Carta again after that class in the ninth
grade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The noblemen who came up with the Magna Carta may have been thinking
only of themselves, but might have unwittingly paved the way for
others. Intention is one thing, but the final result is another
thing. (And history shows that there never is a final result either.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;some-interesting-resources-on-the-magna-carta&#34;&gt;Some interesting resources on the Magna Carta&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a &lt;a href=&#34;http://the-orb.net/textbooks/muhlberger/magna_carta.html&#34;&gt;medieval studies textbook section on the Magna Carta&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did not touch upon the religion aspect of the power struggles in the
medieval era (such as King John&amp;rsquo;s fights with the Pope; three hundred
years after King John, the whole
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Church_of_England&#34;&gt;Church of England&lt;/a&gt;
finally split off from Catholicism when King Henry VIII wanted to
annul a marriage but the Pope wouldn&amp;rsquo;t let him), but here is a
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/09531a.htm&#34;&gt;Catholic encyclopedia article about the Magna Carta&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s an article about a Magna Carta skeptic, a British judge who
calls it an insignificant, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/uknews/law-and-order/11670716/Magna-Carta-Turgid-document-was-eclipsed-by-the-French-says-top-judge.html&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;turgid document&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can search online for a whole lot more commentary, given the
hugeness of this 800th anniversary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;here-s-that-fictional-depiction&#34;&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s that fictional depiction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:A_Chronicle_of_England_-_Page_226_-_John_Signs_the_Great_Charter.jpg#/media/File:A_Chronicle_of_England_-_Page_226_-_John_Signs_the_Great_Charter.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;A Chronicle of England - Page 226 - John Signs the Great Charter.jpg&#34; src=&#34;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/d/d6/A_Chronicle_of_England_-_Page_226_-_John_Signs_the_Great_Charter.jpg&#34; height=&#34;480&#34; width=&#34;598&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#34;&lt;a href=&#34;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:A_Chronicle_of_England_-_Page_226_-_John_Signs_the_Great_Charter.jpg#/media/File:A_Chronicle_of_England_-_Page_226_-_John_Signs_the_Great_Charter.jpg&#34;&gt;A Chronicle of England - Page 226 - John Signs the Great Charter&lt;/a&gt;&#34; by &lt;a href=&#34;//en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_William_Edmund_Doyle&#34; class=&#34;extiw&#34; title=&#34;en:James William Edmund Doyle&#34;&gt;James William Edmund Doyle&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;a href=&#34;//en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_William_Edmund_Doyle&#34; class=&#34;extiw&#34; title=&#34;w:James William Edmund Doyle&#34;&gt;Doyle, James William Edmund&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;span style=&#34;white-space:nowrap&#34;&gt;1864&lt;/span&gt;) &#34;&lt;a rel=&#34;nofollow&#34; class=&#34;external text&#34; href=&#34;http://books.google.com.sg/books?id=YcM_AAAAYAAJ&amp;amp;pg=PA226&#34;&gt;John&lt;/a&gt;&#34; in &lt;a rel=&#34;nofollow&#34; class=&#34;external text&#34; href=&#34;http://books.google.com.sg/books?id=YcM_AAAAYAAJ&#34;&gt;A Chronicle of England: B.C. 55 – A.D. 1485&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;//en.wikipedia.org/wiki/London&#34; class=&#34;extiw&#34; title=&#34;en:London&#34;&gt;London&lt;/a&gt;: Longman, Green, Longman, Roberts &amp;amp; Green, pp.&amp;nbsp;p. 226 Retrieved on &lt;span style=&#34;white-space:nowrap&#34;&gt;12 November 2010&lt;/span&gt;.. Licensed under Public Domain via &lt;a href=&#34;//commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/&#34;&gt;Wikimedia Commons&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;extrapolations&#34;&gt;Extrapolations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, all around us we see fights that are supposedly about principle
but are really power struggles. Instead of landed nobility, we have
powerful lobbying groups, multinational corporations, you name
it. When any of these interests collude to win a battle over some
other one, they might not be in the game for you and me, but for
themselves. The purported idea of &amp;ldquo;democracy&amp;rdquo; is in fact under siege
today on many fronts. In future blog posts, I will begin exploring
what some of these are; they mostly involve technology-based power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2015-06-14&#34;&gt;(Update of 2015-06-14)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the local paper, I just read this really interesting article by
University of Pittsburgh law professor Bernard Hibbits on the
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.post-gazette.com/news/world/2015/06/14/How-Magna-Carta-helped-make-America/stories/201506150001&#34;&gt;opportunistic use of the Magna Carta by Americans&lt;/a&gt; throughout history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2015-06-16&#34;&gt;(Update of 2015-06-16)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A random
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bbc.com/news/uk-33126723&#34;&gt;news article about the celebrations&lt;/a&gt;
feature nothing but photos or descriptions of an Archbishop, the
Queen, various Dukes, a Prince, a Princess, a Lord, a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.therichest.com/celebnetworth/politician/minister/david-cameron-net-worth/&#34;&gt;Prime Minister&lt;/a&gt;
who
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_Cameron#Inheritance_and_family_wealth&#34;&gt;inherited much wealth (a lot hidden in tax shelters)&lt;/a&gt;,
and had no photos of &amp;ldquo;regular people&amp;rdquo;, or quotes from them asking what
they thought of the lavish occasion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yeah, same old, same old, 800 years later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Learning about the Magna Carta as a twelve-year-old was an important
part of my growing up in life. I learned that people are human and
selfish and have different motivations, but sometimes can work toward
agreements at least among themselves as equals, and some other party
as well. But I also learned the lesson that there are always those
who are left out at the bargaining table, and that the nobility are
always looking out for themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When did you learn about the Magna Carta in school? Did you learn it
  in the same gritty way that I did, or in a more romanticized way?
  Are there things you learned in history classes in school that
  changed your life, changed what you believe and how you act (as a
  voter or activist)?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Yes, I want my writing to be dated!</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/05/31/yes-i-want-my-writing-to-be-dated/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 May 2015 22:55:05 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/05/31/yes-i-want-my-writing-to-be-dated/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I just finished
&lt;a href=&#34;http://conscientiousprogrammer.com/blog/2015/05/31/why-i-switched-from-octopress-2-to-hugo/&#34;&gt;migrating both this blog and my programming blog from Octopress 2 to Hugo&lt;/a&gt;. During
this process, I made sure to preserve my old URLs as well as Disqus,
because nothing is as distressing to me, as a reader, as moved or
broken links when I&amp;rsquo;m looking for old blog posts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, there&amp;rsquo;s always the possibility of changing the &amp;ldquo;real&amp;rdquo; URLs and
just using an alias with a URL redirect for the sake of old URL
schemes. One possibility was to remove dates from my URLs, e.g.,
change something like
&lt;code&gt;http://conscientiousprogrammer.com/blog/2015/05/31/why-i-switched-from-octopress-2-to-hugo/&lt;/code&gt;
to
&lt;code&gt;http://conscientiousprogrammer.com/blog/why-i-switched-from-octopress-2-to-hugo/&lt;/code&gt;. Matt
Gemmell, among many others, has argued for &lt;a href=&#34;http://mattgemmell.com/permalinks/&#34;&gt;permalinks that do not
include the clutter of embedded dates&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I made the decision years ago, when I had the choice, to keep
the embedded dates, and I still stand by my decision today. Here&amp;rsquo;s why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;are-embedded-dates-actually-bad-user-interface-design&#34;&gt;Are embedded dates actually bad user-interface design?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not sure long date-embedded permalinks are really so bad
visually:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nobody goes around having to manually type in these links anyway.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I believe that in the long run, people actually do care about the
date, and having it in the URL makes it that much easier to know the
date.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Redundancy can be a good thing, if it exposes useful information
that in theory one could determine more indirectly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-bigger-philosophical-issues&#34;&gt;The bigger philosophical issues&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the main reason I deliberately choose to expose the date of a
post is that I disagree with Matt Gemmell&amp;rsquo;s statement that one should
prefer to boost one&amp;rsquo;s article&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;standing&amp;rdquo; by giving the impression
that one is making a &amp;ldquo;definitive goddamned opinion&amp;rdquo; on a topic, some
kind of timeless statement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;relevance&#34;&gt;Relevance?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I understand that there are people who would be swayed by this
psychological trick, and I totally confess that sometimes when I do a
Web search and up pops a link to a four-year-old post, I wonder
whether to read something else instead that might be more &amp;ldquo;relevant&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But as a reader who seeks genuinely useful information, no matter how
recent or old, I overcome my initial twinge at encountering an &amp;ldquo;old&amp;rdquo;
article, and check it out for its own merits. And often, I find that
it is just fine. For example, there are some fantastic Haskell blogs
filled with information still useful today. For example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Any of Dan Piponi&amp;rsquo;s articles are great, e.g., a random 2009 article
on
&lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.sigfpe.com/2009/01/haskell-monoids-and-their-uses.html&#34;&gt;monoids and their uses&lt;/a&gt;,
with an ungainly URL of
&lt;code&gt;http://blog.sigfpe.com/2009/01/haskell-monoids-and-their-uses.html&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Any of Gabriel Gonzalez&amp;rsquo;s articles are great, e.g., a 2012 article
on
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.haskellforall.com/2012/06/you-could-have-invented-free-monads.html&#34;&gt;free monads&lt;/a&gt;
with the URL
&lt;code&gt;http://www.haskellforall.com/2012/06/you-could-have-invented-free-monads.html&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, the dating is actually useful because once you see
another article by the same author with a different date, you know
which one came first and can retrace the &lt;em&gt;history&lt;/em&gt; of the author&amp;rsquo;s
thinking just throw the URL. In fact, I track my own history through
the fact that on my file system, my posts are in alphabetical order
according to date.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-reality-and-humanity-of-transience&#34;&gt;The reality and humanity of transience&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, the main fact I want to emphasize when I write is precisely
that I am not giving my definitive opinion about anything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I have no &amp;ldquo;forever&amp;rdquo; opinions about any topic!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I change my mind as I continue to grow and learn, and I want my
writing to reflect that, and in a way such that a reader can easily
track what changed and when. I do not write to give an illusion that I
am writing eternal truths. I do not write in order to be an authority
on a topic, but to share a snapshot of what I understand at a
particular moment in my life. When I change my mind, I do often go
back and add a dated update section linking to a new article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have retained dated permalinks for my migrated blogs, despite some
voices that argue otherwise, because of the extra information they
provide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Do you agree that dated permalinks are worth the ugliness or not? Is
  this your opinion as an author, a reader, a critic, or a search
  engine user?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hiroo Onoda and the Six Million Dollar man: what does it mean to know how to die or live?</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/01/17/hiroo-onoda-and-the-six-million-dollar-man/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2014 22:50:24 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/01/17/hiroo-onoda-and-the-six-million-dollar-man/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A news article just came my way that fascinated me: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.washingtonpost.com/world/asia_pacific/hiroo-onoda-japanese-soldier-who-hid-in-philippine-jungle-for-29-years-dies-at-91/2014/01/17/7016d806-7f8b-11e3-93c1-0e888170b723_story.html&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Hiroo Onoda, Japanese soldier who hid in Philippine jungle for 29 years, dies at 91&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, I had long heard of &amp;ldquo;stragglers&amp;rdquo; who did not realize that a war or persecution was over and kept fighting or fleeing, away from &amp;ldquo;civilization&amp;rdquo;, unaware of how the rest of the world was changing. The most recent case of that I read about was a really moving story, astonishing and sad, about an Old Believer &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.smithsonianmag.com/history/for-40-years-this-russian-family-was-cut-off-from-all-human-contact-unaware-of-world-war-ii-7354256/&#34;&gt;Russian family that hid out for forty years&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in the case of this Japanese soldier, although I had not earlier read about his particular story, I instantly remembered an old TV episode I watched as a young child that was an astoundingly memorable episode, whose details are etched in my mind. This was &lt;a href=&#34;http://bionic.wikia.com/wiki/The_Last_Kamikaze&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Last Kamikaze&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, an episode of &amp;ldquo;The Six Million Dollar Man&amp;rdquo; TV series that I watched religiously back in the day. This episode was about a Japanese straggler from World War II. &lt;strong&gt;It changed my life forever.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-last-kamikaze&#34;&gt;The Last Kamikaze&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amazingly, I found the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dailymotion.com/video/xtp86d_the-six-million-dollar-man-the-last-kamikaze-jan-19-1975_shortfilms&#34;&gt;whole episode online&lt;/a&gt;. You may want to watch this episode before reading my spoilers below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe frameborder=&#34;0&#34; width=&#34;480&#34; height=&#34;270&#34; src=&#34;http://www.dailymotion.com/embed/video/xtp86d&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dailymotion.com/video/xtp86d_the-six-million-dollar-man-the-last-kamikaze-jan-19-1975_shortfilms&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;The Six Million Dollar Man&amp;ndash;The Last Kamikaze&amp;hellip;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;i&gt;by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dailymotion.com/dwyerjoss&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;dwyerjoss&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;discussion-with-spoilers&#34;&gt;Discussion, with spoilers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It made a profound impact on me when I watched it over 30 years ago. First, there was the exciting action aspect, of course (all the booby traps in the jungle). But mostly, it was in some sense my first exposure to something from Japanese culture, in particular regarding notions of &amp;ldquo;honor&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OK, it was just TV, and American 1970s TV at a time when there weren&amp;rsquo;t a lot of Asians even being portrayed at all, but in retrospect, it wasn&amp;rsquo;t bad at all. I was confused by the attempted &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Seppuku&#34;&gt;seppuku&lt;/a&gt;, and my parents had to explain what that was about (not being Japanese, but actually living during World War II in Taiwan under Japanese rule and remembering the Allies defeating Japan).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;death-and-life&#34;&gt;Death and life&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the real climax of the episode was when Steve Austin intervenes in the attempt and saves the character Kuroda, saying &amp;ldquo;You have shown that you know how to die. Now for the sake of your enemies, show me that you know how to live.&amp;rdquo; I reflected on what it might mean to &amp;ldquo;know how to die&amp;rdquo; or to &amp;ldquo;know how to live&amp;rdquo;. In that moment of the TV episode, &lt;em&gt;my life was changed forever&lt;/em&gt;. I was around seven years old at the time. I suppose you could say I lost my &amp;ldquo;innocence&amp;rdquo; at that exact moment in time; I became a philosopher then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought a lot about life and death after that episode. What is the meaning of life, or of death? And most of all, what do we choose, and why do we choose? What is honor?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My questioning may have begun at seven, but it has not yet ended. I do not have the final answer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that one TV episode got me started on a lifelong philosophical journey. When I was older, I studied the Christian Bible, which is all about exploring what it means to live and die: Jesus dying and living again, and the command to be &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=Romans%206&#34;&gt;dead to sin but alive in Christ&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, there is also the controversial choice of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Socrates&#34;&gt;Socrates&lt;/a&gt; to commit suicide, which I read various conflicting opinions about: when I had just finished high school, the book &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ifstone.org/trial_of_socrates.php&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Trial of Socrates&amp;rdquo; by I.F. Stone came out&lt;/a&gt; that was very provocative and turned me against Socrates, whom I had earlier considered a hero, from reading Plato&amp;rsquo;s dialogues about him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was also bothered but fascinated by the lore that &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gautama_Buddha&#34;&gt;Gautama Buddha&lt;/a&gt; deliberately ate rotting food in order not to offend his host, and died as a result.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And what of the controversial mass suicide by Jews at &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Masada&#34;&gt;Masada&lt;/a&gt;? Or that of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Self-immolation&#34;&gt;self-immolating&lt;/a&gt; Buddhist monks in Vietnam?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In college, I took a philosophy course by &lt;a href=&#34;http://philosophy.columbia.edu/directories/faculty/frederick-neuhouser&#34;&gt;Frederick Neuhouser&lt;/a&gt; and studied Nietzsche, who had his character Zarathustra say, &lt;a href=&#34;http://4umi.com/nietzsche/zarathustra/21&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Die at the right time&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. I was profoundly affected by the challenges that Nietzsche threw at his readers. That course changed my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Very recently, Stoicism has become popularized as a living philosophy for today, with proponents such as &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ttbook.org/book/transcript/transcript-william-irvine-stoic-life&#34;&gt;William Irvine&lt;/a&gt;, who talks about &amp;ldquo;contemplation of death&amp;rdquo;. I very much enjoyed his book &lt;a href=&#34;http://global.oup.com/academic/product/a-guide-to-the-good-life-9780195374612&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;A Guide to the Good Life: the Ancient Art of Stoic Joy&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; not long after it came out; reading it in early 2011, I changed the course of my life. (Don&amp;rsquo;t forget that &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Seneca_the_Younger&#34;&gt;Seneca&lt;/a&gt; was also forced to commit suicide.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am fascinated by deliberate, reasoned decisions about life and death.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>