<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Marriage on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/marriage/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Marriage on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/marriage/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>The hug system of habit breaking and forming</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/01/08/the-hug-system-of-habit-breaking-and-forming/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jan 2013 12:25:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/01/08/the-hug-system-of-habit-breaking-and-forming/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I came up with a very useful way of dealing with a type of conflict in marriage that seems pretty common: that of one person being annoyed by the other&amp;rsquo;s bad habit, and repeatedly, because the other person after being criticized promises to change but doesn&amp;rsquo;t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason for the failure to change is not necessarily malice, of course. Just taking myself as an example, I reflected on which changes I have made during marriage and which I have not, and tried to understand why I might &amp;ldquo;forget&amp;rdquo; one thing and not another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that the answer was usually surprisingly simple, and must reflect on human nature in general. When there is something annoying I do and Abby just goes relentlessly negative on me, I am &lt;em&gt;less&lt;/em&gt; likely to actually correct my behavior, even if I grudgingly acknowledge that I should change it. But if she told me in a loving way, I was more likely to catch myself in the future in the relevant situation, and either do what she wanted or not do what she did not want me to do!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All I have said here also applies to the exact opposite situation when Abby annoys me and I harp on her. The more vocal I am, the more insistent, the less effective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In retrospect, this was just as true when I was a child also. I suppose we all still have a little child inside of us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;one-part-of-the-solution&#34;&gt;One part of the solution&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no silver bullet for &amp;ldquo;making people change&amp;rdquo;, but the thing is to have them want to change and make it easy, rather than demand it. We are human, not robots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that when I get a hug, at the same time as when being told gently of something that I should do, I am more likely to remember the task, and associate it with something positive, and actually do it. It seems that when I am yelled at, the effect is to actually associate the task with a negative memory and block it out of my consciousness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, you could say, this is crazy childish behavior, that &amp;ldquo;adults&amp;rdquo; should just take responsibility and do the right thing. That&amp;rsquo;s why Abby used to say and I used to say. It leads to an escalating arms race of &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m better than you&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &amp;ldquo;hug system&amp;rdquo; seems to work a lot better for us, we found out to our surprise. If it works with human nature and the other way doesn&amp;rsquo;t, then theories about how we &amp;ldquo;should&amp;rdquo; know how to behave kind of don&amp;rsquo;t matter. Results matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wish I had known about this earlier. Unfortunately, the authoritarian way in which I was raised led me to internalize the psychologically dubious assumption that &lt;em&gt;tone doesn&amp;rsquo;t matter; reasoning and truth and right matter, and it is the purely the job of the offender to do all the work&lt;/em&gt;. I now totally disagree with that. &lt;em&gt;Tone matters, whether or not you believe it should.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The toilet seats are always down now at home, as well as a large number of other little things I now remember to do that I mysteriously did not before. Maybe in theory I should have been able to get this all working no matter whether I was getting yelled at or not. Maybe I&amp;rsquo;m a weak, irrational husband, a sad excuse of a human being. Or maybe imperfection only needs a little bit of help to do a lot better.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Meditations on climbing the 36 floors of the Pitt Cathedral of Learning</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/12/28/meditations-on-climbing-the-36-floors-of-the-pitt-cathedral-of-learning/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Dec 2012 18:39:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/12/28/meditations-on-climbing-the-36-floors-of-the-pitt-cathedral-of-learning/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/cathedral-of-learning-steps/cathedral.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Cathedral of Learning&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Tonight I climbed the steps of the 36 accessible floors of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cathedral_of_Learning&#34;&gt;University of Pittsburgh Cathedral of Learning&lt;/a&gt; for the first time in probably a couple of years. As I mentioned after my last big stair climb, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/10/06/the-fineview-stepathon-2012-pittsburghs-grueling-urban-trail-race/&#34;&gt;this year&amp;rsquo;s Fineview Stepathon&lt;/a&gt;, I used to do some training here, when preparing for the tortuous annual 35-mile &lt;a href=&#34;http://rachelcarsontrails.org/rct/challenge&#34;&gt;Rachel Carson Trail Challenge&lt;/a&gt; held in June, which I did in 2005, 2006, and 2007.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/6/6b/Cathedral_of_Learning_stitch_1.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Wikipedia photo&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I thought a lot about how my physical fitness took a sharp turn downward in the past five years, and how for the coming new year of 2013 I plan to get back into the shape I was in five years ago, and why that is important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m going to frame my discussion in terms that are used in &lt;a href=&#34;http://charlesduhigg.com/&#34;&gt;Charles Duhigg&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s fantastic book I just read, &lt;a href=&#34;http://charlesduhigg.com/the-power-of-habit/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Power of Habit&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; (which everyone should read).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;walking-to-the-cathedral-of-learning&#34;&gt;Walking to the Cathedral of Learning&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I took a short walk from my office at CMU to the Cathedral of Learning. There was a bit of snow and ice on the roads and sidewalks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought about how until the snow fell this week, it was still possible to go &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/12/i-love-trail-running-in-frick-park/&#34;&gt;running in the trails of Frick Park&lt;/a&gt;, one of my favorite things to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Except that I basically &lt;em&gt;haven&amp;rsquo;t been running&lt;/em&gt; for two months now. I got &amp;ldquo;busy&amp;rdquo;, it got &amp;ldquo;cold&amp;rdquo;, and I more or less stopped exercising at all. One thing I learned when &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/23/happiness-is-finishing-39th-of-43-men-in-a-race/&#34;&gt;over a decade ago I started running&lt;/a&gt; and really did acquire a regular daily exercise schedule, is that the benefits of exercise are tremendous, and carry over into all aspects of life, from building endurance to attaining mental balance and sharpness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, my exercise schedule has more or less fallen apart in the last five years, with some seasonal variation in that in the summer, it&amp;rsquo;s much easier to just go outside and run or hike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;beginning-the-climb&#34;&gt;Beginning the climb&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the ground floor of the Cathedral of Learning, with stairway entrance in sight:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/cathedral-of-learning-steps/floor-g.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Floor G&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;habits-and-social-support&#34;&gt;Habits and social support&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A regular exercise &lt;em&gt;habit&lt;/em&gt; starts somewhere. Some kind of decision, some kind of cue. It&amp;rsquo;s important to get started, and conquer anxiety and excuses. Given that I hadn&amp;rsquo;t done this stair climb in years, I didn&amp;rsquo;t really know how I would fare going up. I saw no reason to believe that I couldn&amp;rsquo;t make it all the way up just once, but I didn&amp;rsquo;t want to run out of steam. I wanted to be steady and strong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s important not to try to do too much all at once.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, &lt;em&gt;social support&lt;/em&gt; is really quite important. It turns out that in the past, I had friends who were totally into serious running and hiking and the like. One by one they moved away, and furthermore after I met Abby, my entire life routine changed. To be clear, I&amp;rsquo;m not &amp;ldquo;blaming&amp;rdquo; her presence in my life for my broken exercise routine; I take full responsibility for not adapting fully to circumstances. Nobody said the transition from bachelorhood to marriage was easy. It turns out that Abby is not at all interested in extreme endurance events such as marathons or the Rachel Carson Trail Challenge, and helped dissuade me from participating further in such events; but I made the decision with her, of my own free will, feeling that the time and energy spent toward such pursuits would be better spent on other activities instead, now that she was in my life. Every couple has to negotiate these kinds of life changes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, what happened to me was that I didn&amp;rsquo;t fully realize how interconnected all of my exercise-related activities were, such that removing an admittedly unnecessary and extreme part of it had an indirect effect on my motivation and routine for less extreme activities. The goal of participating in the events had somehow become a major motivator in doing things that didn&amp;rsquo;t necessarily have to require participating in those events. Basically, I had inadvertently created for myself a &lt;em&gt;reward&lt;/em&gt; that I depended on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, my &lt;em&gt;cue&lt;/em&gt; was broken. My cue used to be to wake up, hop out of bed, and prepare to run or lift weights or something. But I have not been doing that since Abby came into the picture, for various reasons, some of which are no longer even relevant, but the cue was destroyed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This indirect effect, combined with the addition of a lot more into my life that had formerly not existed (not just time spent with Abby, but also more recent new activities involving taking up &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/11/17/a-childhood-dream-come-true-i-am-now-finally-singing-for-real/&#34;&gt;playing music&lt;/a&gt; and getting into &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/06/my-pittsburgh-ruby-talk-nil/&#34;&gt;personal computer programming projects and social meetups&lt;/a&gt;), served to completely disrupt all of my usual routines, not just the exercise one. Even if I had time and energy to exercise, often I&amp;rsquo;d find some other thing I &amp;ldquo;had&amp;rdquo; to do instead, like practice music or going to a computer programming meetup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;going-up&#34;&gt;Going up&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/cathedral-of-learning-steps/warning.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Warning sign&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The famous warning sign about the stairwell not being meant for &amp;ldquo;exercise or other athletic activity&amp;rdquo; certainly did not deter people like Danny Chew, who did &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dannychew.com/101timesupCoL.html&#34;&gt;101 repetitions in over 17 hours&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;ve never done more than a single repetition.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/cathedral-of-learning-steps/stairway.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Stairway&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-rhythm-established&#34;&gt;A rhythm established&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make something a habit, it must be regular and sustainable, in order to build confidence and strength. So I established a simple rhythm going up the steps just one at a time (not two at a time as I used to when I was more fit). One step at a time is much, much easier than two steps at a time. I only did two for the challenge of going fast. Speed is of no concern to me right now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a clip of my going between floors 17 and 21. Some guy wearing a CamelBak actually passed me while he was going down; you can hear him but can&amp;rsquo;t see him in the video:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34;
src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/CDJDZcixA2A&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used to exercise every morning before eating breakfast. But for the first couple of years with Abby, that routine was broken, because she had no such routine. A lot of the radical changes in one&amp;rsquo;s life when no longer being alone are, I think, a result of individual differences. If X used to do something, but Y did not, then by default it is easy to slip into a joint routine in which neither do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ironically, relatively recently, Abby did take up semi-regular exercise before breakfast, going out for a walk, in an attempt to encourage me to do likewise with her. But I&amp;rsquo;m not interested in going for a leisurely walk before breakfast. I want to do something strenuous and then get going with my day. Meanwhile, I had fallen into a pattern of sleeping later and later, which was the real problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two days ago, I resolved on a major life change. I&amp;rsquo;m going to become a genuine morning person. I woke up spontaneously before 5 AM yesterday, and also today. I have not been ready to launch into a super-early morning exercise program yet, and it is a good idea to change &lt;em&gt;one habit at a time&lt;/em&gt; rather than multiple, so I am focusing right now simply on sleeping earlier and waking earlier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;just-a-few-more-floors-left&#34;&gt;Just a few more floors left&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was pleased that at the rhythm and pace I had chosen, I was going up pretty well, without running out of breath or having to use the handrails for support. I suspect that a couple of things I&amp;rsquo;ve done in the past couple of years have helped a lot. I know I&amp;rsquo;ve improved my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/17/the-joys-of-convict-conditioning-bodyweight-exercising/&#34;&gt;core strength&lt;/a&gt; through doing bodyweight exercises such as pushups, pullups, squats, and lunges. As a result, despite my overall being less fit than years ago, I have better balance and stability, enabling me to activate my glutes rather than lean on my quads when climbing stairs.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/cathedral-of-learning-steps/floor-31.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Floor 31&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Right after the 31st floor, I was amused to see some posters people had put up for the annual &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lung.org/pledge-events/pa/pittsburgh-climb-fy13/&#34;&gt;Fight for Air Climb&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;ve never done this event, actually. I have to confess that an indoor stair climb is not the most exciting thing in the world for me, and I do the Cathedral of Learning climb mainly when the weather outside is not as good as I like.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/cathedral-of-learning-steps/fight-for-air-climb.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Posters for Fight for Air Climb&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-top&#34;&gt;The top&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 36th floor is the last one accessible. There are a couple more going up, but the door after the 36th floor is locked.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/cathedral-of-learning-steps/floor-36.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Floor 36&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Some night views out the windows on the 36th floor:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/cathedral-of-learning-steps/night-view.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Night view&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/cathedral-of-learning-steps/night-view-2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Another night view&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I arrived at the 36th floor without any distress. It felt &amp;ldquo;easy&amp;rdquo;, even, but then again, I was going slowly and one step at a time. Nevertheless, this gives me confidence. I will continue to do the stair climb this winter. Also, perhaps next time I will do two repetitions, which I&amp;rsquo;ve never done before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed getting back to exercising and doing the Cathedral of Learning stair climb. I used the time to also reflect on my shortcomings in recent years in sticking to an exercise plan, and to commit to my vision of becoming more fit in 2013 than I was in 2007, one step at a time. And finally, I am taking full responsibility for my slacking: the fact that it happened as a result of taking a new direction in life with Abby is not at all her fault, especially given that she has been trying to get me to start exercising regularly again!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Enjoying more French dancing in Pittsburgh</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/02/20/enjoying-more-french-dancing-in-pittsburgh/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Feb 2012 01:03:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/02/20/enjoying-more-french-dancing-in-pittsburgh/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A month ago I reported on how Abby and I had our &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/01/23/discovering-french-traditional-dance-in-pittsburgh&#34;&gt;first experience of French traditional dance&lt;/a&gt;. On Saturday, we went again to Skibo Gym at Carnegie Mellon University for another fun session of French dancing from 4:00 to 7:00 PM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had a great time again, and afterwards joined the instructors and some other people in having dinner at &lt;a href=&#34;http://gulliftys.us/&#34;&gt;Gullifty&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;attendance&#34;&gt;Attendance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to some familiar faces, there were many new people we hadn&amp;rsquo;t met before, and I got my office mate John to go too. Abby and I learned some dances that were not taught the last time, and we got to do more of the dances we had learned the last time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The male-female ratio was not so great this time: it would be nice to have more men attend these workshops and dances! If you are male and interested in learning French dance, come next month!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;3-count-bourrée&#34;&gt;3-count bourrée&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last month, we had learned the 2-count bourrée, but this month we also added the 3-count. That&amp;rsquo;s really fast and was a real workout!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;dances-from-last-time&#34;&gt;Dances from last time&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We went over the dances from last time also. Since they were no longer new to me, I felt freer to feel the music more and make the most of enjoying the dances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, in a very simple circle dance, I felt like lifting my body up when we swung our arms upward, and letting my body bend naturally to the &amp;ldquo;1-2-3, down&amp;rdquo; movement. Otherwise, just stepping endlessly like a rigid robot was getting quite boring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last time, I was rather stiff and clumsy at the Schottische, waltz, and mazurka, because I was out of practice in these turning dances. This time I got more into the swing of things and remembered the fun I had doing ballroom dancing over ten years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were two other circle dances from last time that we did again. I really enjoy these partner switching dances. Again, since I knew the moves already, I felt freer to improve my technique and personal expression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;social-dancing&#34;&gt;Social dancing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A familiar musician, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/16/playing-recorder-and-flute-at-the-holiday-ball/&#34;&gt;Donna Isaac&lt;/a&gt;, played fiddle for us, with Gregory on his Irish flute again. I liked the different texture from last month&amp;rsquo;s piano and flute, but I have to confess that missing a bass line made the music harder to dance to. In fact, I ended up starting to hum my own bass line to fill in the harmonies to feel less of a musical omission and help my rhythm while dancing!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again I thank everyone who was at the workshop and dance. It was a great group. I am so happy to be dancing again. I had put it aside for a couple of years after Abby and I got married, but now I envision our making it a regular part of our lives again!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Sorry, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/02/19/why-i-have-not-posted-many-photos-or-videos-recently-exploitation/&#34;&gt;I took no photos or videos this time&lt;/a&gt;. I spent the whole time immersed in dancing!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;dinner-at-gullifty-s&#34;&gt;Dinner at Gullifty&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since people were talking about going to dinner afterwards, and this time Abby and I did not leave the dance early before it ended, we ended up joining six others for dinner. We helped pack stuff up and drove home and walked to Gullifty&amp;rsquo;s. I hadn&amp;rsquo;t been there in at least ten years. It&amp;rsquo;s not my favorite idea of food, but I made the most of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ordered a &amp;ldquo;pierogie burger&amp;rdquo; for dinner. Only in Pittsburgh, ha! It was actually pretty good. It was a burger that had pierogies on top, all encased in a bun. It came with a pickle and fries. Not the kind of food I usually eat, but &amp;ldquo;cheating&amp;rdquo; once in a while is fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, we &amp;ldquo;had&amp;rdquo; to have dessert. Gullifty&amp;rsquo;s is &amp;ldquo;famous&amp;rdquo; for desserts. Abby and I had reservations about continuing our &amp;ldquo;cheating&amp;rdquo; to desserts, but what the heck, we shared a triple chocolate cake. Unfortunately, we got a huge chunk of cake, as the waitress explained that it was the end of the cake so we got probably twice as much as we would ordinarily have received. We ate the whole thing, but I ended up feeling quite sugared out and bloated. That&amp;rsquo;s the punishment for &amp;ldquo;cheating&amp;rdquo; way too much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;blues-and-other-dancing&#34;&gt;Blues and other dancing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People at dinner were talking about needing to take a nap afterwards and then going to a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pittsburghdancecenter.com/&#34;&gt;blues dance&lt;/a&gt; at midnight. That&amp;rsquo;s very late for Abby and me to be dancing! We&amp;rsquo;ve never done blues dancing before but are interested in trying it out sometime (but not if it&amp;rsquo;s too late at night).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dinner gang was also into Lindy hop. I did a little bit of Lindy and swing a decade ago, but never got much into it. Maybe Abby and I should check that out too. I know there&amp;rsquo;s a lot of it here in Pittsburgh. In the past, I&amp;rsquo;ve gone to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.swingpgh.com&#34;&gt;Swing City&lt;/a&gt;. There&amp;rsquo;s the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.coalcountry.org/swingdances.html&#34;&gt;Edgewood Club&lt;/a&gt; also.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m kind of interested in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.chickenswing.com/&#34;&gt;Chicken Swing&lt;/a&gt; because it meets right at Carnegie Mellon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there&amp;rsquo;s West Coast swing in town too, at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pghwcs.com/&#34;&gt;Absolute Ballroom&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a lot of fun dancing with Abby more again, and also with other people, and hanging out at dinner. I am not a dance maniac any more, and time is limited, but I am excited about continuing with Abby to further explore dances we haven&amp;rsquo;t done much of before. It&amp;rsquo;s great exercise and great socializing!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2012-05-14&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-05-14)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three months later, I ended up beginning to &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/05/14/playing-french-music-for-first-time-and-dancing-blues-for-first-time/&#34;&gt;play French music on flutes&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>