<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Goldberg Variations on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/goldberg-variations/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Goldberg Variations on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/goldberg-variations/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>The single greatest performance of Bach&#39;s Goldberg Variations: Pierre Hantaï with rhythmic drive and life</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/05/the-single-greatest-performance-of-bachs-goldberg-variations-pierre-hantai/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2014 22:32:07 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/05/the-single-greatest-performance-of-bachs-goldberg-variations-pierre-hantai/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been listening to JS Bach&amp;rsquo;s Goldberg Variations for a quarter of a century now. I haven&amp;rsquo;t actually said much about this piece on this blog, although I did mention attending a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/11/19/chamber-music-concert-at-cmu-featured-bachs-goldberg-variations-arranged-for-string-trio/&#34;&gt;concert featuring a string trio arrangement of it a year ago&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a favorite recording, out of probably a dozen recordings I have heard since a college friend introduced me to the piece performed by Glenn Gould on piano . Several years ago I discovered my true favorite, upon encountering &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pierre_Hanta%C3%AF&#34;&gt;Pierre Hantaï&lt;/a&gt; on harpsichord in a CD recording.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-hantaï-stands-out-for-me&#34;&gt;Why Hantaï stands out for me&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given that there are plenty of other performances that I consider worthy, why is Hantaï&amp;rsquo;s by far my favorite?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;sustained intensity (many performances have me getting bored and sleepy)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;rhythmic&lt;/em&gt; drive is always there; the music never droops&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;subtlety and shape to all phrasing and contrast&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;no distractions of self-absorption (many performances have certain kinds of oddities that are magnified when spread out over an hour or more)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;nice harpsichord sound&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: I once didn&amp;rsquo;t like harpsichord, and always preferred a piano when possible, but now I actually prefer Bach&amp;rsquo;s music on harpsichord, because of the nature of articulation and decay and how dissonances are more delicious on this instrument.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a treat I just found by accident: a video of Hantaï performing the Goldberg Variations. Watch it if you care about the Goldberg Variations at all!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/9NYqiKm3gng&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you are already a fan of the Goldberg Variations, what is your favorite performance, and why? Also, does it matter to you whether piano or harpsichord is used?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Discovering the beautiful keyboard playing of Robert Hill by accident on YouTube changed my life</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/08/21/discovering-the-beautiful-keyboard-playing-of-robert-hill-by-accident-on-youtube-changed-my-life/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2014 22:14:23 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/08/21/discovering-the-beautiful-keyboard-playing-of-robert-hill-by-accident-on-youtube-changed-my-life/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.mh-freiburg.de/typo3temp/_processed_/csm_prof.-dr.-robert-hill_c7981b16bc.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Robert Hill&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Recently, I completely accidentally discovered a fascinating musician, &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Hill_%28musician%29&#34;&gt;Robert Hill&lt;/a&gt;, on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/user/earlymus&#34;&gt;YouTube&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story is as you might expect: I heard a piece of music, and wanted to find some performance of it by somebody, anybody on YouTube as long as it had a decent user rating (yes, I find ratings actually useful when checking out unfamiliar music), and I happened to come across some random guy&amp;rsquo;s performance, and it was so fascinating that I looked at other uploads of his, subscribed to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/user/earlymus&#34;&gt;his YouTube channel&lt;/a&gt;, and looked him up on the Web to find out who he was!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s especially great that he regularly uploads new videos to his YouTube channel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So who is Robert Hill, and why do I like his performances so much that I&amp;rsquo;m recommending that you check them out?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-i-found-robert-hill&#34;&gt;How I found Robert Hill&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The short story is that I just heard someone playing, on piano, Johann Sebastian Bach&amp;rsquo;s Allemande from the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/French_Suites_%28Bach%29&#34;&gt;French Suite&lt;/a&gt; no. 4 in E-flat, BWV 815.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note that I actually have had very little interest in much of Bach&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Works_for_keyboard_by_J.S._Bach&#34;&gt;keyboard music&lt;/a&gt; and have almost completely ignored them for decades&lt;/em&gt;; there are only two exceptions: the Goldberg Variations and some of the Well-Tempered Clavier.  In particular, I have not listened to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/French_Suites_%28Bach%29&#34;&gt;French Suites&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/English_Suites_%28Bach%29&#34;&gt;English Suites&lt;/a&gt;, or &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Partitas_for_keyboard_%28Bach%29&#34;&gt;Partitas&lt;/a&gt; at all!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But because I just accidentally heard this Allemande played live, and liked it, I wanted to hear it again when I got home, and so I went to YouTube to find it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found a lot of performances online, of course, but I&amp;rsquo;m a sucker for the unusual, so I was particularly interested when I saw in the search results a link to some guy, Robert Hill, performing it on an unusual instrument I had never heard of in my life, a &amp;ldquo;lute-harpsichord&amp;rdquo;. And it got well over a hundred thumb-up ratings and only one thumb-down, so of course I was going to check it out!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I watched the video, and was &lt;em&gt;totally blown away&lt;/em&gt; by the beauty of the performance:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The instrument has a gorgeous sound.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Robert Hill played very expressively, with the full freedom and emotion that treasure.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Structurally, I could hear the different voices and phrases with total clarity because of how he plays.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This single performance made me think that I needed to give old Bach another shot and check out more of his keyboard music.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Listen for yourself (it&amp;rsquo;s less than two minutes long):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/woh8UHdjl1M&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;who-is-robert-hill&#34;&gt;Who is Robert Hill?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did a Web search on Robert Hill and found &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Hill_%28musician%29&#34;&gt;information about him&lt;/a&gt;. He is an American keyboard instrument performer (especially early keyboard instruments such as harpsichord, clavichord, lute-harpsichord, fortepiano) and musicologist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had to search hard to find an actual Web site of his own, and it&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://robert-hill.tripod.com/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. It basically looks like it hasn&amp;rsquo;t been updated since around 2001, which is also his last recording time period on his &lt;a href=&#34;http://robert-hill.tripod.com/id11.html&#34;&gt;discography&lt;/a&gt;. At some point he must have decided to just share his music through YouTube. He is a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mh-freiburg.de/lehrende/person/details/hill/&#34;&gt;music professor in Freiburg&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I just mentioned, my fascination with the performances of Robert Hill comes from his &lt;em&gt;expressiveness&lt;/em&gt;, which comes about from adjustments of tempo, rhetorical gestures, ornamentation, rhythmic sense. He plays a lot more expressively than many keyboard musicians do today, and I like that. I now believe that I was turned off by much of Bach&amp;rsquo;s keyboard music not because of Bach, but because of the relatively bland performances his music has received, especially from modern pianists. Bach was an emotional man living in an emotional age (the Baroque era of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Doctrine_of_the_affections&#34;&gt;affect&lt;/a&gt;), and I feel blessed that musicians like Robert Hill are taking this seriously. There are others, of course, besides him, but I think his performances have a particular edge to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;regular-harpsichord&#34;&gt;Regular harpsichord&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is an example of Robert Hill playing regular harpsichord.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;bach-s-allemande-from-the-partita-in-d-major-bwv-828&#34;&gt;Bach&amp;rsquo;s Allemande from the Partita in D major, BWV 828&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I discovered this beautiful, haunting work of music by Bach for the first time, by sheer accident, when browsing Hill&amp;rsquo;s YouTube channel (live performance from 1997):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/oEoqPSFklkE&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I cannot believe I went four decades without ever having heard this piece in my life. Now I can&amp;rsquo;t get it out of my head.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hill did some extreme things in this performance (tempo modifications and hesitations) that are not to my taste, but I applaud him for having the courage to play from the heart, because much of what he did spoke to mine! He lives dangerously. Maybe that&amp;rsquo;s why he only posts live recording clips to YouTube now rather than make CDs?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;fortepiano&#34;&gt;Fortepiano&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He also plays fortepiano, which is a fascinating instrument I love. I have mentioned my first experience with a fortepiano in college in a blog post earlier this year celebrating the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/03/08/happy-300th-birthday-carl-philipp-emanuel-bach/&#34;&gt;300th birthday of Johann Sebastian&amp;rsquo;s son Carl Philipp Emanuel&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;cpe-bach-s-fantasie-in-f-sharp-minor&#34;&gt;CPE Bach&amp;rsquo;s Fantasie in F-sharp minor&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heck, I had to check out Hill&amp;rsquo;s performance of my favorite CPE Bach keyboard work. In my earlier blog post, I had praised Andreas Staier&amp;rsquo;s performance I discovered in college, but now having heard Hill&amp;rsquo;s, I have another favorite (live from April 2014). This totally plays up Hill&amp;rsquo;s maximally emotive expressive style:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/LOT_nUPvE98&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;js-bach-well-tempered-clavier-selections&#34;&gt;JS Bach: Well-Tempered Clavier selections&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was fascinating to find Hill performing JS Bach on fortepiano; I had never heard anyone playing JS Bach on fortepiano before. I love that he experiments with different styles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The famous WTC I, Prelude in C major, in a fluid, beautiful Romantic-style (vs. Baroque-style) performance he just uploaded a couple of days ago:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/jiBQD0vV5qI&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A totally gorgeous Romantic-style interpretation of the slow Bach WTC I, Prelude in C# minor:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/9iGj4U7nqqY&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love how he makes full use of the expressive possibilities of the fortepiano (power and dynamics and sustain).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;beethoven-s-moonlight-sonata&#34;&gt;Beethoven&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Moonlight&amp;rdquo; sonata&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, he plays Beethoven too, on fortepiano.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that Beethoven did call it &amp;ldquo;sonata quasi fantasia&amp;rdquo; so it should be played freely &amp;ldquo;like a fantasy&amp;rdquo;, freely, and he does this. If you&amp;rsquo;ve only heard it played more &amp;ldquo;squarely&amp;rdquo;, check this out. In this case, I prefer a more subtle freedom than the exaggerated gestures Hill provides, because I feel he disrupts the rhythmic flow too much, so I consider his experiment not a full success, but still, I respect his willingness to go all out:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/6gpmZsqOzZs&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;pianoforte&#34;&gt;Pianoforte!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, of course Robert Hill plays the modern piano too. And I love what he does with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;brahms&#34;&gt;Brahms&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hill brings out the different voices very well, the counterpoint through the thick textures of Brahms. These are truly beautiful performances of some of &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/05/07/happy-birthday-johannes-brahms/&#34;&gt;my favorite piano music of all time, Brahms&amp;rsquo; intermezzi&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A passionate performance of Op. 117, No. 2 in B-flat minor:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/U_rlk4H-DQ0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And Op. 119, No. 1 in B minor (some favorite performances of which I discussed in &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/05/07/happy-birthday-johannes-brahms/&#34;&gt;my blog post last year&lt;/a&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/NOpe_KvXQzA&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is one of the most emotionally raw performances I have ever heard of this intermezzo. Hill makes the most of the suspensions, silences, dissonances, and clashing lines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Discovering the musical performances of Robert Hill on keyboard instruments has been one of the happy surprises of my life this year. Not only has he provided me listening pleasure, but also has sharpened my conception of what the music he plays is about and how to express it. He has forever changed my expectation from myself of how I should play music. I expect that from now on, I will never again hold back from &amp;ldquo;weird&amp;rdquo; interpretations that I feel come from my heart and mind. I don&amp;rsquo;t expect that all my experiments will succeed, but seeing someone else try, and publicly, how can I not do likewise?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Have you recently discovered a musician who has changed your hearing and/or your own playing? Who was it and what did you learn?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Chamber music concert at CMU featured Bach&#39;s Goldberg Variations arranged for string trio</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/11/19/chamber-music-concert-at-cmu-featured-bachs-goldberg-variations-arranged-for-string-trio/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Nov 2013 23:04:37 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/11/19/chamber-music-concert-at-cmu-featured-bachs-goldberg-variations-arranged-for-string-trio/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.cmu.edu/news/stories/archives/2013/november/images/chamber-recital_400x340.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;David Harding, Noah Bendix-Balgley, Lorna McGhee, Amit Peled&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I attended a special &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cmu.edu/news/stories/archives/2013/november/nov8_chambermusic.html&#34;&gt;chamber music concert at CMU&lt;/a&gt; that featured some truly excellent musicians.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-musicians&#34;&gt;The musicians&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was particularly interested in seeing &lt;a href=&#34;http://trioverlaine.com/bios/lorna-mcghee/&#34;&gt;Lorna McGhee&lt;/a&gt;, the current principal flute of the Pittsburgh Symphony Orchestra, and violinist &lt;a href=&#34;http://noahbendixbalgley.com/&#34;&gt;Noah Bendix-Balgley&lt;/a&gt;, the concertmaster, both of whom are relatively recent additions to the orchestra. The other two musicians, also fantastic, were violist and CMU professor &lt;a href=&#34;http://trioverlaine.com/bios/david-harding/&#34;&gt;David Harding&lt;/a&gt; and cellist &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amitpeled.com/&#34;&gt;Amit Peled&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;mozart-s-flute-quartet-no-1-in-d-major&#34;&gt;Mozart&amp;rsquo;s flute quartet no. 1 in D major&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lorna McGhee played in the first part of the program, which was Mozart&amp;rsquo;s first flute quartet. I was very curious how she would approach the work, because I&amp;rsquo;m very picky nowadays about the performance of music from the 18th century or earlier, which I far prefer to be both on period instruments and in period style. The typical &amp;ldquo;modern&amp;rdquo; performance I can no longer enjoy, because of stylistic anachronisms that in my mind invalidate the beauty and freshness of early music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed the quartet&amp;rsquo;s performance of the Mozart. The playing was crisp, lively, and transparent. There was little to quibble with in Lorna McGhee&amp;rsquo;s performance: she played with verve, sensitivity, and clarity. In some phrases she held a legato longer than I would like, but overall I quite liked the performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;bach-s-goldberg-variations-arranged-for-string-trio-by-dmitry-sitkovetsky&#34;&gt;Bach&amp;rsquo;s Goldberg Variations arranged for string trio by Dmitry Sitkovetsky&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bulk of the program was devoted to a performance by the string trio of the entire Goldberg Variations by Bach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past quarter century, I&amp;rsquo;ve listened to countless performances of the Goldberg Variations on all kinds of keyboard instrument, including harpsichord, fortepiano, and modern piano, but until tonight, I hadn&amp;rsquo;t bothered listening to Sitkovetsky&amp;rsquo;s arrangement for string trio that came out several years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought it worked out pretty well tonight, with the three string players working really hard to create dynamism and contrast along with unity in this monumental work. I couldn&amp;rsquo;t help but think that it&amp;rsquo;s actually harder to pull off as a trio than as a solo keyboard piece. What was particularly interesting was visually seeing and hearing (in the different tonal qualities) all the different voices in the music. They are there in the original version, of course, but experiencing the spatial separation just made me even more amazed by Bach&amp;rsquo;s creation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I appreciate the time the four musicians took to perform in this chamber music recital free to the public, and thank you, CMU, for bringing them in for these invigorating performances of Mozart and Bach!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Flute update: celebrating Bach&#39;s birthday, using a Thumbport, improvising to bossa nova</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/03/21/flute-update-celebrating-bachs-birthday/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Mar 2012 20:57:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/03/21/flute-update-celebrating-bachs-birthday/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s been eleven days since &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/10/flute-loving-it-again/&#34;&gt;my last blog post on my flute progress&lt;/a&gt;. During this time, there have been various changes in my life, including &lt;em&gt;radical&lt;/em&gt; changes in my musical life. It will take me a couple of additional blog posts to discuss these changes, but for now, I&amp;rsquo;ll talk only about today&amp;rsquo;s snapshot of my flute activity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2012-03-12&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-03-12)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had ended up &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/12/quitting-the-cmu-all-university-orchestra-one-of-the-hardest-decisions-in-my-life/&#34;&gt;quitting the CMU AUO&lt;/a&gt;, and then having a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/17/st-patricks-day-party-playing-tin-whistle-and-flute/&#34;&gt;wonderful musical experience a birthday party&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;thumbport&#34;&gt;Thumbport&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.thumbport.com/images/position.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Thumbport&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Today I received a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.thumbport.com/&#34;&gt;Thumbport II&lt;/a&gt; I ordered recently. It&amp;rsquo;s a snap-on device that helps with holding a flute, by making it easier to balance the flute on the right thumb, thereby decreasing rolling of the flute and pressure on the right pinkie finger. I tried it for the first time today and it seems useful. We&amp;rsquo;ll see if it helps a bit with my form and &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/07/flute-taking-a-break-while-clarifying-my-goals/&#34;&gt;injury issues&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;i-celebrated-the-327th-birthday-of-johann-sebastian-bach&#34;&gt;I celebrated the 327th birthday of Johann Sebastian Bach&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t follow celebrity birthdays, but I could not avoid hearing about the birthday of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Johann_Sebastian_Bach&#34;&gt;Johann Sebastian Bach, born in 1685&lt;/a&gt;, thanks to some music blogs I follow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How to celebrate? The last time I celebrated a composer&amp;rsquo;s birthday, it was last October, for Franz Liszt&amp;rsquo;s 200th birthday. Then, I listened to a piece of music by the composer and &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/22/happy-200th-birthday/&#34;&gt;wrote up my impressions of it&lt;/a&gt;. Today, I again had the option to read about Bach or his music, and but I mostly chose to play his music, in order to celebrate as &lt;em&gt;actively&lt;/em&gt; as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;playing-the-cello-suite-no-1-in-g-major-bwv-1007&#34;&gt;Playing the cello suite no. 1 in G major, BWV 1007&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I sight read a bunch of old Bach&amp;rsquo;s music that eventually I should practice seriously to play well, including various minuets and bourrées.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the main piece I sight read was the full &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cello_Suites_(Bach)&#34;&gt;cello suite&lt;/a&gt; no. 1 in G major, using an &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pjb.com.au/mus/arr.html&#34;&gt;arrangement for flute by Peter Billam&lt;/a&gt;. (I had actually obtained this a long time ago intending to play it on alto &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/recorder/&#34;&gt;recorder&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This music is deceptively simple but really quite beautiful. Even visually it is pleasing: check out Bach&amp;rsquo;s handwritten score:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/9/9c/Bachs1a.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Bach cello suite no. 1, first page&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h4 id=&#34;visual-animation&#34;&gt;Visual animation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, you must check out the following unconventional visual animated representation of this music (see the creator&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.chenalexander.com/2011/baroque-bach-cello/&#34;&gt;blog post about its construction&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe src=&#34;http://player.vimeo.com/video/31179423?title=0&amp;amp;byline=0&amp;amp;portrait=0&#34; width=&#34;400&#34; height=&#34;225&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen allowFullScreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://vimeo.com/31179423&#34;&gt;Baroque.me: J.S. Bach - Cello Suite No. 1 - Prelude&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href=&#34;http://vimeo.com/alexanderchen&#34;&gt;Alexander Chen&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&#34;http://vimeo.com&#34;&gt;Vimeo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;bossa-nova&#34;&gt;Bossa nova&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://s3.amazonaws.com/halleonard-closerlook/00843016/00843016FC.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Latin Jazz: 10 Latin Jazz Classics&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Today I also picked up from the public library another play-along score/CD set, this time a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.halleonard.com/product/viewproduct.do?itemid=843016&amp;amp;lid=1&amp;amp;keywords=latin&amp;amp;seriesfeature=JZPLYA&amp;amp;&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Latin jazz&amp;rdquo; collection&lt;/a&gt;. Apart from the famous mambo &amp;ldquo;Ran Kan Kan&amp;rdquo; by Tito Puente, the rest was actually bossa nova, which was what I got it for. Recently I decided to get more into playing jazz and working on improvisation. Since I love the harmonies and tunes of classic bossa nova, I decided this was a good place to get started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a lot of fun playing around with the accompaniment CD. Actually, I would also like to sing this music, but unlike with salsa and bolero, where I am completely comfortable singing in Spanish, I am not proficient in the Portuguese language and it trips me up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I just thought I&amp;rsquo;d provide a short update on some of my current musical activities, until I have time to write about the big changes I&amp;rsquo;ve made in my musical life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-musical-tangent-bach-s-goldberg-variations&#34;&gt;A musical tangent: Bach&amp;rsquo;s Goldberg Variations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In turns out there is a whole series of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.npr.org/blogs/deceptivecadence/148455347/goldberg-week&#34;&gt;posts on the NPR music blog about the Goldberg Variations&lt;/a&gt;. I could not resist dipping into this series, because I am a Goldberg geek. I would like someday to get good enough on piano to play much of it.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>