<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Marathon on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/marathon/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Marathon on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/marathon/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Getting up when reality punches you in the face: running the second Liberty Mile in Pittsburgh</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/08/09/getting-up-when-reality-punches-you-in-the-face-running-the-second-liberty-mile-in-pittsburgh/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Aug 2013 20:49:35 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/08/09/getting-up-when-reality-punches-you-in-the-face-running-the-second-liberty-mile-in-pittsburgh/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Last year, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/08/17/the-inaugural-liberty-mile-a-review-of-pittsburghs-first-road-mile-race/&#34;&gt;I reported on the excitement I had running in and watching&lt;/a&gt; the first &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.libertymile.org/&#34;&gt;GNC Live Well Liberty Mile&lt;/a&gt;. I was so excited about running it again that late this May, having mostly recovered from my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/05/06/2013-pittsburgh-marathon-my-135th-race-was-my-worst-i-finished/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Marathon disaster&lt;/a&gt;, I quickly pre-registered for the Liberty Mile for this year. I anticipated training to run well in this year&amp;rsquo;s Liberty Mile, given that I was not really trained last year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, this year I have been in very poor shape since the marathon, because of a whole series of health problems and disruptions in my life resulting from a skin rash I got during a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/05/12/my-rachel-carson-trail-hike-for-the-year/&#34;&gt;Rachel Carson Trail hike in May&lt;/a&gt;. The upshot is that I have been running (and exercising in general) very little in the past three months. As the Liberty Mile approached, I wished that I had not registered for it at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I faced a dilemma: what should I do about the race?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;deciding-to-run-it&#34;&gt;Deciding to run it&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The good thing about the mile is that it&amp;rsquo;s short enough that of course I can finish the thing. So I felt there was no excuse to just bail out and forfeit my pre-registration. I was going to run it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bad thing about the mile is that it is brutal to actually run &lt;em&gt;fast&lt;/em&gt;. I have always felt pukey after running a mile as &amp;ldquo;fast&amp;rdquo; as I can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, I decided to still try to run the Liberty Mile as fast as I could, knowing that I would probably suffer for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In recent weeks I&amp;rsquo;ve been trying to go out periodically for short, slow runs, something like two miles at a time, to gain at least have &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; kind of conditioning. Also, earlier this week I put in some &amp;ldquo;fast&amp;rdquo; repeats of about 300m out in Frick Park: the only &amp;ldquo;fast&amp;rdquo; running I&amp;rsquo;ve done since April!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this whole week I was feeling bad, stress exacerbated by home repair disruptions with the contractors coming over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;support-from-abby&#34;&gt;Support from Abby&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, I went to the race alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year, Abby offered to go downtown with me so she could watch the race and be with me. (In May when I was pre-registering for the race, she had just spent months barely mobile because of a broken foot and was simply not certain she would be able to even run a mile again by August.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really appreciated this because I felt rather vulnerable about this race. We planned to watch the first wave start, and then have me run my heat (again the &amp;ldquo;Unstoppable 40+&amp;rdquo; heat), then hang out afterwards and watch the elite heats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We drove downtown and parked and walked to the packet pickup area in Market Square. I was pleased that it wasn&amp;rsquo;t raining; it had rained earlier in the day, but that was all over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because we arrived later than other people, they had run out of Small T-shirts and so I got a Medium.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/liberty-mile-2013/abby.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby holding my T-shirt&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;changes-in-the-course&#34;&gt;Changes in the course&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I should note that the course was changed from last year. The change makes sense because it considerably simplifies the logistics. Last year, the course was a straight shot down Liberty Ave toward downtown. This year, the course was an almost-loop course, first going out on Penn Ave, then turning to head back in on Liberty Ave. The advantage is that the start and finish are close together, so it is much easier for people to plan to spectate or get back to their cars or whatever. I do like the concept of the straight downhill road course, but understand the logistical difficulties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My plan was to do my best to avoid going out too fast, and try to push hard in the final downhill portion of the race. Easier said than done, because last year I certainly wanted to avoid going out too fast, but did anyway!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;before-the-race&#34;&gt;Before the race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wore my Vibram FiveFingers Bikila LS shoes again.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/liberty-mile-2013/before-start.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin before race&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At the GNC booth, I saw they were giving out free samples of energy bars and other stuff. I was feeling hungry, and although I know that it is best not to race having just eaten, especially unfamiliar foods, I took a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.gnc.com/product/index.jsp?productId=4468895&#34;&gt;GNC Pro Performance Pro Crunch Lite&lt;/a&gt; energy bar, and ate a couple of bites before giving the remainder to Abby to put away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was probably a big mistake to have eaten from the energy bar, because it didn&amp;rsquo;t really agree with me. Oops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;start-and-finish-lines&#34;&gt;Start and finish lines&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We checked out the start and finish lines.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/liberty-mile-2013/start-line.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Start line&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/liberty-mile-2013/finish-line.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Finish line&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;first-heat-at-7-00-pm&#34;&gt;First heat (at 7:00 PM)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We watched as the first &amp;ldquo;fun run&amp;rdquo; heat went.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/liberty-mile-2013/first-heat-start.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-race-heat-at-7-20-pm&#34;&gt;My race (heat at 7:20 PM)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got to the start line and lined up &lt;em&gt;at the back&lt;/em&gt;, where I knew I belonged. I was not sure that I would not be last place in my heat!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/liberty-mile-2013/my-heat-start.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here I am, looking as tired as I in fact was, still taking medication for my skin problem that is not completely gone (usually showing up as spots on my neck or hands and arms):&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/liberty-mile-2013/franklin-before.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin before the race&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As the race began, I tried not to go too fast, but did. 1:34 for the first quarter mile, not good at all! Last year, I ran the mile in 6:39, and went out in 1:29 for the first quarter. This year, I was hoping to go under 7:00 at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I slowed down for the second quarter, then finally found a steady pace for the third quarter. During the final quarter, I saw the finish line and eventually saw the clock ticking up toward 7:00. I was &lt;em&gt;furious&lt;/em&gt; that I might not be able to finish a 7-minute mile. I sprinted all out and didn&amp;rsquo;t actually finish under 7:00 according to the clock (the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.areep.com/events/libertymile/&#34;&gt;official race results&lt;/a&gt; say I finished in 7:02), but my chip time was 6:56, so I actually did run the mile in under 7 minutes!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My splits:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1:34 (went too fast)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1:56 (uphill, deliberately slowed down)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1:46 (steady)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1:40 (final kick)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;more-photos-of-the-liberty-mile&#34;&gt;More photos of the Liberty Mile&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More photos of the entire event can be seen &lt;a href=&#34;http://petemadia.photoshelter.com/gallery/2013-GNC-Live-Well-Liberty-Mile/G0000gQc.MfyoOAE/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;after-my-race&#34;&gt;After my race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Afterwards, I felt really, really crappy:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/liberty-mile-2013/done-in-pain.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin done for a while but still in pain&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In fact, for a full half hour after the race, all I could do was walk and sit around with Abby trying to feel less crappy. &lt;strong&gt;I have never felt so bad for so long after any race of any distance.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;reflections&#34;&gt;Reflections&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mentally, also, I was still very &lt;em&gt;angry&lt;/em&gt; at myself: I came in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.areep.com/events/libertymile/results/13lm_uno.txt&#34;&gt;60th place out of 74&lt;/a&gt;, running a chip time of 6:56, a whopping &lt;em&gt;18 seconds&lt;/em&gt; slower than last year. That&amp;rsquo;s a huge decrease in fitness for a mile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My plan for this year, 2013, was supposed to be to get back into great health and fitness, &amp;ldquo;the shape I was in five years ago&amp;rdquo;. It&amp;rsquo;s why, for the new year, I got into &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/28/meditations-on-climbing-the-36-floors-of-the-pitt-cathedral-of-learning/&#34;&gt;climbing the Cathedral of Learning&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s why I got into running in the winter](/blog/2012/12/31/why-i-went-frick-park-trail-running-in-snowfall-for-the-first-time-in-a-decade/). It&amp;rsquo;s why I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/30/why-and-how-i-am-going-to-run-the-2013-pittsburgh-marathon/&#34;&gt;decided to run the Pittsburgh Marathon&lt;/a&gt;. I blew it my overtraining for the marathon and then suffering freak skin problems after a hike that ended up seeing doctors something like five times, and being put on medication that messed with me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a lot to be angry about. But after I recovered, I became calm and stopped being angry about being punched in the face by reality. I decided that it was motivation for me to turn my life around. I decided that I was going to get back into a regular exercise routine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In just the past three months, I have lost all of my fitness of the past several years. But I have a plan to get back on track, starting &lt;em&gt;tomorrow&lt;/em&gt;. I believe that for 2014, I can still get back into my 2008 shape. It&amp;rsquo;s a matter of making it a priority, over all the other things I have been doing in my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;going-home&#34;&gt;Going home&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After I recovered enough that I felt like eating and walking again, Abby and I went back to our car and we went home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only minutes after getting home did I realize that I had &lt;em&gt;totally forgotten&lt;/em&gt; to stick around to watch the elite runners&amp;rsquo; races!! That was far from my mind when I was feeling nauseous and reflecting on my poor fitness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The race was very well organized, and I&amp;rsquo;m thankful for the continuation of this new Pittsburgh tradition. Although I had a humbling experience in my heat, I totally want to be back for a third try at executing a good mile next year! And I am thankful that I actually ran it, because it gave me the resolve to regain my lost fitness.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Boston Marathon tragedy: please avoid the news porn</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/04/15/boston-marathon-tragedy-please-avoid-the-news-porn/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Apr 2013 19:49:22 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/04/15/boston-marathon-tragedy-please-avoid-the-news-porn/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Since I am a runner (and happening to be in the last stages of training for my second Pittsburgh Marathon, which is coming in less than three weeks), I woke up this morning knowing that it was Boston Marathon day. Also, by sheer coincidence, a fellow Pittsburgher I have never met but follow on Twitter happened to tweet a photo of his running gear while ready to run in Boston, and happened to mention some sock sleeves that he wears that I had never seen before, and I tweeted him for the first time in my life, and I got a reply from him after he finished, and I went and ordered a pair of these &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cepcompression.com/1922-Allsports-Sleeves.aspx&#34;&gt;sock sleeves online&lt;/a&gt;, since I have a tendency toward calf cramping in long distance races.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it was particularly eerie and somewhat personal to me when in the afternoon I heard from my office mate at work that the Boston Marathon had been bombed and people were dead and horribly injured.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first thought was, &lt;strong&gt;this is fucking insane&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My second thought was extreme anger that criminals would do such a thing, and sadness for the runners and spectators who were so victimized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My third thought was, &amp;ldquo;Uh oh, here we go again: time for news porn&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;9-11-and-news&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;9&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;11&lt;/sub&gt; and news&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because I remember &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/September_11_attacks&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;9&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;11&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some excerpts from my journal on September 11, 2001 (at this time in my life I was jotting down journal entries regularly during the waking day):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;11:12: &amp;ldquo;Oh G-d!!!!!!!!!!!  The World Trade Center has been destroyed.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;11:36: &amp;ldquo;Things will never be the same again in this country.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;12:11: &amp;ldquo;Can&amp;rsquo;t let terrorists disrupt my life.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;18:28: &amp;ldquo;Wait, are we attacking Afghanistan??????&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;22:14: &amp;ldquo;Watched some TV footage for the first time.  Disturbing.  Especially people jumping out of the buildings.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;23:31: &amp;ldquo;Other people on &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zephyr_%28protocol%29&#34;&gt;zephyr&lt;/a&gt; [an internal chat system at Carnegie Mellon University] are saying they watched more TV today than all year.  Same with me.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, during this whole time, I did immediately try to call my sister who lived and worked in New York City, and of course failed. She reached me eventually and said she was OK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I realized something that day. I realized that I could not let relentless news porn rule my life. There was no benefit to my seeing again and again footage about the tragic terrorist attacks and all the speculations, the anger, the crying. I did not quit watching TV that evening, but did realize that I was being manipulated in a way that did not help me or help the world, really.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much later, I learned that a high school classmate of mine had died on &lt;sup&gt;9&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;11&lt;/sub&gt;. And a college classmate was across the street when it happened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;news&#34;&gt;News&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point, years later, I did completely quit following news. By this, I mean that I stopped watching news on TV, I stopped reading printed newspapers, and I stopped reading online news sites as well. Seriously. It has improved my life. Periodically I try to spread the message of news avoidance, having seen the damage that following news has done to some family members and friends, without noticeable benefit in return.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, just yesterday on Twitter I retweeted &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.guardian.co.uk/media/2013/apr/12/news-is-bad-rolf-dobelli&#34;&gt;yet another article on news avoidance&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you haven&amp;rsquo;t done the experiment of avoiding news, your first thought might be, &amp;ldquo;Franklin must be an ignoramus who doesn&amp;rsquo;t care about the world or know what goes on in it&amp;rdquo;. But actually, I am not completely ignorant of news: I simply have some filters. I do actively follow blogs, Twitter, Facebook, and Google+, and so I implicitly get a curated summary of whatever news is forwarded around through those channels. I see links and check the headlines, and I can choose to ignore or follow up on the news. And I selectively retweet what I find interesting and &lt;em&gt;useful&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, the social media has for the past couple of hours become overwhelmingly dominated by a lot of emotions over the Boston Marathon terrorist attack, so as I write this, I am imposing a complete blackout on blogs, Twitter, Facebook, and Google+.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;local&#34;&gt;Local&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The local and federal authorities are, I presume, doing what they can to aid the victims and seek out the criminals, and following their every move would not help me be useful. If this tragedy had happened in Pittsburgh, then I would be monitoring the situation much more closely, in case I can actually be of direct aid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;couldn-t-avoid-tv-today&#34;&gt;Couldn&amp;rsquo;t avoid TV today&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, by coincidence, I could not avoid TV today. This evening, I was in the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/10/26/yet-another-haircut-from-joe-always-worth-the-wait/&#34;&gt;barber shop&lt;/a&gt; getting a haircut, and not only could people not refrain from commenting on the tragedy, but he also had the radio on and turned on his TV as well. I refused to look at the TV screen, but could not help repeatedly hearing about body parts being blown off, eardrums being perforated, panic, the audio clips of explosions and screaming, again and again. I remained silent and maintained my composure until my haircut was done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-media-blackout&#34;&gt;A media blackout&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am taking a break from the Web overall for the rest of the evening. Last I checked my social media feeds, they are now all about the Boston Marathon attacks. I cannot help anyone by sitting in front of my computer getting all emotional and confused following all these feeds. I humbly recommend that you consider doing this also.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have not found news porn to be useful in helping me cope with tragedy or in enabling me be of aid to those who need help. Given that, I am opting out of the news frenzy.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>18 miles in Vibram FiveFingers: training for the Pittsburgh Marathon through a St. Patrick&#39;s Day parade</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/03/16/18-miles-in-vibram-fivefingers-training-for-the-pittsburgh-marathon/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Mar 2013 18:22:34 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/03/16/18-miles-in-vibram-fivefingers-training-for-the-pittsburgh-marathon/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/18-miles/st-patricks-day-parade-prep.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Pittsburgh St. Patrick&amp;#39;s Day preparation&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My second &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.steelcityrrc.org/scrrcevents?eventId=619953&amp;amp;EventViewMode=2&amp;amp;CalendarViewType=1&amp;amp;SelectedDate=3/30/2013&#34;&gt;Saturday group training run with the Steel City Runners&lt;/a&gt; happened to be on St. Patrick&amp;rsquo;s Day weekend, and therefore took place just before the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pittsburghirish.org/parade/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh St. Patrick&amp;rsquo;s Day parade&lt;/a&gt;, which starts at 10 AM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;overtraining-and-knees&#34;&gt;Overtraining and knees&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/09/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings-in-one-12-mile-run/&#34;&gt;Last week I mentioned&lt;/a&gt; that I was having problems because of overtraining; I ran five days one week only to have to scale back to three the next. This week I consciously got in four days of running, with higher total mileage than either of the previous two weeks (when I did 26 and 23). This week, I got in 29. It wasn&amp;rsquo;t easy, especially given that I ran last week&amp;rsquo;s long run too hard and therefore had left knee oddness that actually lasted three days! It wasn&amp;rsquo;t so bad that I couldn&amp;rsquo;t run, but I clearly had to let it heal up, which it did in time for another long run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, both of John&amp;rsquo;s knees were in serious pain the day after last week&amp;rsquo;s training run, and a week later, he is still waiting for them to heal up, and therefore did not join me for today&amp;rsquo;s training run. Oops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;plan&#34;&gt;Plan&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For today&amp;rsquo;s run, I decided to run &lt;em&gt;only the first 16 miles&lt;/em&gt; and then walk the last 2 miles. Also, I joined the 10-minute pace group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that a lot of things went &amp;ldquo;wrong&amp;rdquo; on this run, but I got back to the start OK in the end!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;unknown-territory&#34;&gt;Unknown territory&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wore my Vibram FiveFingers Bikila LS shoes again. This is an important test, because I have &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; been on the road for 18 miles straight in these shoes before, run or walk! I need to know whether wearing these for the Pittsburgh Marathon will work out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;weather-conditions&#34;&gt;Weather conditions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had watched the forecast all week with concern that it might be pouring rain, but I was committed to do this run regardless of conditions, because if the Pittsburgh Marathon involves running in rain, I need to be ready to deal with that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that we lucked out; although it was cold, there was drizzling rain but no downpour!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/18-miles/start.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Start of run&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-route&#34;&gt;The route&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is the route of the 18-mile training run:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe id=&#34;mapmyfitness_route&#34; src=&#34;http://snippets.mapmycdn.com/routes/view/embedded/180281790?width=560&amp;height=400&amp;elevation=true&amp;info=true&amp;line_color=E60f0bdb&amp;rgbhex=DB0B0E&amp;distance_markers=1&amp;unit_type=imperial&amp;map_mode=TERRAIN&amp;last_updated=2013-03-11T10:51:41-04:00&#34; height=&#34;590px&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: right; padding-right: 20px;&#34;&gt;&lt;a target=&#34;_blank&#34; href=&#34;http://mapmyrun.com/routes/create/&#34;&gt;Create Maps&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a target=&#34;_blank&#34; href=&#34;http://mapmyrun.com/routes/&#34;&gt;search&lt;/a&gt; from 80 million at &lt;a href=&#34;http://mapmyrun.com&#34;&gt;MapMyRun&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-run&#34;&gt;The run&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started with the 10-minute pace group. I actually immediately fell back, wanting to start off running more slowly,  but was never too far from the pack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;st-patrick-s-day&#34;&gt;St. Patrick&amp;rsquo;s Day&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Immediately and throughout the run, I saw people in green who were a little loud and clearly had a bit to drink. I was amused that they were up and around already at 8 AM in the morning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We ended up running on Liberty Avenue through the setup for St. Patrick&amp;rsquo;s Day parade downtown (which begins at 10 AM). We got some cheers (many of us were wearing green) as well as some jeers. It was a strange experience, and I felt a bit embarrassed to be running through parade preparation.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/18-miles/st-patricks-day-parade-prep.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Pittsburgh St. Patrick&amp;#39;s Day preparation&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;first-water-stop&#34;&gt;First water stop&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the first water stop, I drank some water and grabbed a GU gel to go. I caught up to the 10-minute pace group at the first water stop, since a lot of people didn&amp;rsquo;t immediately keep going but waited for everyone to get water.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My new system with gels is to take one and then eat it some minutes after drinking water, rather than immediately with water. It saves time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;big-uphill-and-losing-my-map&#34;&gt;Big uphill and losing my map&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a big uphill going east on Liberty Ave during which I lost the 10-minute pace group because I prefer to go slower uphill to maintain an even &lt;em&gt;effort&lt;/em&gt; rather than &lt;em&gt;pace&lt;/em&gt;. I always make up the loss on the downhills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;second-water-stop&#34;&gt;Second water stop&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second water stop was near mile 8 in Shadyside. I caught up yet again to the 10-minute pace group at that point, and took another GU gel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, I realized that I must have lost my paper map while running up Liberty Avenue. This was bad, because although I roughly knew the route, I did not know all the details. I did have my smartphone on me, but the MapMyRun Web site did not display very well on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Worse, it appeared after the second water stop that the 10-minute pace group was either going much slower or I was all &amp;ldquo;warmed up&amp;rdquo; and going much faster, because I could not tolerate their pace, and I decided I had to forge ahead into Oakland, even though there was nobody ahead that I could follow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did find two other people who were willing to go at a faster pace along with me, so the three of us took off into Oakland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;birmingham-bridge&#34;&gt;Birmingham Bridge&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The three of us crossed the Birmingham Bridge together to the South Side. I remarked that the last time I did the Pittsburgh Marathon ten years ago, I was humbled by the uphill going &lt;em&gt;into&lt;/em&gt; Oakland (in the other direction) on the bridge.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/18-miles/birmingham-bridge.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Birmingham Bridge to South Side&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;south-side-and-falling-behind&#34;&gt;South Side and falling behind&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The South Side was a total party scene, as might be expected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Going east on Carson Street, I suddenly noticed at around mile 11 that I had lost one of my gloves. I had taken off my gloves earlier as it was getting warmer, and put them in my pockets, but just as I had lost my map because I hadn&amp;rsquo;t zipped my jacket pockets, I had now lost a glove. I apologized to my two companions and said I was turning back to find my glove if possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckily, my glove was just a block back, and a group of runners saw it and picked it up and gave it to me. But now my two companions were far away from me. I could still see them, but I didn&amp;rsquo;t want to run super fast just to catch them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;three-rivers-heritage-trail-and-getting-lost&#34;&gt;Three Rivers Heritage Trail and getting lost&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I saw my companions turn onto the Three Rivers Heritage Trail. At this point, I no longer knew exactly what the rest of the route was for the last 8 miles. I knew that there was a water/gel stop at some point in the next 7 miles before the West End Bridge, but had no idea where it was!! I really didn&amp;rsquo;t want to miss the final water/gel stop, since that would mean going 8 miles without any water or fuel. Of course, I did have some money on me, so I could stop somewhere to refuel, but I didn&amp;rsquo;t really want to stop if I didn&amp;rsquo;t have to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So now I&amp;rsquo;d run around 12 miles and my feet were definitely sore. It was a huge relief to be running on the trail, actually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then I made a mistake. I suddenly saw what seemed to be a water stop because a bunch of runners were gathering there. I approached and asked if it was the Steel City Road Runners water stop and they said no, it was Elite Runners and Walkers. They offered to give me some water anyway, but I declined, which was a mistake, because during the seconds I spent on this detour, I lost sight of my two companions!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I kept on running on the trail but they were just gone, and I never saw them again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;running-to-the-west-end-bridge&#34;&gt;Running to the West End Bridge&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I just kept on running west, figuring I would eventually get to the West End Bridge. I went through Station Square and made it across the West End Bridge. Now, I had planned ahead of time to stop running shortly after crossing the West End Bridge, because it was going to be 16 miles then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I started feeling cold, and so I did some run/walking east all the way back to the start. It was very lonely going the last 8 miles of the route alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;safe-and-warm&#34;&gt;Safe and warm&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I made it back OK. I grabbed two energy bars and went inside to get warm and stretch and devour the two energy bars. My feet were totally killing me, but I had survived 18 miles on them in Vibram FiveFingers Bikila LS shoes. I still have no idea whether I can last a whole marathon in them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;my-feet&#34;&gt;My feet&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although my feet are sore, everything seems to be OK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/18-miles/feet.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin&amp;#39;s feet&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/18-miles/shoes.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Vibram FiveFingers Bikila LS shoes&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/18-miles/soles.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin&amp;#39;s soles of feet&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;photos&#34;&gt;Photos&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/steelcityrrc&#34;&gt;Steel City Road Runners Facebook site&lt;/a&gt; is a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/media/set/?set=a.425827677512050.1073741827.391728257588659&amp;amp;type=1&#34;&gt;photo album of the St. Patrick&amp;rsquo;s Day run&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ran about 16 miles of the 18-mile route, as planned, but got lost, which I did not plan. I learned some lessons. In the future, I am zipping my jacket pockets, and I am also studying the printed map thoroughly before starting one of these runs. My super-sore feet have me worried about running the marathon in Vibram FiveFingers, so I will investigate alternatives. I&amp;rsquo;m still waiting for my order this week of &lt;a href=&#34;http://lunasandals.com/&#34;&gt;Luna Sandals&lt;/a&gt; to come in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, I&amp;rsquo;m thankful that Steel City Road Runners made it possible for me to do such a long run without feeling completely alone, and not having to haul all the water and fuel I needed during and after the run. Ten years ago when I was marathon training, I did carry along everything I needed, but it really is much nicer to simulate actual race conditions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am grateful that when I was done and called home, Abby baked a pizza for us to share when I got back. Fuel! Abby has been understanding and supportive during my training for the Pittsburgh Marathon. She thinks it&amp;rsquo;s a crazy thing to do, and it is, but I want to do it this once again while I have the opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>11 Pittsburgh bridge crossings in one 12-mile run</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/03/09/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings-in-one-12-mile-run/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Mar 2013 21:21:26 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/03/09/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings-in-one-12-mile-run/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://sphotos-b.xx.fbcdn.net/hphotos-ash3/602768_422297731198378_798317370_n.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;View from Mount Washington&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My first ever &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.steelcityrrc.org/scrrcevents?eventId=568739&amp;amp;EventViewMode=2&amp;amp;CalendarViewType=1&amp;amp;SelectedDate=3/16/2013&#34;&gt;Steel City Road Runners Saturday morning training run&lt;/a&gt; was a 12-mile run. My office mate John went with me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last time I ran as far as 12 miles &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/02/24/2013-pittsburgh-marathon-training-progress-since-signing-up-three-weeks-ago/&#34;&gt;was in February&lt;/a&gt;, so I expected to do OK. The important difference is that I have been increasing my weekly mileage. I had a monster training week last week, going up from 13 miles to 26 miles last week, the &lt;em&gt;largest&lt;/em&gt; training volume I have had in a single week in years. I&amp;rsquo;ll confess that this has taken a toll on me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result, I have backed off this week, such that including this 12-mile run (I will not run tomorrow), this week I will have 23 miles. In the long haul, &lt;em&gt;overtraining&lt;/em&gt; is a huge waste of time and energy. Unfortunately, in my attempt to &amp;ldquo;catch up&amp;rdquo; some because of the marathon coming in less than two months, I did in fact overtrain to an extent; last week I ran five out of seven days in order to reach that mileage of 26. This week, I tried to up the mileage but felt tired and wisely decided to rest when I needed to, even though that meant this week I ran only three days! Obviously, in retrospect, it would have been wiser to run four days last week and four this week, with better overall training.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I did enjoy today&amp;rsquo;s training run. It involved the most bridge crossings I have ever done in my life in a single day (by foot or otherwise): eleven!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is my report on the training run, including, of course, photos of bridge crossings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;sign-in&#34;&gt;Sign in&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;John and I signed in at 8 AM. It was going to be a beautiful, sunny day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We received printed maps of the route. I did have my smartphone with me, wearing it in my SPIbelt, so I felt pretty safe about knowing where I am or where to go in case I got lost.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings/sign-in.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Steel City Road Runners sign in&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There is indoor access to restrooms, water fountains, and warmth at these Steel City Road Runners training run meetings. Very nice for winter!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were designated pacers. I was uncertain about which pace group I should join, if any at all. I felt that probably the 10-minute pace group might be on the slow side, but definitely I did not expect to keep up with the 9-minute pace group for a long run. But we decided to start off with the 9-minute pace group and see what happens.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings/pace-groups.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Pacers&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I wore my Vibram FiveFingers Bikila LS shoes, which have been my main running shoes all winter (when there is no snow or water on the ground):&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings/vibram-fivefingers-bikila-ls.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin wearing Vibram FiveFingers Bikila LS&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-route&#34;&gt;The route&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is the route of the 12-mile training run:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe id=&#34;mapmyfitness_route&#34; src=&#34;http://snippets.mapmycdn.com/routes/view/embedded/178234904?width=560&amp;height=400&amp;elevation=true&amp;info=true&amp;line_color=E60f0bdb&amp;rgbhex=DB0B0E&amp;distance_markers=1&amp;unit_type=imperial&amp;map_mode=TERRAIN&amp;last_updated=2013-03-08T12:47:36-06:00&#34; height=&#34;590px&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: right; padding-right: 20px;&#34;&gt;&lt;a target=&#34;_blank&#34; href=&#34;http://mapmyrun.com/routes/create/&#34;&gt;Create Maps&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a target=&#34;_blank&#34; href=&#34;http://mapmyrun.com/routes/&#34;&gt;search&lt;/a&gt; from 80 million at &lt;a href=&#34;http://mapmyrun.com&#34;&gt;MapMyRun&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-bridge-crossings&#34;&gt;The bridge crossings&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 9-minute pace group was clearly going too fast for me. I hung off the back hoping to simply keep them in sight as they kept getting more ahead of me. To my surprise, John went with the group, even though he has not run in months. I was not sure it was wise of him not to have done any running before this training run, and am worried about his going too fast all of a sudden.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings/on-our-way.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;nine-minute pace group&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;rachel-carson-bridge-inbound-over-the-allegheny-river&#34;&gt;Rachel Carson Bridge, inbound over the Allegheny River&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings/rachel-carson-bridge.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;On Rachel Carson Bridge inbound&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We can see downtown Pittsburgh:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings/rachel-carson-bridge-see-downtown.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;On Rachel Carson Bridge, seeing downtown&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;7th-street-bridge-outbound&#34;&gt;7th Street Bridge, outbound&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings/7th-street-bridge.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;On 7th Street Bridge outbound&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;roberto-clemente-bridge-inbound&#34;&gt;Roberto Clemente Bridge, inbound&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings/roberto-clemente-bridge.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Approaching Roberto Clemente Bridge inbound&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;fort-duquesne-bridge-outbound&#34;&gt;Fort Duquesne Bridge, outbound&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings/fort-duquesne-bridge.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;On Fort Duquesne Bridge outbound&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;west-end-bridge-south-over-the-monongahela-river&#34;&gt;West End Bridge, south over the Monongahela River&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings/west-end-bridge.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;On West End Bridge south&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;first-water-stop-and-getting-lost&#34;&gt;First water stop and getting lost!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our first water stop was after 4 miles:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings/first-water-stop.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;First water stop&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;By the time I had reached this water stop, John and the rest of the 9-minute pace group were way ahead of me and barely visible. Unfortunately, after I drank some Gatorade, I noticed that I didn&amp;rsquo;t see them at all any more. So for almost the rest of the run, the following 8 miles, I was mostly alone! This was disconcerting because it meant that I&amp;rsquo;d have to try to follow the printed map and directions, and avoid getting lost. It would turn out that I would get lost a couple of times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;fort-pitt-bridge-inbound&#34;&gt;Fort Pitt Bridge, inbound&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings/fort-pitt-bridge.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;On Fort Pitt Bridge inbound&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;smithfield-street-bridge-outbound&#34;&gt;Smithfield Street Bridge, outbound&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings/smithfield-street-bridge.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;On Smithfield Street Bridge outbound&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Check out this view of bridges along the Monongahela River:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings/monongahela-river.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Monongahela River&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;10th-street-bridge-inbound&#34;&gt;10th Street Bridge, inbound&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leaving the South Side:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings/10th-street-bridge.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;On 10th Street Bridge inbound&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;liberty-bridge-outbound&#34;&gt;Liberty Bridge, outbound&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not having anyone to follow, I got confused about how to get onto the Liberty Bridge, missing the steps, and had to do some backtracking to find the way to get on.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings/liberty-bridge-outbound.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;On Liberty Bridge outbound&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;to-mount-washington&#34;&gt;To Mount Washington&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This training run featured a big, long uphill to Mount Washington, with a water stop at the very top!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings/to-mount-washington.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;To Mount Washington&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;After being alone for quite some time, I did encounter John and other runners coming back down Mount Washington when I was still going up. They were going really fast downhill!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings/up-to-mount-washington.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Uphill to Mount Washington&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;second-water-stop&#34;&gt;Second water stop&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My phone started acting funny when I got to the water stop at the top of Mount Washington, so I did not bother to try take any more photos after that. I was bummed that I didn&amp;rsquo;t get a photo of the view of Pittsburgh from the top, but someone did and posted it on Facebook, so here it is:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://sphotos-b.xx.fbcdn.net/hphotos-ash3/602768_422297731198378_798317370_n.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;View from Mount Washington&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At this water stop, at mile 9, I felt hungry, and saw some GU gels, and took one and ate it before continuing my run. It was &lt;a href=&#34;http://guenergy.com/products/products-roctane-gels&#34;&gt;GU Roctane&lt;/a&gt;. I didn&amp;rsquo;t look at the ingredients till after I got home and did a Web search on it. That explained a lot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While running down from Mount Washington, I felt a surge of energy and decided to run really, really fast, in hope of possibly catching sight of John at some point. In fact, I did not see any runner again for the next 3 miles until I reached the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;back-across-the-liberty-bridge-inbound&#34;&gt;Back across the Liberty Bridge, inbound&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then running through downtown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;16th-street-bridge-outbound&#34;&gt;16th Street Bridge outbound&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was kind of zoned out and missed the turn onto the bridge because I was just running fast, but luckily, I was off by just a block before I realized my mistake and backtracked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-end&#34;&gt;The end&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got back to the start in a bit less than two hours, so given my rest stops and getting lost, I definitely averaged under 10-minute pace. But I was definitely not running anywhere near 9-minute pace. I&amp;rsquo;ll keep that in my mind for the next training run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;John had finished well before me, but he himself had gotten lost near the end also.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We snacked on provided orange slices and chips:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings/after.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Steel City Road Runners snacks&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/11-pittsburgh-bridge-crossings/franklin.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Then I drove us back to our places. After both of us had showered and changed, we met up for lunch buffet at Coriander India Grill, a favorite place to eat &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/02/26/snowing-means-sambar-at-coriander-india-grill/&#34;&gt;after getting very hungry after a lot of exercise&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-next&#34;&gt;What next?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next week will be an 18-mile training run. As I have mentioned, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/02/24/2013-pittsburgh-marathon-training-progress-since-signing-up-three-weeks-ago/&#34;&gt;I do not intend to actually do such a long run&lt;/a&gt;, so I will think of a good way to run 16 miles instead: either I start walking earlier, or I walk near the end. And for sure, I will start with the 10-minute pace group rather than then 9-minute pace group. These training runs are not races. I don&amp;rsquo;t want to run too fast. In fact, I&amp;rsquo;m worried that I ran the last 3 miles today too fast, especially downhill from Mount Washington. My left knee is feeling a little funny. I hope it will recover after a day of rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve started to figure out the gel thing. I used eat gels a decade ago, but stopped because I had no reason to, but on these long runs, they do help, and I have to start planning what to use for fuel in the Pittsburgh Marathon, which will officially supply GU gel and Gatorade. I did learn, after the fact, that GU Roctane contains an insane amount of caffeine, and that&amp;rsquo;s probably what got me all hopped up to run super fast, but to my detriment today. So I need to be careful if I use Roctane in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a very instructive and tiring training run. I have a long way to go before being ready for the marathon in less than two months, but am happy to have finally joined a group training run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m very grateful for the opportunity to train with the Steel City Road Runners. Sometimes, it is much easier to commit to getting up early and going for a long run when you know that you&amp;rsquo;ll have company, that there will be support (in the form of a planned route and aid stations). Even for an introvert like me who usually prefers to run alone, the unique pains of marathon training cause me to value camaraderie for some tough runs.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why and how I am going to run the 2013 Pittsburgh Marathon</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/01/30/why-and-how-i-am-going-to-run-the-2013-pittsburgh-marathon/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Jan 2013 20:31:41 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/01/30/why-and-how-i-am-going-to-run-the-2013-pittsburgh-marathon/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I surprised myself by deciding suddenly to run the &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburghmarathon.com/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Marathon&lt;/a&gt; this year, 2013. This was not part of the plan when I was &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/31/why-i-went-frick-park-trail-running-in-snowfall-for-the-first-time-in-a-decade/&#34;&gt;thinking about my running plans for 2013 a month ago&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will be my second Pittsburgh Marathon, because the last time I ran it was in 2003, and that was my first marathon ever. It was quite an ordeal to finish, because of a lot of rookie mistakes, but I made it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here I am in 2003 near the finish line (photo courtesy of my sister Linda):&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2003/P5040055.JPG&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin near finish line in 2003&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And here I am wearing my medal for finishing in 2003:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2003/P5040061.JPG&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin inside with medal&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So: why am I running the Pittsburgh Marathon again, &lt;em&gt;now&lt;/em&gt;, ten years later? What do I hope to accomplish? And how?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why&#34;&gt;Why?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;do-it-better&#34;&gt;Do it better&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2003, I ran my first marathon for a variety of reasons, and trained in certain ways, had certain expectations. I will write in depth later about that first marathon, because one reason I am running the Pittsburgh Marathon again now is to &lt;em&gt;do everything better&lt;/em&gt; this time, with the benefit of experience and new self-knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;maintain a smart pace&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;finish strong&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;avoid leg muscle cramping&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;avoid foot blistering&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;conquer the hills&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In sharp contrast to my first marathon, I do &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; plan to race this marathon as fast as I can. That blew up on me, and I do not have the time or desire to maximize my marathon performance at this point in my life. I do want to run strong, but not maximally. So I am not almost certainly not going to run faster than I did ten years ago; I am specifically expecting to run &lt;em&gt;slower&lt;/em&gt; but to have a &lt;em&gt;better&lt;/em&gt; overall experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will not be the second time I run a marathon distance; I have done that two or three times on my own while training for the &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/rachel-carson-trail-challenge/&#34;&gt;Rachel Carson Trail Challenge&lt;/a&gt; and have also run just over a marathon distance in the annual Sammy&amp;rsquo;s Birthday Run (a 6-hour ultra event) in 2006 and 2008. But those I did pretty slowly just for training and fun, in well over four hours. In the 2013 Pittsburgh Marathon, I&amp;rsquo;d like to finish close to the completely arbitrary magic number of 4:00:00. This is very low priority compared to the other goals, but it&amp;rsquo;s useful to have a little bit of ambition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;experiment&#34;&gt;Experiment&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides what I &lt;em&gt;know&lt;/em&gt; now that I didn&amp;rsquo;t, there are also things that I didn&amp;rsquo;t know then and still don&amp;rsquo;t know now, but have hypotheses about. So the experience will be an opportunity to test my hypotheses. In particular, the kind of exercise and diet I follow now different in various ways from ten years ago. I do a lot more core and strength training and less endurance training. So my main goal, in fact, is to run this marathon with relatively &lt;em&gt;low mileage&lt;/em&gt;. Instead of spending huge amounts of time and energy banging out the miles in training, I want to try ways of getting in really high-quality training that will enable me to handle the marathon distance better and gut it out through strength.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;social&#34;&gt;Social&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first Pittsburgh Marathon experience had me running all alone. I did have support as far as my sister coming to town and my friend Nathaniel watching me and cheering me on at certain points along the course, but out there, I was alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This time, I decided not to do the marathon unless I had at least a friend or two joining me. I got my office mate John to sign up (he also did the marathon over a decade ago). &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.runoverit.com/&#34;&gt;Chris&lt;/a&gt; is signed up for it, although he actually has yet to run his first marathon, which will be coming up in March. There are a bunch of others I also know who will be running. I guess when time comes, we&amp;rsquo;ll figure out how our likely paces might coincide (or not).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;it-will-be-on-my-birthday&#34;&gt;It will be on my birthday&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What can I say: it will be my very first race of any distance run &lt;em&gt;on my birthday&lt;/em&gt;. I thought it would be amusing and cool to celebrate my birthday by running the Pittsburgh Marathon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;discount&#34;&gt;Discount&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As staff at CMU, I (and my office mate John) get a &lt;a href=&#34;http://athletics.cmu.edu/fitness/fitkit2013&#34;&gt;special discount for the Pittsburgh Marathon&lt;/a&gt;. This explains why I registered today, right before the deadline!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the reduced registration fee, part of the deal is &amp;ldquo;Special access to private finish line tent with gourmet food, private massages, and more!&amp;rdquo; as well as 6 months free membership to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.steelcityrrc.org/&#34;&gt;Steel City Road Runners&lt;/a&gt;. Not bad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;update-of-2013-03-16&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-03-16)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I should note that the Steel City Road Runners was formed in 2011. John and I had in fact attended its &amp;ldquo;kick-off party&amp;rdquo; on Tuesday, September 13, 2011 where we did a free training run, but we ended up not joining the club or participating further, since we were not planning to do the Pittsburgh Marathon in 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;how&#34;&gt;How?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There isn&amp;rsquo;t actually much time before the marathon (three months), so I have to be smart about training and try to avoid setbacks. Some things I need to do:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;immediately start extending the distance of my runs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;continue core and strength training&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;keep up stair climbing and hill running&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;build up to some rigorous interval training&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;schedule long races to run in before the marathon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;cut back on various commitments in the next three months&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;removing-chess&#34;&gt;Removing chess&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve already decided on one major activity I am going to cut out: after I finish the current Tuesday night chess tournament, the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/02/04/pittsburgh-chess-club-championship-2013-round-3-attack-defense-and-sacrifices/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Chess Club Championship&lt;/a&gt;, I will take a break and not play in any more Tuesday night chess tournaments until possibly the fall (in summer I&amp;rsquo;d rather be playing outside in the sun rather than hunched over a chess board indoors!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Time and energy are limited. We can&amp;rsquo;t do everything all the time. In fact, as things are, I have not even been able to play in the monthly &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pitt.edu/~schach/ChessPA/ChessLeague/wpapcl.htm&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Chess League&lt;/a&gt; team matches since &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/11/11/pittsburgh-chess-league-round-3-back-to-chess-after-a-month-off/&#34;&gt;November&lt;/a&gt;: in December I was occupied with &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/02/oblivion-obsession-time-to-start-playing-melodica/&#34;&gt;music rehearsal&lt;/a&gt;, and just now in January I was coming off a hard week during which I was &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/25/notes-on-exercising-while-sick-or-tired/&#34;&gt;sick and overbooked&lt;/a&gt;. I do hope to make it to the February team match.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m doing well in the Pittsburgh Chess Club Championship so far, with a perfect score in my first three rounds, so I hope I&amp;rsquo;ll be able to say goodbye while winning it after another three rounds!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;footwear&#34;&gt;Footwear&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost certainly I will wear my &lt;em&gt;worn-out and holey&lt;/em&gt; pair of &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/08/28/five-reasons-we-just-stocked-up-on-vibram-fivefingers-kso-trek-shoes/&#34;&gt;Vibram FiveFingers KSO Trek shoes&lt;/a&gt;. The reason is that I have &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; been blistered wearing these shoes, no matter the distance. The leather is really comfortable for me. And I will wear the worn-out pair rather than a newer pair because on the roads, I don&amp;rsquo;t want the deeply lugged outsoles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other alternative I thought about was wearing huaraches such as my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/30/running-my-10th-great-race-10k-obscene-but-in-a-good-way/&#34;&gt;Xero Shoes that I wore in the Great Race 10K&lt;/a&gt;. I will do some experiments in the spring running much longer distances than 10K in huaraches, but I am currently very skeptical about running an entire marathon in them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m excited to be back for marathon running. I hope to have a stimulating adventure in the next three months as I train for and participate in the 2013 Pittsburgh Marathon!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-02-24&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-02-24)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/02/24/2013-pittsburgh-marathon-training-progress-since-signing-up-three-weeks-ago/&#34;&gt;A progress report describes setbacks to overcome.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The inaugural Liberty Mile: a review of Pittsburgh&#39;s first road mile race, a great community event</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/08/17/the-inaugural-liberty-mile-a-review-of-pittsburghs-first-road-mile-race/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Aug 2012 21:44:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/08/17/the-inaugural-liberty-mile-a-review-of-pittsburghs-first-road-mile-race/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/liberty-mile-2012.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin&amp;#39;s race number and Bikila LS shoes&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Tonight I was really excited to race in, and also watch, the inaugural &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.libertymile.org/&#34;&gt;GNC Live Well Liberty Mile&lt;/a&gt;, a road race that runs along Liberty Avenue in Pittsburgh, starting from the Strip District and ending downtown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s about time Pittsburgh had a road mile race! Pittsburgh already has the wonderful&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://rungreatrace.com/&#34;&gt;Great Race&lt;/a&gt;, which &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/25/blistered-but-blissful-in-the-burgh/&#34;&gt;I ran for my ninth time last year&lt;/a&gt; and will run for my tenth time this year (good think I pre-registered early, because today it &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburgh.cbslocal.com/2012/08/17/2012-great-race-officially-sold-out/&#34;&gt;already sold out!!&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pittsburghmarathon.com/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Marathon&lt;/a&gt;, which I&amp;rsquo;ve run once.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope this event is here to stay. Here&amp;rsquo;s my report on the event as both a runner and a spectator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-history-in-the-mile&#34;&gt;My history in the mile&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve run a mile race only twice before in my life, and that was on the track at Carnegie Mellon University. A decade ago, in June 2002, I ran in my first track mile, the Pittsylvania Mile on that track, and did it in 6:22. I could have run faster, but because of total inexperience, went out way too fast for the first quarter, doing it in 1:22, and paying the price in the other laps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following year, 2003, in probably my peak condition in my life, I improved, doing the Pittsylvania Mile in 6:10. I still went out too fast, in 1:26, had no sense of rhythm, slowed down a lot to try to compensate for going out too fast, then had too much energy at the end, which was wasted. Again, I had not trained for the mile distance at all, but happened to be in my peak condition anyway just because I was still conditioned from my intense training for the Pittsburgh Marathon that I had just done in May (my lifetime personal best in the 5K of 20:37 was achieved just two weeks after the Pittsburgh Marathon).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I never broke a 6-minute mile during my peak.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That was the last timed mile I ever ran, until tonight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;preparation&#34;&gt;Preparation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, I wasn&amp;rsquo;t prepared for the mile at all. Apart from not having run much because of a non-running injury to my left leg that happened a month ago (from which I have fully recovered), I have just come back from a week of unexpected travel and am still kind of recovering from that. And no speed work to speak of in the past month, other than a few random sprints (which I do for general physical conditioning when I don&amp;rsquo;t do much else).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had no idea what &amp;ldquo;mile pace&amp;rdquo; feels like. I just figured I would run a bit faster than 5K pace (which I always have a reasonable feel for).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hoped to finish somewhere near 6:30.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;dr-vonda-wright&#34;&gt;Dr. Vonda Wright&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://vondawright.com/images/stories/vonda-at-work.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Vonda Wright&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I bumped into &lt;a href=&#34;http://vondawright.com/&#34;&gt;Dr. Vonda Wright&lt;/a&gt; while heading toward the start line, and thanked her for her support of those of us who care about maintaining our health as we get older. I want to plug her great work in promoting lifetime fitness, especially for those over 40. She has written a book &lt;a href=&#34;http://vondawright.com/index.php?option=com_content&amp;amp;view=article&amp;amp;id=62&amp;amp;Itemid=83&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Fitness After 40&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; which is pretty good and has a lot of scientifically-backed tips on remaining strong and vital and even reversing what used to be considered &amp;ldquo;normal aging&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I heard about Dr. Wright from a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/01/20/cmu-fitness-challenge-keynote-lecture-by-vonda-wright-stay-strong-at-any-age/&#34;&gt;CMU &amp;ldquo;healthy campus week&amp;rdquo; talk she gave this January&lt;/a&gt;. Even though I had already known some of what she advocated, I was impressed that she summarized well the whole gamut of what we now know to be effective ways to increase strength and flexibility and avoid injury. Again, I recommend her books to anyone of any age who wants to be smart about diet and exercise and more than that, a whole philosophical approach to living in general.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-race-in-waves&#34;&gt;The race, in waves&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The race was held in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.libertymile.org/Race-Waves.asp&#34;&gt;waves separated by ten or twenty minutes&lt;/a&gt;. This is obviously necessary because of the variation in people&amp;rsquo;s speed. The slower, open waves were held first, and the elite racers were in the final waves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;early-waves&#34;&gt;Early waves&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I arrived to pick up my race number when the first wave was already in progress. There was a bit of confusion in the first two waves because a good number of people arrived late or were unclear about when to run, and therefore missed the first wave. Most of these seemed to be kids. By the way, it was great to see so many kids at the Liberty Mile. Running a 5K (3.1-mile) race can be daunting for a kid, but a single mile is surely a great introduction to many kids (and adults too!) to the joy of running. I think it is really great that the Liberty Mile is not just an elite race, but also a race anyone can participate in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;my-race-in-the-masters-wave&#34;&gt;My race, in the Masters wave&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Masters &amp;ldquo;Winning at 40+&amp;rdquo; wave was the first qualification-required wave.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ran in this serious, competitive wave, not one of the open waves, because I easily qualified to run in this wave, whose requirement was proof of ability to run an 8-minute mile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lining up, I saw a lot of really fit-looking people in this wave, many of whom were clearly well over 40. In any case, anyone who looked anywhere near my age (42) was obviously going to kick my butt all the way to the moon. There was no chance for an age-group prize for me today! No problem: as a non-elite racer, I don&amp;rsquo;t race for prizes, but just to do the best that I can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ended up running &lt;a href=&#34;http://runhigh.com/2012RESULTS/R081712AD.html&#34;&gt;6:38.8&lt;/a&gt;, good for 26th place out of 27 in my age group, ha! I was disappointed that I didn&amp;rsquo;t make 6:30 as I had originally hoped when I signed up a month ago, but that&amp;rsquo;s OK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the first quarter, I ran 1:29; oops, went out too fast yet again! &lt;strong&gt;I hereby pledge that before the next mile race I run, I will actually train and learn not to go out too fast.&lt;/strong&gt; There is no excuse for running three mile races going out too fast. I don&amp;rsquo;t go out too fast in 5K or longer distances, after all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the second and third quarters, 1:46 and 1:46 showed that I had gone out too fast. I did save something for the sprint finish, however, and did the final quarter in 1:38.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A serious and unexpected problem I had while running this race was that my mouth got very dry and I had trouble breathing as a result. It was pretty weird. I don&amp;rsquo;t exactly remember this in my mile races from a decade ago. I did hydrate considerably before the race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, of course, as I do in 5K races, I felt like puking during the final quarter, and my arms were getting tingly and losing sensation. It&amp;rsquo;s just what happens to me in the final push. I believe there is no way to avoid feeling like puking if I&amp;rsquo;m running as hard as I can, but I have a feeling that the problem with my arms has to do with my tightening up (rather than relaxing) and flailing around. I plan to try to fix that for my next races this month and next month; what is required, clearly, is disciplined speed work, which is something I have not done in years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;enjoying-being-a-spectator&#34;&gt;Enjoying being a spectator&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The really cool thing about a mile race held in waves is that you get to be a spectator for the remaining waves after you&amp;rsquo;re done. In a 5K race or longer, there aren&amp;rsquo;t any heats and you never get to be a spectator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was wowed watching the &amp;ldquo;Unstoppable&amp;rdquo; under-40 wave whose qualification time was running faster than 6:00. Watching good, fast running is a real pleasure to me, like watching skilled dancers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also a treat was getting to watch the female elite wave and male elite wave. These &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/27/why-i-do-not-watch-the-olympics-any-more/&#34;&gt;Olympic&lt;/a&gt;-caliber runners looked so elegant with their long, powerful strides.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-shoes&#34;&gt;My shoes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d been considering running a race soon wearing my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/26/walking-and-running-in-invisible-shoes-a-review/&#34;&gt;Invisible Shoes huaraches&lt;/a&gt;, but without testing them out with speed work, I&amp;rsquo;m not ready to go there yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I wore the shoes I&amp;rsquo;ve been &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/23/happiness-is-finishing-39th-of-43-men-in-a-race/&#34;&gt;road racing in for almost a full year now&lt;/a&gt;, the Vibram FiveFingers Bikila LS. They worked out just fine. I didn&amp;rsquo;t get blistered because it was cool and it was only a mile. Next month I&amp;rsquo;ll see whether I get blistered in the Great Race &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/25/blistered-but-blissful-in-the-burgh/&#34;&gt;the way I did last year&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;race-organization&#34;&gt;Race organization&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought the race was pretty well-organized, especially given that this was the first time such a race has been held in Pittsburgh. Thanks go to the sponsors, the timers, the announcers, the volunteers who handed out race numbers and stocked water and bagels at the finish line and handed out goodie bags and T-shirts, the police officers who closed the roads and lanes where necessary and directed traffic and kept Liberty Avenue clear, the spectators who cheered, the providers of the many port-a-johns near the start line, the &lt;a href=&#34;http://bringbackthemile.com/news/detail/Miller_and_Kampf_Win_GNC_Live_Well_Liberty_Mile&#34;&gt;elite runners who put on a display of amazing running&lt;/a&gt;. Everyone without question was helpful and friendly. The whole experience was just wonderful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The inaugural GNC Live Well Liberty Mile was a great event. I hope it is the beginning of a Pittsburgh tradition that, like the Great Race and the Pittsburgh Marathon, will continue for years and decades to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-08-09&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-08-09)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/08/09/getting-up-when-reality-punches-you-in-the-face-running-the-second-liberty-mile-in-pittsburgh/&#34;&gt;I ran the second Liberty Mile a year later.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Flute versus recorder: why do I play both?</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/11/17/flute-versus-recorder/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Nov 2011 22:35:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/11/17/flute-versus-recorder/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A week ago, I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/09/taking-up-flute-again-after-decades/&#34;&gt;started playing the flute again after decades&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I started playing &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/recorder/&#34;&gt;recorder&lt;/a&gt; in February, and made it my main instrument, I am torn by the fact that I have been playing it every other day now rather than every day, and playing flute every other day. It feels weird dividing my attention in this way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suppose it&amp;rsquo;s time to talk more about why I started playing recorder in the first place, and why I am back to flute now (in addition).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-appeal-of-the-recorder&#34;&gt;The appeal of the recorder&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;social&#34;&gt;Social&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I took up recorder in large part because of the knowledge that there was a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.andrew.cmu.edu/user/lukas/pcars/Welcome.html&#34;&gt;local branch of the American Recorder Society&lt;/a&gt; here in Pittsburgh, which I joined just shortly after beginning to play the alto recorder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s much easier to keep a hobby going seriously when one is not pursuing it alone. That is true even for someone as self-motivated and driven as I often am (I trained for and ran my first marathon all by myself and alone, not with any friend or running club). There are many reasons for this. One is that it is easy to get discouraged, and having emotional support can prevent giving up prematurely. Another is that in addition to emotional support, people can give technical support as well: improving my recorder playing technique in the first few months would have been impossible without personal feedback. Yet another reason is that goals can become much more concrete: to equal the ability of an admired peer, or to be able to play without too much embarrassment in an ensemble or in a particular concert (if one is actually performing in public at all).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;inexpensive&#34;&gt;Inexpensive&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Decent plastic recorders from Yamaha are quite inexpensive compared to a lot of more modern instruments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;versatile&#34;&gt;Versatile&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I always knew that there was the opportunity to play many different recorders, because I actually started out with soprano briefly before going to alto, and then I eventually acquired also a tenor, bass, and sopranino. It&amp;rsquo;s a great feeling knowing that by learning one instrument, one can play several others with relatively minor changes in technique.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;simplicity&#34;&gt;Simplicity&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is easy to get started on recorder. The breath pressure required is low, there is no embouchure to develop, no reeds, the basic fingerings are intuitive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;anachronistic&#34;&gt;Anachronistic&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One important element of the appeal of the recorder is that it is an anachronism: to embrace it today entails at least some &amp;ldquo;rebellious&amp;rdquo; mindset that declares that technology is not everything, that there is value in the past, in more primitive instruments; and by association, that there is value in old music of the 17th century and earlier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some recorder (and other early instrument) enthusiasts actually adopt what I think of as an extreme version of this mindset, being very negative about all music after Bach, for example. Interestingly, many such enthusiasts are fans of the avant garde and simply reject the Western music from between Bach and the 20th century, or some similar time frame.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I myself don&amp;rsquo;t subscribe to any such ideology. I took up recorder while actually being a stranger to almost all music before Bach. I took up recorder in part because I was seeking &lt;em&gt;novelty&lt;/em&gt; in the past, rather than because I already enjoyed early music and was seeking comfort there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;quiet&#34;&gt;Quiet&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The recorder is a relatively quiet instrument. This can be a virtue when one does not have a soundproof home or soundproof room in the home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-appeal-of-the-modern-flute&#34;&gt;The appeal of the modern flute&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is of course easier to list the reasons for enjoying the modern flute. I&amp;rsquo;ll juxtapose them with reasons for &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; enjoying the recorder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;popular&#34;&gt;Popular&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The modern flute is popular. There is a huge repertoire of music written specifically for it, or arranged for it. A lot of people &lt;em&gt;love&lt;/em&gt; the sound.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By contrast, a lot of people &lt;em&gt;hate&lt;/em&gt; the sound of the recorder (I won&amp;rsquo;t name any names, but a large number of people I personally know do not like the recorder and eagerly tell me that). Recorder music is not as easy to come by or popular. It is easy to pick up a flute and play in an orchestra or a chamber music ensemble or marching band, or jam with friends playing jazz or salsa or tango.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My desire to play an instrument in the widest possible settings has forced me to look back to modern instruments. I&amp;rsquo;m not interested in only playing early music with early music devotees; I want to participate in a lot of other music also.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;flexible&#34;&gt;Flexible&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s face it, the flute has a much larger range than the recorder, can be played with much more dynamics, control of tone, etc. The ability to really &lt;em&gt;sing&lt;/em&gt; with an instrument is what I miss most when playing the recorder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I said earlier that the recorder is an easy instrument to start playing. But it is surprisingly difficult to play &lt;em&gt;well&lt;/em&gt;. There are subtleties in playing notes in tune, because there is no embouchure to adjust. Legato is harder. Interestingly, of course, these difficulties are not entirely negative. I have quite enjoyed the focus, in recorder playing, on rhythmic awareness, full range of articulation (versus legato). Nevertheless, the flute must be considered more flexible. There is no reason one cannot play with a recorder-induced sensitivity on the flute as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;baroque-flute&#34;&gt;Baroque flute?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One idea that I entertained a couple of months ago was that of taking up the Baroque flute, the wooden flute from the 17th century that was the predecessor to the modern flute. I first encountered the Baroque flute when taking a music class at CMU from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.stephenschultz.net/&#34;&gt;Stephen Schultz&lt;/a&gt;, a virtuoso performer on the Baroque flute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have shelved the idea of trying the Baroque, for several reasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cost was one. Why buy a Baroque flute when I already have a modern one?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another was, where would I actually play a Baroque flute, other than just with specific people who I know are into early musical instruments (such as Baroque violin, harpsichord)?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s still possible that at some point in my life, I&amp;rsquo;ll try out Baroque flute, but it can wait.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;daniel-waitzman-from-recorder-to-flute&#34;&gt;Daniel Waitzman, from recorder to flute&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Daniel Waitzman was a prodigy on recorder and then on Baroque flute as well. I found a couple of recorder technique and practice music books by him at the local library. He wrote a fascinating article, &lt;a href=&#34;http://home.sprynet.com/~danwaitz/memoir.htm&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Up from authenticity, or how i learned to love the metal flute: a personal memoir&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, which I found very inspiring, and highly recommend to anyone who is passionate about early instruments and music. He touches upon some of the points I only mentioned above in passing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not giving up recorder, but have returned to flute in a strange, roundabout way. We&amp;rsquo;ll see how far I continue with the flute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2011-11-30&#34;&gt;(Update of 2011-11-30)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that just days after I wrote this blog post, I reconsidered and &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/30/bought-a-baroque-flute/&#34;&gt;decided to buy a Baroque flute&lt;/a&gt;!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2012-10-30&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-10-30)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, I would end up spending the summer months of 2012 practicing almost exclusively the Baroque flute, including going to a music camp in which I took a class devoted to Baroque flute technique.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>