<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Ernesto Nazareth on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/ernesto-nazareth/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Ernesto Nazareth on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/ernesto-nazareth/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Accidentally discovering and performing some music by Brazilian composer Ernesto Nazareth: Coração que Sente</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/12/29/accidentally-discovering-and-performing-some-music-by-brazilian-composer-ernesto-nazareth-cora%C3%A7%C3%A3o-que-sente/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Dec 2015 23:05:10 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/12/29/accidentally-discovering-and-performing-some-music-by-brazilian-composer-ernesto-nazareth-cora%C3%A7%C3%A3o-que-sente/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In November, I fell in love with some music I accidentally discovered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What happened was that I was looking for some music for &lt;em&gt;flute&lt;/em&gt; and
&lt;em&gt;guitar&lt;/em&gt; to play, with me on flute and one of my friends on guitar, and
I did a simple search in the
&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/30/free-to-the-people-since-1895/&#34;&gt;local library&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://librarycatalog.einetwork.net/&#34;&gt;online catalog&lt;/a&gt;, and at the top
sorted by date was
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.halleonard.com/product/viewproduct.action?itemid=49044167&amp;amp;&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Brazilian folk tunes for flute and guitar&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;,
which came with a CD of sample performance tracks,
so I picked it up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What followed was a series of explorations that resulted in unexpected
changes in my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;exploring-the-brazilian-music-in-the-score-book&#34;&gt;Exploring the Brazilian music in the score book&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I listened to some tracks on the CD of this book of arrangements and
found the music (Brazilian polkas, tangos, waltzes) really
enchanting. Most of the music was by a composer
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ernesto_Nazareth&#34;&gt;Ernesto Nazareth&lt;/a&gt;,
who lived 1863-1934. I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t call this music &amp;ldquo;folk tunes&amp;rdquo;: it&amp;rsquo;s
a sophisticated combination of popular and classical styles using
catchy dance rhythms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m a real sucker for waltzes, so at first I thought I would pick one
of the beautiful waltzes to choose to suggest to play with a partner
on guitar. It came down to &amp;ldquo;Confidências&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;Coração que Sente&amp;rdquo;
(English translation: &amp;ldquo;Heart that Feels&amp;rdquo;). The
latter was much easier and shorter, as I learned while sight reading
through it with the CD track, so I thought I was done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;finding-astounding-performances-of-coração-que-sente-on-youtube&#34;&gt;Finding astounding performances of &amp;ldquo;Coração que Sente&amp;rdquo; on YouTube&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking for performances of the piece on YouTube to get an idea of
how people play it, I immediately entered a strange new world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, I learned that the original music was for
&lt;em&gt;piano&lt;/em&gt;. OK. Then, while listening to and/or watching a dozen or so
videos of performances of this piece (OK, I was obsessed), I found a
huge variety of interpretations, and some of them spoke to me more
than others. Some I found light and boring. The ones that interested
me were the ones that were extremely intense and probing. You might
think this music was just fluff, but I found a dark undercurrent
behind it that spoke to me, in that its different sections (the piece
is roughly in rondo form) present clear emotional contrasts, with
longing, melancholy, and manic excitement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;arthur-moreira-lima&#34;&gt;Arthur Moreira Lima&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A very intense performance I found was by a pianist named
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arthur_Moreira_Lima&#34;&gt;Arthur Moreira Lima&lt;/a&gt;
in 1975, used after the fact as soundtrack on YouTube for a silent
film using footage from 1929. What an odd pairing!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lima goes all out in Romantic expressiveness, with extensive rubato
and dynamic and rhythmic flexibility. It was completely different from
the relatively straight, danceable version on the flute/guitar CD
demo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have to listen to his performance (ignore the film or watch it, as
you wish):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Mmjt8RrfXtA&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;joão-carlos-assis-brasil&#34;&gt;João Carlos Assis Brasil&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even more extreme than Lima was this weird guy João Carlos Assis
Brasil, who is apparently so unknown in the English-speaking world
that Wikipedia doesn&amp;rsquo;t have an entry on him, although I found this
random
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bach-cantatas.com/Bio/Assis-Brasil-Joao-Carlos.htm&#34;&gt;pieced-together bio&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His live performance here from 2013 is the single most extreme, yet
deepest, interpretation of this waltz I found (he adds his own
ornamentation). I was deeply moved by it. (Warning, bad sound
quality.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/iG_o94sU1tE&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;other-good-performances&#34;&gt;Other good performances&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://pt.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fernanda_Chaves_Canaud&#34;&gt;Fernanda Canaud&lt;/a&gt;,
with a very expressive performance (including her own extensive
embellishments), uses drastic changes in articulation and tempo for
contrast. I particularly liked how naturally she seemed to express her
personality through the piece:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/-DfOYvNCaqk&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://pt.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maria_Teresa_Madeira&#34;&gt;Maria Theresa Madeira&lt;/a&gt;
captures well the moods of the different sections of the piece; I
really like the rhythmic alertness and drive throughout:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/eeztzLsF6Cc&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some random YouTube guy named Ilton, playing a really crappy upright
piano, but with amazing rhythmic expression that I totally love (if he
played this on a good piano, I would consider his interpretation one
of my favorites, period):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/b-gYk_YUoIM&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://lucianoalves.com.br/&#34;&gt;Luciano Alves&lt;/a&gt;, 2013, in an elegant
performance:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/y8LchR8Mi5Y&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://pt.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marcelo_Bratke&#34;&gt;Marcelo Bratke&lt;/a&gt; in a
relaxed, easygoing, dream interpretation with a lilt (but after all
the intense interpretations, I find this tame, I confess):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Pn5vYhfQYHs&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-performance-that-made-me-decide-to-learn-and-play-the-piece&#34;&gt;The performance that made me decide to learn and play the piece&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I spent a lot of time listening to and watching performances of the
piece, but one performance was the one that made me decide to go learn
and play the piece! It was this one by some random guy Marcelo Chiarella:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/QaQL9VlJy8s&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why? Because I could &lt;em&gt;relate to&lt;/em&gt; his playing:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;He wasn&amp;rsquo;t some famous pro pianist, as far as I could tell.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The sound quality was good and the recording was as though I were
standing right there, made me feel like I was in his home, and
nobody else there.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I could see his hands up close.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I liked various things he did with expression (especially when he
&lt;em&gt;wasn&amp;rsquo;t&lt;/em&gt; pedaling).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I knew that I could be much more expressive and personal
(remember, the title in English translation is &amp;ldquo;Heart that feels&amp;rdquo;)
while playing this piece &lt;em&gt;solo&lt;/em&gt;, on piano, than in a flute/guitar
duet. So I decided to go for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;finding-an-official-free-score&#34;&gt;Finding an official free score&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had to find a score. Luckily, it turned out that there was some
big
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ernestonazareth150anos.com.br/&#34;&gt;150-year anniversary celebration for Ernesto Nazareth&lt;/a&gt;
in 2013, and I found an official &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ernestonazareth150anos.com.br/files/uploads/work_elements/work_43/coracao_que_sente_piano.pdf&#34;&gt;free PDF score&lt;/a&gt; on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ernestonazareth150anos.com.br/works/view/43&#34;&gt;page for the piece&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That page also had a story about the title of the piece and why it was
composed. It was in Portuguese, so I tried with the help of Google
Translate to translate it (I only studied Portuguese for several weeks
many years ago), and pieced together (I hope I didn&amp;rsquo;t get this too
wrong) that Nazareth dedicated it to a student of his, Gabriella
Crauz, who had showed great emotion as Nazareth described the last
days of a dying nephew, as though she had been there herself
experiencing what he experienced as he saw the sights in the city one
last time. (If you know Portuguese, please correct me if I got the
story wrong.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This story only added to the sense I already had that this seemingly
simple piece hid a depth of emotion that some performers already
revealed for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-performance-of-coração-que-sente&#34;&gt;My performance of &amp;ldquo;Coração que Sente&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I started working on the piece, I had to decide where and when to
perform it. It turned out that I learned that friends who mean a lot
to me decided to move. This was really tough news to me, and they have
always invited me and Abby to their December holiday party, where I
play music, so I decided that I was going to perform the piece at
their (now farewell) party and openly dedicate my performance to them,
because they are human beings of deep feeling, hence &amp;ldquo;Heart that
feels&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I performed the piece at the party the day after Christmas. In my
nervousness, I completely lost my train of thought a couple of times
and botched things up inexplicably (I had gone through the piece with
no errors so many times at home), but I made it through, and my
gesture was appreciated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I then decided to quickly record myself at home soon after (and still
botched some things up), so here I am. This is for Henry and Gina:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34;
src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/VBOS9btMUPI&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;
allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;other-music-by-ernesto-nazareth&#34;&gt;Other music by Ernesto Nazareth&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spent all this time talking about just one piece by Nazareth, but he
wrote much more, and more substantial pieces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I totally love Fernanda Canaud&amp;rsquo;s performance of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ernestonazareth150anos.com.br/works/view/133&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Batuque&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, &amp;ldquo;Coração
que Sente&amp;rdquo;, and
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ernestonazareth150anos.com.br/works/view/136&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Odeon&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;
(the performance of &amp;ldquo;Coração que Sente&amp;rdquo; is very different from the one
I posted above: more inward, refined, beautiful rather than super-dramatic):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/U6WaAgRWqaw&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is Nazareth playing his own pieces in recordings from 1912-1930:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/eZS3bDNJEUY&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a one-hour special documentary video &amp;ldquo;Nazareth Revisitado&amp;rdquo;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/TJAT3pJJR6M&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-note-on-the-english-language-oriented-web&#34;&gt;A note on the English-language-oriented Web&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found a whole world of music and musicians that barely register in
the English-language-oriented part of the Web. Most of what I found
when trying to look up Nazareth or various Brazilian pianists was in
Portuguese. So it&amp;rsquo;s been really humbling to remember that many in the
English-speaking world might not even know about all these Brazilian
composers and musicians who are not big enough stars to warrant
international fame.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am grateful for accidentally discovering an entire world of
Brazilian music and performers of it through my search in the local
library catalog for music to play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am grateful for friends who inspire me by their examples as human
beings of genuine and great feeling.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>