<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Orchestra on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/orchestra/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Orchestra on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/orchestra/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Quitting the CMU All-University Orchestra: one of the hardest decisions in my life</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/03/12/quitting-the-cmu-all-university-orchestra-one-of-the-hardest-decisions-in-my-life/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Mar 2012 22:45:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/03/12/quitting-the-cmu-all-university-orchestra-one-of-the-hardest-decisions-in-my-life/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s the Monday after what would have been the regular Sunday evening CMU All-University Orchestra rehearsal, except that there was no rehearsal because of Spring Break.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surprise (or not)!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have decided to immediately &lt;em&gt;quit&lt;/em&gt; the CMU AUO that I had &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/02/01/joining-an-orchestra-learning-in-the-face-of-terror/&#34;&gt;just joined less than two months ago&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have already told everyone that I&amp;rsquo;m quitting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t like quitting. I don&amp;rsquo;t like being a quitter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what&amp;rsquo;s the story? And what next?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;orchestra-morale-problems&#34;&gt;Orchestra morale problems&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Five days ago, I reported on &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/07/flute-taking-a-break-while-clarifying-my-goals/&#34;&gt;problems in the orchestra&lt;/a&gt; and deciding that I would probably quit the orchestra after the spring term is over. The memories of that have lingered in my mind. And my relief yesterday at not having rehearsal was a real message to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2012-03-21&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-03-21)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maria just sent the mailing list (which I&amp;rsquo;m still on despite having quit the orchestra) an email saying, &amp;ldquo;It seems that over spring break we may have lost much of what we did in the first portion of the semester.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No kidding. As I had observed earlier, people clearly just weren&amp;rsquo;t taking practice seriously. They probably didn&amp;rsquo;t touch their instruments when they went on spring break. I&amp;rsquo;m so glad I quit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;personal-musical-goals&#34;&gt;Personal musical goals&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past couple of days while off the hook on orchestral practice, I had an opportunity to think about &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/10/flute-loving-it-again/&#34;&gt;what I actually love about music, and what role I want it to play in my life&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;a-chance-opportunity&#34;&gt;A chance opportunity&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that Abby and I have just been invited to a St. Patrick&amp;rsquo;s Day party by Henry, whose &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/01/27/a-new-friends-very-musical-birthday-party-changed-my-life/&#34;&gt;birthday party less than two months ago&lt;/a&gt; had so moved me musically (and right after I had joined the AUO). I was so eager to attend that I asked Henry whether I should bring a tin whistle and play some Irish music, and he said, sure! I had promised myself after his birthday party that if we were ever invited to a party by him, I would play music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;brute-reality&#34;&gt;Brute reality&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, I can no longer deny the reality: being in an orchestra is &lt;em&gt;completely contrary&lt;/em&gt; to the kind of musical life I actually enjoy and want. I need to play music of my choice, I want to improvise, I want to play in small groups. The task of mastering some difficult flute parts in a big orchestral work and being a tiny part of a performance, &lt;em&gt;does not appeal to me at all&lt;/em&gt;, even if I could do it well (which I currently cannot at all).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a concrete example: I could spend my time this week slogging away at AUO music practice, or I could be learning some tunes on tin whistle so that I can play them on Saturday at Henry&amp;rsquo;s party and have a blast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s no comparison, whether in the short term or in the long term.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But emotionally, it&amp;rsquo;s just tough to quit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-did-i-really-ever-hope-to-get-out-of-orchestra&#34;&gt;What did I really ever hope to get out of orchestra?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think part of me hoped that somehow, being in an orchestra was a standard rite of passage that a &amp;ldquo;serious&amp;rdquo; musician should do. When I was a kid, I was kind of envious that classmates joined the school orchestra, while I remained out of music entirely. My younger sister played violin in various orchestras in middle school and in high school and college.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But now it occurs to me that not much of what I could get out of orchestra would help me with my real musical goals anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-art-of-quitting&#34;&gt;The art of quitting&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a policy of never just &lt;em&gt;quitting&lt;/em&gt; something, but &lt;em&gt;replacing&lt;/em&gt; the void instead. &lt;em&gt;Quitting&lt;/em&gt; is negative. &lt;em&gt;Replacing&lt;/em&gt; is positive. In my case, quitting orchestra frees up a considerable amount of time to work toward my real musical goals. Instead of fruitlessly working on difficult flute parts that are currently beyond my capabilities, and beyond my interests, I can focus on gradually improving at the music I do want to play, and building the technique necessary, without arbitrary deadlines like some big concert.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;resources&#34;&gt;Resources&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the United States, we are constantly bombarded with messages in the media and general culture not to be a &amp;ldquo;quitter&amp;rdquo;. And I got that a lot from my parents (who came from Taiwan) when I was a kid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My current point of view: &lt;em&gt;not learning to be an effective quitter was the single worst mistake of my first decades in life&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some articles that really resonated with me about the benefits of quitting correctly:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.projecthappilyeverafter.com/2009/03/sometimes-its-better-to-be-a-quitter/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Sometimes it&amp;rsquo;s better to be a quitter&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cormackcarr.com/2009/12/05/how-to-be-a-quitter/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;How to be a quitter&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s never easy for me to quit something. Part of me always feels like I failed, wasn&amp;rsquo;t good enough, wasn&amp;rsquo;t courageous enough, or something like that. Maybe sometimes that is actually true. But other times, it clearly is not. All signs point to quitting orchestra as the best thing I can do now for my flute playing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-is-your-own-relationship-to-quitting&#34;&gt;What is your own relationship to quitting?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is your gut reaction when hearing about someone quitting (like me just now), or when considering quitting something yourself? Is your &lt;em&gt;gut reaction&lt;/em&gt; one of disdain and shame, or of liberation? Is this a result of your upbringing, or the nature of your relationships with peers? Is it a deliberate rational philosophical position? Or is primarily emotional, based on either moral sentiment or ego?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When was the last time you quit and felt &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt; about it? When was the last time you quit and felt &lt;em&gt;bad&lt;/em&gt; about it? When was the last time you quit and &lt;em&gt;at the time&lt;/em&gt; felt one way, but later felt you had made the wrong decision?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Flute: loving it again, remembering why I dance, and how I met my wife!</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/03/10/flute-loving-it-again/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Mar 2012 21:28:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/03/10/flute-loving-it-again/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, after four days of &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/07/flute-taking-a-break-while-clarifying-my-goals&#34;&gt;not even touching my (modern) flute&lt;/a&gt; and having spent the time having fun with my Baroque flute instead, I felt the urge to return to the modern flute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still have not regained the inclination to continue working on the orchestra music I still have to improve a lot on in the coming week, but I rediscovered the joy of simply playing my instrument.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;sound-intonation&#34;&gt;Sound, intonation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The perpetual challenges of getting clean sounds and accurate pitches on the Baroque flute in the past four days have given me an increased appreciation for the modern flute. I picked it up and spent time just trying to make beautiful sounds. Freed from the stress of orchestra practice, I felt much more relaxed on the instrument than I have for a while now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To my surprise (but not really), I have improved considerably on the flute after not playing it for four days. I really needed a break, a consolidation of lessons learned. My production of tones is much improved, and high notes are squeaking less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;music-for-dance&#34;&gt;Music for dance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing I&amp;rsquo;ve truly come to realize is that I particularly enjoy playing rhythmic music suitable for dancing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, every time I attend a dance, and there is live music, I experience a strange internal conflict: I do like to dance, but sometimes, I&amp;rsquo;d rather be on the other side of the dance floor, being the musical performer! The &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; time I&amp;rsquo;ve been on the other side has been at last year&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburghcontra.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Contras and Squares&lt;/a&gt; Holiday Ball.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most recent instance of my wishing I could sometimes stop dancing and just join the musicians has been at the local &lt;a href=&#34;http://coalcountry.org/frenchdance.html&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh French dance workshop and social&lt;/a&gt;, where we&amp;rsquo;ve had live piano, fiddle, and of course, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~gdyke/&#34;&gt;Gregory&lt;/a&gt; on his Irish flute. I wonder whether at some point I might be qualified to play for the event, using either my modern flute or Baroque flute. (By the way, it was held again today, but unfortunately, Abby and I chose not to go because we had too many things to do this weekend.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;remembering-dancing&#34;&gt;Remembering dancing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday I spent time playing along to a score/CD set I&amp;rsquo;ve mentioned before, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/World-Music-Cuba-Flute-play-along/dp/3702465804&#34;&gt;World Music Cuba&lt;/a&gt;. While playing the bolero, cha cha, and mambo pieces in particular, I felt I was returning &amp;ldquo;home&amp;rdquo; in many ways. This was among the first music I heard and saw people dancing to when I was curious and visited the &lt;a href=&#34;http://cmubdc.org/&#34;&gt;CMU Ballroom Dance Club&lt;/a&gt; in 2000, and fell in love with, and learned to dance to. I also played along to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Play-along-Argentina-Flute-World-Music/dp/3702465871&#34;&gt;World Music Argentina&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;some-photos-of-my-ballroom-dance-days&#34;&gt;Some photos of my ballroom dance days&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some photos of me dancing in 2002 with my last dance partner, Amy, before I quit competitive ballroom dancing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here we are at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dcdancesportinferno.com/&#34;&gt;DC DanceSport Inferno&lt;/a&gt; in 2002 doing a hockey stick in international rumba:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/ballroom/dcdi-2002-hockey-stick.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Amy and Franklin at DCDI 2002 in rumba&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And here were are at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://comp.cornelldancesport.org/&#34;&gt;Cornell DanceSport Classic&lt;/a&gt; in 2002 in cha cha, rumba, and tango:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/ballroom/cornell-2002-new-yorker.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Amy and Franklin at Cornell 2002 in cha cha&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/ballroom/cornell-2002-hockey-stick.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Amy and Franklin at Cornell 2002 in rumba&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/ballroom/cornell-2002-tango-promenade.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Amy and Franklin at Cornell 2002 in tango&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;dancing-with-abby&#34;&gt;Dancing with Abby&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But never mind the ballroom dance days. It was through salsa dancing that I met my wife!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;how-i-met-abby&#34;&gt;How I met Abby&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was through dancing that I met Abby in the first place. After quitting dancing in 2003, I never danced again until late 2006, when my friend Jon told me he had recently started salsa dancing (because of a girlfriend who got him into it) and invited me to join him at a free outdoors dance, and I went. Then as I re-entered the Pittsburgh salsa dance scene, I kept running into Abby.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;some-photos-of-us-dancing-salsa&#34;&gt;Some photos of us dancing salsa&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are not many photos of Abby dancing with me, because when I&amp;rsquo;m dancing, I&amp;rsquo;m not holding my camera, but here are some photos a friend took at a big salsa dance weekend at the Palisades in McKeesport in April 2008, a year after we started dating in 2007.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/palisades-2008/abby-franklin.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby and Franklin dancing salsa at Palisades&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/palisades-2008/abby-franklin-hair.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby and Franklin dancing salsa at Palisades, hair flying&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;expression-and-improvisation-in-dance-and-in-music&#34;&gt;Expression and improvisation in dance and in music&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;dance&#34;&gt;Dance&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One reason I gave up ballroom dancing was that I felt there was an overemphasis on &amp;ldquo;syllabus steps&amp;rdquo; (I realize this is an oversimplification of the ballroom dance culture; all very good ballroom dancers go beyond the syllabus mindset). After quitting ballroom dancing, I explored Argentine tango, which is all about improvisation, but I left it because (at the time) it seemed that most of the women in the local scene were very tall, which made dancing awkward for me. I got into salsa because freed from the closed embrace, there was clearly a lot of room for personal improvisation. Ironically, I first got into making stuff up as a result of my imperfect memory: I could never memorize long choreography of step patterns, whether I was doing ballroom dancing or anything else. So I would always make a &amp;ldquo;mistake&amp;rdquo;, then I would make something out of the mistake. I learned that as long as you get back in time with the music, and keep the lead and follow communication strong, there is no such thing really as a mistake. You just keep going, with whatever is happening at the present moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I now have a long-term goal of developing my technique and releasing my inhibitions so that I can improvise musically at will. Yesterday, I played with improvising when playing bolero, cha cha, and tango. It was a lot of fun and profoundly satisfying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;music&#34;&gt;Music&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I actually credit my study of the recorder and the Baroque flute for reawakening me to my dream of free expression and improvisation. Baroque music leaves room for a lot of interpretation of trills and ornamentation and articulation (subject, of course, to &amp;ldquo;good taste&amp;rdquo;). I want to go beyond that, but it has been a great starting point. For some reason, too much exposure to later music (such as Beethoven) had turned me into a score-reader, since such later music has so much already marked up for the performer to simply &lt;em&gt;obey&lt;/em&gt;. The sparse annotations in Renaissance and Baroque music give one much more freedom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am enjoying playing the flute again, now that I know what I really want to do with it. And I would like to merge my dance and music lives, just as Abby has always played the Balkan music she also dances to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2012-03-12&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-03-12)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ended up &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/12/quitting-the-cmu-all-university-orchestra-one-of-the-hardest-decisions-in-my-life/&#34;&gt;quitting the CMU AUO&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2013-01-26&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-01-26)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost a year later, I finally played tangos on flute &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/26/music-i-just-played-for-the-first-time-recorder-sonata-tangos/&#34;&gt;at a party&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2013-03-17&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-03-17)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost exactly a year later, I ended up playing selections from the World Music Cuba book &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/17/finally-doing-some-latin-music-jamming-on-flute/&#34;&gt;at a party&lt;/a&gt;, and improvising freely with two other guys!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Flute: taking a break while clarifying my goals</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/03/07/flute-taking-a-break-while-clarifying-my-goals/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Mar 2012 21:41:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/03/07/flute-taking-a-break-while-clarifying-my-goals/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is my first blog post in over a week. I&amp;rsquo;ve been very busy, and therefore have had to recently &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/02/23/saying-no-in-order-to-say-yes/&#34;&gt;say &amp;ldquo;no&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; to blogging while saying &amp;ldquo;yes&amp;rdquo; to many other activities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another thing I&amp;rsquo;ve said &amp;ldquo;no&amp;rdquo; to in the past three days has been playing the (modern) flute. In my last blog post I was worried about flute &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/02/27/flute-practice-dealing-with-burnout-and-injury&#34;&gt;burnout and injury&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a flute status update.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;injury&#34;&gt;Injury&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I fixed some things in how I was handling my flute so that I would experience less stress on my left hand, so I believe I have for now avoided serious injury, although I am still planning to investigate buying a more suitably shaped flute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;last-sunday-s-orchestra-rehearsal&#34;&gt;Last Sunday&amp;rsquo;s orchestra rehearsal&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I felt rather demoralized after &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.andrew.cmu.edu/user/auo/&#34;&gt;CMU AUO&lt;/a&gt; rehearsal three days ago. I had had a really packed weekend and therefore was quite drained after rehearsal, which lasted from 7:30 PM to 10:00 PM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The orchestra was still struggling to get things in place. We do get better, but very slowly. Our director is visibly impatient, and rightly so. I have wondered whether to describe my own complaints, because I wish no harm and am still committed to doing my best to contribute to the concert on April 15. But I think that what I share here will probably not be very surprising.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;immaturity-and-dishonesty&#34;&gt;Immaturity and dishonesty&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The experience of being in this non-audition orchestra composed primarily of undergraduates reminds me a lot of my negative experiences in band when I was a pre-teen. There is a lot of disruptive chatting during rehearsal that is quite &amp;ldquo;unprofessional&amp;rdquo;; I take music seriously and given the huge investment of two and a half hours on a Sunday evening every week, would like to make the most of the time. I realize that these are not music major students, and therefore many treat this activity as a casual hobby.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was demoralizing when the director had to confront the orchestra and note that every week, after the break halfway in the rehearsal, suddenly there are more empty seats, meaning that people have been leaving, after having checked in (there is a strict attendance policy). Also, I have noticed people regularly not showing up in the first half, and coming in only for the second half. Yes, it is true that sometimes a student may have some other commitment, but still, the absences affect our rehearsal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, the girl who is in charge of attendance sternly said after the rehearsal that she had done some counting and noticed that some instrument sections had more check marks than people she actually saw; in other words, people were signing in for friends who weren&amp;rsquo;t showing up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;lack-of-passion&#34;&gt;Lack of passion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another fundamental problem is the lack of passion many of the orchestra members have for the music. This Bernstein and Gershwin music we&amp;rsquo;re playing is good music: it&amp;rsquo;s very rhythmic, syncopated, and a lot of us are playing it in some kind of sleepy, tentative way. I find this lack of spirit extremely offensive, frankly. Why waste time playing music if you&amp;rsquo;re not going to breathe it and be moved by it? It boggles my mind. My attitude, whether running a 5K race or writing a computer program or cooking or playing music or dancing, is that my time and energy are precious, and if I&amp;rsquo;m going to do it, I want to give it my all, the moment that I&amp;rsquo;m doing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;summary-of-my-orchestra-experience&#34;&gt;Summary of my orchestra experience&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So as far as the atmosphere in the orchestra is concerned, I find it completely at odds with what I&amp;rsquo;m looking for in an ensemble. This is not much of a surprise, but it is disappointing anyway. However, I will continue to get and give all I can to our rehearsals and upcoming performance, for the experience, and then I don&amp;rsquo;t really expect to continue in the orchestra when the fall term arrives. I have many musical goals that I already have lined up for the summer and beyond; more on that in a later post, where I will also discuss why I don&amp;rsquo;t really fit in an orchestra, even if I played much better and everyone had a professional attitude toward rehearsal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;for-now-off-the-modern-flute-to-the-baroque-flute&#34;&gt;For now: off the modern flute to the Baroque flute&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next Sunday there is no orchestra rehearsal because of spring break. So the pressure to keep on trying to improve my play (I still have a lot of work to do, especially in the Gershwin because I have not practiced it much) is lessened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of all the recent negative associations, I decided to take a short break from the modern flute altogether. For fun, I finally started getting serious about the Baroque flute.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://static.musiciansfriend.com/derivates/18/001/590/857/DV016_Jpg_Large_464489.901_black_matte.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Aulos Baroque flute A440&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve begun practicing the Baroque flute, starting with D major work and now adding G major also. The technique is rather different from that for the modern flute. I have to admit it is a frustrating instrument, but it has its own odd charm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I feel like it again (probably by next Monday), I&amp;rsquo;ll return to continuing practicing modern flute, getting prepared for the next orchestra rehearsal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m having some musical rough spots, but I&amp;rsquo;m still very much in love with music and always find some outlet somehow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2012-03-12&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-03-12)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ended up &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/12/quitting-the-cmu-all-university-orchestra-one-of-the-hardest-decisions-in-my-life/&#34;&gt;quitting the CMU AUO&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Flute practice: dealing with burnout and injury</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/02/27/flute-practice-dealing-with-burnout-and-injury/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Feb 2012 11:27:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/02/27/flute-practice-dealing-with-burnout-and-injury/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/left-hand.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin&amp;#39;s left hand&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, I attended yet another &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/02/22/flute-progress-still-hanging-in-there/&#34;&gt;rehearsal&lt;/a&gt; of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.andrew.cmu.edu/user/auo/&#34;&gt;Carnegie Mellon All-University Orchestra&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did this while feeling burned out and injured.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;burnout-and-injury&#34;&gt;Burnout and injury&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past couple of days, I have experienced decreased desire to practice flute, although by changing up my material, I did manage to get some decent sessions in. Still, I could tell that I was beginning to risk burnout.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to mental fatigue, my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/02/14/flute-progress-report-day-of-reckoning-approaches/&#34;&gt;left forefinger soreness&lt;/a&gt; got worse in the past couple of days, such that yesterday, I didn&amp;rsquo;t practice before rehearsal. I started experiencing &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jennifercluff.com/lineup.htm#indentation&#34;&gt;tingling and numbness&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://theskooloflife.com/wordpress/sometimes-its-best-to-call-it-a-day/&#34;&gt;Sometimes it&amp;rsquo;s best to call it a day.&lt;/a&gt; So I decided yesterday that today, I would take a day completely off from practicing my flute, the first break I have given myself since January 19.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;injury&#34;&gt;Injury&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clearly I need a real strategy to take care of the side of my left finger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is pretty easy to get injured playing music. There are many unnatural positions and movements to work with to make as relaxed as possible. My favorite book for musicians, &lt;a href=&#34;http://musiciansway.com/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Musician&amp;rsquo;s Way&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; has two entire chapters on injury prevention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next time I pick up my flute, I will focus on what I might be doing that causes particular stress on my left finger, and try to adjust. Earlier in my practice, I had problems with my right pinkie finger and solved them, so I have hope of treating my left finger better also. I have read about balance points, using the chin, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-instrument&#34;&gt;My instrument&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One problem that I definitely have is that the instrument I have is not optimal for me, and I know it. My main fundamental problem (and this has been a problem for me with piano, guitar, ukulele) is that I have a small hand and short fingers. There are solutions to this problem for the flute. One very common option that would immediately solve some of my problems is the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flutesonline.com/in_offg.htm&#34;&gt;offset G&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.flutesonline.com/shopping/in_offg.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Offset G flute&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve always thought that I would like to get an offset G flute when I &amp;ldquo;upgrade&amp;rdquo; from my intermediate student flute. &lt;strong&gt;Now I&amp;rsquo;m thinking I should do this sooner rather than later.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;no-excuse&#34;&gt;No excuse&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another book on music practice that I enjoy, Madeline Bruser&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://artofpracticing.com/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Art of Practicing&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, has an anecdote (page 107) about a flutist, Janet Weiss, who found that the traditional flute did not fit her hand, and became a pioneer in redesigning it. Weiss was quoted as saying, &amp;ldquo;The instrument we&amp;rsquo;re playing is incorrect for many people&amp;hellip; it&amp;rsquo;s like trying to dance in a pair of shoes that don&amp;rsquo;t fit.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed! If we love music enough, we should take the initiative to make sure that we are not hampered by our instruments. Just as, I love running and hiking, and struggled with bad footwear for years, decades, until I solved most of my problems, by moving toward &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/fivefingers/&#34;&gt;Vibram FiveFingers&lt;/a&gt; shoes that do not cramp my very wide feet and do not introduce cushioning that causes me to mess up my knees and shins and ankles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have to do what we have to do. We can&amp;rsquo;t just complain that other people are lucky and mass-produced clothing and tools work for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-orchestra-rehearsal-last-night&#34;&gt;The orchestra rehearsal last night&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was still struggling at rehearsal last night. I still cannot play all of the music at full speed. If it were entirely up to me, I would improve at my own pace, rather than feel forced to tackle material that is currently more beyond me than I&amp;rsquo;d like. But in real life, we often have to cut corners. The question is, which corners?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One option is to just bumble through everything in an equally mediocre way. I don&amp;rsquo;t see how that would help the orchestra&amp;rsquo;s concert performance or my own long-term development. So I have chosen to refine what is easiest, and get that working fully, while &amp;ldquo;giving up&amp;rdquo;, at least temporarily, on what is most out of reach. I&amp;rsquo;ve been closing the gap, and believe that I can close it within another three weeks. That would mean I will feel fully ready probably two weeks before the actual concert.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone else is also still improving. We don&amp;rsquo;t sound very good right now, even at slowish speeds. But we are sounding better every week! That&amp;rsquo;s what matters. It&amp;rsquo;s exciting to feel us coming together more and more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m dealing with a temporary setback in motivation and physical condition right now, but hope to bounce back tomorrow. &lt;strong&gt;The show must go on.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2012-03-12&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-03-12)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ended up &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/12/quitting-the-cmu-all-university-orchestra-one-of-the-hardest-decisions-in-my-life/&#34;&gt;quitting the CMU AUO&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Flute progress after one month in orchestra: still hanging in there</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/02/22/flute-progress-still-hanging-in-there/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Feb 2012 20:19:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/02/22/flute-progress-still-hanging-in-there/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It was exactly one month ago, January 22, when &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/02/01/joining-an-orchestra-learning-in-the-face-of-terror/&#34;&gt;I joined&lt;/a&gt; the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.andrew.cmu.edu/user/auo/&#34;&gt;Carnegie Mellon All-University Orchestra&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another week has gone by, and what I thought might be a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/02/14/flute-progress-report-day-of-reckoning-approaches/&#34;&gt;day of reckoning&lt;/a&gt; has come and gone, and I am still playing the flute in the CMU AUO and have not dropped out!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a sample of the hardest music from Bernstein&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Symphonic Dances from West Side Story&amp;rdquo; that I&amp;rsquo;m still struggling to play correctly, cleanly, and in tempo:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/flute-music/west-side-story-fugue.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;West Side Story: Fugue&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/flute-music/west-side-story-rumble.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;West Side Story: Rumble&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It is not very visible from my photos, but I have a huge number of pencil markings on my copy of the score.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story as of now:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;practice-in-the-past-week&#34;&gt;Practice in the past week&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;getting-down-the-basics&#34;&gt;Getting down the basics&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last Wednesday, I continued with focusing purely on improving technique with the Rubank method book. I did not even look at the Gershwin or Bernstein music for orchestra. I simply recognize that I have to focus on making fundamental progress in technique and trust that this will enable me to actually play the hard music at hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have not written much about this strategy, but I feel that it is effective and that many &lt;em&gt;amateurs&lt;/em&gt; do not practice or pursue their various life activities with this discipline, and therefore fall short of reaching their potential. And then typically, we amateurs make excuses, blaming lack of talent or lack of time for our slow progress or quick plateau at a mediocre level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is something in the general culture that encourages immediate gratification at the expense of true &lt;em&gt;craft&lt;/em&gt;. Yes, it is true that we cannot give our all toward our hobbies, the way we might for what we consider our jobs, but at the same time, if you add up the number of hours we spend at our hobbies, they actually do add up, and we might as well have made them count efficiently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me to attack the hard passages of music prematurely without building up technique would be analogous to the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;never running before but aiming to run a marathon in four months, and jumping straight into trying to run 15 miles&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;being a non-programmer and wanting to create a cool Web site in a month, but trying to read a book like &amp;ldquo;Learn Web Programming in 7 Days&amp;rdquo; and not really mastering concepts such as variables and functions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;never having cooked but deciding to make a really fancy and subtle French dish without mastering the basics of knife usage or the properties of butter&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People like shortcuts. But they usually do not succeed, and even if they do, don&amp;rsquo;t provide a sustainable path of growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My real goal isn&amp;rsquo;t just to survive playing in an orchestra concert. That&amp;rsquo;s actually just an incentive for my real goal, which is to improve my overall technique, so that I can continue to play music in any genre, any ensemble, as I wish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;an-off-day&#34;&gt;An off day&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, the next day, Thursday, I was feeling tired and unmotivated for practice. This happens sometimes. In fact, typically it happens once a week. I&amp;rsquo;m human. I can&amp;rsquo;t magically improve a huge amount every single day. Sometimes I&amp;rsquo;m tired. Sometimes I backslide, and notes come out jumbled, slow, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This, too, is a part of life. I&amp;rsquo;ve found the hard way that it&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; best to just push through and waste time and emotional energy. &lt;em&gt;Overtraining&lt;/em&gt; doesn&amp;rsquo;t help. Sometimes it is best to just take a break. I generally prefer to take an &lt;em&gt;active&lt;/em&gt; break.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, on Thursday I decided to put away the technique practice, which was not going well, and instead have fun sight-reading a bunch of music I had gotten out of the library earlier. I played around sight-reading &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Play-Puccini-Arias-Transcribed-Flute/dp/0634046209/&#34;&gt;transcribed opera arias from Puccini&lt;/a&gt; (I secretly love singing them in Italian even though I&amp;rsquo;m not a soprano or female!), &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Debussy-Album-Flute-Piano/dp/9043129712/&#34;&gt;transcriptions from Debussy&amp;rsquo;s piano music&lt;/a&gt; (I want to play the original piano pieces some day), and a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/World-Music-Cuba-Flute-play-along/dp/3702465804&#34;&gt;World Music Cuba&lt;/a&gt; album. It was a lot of fun playing real, lyrical music. I especially liked playing the Cuban music, since I always dreamed about doing that back when I was dancing salsa, rumba, cha cha, and bolero (I also have a goal of seriously singing this genre of music).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: eventually I would like to actually practice some of these music arrangements seriously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;update-of-2012-11-17&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-11-17)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nine months after this blog post, I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/11/17/a-childhood-dream-come-true-i-am-now-finally-singing-for-real/&#34;&gt;sang bolero for the first time in my life, to Abby&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;update-of-2013-03-17&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-03-17)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over a year later, I ended up playing selections from the World Music Cuba book &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/17/finally-doing-some-latin-music-jamming-on-flute/&#34;&gt;at a party&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;continued-practice&#34;&gt;Continued practice&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Friday and Saturday I was back doing technique, and Saturday I finally hit the CMU AUO music again. I noticed that I was playing the high notes on the flute better. Also, of course, I improved my speed and facility at many scales, but I won&amp;rsquo;t bore with listing metronome numbers to indicate my progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;sunday-s-orchestra-rehearsal&#34;&gt;Sunday&amp;rsquo;s orchestra rehearsal&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;sectional-for-woodwinds&#34;&gt;Sectional for woodwinds&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I arrived at 6:30 PM on Sunday for the woodwind sectional, but only one other person was there! People were running late, apparently. I was concerned when only three flutes (plus piccolo) showed up: did we lose another flute? (Later in the full rehearsal, two others joined us.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that in the woodwind sectional, collectively we were still struggling, and therefore I was not as out of place as I had feared I might be. It was a very useful rehearsal, in which many different instruments&amp;rsquo; parts started falling in place. It was at this point that I realized that I was having trouble not only because of my own problems but also because other peoples&amp;rsquo; problems were affecting me. I was having trouble coming in at the right time in many places not only because I was counting badly (although I&amp;rsquo;ve been working steadily at improving my counting) but also because so many other lines were not coming in at the right place either, so I could not rely on listening to others as a way of finding my place. Anyway, we made huge progress in some very difficult music. I actually believe, for the first time, that we might be able to get this stuff working for the concert.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;full-rehearsal&#34;&gt;Full rehearsal&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maria kept on being disappointed in the full rehearsal, asking if we had actually listened to the music, because we were still having so much trouble. (Actually, I have the music and listen to the whole thing at least once every other day.) Perhaps it was a blessing in disguise that so many of us were still unprepared, because it enabled me to not be completely left behind, as we kept the tempos still on the slow side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even so, there were sections in which I simply was unable to keep up. I feel that I really need to master most of them by next rehearsal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;this-week-s-practice&#34;&gt;This week&amp;rsquo;s practice&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My practice this week so far since the rehearsal has been good. I&amp;rsquo;m still focusing on building technique.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Monday, I made significant improvements in my high notes with scales. I worked some with the Bernstein.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Tuesday, I continued Rubank, and went back to some real basics, playing long tones, working on control of dynamics, and relaxation. I did not touch orchestra music at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, I did an abbreviated Rubank practice, then launched into much work on the Bernstein, to make things faster. As I do once or twice a week, I included a &amp;ldquo;test&amp;rdquo; for myself in which I played through all the problematic sections of the piece along with an actual recording. I&amp;rsquo;m doing much, much better now. There is still hope that I might be able to play most of the piece at full speed by Sunday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-look-back-to-three-months-ago&#34;&gt;A look back to three months ago&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is amusing to look back to what I was still having trouble playing, as a flute beginner, three months ago. I was just starting to work through a collection of &amp;ldquo;easy flute classics&amp;rdquo;:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/flute-music/moyse-easy-classics.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Moyse Collection of Easy Flute Classics&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Compare these simple, slow scores with the Bernstein excerpts in the photos at the beginning of this blog post!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;recorder&#34;&gt;Recorder&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Needless to say, I&amp;rsquo;ve completely put away my recorders. I did go to the monthly meeting of the Pittsburgh chapter of the American Recorder Society on Sunday to play, but that is all I will do with recorder until after the April orchestra concert. I would like to get serious about recorder again for late spring and summer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, I felt I was automatically slightly better at playing recorder even without touching it for a month. It&amp;rsquo;s the cross-training effect. Music is music, whichever instrument you&amp;rsquo;re playing: breath control, tone awareness, flexibility of fingers, etc. Even if I did sometimes forget my fingerings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m still enjoying improving at flute and slowly getting closer to being able to play the second flute part of the Bernstein in its entirety. I get less and less panicky about being in the orchestra as I &amp;ldquo;catch up&amp;rdquo; according to plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2012-03-12&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-03-12)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ended up &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/12/quitting-the-cmu-all-university-orchestra-one-of-the-hardest-decisions-in-my-life/&#34;&gt;quitting the CMU AUO&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Flute progress report: day of reckoning approaches</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/02/14/flute-progress-report-day-of-reckoning-approaches/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Feb 2012 20:47:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/02/14/flute-progress-report-day-of-reckoning-approaches/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/02/01/joining-an-orchestra-learning-in-the-face-of-terror/&#34;&gt;Two weeks ago, I wrote&lt;/a&gt; about joining the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.andrew.cmu.edu/user/auo/&#34;&gt;Carnegie Mellon All-University Orchestra&lt;/a&gt;, the first orchestra I have ever been in. I wrote of my terror as I realized that as a total beginner at flute, I was basically unable to play &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; of the music handed out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided to work very hard at improving my flute skills to see whether I could get good enough in time to make it to the April 15 concert in respectable shape. &lt;strong&gt;I believe this is the most ambitious goal I have ever set for myself in my entire life.&lt;/strong&gt; Not because it is the &lt;em&gt;hardest&lt;/em&gt; goal to achieve, but because of the &lt;em&gt;time&lt;/em&gt; pressure involved. If I were given eight months, I would say, yes, I can do it; it took me eight months to start playing the recorder and then be sufficiently skilled (at merely an intermediate level) to play easy music in a concert. But &lt;em&gt;two&lt;/em&gt; months is another story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, the day of reckoning is not April 15. I feel it is next Sunday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-day-of-reckoning&#34;&gt;A day of reckoning&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More precisely, next Sunday is the first day on which I might be in a lot of trouble if I can&amp;rsquo;t reach a certain level. The woodwind section will have a sectional before the main rehearsal to iron out our special problems. All of us flutes will be pretty naked at the sectional. I know where I&amp;rsquo;m still falling short.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;good-news&#34;&gt;Good news&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The good news is that I have made &lt;em&gt;huge&lt;/em&gt; progress in the past two weeks. Whereas two weeks ago I classified myself as a &amp;ldquo;beginner&amp;rdquo;, now I would classify myself as an &amp;ldquo;advanced beginner&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There have been exciting days during which I made a lot of progress and bad days during which I felt that I made little progress or backslid, but I kept the faith and kept going. I&amp;rsquo;ve put aside various other personal projects in order to work as much on flute as possible: some days I have practiced two hours instead of one, and sometimes even three or four hours (on weekends). My left forefinger is permanently sore!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also good news is that we were down to four flutes and one piccolo as of two weeks ago, but this week were have not lost more flutes! I expect the rest of us are in it for the long haul: two of us on first flute, two of us on second flute, and one of us on piccolo. I&amp;rsquo;m not sure if I should, but I would feel very uncertain if I were the only second flute remaining now. It&amp;rsquo;s nice to know someone else may be sharing my pain, and maybe we can help each other in the sectionals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;practice-details&#34;&gt;Practice details&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bulk of my practice has been continuing to get down basic technique by working through the Rubank intermediate method. I keep on filling in gaps, adding new exercises while continuing to improve on exercises I have begun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;high-notes&#34;&gt;High notes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the music that we are playing for the concert, it has been of very high priority that I manage to play the very high notes (of the third register) effectively. This has been quite, quite difficult. It takes time to learn to form the embouchure and use it; what has been helpful has been looking at Web resources and reminding myself to &lt;em&gt;relax&lt;/em&gt;. Undirected powering through, like powering through in any other activity, from running to rowing to programming, doesn&amp;rsquo;t work. I still have difficulty producing the kinds of notes in the third register I would like (our director Maria has repeatedly told us flutes collectively to work on our intonation, and you bet that in Sunday&amp;rsquo;s sectional I will be doing what I can to get it where it needs to be), but at least I now know the fingerings for A-flat, A, B-flat, and B, and am still hard at work practicing scales and arpeggios way up there. It is only this week, actually, that I managed to be able to get B-flat and B out of my instrument at all. A-flat remains weird, but A is clean. Also, F, F-sharp, and G were shaky for me at last report, but I&amp;rsquo;m more or less getting them now. E does not speak so well, unfortunately; I think this is partially an inherent flute matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;dynamics&#34;&gt;Dynamics&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maria also repeatedly reminded the whole orchestra that we were not very good with dynamics, and generally played at some kind of nondescript mezzo-forte. We need to be able to play pianissimo and crescendo to fortissimo, etc., for expression and effect as indicated in the score.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve improved on dynamics, but it is still very hard for me to play high notes softly, for example. I know the theory, but making my mouth and breath do this is taking time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;rhythm&#34;&gt;Rhythm&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maria works with the entire group large on rhythm. The music we have to play is jazzy and swings and has all kinds of syncopations, accents that have to be felt and interpreted. It is indeed more effective to listen and copy these rhythms rather than try to play the notations in the score. She tells us not to play so square, ha!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Needless to say, I still have anxiety about coming in at the wrong times, and blasting a note where there is supposed to be a rest. So you bet I am working on getting the tricky rhythms down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;speed&#34;&gt;Speed&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maria has been ramping up the speeds in the rehearsals. Unfortunately, last Sunday an important section of the Bernstein was run through at a speed exceeding what I could handle at the time. So I have been working on that. I feel I am always playing catch-up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For development of speed, there is no substitute for just plain foundational technique work with the metronome. The metronome does not lie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;progress-on-old-exercises&#34;&gt;Progress on old exercises&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some examples of progress:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last week I gave a record of speed progress on an exercise:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 24: 100&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 25: 106&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 26: 109&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 27: 130&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 28: 131&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 29: 133&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 31: 141&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Add to that the following improvements, which get me to roughly where I feel I need to be:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 2: 143&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 6: 145&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 7: 146&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 8: 147&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 11: 148&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 14: 149&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the Pareto rule, I will not seek further improvement on this exercise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 25: 95&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 26: 96&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 27: 102&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 28: 106&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 29: 107&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 1: 115&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve improved on this one to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 2: 118&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 3: 119&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 6: 120&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 7: 122&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 8: 123&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 10: 124&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve topped out there too for now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s an interesting exercise from last time that I had found rather difficult:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 25: 100&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 26: 102&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 27: 105&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 29: 106&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 30: 107&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 31: 108&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have made radical improvements as a result of noticing the need for relaxation and for adjusting my holding of the instrument and the alignment of my right wrist (and many other things I still keep on refining):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 2: 110&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 3: 114&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 6: 120&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 7: 136&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 8: 138&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 11: 139&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 14: 140&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will stop trying to improve on this also.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a difficult arpeggio study at which I have made a big leap:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 27: 70&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 31: 71&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 1: 72&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 2: 73&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 3: 74&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 6: 78&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 7: 94&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 10: 95&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that in a single day, something clicked and I was able to go much faster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s an exercise that is wicked and works the right ring finger and other stuff:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 31: 86&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 1: 87&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 2: 110&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 3: 112&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 6: 114&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 7: 116&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 8: 118&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 10: 122&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 11: 123&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 12: 124&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 14: 126&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;new-exercises&#34;&gt;New exercises&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously, I have also attacked brand new exercises since my last post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s one on thirds:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 7: 110&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 11: 130&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 12: 132&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 14: 136&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another on thirds:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 8: 92&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 10: 120&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 11: 130&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 12: 132&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 14: 136&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rapid improvement on these new exercises comes because, as I have admitted, I have been a total beginner with almost no technique at all, never having practiced scales or arpeggios in any key, so when I&amp;rsquo;m learning a new key, I start off all confused but then make progress quickly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the Bernstein and Gershwin music have all kinds of keys, changes of key, accidentals, the works, so there is no escaping mastering everything. I&amp;rsquo;m working particularly on A major and A-flat major now, with their four sharps and four flats, respectively. The scariest, fastest section of the Bernstein actually has a key signature with six sharps (although I have to wonder why, because the music is full of accidentals and almost atonal).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;motivation&#34;&gt;Motivation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are times when I do not feel motivated to practice the concert music at all. I have a confession to make: playing flute in an orchestra is not my favorite musical activity by a long shot. It&amp;rsquo;s something I&amp;rsquo;m doing because it is novel to me and because I hope to enjoy being a part of a group effort in which we somehow manage to sound on April 15 a lot better than we sound now. Also, having a goal, and having the threat of social shame, has proved sometimes to be an effective motivator for me to achieve my &amp;ldquo;real&amp;rdquo; goals as a side effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I really like doing, and aim to do more of, is playing music in very small groups. I like playing recorder with one or two or three or four others. So sometimes when I&amp;rsquo;m practicing I feel frustrated that I&amp;rsquo;m working on a second flute part of a large orchestral piece, rather than on a duet or something like that. Amusingly, the fact that there are only two of us second flutes left helps me feel like I am &amp;ldquo;making a difference&amp;rdquo;, however.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m still hanging in there with my crazy attempt to just jump into a new level of flute playing, with a hard deadline. It would be less stressful if I were just trying to improve at my own pace, but I have to admit that from November through December, when I was working on the flute, the fact that I did not have a concrete level of mastery as a goal definitely made my practice less effective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2012-03-12&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-03-12)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ended up &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/12/quitting-the-cmu-all-university-orchestra-one-of-the-hardest-decisions-in-my-life/&#34;&gt;quitting the CMU AUO&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Joining an orchestra: learning in the face of terror</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/02/01/joining-an-orchestra-learning-in-the-face-of-terror/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2012 19:29:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/02/01/joining-an-orchestra-learning-in-the-face-of-terror/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have not written about my &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/flute/&#34;&gt;flute activities&lt;/a&gt; since &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/01/08/finding-and-using-my-childhood-flute-books/&#34;&gt;a month ago&lt;/a&gt;, but that&amp;rsquo;s not for lack of action: in fact, I&amp;rsquo;ve been spending a lot of time on the flute, at the expense of other personal projects, including writing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two months ago, I mentioned that I was &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/01/im-going-to-perform-music-much-sooner-than-i-expected-monday/&#34;&gt;considering joining&lt;/a&gt; the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.andrew.cmu.edu/user/auo/&#34;&gt;Carnegie Mellon All-University Orchestra&lt;/a&gt;, which I claimed was &amp;ldquo;not very good&amp;rdquo; and that &amp;ldquo;I don&amp;rsquo;t have to be super good to be a part of it.&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;I take back those comments&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I joined the CMU AUO two Sundays ago, attending the first rehearsal then, and &lt;strong&gt;it was one of the most frightening experiences in my entire life&lt;/strong&gt;. I almost left before even entering the rehearsal room. But I went in, stayed for the two and a half hours, and last Sunday, I went to the second rehearsal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me put it this way: at the first rehearsal, there were about ten flutes and one piccolo in the flute section. At the second rehearsal, we are down to four flutes and one piccolo. I hope that we don&amp;rsquo;t lose any more flutes at the next rehearsal. OK, maybe some students happened to be busy and will be returning. Or maybe some of them had the same reaction that I had: &lt;em&gt;absolute terror&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me explain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-music-we-are-to-play-for-the-april-15-concert&#34;&gt;The music we are to play for the April 15 concert&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the door of the rehearsal room, we got to pick up the music for the concert scheduled for April 15. There are four works, but one is for brass and percussion only, and the other for strings only, so there are only two I would play in on flute:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;George Gershwin, &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rhapsody_in_Blue&#34;&gt;Rhapsody in Blue&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Leonard Bernstein, &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/West_Side_Story#Symphonic_Dances_from_West_Side_Story&#34;&gt;Symphonic Dances from West Side Story&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On inspection at the door, I immediately realized that I could not play &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; of this music. Both the Gershwin and Bernstein were totally out of my current abilities. Worse, the Bernstein piece looked particularly insanely hard to me, even though I picked up the &amp;ldquo;flute 2&amp;rdquo; part, not the &amp;ldquo;flute 1&amp;rdquo; part. There were a lot syncopations, accents, extreme dynamics, very high notes (some of which I had not yet even learned the fingerings for yet), and the music was very fast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was filled with terror. I almost left without entering the room and signing in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-i-stayed&#34;&gt;Why I stayed&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went in anyway. I decided that I needed to see what this orchestra was about, since I have never been in an orchestra in my life (I stopped my feeble playing of the flute at age 13 and never played again after that).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a &amp;ldquo;fail fast&amp;rdquo; plan: if I really felt I couldn&amp;rsquo;t make a decent contribution in this orchestra, I would walk out as soon as I felt I was a hopeless burden to the team. &lt;em&gt;Forget ego&lt;/em&gt;: what I do or do not do must be based entirely on objective considerations. I wasn&amp;rsquo;t going to walk away already just because I believed (and still believe!) that I must be the worst musician in the entire orchestra, nor would I be afraid to walk away in the future if I found that I was harming the team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-first-rehearsal&#34;&gt;The first rehearsal&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ended up surviving the first rehearsal, in that we did a sight-reading session in which although I could barely play any of the music, I sat there trying to learn and did what I could, playing a few notes here and there when I could, and sitting out when there was just no way I could get anything right at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, I sat next to a guy who was playing piccolo, and he seemed to nail everything, although I had asked him earlier how long he&amp;rsquo;d been playing flute and he said twelve years. Note: I have been playing flute seriously for only three months, and on the membership form for the orchestra, it asked for a self-rating of experience level, ranging from Beginner to Advanced Beginner to Intermediate to Advanced, and with all honesty I checked off &lt;strong&gt;Beginner&lt;/strong&gt; (not even Advanced Beginner).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, it gave me some hope when I realized that everyone was having a hard time with the music. I&amp;rsquo;m sure nobody was having as hard a time as me, but we were struggling while sight reading at a very slow tempo. It also gave me hope that the director, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sellner.org/maria/Home.html&#34;&gt;Maria Sensi Sellner&lt;/a&gt;, happened to mention that we were tackling probably the hardest work the orchestra had attempted in its history, because she is leaving after this season and wanted to do something ambitious. OK, so it wasn&amp;rsquo;t just me thinking this music was hard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, she seemed to me very effective in helping us get started with the music. She worked out the tricky rhythms with us, and the music began to make more sense to me during the rehearsal. She told us that we should listen to recordings and check out the West Side Story musical so that we would understand the music in the context of the action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I left the rehearsal still shell-shocked, but I reasoned to myself that it would be stupid to quit this early on, before having had a chance to study the score more, continue to improve my technique, etc. I had grave doubts that I would return for the second rehearsal, but I had &lt;em&gt;one week&lt;/em&gt; to decide whether I should even come back. (Note that the orchestra has an attendance policy, so that anyone missing too many rehearsals may not play in the concert.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-sample-auo-performance&#34;&gt;A sample AUO performance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For fun, here is the CMU AUO performing last fall Bernstein&amp;rsquo;s Overture to Candide. They weren&amp;rsquo;t bad. That gives me hope, because we sounded pretty bad sight reading the Symphonic Dances from West Side Story, so I actually have faith that Sellner can get us into reasonable shape in two months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/ZelG_nJ-QvE&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-practice-strategy-for-a-week-after-the-first-rehearsal&#34;&gt;My practice strategy for a week after the first rehearsal&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All January I had been working really hard for three weeks on flute practice, in anticipation of the first CMU AUO rehearsal that occurred on January 22. I was making a &lt;em&gt;huge&lt;/em&gt; amount of progress working through &amp;ldquo;easy&amp;rdquo; stuff. Flute is much, much harder to play than &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/recorder/&#34;&gt;recorder&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the first rehearsal, I decided that there was no way I could ever play the Gershwin or Bernstein without focusing really hard on pure technique. So the bulk of my practice was beginning to systematically work through the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Rubank-Intermediate-Method-Piccolo-Educational/dp/1423444221&#34;&gt;Rubank Intermediate Method: Flute or Piccolo&lt;/a&gt; that I mentioned &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/01/08/finding-and-using-my-childhood-flute-books/&#34;&gt;finding in early January&lt;/a&gt; and never having used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spent a little bit of time trying to play excerpts from the Gershwin and Bernstein at a very slow tempo, but frankly, these attempts were very frustrating because I was still having problems just playing the high notes at all, for example. &lt;strong&gt;I had to learn the fingerings for some notes I had never played in my life.&lt;/strong&gt; I also had to improve my embouchure in order to produce those notes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(By the way, I have almost completely stopped playing recorder for a month. I am still attending the monthly meetings of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.andrew.cmu.edu/user/lukas/pcars/Welcome.html&#34;&gt;local recorder group&lt;/a&gt;, and practicing a little before attending, but I cannot devote any more time to improving on recorder while trying to get successfully to the April 15 CMU AUO concert.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-second-rehearsal&#34;&gt;The second rehearsal&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the second rehearsal approached, I wondered what we were supposed to be preparing for it. I sent email to the guy I had contacted last year about joining the orchestra, asking him if I had been put on the announcement mailing list yet, and he apologized, saying that he hadn&amp;rsquo;t, and he put me on. So it was only hours before the second rehearsal that I learned we were supposed to have been for days watching some YouTube videos and working on the two very hardest sections of the Bernstein!!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I almost didn&amp;rsquo;t go to the second rehearsal, as a result. I had not even looked at the hardest sections of the Bernstein yet: during the entire week, I had worked on the sections just up till those hardest sections!! I spent half an hour before the Sunday evening rehearsal trying to do a little work on the hardest sections, but failing pretty miserably. Oh well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went to the second rehearsal anyway. I half expected that I would be asked to leave after being found out to be completely incompetent (as well as not doing my homework).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that many of us had not done our homework, or had done it but were still having a lot of problems. The director was patient and slowed things down a lot and again focused on our getting the rhythms and syncopation right, and all the instruments just staying together at all. Because we were so unprepared, we ran out of time to work on the Gershwin, which she had originally planned to cover as well as the Bernstein.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, we lost most of our flutists!! In fact, with only four flutes and a piccolo left, during a flute-dominated passage of the Bernstein, we found out that only one of us was playing &amp;ldquo;flute 1&amp;rdquo;. The director asked for someone else to join her, and so I guess now we have two on &amp;ldquo;flute 1&amp;rdquo;, and me and the other person on &amp;ldquo;flute 2&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-practice-strategy-for-this-week-after-the-second-rehearsal&#34;&gt;My practice strategy for this week after the second rehearsal&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we were having a rehearsal again next Sunday, I would be seriously worried and contemplate probably having to drop out of the orchestra then. Luckily, we are skipping Super Bowl Sunday. &lt;strong&gt;This gives me two weeks, rather than one, to improve drastically.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The director had said it was up to us individually and in the upcoming sections to get our act together on the Bernstein sections in question. So I have at least one concrete goal for the next rehearsal: being prepared to play reasonably accurately the difficult Bernstein sections, and at tempo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For three days now so far this week, I have continued with working through the Rubank intermediate method. I have made so much progress that I think that in another couple of days I may consider myself an Advanced Beginner at flute rather than just a Beginner, ha!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;deliberate-practice&#34;&gt;Deliberate practice&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am putting in the focused, &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Practice_%28learning_method%29#Deliberate_practice&#34;&gt;deliberate practice&lt;/a&gt; to improve as rapidly and efficiently as I can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, I have to put in a plug for Gerald Klickstein, author of the wonderful book &lt;a href=&#34;http://musiciansway.com/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Musician&amp;rsquo;s Way&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, and his &lt;a href=&#34;http://musiciansway.com/blog/&#34;&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt; as well as his &lt;a href=&#34;http://twitter.com/klickstein&#34;&gt;Twitter feed @klickstein&lt;/a&gt;, which have been profoundly inspirational and useful in not only my music practice but also all of my other serious pursuits. He even replies to questions and comments promptly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regarding learning, I will be writing blog posts in the future about my various strategies for learning that I find effective. A recent article talks about &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wired.com/geekdad/2012/01/everything-about-learning/&#34;&gt;interleaving&lt;/a&gt;, which I have used to great effect to &amp;ldquo;parallelize&amp;rdquo; my learning, and I definitely use it in my music practice. I work on many things in one session, not just one thing, because there is no way to just get massively better at one thing during one session, and then do the same for something else at the next session. I have to parallelize, to make small bits of progress every day on something. For example, every day I work on&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;breath&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;intonation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;tone&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;high notes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;dynamics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;articulation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;rhythm: meters, syncopation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;tonguing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;speed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;passage work in keys (scales, arpeggios, thirds)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;tricky fingerings&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;style, expression&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;actual music&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I squeeze as much as I can out of an hour of practice at home. I&amp;rsquo;ve found that there are diminishing returns of all kinds after an hour. Obviously, if I were a music student or professional, I&amp;rsquo;d use multiple sessions to get more hours, but for much of my life these days I use the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pareto_principle&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;80&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;20&lt;/sub&gt; rule&lt;/a&gt; to maximize the returns on my practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;speed&#34;&gt;Speed&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I use the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/29/a-musicians-best-friend/&#34;&gt;metronome&lt;/a&gt; extensively in my practice to gauge my progress, by making note each day of the fastest speed at which I can execute an exercise with the best musical qualities I am capable of currently, and then trying to do it faster the next day. This method worked very well for me when I was learning the recorder from scratch, and it is working for me well now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, here is the record for one of the twenty or so exercises I have worked on in the Rubank book for the past week and a half:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 24: 100&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 25: 106&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 26: 109&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 27: 130&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 28: 131&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 29: 133&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 31: 141&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 24: 120&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 25: 135&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 26: 137&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 27: 139&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 28: 144&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 29: 146&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 30: 148&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 31: 152&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 1: 154&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 25: 95&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 26: 96&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 27: 102&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 28: 106&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 29: 107&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;February 1: 115&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another (in which I have been finding the series of arpeggios rather difficult):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 25: 100&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 26: 102&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 27: 105&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 29: 106&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 30: 107&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 31: 108&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Where there is a gap in the record, I either did not play that exercise that day, because I chose to work on another, or I did but could not go faster without error.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that the progress is not always linear. Sometimes there are &amp;ldquo;trouble spots&amp;rdquo; that hold me back for a while before I overcome them. Sometimes I am stagnant for a day or even a couple of days before I suddenly get better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keeping detailed records is vital to an objective assessment of where one is in one&amp;rsquo;s practice. I kept detailed records when losing thirty pounds over a decade ago, and when transforming myself from a non-runner into a marathoner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;progress-on-the-bernstein&#34;&gt;Progress on the Bernstein&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As mentioned, I have not practiced the Bernstein music that much, because I devote around 80 or 90 percent of my time to just improving my technique. The &lt;em&gt;fundamentals&lt;/em&gt; matter (I will talk about this in future blog posts) when trying to get good at something. One cannot just rush in without mastering fundamentals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some metronome improvement numbers for sections of the Bernstein music:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 28: 40&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January 29: 70&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;January 30: 128 (full speed)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;January 28: 100&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;January 31: 110 (I still need to get up to 128)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;January 30: 100 (I still need to get up to 160!!)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously, my goal for the next rehearsal is to get as much up to full speed as possible in the sections that I need the most work on. If I fail miserably to measure up, I will feel justified in quitting the orchestra. But given my improvement in the Rubank method, I think I have a fighting chance in the next ten days to get much better in the Bernstein music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By deciding to take on the challenge of joining the CMU All-University Orchestra while being pathetically incompetent at flute, I am trying to push the limits of my learning and practice abilities. I will drop out if I only manage to hold back rehearsals or feel that I will play badly at the scheduled concert. But so far, I am still hanging in there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2012-03-12&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-03-12)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ended up &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/12/quitting-the-cmu-all-university-orchestra-one-of-the-hardest-decisions-in-my-life/&#34;&gt;quitting the CMU AUO&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>