<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Johann Sebastian Bach on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/johann-sebastian-bach/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Johann Sebastian Bach on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/johann-sebastian-bach/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Revisiting Bach&#39;s Air on G String, from a singing and dancing viewpoint</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/06/10/revisiting-bachs-air-on-g-string-from-a-singing-and-dancing-viewpoint/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jun 2015 23:46:26 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/06/10/revisiting-bachs-air-on-g-string-from-a-singing-and-dancing-viewpoint/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Three years ago, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/14/passion-of-bachs-air-on-the-g-string-three-different-interpretations/&#34;&gt;I wrote a post comparing three very different
performance styles&lt;/a&gt;
for Johann Sebastian Bach&amp;rsquo;s famous music,
&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Air_on_the_G_String&#34;&gt;Air on G String&lt;/a&gt;
and indicating which I preferred.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have received an unexpected number comments over the years, and
thought it was time to write an update of my thoughts in response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Primarily, I am responding to those who (correctly) criticized the
unfortunately chosen exemplar of the style that I preferred. I tried
to find better versions that might illustrate my perceptions. I also
integrated some thoughts based on how I perceive music as a singer and
as a dancer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;better-than-the-rushed-croatian-baroque-ensemble-s-performance&#34;&gt;Better than the rushed Croatian Baroque Ensemble&amp;rsquo;s performance?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I agreed quickly with the first commenters that the Croatian
ensemble&amp;rsquo;s performance was too perfunctory, even downright brutal and
unpleasant in various ways. I wish I had
chosen a better example of what I actually &lt;em&gt;like&lt;/em&gt; rather than &lt;em&gt;prefer
to the other two versions&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I searched YouTube for period-style performances that are
closer to what I envision than either the Croatian ensemble&amp;rsquo;s or
Koopman&amp;rsquo;s. It proved impossible for me to find a perfect performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-period-performance-i-like-more-christopher-hogwood&#34;&gt;A period performance I like more: Christopher Hogwood&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like this version by the late &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christopher_Hogwood&#34;&gt;Christopher Hogwood&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s Academy of
Ancient Music:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/nrtdhH8_47k&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a sweetness and &lt;em&gt;bouncy lightness&lt;/em&gt; to this version that I
like, but it is also somewhat anemic. Personally, I would play up more
contrast and fullness of sound and passion, but the overall tempo and
breathing to this version seems right to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;voices-of-music-richer-sound&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Voices of Music&amp;rdquo;: richer sound&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Voices of Music&amp;rdquo; here in a good performance:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/pzlw6fUux4o&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like the richness of sound in this performance. I miss the lighter,
more bouncy feeling that Hogwood brought out though. This performance
is a bit too legato for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;i-care-about-singing&#34;&gt;I care about singing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I approach this music from the viewpoint of singing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bouncy lightness is very important to me, along with the rhythmic
characterization. I feel this music as a song (it is an &amp;ldquo;air&amp;rdquo;, after
all), and I cannot help singing along when I hear it. Therefore, when
it&amp;rsquo;s taken too slow for me to sing and make it to natural breathing
points in phrases, that considerably lessens my pleasure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;yehudi-menuhin-solo-violin&#34;&gt;Yehudi Menuhin, solo violin&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s an interesting old black and white video of a performance by a young Yehudi Menuhin on violin with
accompaniment. It&amp;rsquo;s not a period performance, but moves along at a
decent &amp;ldquo;singing&amp;rdquo; tempo, as befits violin, that singing instrument.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34;
src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/08bDiKXW0gg&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;
allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I confess that I rather like this performance for its virtues,
although it distorts Bach&amp;rsquo;s music by so emphasizing just the musical
line, at the expense of the balance of the other voices and the
essential character of the dissonances among the voices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;more-menuhin-but-as-conductor&#34;&gt;More Menuhin, but as conductor&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s Yehudi Menuhin not as violin soloist but as conductor of the
Bath Festival Orchestra in 1960. Again, not a period performance, but
he takes the music briskly, and has the violins create sufficient
phrase delineations that I feel the music alertly as though it sings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s direct and clear, maybe not the most subtle and warm,
but I like it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/kaBAE4stNIo&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;dancing-is-possible-too&#34;&gt;Dancing is possible too&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also like to dance to expressive music. A pioneer of modern dance,
Doris Humphrey, famously choreographed a dance to a slowish
performance of this music:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/NjwJyaSIRqY&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not how I would dance to it, because I feel the music
differently. Surprisingly, I could find few examples on YouTube of
dancing to this music. I may consider choreographing a dance myself as
a project to express my own personal vision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing I would like to mention is that I feel that the &lt;em&gt;walking bass&lt;/em&gt;
is very important in this music and gives it the impetus. When played
too slow, the walking bass no longer feels like it&amp;rsquo;s walking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel this music in my legs, not just in my lungs. Yes, I have
actually hummed it to myself while walking in time to the bass
leisurely in the local park. There is a limit to how &amp;ldquo;leisurely&amp;rdquo; I can
walk without feeling frustrated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;ice-dancing&#34;&gt;Ice dancing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found this somewhat frenetic but nevertheless beautiful ice dancing
performance from the 1992 World Figure Skating Championships:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/1JjbwtM_E3g&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;recorder-quartet&#34;&gt;Recorder quartet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A final performance to enjoy: the Japanese &amp;ldquo;Sekishi Recorder Quartet&amp;rdquo;
playing their hearts out in 2009. I think it&amp;rsquo;s lovely: impeccable
phrasing, transparency,
and rich ensemble balance and tone. (As a twist, the melody line performer adds
his own ornamentations.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/pRRRK0UClNs&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was inspired by the accumulated comments on my previous post on
Bach&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Air on G String&amp;rdquo; that I decided to flesh out my thoughts by
using more example performances, as well as relate the orchestral
music to singing and dancing. I hope you have enjoyed these
explorations. There is no single &amp;ldquo;right&amp;rdquo; way to experience music, but
I wanted to share how I experience it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;ve read my previous post, does this one help clarify where
  I&amp;rsquo;m coming from with my musical values? Do you dance
  or sing? Does this affect how you perceive this piece of music and
  like to perform it or hear it performed?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The single greatest performance of Bach&#39;s Goldberg Variations: Pierre Hantaï with rhythmic drive and life</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/05/the-single-greatest-performance-of-bachs-goldberg-variations-pierre-hantai/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2014 22:32:07 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/05/the-single-greatest-performance-of-bachs-goldberg-variations-pierre-hantai/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been listening to JS Bach&amp;rsquo;s Goldberg Variations for a quarter of a century now. I haven&amp;rsquo;t actually said much about this piece on this blog, although I did mention attending a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/11/19/chamber-music-concert-at-cmu-featured-bachs-goldberg-variations-arranged-for-string-trio/&#34;&gt;concert featuring a string trio arrangement of it a year ago&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a favorite recording, out of probably a dozen recordings I have heard since a college friend introduced me to the piece performed by Glenn Gould on piano . Several years ago I discovered my true favorite, upon encountering &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pierre_Hanta%C3%AF&#34;&gt;Pierre Hantaï&lt;/a&gt; on harpsichord in a CD recording.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-hantaï-stands-out-for-me&#34;&gt;Why Hantaï stands out for me&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given that there are plenty of other performances that I consider worthy, why is Hantaï&amp;rsquo;s by far my favorite?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;sustained intensity (many performances have me getting bored and sleepy)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;rhythmic&lt;/em&gt; drive is always there; the music never droops&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;subtlety and shape to all phrasing and contrast&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;no distractions of self-absorption (many performances have certain kinds of oddities that are magnified when spread out over an hour or more)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;nice harpsichord sound&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: I once didn&amp;rsquo;t like harpsichord, and always preferred a piano when possible, but now I actually prefer Bach&amp;rsquo;s music on harpsichord, because of the nature of articulation and decay and how dissonances are more delicious on this instrument.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a treat I just found by accident: a video of Hantaï performing the Goldberg Variations. Watch it if you care about the Goldberg Variations at all!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/9NYqiKm3gng&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you are already a fan of the Goldberg Variations, what is your favorite performance, and why? Also, does it matter to you whether piano or harpsichord is used?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Discovering the beautiful keyboard playing of Robert Hill by accident on YouTube changed my life</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/08/21/discovering-the-beautiful-keyboard-playing-of-robert-hill-by-accident-on-youtube-changed-my-life/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2014 22:14:23 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/08/21/discovering-the-beautiful-keyboard-playing-of-robert-hill-by-accident-on-youtube-changed-my-life/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.mh-freiburg.de/typo3temp/_processed_/csm_prof.-dr.-robert-hill_c7981b16bc.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Robert Hill&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Recently, I completely accidentally discovered a fascinating musician, &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Hill_%28musician%29&#34;&gt;Robert Hill&lt;/a&gt;, on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/user/earlymus&#34;&gt;YouTube&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story is as you might expect: I heard a piece of music, and wanted to find some performance of it by somebody, anybody on YouTube as long as it had a decent user rating (yes, I find ratings actually useful when checking out unfamiliar music), and I happened to come across some random guy&amp;rsquo;s performance, and it was so fascinating that I looked at other uploads of his, subscribed to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/user/earlymus&#34;&gt;his YouTube channel&lt;/a&gt;, and looked him up on the Web to find out who he was!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s especially great that he regularly uploads new videos to his YouTube channel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So who is Robert Hill, and why do I like his performances so much that I&amp;rsquo;m recommending that you check them out?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-i-found-robert-hill&#34;&gt;How I found Robert Hill&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The short story is that I just heard someone playing, on piano, Johann Sebastian Bach&amp;rsquo;s Allemande from the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/French_Suites_%28Bach%29&#34;&gt;French Suite&lt;/a&gt; no. 4 in E-flat, BWV 815.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note that I actually have had very little interest in much of Bach&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Works_for_keyboard_by_J.S._Bach&#34;&gt;keyboard music&lt;/a&gt; and have almost completely ignored them for decades&lt;/em&gt;; there are only two exceptions: the Goldberg Variations and some of the Well-Tempered Clavier.  In particular, I have not listened to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/French_Suites_%28Bach%29&#34;&gt;French Suites&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/English_Suites_%28Bach%29&#34;&gt;English Suites&lt;/a&gt;, or &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Partitas_for_keyboard_%28Bach%29&#34;&gt;Partitas&lt;/a&gt; at all!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But because I just accidentally heard this Allemande played live, and liked it, I wanted to hear it again when I got home, and so I went to YouTube to find it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found a lot of performances online, of course, but I&amp;rsquo;m a sucker for the unusual, so I was particularly interested when I saw in the search results a link to some guy, Robert Hill, performing it on an unusual instrument I had never heard of in my life, a &amp;ldquo;lute-harpsichord&amp;rdquo;. And it got well over a hundred thumb-up ratings and only one thumb-down, so of course I was going to check it out!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I watched the video, and was &lt;em&gt;totally blown away&lt;/em&gt; by the beauty of the performance:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The instrument has a gorgeous sound.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Robert Hill played very expressively, with the full freedom and emotion that treasure.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Structurally, I could hear the different voices and phrases with total clarity because of how he plays.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This single performance made me think that I needed to give old Bach another shot and check out more of his keyboard music.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Listen for yourself (it&amp;rsquo;s less than two minutes long):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/woh8UHdjl1M&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;who-is-robert-hill&#34;&gt;Who is Robert Hill?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did a Web search on Robert Hill and found &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Hill_%28musician%29&#34;&gt;information about him&lt;/a&gt;. He is an American keyboard instrument performer (especially early keyboard instruments such as harpsichord, clavichord, lute-harpsichord, fortepiano) and musicologist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had to search hard to find an actual Web site of his own, and it&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://robert-hill.tripod.com/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. It basically looks like it hasn&amp;rsquo;t been updated since around 2001, which is also his last recording time period on his &lt;a href=&#34;http://robert-hill.tripod.com/id11.html&#34;&gt;discography&lt;/a&gt;. At some point he must have decided to just share his music through YouTube. He is a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mh-freiburg.de/lehrende/person/details/hill/&#34;&gt;music professor in Freiburg&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I just mentioned, my fascination with the performances of Robert Hill comes from his &lt;em&gt;expressiveness&lt;/em&gt;, which comes about from adjustments of tempo, rhetorical gestures, ornamentation, rhythmic sense. He plays a lot more expressively than many keyboard musicians do today, and I like that. I now believe that I was turned off by much of Bach&amp;rsquo;s keyboard music not because of Bach, but because of the relatively bland performances his music has received, especially from modern pianists. Bach was an emotional man living in an emotional age (the Baroque era of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Doctrine_of_the_affections&#34;&gt;affect&lt;/a&gt;), and I feel blessed that musicians like Robert Hill are taking this seriously. There are others, of course, besides him, but I think his performances have a particular edge to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;regular-harpsichord&#34;&gt;Regular harpsichord&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is an example of Robert Hill playing regular harpsichord.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;bach-s-allemande-from-the-partita-in-d-major-bwv-828&#34;&gt;Bach&amp;rsquo;s Allemande from the Partita in D major, BWV 828&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I discovered this beautiful, haunting work of music by Bach for the first time, by sheer accident, when browsing Hill&amp;rsquo;s YouTube channel (live performance from 1997):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/oEoqPSFklkE&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I cannot believe I went four decades without ever having heard this piece in my life. Now I can&amp;rsquo;t get it out of my head.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hill did some extreme things in this performance (tempo modifications and hesitations) that are not to my taste, but I applaud him for having the courage to play from the heart, because much of what he did spoke to mine! He lives dangerously. Maybe that&amp;rsquo;s why he only posts live recording clips to YouTube now rather than make CDs?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;fortepiano&#34;&gt;Fortepiano&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He also plays fortepiano, which is a fascinating instrument I love. I have mentioned my first experience with a fortepiano in college in a blog post earlier this year celebrating the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/03/08/happy-300th-birthday-carl-philipp-emanuel-bach/&#34;&gt;300th birthday of Johann Sebastian&amp;rsquo;s son Carl Philipp Emanuel&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;cpe-bach-s-fantasie-in-f-sharp-minor&#34;&gt;CPE Bach&amp;rsquo;s Fantasie in F-sharp minor&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heck, I had to check out Hill&amp;rsquo;s performance of my favorite CPE Bach keyboard work. In my earlier blog post, I had praised Andreas Staier&amp;rsquo;s performance I discovered in college, but now having heard Hill&amp;rsquo;s, I have another favorite (live from April 2014). This totally plays up Hill&amp;rsquo;s maximally emotive expressive style:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/LOT_nUPvE98&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;js-bach-well-tempered-clavier-selections&#34;&gt;JS Bach: Well-Tempered Clavier selections&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was fascinating to find Hill performing JS Bach on fortepiano; I had never heard anyone playing JS Bach on fortepiano before. I love that he experiments with different styles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The famous WTC I, Prelude in C major, in a fluid, beautiful Romantic-style (vs. Baroque-style) performance he just uploaded a couple of days ago:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/jiBQD0vV5qI&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A totally gorgeous Romantic-style interpretation of the slow Bach WTC I, Prelude in C# minor:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/9iGj4U7nqqY&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love how he makes full use of the expressive possibilities of the fortepiano (power and dynamics and sustain).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;beethoven-s-moonlight-sonata&#34;&gt;Beethoven&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Moonlight&amp;rdquo; sonata&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, he plays Beethoven too, on fortepiano.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that Beethoven did call it &amp;ldquo;sonata quasi fantasia&amp;rdquo; so it should be played freely &amp;ldquo;like a fantasy&amp;rdquo;, freely, and he does this. If you&amp;rsquo;ve only heard it played more &amp;ldquo;squarely&amp;rdquo;, check this out. In this case, I prefer a more subtle freedom than the exaggerated gestures Hill provides, because I feel he disrupts the rhythmic flow too much, so I consider his experiment not a full success, but still, I respect his willingness to go all out:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/6gpmZsqOzZs&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;pianoforte&#34;&gt;Pianoforte!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, of course Robert Hill plays the modern piano too. And I love what he does with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;brahms&#34;&gt;Brahms&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hill brings out the different voices very well, the counterpoint through the thick textures of Brahms. These are truly beautiful performances of some of &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/05/07/happy-birthday-johannes-brahms/&#34;&gt;my favorite piano music of all time, Brahms&amp;rsquo; intermezzi&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A passionate performance of Op. 117, No. 2 in B-flat minor:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/U_rlk4H-DQ0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And Op. 119, No. 1 in B minor (some favorite performances of which I discussed in &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/05/07/happy-birthday-johannes-brahms/&#34;&gt;my blog post last year&lt;/a&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/NOpe_KvXQzA&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is one of the most emotionally raw performances I have ever heard of this intermezzo. Hill makes the most of the suspensions, silences, dissonances, and clashing lines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Discovering the musical performances of Robert Hill on keyboard instruments has been one of the happy surprises of my life this year. Not only has he provided me listening pleasure, but also has sharpened my conception of what the music he plays is about and how to express it. He has forever changed my expectation from myself of how I should play music. I expect that from now on, I will never again hold back from &amp;ldquo;weird&amp;rdquo; interpretations that I feel come from my heart and mind. I don&amp;rsquo;t expect that all my experiments will succeed, but seeing someone else try, and publicly, how can I not do likewise?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Have you recently discovered a musician who has changed your hearing and/or your own playing? Who was it and what did you learn?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The perfect music for Good Friday: some favorite interpretations of Bach&#39;s &#34;Erbarme dich&#34; from the St. Matthew Passion</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/04/18/the-perfect-music-for-good-friday-some-favorite-interpretations-of-bachs-erbarme-dich-from-the-st-matthew-passion/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Apr 2014 07:38:07 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/04/18/the-perfect-music-for-good-friday-some-favorite-interpretations-of-bachs-erbarme-dich-from-the-st-matthew-passion/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;You might assume, since I&amp;rsquo;m talking about &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Good_Friday&#34;&gt;Good Friday&lt;/a&gt;, that I&amp;rsquo;m Christian, and that I&amp;rsquo;m here to talk about my faith. Actually, I&amp;rsquo;m not Christian, but I also believe that Easter is not irrelevant. Here&amp;rsquo;s another non-Christian writing about &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rsablogs.org.uk/2014/socialbrain/meaning-easter-bunnies/&#34;&gt;why Easter matters&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve found it impossible to escape the fact that one of my favorite music composers, Johann Sebastian Bach, was not only Christian, but clearly imbued his music in some way or other with his deep faith. Two years ago, while listening to the opening chorus of his &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/St_Matthew_Passion&#34;&gt;St. Matthew Passion&lt;/a&gt;, which was first performed on Good Friday in 1727, I also saw a thoughtful article by a Muslim, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.telegraph.co.uk/culture/music/opera/9206775/Can-non-Christians-appreciate-Bachs-St-Matthew-Passion.html&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Can non-Christians appreciate Bach&amp;rsquo;s St. Matthew Passion&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;m not here to add to that debate, but to share one of the most moving pieces in the entire history of Western music, the aria &amp;ldquo;Erbarme dich&amp;rdquo; from the St. Matthew Passion. I hope you will check it out, whether you are Christian or not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;erbarme-dich&#34;&gt;Erbarme dich&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The aria features a prominent violin solo part as well as a sung alto solo part. It represents the disciple Peter&amp;rsquo;s anguished and lonely weeping (&amp;ldquo;Have mercy, my Lord&amp;rdquo;) after &lt;a href=&#34;http://biblehub.com/matthew/26-75.htm&#34;&gt;he has three times denied knowing Jesus&lt;/a&gt;, guilty of the most shameful betrayal. The way Bach depicts Peter&amp;rsquo;s emotional state through music is astounding and gripping. You just have to hear it for yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;sophie-gent-damien-guillon&#34;&gt;Sophie Gent, Damien Guillon&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One performance I like features Sophie Gent on violin and Damien Guillon as countertenor. It is a very meditative, pure-sounding performance:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/nZb7FcP84CM&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;unknown-violinist-andreas-scholl&#34;&gt;Unknown violinist, Andreas Scholl&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I do prefer an edgier performance, and here is one that is more urgent and dramatic (audio only, no video of the performance) by Andreas Scholl as countertenor. Scholl really impresses here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/0WLedpz9a40&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can actually follow along in the score by a synchronized video score &lt;a href=&#34;http://musescore.com/rpbouman/scores/141997&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;fredrik-from-anne-sofie-von-otter&#34;&gt;Fredrik From, Anne Sofie von Otter&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An even more urgent performance that might be my favorite is by Fredrik From on violin, Anne Sofie von Otter as mezzo-soprano. I have to confess that I feel that the tempo is a bit fast, but that does, in conjunction with the impeccable articulation and ensemble unity of purpose and style, give a driving force to Peter&amp;rsquo;s anguish. For me, this is the most &lt;em&gt;expressive&lt;/em&gt; of the performances I&amp;rsquo;m listing here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few notes on this video:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This is a video of a recording session, so it is curious to see von Otter in everyday clothing and moving and gesturing while singing for the purpose of a recording, where the audience is not meant to know what she was wearing or how she was privately swaying to the music. I find watching her both mesmerizing and distracting, but I feel that somehow her being free to express herself any way she wanted, sight unseen, might have been a good thing, because hers is truly an emotionally raw performance. &lt;strong&gt;How do you feel about peeking into a recording session where conditions are optimal for the performer and not meant to be seen by the outside world?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The second half of the video is an interview with von Otter about the recording project.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/XR-DFZEBAic&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;unknown-violinist-nathalie-stutzmann&#34;&gt;Unknown violinist, Nathalie Stutzmann&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the topic of visually expressive performances, here is one of Nathalie Stutzmann as contralto and also as conductor. Both she and the violinist are totally into the music, holding nothing back physically as they express it. A rather unusual setting and view, but very powerful:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/Jeil9S2exIU&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;frederick-chiu-on-piano&#34;&gt;Frederick Chiu on piano&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pianist Frederick created his own transcription for piano of the aria. His performance is rather restrained for my taste, but it&amp;rsquo;s something different:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/U3nUvzApF2E&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve shared a few interesting performances of Bach&amp;rsquo;s aria &amp;ldquo;Erbarme dich&amp;rdquo; from his St. Matthew Passion. There are many other performances out there, of course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Which of the performances I linked to are your favorite, and why? Or which ones I did not link to do you prefer, and why? And do you feel you need to be a Christian to appreciate and enjoy this kind of sacred music?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My third year of celebrating Johann Sebastian Bach&#39;s birthday: who was this guy anyway?</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/03/31/my-third-year-of-celebrating-johann-sebastian-bachs-birthday-who-was-this-guy-anyway/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Mar 2014 21:23:31 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/03/31/my-third-year-of-celebrating-johann-sebastian-bachs-birthday-who-was-this-guy-anyway/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is my third year of celebrating the birthday of Johann Sebastian Bach. I did this &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/21/flute-update-celebrating-bachs-birthday/&#34;&gt;in 2012&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/21/my-second-year-of-celebrating-johann-sebastian-bachs-birthday/&#34;&gt;in 2013&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first year, I consciously chose to play some of his music rather than read about it (or about his life). The second year, I played some more of his music, on flute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year, I did something different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, I learned that I had gotten his birthday &amp;ldquo;wrong&amp;rdquo; in the past two years! This year I decided to celebrate the actual birthday (in terms of passing of time) rather than his birth date (which was March 21 according to the old Julian calendar). A minor detail, but symbolic of my intention.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/bach-gardiner.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Bobblehead and Gardiner&amp;#39;s book about J S Bach&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This photo is of &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/20/my-first-bobblehead-doll-guess-who/&#34;&gt;my Bach bobblehead&lt;/a&gt; next to a new book about Bach by John Eliot Gardiner that I just got out of the Carnegie Library today; I had decided that for this year, I would learn more about Bach, the man.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-brand-new-book-about-johann-sebastian-bach&#34;&gt;A brand new book about Johann Sebastian Bach&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A couple of months ago, I came across an interview &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.npr.org/blogs/deceptivecadence/2013/10/25/240780499/bach-unwigged-the-man-behind-the-music&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Bach unwigged: the man behind the music&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; with &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Eliot_Gardiner&#34;&gt;John Eliot Gardiner&lt;/a&gt;, who had finally come out with his long-awaited book about Johann Sebastian Bach, &amp;ldquo;Bach: Music in the Castle of Heaven&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Gardiner has been one of my favorite conductors for a quarter of a century; some of the very first CDs I bought in the late 1980s and early 1990s were of his recordings of Mozart&amp;rsquo;s music with the English Baroque Soloists; I still have them.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I learned that Gardiner tried to get inside the mind of Bach, through his music as well as texts, exploring the possible contradictions within them, and what that might mean about Bach&amp;rsquo;s inner thoughts and feelings about things. Obviously, this is a somewhat subjective exercise, but definitely an intriguing one. Also, Gardiner examined facts about Bach&amp;rsquo;s actual life, including arguments and disputes with authorities, and his basically crazy busy existence in all his professional and personal roles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I saw that interview transcript, I was a little curious, but not enough to rush out and get the book. But then I kept on seeing links to reviews of the book, and most recently, last month, after reading &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nybooks.com/articles/archives/2014/feb/20/why-bach-moves-us/&#34;&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt;, I thought, hmm, maybe sensationalist, but maybe worth checking out: Bach as &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;reformed teenage thug&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo;?!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I put the book on hold at the Carnegie Library and picked it up today. I haven&amp;rsquo;t started reading it yet, but&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;bach-a-passionate-life-a-bbc-documentary-free-to-watch-online&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Bach: A Passionate Life&amp;rdquo;, a BBC documentary (free to watch online)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started with a &amp;ldquo;shortcut&amp;rdquo; to the book: I found a documentary online that Gardiner was involved in. It&amp;rsquo;s still quite long (an hour and a half), but at least you get to see scenery, see musical excerpts being performed, and it&amp;rsquo;s not a 600-page book!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/SOO8IC8_VaY&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;playing-his-music&#34;&gt;Playing his music&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, I had to play some of his music to celebrate also. I pulled out my flute and ran some of his flute sonatas&amp;rsquo; movements along with keyboard backing tracks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-favorite-musical-selection-to-end-the-day-chaconne-from-partita-for-violin-no-2-http-en-wikipedia-org-wiki-partita-for-violin-no-2-28bach-29&#34;&gt;A favorite musical selection to end the day: &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Partita_for_Violin_No._2_%28Bach%29&#34;&gt;Chaconne from partita for violin no. 2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe one day I&amp;rsquo;ll write more about Bach&amp;rsquo;s Chaconne, but for today all I will say is, this is my favorite music of all time of any kind, and what I would hope to leave this world with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And here is my favorite performance, by the wonderful violinist &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gidon_Kremer&#34;&gt;Gidon Kremer&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s way intense:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/DBJPVnJ8m-Y&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m generally more interested in the artistic output of people rather than their life stories, but thanks to the positive and somewhat sensationalist coverage of Gardiner&amp;rsquo;s new book, I took the bait!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Chamber music concert at CMU featured Bach&#39;s Goldberg Variations arranged for string trio</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/11/19/chamber-music-concert-at-cmu-featured-bachs-goldberg-variations-arranged-for-string-trio/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Nov 2013 23:04:37 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/11/19/chamber-music-concert-at-cmu-featured-bachs-goldberg-variations-arranged-for-string-trio/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.cmu.edu/news/stories/archives/2013/november/images/chamber-recital_400x340.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;David Harding, Noah Bendix-Balgley, Lorna McGhee, Amit Peled&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I attended a special &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cmu.edu/news/stories/archives/2013/november/nov8_chambermusic.html&#34;&gt;chamber music concert at CMU&lt;/a&gt; that featured some truly excellent musicians.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-musicians&#34;&gt;The musicians&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was particularly interested in seeing &lt;a href=&#34;http://trioverlaine.com/bios/lorna-mcghee/&#34;&gt;Lorna McGhee&lt;/a&gt;, the current principal flute of the Pittsburgh Symphony Orchestra, and violinist &lt;a href=&#34;http://noahbendixbalgley.com/&#34;&gt;Noah Bendix-Balgley&lt;/a&gt;, the concertmaster, both of whom are relatively recent additions to the orchestra. The other two musicians, also fantastic, were violist and CMU professor &lt;a href=&#34;http://trioverlaine.com/bios/david-harding/&#34;&gt;David Harding&lt;/a&gt; and cellist &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amitpeled.com/&#34;&gt;Amit Peled&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;mozart-s-flute-quartet-no-1-in-d-major&#34;&gt;Mozart&amp;rsquo;s flute quartet no. 1 in D major&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lorna McGhee played in the first part of the program, which was Mozart&amp;rsquo;s first flute quartet. I was very curious how she would approach the work, because I&amp;rsquo;m very picky nowadays about the performance of music from the 18th century or earlier, which I far prefer to be both on period instruments and in period style. The typical &amp;ldquo;modern&amp;rdquo; performance I can no longer enjoy, because of stylistic anachronisms that in my mind invalidate the beauty and freshness of early music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed the quartet&amp;rsquo;s performance of the Mozart. The playing was crisp, lively, and transparent. There was little to quibble with in Lorna McGhee&amp;rsquo;s performance: she played with verve, sensitivity, and clarity. In some phrases she held a legato longer than I would like, but overall I quite liked the performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;bach-s-goldberg-variations-arranged-for-string-trio-by-dmitry-sitkovetsky&#34;&gt;Bach&amp;rsquo;s Goldberg Variations arranged for string trio by Dmitry Sitkovetsky&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bulk of the program was devoted to a performance by the string trio of the entire Goldberg Variations by Bach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past quarter century, I&amp;rsquo;ve listened to countless performances of the Goldberg Variations on all kinds of keyboard instrument, including harpsichord, fortepiano, and modern piano, but until tonight, I hadn&amp;rsquo;t bothered listening to Sitkovetsky&amp;rsquo;s arrangement for string trio that came out several years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought it worked out pretty well tonight, with the three string players working really hard to create dynamism and contrast along with unity in this monumental work. I couldn&amp;rsquo;t help but think that it&amp;rsquo;s actually harder to pull off as a trio than as a solo keyboard piece. What was particularly interesting was visually seeing and hearing (in the different tonal qualities) all the different voices in the music. They are there in the original version, of course, but experiencing the spatial separation just made me even more amazed by Bach&amp;rsquo;s creation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I appreciate the time the four musicians took to perform in this chamber music recital free to the public, and thank you, CMU, for bringing them in for these invigorating performances of Mozart and Bach!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New goals for a new season of the Pittsburgh Recorder Society</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/09/15/new-goals-for-a-new-season-of-the-pittsburgh-recorder-society/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Sep 2013 20:40:25 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/09/15/new-goals-for-a-new-season-of-the-pittsburgh-recorder-society/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-recorder-society-2013-09-15.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Recorder group&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I was delighted to pay my membership dues at the first meeting of the new 2013-2014 season of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/PittsburghRecorderSociety&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Recorder Society&lt;/a&gt;. I hadn&amp;rsquo;t played recorder much since this July&amp;rsquo;s Mideast early music workshop, because of my having &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/08/23/another-unexpected-life-change-one-month-of-learning-to-play-ukulele/&#34;&gt;taken up ukulele the day after I got back from that&lt;/a&gt;; in fact, apart from that week-long workshop, I had not attended any meetings of the Pittsburgh Recorder Society since April (since I had to miss the May one on travel), and although there are meetings all through the summer as well, they only take place in the North Hills, which is kind of far for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As with the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/16/excited-by-the-new-season-of-the-pittsburgh-recorder-society/&#34;&gt;opening of the last season&lt;/a&gt;, we have exciting new plans for this season. And I have my own new plans in addition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;introductions&#34;&gt;Introductions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have some new members, which is always great, so we went around briefly introducing ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;raising-our-level&#34;&gt;Raising our level&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is really inspiring, though, is the large number of formerly &amp;ldquo;new&amp;rdquo; people who joined during last season and have stayed with the group, so that we are in fact growing in numbers. Not only that, we have all improved considerably in the past year. Our director Fred is so excited by how far we have come that he has plans for us to work on harder music and improve our individual technique and ensemble playing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today we started working on music by Bach and Buxtehude: some lovely contrapuntal pieces. I look forward to our polishing up this stuff and really doing the old masters proud!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;bass-recorder&#34;&gt;Bass recorder&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to continuing work on my technique and musicality, I decided that for this season, I would like to do play more on bass recorder. In the past year, I&amp;rsquo;ve gravitated toward deliberately volunteering to play tenor lines, to experience the unique position of bringing out the inner voice as well as making it blend harmoniously with the others. For the new season, I have an interest in focusing on the bass line, to experience being the rock solid underpinning of ensemble music. So I told Fred on my plan, and he&amp;rsquo;ll come up with some stuff for me to get into that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been playing recorder for two and a half years now, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/02/23/celebrating-two-years-of-playing-recorder/&#34;&gt;starting in spring 2011&lt;/a&gt;. I am happy to be continuing on, with the companionship of everyone in the Pittsburgh Recorder Society! Making music together is really special.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>More summer musical partying, and another ten-year-old dream fulfilled!</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/07/04/more-summer-musical-partying/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Jul 2013 23:25:39 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/07/04/more-summer-musical-partying/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I went to a party at Gina&amp;rsquo;s. We hadn&amp;rsquo;t been over in &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/22/playing-tango-on-melodica-and-singing-christmas-carols/&#34;&gt;more than half a year&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had a great time, sharing a ton of food (I made a cabbage dish of my own invention that included onion, garlic, olive oil, cumin seeds, thyme, lime juice, salt and pepper) and hanging out inside as well as in the backyard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I somehow started an arm wrestling competition with the guys, and then we challenged each other to pullups and chinups too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also ended up playing three games of speed chess at a time handicap (my 3 minutes to his 10 minutes). I barely managed to win all three games. The final game should have been a draw, but I won through a swindle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;music&#34;&gt;Music&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I told Henry I was much improved musically since &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/05/03/playing-violin-music-on-flute/&#34;&gt;we played together two months ago&lt;/a&gt;. A lot of things have been falling in place for me. Of course, this only makes me be more ambitious about music to play, and in return, get humbled yet again by how much more improvement is left for me!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;telemann-s-flute-sonata-in-b-minor-tmv-41-h4&#34;&gt;Telemann&amp;rsquo;s flute sonata in B minor, TMV 41:h4&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One piece we tackled was &lt;a href=&#34;http://imslp.org/wiki/Flute_Sonata,_TWV_41:h4_%28Telemann,_Georg_Philipp%29&#34;&gt;Telemann&amp;rsquo;s flute sonata in B minor, TMV 41:h4&lt;/a&gt;. I had only actually gone over the first two movements, so we were both sight reading the last two. That was something of a wreck for me, but gives me homework to do: originally I had not actually planned on learning the whole sonata, now I want to!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;bach-s-flute-sonata-in-e-major-bwv-1035&#34;&gt;Bach&amp;rsquo;s flute sonata in E major, BWV 1035&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another piece we did was &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sonata_in_E_major_for_flute_or_recorder_and_basso_continuo&#34;&gt;Bach&amp;rsquo;s flute sonata in E major, BWV 1035&lt;/a&gt;, which I have already mentioned my obsession with in a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/21/my-second-year-of-celebrating-johann-sebastian-bachs-birthday/&#34;&gt;blog post over three months ago&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: I am still not playing this on Baroque flute or modern flute, because of the difficulty! I have been working with a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.universaledition.com/Sonata-F-major-BWV-1035-for-treble-recorder-basso-continuo-Johann-Sebastian-Bach/composers-and-works/composer/32/work/4801&#34;&gt;recorder transcription for F major&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because I have actually been playing more of this sonata myself in the past months, I have come to change my mind about performances I listed in that blog post! There is nothing like actually studying and playing a piece of music to change one&amp;rsquo;s perception of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My favorite performance so far I&amp;rsquo;ve found on YouTube is by Wilbert Hazelzet on Baroque flute. It&amp;rsquo;s split over two parts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/ZGtjxNeBTAs&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/Oetbg7eRa60&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, Henry and I ran through the sonata. Again, I had not actually ever run through the final movement, so it was an embarrassing sight reading scramble for me. But he really enjoyed the last movement, and I did too, and realized that I wanted to actually study and practice it. It&amp;rsquo;s funny how I came to enjoy this movement much more after having tried to play it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;gabriel-fauré-après-un-rêve-fulfilling-my-ten-year-old-dream&#34;&gt;Gabriel Fauré, Après un rêve: fulfilling my ten-year-old dream&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After all the Baroque stuff, I decided to play something different with Henry. I pulled out my modern flute, and we did Fauré&amp;rsquo;s song &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trois_m%C3%A9lodies,_Op.7_%28Faur%C3%A9%29&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Après un rêve&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; in a flute and piano arrangement that I bought in 2003.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a story I have never told anyone until now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I bought that score because I was in love with the song, but never imagined that I would be able to sing it properly. So I thought to myself that if I ever played flute again (recall that the last time I had touched flute was twenty years earlier, in childhood), my goal would be to at least be able to play &lt;em&gt;this one song&lt;/em&gt; on flute reasonably close to how I feel it should be played or sung. (There is also a second piece for flute that I wanted to play as well. I will reveal it once I have actually played it with someone.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ever since I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/09/taking-up-flute-again-after-decades/&#34;&gt;got back to flute almost two years ago&lt;/a&gt;, &amp;ldquo;Après un rêve&amp;rdquo; has been on my mind as well as on my shelf, and as a measure of progres, I have actually periodically pulled it out to try to play it. For well over a year, I could not play it anywhere near how I want it to sound. Here&amp;rsquo;s a piano accompaniment track I&amp;rsquo;ve been using in the past months:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/EAAe0GDO928&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eight months ago, I fulfilled a childhood dream, by throwing myself into singing, and in fact, one song I did sing was &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/11/17/a-childhood-dream-come-true-i-am-now-finally-singing-for-real/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Après un rêve&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;! I still don&amp;rsquo;t sing it as well as I&amp;rsquo;d like, and will continue working on singing it, but singing in general has had a tremendous positive transferring effect on my flute playing! I am now almost able to play &amp;ldquo;Après un rêve&amp;rdquo; how I want (the remaining difficulties being cleaning up the high passages in the arrangement as well as controlling the breath there as well). In any case, I went and played it with Henry for the first time, and it wasn&amp;rsquo;t horrible. In summary, ten years after I bought that score with wishful thinking, I made my dream reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, here&amp;rsquo;s a nice performance on flute that inspires me:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/95f57lYWgks&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;roland-de-lassus-http-en-wikipedia-org-wiki-orlande-de-lassus-as-recorder-duets&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Orlande_de_Lassus&#34;&gt;Roland de Lassus&lt;/a&gt;, as recorder duets&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The surprise of the day was when, after watching me mess around with bass recorder, Henry got the idea of playing recorder duets with me. I hadn&amp;rsquo;t known that he played recorder. He said he could play recorders in C (soprano and tenor), and since I didn&amp;rsquo;t have my tenor on me, I gave him my soprano recorder. He picked up a book and went through it to find some early music duets that we could do on recorders. We did some with soprano and bass, then I switched to alto and we did soprano and alto for the rest we found in the book. It was immense fun!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/recorder-duets-with-henry.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Henry and Franklin on recorders&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel blessed to have the opportunity and inspiration from Henry to continue improving at playing music, and stretch myself further. I have come so far in the past two years.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My second year of celebrating Johann Sebastian Bach&#39;s birthday: a tale of accidental love</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/03/21/my-second-year-of-celebrating-johann-sebastian-bachs-birthday/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Mar 2013 20:55:43 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/03/21/my-second-year-of-celebrating-johann-sebastian-bachs-birthday/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Last year I reported on celebrating the birthday of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Johann_Sebastian_Bach&#34;&gt;Johann Sebastian Bach, born in 1685&lt;/a&gt;. I was still just barely beginning to play the flute seriously then, and I read through some music of his transcribed for flute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have progressed tremendously on flute in the past year; the difference between having played flute for a few months and playing it for a few months &lt;em&gt;plus a whole year&lt;/em&gt; is really huge. So this year, to celebrate, I played for myself some of Bach&amp;rsquo;s actual music written for flute: selections from his flute sonatas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/20/my-first-bobblehead-doll-guess-who/&#34;&gt;my Bach bobblehead&lt;/a&gt; still watches over me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/bach-and-franklin.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;J S Bach bobblehead and Franklin&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I have a tale of accidental love to tell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;falling-instantly-in-love-with-bach-s-flute-sonata-in-e-major-bwv-1035-first-movement&#34;&gt;Falling instantly in love with Bach&amp;rsquo;s flute sonata in E major, BWV 1035, first movement&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;alto-recorder&#34;&gt;Alto recorder&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2011, I started playing alto &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/recorder/&#34;&gt;recorder&lt;/a&gt;, teaching myself and joining the Pittsburgh Recorder Society. I first completed the two-volume method by Orr, over the course of approximately two months, February through April 2011. Then I moved on to the two-volume method by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.aswltd.com/adultmet.htm#begin&#34;&gt;Mario Duschenes&lt;/a&gt;. One of the great things about the second volume of the Duschenes method is that it contains excerpts of real music. One excerpt that came up was the first movement of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sonata_in_E_major_for_flute_or_recorder_and_basso_continuo&#34;&gt;Bach&amp;rsquo;s flute sonata in E major&lt;/a&gt;, transposed for alto recorder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had never heard this music before, so I looked for recordings of it. This was not so easy! The reason is that I kept on finding recordings of the original flute version, but at the time, I was not yet playing the flute, only recorder, and only interested in recorder. Then I found a recording by &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michala_Petri&#34;&gt;Michala Petri&lt;/a&gt; and Keith Jarrett. So I worked on this &lt;em&gt;adagio ma non tanto&lt;/em&gt; first movement and periodically played along with Petri&amp;rsquo;s recording.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, I didn&amp;rsquo;t much like Petri&amp;rsquo;s performance at all: it lacked in articulation, contrast, and expression:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/809awZvxx80&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;falling-in-love&#34;&gt;Falling in love&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What really got to me was this passionate performance I found on YouTube on recorder by Maurice Steger. There are idiosyncratic things he does that I don&amp;rsquo;t do, but there is no doubt about his commitment to full emotional expression:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/_MGBQy33pkE&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I couldn&amp;rsquo;t explain why, but seeing this video was one of the first times I really fell in love with Baroque music. To me, the long phrases, chromaticism, and Bach&amp;rsquo;s own style of ornamentation give a meditative expression of melancholy and longing. I poured myself into playing this on recorder, inspired by Maurice Steger&amp;rsquo;s passion for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;baroque-flute-vs-modern-flute&#34;&gt;Baroque flute vs. modern flute?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/09/taking-up-flute-again-after-decades/&#34;&gt;accidentally started playing modern flute again in late 2011&lt;/a&gt;, I eventually looked up actual flute recordings of Bach&amp;rsquo;s flute sonatas. I completely stopped playing Bach transposed for the recorder. I just felt that, despite Maurice Steger&amp;rsquo;s example, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/17/flute-versus-recorder/&#34;&gt;I could not get everything I wanted out of the recorder&lt;/a&gt;, and I wanted to move to flute. However, the modern flute seemed not so well suited to the music. &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/30/bought-a-baroque-flute/&#34;&gt;Eventually, I bought a Baroque flute&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, because Bach on the &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/baroque-flute/&#34;&gt;Baroque flute&lt;/a&gt; has remained much more difficult for me to play than on the modern flute, I have resigned myself to mostly playing Bach&amp;rsquo;s flute music on modern flute, while trying to keep the music crisply articulated and with minimal vibrato.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(I played the first movement of Bach&amp;rsquo;s flute sonata in E minor, BWV 1034, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/26/music-i-just-played-for-the-first-time-recorder-sonata-tangos/&#34;&gt;at a party earlier this year&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some videos illustrating a little bit of how the sounds and interpretations may differ.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;baroque-flute-jed-wentz&#34;&gt;Baroque flute: Jed Wentz&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A performance by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jedwentz.com/jedwentz.com/Welcome.html&#34;&gt;Jed Wentz&lt;/a&gt; on Baroque flute:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/m0CiLHDH5FQ&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;update-of-2013-07-04&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-07-04)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I no longer like this performance as much as I did initially. It is a bit frantic, with some blazing fast playing that I would like to be a bit slower.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;modern-flute-emmanuel-pahud&#34;&gt;Modern flute: Emmanuel Pahud&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A performance by Emmanuel Pahud on modern flute, but playing with fine sensitivity to elements of Baroque style:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/YyePpU1_lKo&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;update-of-2013-07-04-1&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-07-04)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My, taste changes in three months: I no longer like this performance. It is simultaneously still too smooth and too restrained.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;another-modern-flutist-nikos-nikopoulos&#34;&gt;Another modern flutist: Nikos Nikopoulos&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A random modern flutist playing in a bland legato-all-the-time style:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/uc3ck2MayjE&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bach&amp;rsquo;s birthday is a good time to remember and re-create and re-experience what was beautiful and special about the music of the Baroque era, before changes in taste and style came along in the late 18th century and onward. For me, the flute sonatas will always be a source of rediscovery and exploration of the Baroque world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-07-04-2&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-07-04)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have more &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/07/04/more-summer-musical-partying/&#34;&gt;thoughts on this sonata&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Music I just played for the first time: recorder sonata, tangos</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/01/26/music-i-just-played-for-the-first-time-recorder-sonata-tangos/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Jan 2013 23:03:10 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/01/26/music-i-just-played-for-the-first-time-recorder-sonata-tangos/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Abby and I went to Henry&amp;rsquo;s birthday party, marking an important anniversary: we attended his birthday party for the first time a year ago, and that began &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/01/27/a-new-friends-very-musical-birthday-party-changed-my-life/&#34;&gt;one of the most important developments in my entire life, my decision to make music playing an integral part of my life&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of music happened, as usual, and this time, unlike a year ago, I played. What a year it&amp;rsquo;s been!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;handel-s-recorder-sonata-in-g-minor&#34;&gt;Handel&amp;rsquo;s recorder sonata in G minor&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided to finally give a shot at playing, for the first time outside of home, &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Recorder_sonata_in_G_minor_%28HWV_360%29&#34;&gt;Handel&amp;rsquo;s recorder sonata in G minor, op. 1 no. 2&lt;/a&gt;, me being on alto recorder and Henry on piano.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This piece is extremely special to me, because I discovered it by accident as one of the first &amp;ldquo;real&amp;rdquo; recorder pieces that I started working on when I was just a beginner at recorder. A method book I was using at the time, one and half years ago, in May 2011, by Mario Duschenes, had a section with the title &amp;ldquo;How to practise a difficult piece&amp;rdquo;, and the example and suggestions on practice was the Andante from this recorder sonata by Handel. I hunted down the complete score of the recorder sonata and started to learn the whole thing. I did this intermittently over the course of a year or so while doing other things, but always had the intention of at some point polishing it up for actual performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main holdup eventually was that I wanted to be able to really express myself well, and incorporate my own ornamentations. To this end, I made some study of Baroque ornamentation and checked out a book I found in the library, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.oup.com/us/catalog/general/subject/Music/PerformanceStudiesAppliedMusic/WindsBrass/?view=usa&amp;amp;ci=9780198790013&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Playing Recorder Sonatas&amp;rdquo;, by Anthony Rowland-Jones&lt;/a&gt;. I have found this book quite useful as a guide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I had fun reading through this with Henry. Eventually I want to play it for real, as performance, in a setting with harpsichord continuo, rather than with piano.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-02-23&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-02-23)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ended up performing the recorder sonata with bass recorder accompaniment at the Pittsburgh Recorder Society&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/02/23/celebrating-two-years-of-playing-recorder/&#34;&gt;Midwinter Musical Feast&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;bach-s-flute-sonata-in-e-minor-bwv-1034&#34;&gt;Bach&amp;rsquo;s flute sonata in E minor, BWV 1034&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I played music by Johann Sebastian Bach on flute for the first time outside the home. I&amp;rsquo;ve held back because I feel like I&amp;rsquo;m still not doing the music justice, but decided I can&amp;rsquo;t hide forever my love of Bach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On modern flute with Henry on piano, I played the first movement of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sonata_in_E_minor_for_flute_or_recorder_and_basso_continuo&#34;&gt;Bach&amp;rsquo;s flute sonata in E minor&lt;/a&gt;. I would have considered playing it on Baroque flute, but the piano as well as the the party environment &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/21/my-first-time-singing-bossa-nova-also-a-temporary-farewell-to-baroque-flute/&#34;&gt;is not friendly for Baroque flute&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-03-21&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-03-21)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Bach&amp;rsquo;s birthday in 2013, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/21/my-second-year-of-celebrating-johann-sebastian-bachs-birthday/&#34;&gt;I reflected on&lt;/a&gt; how the very same recorder method book by Duschenes I mentioned above was the impetus for my getting into Bach flute sonatas!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;tangos&#34;&gt;Tangos&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I played tango on flute for the first time ever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/11/17/a-childhood-dream-come-true-i-am-now-finally-singing-for-real/&#34;&gt;sing tango for the first time recently&lt;/a&gt;, and also played &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/22/playing-tango-on-melodica-and-singing-christmas-carols/&#34;&gt;tango on melodica for the first time&lt;/a&gt;, but had not yet dared to play on flute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, I did, and not only that, one of them ended up becoming a flute-violin duet, in which Barbara (whom I met exactly a year ago at the last birthday party) played violin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story is that several months ago, in October, I got hold of a book of tangos for violin duet. I judged that with some modifications I could play the first part on flute, if only I could simultaneously find someone on violin (and someone on piano). The opportunity did not spontaneously arise until today!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, I played &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/El_Choclo&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;El Choclo&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; with just Henry on piano.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then Barbara joined in on violin and we played &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Por_una_Cabeza&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Por una Cabeza&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; with Henry. This was one of the most satisfying experiences of my life. It&amp;rsquo;s one thing playing duets with Henry, but it&amp;rsquo;s another having three to really fill in the harmonies and textures and two melodic voices playing off each other. Wow. I need to do this more often. And I have to confess, I never tire of this particular classic tango, because it&amp;rsquo;s so dramatic and expressive, and has that suddenly shift from major to the lyrical chorus in minor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;more-bach-double-violin-concerto&#34;&gt;More Bach: double violin concerto&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Barbara was so excited that she goaded me into trying to sight read &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Concerto_for_Two_Violins_%28Bach%29&#34;&gt;Bach&amp;rsquo;s double violin concerto&lt;/a&gt; on the spot together with Henry. I knew I was probably going to cause a minor disaster, but heck, it&amp;rsquo;s a party, we&amp;rsquo;re just having fun. And indeed, I got confused or lost many times, because first of all, I&amp;rsquo;m not so great on flute right now at all, and second, this music was for violin and some stuff was not very suitable for flute and also needed me to go up an octave all of a sudden because the violin has a bigger range. So, it was a struggle for me, but I enjoyed some nice moments in the less frantic slow movement, where the two melodic voices really combine beautifully.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, it was all in fun, Bach forgive me!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As at all of Henry&amp;rsquo;s parties, I strive to go to them prepared to do something better and new and interesting musically, for our enjoyment as well as that of the other guests. I had a great time again. I am so grateful for the past year of getting to know Henry and his sharing the gift of music with me!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Report on CMU Baroque Ensemble concert, with Stephen Schultz on Baroque flute</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/11/18/report-on-cmu-baroque-ensemble-concert-with-stephen-schultz-on-baroque-flute/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Nov 2012 20:53:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/11/18/report-on-cmu-baroque-ensemble-concert-with-stephen-schultz-on-baroque-flute/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I attended a free concert of the CMU Baroque Ensemble concert for the second time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/04/29/attending-my-first-cmu-baroque-ensemble-concert/&#34;&gt;My first time&lt;/a&gt;, several months ago, I enjoyed as my main attraction Bach&amp;rsquo;s Brandenburg concerto no. 2; this time, although the Brandenburg concerto no. 3 was performed, it was not the main draw for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I really looked forward to was simply seeing Stephen Schultz playing Baroque flute (amplified), premiering a new piece by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nancygalbraith.com/&#34;&gt;Nancy Galbraith&lt;/a&gt;, &amp;ldquo;Effervescent Air&amp;rdquo;. I had never seen him playing Baroque flute before, other than a demo of a few seconds when I was taking his course &amp;ldquo;Survey of Western Musical History&amp;rdquo; in 2006. That was actually the very first time I had ever seen a Baroque flute, and the first time I learned that anyone still played this instrument.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/cmu-baroque-2012-11-18.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Stephen Schulz&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed the concert. The standard Baroque pieces were performed with energy, and the newly composed piece for electric, amplified Baroque flute and piano, with orchestra, was a pleasant, fluttery soundscape, with some lovely textures as well as special echo effects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can listen to &amp;ldquo;Effervescent Air&amp;rdquo; here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;100%&#34; height=&#34;450&#34; scrolling=&#34;no&#34; frameborder=&#34;no&#34; src=&#34;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fapi.soundcloud.com%2Fplaylists%2F4222492&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I look forward to hearing more new music composed for Baroque flute in future CMU Baroque Ensemble concerts!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thank you, Glenn Gould, for introducing me to Schönberg!</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/09/25/thank-you-glenn-gould/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Sep 2012 19:16:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/09/25/thank-you-glenn-gould/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://media.npr.org/assets/img/2012/09/11/gould-d36370bc547843a1b3c7ab16e31373b751a52b05-s3.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Glenn Gould at piano&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Today would have been the 80th birthday of the eccentric Canadian pianist &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Glenn_Gould&#34;&gt;Glenn Gould&lt;/a&gt;, who actually died at age 50 in 1982, before I ever knew about him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was nice to see an article about &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.npr.org/blogs/deceptivecadence/2012/09/25/160957849/glenn-gould-beyond-bachs-goldberg-variations&#34;&gt;Gould playing music other than the Bach he is mostly known for&lt;/a&gt;. Not surprisingly, my own first exposure to Glenn Gould was through his recordings of the music of Bach. I was an undergraduate and one of my friends was a big fan of Gould&amp;rsquo;s and shared some recordings with me, including both the 1955 and 1982 recordings of the Goldberg Variations, and I was hooked by his uniquely quirky, rhythmic style. But my friend, being such a Gould fan, also had recordings of Gould playing anything else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be honest, I had mixed feelings about almost all of his recordings, because he so imposed his personal notions of how he wanted composers&amp;rsquo; music to sound; sometimes I could not tell whether he was being serious or being deliberately annoying, because there was so much I &lt;em&gt;loved&lt;/em&gt; and so much I &lt;em&gt;hated&lt;/em&gt;. He was never just plain solid and boring: there was no middle of the road for him. He brought his full love or boredom to everything he did. Much of his Mozart and Beethoven were terrible, to my ears (while some of it pretty good). His Brahms was uneven. Actually, much of what he did was simply &lt;em&gt;perverse&lt;/em&gt;, for lack of a better word. But in any case, I love that Gould did what he felt compelled to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;arnold-schönberg&#34;&gt;Arnold Schönberg&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/a/ad/Arnold_Schoenberg_la_1948.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Arnold Schönberg&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Fascinatingly, it was through Glenn Gould that I came to enjoy (some of) the music of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arnold_Schoenberg&#34;&gt;Arnold Schönberg&lt;/a&gt;. I have to confess that I don&amp;rsquo;t (yet?) understand or like Schönberg&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Twelve-tone_technique&#34;&gt;twelve-tone&lt;/a&gt; music, but I rather enjoy his very brief free &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Atonality&#34;&gt;atonal&lt;/a&gt; piano music, which Gould played with such love that it reflected the late &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/German_Romanticism&#34;&gt;German romantic&lt;/a&gt; roots and sensibilities that were Schönberg&amp;rsquo;s heritage. The three &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Drei_Klavierst%C3%BCcke&#34;&gt;Klavierstücke Op. 11&lt;/a&gt;, that I discovered purely from browsing through Gould&amp;rsquo;s recordings as lent to me in college, are beautiful and expressive works, deeply &lt;em&gt;emotional&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My favorite of the three are the first and second, because the third is too violent and chaotic for me to really enjoy. As an undergrad, the second was my favorite, but now the first is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can click on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.npr.org/blogs/deceptivecadence/2012/09/25/160957849/glenn-gould-beyond-bachs-goldberg-variations&#34;&gt;the link to the article&lt;/a&gt; to listen to the track of Gould playing No. 1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it is not an accident that Gould took to this music, because I perceive him also to be a paradoxical &lt;em&gt;Romantic&lt;/em&gt; at heart who superficially seemed to reject Romanticism, for Romantic reasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;other-recordings&#34;&gt;Other recordings&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.bruceduffie.com/pollini8.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Maurizio Pollini&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Actually, since my first discovery of this music, I prefer other performances to those of Gould. I like &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maurizio_Pollini&#34;&gt;Maurizio Pollini&lt;/a&gt;: below are performances of all three by him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/DUHn7knkrLc&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/H-j497I2DfA&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/8vHNcNrojDM&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I celebrated Glenn Gould&amp;rsquo;s birthday not by playing any of his Bach recordings I have, but by enjoying him playing Schönberg and other composers, and listening to others also play Schönberg. I am grateful to Gould for all he did to share with the world his personal approach to music.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My first bobblehead doll: guess who?</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/09/20/my-first-bobblehead-doll-guess-who/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Sep 2012 09:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/09/20/my-first-bobblehead-doll-guess-who/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/j-s-bach-bobblehead.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Johann Sebastian Bach bobblehead&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I now own my first &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bobblehead&#34;&gt;bobblehead doll&lt;/a&gt;! Abby was reluctant to let me take him home, but I argued that he would inspire me in the playing of his music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So &lt;em&gt;who&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;pittsburgh-music-alliance-launch-party&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Music Alliance launch party&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;about&#34;&gt;About&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburghmusicalliance.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Music Alliance&lt;/a&gt; had a launch party that Abby and I attended, held at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.contemporarycraft.org/&#34;&gt;Contemporary Craft&lt;/a&gt; in the Strip.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Pittsburgh Music Alliance is a new collaboration of five Pittsburgh music organizations for the purpose of increasing their audience:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bachchoirpittsburgh.org/&#34;&gt;Bach Choir of Pittsburgh&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pittsburghcamerata.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Camerata&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.chathambaroque.org/&#34;&gt;Chatham Baroque&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rbsp.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Renaissance and Baroque&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pittsburghchambermusic.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Chamber Music Society&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can find more information on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/PittsburghMusicAlliance&#34;&gt;Facebook page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;food-and-information-tables&#34;&gt;Food and information tables&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/189232_472125132808229_857638441_n.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Food and tables&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As we wandered around at the party, we sampled the food and checked out the tables of the five organizations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(There are &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/media/set/?set=a.472125112808231.106189.197956923558386&amp;amp;type=3&#34;&gt;photos of the party here&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;live-music&#34;&gt;Live music&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/199595_10151047722351513_1243992903_n.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Recorder quartet&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We arrived in time to see my &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/recorder/&#34;&gt;recorder&lt;/a&gt; friends perform as a recorder quartet, playing a variety of selections. Fred, Helen, Mike, and Annie were delightful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Afterwards, members of the five music organizations took turns performing for us. Unfortunately, the acoustic situation was quite poor amidst the party conversations going on everywhere, but I enjoyed watching the people who sang and played for us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-bobbleheads&#34;&gt;The bobbleheads&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We saw approximately ten bobbleheads, each in its unopened box, sitting around. I got very excited. It turned out that they were being given away. I secretly always wanted one since seeing my friend Henry with one on top of his piano; he had one of Beethoven:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/beethoven-bobblehead.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Beethoven bobblehead&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;By the bobbleheads, there was a sheet saying something like, &amp;ldquo;Name a piece I wrote and you can take me home.&amp;rdquo; It seemed that nobody was really enforcing this, but when I offered to take one, I said the bobblehead would help me as I worked on the composer&amp;rsquo;s [flute sonatas]().&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;notes-on-johann-sebastian-bach-s-flute-sonatas&#34;&gt;Notes on Johann Sebastian Bach&amp;rsquo;s flute sonatas&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The composer whose bobblehead I got was, of course, &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/johann-sebastian-bach/&#34;&gt;Johann Sebastian Bach&lt;/a&gt;, a hero of mine in the past year during which I&amp;rsquo;ve gradually fallen in love with Baroque music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-instrument&#34;&gt;What instrument?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am faced with a conundrum when trying to play Bach&amp;rsquo;s flute sonatas: &lt;em&gt;what instrument should I use to play this music?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the case of his son, &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carl_Philipp_Emanuel_Bach&#34;&gt;CPE Bach&lt;/a&gt;, two months ago in a recital &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/28/my-first-appearance-on-a-music-recital-program/&#34;&gt;I played a movement of CPE Bach&amp;rsquo;s solo flute sonata&lt;/a&gt; using a modern flute. I feel that the nature of CPE Bach&amp;rsquo;s music, more dramatic and agitated, makes the modern flute a reasonable instrument for the piece; I feel that it is definitely reasonable to play the music on a Baroque flute instead, but that I actually prefer it on modern flute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Plus, CPE Bach&amp;rsquo;s music is much easier to play on modern flute.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, Johann Sebastian Bach&amp;rsquo;s flute sonatas, although I prefer them on Baroque flute than to modern flute, are much harder to play on Baroque flute. It turns out that I dislike almost all recordings I&amp;rsquo;ve come across of this music on modern flute, with one exception: the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pahudbach.com/&#34;&gt;recordings&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/emmanuel-pahud/&#34;&gt;Emmanuel Pahud&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;my-decision&#34;&gt;My decision&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve made an unpleasant decision. I work on the slow, easy movements of the flute sonatas on Baroque flute, and I don&amp;rsquo;t currently work on the harder movements at all. I&amp;rsquo;m still far worse on Baroque flute than on modern flute, and those fast movements are beyond me on Baroque flute. And I don&amp;rsquo;t really want to play the music on modern flute. This is just my personal choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a great time at the Pittsburgh Music Alliance season launch party. It was inspiring to see my recorder friends playing, and to see others in the early music community performing with enthusiasm. (Seeing people singing as an ensemble even got me thinking about getting into that sometime maybe.) If you enjoy fresh, vital performances of early music, check out the five organizations mentioned!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I&amp;rsquo;m grateful to now be the proud owner of a Johann Sebastian Bach bobblehead doll. Every time I see him, I remember that I must play his music with verve and soul, because he&amp;rsquo;s watching.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The passion of Bach&#39;s Air on the G String: three very different interpretations</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/09/14/passion-of-bachs-air-on-the-g-string-three-different-interpretations/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Sep 2012 06:45:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/09/14/passion-of-bachs-air-on-the-g-string-three-different-interpretations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, while driving home from work, I had my radio on, tuned to Pittsburgh&amp;rsquo;s classical music station, &lt;a href=&#34;http://wqed.org/fm&#34;&gt;WQED FM&lt;/a&gt;, as usual, and I immediately recognized the piece that was being performed. I listened with curiosity and then anger and disappointment as I made my way home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a movement from one of Johann Sebastian Bach&amp;rsquo;s orchestra suites
(Orchestral Suite No. 3 in D major, BWV 1068), the movement that has been popularized in the form of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Air_on_the_G_String&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Air on the G String&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think this piece is a good litmus test of how we perceive and appreciate Baroque music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2015-06-10&#34;&gt;(Update of 2015-06-10)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many readers have commented on this post, and therefore I have written
an &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2015/06/10/revisiting-bachs-air-on-g-string-from-a-singing-and-dancing-viewpoint/&#34;&gt;important sequel&lt;/a&gt; to this post, 3 years later!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-listening-test&#34;&gt;A listening test&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please click around on the YouTube videos to get a taste of different ways of performing the Air from Bach&amp;rsquo;s suite. I&amp;rsquo;ve embedded three very different interpretations, each with its own qualities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Which do you like most of the three?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Which do you dislike most of the three?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People can get very emotional about differences in musical taste, and I&amp;rsquo;m not here to start an argument (just look at any of the comment threads on YouTube videos and you see what I mean!), but rather a discussion. I recognize that your choices might be &lt;em&gt;completely different&lt;/em&gt; from mine, and I&amp;rsquo;m &lt;em&gt;completely OK&lt;/em&gt; with that, and hope that you might be &lt;em&gt;completely OK&lt;/em&gt; with my choices also!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/e2OoJamNLMQ&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/SZ6nS1wau0I&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/VEpCjxOJgms&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;objective-comparisons&#34;&gt;Objective comparisons&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;stokowski&#34;&gt;Stokowski&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first version is an arrangement by Leopold Stokowski, from maybe the 1950s. It is a very slow, richly scored, melodically oriented version with emphasis on a deep, swelling vibrato-filled string sound. Different lines are given emphasis, one after another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;croatian-baroque-ensemble&#34;&gt;Croatian Baroque Ensemble&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second version is a live performance from 2010 by the Croatian Baroque Ensemble. It is played on period instruments, very briskly, with a prominent harpsichord continuo, with minimal vibrato in the strings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;karajan&#34;&gt;Karajan&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third version is from a recording by Herbert von Karajan and the Berlin Philharmonic, from maybe the 1980s. It is marked by a blend of legato voices, with an emphasis on unified beautiful tone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-your-preference-means&#34;&gt;What your preference means&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, I would like to point out that of these three versions, although I have a clear personal ranking, there are many things I don&amp;rsquo;t like about my favorite version of the three. If I were setting up a performance of this piece, I would make many different interpretive choices. Therefore, my indication of my preference is not an endorsement of every element of my preferred version.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The style classification system I&amp;rsquo;m using here is directly taken from the fascinating book by &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bruce_Haynes&#34;&gt;Bruce Haynes&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.oup.com/us/catalog/general/subject/Music/MusicHistoryWestern/EarlyMusicMedievalRenaissance/~~/dmlldz11c2EmY2k9OTc4MDE5NTE4OTg3Mg==&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The End of Early Music&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. In fact, the Air from the G String is used as an example in his book. My observations and descriptions here, however, are my own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;stokowski-the-romantic-style&#34;&gt;Stokowski: the Romantic style&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you liked the Stokowski best, you favor the old-fashioned Romantic style, music played with a long heart-throbbing melodic line and rich accompaniment. Soulful cellos are your thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you dislike, you have a problem with odd composer-unintended arrangements, super-slow sentimentality, and personal idiosyncrasies such as slowing down to savor a particular romantic moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;croatian-baroque-ensemble-the-period-style&#34;&gt;Croatian Baroque Ensemble: the Period style&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you like the Croatian Baroque Ensemble best, you favor a quick rhythm and counterpoint, with an emphasis on dissonance, as the carrier of heightened emotion. You like music to be played as though spoken, with many separated phrases, as though question and answer pairs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you dislike, you don&amp;rsquo;t like the rougher sound of non-vibrato violins, the dissonant attacks, and most of all, the speed and detachment of phrases that removes the relaxing, romantic mood you prefer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;karajan-the-modern-style&#34;&gt;Karajan: the Modern style&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you like Karajan, you focus on clear, beautiful tone, and seamless integration of instruments, avoidance of roughness and imperfection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you dislike, you find the endless legato lifeless and missing the extra edge of passion, and you perceive that the emphasis on integration detracts from the clarity of individual voices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-preferences&#34;&gt;My preferences&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I prefer the Period approach of the Croatian Baroque Ensemble. I find it the most poignant and passionate of the three selections. I like the pauses of silence, the emphasis and swelling into the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bach.org/bach101/instrumental/3rd_suite_orch_bwv1068.html&#34;&gt;dissonant moments&lt;/a&gt;. The tempo is fast enough that the phrases feel like speaking and breathing. This is the Bach I have fallen in love with and have been enjoying playing myself in the past two years on &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/recorder/&#34;&gt;recorder&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/baroque-flute/&#34;&gt;Baroque flute&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, I have an honest, real emotional response to the Romantic approach of Stokowski, however perverse and bizarre it may be. It&amp;rsquo;s clearly nothing resembling what Bach would have expected in a performance. But on its own, it&amp;rsquo;s an ingenious product of Stokowski&amp;rsquo;s personal vision. You could say that Stokowski stole Bach&amp;rsquo;s notes and then composed his own thing using them as a starting point, changing everything else (from instrumentation to tempo to dynamics to articulation). I respect that. So even though part of me is horrified by this kind of plagiarism, part of me is also excited and wish that more of this perverse creativity would happen today. The Romantic approach went out of style decades ago, however, in favor of the Modern approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, the Modern approach basically leaves me cold. Yes, the Karajan version was the one I heard in my car while driving home from work. I felt angry and sad by how the performance did not really inspire me. It was boring and muddy to me. Karajan may have been playing the pitch values of the notes the way Bach wrote them down, and not &amp;ldquo;disrespectfully&amp;rdquo; messed with the elements that Stokowski eagerly transformed and added to, but to me, his performance was more of a boring lecture to sit through than something that made me sit up and engage with the music. &lt;em&gt;It was muzak to me.&lt;/em&gt; That was my reaction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;period-contrast-ton-koopman-with-amsterdam-baroque-orchestra&#34;&gt;Period contrast: Ton Koopman with Amsterdam Baroque Orchestra&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I mentioned earlier that there are many things I would do differently than the Croation Baroque Ensemble. The Period approach, like the Romantic and Modern ones, is not a single interpretation: it&amp;rsquo;s an entire approach with much diversity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a live performance in Period style that is noticeably different from the Croatian Baroque Ensemble performance. It is slower and sweeter, for example. But it also has more contrast between the long legato lines and the detached figures within them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/NlT8yeEYbMs&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;which-do-i-like-better&#34;&gt;Which do I like better?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of the two sample Period performances, which do I prefer?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Who knows??&lt;/em&gt; When there are things I like and dislike about both? At some point (I try to make this quick), I stop being a listener or critic, and feel the need to &lt;em&gt;stop listening&lt;/em&gt;, and go to work &lt;em&gt;myself&lt;/em&gt; on how I would do things very differently, from anyone else, as a performer, to express my personal feeling for the music. That is why I&amp;rsquo;ve switched in the past two years from being a listener to being a performer. I can&amp;rsquo;t sit around pining away waiting from someone to play something the way I really like it. I have to do the work myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope this little exercise is helpful in clarifying some of the differences in the approach to performing and enjoying Baroque era music. The question of how to best deal with music from the 1700s is one that everyone who plays or listens to it has to grapple with, whether implicitly or explicitly. I think Haynes&amp;rsquo; basic framework of three different styles is a useful one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Myself, in the past year or two during which I have suddenly fallen in love with Baroque music, after a lifetime of not really liking it at all, I have been persuaded by the Period approach, both as a listener and now also as a performer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2015-06-10-1&#34;&gt;(Update of 2015-06-10)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many readers have commented on this post, and therefore I have written
an &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2015/06/10/revisiting-bachs-air-on-g-string-from-a-singing-and-dancing-viewpoint/&#34;&gt;important sequel&lt;/a&gt; to this post, 3 years later!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Attending my first CMU Baroque Ensemble concert: enjoying Bach&#39;s Brandenburg 2</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/04/29/attending-my-first-cmu-baroque-ensemble-concert/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Apr 2012 23:44:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/04/29/attending-my-first-cmu-baroque-ensemble-concert/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I attended a free concert of the CMU Baroque Ensemble for the very first time!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The CMU Baroque Ensemble under &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.stephenschultz.net/&#34;&gt;Stephen Schultz&lt;/a&gt; has been around for over a decade, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.stephenschultz.net/teaching.html&#34;&gt;starting in 2002&lt;/a&gt;, but I had never attended one of their concerts, because basically, until I started playing recorder last year, I had very little interest in Baroque music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But now I&amp;rsquo;m really immersing myself in Baroque music, so I decided to check out the student ensemble. Also, I&amp;rsquo;d never seen Stephen Schultz in action before outside the CMU lecture hall (I took his &amp;ldquo;Survey of Western Musical History&amp;rdquo; in 2006) and his CD recordings of Baroque flute music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The students played modern instruments, but Schultz clearly aimed to evoke a crisp, Baroque style of play from the ensemble. He is an enthusiastic and clear conductor and it is enjoyable watching him direct this music he clearly loves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;bach-s-brandenburg-2&#34;&gt;Bach&amp;rsquo;s Brandenburg 2&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Various pieces were performed in this concert, but the highlight for me was Bach&amp;rsquo;s Brandenburg concerto no. 2, which I have recently come to love. I had ignored the Brandenburg concertos for much of my life, but when I started playing recorder last year, I found that one of the method books I used, a two-volume method by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.aswltd.com/adultmet.htm#begin&#34;&gt;Mario Duschenes&lt;/a&gt;, ends with challenging solo recorder parts for the Brandenburg concerto no. 2 and no. 4, and I aspired to be able to play these, and listened to some recordings I found of them, and truly fell in love with the music! (Note: the CMU Baroque Ensemble did not use recorder, but flute, in the Brandenburg 2.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was thrilling for me to watch the Brandenburg 2 performed live, because of the prominent &lt;a href=&#34;http://abel.hive.no/trumpet/bach/brandenburg/&#34;&gt;high trumpet part&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;d never seen this in action before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, here&amp;rsquo;s a performance of the first movement of the Brandenburg 2, on historical instruments (rather than the modern instruments played in the CMU Baroque Ensemble concert). Check out the recorder and trumpet!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/EC1E4_imS0A&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed the concert and will probably continue to attend more by the CMU Baroque Ensemble, to continue my Baroque &amp;ldquo;education&amp;rdquo;. It is, of course, not a professional ensemble, but it is great to see CMU students dedicated to performing Baroque music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-11-25&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-11-25)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fine trumpet player in this concert was &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/11/25/a-fine-trumpet-recital-by-erin-yanacek&#34;&gt;Erin Yanacek&lt;/a&gt;, whom I&amp;rsquo;d later coincidentally encounter through her writings and from meeting her by accident.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>