<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Bolero on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/bolero/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Bolero on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/bolero/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Thoughts on Cuba while watching Cuban musicians performing the 1947 bolero &#34;La gloria eres tú&#34;</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/12/13/thoughts-on-cuba-while-watching-cuban-musicians-performing-the-1947-bolero-la-gloria-eres-tu/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Dec 2014 21:01:47 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/12/13/thoughts-on-cuba-while-watching-cuban-musicians-performing-the-1947-bolero-la-gloria-eres-tu/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t expect to be thinking so much about Cuba today. It all started with a random musical itch I was scratching.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;la-comparsa-and-the-wooden-flute-headjoint&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;La comparsa&amp;rdquo; and the wooden flute headjoint&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I was in a Latin music mood as I was playing my flute at home, and started looking up flute versions of music on YouTube for fun and inspiration. One piece that came to mind was the famous &amp;ldquo;La comparsa&amp;rdquo;, by Cuban composer &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ernesto_Lecuona&#34;&gt;Ernesto Lecuona&lt;/a&gt;. Last year when Bebo Valdés died, I wrote about being moved by the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/22/rip-bebo-valdes/&#34;&gt;reunion of Bebo with his son Chucho in a tearful duet performance of this piece on two pianos&lt;/a&gt;, and thinking about their separation as Bebo abandoned his family to flee Cuba for Sweden while his son stayed behind to become one of Cuba&amp;rsquo;s great musicians.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found a really quirky Latin jazz performance of &amp;ldquo;La comparsa&amp;rdquo; on YouTube by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.chipboaz.com/blog/2014/07/10/cuban-flautist-bobby-ramirez-releases-jazz-flute/&#34;&gt;Cuban-American&lt;/a&gt; jazz flutist &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bobbyramirez.com/&#34;&gt;Bobby Ramirez&lt;/a&gt; and Puerto Rican &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.negronistrio.com/&#34;&gt;Jose Negroni&lt;/a&gt; on keyboard:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/4Nro7myJ6Nw&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ramirez on flute was unfortunately out of tune with the keyboard, but what I noticed was his wooden headjoint. I&amp;rsquo;ve never seen the old traditional Cuban wooden &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.descarga.com/cgi-bin/db/archives/Article15&#34;&gt;Charanga flute&lt;/a&gt;, but do see flutists playing the modern Boehm flute with a wooden headjoint for a different sound. In fact, I love and prefer wooden flutes, but they are expensive and I own only one, a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/30/got-my-new-casey-burns-small-handed-irish-flute/&#34;&gt;Casey Burns Irish flute&lt;/a&gt;. So just for the fun of it (I can&amp;rsquo;t really justify the investment right now), I decided to search the Web for makers of wooden headjoints.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;juan-novo-wooden-flute-headjoints&#34;&gt;Juan Novo wooden flute headjoints&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the top Web hits was &lt;a href=&#34;http://jnovoheadjoints.com/&#34;&gt;Juan Novo&lt;/a&gt;. It had the benefit of having an embedded YouTube video with the caption &amp;ldquo;This musician appreciated Mr. Novo’s craftsmanship so much, that this song was dedicated to him.&amp;rdquo; So I checked out the video. Indeed, the young woman playing the flute said, &amp;ldquo;Está para Juan Novo&amp;rdquo;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/kBzrwhpVvDE&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, I noticed that Juan Novo&amp;rsquo;s biography said he was sent from Cuba to the US all alone by his parents in 1962 to &lt;a href=&#34;http://jnovoheadjoints.com/about-juan-novo/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;escape the rampant communist indoctrination&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;la-gloria-eres-tú&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;La gloria eres tú&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was captivated not so much by the flute playing, but by the beautiful singing, of the young woman in this video of the classic bolero &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cancioneros.com/nc/2806/0/la-gloria-eres-tu-jose-antonio-mendez&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;La gloria eres tú&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; written by Cuban composer &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.encaribe.org/es/article/jose-antonio-mendez-garcia/1296&#34;&gt;José Antonio Méndez&lt;/a&gt; in 1947. I was really touched by her clear, unexaggerated but free expression and style, especially in light of much more famous performances of the song in my memory:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;La gloria eres tú&amp;rdquo; is one of my favorite boleros (&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/08/10/rip-eydie/&#34;&gt;my favorite being &amp;ldquo;Sabor a mî&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;) of all time. For comparison:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;luis-miguel&#34;&gt;Luis Miguel&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first exposure to &amp;ldquo;La gloria eres tú&amp;rdquo; was, like probably many others of my generation or younger worlwide, through the revival of the bolero by Mexican pop star &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Luis_Miguel&#34;&gt;Luis Miguel&lt;/a&gt; in the 1990s and onwards. I have all his bolero albums, a result of taking up Latin ballroom dancing in 2000 and hearing him singing in much of the music we practiced, performed, and competed to, including my first discovery of &amp;ldquo;Sabor a mî&amp;rdquo;, which was also on the 1997 album &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Romances_%28Luis_Miguel_album%29&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Romances&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. Luis Miguel is a great musician, I will continue to admit, but in time I drew away from his high-powered, slick performances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here he is live, from his 2000 DVD &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vivo_%28Luis_Miguel_album%29&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Vivo&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, which was the last thing I bought by him before backing away from his work:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/GNldCVbD4b4&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;olga-guillot&#34;&gt;Olga Guillot&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, the gold standard for &amp;ldquo;La gloria eres tú&amp;rdquo; is the performance by Cuban &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Olga_Guillot&#34;&gt;Olga Guillot&lt;/a&gt;, the &amp;ldquo;queen of the bolero&amp;rdquo;. (In 1961, she was yet another musician who fled Cuba.) I like how she alternates between different moods, starting out gently and almost like a prayer, but then gets more and more passionate. She very quickly changes the color of her voice and dynamics. For me it&amp;rsquo;s still the greatest performance of this bolero:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/xEAOX2nxsEo&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;elena-burke&#34;&gt;Elena Burke&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another recording I have of the bolero is from an album by Cuban singer &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elena_Burke&#34;&gt;Elena Burke&lt;/a&gt;. She has her own style, with a low voice, and more staccato delivery:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/yuHpvIvukOg&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elena died in Havana in 2002. Her daughter &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Malena_Burke&#34;&gt;Malena&lt;/a&gt; came to Miami in the US in 1995 with her family. Here is Malena Burke performing the bolero with Arturo Sandoval on piano:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/2_LxxwXda8Y&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Malena Burke&amp;rsquo;s oldest daughter &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lena_Burke&#34;&gt;Lena&lt;/a&gt; is also a musician, a pianist and singer, and has worked with Gloria Estefan and others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s Lena singing the famous 1929 bolero-son &lt;a href=&#34;http://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/L%C3%A1grimas_negras&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Lágrimas negras&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; with Bebo Valdés and others. This is such a weird combo, with her being sixty years younger than Bebo and stylistically very &amp;ldquo;American pop&amp;rdquo;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/x56VtBF6iGo&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;arturo-sandoval&#34;&gt;Arturo Sandoval&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arturo_Sandoval&#34;&gt;Arturo Sandoval&lt;/a&gt;, he defected from Cuba to the US in 2000. I discovered him initially when his biographical film &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/For_Love_or_Country:_The_Arturo_Sandoval_Story&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;For Love or Country&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; about his life before defection came out, and I saw him perform in the Three Rivers Arts Festival in Pittsburgh in 2002.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a Latin jazz version by Arturo Sandoval on flugelhorn, from his 1994 album &amp;ldquo;Tenderly&amp;rdquo;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/AZW15092fx4&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;where-is-blau-colonial-cayo-coco&#34;&gt;Where is Blau Colonial Cayo Coco?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So there were many thoughts and questions already in my mind as a result of listening to this old Cuban bolero, as a result of my remembering past performances by musicians who had left Cuba. When I hear classic boleros, I think about old Cuba, the culture and society that produced this kind of music and musicians, the political upheaval, the consequences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But back to that little band Nucay, captured presumably on a phone outside on a windy day by a random tourist who posted the video on YouTube in 2010. What has life been like for the members of Nucay, and for the charming young flutist/singer?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, what and where is &amp;ldquo;Blau Colonial Cayo Coco&amp;rdquo;? Apparently it&amp;rsquo;s a resort now named just &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cayocococuba.net/hotel_colonialcayococo.html&#34;&gt;Colonial Cayo Coco&lt;/a&gt; on the island of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cayo_Coco&#34;&gt;Cayo Coco&lt;/a&gt; that is part of Cuba. In particular, this place was designed to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cubahotelreservation.com/hotel.asp?hotel_code=sctblacolonial&#34;&gt;look like a village&lt;/a&gt;. This kind of thing makes me uncomfortable. I guess tourists fly in to pretend to have a nice &amp;ldquo;village&amp;rdquo; experience, while the hired musicians are probably paid to look and act the part.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;nucay&#34;&gt;Nucay&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I looked up more performances on YouTube by this band Nucay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;oye-como-va-cha-cha&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Oye como va&amp;rdquo;, cha-cha&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The caption for this video reads, &amp;ldquo;Ramon Almeida and daughter Arleytis [sic] lead this wonderful group of talented Cuban musicians.&amp;rdquo; So now we have some names. I presume the leader with maracas is the father? (Later I determined his daughter&amp;rsquo;s name is actually &amp;ldquo;Arletis&amp;rdquo;: read on.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was a fine performance of the classic cha-cha &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oye_Como_Va&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Oye coma va&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; written by &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tito_Puente&#34;&gt;Tito Puente&lt;/a&gt; in 1963. No, Puente was not Cuban; he was born in New York and was a big force in creating the mambo/salsa scene in the US in the 1950s. A great Latin jazz musician. I should have gone to see him perform live when he was in Pittsburgh in 2000 before he died. His music was great for listening to as well as dancing to; I still remember practicing my dancing to the first album of his I bought, &amp;ldquo;Mambo Birdland&amp;rdquo; (which has an &amp;ldquo;Oye como va&amp;rdquo; track).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I&amp;rsquo;ll confess that hearing performances of this work over a decade ago inspired me to think about taking up flute again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arletis did a fine job on flute here, jazzing things up:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/l4uWBPD7y70&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;ay-maria-merengue&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Ay Maria!&amp;rdquo;, merengue&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The musicians seem to be having fun; how could one not, given the catchy music and all of them singing? I really enjoyed flute action by Arletis in this upbeat classic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Merengue_music&#34;&gt;merengue&lt;/a&gt; is not Cuban, but comes from the Dominican Republic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/tAgVVL_ZTmI&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;sabor-a-mî&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Sabor a mî&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My favorite bolero, performed well. The caption reads &amp;ldquo;Cuban Music with the help of young percussionist from Quebec&amp;rdquo;, but this is wrong: &lt;a href=&#34;http://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sabor_a_m%C3%AD_%28canci%C3%B3n%29&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Sabor a mî&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; was composed in 1959 by a Mexican composer, &lt;a href=&#34;http://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/%C3%81lvaro_Carrillo&#34;&gt;Álvaro Carrillo&lt;/a&gt;. These distinctions matter to me: &amp;ldquo;Latin&amp;rdquo; music is not all the same, any more than the people or the distinct cultures are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/RmOIKdY3LYw&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;some-salsa-song&#34;&gt;Some salsa song&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is some salsa song; I&amp;rsquo;m afraid I cannot identify it offhand, the way I did the other songs. I&amp;rsquo;d have to try to transcribe the lyrics and hope that a Web search finds something, but have my doubts when it comes to salsa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I loved the father-daughter musical interplay here, with Ramón singing and Arletis on flute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/sAMdEezxYJs&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;summary-of-nucay&#34;&gt;Summary of Nucay&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OK, so Nucay is a pretty good band and plays a lot of classics to please the tourists. What else?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;arletis-almeida-sentirse-asi&#34;&gt;Arletis Almeida, &amp;ldquo;Sentirse Asi&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that a search for more Nucay material on YouTube reveals the following slick, professionally produced video uploaded by someone in 2012, promoting Arletis Almeida as a singer, with the caption &amp;ldquo;Arletis Almeida, flutist of Grupo Nucay in Cayo Coco Cuba, with her original song Sentirse Asi written by her father and band member Ramon Almeida&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, she is almost unrecognizable to me, very much made up and glamorous and placed in an urban nightlife setting, with shots of handsome men, alcohol, cigarettes. The contrast between this angsty, sensualized persona and the cheerful flutist playing at Colonial Cayo Coco with her father was quite jarring to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The singing is beautiful, and the song actually breaks out into a standard bolero accompaniment. It&amp;rsquo;s really something hearing bolero singing of this quality from a young person today. My overall feeling when hearing either this newly composed bolero or the classic music in the earlier videos is this: there&amp;rsquo;s some kind of time bubble that can still happen in the world, for better or for worse (a subject bigger than this blog post), and Nucay and Arletis Almeida illustrate it. Here in the US, no young people sing in this way. The many influences from pop, hip hop, and much more result in much more &amp;ldquo;fusion&amp;rdquo;. You saw that above in Lena Burke&amp;rsquo;s singing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/P1PZhDtCmLM&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;thoughts-on-cuba&#34;&gt;Thoughts on Cuba&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After watching this video, I wonder what has become of Arletis Almeida. Does she still play flute? Has she embarked on some kind of lounge career? Who knows? She&amp;rsquo;s in Cuba. Cuba is a world away. It took tourists to make her name even register on the Web, through the links to the YouTube videos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve waited for decades for an end to the senseless &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_States_embargo_against_Cuba&#34;&gt;embargo of Cuba&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;ve already run out of space here to even begin talking about the politics of the Cold War, about the human cost of isolating Cuba. Cuba, a place with a complicated history, but once an advanced nation by any standard, filled with culture, music classical and popular, home of world chess champion &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jos%C3%A9_Ra%C3%BAl_Capablanca&#34;&gt;Capablanca&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;con-los-años-que-me-quedan-and-nostalgia&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Con los años que me quedan&amp;rdquo; and nostalgia&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For some reason, I was reminded of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gloria_Estefan&#34;&gt;Gloria Estefan&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s music video of the bolero &amp;ldquo;Con los años que me quedan&amp;rdquo; from her nostalgic 1993 album &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mi_Tierra&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Mi Tierra&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s an odd kind of nostalgia, given that her parents fled Cuba when she was young. She made this album to embrace her Cuban heritage. But what world is portrayed here? Something like the world the tourists at Cayo Cayo hope to see? And what is Arletis trying to do as she sings boleros today?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, it&amp;rsquo;s definitely a beautiful song, and Estefan sings it soulfully:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/l6LjNOYvhMk&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2014-12-17&#34;&gt;(Update of 2014-12-17)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Totally by coincidence, news has come of the apparent &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2014/12/18/world/americas/us-cuba-relations.html&#34;&gt;plan by President Obama to normalize relations with Cuba&lt;/a&gt; after half a century. I cannot process this news right now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Life for Arletis and her father may well change one day in interesting ways.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>RIP Cheo Feliciano: wonderful singer of salsa and bolero</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/04/17/rip-cheo-feliciano-wonderful-singer-of-salsa-and-bolero/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Apr 2014 20:45:07 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/04/17/rip-cheo-feliciano-wonderful-singer-of-salsa-and-bolero/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://i2.cdn.turner.com/cnn/dam/assets/140417104237-cheo-feliciano---story---restricted-story-top.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Cheo Feliciano&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I learned that &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cheo_Feliciano&#34;&gt;Cheo Feliciano&lt;/a&gt; just &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cnn.com/2014/04/17/showbiz/cheo-feliciano-obit/&#34;&gt;died in a car accident at age 78&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-i-have-been-a-fan-of-cheo-feliciano&#34;&gt;Why I have been a fan of Cheo Feliciano&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Born in Puerto Rico, he was one of my favorite singers of salsa and bolero when I was regularly doing Latin dancing and seeking out the best music out there. As a particular fan of bolero, I was drawn to his magnetic voice and style: rich, smooth, flexible. His singing always seemed so resonant and never harsh; in particular, as a learner of Spanish, I appreciated how easy it was to hear his words, because of his clear, conversational articulation even as he sang.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check him out:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;some-favorite-musical-selections&#34;&gt;Some favorite musical selections&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My single favorite recording of his is of the bolero (you know how I love bolero) &amp;ldquo;Delirio&amp;rdquo;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/M4Unt7OwkJc&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He was fantastic at uptempo salsa too, of course. Here is a video of him performing &amp;ldquo;Busca lo Tuyo&amp;rdquo;. I particularly like his &lt;em&gt;improvisation&lt;/em&gt; in salsa: he sounds so natural while inventive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/erddzOK3Eys&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you love classic salsa and bolero, take some time out to review his old albums and remember how great he was. And remember to keep dancing to his fine music!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How do you feel when you learn that a favorite musician of yours has died? Do you do anything to celebrate his or her life and contribution to yours? I like to reflect on what I found so special that touched my life, and share that so that others will remember, or learn anew.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Many faces of the bolero &#34;Dos Gardenias&#34;</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/02/10/many-faces-of-the-bolero-dos-gardenias/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2014 21:43:12 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/02/10/many-faces-of-the-bolero-dos-gardenias/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I encountered an intriguing article &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.npr.org/2014/02/10/274687110/brazils-maria-rita-rediscovers-her-mother-through-music&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Brazil&amp;rsquo;s Maria Rita Rediscovers Her Mother Through Music&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;maria-rita&#34;&gt;Maria Rita&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The name &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maria_Rita&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Maria Rita&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; was familiar to me for only one reason: exactly one year ago, by coincidence, right after &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/02/10/attending-j-jam-in-squirrel-hill-but-not-playing-music-in-it/&#34;&gt;attending a music performance&lt;/a&gt;, I was looking up performances of the bolero &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pbs.org/buenavista/music/songs/dos_gardenias.html&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Dos Gardenias&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; on YouTube, in order to see what was out there, and also to find a &amp;ldquo;karaoke&amp;rdquo; version I could use to practice singing to and playing the flute to (I ended up &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/17/finally-doing-some-latin-music-jamming-on-flute/&#34;&gt;playing the piece on flute a month later at a party&lt;/a&gt;), and one of the performances that struck me as notable and unusual was hers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that in this NPR program, when asked to choose a musical selection to end the program with, Maria Rita chose her recording of &amp;ldquo;Dos Gardenias&amp;rdquo;. You can watch a video of a live performance of hers &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4DoBORm4iyE&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; (sorry, the provider did not allow it to be embeddable). Do watch it: I found it strangely mesmerizing. It is understated compared to &amp;ldquo;normal&amp;rdquo; bolero style, yet expressive in its own way. Also, this video has her moving to the music while singing, eyes closed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, it turns out that Maria Rita&amp;rsquo;s mother was the famous Brazilian singer &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elis_Regina&#34;&gt;Elis Regina&lt;/a&gt;, who died at 36. The interview was interesting because it brought up the issue of what it&amp;rsquo;s like being the child of a famous musician, because if you&amp;rsquo;re a musician also, then there are always comparisons and questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what I want to return to my real topic, which is the bolero &amp;ldquo;Dos Gardenias&amp;rdquo;, one of my favorite boleros ever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;love-on-first-listen-ibrahim-ferrer-1999&#34;&gt;Love on first listen: Ibrahim Ferrer, 1999&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I first encountered &amp;ldquo;Dos Gardenias&amp;rdquo; through Ibrahim Ferrer&amp;rsquo;s performance in &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Buena_Vista_Social_Club_%28album%29&#34;&gt;Buena Vista Social Club&lt;/a&gt;, the film and the CD, which I came across in 2000, shortly after it came out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still love this live performance by Ibrahim Ferrer:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/mz_01le5pMs&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here he is from the CD:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/5pKW7qvYSHU&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-i-love-this-song&#34;&gt;Why I love this song&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://lyricstranslate.com/en/dos-gardenias-two-gardenias.html&#34;&gt;lyrics&lt;/a&gt; are singable and comprehensible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The harmonic structure is distinctive, because it uses both the natural minor and the altered harmonic minor (raised 7th). This gives the song both an exotic and unstable feeling, corresponding to the emotional content of the lyrics. Check out when the 7th is raised and when it is not. In addition, the 4th is augmented. All this chromaticism drives well the song&amp;rsquo;s emotional content, implying various different modal regions coinciding with changes in the narrative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The melody has a good dramatic range, and has varying intervals in motion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;antonio-machin-1947&#34;&gt;Antonio Machin, 1947&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m always interested in alternate performances of songs, both new and old. So I went back to the source, the great &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Antonio_Mach%C3%ADn&#34;&gt;Antonio Machin&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/OPq2ye7hJQg&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is faster than Ferrer&amp;rsquo;s rendition. If you examine the history of bolero performance in general, you will find that things have gotten slower and more sentimental over the years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find that there are pluses and minuses to different styles and speeds. I rather like the clarity and drama of the older faster tempo and style, but also like the room for more emotional expressiveness and freedom when slower.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;omara-portuondo-2010&#34;&gt;Omara Portuondo, 2010&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that Abby and I went to a &lt;a href=&#34;http://trustarts.culturaldistrict.org/production/25334&#34;&gt;concert by Omara Portuondo here in Pittsburgh on November 7, 2010&lt;/a&gt;, in which she performed &amp;ldquo;Dos Gardenias&amp;rdquo;. And someone captured that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/9QjS2MnAfR0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was an interesting, very free rendition, without the usual full rhythmic backup, but instead featuring some subtle guitar accompaniment. It was different, but I did not like it so much. I think the regular structure of the song, the way the lyrics fit into the movement, makes it work better when the original motoric bolero rhythm is maintained, with the harmonic motion driving the narrative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;lucrecia-1996&#34;&gt;Lucrecia, 1996&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a random other performance I found. I didn&amp;rsquo;t like it at all. The phrasing seems all weird and distorted, and the song&amp;rsquo;s been reharmonized strangely also.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/zgoEHFgwGes&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;sertab-erener-2007&#34;&gt;Sertab Erener, 2007&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I liked the performance of this Turkish pop singer Sertab Erener. She includes some distinctive middle Eastern styling that are unusual for this Cuban music, but her musicality cannot be denied. (Unfortunately, the &amp;ldquo;dance&amp;rdquo; sequences in this video are not at all bolero. Ignore the video.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/d-0SKj7AjZg&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What can I say, I&amp;rsquo;m obsessed with this beautiful bolero. However you like this song interpreted, it&amp;rsquo;s a must-listen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I haven&amp;rsquo;t sung it outside my home yet, but I guess I should get around to it, maybe at a party in the near future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;postscript-on-elis-regina&#34;&gt;Postscript on Elis Regina&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out Maria Rita&amp;rsquo;s mother, Elis Regina, singing the famous bossa nova song &amp;ldquo;Triste&amp;rdquo; in 1976:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/5wiJPgmEqR0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Appreciating the unique singer La Lupe</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/12/19/appreciating-the-unique-singer-la-lupe/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Dec 2013 21:41:19 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/12/19/appreciating-the-unique-singer-la-lupe/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/la-lupe-cds.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;La Lupe CDs&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I recently listened to a great &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.npr.org/blogs/altlatino/2013/12/19/255282456/la-lupe-queen-of-latin-soul-the-original-alt-latina&#34;&gt;program &amp;ldquo;La Lupe: queen of Latin soul&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; about the black Cuban singer &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/La_Lupe&#34;&gt;La Lupe&lt;/a&gt;, who died in 1992 (born in 1936) well before I was even aware of her existence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(I also then found information on a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pbs.org/independentlens/lalupe/&#34;&gt;film about La Lupe&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;first-encounter&#34;&gt;First encounter&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still remember the exact moment I first heard her electrifying singing, and remember looking her up to find more music sung by her. It was sometime around the year 2003.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was during the final credits of the old 1988 film &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Women_on_the_Verge_of_a_Nervous_Breakdown&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Women on the Verge of a Nervous Breakdown&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pedro_Almod%C3%B3var&#34;&gt;Pedro Almodóvar&lt;/a&gt;. It was a quiet evening alone as I was watching it on DVD in part because I was taking a course on Spanish, finally having decided to learn the language for real after having been exposed to it a lot thanks to Latin ballroom dancing and salsa and tango, listening to a lot of the music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A strident voice rang out at me from the TV screen. I almost want to say &amp;ldquo;harsh&amp;rdquo;, but the unique quality of the voice and the singing were so compelling that I don&amp;rsquo;t want to use the word &amp;ldquo;harsh&amp;rdquo;. This voice came out during the singing of a bolero, the musical genre that I love that usually involves a more smooth kind of voice and delivery. So it was really unusual being captivated by this amazing performance that played up the sense of loss and betrayal that were certainly in the lyrics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It wasn&amp;rsquo;t just that the emotional directness and yet control of the singing that captivated. I was also really pleased that I could &lt;em&gt;hear every word&lt;/em&gt;, even as a beginning student of Spanish. This was a singer with impeccable articulation that could make a song seem as though it were spoken, telling a story. When she sang, it was the complete package: drama, phrasing, silence, a cold stare or a haughty laugh. It was not just notes or words. It was a &lt;em&gt;performance&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The song is so raw that I can&amp;rsquo;t really listen to it very often, but here it is (as linked from the program I just mentioned). I&amp;rsquo;m talking about &amp;ldquo;Puro Teatro&amp;rdquo;, of course. (Here&amp;rsquo;s an &lt;a href=&#34;http://lyricstranslate.com/en/puro-teatro-pure-theater.html&#34;&gt;English translation of the lyrics&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/R-CpdAtgKQY&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;finding-more-of-her-music&#34;&gt;Finding more of her music&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had no idea who La Lupe was at the time when hearing her sing in the film. I managed to order an Almodóvar soundtrack CD that included her &amp;ldquo;Puro Teatro&amp;rdquo;, got her name, then looked her up. Eventually I found more songs by her, buying a CD of just her music. Of course, now with YouTube, it is easy to find anything by anybody. But there was a time when it was much harder to find music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.npr.org/blogs/altlatino/2013/12/19/255282456/la-lupe-queen-of-latin-soul-the-original-alt-latina&#34;&gt;NPR program&lt;/a&gt; has embedded YouTube videos of several of her performances. She was fantastic in all kinds of music, ranging from really fast dance music to more moderate salsa or cha cha or slower boleros. She also sang, in heavily accented English, some songs in the English languages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I am such a fan of slow boleros, here is &amp;ldquo;Que te pedí&amp;rdquo;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/3weAOwmKZXo&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;about-la-lupe&#34;&gt;About La Lupe&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tend not to know a lot about the performers of music I have listened to, because I tend not to read music programs or the like. I did appreciate listening to this NPR program, because I hadn&amp;rsquo;t realized many unique things about La Lupe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She was really revolutionary back in the day: in the 1950s in Cuba, then after leaving Cuba, in the 1960s and 1970s. I had no idea she dated from way back. Not only was she a black Cuban who made it, but also as a woman she was controversial for her sensual presence and musical delivery (which included growls, gasps, sniffs, sighs, orgasmic moans, and a kind of maniacal laugh; you can hear it for yourself, it&amp;rsquo;s still kind of shockingly direct for today I think). She was completely uninhibited. That&amp;rsquo;s why I was surprised she was operating in the 1950s. I would have thought, OK, 1980s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was nice for me to have the opportunity to learn something about an amazing singer who has long since gone, and I hope people continue appreciating the quality of her art.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>RIP, Eydie Gormé</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/08/10/rip-eydie/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Aug 2013 23:08:41 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/08/10/rip-eydie/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I learned that American singer &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eydie_Gorm%C3%A9&#34;&gt;Eydie Gormé&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.npr.org/blogs/thetwo-way/2013/08/10/210927460/reports-singer-eydie-gorme-dies-at-84&#34;&gt;just died&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I actually knew very little about her until reading about her death.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But she made a huge difference in my life!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/c/ca/Eydie_Gorme.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Eydie Gormé&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;eydie-gormé-and-los-panchos&#34;&gt;Eydie Gormé and Los Panchos&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know of her only through her famous recordings from the 1960s of Latin music with &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Los_Panchos&#34;&gt;Los Panchos&lt;/a&gt;. They recorded a number of classic &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/bolero/&#34;&gt;boleros&lt;/a&gt; that constantly kept me company when I was doing &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/ballroom-dance/&#34;&gt;ballroom dance&lt;/a&gt; over a decade ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In particular, I really enjoyed their performance of &amp;ldquo;Sabor a mî&amp;rdquo;, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/11/17/a-childhood-dream-come-true-i-am-now-finally-singing-for-real/&#34;&gt;my favorite bolero of all time&lt;/a&gt;, both to listen to and to dance to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/0Uz6ZDJjXvE&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was interesting for me to learn, just now, that her parents were Sephardic Jews, her father from Sicily and her mother from Turkey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;should-i-thank-people-before-they-die&#34;&gt;Should I thank people before they die?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is always strange to me when people die and I realize I barely knew anything about them, but feel deep gratitude for how they&amp;rsquo;ve so much enhanced my life. This was the case with Eydie Gormé.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve never been into &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fandom&#34;&gt;fandom&lt;/a&gt;, but lately I&amp;rsquo;ve been wondering, in an era when it actually is much easier to contact &amp;ldquo;celebrities&amp;rdquo;, whether sending a simple one-shot note to someone expressing gratitude, well before death, might be appropriate. Especially in the case of people who are actually not major celebrities (either because their prime time has passed or because their contribution is in a narrow niche). &lt;strong&gt;What do you think?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Finally doing some Latin music jamming on flute; also Irish and French</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/03/17/finally-doing-some-latin-music-jamming-on-flute/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Mar 2013 23:36:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/03/17/finally-doing-some-latin-music-jamming-on-flute/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;St. Patrick&amp;rsquo;s Day weekend means, of course, a party at Henry&amp;rsquo;s. Last year Abby and I even went to two of his St. Patrick&amp;rsquo;s Day parties! At the first, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/17/st-patricks-day-party-playing-tin-whistle-and-flute/&#34;&gt;I played tin whistle for the first time&lt;/a&gt;, and I played some easy recorder music &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/30/a-delayed-st-patricks-day-party-playing-tin-whistle-and-alto-recorder/&#34;&gt;at the second&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year, I reflected on how far I&amp;rsquo;ve come musically, and as usual, wanted to do something new and challenging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;irish-music&#34;&gt;Irish music&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I brought my tin whistle and Irish flute ready to jam. It turned out that Barbara had come with violin ready for some Irish jamming also. When she went at it with Henry on piano, she ended up playing &amp;ldquo;Danny Boy&amp;rdquo; (&amp;ldquo;Londonderry Air&amp;rdquo;) as one selection. Unfortunately, I had planned on playing it on flute, &amp;ldquo;redeeming&amp;rdquo; myself after being terrible on flute a year ago &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/17/st-patricks-day-party-playing-tin-whistle-and-flute/&#34;&gt;when I tried it&lt;/a&gt;, so since she had already done it, I quietly scrapped my original plan. No problem: there were many other things to play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Barbara joined me and Henry in some jigs, reels, and waltzes that I pulled out, some of which I did on tin whistle and some of which I did on Irish flute. That was fun, if pretty exhausting: lots and lots of notes, not so easy to just plain sight read. But of course, nobody has to play all the notes. That&amp;rsquo;s the beauty of this music. There never were official notes anyway; these are traditional tunes with a certain recognizable rhythm and shape and harmonic movement, but everyone does the notes differently anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;french-music&#34;&gt;French music&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d asked Vasili to learn on accordion &amp;ldquo;Les Ormeaux&amp;rdquo;, which I had learned just recently &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/02/25/stepping-it-up-at-the-french-and-blues-jam/&#34;&gt;at a French jam&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s not actually a traditional tune, but it&amp;rsquo;s a great one. Unfortunately, it turned out that Vasili had learned it in a different key from the one I was using on modern flute, so one of us (him) transposed on the fly to try to match, and the result therefore wasn&amp;rsquo;t as good as it could have been. Next time! Anyway, Abby and I jammed with Vasili on stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;latin-music&#34;&gt;Latin music&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;bolero&#34;&gt;Bolero&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The musical highlight for me was my debut in playing Latin, or more specifically, Cuban music. I fell in love with this music when I was &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/10/flute-loving-it-again/&#34;&gt;introduced to Latin ballroom dance back in 2000&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started off with an unnamed bolero from a World Music Cuba book I had first encountered &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/02/22/flute-progress-still-hanging-in-there/&#34;&gt;a year ago when I was just barely playing flute&lt;/a&gt;. I got on flute and Henry enthusiastically improvised along on piano and we took a couple of turns. That was great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I pulled out &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pbs.org/buenavista/music/songs/dos_gardenias.html&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Dos Gardenias&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, one of my favorite boleros of all time (and the bolero is one of my favorite musical genres). (By the way, I am working on being ready to sing this and other boleros before too long, making my debut as a bolero singer.) Again, more fun opportunities for inventiveness for Henry and me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;buena-vista-social-club&#34;&gt;Buena Vista Social Club&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, I first encountered &amp;ldquo;Dos Gardenias&amp;rdquo; through Ibrahim Ferrer of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Buena_Vista_Social_Club_%28album%29&#34;&gt;Buena Vista Social Club&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/5pKW7qvYSHU&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Buena Vista Social Club&amp;rdquo; was a very important music recording to me. At a time in my life around thirteen years ago when I was trying to explore Latin music and asked around for suggestions, my grad school classmate Andrej recommended this CD to me and my musical world was changed forever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;cha-cha&#34;&gt;Cha cha&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I pulled out an unnamed cha cha from the World Music Cuba book. We really went wild for this one, especially since Chad, one of Henry&amp;rsquo;s piano students (and a fine improviser) decided to join us and sat at the piano with Henry as both of them played with me and we kept going and going and I became very excited and inspired along with them. Wow. That was one of the most intense musical experiences I&amp;rsquo;ve ever had. It was frightening (didn&amp;rsquo;t know when I&amp;rsquo;d hit the limits of my technique or inventiveness) and exhilarating at the same time. When I was done, I was sweating from all the effort. Abby said she&amp;rsquo;d never seen me so animated before playing music, since she&amp;rsquo;s only ever seen me play Baroque and other such music mainly, or Irish and French. Well, Latin jazz is different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;chess&#34;&gt;Chess&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point in the evening, I needed a break from playing music and from socializing and decided to rest. However, it turned out that my &amp;ldquo;rest&amp;rdquo; consisted of relaxing in a chair while closing my eyes and&amp;hellip; &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/17/my-second-ever-blindfold-chess-game/&#34;&gt;playing blindfold chess&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2014-03-16&#34;&gt;(Update of 2014-03-16)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I couldn&amp;rsquo;t make it to Henry&amp;rsquo;s St. Patrick Day party in 2014. I felt sad about this, but our other plans made earlier made it impractical to try to attend.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A childhood dream come true: I am now finally singing for real!</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/11/17/a-childhood-dream-come-true-i-am-now-finally-singing-for-real/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 Nov 2012 23:25:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/11/17/a-childhood-dream-come-true-i-am-now-finally-singing-for-real/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Abby and I went to a pre-Thanksgiving party hosted by Henry and yet again, &lt;strong&gt;I changed my life&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the last party at Henry&amp;rsquo;s, two months ago, I had begun singing there for the first time, and afterwards &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/21/my-first-time-singing-bossa-nova-also-a-temporary-farewell-to-baroque-flute/&#34;&gt;vowed that I would take up singing for real&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d followed up very slowly, taking a month before &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/10/27/singing-an-irish-ballad-as-an-asian-pirate-at-a-halloween-belly-dance-hafla/&#34;&gt;actually singing in public&lt;/a&gt;, and then the day after that, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/10/28/singing-and-playing-bossa-nova-favorite-chega-de-saudade-at-dunkin-donuts-for-j-jam/&#34;&gt;continuing to sing in public at J-Jam&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was the last event, J-Jam, that got me to decide to really prepare some songs to sing for the next J-Jam. What happened was that I had started off by trying to find some suitable flute/guitar music to work on with Cantor Ben Rosner for J-Jam, but I noticed that I was picking some material that was actually originally sung and then transcribed for flute. After being &lt;em&gt;unsatisfied&lt;/em&gt; with playing these songs on flute, because I couldn&amp;rsquo;t get quite the expression I wanted, I bit the bullet: I decided that &lt;em&gt;the voice is the original and best instrument we have&lt;/em&gt;, and that I should use the &lt;em&gt;best&lt;/em&gt; instrument to achieve what I wanted to do, which was to maximize expressiveness in lyrical music. So I started looking for transpositions of songs to a suitable range for me in order for me to sing them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then when Henry&amp;rsquo;s party invitation came up, I jumped at the opportunity to try out some of the music I was preparing for J-Jam, to perform with Henry on piano.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What did I do?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;one-year-anniversary-of-my-deciding-to-sing&#34;&gt;One year anniversary of my deciding to sing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By coincidence, it&amp;rsquo;s almost exactly one year since &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/18/i-want-to-sing/&#34;&gt;I decided here on this blog that I was going to get into singing&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;music-plan&#34;&gt;Music plan&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I picked out four pieces to give Henry advance warning on, so that I could give him the piano parts for him to take a look at before the party. During the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/11/13/round-1-of-pittsburgh-chess-club-tournament-revenge-of-the-knight/&#34;&gt;first round of the chess tournament we were both playing in&lt;/a&gt;, I gave him a big collection of music, not only for the upcoming party but for possible future projects also.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The selections I chose to work on for the party:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gabriel Fauré: Sicilienne (flute and piano)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gabriel Fauré: Après un rêve (voice and piano)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Robert Schumann: Widmung (voice and piano)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Carlos Gardel: Por una cabeza (voice and piano)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;at-the-party&#34;&gt;At the party&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;food&#34;&gt;Food&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Barbara rather than Anna took charge of providing the main food this time, while the rest of us pitched in with our contributions. There were over twenty people at this party, I believe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I made my own very small contributions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;cabbage-with-leeks-and-potatoes&#34;&gt;Cabbage with leeks and potatoes&lt;/h4&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pre-thanksgiving-2012/cabbage.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Cabbage with leeks and potatoes&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Cabbage with leeks and potatoes, with olive oil and butter and seasoning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Make sure to &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Caramelization&#34;&gt;caramelize&lt;/a&gt; in the skillet.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;turnips-and-carrots&#34;&gt;Turnips and carrots&lt;/h4&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pre-thanksgiving-2012/turnips.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Roasted turnips and carrots&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Roasted turnips and carrots, with olive oil and seasoning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;music&#34;&gt;Music&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I unexpected ended up providing a lot of the music this evening. There were fewer people involved in playing music than in some of the other parties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This time, I brought just my (modern) flute and my voice. I left my recorders and Baroque flute and Irish flute and tin whistle at home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started off with singing the tango &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Por_una_Cabeza&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Por una cabeza&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; (made famous in &amp;ldquo;Scent of a Woman&amp;rdquo;), very hesitatingly:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pre-thanksgiving-2012/franklin-por-una-cabeza.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin&amp;#39;s first try at Por una Cabeza&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I was so nervous that my legs were shaking and my arms trembling as I began; it was exactly as what happened &lt;em&gt;eight months ago&lt;/em&gt; at the first of Henry&amp;rsquo;s parties at which &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/17/st-patricks-day-party-playing-tin-whistle-and-flute/&#34;&gt;I played an instrument&lt;/a&gt;. The difference was that although that one time, I knew I was playing the flute &lt;em&gt;badly&lt;/em&gt;, this time, I was confident that I was singing OK: not great yet, but not badly. I&amp;rsquo;d worked two weeks on singing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;memory&#34;&gt;Memory&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing I have observed again and again during my past year of music is that it really is ideal to have stuff memorized. I have not put enough work into that, since with my limited time, I tend to use it on working on technique and on learning material, rather than on memorizing what I can play off a score or sing off a printed set of lyrics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I did make a special effort to memorize at least two of the songs I had prepared: the Fauré and the Schumann. I did manage to more or less memorize them in time, since the French and German vocabulary of these love songs were fairly straightforward (I studied French and German in high school and college). The tango in Spanish, &amp;ldquo;Por una cabeza&amp;rdquo;, I did not have hope of memorizing any time soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I brought along printouts to help me so I could glance at them at least now and then. Obviously, I aim to become independent of these aids so that I can sing unencumbered by looking at a printout, and connect directly with the audience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;what-it-s-like-to-sing&#34;&gt;What it&amp;rsquo;s like to sing&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The feeling of singing is like nothing else. It&amp;rsquo;s so &lt;em&gt;physical&lt;/em&gt; in a primal way, compared to playing flute or recorder. I completely lose myself in emotion, when I can squeeze as much expression out of the voice as I can. It&amp;rsquo;s an amazing sensation. It&amp;rsquo;s a communication that is very direct.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe if I played a violin I would feel something like that, because of the expressive qualities of the violin. On flute, I cannot do everything that I can do with my voice. I try, but it is not the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;flute&#34;&gt;Flute&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My focus on singing overshadowed the fact that I was actually making something of a debut on modern flute here. I had played modern flute in anyone&amp;rsquo;s presence outside the home only a handful of times before:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/17/st-patricks-day-party-playing-tin-whistle-and-flute/&#34;&gt;for St. Patrick&amp;rsquo;s Day&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/04/27/baroque-jam-session-at-cmu/&#34;&gt;Baroque jam session in March&lt;/a&gt;, playing a Baroque piece&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/28/my-first-appearance-on-a-music-recital-program/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Recorder society potluck/recital&lt;/a&gt;, playing a pre-Classical piece&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/10/28/singing-and-playing-bossa-nova-favorite-chega-de-saudade-at-dunkin-donuts-for-j-jam/&#34;&gt;J-Jam&lt;/a&gt;, where I did a bit of bossa nova improvisation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s not only because I was focusing on other instruments all year. It&amp;rsquo;s also because I&amp;rsquo;ve found it very challenging to make the kinds of sounds on the modern flute I want to hear. On each of those four occasions in which I played the modern flute, I felt that I needed to improve a lot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have improved a lot, actually, but I&amp;rsquo;m still far from satisfied; I&amp;rsquo;ve only now gotten to the point at which I feel I am not an embarrassment. Developing a truly beautiful, flexible tone seems a years-long task, and I keep working at it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I have finally jumped into the late 19th century, out of the 18th, to play Romantic music on the instrument that is suited for it, the modern flute:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pre-thanksgiving-2012/franklin-flute.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin playing Fauré, Sicilienne&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h4 id=&#34;unexpected-singing&#34;&gt;Unexpected singing&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Henry so enjoyed going through songs with me that he had me repeat &amp;ldquo;Por una cabeza&amp;rdquo; later in the party. I did, and I felt &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; more relaxed than when I did it the first time. I thought I did much better this time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I thought, hey, I had given him a whole folder of stuff, so we should just sight read some of it. I ended up singing Schubert&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Nacht und Traüme&amp;rdquo; as well as &amp;ldquo;An die Musik&amp;rdquo;, which I had intended for a later occasion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, finally, before Abby and I had to leave, I decided that I wanted to sing a song especially for Abby, and pulled out Alvaro Carrillo&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Sabor a mî&amp;rdquo;, which I know by heart (I will explain in a later blog post the significance of this song for me), and sang it to her, with Henry providing great accompaniment on first sight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;dancing&#34;&gt;Dancing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dancing with Abby at these parties is always a special pleasure for us&amp;hellip; Vasili on accordion.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pre-thanksgiving-2012/abby-franklin-dance.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby and Franklin dancing waltz&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-did-so-few-other-people-sing&#34;&gt;Why did so few other people sing?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the guests had been introduced to me as singers, yet &lt;em&gt;none&lt;/em&gt; of them sang at the party! This was puzzling to me. There could be many reasons, but I won&amp;rsquo;t speculate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for those who expressed enjoyment of singing to themselves, but identified themselves as non-singers (as I did), that&amp;rsquo;s very easy to understand, because I was there myself. I&amp;rsquo;ve simply chosen to overcome my fear and anxiety, work on improvement, and then put myself out there, warts and all. I do this because I saw the younger people under 20 do this, and I decided that if being &amp;ldquo;old&amp;rdquo; means being afraid, I&amp;rsquo;d rather do what the younger people do, and just get out there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-next&#34;&gt;What next?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m going to do serious study of singing. Henry mentioned a book &amp;ldquo;Singing for Dummies&amp;rdquo; that I&amp;rsquo;ll check out. I would like to work through it systematically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way: I noticed that my flute and recorder playing have improved in several dimensions since I started working on singing. My breath awareness is better, my control over my breath stream, and even more than that, I&amp;rsquo;m really trying to treat my instruments as parts of my body, to get that integrated feel I have when just singing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m singing now. &lt;strong&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s no going back.&lt;/strong&gt; It&amp;rsquo;s like when I originally started dancing, after decades as a non-dancer, or started running, or started cooking, or started public speaking. There&amp;rsquo;s just no going back, after the first big step.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Latin jazz in Pittsburgh: Puro Queso</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/08/26/latin-jazz-in-pittsburgh-puro-queso/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Aug 2012 22:31:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/08/26/latin-jazz-in-pittsburgh-puro-queso/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One great thing about Pittsburgh is the free cultural programs at the Carnegie Library. Abby and I checked out a local Latin jazz quartet, &lt;a href=&#34;http://puroquesojazz.com/&#34;&gt;Puro Queso&lt;/a&gt;, performing at the main branch of the library in Oakland, as part of their regular &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.carnegielibrary.org/events/details.cfm?event_id=69113&#34;&gt;Sunday afternoon World Kaleidoscope series&lt;/a&gt;. This event was also posted on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/pittsburgh-free/events/77709582/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Free and Almost Free in Pittsburgh&amp;rdquo; meetup group&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was amused to notice that when we arrived, I recognized the saxophonist! It was someone I had seen around a lot on campus at work at CMU. I figured he must be staff or faculty. (I looked him up and sure enough, he is &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.history.cmu.edu/faculty/eiss.html&#34;&gt;Paul Eiss, professor in the history department&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/puro-queso/soprano-sax.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Paul Eiss on soprano sax&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/puro-queso/tenor-sax.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Paul Eiss on tenor sax&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As usual at these library events, where time is limited and the purpose is to spark interest not only in the music but also to encourage concert attendance and CD purchases, the mustical selections tended toward well-known classic crowd pleasers, rather than more adventurous material or wilder improvisation. In any case, it was fun, and Abby and I danced a little too. Some of the selections I recognized:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;bossa nova: Song of the Jet (&lt;a href=&#34;http://letras.mus.br/tom-jobim/49065/&#34;&gt;Samba do Avião&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;bossa nova: &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mas_que_Nada&#34;&gt;Mas Que Nada&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;bolero: &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/B%C3%A9same_Mucho&#34;&gt;Besame mucho&lt;/a&gt;, featuring a female vocalist&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a Cuban &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Son_%28music%29&#34;&gt;son&lt;/a&gt; whose name I have forgotten&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Flute: loving it again, remembering why I dance, and how I met my wife!</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/03/10/flute-loving-it-again/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Mar 2012 21:28:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/03/10/flute-loving-it-again/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, after four days of &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/07/flute-taking-a-break-while-clarifying-my-goals&#34;&gt;not even touching my (modern) flute&lt;/a&gt; and having spent the time having fun with my Baroque flute instead, I felt the urge to return to the modern flute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still have not regained the inclination to continue working on the orchestra music I still have to improve a lot on in the coming week, but I rediscovered the joy of simply playing my instrument.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;sound-intonation&#34;&gt;Sound, intonation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The perpetual challenges of getting clean sounds and accurate pitches on the Baroque flute in the past four days have given me an increased appreciation for the modern flute. I picked it up and spent time just trying to make beautiful sounds. Freed from the stress of orchestra practice, I felt much more relaxed on the instrument than I have for a while now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To my surprise (but not really), I have improved considerably on the flute after not playing it for four days. I really needed a break, a consolidation of lessons learned. My production of tones is much improved, and high notes are squeaking less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;music-for-dance&#34;&gt;Music for dance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing I&amp;rsquo;ve truly come to realize is that I particularly enjoy playing rhythmic music suitable for dancing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, every time I attend a dance, and there is live music, I experience a strange internal conflict: I do like to dance, but sometimes, I&amp;rsquo;d rather be on the other side of the dance floor, being the musical performer! The &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; time I&amp;rsquo;ve been on the other side has been at last year&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburghcontra.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Contras and Squares&lt;/a&gt; Holiday Ball.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most recent instance of my wishing I could sometimes stop dancing and just join the musicians has been at the local &lt;a href=&#34;http://coalcountry.org/frenchdance.html&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh French dance workshop and social&lt;/a&gt;, where we&amp;rsquo;ve had live piano, fiddle, and of course, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~gdyke/&#34;&gt;Gregory&lt;/a&gt; on his Irish flute. I wonder whether at some point I might be qualified to play for the event, using either my modern flute or Baroque flute. (By the way, it was held again today, but unfortunately, Abby and I chose not to go because we had too many things to do this weekend.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;remembering-dancing&#34;&gt;Remembering dancing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday I spent time playing along to a score/CD set I&amp;rsquo;ve mentioned before, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/World-Music-Cuba-Flute-play-along/dp/3702465804&#34;&gt;World Music Cuba&lt;/a&gt;. While playing the bolero, cha cha, and mambo pieces in particular, I felt I was returning &amp;ldquo;home&amp;rdquo; in many ways. This was among the first music I heard and saw people dancing to when I was curious and visited the &lt;a href=&#34;http://cmubdc.org/&#34;&gt;CMU Ballroom Dance Club&lt;/a&gt; in 2000, and fell in love with, and learned to dance to. I also played along to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Play-along-Argentina-Flute-World-Music/dp/3702465871&#34;&gt;World Music Argentina&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;some-photos-of-my-ballroom-dance-days&#34;&gt;Some photos of my ballroom dance days&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some photos of me dancing in 2002 with my last dance partner, Amy, before I quit competitive ballroom dancing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here we are at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dcdancesportinferno.com/&#34;&gt;DC DanceSport Inferno&lt;/a&gt; in 2002 doing a hockey stick in international rumba:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/ballroom/dcdi-2002-hockey-stick.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Amy and Franklin at DCDI 2002 in rumba&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And here were are at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://comp.cornelldancesport.org/&#34;&gt;Cornell DanceSport Classic&lt;/a&gt; in 2002 in cha cha, rumba, and tango:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/ballroom/cornell-2002-new-yorker.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Amy and Franklin at Cornell 2002 in cha cha&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/ballroom/cornell-2002-hockey-stick.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Amy and Franklin at Cornell 2002 in rumba&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/ballroom/cornell-2002-tango-promenade.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Amy and Franklin at Cornell 2002 in tango&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;dancing-with-abby&#34;&gt;Dancing with Abby&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But never mind the ballroom dance days. It was through salsa dancing that I met my wife!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;how-i-met-abby&#34;&gt;How I met Abby&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was through dancing that I met Abby in the first place. After quitting dancing in 2003, I never danced again until late 2006, when my friend Jon told me he had recently started salsa dancing (because of a girlfriend who got him into it) and invited me to join him at a free outdoors dance, and I went. Then as I re-entered the Pittsburgh salsa dance scene, I kept running into Abby.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;some-photos-of-us-dancing-salsa&#34;&gt;Some photos of us dancing salsa&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are not many photos of Abby dancing with me, because when I&amp;rsquo;m dancing, I&amp;rsquo;m not holding my camera, but here are some photos a friend took at a big salsa dance weekend at the Palisades in McKeesport in April 2008, a year after we started dating in 2007.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/palisades-2008/abby-franklin.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby and Franklin dancing salsa at Palisades&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/palisades-2008/abby-franklin-hair.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby and Franklin dancing salsa at Palisades, hair flying&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;expression-and-improvisation-in-dance-and-in-music&#34;&gt;Expression and improvisation in dance and in music&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;dance&#34;&gt;Dance&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One reason I gave up ballroom dancing was that I felt there was an overemphasis on &amp;ldquo;syllabus steps&amp;rdquo; (I realize this is an oversimplification of the ballroom dance culture; all very good ballroom dancers go beyond the syllabus mindset). After quitting ballroom dancing, I explored Argentine tango, which is all about improvisation, but I left it because (at the time) it seemed that most of the women in the local scene were very tall, which made dancing awkward for me. I got into salsa because freed from the closed embrace, there was clearly a lot of room for personal improvisation. Ironically, I first got into making stuff up as a result of my imperfect memory: I could never memorize long choreography of step patterns, whether I was doing ballroom dancing or anything else. So I would always make a &amp;ldquo;mistake&amp;rdquo;, then I would make something out of the mistake. I learned that as long as you get back in time with the music, and keep the lead and follow communication strong, there is no such thing really as a mistake. You just keep going, with whatever is happening at the present moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I now have a long-term goal of developing my technique and releasing my inhibitions so that I can improvise musically at will. Yesterday, I played with improvising when playing bolero, cha cha, and tango. It was a lot of fun and profoundly satisfying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;music&#34;&gt;Music&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I actually credit my study of the recorder and the Baroque flute for reawakening me to my dream of free expression and improvisation. Baroque music leaves room for a lot of interpretation of trills and ornamentation and articulation (subject, of course, to &amp;ldquo;good taste&amp;rdquo;). I want to go beyond that, but it has been a great starting point. For some reason, too much exposure to later music (such as Beethoven) had turned me into a score-reader, since such later music has so much already marked up for the performer to simply &lt;em&gt;obey&lt;/em&gt;. The sparse annotations in Renaissance and Baroque music give one much more freedom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am enjoying playing the flute again, now that I know what I really want to do with it. And I would like to merge my dance and music lives, just as Abby has always played the Balkan music she also dances to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2012-03-12&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-03-12)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ended up &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/12/quitting-the-cmu-all-university-orchestra-one-of-the-hardest-decisions-in-my-life/&#34;&gt;quitting the CMU AUO&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2013-01-26&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-01-26)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost a year later, I finally played tangos on flute &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/26/music-i-just-played-for-the-first-time-recorder-sonata-tangos/&#34;&gt;at a party&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2013-03-17&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-03-17)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost exactly a year later, I ended up playing selections from the World Music Cuba book &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/17/finally-doing-some-latin-music-jamming-on-flute/&#34;&gt;at a party&lt;/a&gt;, and improvising freely with two other guys!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Flute progress after one month in orchestra: still hanging in there</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/02/22/flute-progress-still-hanging-in-there/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Feb 2012 20:19:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/02/22/flute-progress-still-hanging-in-there/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It was exactly one month ago, January 22, when &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/02/01/joining-an-orchestra-learning-in-the-face-of-terror/&#34;&gt;I joined&lt;/a&gt; the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.andrew.cmu.edu/user/auo/&#34;&gt;Carnegie Mellon All-University Orchestra&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another week has gone by, and what I thought might be a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/02/14/flute-progress-report-day-of-reckoning-approaches/&#34;&gt;day of reckoning&lt;/a&gt; has come and gone, and I am still playing the flute in the CMU AUO and have not dropped out!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a sample of the hardest music from Bernstein&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Symphonic Dances from West Side Story&amp;rdquo; that I&amp;rsquo;m still struggling to play correctly, cleanly, and in tempo:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/flute-music/west-side-story-fugue.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;West Side Story: Fugue&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/flute-music/west-side-story-rumble.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;West Side Story: Rumble&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It is not very visible from my photos, but I have a huge number of pencil markings on my copy of the score.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story as of now:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;practice-in-the-past-week&#34;&gt;Practice in the past week&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;getting-down-the-basics&#34;&gt;Getting down the basics&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last Wednesday, I continued with focusing purely on improving technique with the Rubank method book. I did not even look at the Gershwin or Bernstein music for orchestra. I simply recognize that I have to focus on making fundamental progress in technique and trust that this will enable me to actually play the hard music at hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have not written much about this strategy, but I feel that it is effective and that many &lt;em&gt;amateurs&lt;/em&gt; do not practice or pursue their various life activities with this discipline, and therefore fall short of reaching their potential. And then typically, we amateurs make excuses, blaming lack of talent or lack of time for our slow progress or quick plateau at a mediocre level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is something in the general culture that encourages immediate gratification at the expense of true &lt;em&gt;craft&lt;/em&gt;. Yes, it is true that we cannot give our all toward our hobbies, the way we might for what we consider our jobs, but at the same time, if you add up the number of hours we spend at our hobbies, they actually do add up, and we might as well have made them count efficiently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me to attack the hard passages of music prematurely without building up technique would be analogous to the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;never running before but aiming to run a marathon in four months, and jumping straight into trying to run 15 miles&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;being a non-programmer and wanting to create a cool Web site in a month, but trying to read a book like &amp;ldquo;Learn Web Programming in 7 Days&amp;rdquo; and not really mastering concepts such as variables and functions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;never having cooked but deciding to make a really fancy and subtle French dish without mastering the basics of knife usage or the properties of butter&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People like shortcuts. But they usually do not succeed, and even if they do, don&amp;rsquo;t provide a sustainable path of growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My real goal isn&amp;rsquo;t just to survive playing in an orchestra concert. That&amp;rsquo;s actually just an incentive for my real goal, which is to improve my overall technique, so that I can continue to play music in any genre, any ensemble, as I wish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;an-off-day&#34;&gt;An off day&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, the next day, Thursday, I was feeling tired and unmotivated for practice. This happens sometimes. In fact, typically it happens once a week. I&amp;rsquo;m human. I can&amp;rsquo;t magically improve a huge amount every single day. Sometimes I&amp;rsquo;m tired. Sometimes I backslide, and notes come out jumbled, slow, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This, too, is a part of life. I&amp;rsquo;ve found the hard way that it&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; best to just push through and waste time and emotional energy. &lt;em&gt;Overtraining&lt;/em&gt; doesn&amp;rsquo;t help. Sometimes it is best to just take a break. I generally prefer to take an &lt;em&gt;active&lt;/em&gt; break.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, on Thursday I decided to put away the technique practice, which was not going well, and instead have fun sight-reading a bunch of music I had gotten out of the library earlier. I played around sight-reading &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Play-Puccini-Arias-Transcribed-Flute/dp/0634046209/&#34;&gt;transcribed opera arias from Puccini&lt;/a&gt; (I secretly love singing them in Italian even though I&amp;rsquo;m not a soprano or female!), &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Debussy-Album-Flute-Piano/dp/9043129712/&#34;&gt;transcriptions from Debussy&amp;rsquo;s piano music&lt;/a&gt; (I want to play the original piano pieces some day), and a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/World-Music-Cuba-Flute-play-along/dp/3702465804&#34;&gt;World Music Cuba&lt;/a&gt; album. It was a lot of fun playing real, lyrical music. I especially liked playing the Cuban music, since I always dreamed about doing that back when I was dancing salsa, rumba, cha cha, and bolero (I also have a goal of seriously singing this genre of music).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: eventually I would like to actually practice some of these music arrangements seriously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;update-of-2012-11-17&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-11-17)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nine months after this blog post, I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/11/17/a-childhood-dream-come-true-i-am-now-finally-singing-for-real/&#34;&gt;sang bolero for the first time in my life, to Abby&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;update-of-2013-03-17&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-03-17)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over a year later, I ended up playing selections from the World Music Cuba book &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/17/finally-doing-some-latin-music-jamming-on-flute/&#34;&gt;at a party&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;continued-practice&#34;&gt;Continued practice&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Friday and Saturday I was back doing technique, and Saturday I finally hit the CMU AUO music again. I noticed that I was playing the high notes on the flute better. Also, of course, I improved my speed and facility at many scales, but I won&amp;rsquo;t bore with listing metronome numbers to indicate my progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;sunday-s-orchestra-rehearsal&#34;&gt;Sunday&amp;rsquo;s orchestra rehearsal&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;sectional-for-woodwinds&#34;&gt;Sectional for woodwinds&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I arrived at 6:30 PM on Sunday for the woodwind sectional, but only one other person was there! People were running late, apparently. I was concerned when only three flutes (plus piccolo) showed up: did we lose another flute? (Later in the full rehearsal, two others joined us.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that in the woodwind sectional, collectively we were still struggling, and therefore I was not as out of place as I had feared I might be. It was a very useful rehearsal, in which many different instruments&amp;rsquo; parts started falling in place. It was at this point that I realized that I was having trouble not only because of my own problems but also because other peoples&amp;rsquo; problems were affecting me. I was having trouble coming in at the right time in many places not only because I was counting badly (although I&amp;rsquo;ve been working steadily at improving my counting) but also because so many other lines were not coming in at the right place either, so I could not rely on listening to others as a way of finding my place. Anyway, we made huge progress in some very difficult music. I actually believe, for the first time, that we might be able to get this stuff working for the concert.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;full-rehearsal&#34;&gt;Full rehearsal&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maria kept on being disappointed in the full rehearsal, asking if we had actually listened to the music, because we were still having so much trouble. (Actually, I have the music and listen to the whole thing at least once every other day.) Perhaps it was a blessing in disguise that so many of us were still unprepared, because it enabled me to not be completely left behind, as we kept the tempos still on the slow side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even so, there were sections in which I simply was unable to keep up. I feel that I really need to master most of them by next rehearsal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;this-week-s-practice&#34;&gt;This week&amp;rsquo;s practice&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My practice this week so far since the rehearsal has been good. I&amp;rsquo;m still focusing on building technique.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Monday, I made significant improvements in my high notes with scales. I worked some with the Bernstein.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Tuesday, I continued Rubank, and went back to some real basics, playing long tones, working on control of dynamics, and relaxation. I did not touch orchestra music at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, I did an abbreviated Rubank practice, then launched into much work on the Bernstein, to make things faster. As I do once or twice a week, I included a &amp;ldquo;test&amp;rdquo; for myself in which I played through all the problematic sections of the piece along with an actual recording. I&amp;rsquo;m doing much, much better now. There is still hope that I might be able to play most of the piece at full speed by Sunday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-look-back-to-three-months-ago&#34;&gt;A look back to three months ago&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is amusing to look back to what I was still having trouble playing, as a flute beginner, three months ago. I was just starting to work through a collection of &amp;ldquo;easy flute classics&amp;rdquo;:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/flute-music/moyse-easy-classics.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Moyse Collection of Easy Flute Classics&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Compare these simple, slow scores with the Bernstein excerpts in the photos at the beginning of this blog post!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;recorder&#34;&gt;Recorder&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Needless to say, I&amp;rsquo;ve completely put away my recorders. I did go to the monthly meeting of the Pittsburgh chapter of the American Recorder Society on Sunday to play, but that is all I will do with recorder until after the April orchestra concert. I would like to get serious about recorder again for late spring and summer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, I felt I was automatically slightly better at playing recorder even without touching it for a month. It&amp;rsquo;s the cross-training effect. Music is music, whichever instrument you&amp;rsquo;re playing: breath control, tone awareness, flexibility of fingers, etc. Even if I did sometimes forget my fingerings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m still enjoying improving at flute and slowly getting closer to being able to play the second flute part of the Bernstein in its entirety. I get less and less panicky about being in the orchestra as I &amp;ldquo;catch up&amp;rdquo; according to plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2012-03-12&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-03-12)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ended up &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/12/quitting-the-cmu-all-university-orchestra-one-of-the-hardest-decisions-in-my-life/&#34;&gt;quitting the CMU AUO&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>