<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Hiking on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/hiking/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Hiking on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/hiking/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Remembering the gift of being introduced to kayaking six years ago by a total stranger</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/05/25/remembering-the-gift-of-being-introduced-to-kayaking-six-years-ago-by-a-total-stranger/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 May 2014 23:01:47 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/05/25/remembering-the-gift-of-being-introduced-to-kayaking-six-years-ago-by-a-total-stranger/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Over Memorial Day weekend, Abby and I went kayaking on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kiskiminetas_River&#34;&gt;Kiski River&lt;/a&gt;, at the invitation of Steve, the guy we first met six years ago. There&amp;rsquo;s a story I&amp;rsquo;d like to share about what happened by chance six years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;first-meeting-steve-at-his-soup-hike-in-2008&#34;&gt;First meeting Steve at his &amp;ldquo;soup hike&amp;rdquo; in 2008&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I met Steve on a Pittsburgh hiking meetup hike on June 8, 2008 that he hosted in Apollo, PA, the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/pittsburghhikers/events/8046324/&#34;&gt;second &amp;ldquo;soup hike&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; that has since then become a regular tradition. 13 people attended that soup hike. (The first instance of the soup hike, which we did not attend, was &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/pittsburghhikers/events/7578281/&#34;&gt;on April 5, 2008&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The original theme of the soup hike was that since the first one was in cold weather, participants were invited to bring soup to share in Steve&amp;rsquo;s garage after the hike. It would turn out, of course, that people brought all kinds of food, not just &amp;ldquo;soup&amp;rdquo;, but the name has stuck!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The truth is that I had to drag Abby into attending our first soup hike. Although we had done a little bit of hiking after we first met dancing, she had been uninterested in the longer hikes (over five miles) that I liked to do. (It turns out that she had a lot of knee and ankle and endurance problems at the time; we&amp;rsquo;ve found solutions in recent years, largely through the radical change in footwear to Vibram FiveFingers and also changes in diet.) I was very sad about this, because to be honest, I did not know how much longer I could date someone who was not going to be part of my weekend outdoors life (we had been together a year, but I was still spending much of my time hiking with my office mate John on weekends). It was a huge deal to me to encourage Abby to join me for hikes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We both enjoyed the hike tremendously. It&amp;rsquo;s a beautiful hike.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/soup-hike-2008-06-08/abby-franklin.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When Abby saw Jackson Falls, she knew she wanted to come back again to swim!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/soup-hike-2008-06-08/jackson-falls.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;kayaking&#34;&gt;Kayaking&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the hike, I was surprised to see some people taking kayaks out to the Kiski River. Steve was letting people use his kayaks!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/soup-hike-2008-06-08/kayak.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At this point in my life, I had &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; voluntarily been in the water before. I&amp;rsquo;m terrible at swimming, had near-drowning experiences when young, and had never touched a kayak or canoe before. But Abby was all excited, and the view on the river look so nice.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/soup-hike-2008-06-08/kiski.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So Steve said we could briefly get on the river, and each of us took a kayak and just paddled around in the river for a few minutes. I was so scared the first time, and disoriented, but after a while, decided I really enjoyed this!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In summary, it was an amazing day, during which we met this great guy Steve who led us on a great hike, provided space and food in his garage, and even let us play with his kayaks. I was profoundly moved by his generosity, and the sense of fun that everyone brought to the event. Steve put us on his mailing list for his regular paddling trips, and ever since then, Abby and I have tried to join him for a couple of paddling trips a year, as our schedules and weather conditions allow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;some-photos-from-the-paddling-trip-we-just-came-back-from&#34;&gt;Some photos from the paddling trip we just came back from&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The paddling trip &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/kayaking-129/events/181882042/&#34;&gt;we just did&lt;/a&gt; with Steve was a 9-miler on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Conemaugh_River&#34;&gt;Conemaugh River&lt;/a&gt;, from &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blairsville,_Pennsylvania&#34;&gt;Blairsville&lt;/a&gt;. The water was rather low this day, but the weather was perfect: sunny, temperature in the 70s, not too high, and breezy, not so humid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that until today, we had not paddled in two years, because of our life situations last year, so we were really excited to have this opportunity this year.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/paddling-2014-05-25/finishing-loading.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Cute doggie coming with us:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/paddling-2014-05-25/dog.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The group starting down the river while I hang back to take a photo:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/paddling-2014-05-25/starting.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Passing a rookery:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/paddling-2014-05-25/rookery.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Lunch break on the water because the water levels were too low for us to get off on solid ground.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/paddling-2014-05-25/lunch.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A panorama:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/paddling-2014-05-25/panorama.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of several bridges along the route:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/paddling-2014-05-25/bridge.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Turning off to take out:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/paddling-2014-05-25/turn.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Panorama at take-out point:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/paddling-2014-05-25/panorama-take-out.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;logistics&#34;&gt;Logistics&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s really complicated setting up these paddling trips, because not only does Steve personally hoist up and tie up several kayaks to tow himself, but also we try to consolidate people into as few vehicles as possible in order to set up an efficient shuttle between the take-out and put-in points. And after paddling, all the kayaks have to be put back on, and everyone transported back to their appropriate vehicles, and some people ending back up at Steve&amp;rsquo;s place while others just go back home. Basically, if you sign up for one of these trips, plan to spend the whole day outside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, on this trip, which was especially involved because of how far everything was, and because it did not end at Steve&amp;rsquo;s place, we met up at 9:30 AM but didn&amp;rsquo;t leave till more like 10:30 AM. After arriving at the put-in location, we unloaded, Steve went with some others to drive to the take-out location, take one car back to the put-in, and then we finally got on the river at noon! We ended up getting off the river at 3:30 PM, but then had to get back to Steve&amp;rsquo;s place and help unload and clean up, and by the time we were done, it was 5:00 PM, time for a quick shower and then dinner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Very time-consuming, but it&amp;rsquo;s good to invest the time to just relax and go with the flow all day and enjoy the scenery and camaraderie, rather than have anything else planned for later in the day!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;food&#34;&gt;Food&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby made and brought a tasty zucchini dish, and some smoked Gouda cheese, to share for after paddling, and Steve provided burgers to grill. Many of the participants were newcomers and didn&amp;rsquo;t realize they should bring food to contribute, but they know now. In any case, there was still leftover watermelon, chips, cookies, and beers from the previous day. People also brought in foccacia, cole slaw, and pasta salad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ate two leftover homemade cookies immediately!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/paddling-2014-05-25/cookie1.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/paddling-2014-05-25/cookie2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby&amp;rsquo;s zucchini was popular:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/paddling-2014-05-25/zucchini.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Steve&amp;rsquo;s burger patties, just off his grill:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/paddling-2014-05-25/burgers.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;bonfire&#34;&gt;Bonfire&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There have been occasions when we have stayed long enough to sit in front of the bonfire that Steve likes to make (we have camped overnight outside his place a couple of times), but usually we are really beat and head out to drive home before dark, so that&amp;rsquo;s what we did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Six years ago I never went into water, but then thanks to meeting Steve, have had the opportunity to do kayaking a couple of times a year with Abby, expanding my experience of the natural world. It&amp;rsquo;s really a remarkable experience going down the river, powering yourself, facing the vastness of water and under the open sky. Also, it&amp;rsquo;s been inspiring to meet someone like Steve who is so generous and shares his knowledge and love of nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Have you been introduced to something new and beautiful in recent years, thanks to the kindness of someone you just met? If so, what are your thoughts on your fortune?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>When I&#39;m feeling too tired to venture out, there&#39;s always Frick Park</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/05/18/when-im-feeling-too-tired-to-venture-out-theres-always-frick-park/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 May 2014 22:27:39 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/05/18/when-im-feeling-too-tired-to-venture-out-theres-always-frick-park/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Because of the rain forecast and fatigue (I had a tough week), Abby and I ended up not venturing out of the city of Pittsburgh for a hike yesterday. But this afternoon, things seemed to clear up enough that we went for a hike in our local Frick Park. It was a bit chilly actually, so we wore raincoats and also I wore a hat in gloves (yes, it&amp;rsquo;s May).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s been a real blessing that Frick Park is so close to where we live, because that means we have no excuse not to go out into nature and to get some exercise, even if time or energy means we can&amp;rsquo;t do something more adventurous. Fact is, I took Abby around a bunch of trails that she had not yet explored, so there is no shortage of novelty in Frick Park itself! We were out for almost three hours. I led Abby to the network of trails by Nine Mile Run, then backtracked and went north of Fern Hollow, going up Tranquil Trail and branching off, before coming back down, and then back up toward home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Do you have a local favorite hangout (in nature or otherwise) that provides comfort and stimulation when you want to get out of the home but don&amp;rsquo;t want to go too far? How do you keep your experiences there interesting?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A short Sunday hike in Frick Park</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/05/11/a-short-sunday-hike-in-frick-park/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 May 2014 21:09:24 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/05/11/a-short-sunday-hike-in-frick-park/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Abby and I had planned to go on a hike yesterday, but rain discouraged us, plus we had a late start to the day, and we were planning to check out part of the Bach Festival in Pittsburgh anyway (and did). This afternoon, it was nice and clear, so we did a little exploratory hike in Frick Park.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A little stream crossing:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/frick-park-2014-05-11/stream-crossing.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Poison ivy lurks everywhere:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/frick-park-2014-05-11/poison-ivy.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A bridge that has gotten lopsided:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/frick-park-2014-05-11/bridge.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Ducks:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/frick-park-2014-05-11/ducks.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Our first hike at Coopers Rock State Forest</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/05/03/our-first-hike-at-coopers-rock-state-forest/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 May 2014 21:36:12 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/05/03/our-first-hike-at-coopers-rock-state-forest/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Abby and I went on our first hike at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.coopersrockstateforest.com/&#34;&gt;Coopers Rock State Forest&lt;/a&gt;, joining a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/pittsburghhikers/events/169497262&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh hiking meetup event&lt;/a&gt; led by Terri and Jeff. This is a regularly held hike that we simply never got around to in previous years because of schedule conflicts or other circumstances, so we were delighted to have the opportunity to go this time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d only been to Coopers Rock once, as part of a rock climbing trip, which turned out to be an embarrassing disaster for me, because after climbing only a few minutes, I decided the whole thing just made me nervous, and I sat out the rest of the day. But I was there long enough to see how beautiful the area was, and knew I wanted to go back just to hike, not to climb!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;getting-there&#34;&gt;Getting there&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The drive from Pittsburgh took just over an hour and a half; we took the most direct, shortest route involving taking route 51 south. (We returned instead by way of Morgantown, the long route that uses I-79, but this was a huge mistake because of traffic as we neared Pittsburgh. I don&amp;rsquo;t see any reason to take this longer route in the future, since it doesn&amp;rsquo;t actually save any time even if there had not been congestion on the highways.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I took John and Courtney, since each of them also live in Squirrel Hill, in our car to carpool together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;parking&#34;&gt;Parking&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out, as I suspected, that parking is quite scarce in the main Coopers Rock parking lot. Now that spring is here, this is prime season for people to be visiting, of course. We arrived early enough to grab the very last spot, actually, in the main parking lot. There are other parking spaces further out, but even those were not plentiful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;weather&#34;&gt;Weather&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was always a chance of rain. We completely lucked out, because it didn&amp;rsquo;t start raining until after we&amp;rsquo;d completed the main hike. Then it was pouring. Pouring rain would have made the hike far less pleasant, because of the rocks and mud, but part of the experience of hiking is taking whatever nature gives us, in all humility and gratitude. We head out in the morning not knowing exactly what to expect. Sometimes the forecast the day before a planned hike looks pretty bad, in which case Abby and I might choose to cancel, but we tend not to cancel that often.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;photos&#34;&gt;Photos&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re a member of the Pittsburgh meetup group, you can see &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/pittsburghhikers/photos/21676842/&#34;&gt;photos people took&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-hike&#34;&gt;The hike&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The forecast for the day was supposed to be temperatures in the 60s and 70s F in the middle of the day. In the morning at 10 AM, however, it started out rather cool, temperature possibly in the high 30s. I was glad I packed a winter hat and gloves, just in case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Around thirty people showed up for the group hike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Terri had her trail map ready, accompanied by Jeff who acted as the sweep. By the way, this hike is part of an extended camping weekend that they organize, running from Friday through Sunday, so many of the hikers had already camped one night, and many planned to camp another night. Abby and I did not feel ready to do camping yet this year, so we went just for the hike.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/coopers-rock-2014-05-03/terri-and-jeff.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Before we started the hike proper, we checked out the main overlook. It&amp;rsquo;s beautiful. You can see Cheat River and beyond.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/coopers-rock-2014-05-03/overlook.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/coopers-rock-2014-05-03/overlook2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;heading-down&#34;&gt;Heading down&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main hike was an out (mostly down, all the way to the river) and back up, roughly 7 miles. This is not very far at all, but given the terrain and significant elevation change, as well as waiting for everyone (since it was a large group), it took a while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of rhododendron around:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/coopers-rock-2014-05-03/rhododendron.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There were also many little wildflowers along the trails during the hike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We took the rocky, Rattlesnake Trail winding along cliffs. By the way, &lt;strong&gt;using a pair of hiking poles&lt;/strong&gt; during the entire hike made things much easier. Both Abby and I used a pair of hiking poles as well as Vibram FiveFingers KSO Trek shoes (which prompted a lot of questions).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I liked how peaceful and quiet most of the hike was. Sometimes Abby and I have gone on hikes where the hum of civilization never really goes away. Here, the main hum was of water, which was usually not too far away.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/coopers-rock-2014-05-03/up.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Abby spotted a huge toad!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/coopers-rock-2014-05-03/toad.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;lunch-break&#34;&gt;Lunch break&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were warned about poison ivy where we stopped for lunch by the river:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/coopers-rock-2014-05-03/poison-ivy.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/coopers-rock-2014-05-03/lunch-break.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;back-up&#34;&gt;Back up&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I always find it strangely appealing to hike along running water. Water makes me feel like I am not alone or lost, that there is something soothing and dependable out there:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/coopers-rock-2014-05-03/water.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It was fun to see ferns unfurling here and there:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/coopers-rock-2014-05-03/ferns.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We went back a different way than we came, and that involved a bunch of stream crossings over bridges. Here, some of us sat on a bridge for a photo:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/coopers-rock-2014-05-03/bridge.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;henry-clay-iron-furnace&#34;&gt;Henry Clay Iron Furnace&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We took a detour to the historic &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Henry_Clay_Furnace&#34;&gt;Henry Clay Iron Furnace&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/coopers-rock-2014-05-03/henry-clay-iron-furnace.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/coopers-rock-2014-05-03/henry-clay-iron-furnace-back.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I crawled inside to take a look.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/coopers-rock-2014-05-03/henry-clay-iron-furnace-up.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/coopers-rock-2014-05-03/henry-clay-iron-furnace-entrance.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;lost&#34;&gt;Lost?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We got &amp;ldquo;lost&amp;rdquo; on the way back to the parking lot, but not really. We missed a turn, but quickly, Terri noticed that things did not look right, and we backtracked, and turned onto the Rhododenron Trail as we should have. All good!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/coopers-rock-2014-05-03/rhododendron-trail.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/coopers-rock-2014-05-03/map.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Back to civilization:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/coopers-rock-2014-05-03/done.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;missing-the-optional-hike&#34;&gt;Missing the optional hike&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was an optional 3-mile hike planned after the main one, to reach another scenic area, but Terri and Jeff decided it was too complicated to officially reorganize a group for it, and just left it to everyone to figure out appropriate car pools to park in a lot nearer to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The four of us drove to the lot a bit later than some others, and unfortunately, someone pulled into the last parking space. As it was already drizzling rain anyway, and there was no parking to be found nearby, we just waved goodbye and started heading home. Maybe this was a good thing, because the rain quickly began to pour really hard!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coopers Rock State Forest is a great place to visit. The hiking is great, with varied terrain and elevation changes, lots to see. Perhaps in the future Abby and I will check out the camping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Have you been to Coopers Rock? For hiking, cross-country skiing, camping, or rock climbing?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hiking again in Boyce-Mayview Park three months later</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/04/12/hiking-again-in-boyce-mayview-park-three-months-later/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Apr 2014 20:58:26 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/04/12/hiking-again-in-boyce-mayview-park-three-months-later/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;For the New Year in January, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/01/01/happy-new-year-with-a-boyce-mayview-park-hike-wetlands/&#34;&gt;Abby and I went on a brisk winter hike through the Pittsburgh hiking meetup group in Boyce-Mayview Park&lt;/a&gt;, which was new to us at the time. We enjoyed the experience so much that we knew that we were going to return in the spring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So on a warm and sunny afternoon (temperature rising beyond 70 degrees F), we went (by ourselves) to Boyce-Mayview Park to do some hiking. We ended up doing maybe eight miles. Obviously, things just looked different without the snow and ice, and with some vegetation and more active life forms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;parking&#34;&gt;Parking&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(You can download a detailed map of the park &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.twpusc.org/magazine/pdf/boyce-mayview-park_map.pdf&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We originally headed to parking at the trail head right next to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ardolinopizza.com/&#34;&gt;Ardolino&amp;rsquo;s Pizza&lt;/a&gt;, off Boyce Road, but the small parking lot was full, not unexpectedly, so we drove all the way around to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.twpusc.org/crc/crc-home&#34;&gt;Boyce-Mayview community and recreation center&lt;/a&gt; entrance from Mayview Road, to park in a lot further in near the Outdoor Classroom, use the restroom building next to it, and enter the trail systems from there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;our-hike&#34;&gt;Our hike&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We encountered a bit of mud on the trails that we took, but nothing too unpleasant. We both wore our Vibram FiveFingers KSO Trek shoes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We just basically wandered around, without any map or GPS, knowing that as long as we kept Chartiers Creek in sight, we could get back to where we started. Also, with all the many elevation changes, we could often see the community and recreation center up high. So we did not have to worry about getting lost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I very much enjoy hiking in the vicinity of water, seeing it and hearing it, so we spent a good deal time on the trails near Chartiers Creek, just following its curves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At one point in the wetlands we got excited and thought we saw an island and so we went there and hiked a trail there all the way till we realized it wasn&amp;rsquo;t really an island after all. It was fun being surrounded by water on both sides on a strip of land, but also that part of the hike involved a lot of bugs happy to try to bite us!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After about two hours, we eventually ended up at the Boyce Road trail head and I was really hungry and peeked into Ardolino&amp;rsquo;s, but Abby didn&amp;rsquo;t think it was a good idea for us to order pizza (we had packed our own lunch anyway), so we turned around and hiked back up, and stopped somewhere on a trail to sit and eat lunch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then we made our way back to our start. At one point it wasn&amp;rsquo;t clear how to get to a trail connecting where we were, high up, back to the trail next to Chartiers Creek, so we just took a &amp;ldquo;shortcut&amp;rdquo; (hiking poles are very helpful for the Boyce-Mayview Park in general), scrambling down to that trail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-few-photos-of-stuff-we-saw&#34;&gt;A few photos of stuff we saw&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;View from where we parked:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/boyce-mayview-2014-04-12/parking.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Parking&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The Outdoor Classroom and the restroom building:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/boyce-mayview-2014-04-12/outdoor-classroom.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Abby spotting an interesting bird:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/boyce-mayview-2014-04-12/critter.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A view of Chartiers Creek:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/boyce-mayview-2014-04-12/chartiers-creek.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A little garter snake crossed our path. You might be able spot it in this photo. At my request, Abby did &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; pick it up to show to me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/boyce-mayview-2014-04-12/garter-snake.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A sample trail winding around a hill:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/boyce-mayview-2014-04-12/hill-trail.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Rapids! We did see someone in a canoe further upstream.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/boyce-mayview-2014-04-12/rapids.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Flowers (sorry, I know very little about identifying flowers):&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/boyce-mayview-2014-04-12/flowers.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Crossing over to the &amp;ldquo;island&amp;rdquo;:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/boyce-mayview-2014-04-12/island.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We saw woodpeckers, geese, vultures, groundhogs, and other critters during the hike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without leaves on trees obstructing the view, it is fairly easy to see where one is, as far as elevation and landmarks (we knew we had to get back down to the creek level and then back upward to where we parked):&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/boyce-mayview-2014-04-12/elevation.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was great to return to Boyce-Mayview Park in the spring. I expect that we&amp;rsquo;ll go back in a couple more weeks, as more vegetation grows and even more birds hang out. I highly recommend checking out this park, located in Upper St. Clair just half an hour drive from the city of Pittsburgh.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A few sights from the Iron Grate Trail in Frick Park</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/04/06/a-few-sights-from-the-iron-grate-trail-in-frick-park/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Apr 2014 18:41:58 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/04/06/a-few-sights-from-the-iron-grate-trail-in-frick-park/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I did a leisurely hike in Frick Park near home, exploring a trail that I don&amp;rsquo;t usually run on, the Iron Grate Trail, because it is a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mtbproject.com/trail/3003110&#34;&gt;favorite trail for mountain bikers&lt;/a&gt;, and therefore tends to have muddy ruts that are not so pleasant for pedestrians, and also someone on a mountain bike could always come out of nowhere. But we were careful to keep our eyes and ears open, and share the trail, yielding to mountain bikers when perceiving them coming along.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An advantage of occasionally checking out these trails is simply that they are quieter, in terms of fewer pedestrians and dogs, and also, you get to see parts of the park that you wouldn&amp;rsquo;t otherwise see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Iron Grate Trail briefly became infamous in the local news a year ago because of reports of a &lt;a href=&#34;http://foresthills-regentsquare.patch.com/groups/police-and-fire/p/frick-park-visitors-on-edge-after-reports-of-violence&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;hatchet-wielding&amp;rdquo; person&lt;/a&gt; attacking someone on the trail, but I think that was an isolated incident.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;photo&#34;&gt;Photo&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s an amusing photo I took of Abby finding a hiding place along the trail:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/frick-park-hiding.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby hiding in a tree&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t take any photos of the new-looking signs reading &amp;ldquo;Iron Grate Trail&amp;rdquo; that we saw, but I just found out that &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburghparks.org/PTAGworkday04052014&#34;&gt;they were put up just days ago thanks to volunteers for the Pittsburgh Trail Advocacy Group&lt;/a&gt;. We did notice that the trail showed other evidence of having been maintained recently. Very nice work and thank you!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also saw some chickens running around in someone&amp;rsquo;s back yard, from a section of the trail behind a residential area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;video&#34;&gt;Video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a random video I found of someone riding into and along the Iron Grate Trail:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/x-FxY3BoHag&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cold but pretty winter hike in Wingfield Pines</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/01/18/cold-but-pretty-winter-hike-in-wingfield-pines/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Jan 2014 20:10:22 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/01/18/cold-but-pretty-winter-hike-in-wingfield-pines/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Less than three weeks ago, Abby and I went on a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/01/01/happy-new-year-with-a-boyce-mayview-park-hike-wetlands/&#34;&gt;great hike in Boyce-Mayview Park in Upper St. Clair, led by Gary Byrdman&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today we went on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/pittsburghhikers/events/160997422/&#34;&gt;another hike with Gary, very close to the Boyce-Mayview Park, but in a neighboring park&lt;/a&gt;, the Wingfield Pines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;cold&#34;&gt;Cold!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a beautiful day, clear sky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it was pretty freaking cold, hovering around 10F, I think, maybe a bit higher. I was slightly underdressed, and paid the price. I should have worn my thicker gloves and also long underwear. After getting home, it took a long time for my body to return to normal. The problem is that in previous winters of my life, I have not gone out hiking when the temperature is below 20F, so this was a first for me. Now I know better what I need to wear.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/wingfield-pines-abby-franklin.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Wingfield Pines&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;about-the-park&#34;&gt;About the park&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We parked across the street from the park entrance because the parking area at the entrance is pretty small. Across the street is a large parking lot for the community center.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were just six of us braving the cold for this hike. Gary and others being locals, told us a lot about the history of the park. It was really fascinating. The land has undergone many changes of ownership and restoration over the years. I looked online after the hike and found useful information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The land is currently owned by the Allegheny Land Trust and here is the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.alleghenylandtrust.org/properties/wingfield/overview/&#34;&gt;official site of the area&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had a leisurely hike, going about five miles in two and a half hours, stopping often to check out the sights. One of us brought her dog along. She lives nearby and walks her dog twice a day here! What she really loves is that it&amp;rsquo;s officially a legal off-leash area for dogs. So this place is great for dog lovers who want their dogs to truly get their exercise! We bumped into some happy-looking dogs and their owners during the hike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.hedinenv.com/projectpages/wingfieldpines.htm&#34;&gt;water treatment system&lt;/a&gt; is pretty interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;photos&#34;&gt;Photos&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t take many photos because every time I took off my gloves to be able to use my phone camera, my fingers got super cold, so I gave up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But photos some others of us took are available &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/pittsburghhikers/photos/19589162&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Julie took particularly detailed and beautiful photos of cardinals, bluebirds, woodpeckers, and ducks that we saw.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;coming-back-in-spring-and-summer&#34;&gt;Coming back in spring and summer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I will definitely come back in spring and summer. The park is lovely in winter, but it will be even more gorgeous in spring and summer, quite obviously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To get an idea of what the place is like when it&amp;rsquo;s not winter, here is a sample link I found to &lt;a href=&#34;http://upperstclair.patch.com/groups/around-town/p/wingfield-pines-shines-on-a-wet-afternoon&#34;&gt;local coverage&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A video:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/4KmHnkG4Enc&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out Wingfield Pines, in Upper St. Clair. It&amp;rsquo;s less than a half-hour drive from Pittsburgh. It&amp;rsquo;s beautiful.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Happy New Year with a Boyce-Mayview Park hike: wetlands, creeks, beavers, woodpeckers, waterfalls...</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/01/01/happy-new-year-with-a-boyce-mayview-park-hike-wetlands/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2014 19:57:07 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/01/01/happy-new-year-with-a-boyce-mayview-park-hike-wetlands/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Happy New Year 2014!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I started off this new year with a lovely &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/pittsburghhikers/events/157809022&#34;&gt;hike with the Pittsburgh hiking meetup group&lt;/a&gt;, led by Gary Byrdman. It was in Boyce-Mayview Park, a park we&amp;rsquo;d never been to before &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.twpusc.org/rec-leisure/parks-fields&#34;&gt;in Upper St. Clair&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/boyce-mayview-2014-01-01/break.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a beautiful day, not too cold (over 20F), and mostly not too muddy or icy either, thankfully. Abby and I did each use a pair of hiking poles, and many of us used &lt;a href=&#34;http://kahtoola.com/product/microspikes/&#34;&gt;MICROSpikes&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.yaktrax.com/&#34;&gt;Yaktrax&lt;/a&gt; also during the hike, but it turned out that the spikes were actually something of a hassle because snow accumulated under them for people. If it had been more icy out, I would have used spikes, however.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was originally hoping to wear my relatively new minimalist New Balance Minimus Zero trail running shoes for this hike, but quickly decided that this would be a bad idea mainly because of the risk of getting my feet cold and wet, so I wrote my old Montrail Rockridge trail running shoes, which I haven&amp;rsquo;t worn in years because they have gotten a bit small for me, requiring me to wear very thin socks (which I did on this hike). Far from minimalist, but in the winter in the face of water dangers (and indeed, we had a couple of stream crossings in which I got a little wet), I don&amp;rsquo;t have a true minimalist shoe yet.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://s7d5.scene7.com/is/image/ColumbiaSportswear/S11_GM2098_654_f?$MTR_pdp_lg$&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Montrail Rockridge&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The hike lasted about two and a half hours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had a great group of people, and Gary even brought breakfast to share with us. After the hike, I eagerly sampled his treats. What a guy! During the hike, he pointed out interesting features, such as beaver dams, woodpecker holes (and we heard woodpeckers too), places that are great for birding in the spring, and a nice waterfall that was partially iced but running.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;photos&#34;&gt;Photos&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re a member of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/pittsburghhikers&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh hiking meetup group&lt;/a&gt;, you have access to the event page and the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/pittsburghhikers/photos/19309272/&#34;&gt;photo page for the hike&lt;/a&gt;, where I uploaded a couple dozen photos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m posting just a few here, to whet your appetite for this park. There was such varied terrain and so much to see!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Parking at the trail head:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/boyce-mayview-2014-01-01/trail-parking.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Breakfast by Gary:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/boyce-mayview-2014-01-01/gary-breakfast.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A beaver was at this tree:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/boyce-mayview-2014-01-01/beaver-tree.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Stream crossing:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/boyce-mayview-2014-01-01/stream-crossing.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;On a trail:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/boyce-mayview-2014-01-01/trail.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Waterfall:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/boyce-mayview-2014-01-01/waterfall.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Going uphill:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/boyce-mayview-2014-01-01/uphill.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Short break:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/boyce-mayview-2014-01-01/break.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the meadows we crossed:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/boyce-mayview-2014-01-01/meadow.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Up:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/boyce-mayview-2014-01-01/up.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I really enjoyed this hike. We promised ourselves that we would return to it next spring and summer. There&amp;rsquo;s clearly so much to enjoy and explore in Boyce-Mayview Park.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to check it out yourself, the Pittsburgh Meetup group often has hikes in this park.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love living in Western Pennsylvania. There is so much to see around here. I will never get bored here. I feel blessed to be living here in Pittsburgh.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Beechview urban hike: funky steps, Canton Avenue climb, delicious pizza at Slice on Broadway</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/12/28/beechview-urban-hike/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Dec 2013 19:07:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/12/28/beechview-urban-hike/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Abby and I wanted to go out on a hike together, but the trails tend not to be so much to hike on these winter days, so we decided to do an exploratory urban hike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I randomly chose for us to explore &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beechview_(Pittsburgh)&#34;&gt;Beechview&lt;/a&gt;, which is actually still part of the city of Pittsburgh even though it is south, across the Monongahela River. We&amp;rsquo;d never been to this neighborhood before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, the choice wasn&amp;rsquo;t quite random.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/beechview-2013-12-28/mural.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;canton-avenue&#34;&gt;Canton Avenue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I originally thought of checking this place out because of recently hearing about &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Canton_Avenue&#34;&gt;Canton Avenue&lt;/a&gt;, which is used in the annual &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dirty_Dozen_%28bicycle_competition%29&#34;&gt;Dirty Dozen&lt;/a&gt; bike competition (see &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dannychew.com/dd.html&#34;&gt;Danny Chew&amp;rsquo;s site&lt;/a&gt;). Canton Avenue is the &amp;ldquo;steepest officially recorded public street in the United States&amp;rdquo;. I know some people who did the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.npr.org/2013/12/01/248090521/hill-after-hill-hundreds-crank-away-in-pittsburgh-bike-race&#34;&gt;Dirty Dozen this year (2013)&lt;/a&gt;, so Canton Avenue was fresh in my mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have no intention of ever biking up Canton Avenue, but its existence got me curious and I thought, why not check out a new neighborhood and walk up this street as part of a hike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;pizza&#34;&gt;Pizza&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was also craving some pizza. So I checked to see if there was any interesting pizza place in Beechview. It turned out that there was a fairly new place called &lt;a href=&#34;http://sliceonbroadway.com/&#34;&gt;Slice on Broadway&lt;/a&gt; in Beechview! So it was settled. We&amp;rsquo;d walk around the neighborhood, check out Canton Avenue, and eat at Slice on Broadway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We did that and had a good time. And the pizza was actually quite good: a relatively thin crust, the way I like it. We were so hungry that we each ate an antipasto salad (pretty good) before the large specialty pizza was ready (well, yes, we did take home leftovers).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing we didn&amp;rsquo;t do was navigate all the steps we saw, because of the residual ice that obviously made things dangerous. Maybe we&amp;rsquo;ll come back later in the spring and take a tour of the steps. We find the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/08/my-god-its-full-of-stairs-pittsburgh-step-trek-2011/&#34;&gt;steps of Pittsburgh&lt;/a&gt; fascinating, but still have not explored all the neighborhoods that have such steps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;some-photos&#34;&gt;Some photos&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/beechview-2013-12-28/steps-view.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Steps and view&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/beechview-2013-12-28/steps-street.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Steps for sidewalk&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s pretty hilly in Beechview:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/beechview-2013-12-28/hilly.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Hilly streets&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We braved this staircase that involved a little bit of snow:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/beechview-2013-12-28/steps-snowy.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Steps with snow&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There was this weird short trail:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/beechview-2013-12-28/trail.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Trail&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Emerging from the trail:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/beechview-2013-12-28/after-trail.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;After trail&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Well, this is the view going up Canton Avenue. It&amp;rsquo;s steep but short:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/beechview-2013-12-28/canton-avenue.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Canton Avenue&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Some steps along a street:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/beechview-2013-12-28/steps-sloping-street.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Steps sloping on a street&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The trolley in action:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/beechview-2013-12-28/trolley.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The station where the trolley had come from:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/beechview-2013-12-28/station.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;More steps, but we were getting hungry, and so we did not follow them:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/beechview-2013-12-28/steps-to-where.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/beechview-2013-12-28/mural.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Pizza! I almost forgot to take a photo as we already started devouring the pizza:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/beechview-2013-12-28/pizza.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Pizza&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Did glucosamine and MSM relieve my knee pain?</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/28/did-glucosamine-and-msm-relieve-my-knee-pain/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2013 22:39:20 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/28/did-glucosamine-and-msm-relieve-my-knee-pain/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.drug3k.com/img2/msm_16804_4_%28big%29_.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;MSM&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I just saw an article &lt;a href=&#34;http://well.blogs.nytimes.com/2013/10/28/ask-well-glucosamine-and-msm-for-joint-pain/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Glucosamine and MSM for Joint Pain?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; that brought up some old memories. The article examined whether these supplements are actually useful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-story&#34;&gt;My story&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started running and hiking over a decade ago, at age 29. Some of my blog posts here have discussed why and how I started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the first couple of years of such activity, I was plagued with a lot of knee and other pain (especially shin pain). I experimented with many things, including changing types of shoes and foot landing form. Meanwhile, someone told me about &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Methylsulfonylmethane&#34;&gt;MSM&lt;/a&gt; and swore by it for his joint pain, and shared some with me. He showed me packets of white powder he bought from bulk by mail order, and I periodically mixed some in with water to drink. I was never sure whether it was effective, but wanted to believe it was. But I still got knee pain periodically; I never knew whether I got it less bad than when I wasn&amp;rsquo;t taking MSM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-actual-solution-to-pain&#34;&gt;My actual solution to pain&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eventually, I did fix my knee pain, so I stopped taking MSM (and glucosamine, which I was taking also, as late as 2003).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My solution, found by sheer trial and error and desperation, was to migrate entirely to wearing only minimalist shoes: in particular, a zero-drop &lt;em&gt;heel&lt;/em&gt;. Some experiments with different shoes revealed to me a clear correlation between knee pain and the height of the heel of a shoe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was very difficult for me to accept this solution, as I had acquired a large collection of non-minimalist shoes: in fact, I had stocked up on some of the &amp;ldquo;less bad&amp;rdquo; shoes and had boxes of shoes in my basement that I had never opened!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the complete disappearance of my impact pain and injuries said it all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, a decade later, there is much more widespread knowledge of the differences in &lt;em&gt;impact&lt;/em&gt; forces depending on shoe style and foot strike. Obviously, there are many variables and individual differences in biomechanics, but here is a &lt;a href=&#34;http://barefootrunning.fas.harvard.edu/4BiomechanicsofFootStrike.html&#34;&gt;good overview of the sorts of things that happen during foot strike&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://barefootrunning.fas.harvard.edu/Fig1b.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Shoe heel strike&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I seem particularly susceptible to the forces on my knees when running in shoes with a built-up heel, so I have &lt;em&gt;finally&lt;/em&gt; decided to completely abandon them. Up till now, I had abandoned them except for &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/31/why-i-went-frick-park-trail-running-in-snowfall-for-the-first-time-in-a-decade/&#34;&gt;winter running when I did not have a good alternative&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am currently evaluating suitable minimalist running shoes for winter, before winter arrives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I learned a big lesson a decade ago when I tried to solve physical problems by throwing medication and supplements at them, and eventually found out that my problems had to do with misusing my body with shoes that disabled me from running in an optimally healthy way. Since then, I have never resorted to medication or fancy technology as the first step in solving problems.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A new hike in Frick Park with Abby</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/08/04/a-new-hike-in-frick-park-with-abby/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 Aug 2013 17:00:55 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/08/04/a-new-hike-in-frick-park-with-abby/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s August and Abby and I have been upset that, unlike all the other years since we&amp;rsquo;ve been together, most of the year has already gone by without our having gone on a substantial hike together. This is a big deal because hiking is one of the things that &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/05/12/my-rachel-carson-trail-hike-for-the-year/&#34;&gt;first drew us together and that we most enjoy doing together&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reasons for this utterly unfortunate situation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Abby broke her foot in February, at the same time she started a new job, and this totally threw both our lives into chaos. Her full recovery was very slow, and she has still not regained her fitness, and is not in any shape to do any of the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/11/fascinating-bushwhacking-hike-at-pa-state-game-land-51-dunbar/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Hiking meetup hikes that we normally start doing in the spring and throughout the summer&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I got occupied with Pittsburgh Marathon training, then after the marathon, during a hike, came down with a skin rash that resulted in a lot of trouble for me despite multiple trips to the doctor and treatments, still not completely cleared up even today, and that resulted in my not only losing fitness but also being wary of going out on hikes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, we decided that the past is the past, and we should start doing some smaller-scale hiking on our own, just to enjoy being out together again. Today we simply chose to do a little exploratory (for me, anyway) hike of Frick Park. The hike was probably just over 4 miles long (including walking to the park from home and back), so it was quite short, but it was good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s what I discovered:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;showing-me-some-trails&#34;&gt;Showing me some trails&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically, Abby showed me some trails she had discovered when taking her own walk in Frick at some point. These were not the trails I usually run on, but narrower, craggier, steeper trails that clearly are used by mountain bikers (in fact, one came our way during the hike).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby leading the way:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/frick-hike-2013-08-04/abby.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Some views:

&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/frick-hike-2013-08-04/view.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;View from trail&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/frick-hike-2013-08-04/another-view.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Another view from trail&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Fungi:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/frick-hike-2013-08-04/fungi.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Fungi&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A little bridge:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/frick-hike-2013-08-04/bridge.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;A bridge&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We ended up in Fern Hollow, familiar territory:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/frick-hike-2013-08-04/fern-hollow.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;View from Fern Hollow&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Do you see the spider web?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/frick-hike-2013-08-04/spider-web.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Spider web&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We went up the Falls Ravine Trail from Fern Hollow, and then Abby showed me a small trail that leads back up to &amp;ldquo;civilization&amp;rdquo;, emerging behind a bench near the meadow across from the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pittsburghparks.org/frick-kids&#34;&gt;Blue Slide Playground&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This meadow is popular for sledding in the snowy winter, but right now it is popular for some kind of medieval play fighting:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/frick-hike-2013-08-04/fighting.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Play fighting in the meadow&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was very happy to be hiking with Abby again, even if &amp;ldquo;only&amp;rdquo; in our backyard park and for a short distance.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hiking in Boyce Park</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/06/15/hiking-in-boyce-park/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Jun 2013 21:32:24 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/06/15/hiking-in-boyce-park/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I did a tiny short hike together in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.alleghenycounty.us/parks/bpfac.aspx&#34;&gt;Boyce Park&lt;/a&gt;. We&amp;rsquo;ve barely done any hiking at all this year, because of her accident breaking a foot and my doing the Pittsburgh Marathon and then getting poison ivy on a hike I did with a friend last month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We thought we&amp;rsquo;d combine a hike with a trip to Monroeville to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.patelbros.com/&#34;&gt;Patel Brothers&lt;/a&gt; to buy Indian groceries and then eat at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.udipicafepittsburgh.com/&#34;&gt;Udipi Cafe&lt;/a&gt;, so we did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was good to be out together again. We miss hiking so much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;boyce-park&#34;&gt;Boyce Park&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/boyce-park-2013-06-15/sign.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/boyce-park-2013-06-15/ski.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/boyce-park-2013-06-15/playground.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My Rachel Carson Trail hike for the year (13.4 miles): and how this is about love and gratitude</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/05/12/my-rachel-carson-trail-hike-for-the-year/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 May 2013 22:24:40 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/05/12/my-rachel-carson-trail-hike-for-the-year/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today I did my first hike of the year (normally I would have done hiking already in the spring, but the combination of Abby&amp;rsquo;s broken foot and my Pittsburgh Marathon training this year resulted in no space for hiking until after the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/05/06/2013-pittsburgh-marathon-my-135th-race-was-my-worst-i-finished/&#34;&gt;marathon, which I did seven days ago&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first hike of the year just happened to turn out to be a grueling Rachel Carson Trail hike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, I reported on the two Rachel Carson Trail Challenge goal training hikes I did in &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/04/29/a-pretty-rachel-carson-trail-challenge-goal-training-hike/&#34;&gt;late April&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/06/03/a-totally-exhausting-rachel-carson-trail-challenge-goal-training-hike/&#34;&gt;early June&lt;/a&gt;. This year, I did the fourth of eight of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rachelcarsontrails.org/rct/challenge/rctc13/goaltraining&#34;&gt;year&amp;rsquo;s goal training hikes&lt;/a&gt; offered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sunday, May 12&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Leader: Donna Stolz 412-303-6102, Eileen Lessman 412-760-8863&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;13.4 miles&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Elevation change: 5055 ft&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;This hike begins in North Park and heads over to Emmerling Park, then up and over Rich Hill and Lefever Hill. We end at the Log Cabin Road checkpoint location. Meet at Log Cabin Road parking area. Take Route 28 to Exit #12. Turn right at the end of the ramp, then right at the stop sign onto Little Deer Creek Road (aka Russellton Road). Travel about 1.5 miles and turn right on Log Cabin Road. Park about 100 yards ahead on the right.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As of this year, I&amp;rsquo;ve decided to do &lt;em&gt;only one&lt;/em&gt; Rachel Carson Trail hike a year, so this was it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is my report on the hike, as well as my long-awaited explanation of why this trail means so much to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;weather&#34;&gt;Weather&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The conditions were good. It was kind of chilly and windy, probably 45-50 degrees throughout the hike. The sun came and went. There were only short periods of light drizzling rain, thankfully.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;footwear&#34;&gt;Footwear&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Vibram FiveFingers KSO Trek shoes I wore last year on the Rachel Carson Trail developed holes, as a result of which I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/08/28/five-reasons-we-just-stocked-up-on-vibram-fivefingers-kso-trek-shoes/&#34;&gt;stocked up on some new ones&lt;/a&gt;. The pair that I opened, I&amp;rsquo;ve worn only a couple of times, and I wore this pair today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;comparison-with-last-year-s-hike&#34;&gt;Comparison with last year&amp;rsquo;s hike&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/06/03/a-totally-exhausting-rachel-carson-trail-challenge-goal-training-hike/&#34;&gt;Last year on the 18.1 mile hike&lt;/a&gt;, I was stupid about my smartphone, and this year I was smarter. Today&amp;rsquo;s hike was a shorter 13.4, so I was sure the battery would last long enough, if I didn&amp;rsquo;t take photos with flash. And of course, I always have a phone charge in my car now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year&amp;rsquo;s hike went east to west and ended in North Park. This year&amp;rsquo;s hike went west to east and started in North Park. But being shorter, it did not end in Springdale. It is really a different hike when you go on the same trail but in a different direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might enjoy comparing the photos in different directions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;meeting-up-at-log-cabin-road&#34;&gt;Meeting up at Log Cabin Road&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;John and I arrived on time but not early, which meant that when we arrived, we saw a whole contingent of people already carpooling to head to North Park. We never saw those people again. Oops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, although we were ready to go with the hike leader, Donna, latecomers kept on showing up, and we were lenient and waited for them, before all the rest of us remaining headed to North Park.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Waiting for latecomers:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_08.03.20.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Because of Route 910 closures, some detours were necessary as Donna&amp;rsquo;s husband drove us to North Park.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;hike&#34;&gt;Hike&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In North Park about to begin:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_08.45.23.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_08.45.26.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;By the time we started, there were only a handful of us together as a group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was momentarily confused because I saw someone running in the &lt;em&gt;wrong direction&lt;/em&gt; on the trail and thought she might be one of us, and was worried. I tried to follow her to call out to her, but she disappeared quickly:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_08.45.34.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, Donna called out to me, and I rejoined the group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In North Park, a few sections of the trail are on the road, but then we go into the woods for real:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_08.51.43.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_08.51.49.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_08.52.15.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a whole bunch of stream crossings while in North Park. Some of them are easier than others. I should note that one of the harder ones had some fast water and basically ensured that your feet would get wet, because the logs were floating and not completely safe to step on. Some people jumped, but that&amp;rsquo;s not safe. Wearing KSO Trek shoes, since the temperature was around 50, I was fine just getting my feet wet by walking through the water.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_09.05.16.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_09.05.22.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_09.10.50.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_09.10.56.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Out of the woods onto the railroad tracks (note that hiking in the reverse direction is tricky because it&amp;rsquo;s not well-marked where to get off the railroad tracks into the woods; John and I got lost the last time we did the reverse hike and had to backtrack!).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_09.18.50.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_09.19.23.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a good amount of road walking on this section of the Rachel Carson Trail.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_09.27.01.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_09.27.14.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_09.29.46.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_09.53.40.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Crossing Route 8:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_10.03.01.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Finally, the power lines:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_10.04.28.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_10.05.59.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_10.22.47.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I am a bit sentimental about this section of trail in Hampton Park because Abby and I have done some cross country skiing here in winter, when she used to live up here before we got married and she moved to Pittsburgh.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_10.29.52.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Abby and I have also hung out here in the past watching birds.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_10.32.38.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_10.37.55.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_10.41.13.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_10.48.38.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_10.49.37.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_10.54.37.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here is where John and I got lost. I was distracted by this sight and made a turn toward it (the trail turned in the opposite direction) to check it out:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_10.55.25.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;OK, &amp;ldquo;acidic condensate collection tank&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_10.56.02.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Hmm, this didn&amp;rsquo;t look familiar.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_10.57.12.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_11.05.31.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;John and I turned back. We lost about ten minutes.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_11.06.42.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_11.07.38.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_11.15.12.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_11.18.16.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;No animals out and about today!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_11.41.38.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_11.43.09.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Funny how this happens to me once or twice each hike:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_12.01.43.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What the heck is this going on?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_12.07.33.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Uphill.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_12.07.53.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_12.11.35.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_12.19.47.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Finally at Emmerling Park, about 3 hours and 45 minutes into the hike.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_12.28.15.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I hung out at Emmerling Park for about ten or fifteen minutes, using the restroom and then playing on the swing relieving my aching feet while waiting for John and the others to catch up and also use the restroom. The truth is, I was ready to stop hiking already, feeling tired. I was also sore because of two falls I had sustained earlier in the hike. One of the falls involved my tripping on my right foot, causing me to land hard on my left, reinjuring my left knee that I had hurt before the marathon in a fall down the stairs. My left knee was causing me serious pain again now in the hike. I also fell on a steep downhill earlier, landing directly on my butt and on the palm of my left hand, which reinjured my left elbow. Finally, my right Achilles was killing me, because I had not adjusted the strap of my shoe properly; I had readjusted it during the hike, but the damage was already done. I was quite ready to stop hiking, but there were still two hours to go! Oops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Red flower:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_12.49.45.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_12.49.54.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And now we got to sections of the trail that are abused by ATVs and rutted and muddy. (We ended up encountering someone on an ATV, in fact.)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_13.02.18.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Standing water:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_13.05.17.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_13.14.42.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_13.22.04.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_13.24.59.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No fun at all hiking through these muddy ruts:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_13.28.24.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Finally back into open space:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_13.29.43.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Looking back down the big hill:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_13.33.09.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s John and the rest down at the bottom:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_13.34.50.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We keep on going up:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_13.34.55.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_13.38.45.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Finally at the top, looking back:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_13.39.36.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_13.49.12.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_13.51.14.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_13.58.01.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s going on here?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_14.05.03.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_14.05.28.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_14.09.45.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_14.15.19.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_14.20.47.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_14.21.07.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Finally back to the parking lot!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_14.25.11.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;after&#34;&gt;After&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We hiked something like 5 hours and 45 minutes. It felt really long to us, as our first hike of the year. My feet were killing me. I was happy to take my shoes off and drive us back home barefoot!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, my phone still barely had battery power left when we finished. I&amp;rsquo;m not sure it would have lasted another hour. This is useful to know. Of course, I immediately plugged it into my car charger! I should get an extra battery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-hike-this-trail-at-all&#34;&gt;Why hike this trail at all?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby is confused why I like occasionally (once or twice a year) hiking on the Rachel Carson Trail, even though much of the time I find it tiring and weird. I&amp;rsquo;ve never fully explained this in words, so here, finally, is my explanation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have many sentimental reasons to hike this trail. One is that eight years ago, in late May of 2005, when a local running friend said he was doing the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rachelcarsontrails.org/rct/challenge/rctc05&#34;&gt;Rachel Carson Trail Challenge&lt;/a&gt;, I had taken an entire half year off from running was feeling sad and lonely. I looked up the Challenge online, and happened to find that &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rachelcarsontrails.org/rct/challenge/rctc05/training&#34;&gt;training hikes led by Barb Peterson&lt;/a&gt; were being offered in just a few days, and although I had no intention whatsoever to do the Challenge, I thought the training hikes would be a fun way to do and see something different. After doing the third of four, I was so excited by the novelty that I ended up signing up for the Challenge!! With only three weeks left, there was not much training I could do for it, but I figured that if I just took it slowly, I should be able to finish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2005 Challenge was an ordeal for me to finish, but I did, and the side effect was that I fell in love with hiking in general. I met people through doing the Challenge, and in 2006 I roped John into joining me on some longer training hikes, where we met more people, and some of them I began hiking with outside the context of the Challenge, in places like the Laurel Highlands. This was before the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/pittsburghhikers/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Hiking Meetup&lt;/a&gt; was formed in May 2007 and made it much easier to find people to hike with. So the 2005 Challenge had the side effect of getting me into making hiking a regular part of my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, as I was training for the 2007 Challenge, that was the time when I had just met Abby and was dancing with her, but we were not dating yet. When we were chatting at a salsa dance, I learned that she liked to hike and was intrigued. I invited her to join me and John for an April 29 Rachel Carson Trail Challenge training hike that happened to be passing through Hampton (as today&amp;rsquo;s hike did), and she said she would join us for part of it. A comic series of events then took place, in which John and I arrived at Hampton earlier than she had expected, so she had not yet made it to Hampton to meet up with us. When I paused to call her, and she said she would meet us in the trail, John and I got confused and lost because of miscommunication. I kept having to call her again and again until we finally found her, and she set us straight back onto the trail and hiked with us for a bit before turning back. That was my first interaction with Abby outside of dancing; I got to see how she gracefully handled my clumsy mistakes during this outing and how helpful she was. It was a month after that when we finally started dating. Eventually, I proposed right after a hike led by one of the guys I originally first met through a Rachel Carson Trail Challenge training hike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I associate the Rachel Carson Trail not only with falling in love with hiking, and with meeting lots of interesting people I still hike with all these years later, but also I am reminded of how I fell in love with Abby and how hiking is a big part of what we have done and do. It is slightly ironic, of course, that she does not enjoy doing most sections of the Rachel Carson Trail, so in recent years I have been hiking it either alone or with John. And that is why I try to limit how often I hike on the trail; I&amp;rsquo;ve decided now to do it only once a year, so that I spend less time on hiking that Abby doesn&amp;rsquo;t do with me, in order to share more hiking with her. But I would like to spend good time on the trail once a year from now on to remember what it means to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, despite the strange hybrid nature of the trail, I believe in its existence and maintenance. It is a reminder that even in urban/suburban environments, there is still an underlying primitive nature that we can enjoy. The volunteers of the Rachel Carson Trails Conservancy work hard to keep this unusual resource open to the public.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/11/fascinating-bushwhacking-hike-at-pa-state-game-land-51-dunbar/&#34;&gt;Example from March 2012 of the kind of hike that Abby and I have enjoyed doing.&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Rachel Carson Trail will always have a special place in my heart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to Donna for keeping us company for most of the hike as trail sweep, and her husband for driving us to the start!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An unexpected afternoon tour: 9 miles of running, 1 Cathedral of Learning stair climb, 2 chess tournaments</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/02/02/an-unexpected-afternoon-tour-9-miles-of-running/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Feb 2013 17:41:31 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/02/02/an-unexpected-afternoon-tour-9-miles-of-running/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I had an amusing, completely impromptu Saturday afternoon tour in which I ran nine miles (including a couple of miles with a friend I&amp;rsquo;ve never actually seen running before or run with before), did one repetition of the Cathedral of Learning stair climb, and visited two different chess tournaments in Pittsburgh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As of Friday evening, I had only planned to go for a run on Saturday. Here&amp;rsquo;s how I ended up on my unexpected tour instead.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/cathedral-of-learning-full.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Cathedral of Learning&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;i-did-not-run-in-the-morning&#34;&gt;I did not run in the morning&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier in the week, since I had just &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/30/why-and-how-i-am-going-to-run-the-2013-pittsburgh-marathon/&#34;&gt;signed up for the 2013 Pittsburgh Marathon&lt;/a&gt;, I had considered to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.steelcityrrc.org/scrrcevents?eventId=582142&amp;amp;EventViewMode=2&amp;amp;CalendarViewType=1&amp;amp;SelectedDate=2/16/2013&#34;&gt;early Saturday morning training run&lt;/a&gt; of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.steelcityrrc.org/&#34;&gt;Steel City Road Runners&lt;/a&gt;, but by yesterday, had felt that I didn&amp;rsquo;t want to get up early on Saturday, and also it was going to be very cold, possible as low as 10 degrees F, and I felt more comfortable running near 20 degrees F as well as close to home so that I could bail out during my own long run and get back home and warm if needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have not run more than 5 miles continuously in a while. I anticipated running at least 7 miles out in the cold, depending on how I felt. I was certain that I would not run as long as 12 miles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By afternoon, it was over 20 degrees F, so I felt fairly comfortable going out for an extended run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;chess-tournament-1-a-delayed-pittsburgh-chess-club-championship-round-3-game&#34;&gt;Chess tournament 1: a delayed Pittsburgh Chess Club Championship round 3 game&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OK, so I was exaggerating: I did not visit two complete chess tournaments on my tour. I did visit the final unplayed game of round 3 in the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/02/04/pittsburgh-chess-club-championship-2013-round-3-attack-defense-and-sacrifices/&#34;&gt;current Pittsburgh Chess Club Championship&lt;/a&gt; that is played Tuesday nights. The game was between Kurt Wallnau and Peter Jansen, and had been postponed because Kurt couldn&amp;rsquo;t make it on Tuesday. This game was important because likely the winner would be my opponent for round 4 on Tuesday, because of my current perfect score of three wins in the first three rounds so far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that shortly before I was about to go for a run in the afternoon, I got word from Kurt that he was about to play his rescheduled game with Peter at the Pittsburgh Chess Club. So I thought I would run there from home (just a bit over a mile away) to stop by and take a look before continuing on with my run.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/wallnau-jansen.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Wallnau-Jansen from round 3&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When I arrived, the game had barely begun, so I just immediately went back out to continue running.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;chess-tournament-2-2013-pa-state-game-75-championship-http-www-pitt-edu-schach-chesspa-wpastate-htm&#34;&gt;Chess tournament 2: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pitt.edu/~schach/ChessPA/wpastate.htm&#34;&gt;2013 PA State Game/75 Championship&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Originally I had planned to maybe run in Homewood Cemetery for a bit, but I suddenly changed my mind after running for a while and decided to check out the tournament in progress at the William Pitt Union, the 2013 PA State Game/75 Championship. So I ran into Oakland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But as I approached, staring me in the face was the Cathedral of Learning.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/cathedral-of-learning-on-run.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Cathedral of Learning&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;cathedral-of-learning-stair-climb&#34;&gt;Cathedral of Learning stair climb&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suddenly I decided that I would do something I had never done before, which was to do the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/31/doing-an-unexpected-workout/&#34;&gt;Cathedral of Learning stair climb&lt;/a&gt; right after having run a couple of miles. An interesting circuit!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I did one repetition of the 36 floors. I experimented with just continuing to run up the stairs, but quickly found that this was completely unsustainable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As another experiment, I did not just sit down and rest after finishing the stair climb. I stayed on my feet and immediately got on the elevator back down and out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went across the street to the chess tournament in progress. The games in the round were mostly done, so there wasn&amp;rsquo;t that much to see:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/2013-pa-state-game-75.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;2013 PA State Game/75 Championship&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;run-with-jason&#34;&gt;Run with Jason&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I ran back to the Pittsburgh Chess Club in Squirrel Hill to see what was going on there. Kurt and Peter had reached a very strange and unclear position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was planning to go back out to run some more before coming back to the club again when I spotted Jason, a chess club regular whom I have known since winter 2005 when he was one of the first people I met, in addition to &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/18/round-6-of-pittsburgh-chess-club-tournament-playing-pragmatically/&#34;&gt;Jeff&lt;/a&gt;, during my first visits to the Pittsburgh Chess Club. (He also happens to have started playing in chess tournaments again for the first time in several years!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I joked to him, &amp;ldquo;How come you weren&amp;rsquo;t out running with me?&amp;rdquo; and he said that actually, he was about to go out running again, having run &amp;ldquo;a couple of hours&amp;rdquo; &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/27/how-to-gut-out-the-tough-workout/&#34;&gt;in Frick Park&lt;/a&gt; in the morning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m still amazed that Jason so quickly became an &lt;a href=&#34;http://ultrasignup.com/results_participant.aspx?fname=Jason&amp;amp;lname=Maruccio&amp;amp;age=36&#34;&gt;ultrarunner&lt;/a&gt;. A couple of years ago we&amp;rsquo;d gone on some hikes together, and he said he was not a runner. After I hiked the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rachelcarsontrails.org/rct/challenge&#34;&gt;Rachel Carson Trail Challenge&lt;/a&gt; three years in a row, he got excited about signing up for the first time. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rachelcarsontrails.org/rct/challenge/rctc08/volunteers&#34;&gt;Abby and I volunteered&lt;/a&gt; at an aid station for the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rachelcarsontrails.org/rct/challenge/rctc08&#34;&gt;2008 Rachel Carson Trail Challenge&lt;/a&gt;, and greeted Jason as he came through our aid station. Little did I know that he would continue doing not only the Rachel Carson Trail Challenge again and again, but other endurance hikes as well. Eventually, he decided to start running, and he never looked back, and became a full-blown ultrarunner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So Jason went out for a run on the roads in Schenley Park for a couple of miles. It was out first ever run together, actually, and the first time I had ever seen him running. (We haven&amp;rsquo;t hiked together in years.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We came back to the chess club, and I saw that the Wallnau-Jansen game was still in a very strange, complex state, and I decided it was time to go home for the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;back-home&#34;&gt;Back home&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On my way back home, I started feeling really cold and hungry and tired and sore (despite having eaten a banana and some nuts an hour earlier that I had brought with me). The temperature was still around 25F, not terribly cold, but clearly I had taxed my body with my adventures. My toes were blistering and cramping up because of my footwear (I still have to really solve the problem of what shoes to wear for winter running).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was grateful to get home, eat and stretch, shower, and warm back up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did some calculations and I ran a total of about 9 miles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes it&amp;rsquo;s fun to just go and have unplanned adventures.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Five reasons we just stocked up on Vibram FiveFingers KSO Trek shoes</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/08/28/five-reasons-we-just-stocked-up-on-vibram-fivefingers-kso-trek-shoes/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Aug 2012 19:47:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/08/28/five-reasons-we-just-stocked-up-on-vibram-fivefingers-kso-trek-shoes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/85802484@N06/7858001266&#34; title=&#34;&amp;quot;Run Around the Square&amp;quot;, Regent Square by sherpes39, on Flickr&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm8.staticflickr.com/7253/7858001266_58020e37f8.jpg&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; height=&#34;375&#34; alt=&#34;&amp;quot;Run Around the Square&amp;quot;, Regent Square&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I just stocked up on Vibram FiveFingers KSO Trek shoes: we got &lt;em&gt;two&lt;/em&gt; brand new pairs for me and &lt;em&gt;two&lt;/em&gt; for her as well. Why the extravagant purchases? Here are five reasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;reason-1-trail-running&#34;&gt;Reason 1: trail running&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In August 2010, I bought my first pair of KSO Trek shoes, primarily for the purpose of trail running, since I was sick and tired of the knee and shin and blistering problems I seemed to have whenever trail running extensively in any regular shoes, and I wanted more durability and protection against rocks than I got from running in less built-up racing flats meant for road running.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, I had bought the KSO shoes earlier, but they just weren&amp;rsquo;t, for me, suitable for much trail running, because of blistering issues and lack of protection (later, as I got used to more minimalist running, the protection no longer became an issue, but the blistering remained, so the last time I did trail running in the KSO shoes as a test was in June for &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/06/06/i-celebrated-national-running-day-in-schenley-park-remembering-how-i-began-to-run-13-year-ago/&#34;&gt;National Running Day&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a little bit of breaking in, during which I had a few blisters, &lt;em&gt;I never got blistered again, for two years and counting&lt;/em&gt;. The kangaroo leather is very nice and quickly seems to conform to your feet and becomes smooth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I have never run in the trails with my old regular monotoed running shoes again.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I have never experienced knee or shin problems again when trail running.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;reason-2-hiking&#34;&gt;Reason 2: hiking&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At first, I resisted the idea of wearing the KSO Trek hiking, because my typical hike involves terrain considerably rougher than my local trail runs, and goes on for more hours. But a year ago, in August 2011, following the lead of Abby, who started hiking in her Trek Sport shoes (which are similar to the KSO Trek in protection but are not made of kangaroo leather), I finally shed my &amp;ldquo;trail running&amp;rdquo; shoes that I had been hiking in, reluctantly, for several years (even though I always ended up with some knee/shin/calf/ankle/foot pain/soreness and some blistering on long hikes).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;starting-out-with-6-miles&#34;&gt;Starting out with 6 miles&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first KSO Trek hiking experience was on a hike that was only 6 miles long. But that experience was a revelation. I had &lt;em&gt;no problems&lt;/em&gt; at all during the hike. I just had some tightness in my right shin after that hike, undoubtedly due to imperfect form. But no blistering, and no lasting foot soreness. As a result, &lt;em&gt;I have never hiked again in regular monotoed shoes, but only in KSO Trek shoes&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;moving-up-to-20-miles&#34;&gt;Moving up to 20 miles&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/kso-trek/rachel-carson-trail.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;On the Rachel Carson Trail&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This May, I decided I wanted to really put the KSO Trek to the test. I wore the shoes on my most extreme hike of this year, a 20-mile training hike on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://rachelcarsontrails.org/rct&#34;&gt;Rachel Carson Trail&lt;/a&gt;. I finished the hike with no blisters whatsoever, no knee pain. Yes, my feet were sore as heck after all the banging on rocks and tree roots and down the hills, but foot soreness always happened anyway whenever I did a 20-mile hike on the Rachel Carson Trail in any footwear. The interesting thing is that I recovered from this foot soreness extremely quickly, much more quickly than I ever recovered from foot soreness wearing more padded shoes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, I cannot answer the fascinating question of whether I could do the 35-mile &lt;a href=&#34;http://rachelcarsontrails.org/rct/challenge&#34;&gt;Rachel Carson Trail Challenge&lt;/a&gt; in KSO Trek shoes. I have completed the Challenge three times, each time with a different pair of regular monotoed trail running shoes, and each time with leg and foot issues (including severe blisters). The reason I cannot answer the question is that my feet were noticeably &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; sore after 20 miles on the trail in KSO Trek than they ever were in the regular shoes. There might be a problem with scalability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;injinji-socks&#34;&gt;Injinji socks&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, earlier, in March, I had gone on a really tough hilly, bushwhacking exploratory hike that was about 10 miles long, and worn Injinji toe socks with my KSO Trek shoes. The socks provided additional protection that completely removed foot soreness. Unfortunately, I simply did not enjoy the extra bulk around my toes, and therefore have chosen not to wear socks again except when necessary in cold weather. But it is certainly conceivable that with socks, 35 miles on the Rachel Carson might be doable with KSO Trek shoes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;a-recent-hike&#34;&gt;A recent hike&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I enjoyed &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.trails.com/tcatalog_trail.aspx?trailid=HGS212-001&#34;&gt;Atalaya Mountain&lt;/a&gt; in Santa Fe this month when we were in New Mexico. She wore her Trek Sport, I wore my KSO Trek.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/kso-trek/atalaya-abby.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby with Trek Sport&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/kso-trek/atalaya-franklin.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin with KSO Trek&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;reason-3-paddling&#34;&gt;Reason 3: paddling&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point, Abby and I decided to start wearing Vibram FiveFingers shoes kayaking. I started off wearing the KSO, but then realized that wearing the KSO Trek offered a lot of advantages with no down side. Being thicker and leather, they protected better against being under the sun. The extra protection when stepping out into the water and onto rocky shores was also welcome.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rio-grande-paddling.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Kayaking down the Rio Grande&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(Down the Rio Grande in New Mexico, with view of Sandia Crest.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;no-shoe-funk&#34;&gt;No shoe funk&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, there is the &lt;a href=&#34;http://birthdayshoes.com/the-definitive-guide-to-cleaning-vibram-five-fingers-a-k-a-how-to-get-the-smell-out-of-your-vibrams&#34;&gt;infamous problem that the synthetic Vibram shoes tend to end up stinking&lt;/a&gt; after getting wet, even after washing! Abby and I found no perfect solution to this problem. It turns out that the leather shoes don&amp;rsquo;t suffer from this problem &lt;em&gt;at all&lt;/em&gt;. All I have to do is rinse the shoes thoroughly (without even any soap or detergent), air dry them, and then they are just fine. Believe it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;reason-4-holes-in-my-toes-after-two-years-and-over-a-thousand-miles&#34;&gt;Reason 4: holes in my toes after two years and over a thousand miles&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;discovering-holes-on-vulcan&#34;&gt;Discovering holes on Vulcan&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t know when holes started forming in my KSO Trek shoes from 2010, because I did not have a habit of checking regularly for holes. I only know that I started feeling the ground with my toes only after a particular outing during which I spent over an hour running the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nps.gov/petr/planyourvisit/volcanoes.htm&#34;&gt;three Petroglyph volcanoes&lt;/a&gt; near Albuquerque this month.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/kso-trek/petroglyph-volcanoes.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Panorama of Petroglyph volcanoes&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/kso-trek/franklin-petroglyph-volcanoes.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin getting ready to run the volcanoes&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I was fairly high up on Vulcan and descending when I first noticed the sensations of volcanic rock rubbing on my bare toe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Here&amp;rsquo;s Abby hiking toward Vulcan after I had already run down and was headed the other way.)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/kso-trek/abby-hiking-to-vulcan.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby hiking to Vulcan&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;examining-the-holes&#34;&gt;Examining the holes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are the holes, which occurred at the sides of the second toes of both my feet:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/kso-trek/hole-in-left.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Hole in left shoe&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/kso-trek/hole-in-right.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Hole in right shoe&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After Abby and I ordered and received our new shoes (Abby decided to finally also go for KSO Treks, after seeing how much I loved them in the past two years), I took some photos to illustrate the wear and tear:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/kso-trek/old-and-new.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As you can see, the old shoes are pretty worn down:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/kso-trek/old-new-bottom.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/kso-trek/old-new-side.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not going to retire the old shoes yet, of course. I kind of like that they have, through being worn down, become more minimalist; feeling a little bit of dirt touch my toes once in a while is no problem at all (especially given my experiments with entirely barefoot running). I expect to continue to wear the old shoes for years to come; I did just start wearing a new pair (which &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/08/25/my-eighth-time-doing-run-around-the-square-5k/&#34;&gt;I just ran a race in and Abby also&lt;/a&gt;, but will come up with a rotation system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;reason-5-vibram-is-discontinuing-the-kso-trek-shoes-and-they-are-on-sale&#34;&gt;Reason 5: Vibram is discontinuing the KSO Trek shoes and they are on sale!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, the unbelievable news: Vibram is discontinuing the KSO Trek, my favorite shoe!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But a sale is going on right now: we picked up four pairs at a clearance price, and so can you &lt;a href=&#34;http://birthdayshoes.com/labor-day-minimalist-barefoot-sales&#34;&gt;before they disappear for good&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am very sad that Vibram is discontinuing the shoe that I have happily put well over a thousand miles on trail running, hiking, and paddling. I hope that by stocking up, I will be able to enjoy the KSO Trek for several years.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>