<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Recorder on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/recorder/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Recorder on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/recorder/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Revisiting Bach&#39;s Air on G String, from a singing and dancing viewpoint</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/06/10/revisiting-bachs-air-on-g-string-from-a-singing-and-dancing-viewpoint/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jun 2015 23:46:26 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/06/10/revisiting-bachs-air-on-g-string-from-a-singing-and-dancing-viewpoint/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Three years ago, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/14/passion-of-bachs-air-on-the-g-string-three-different-interpretations/&#34;&gt;I wrote a post comparing three very different
performance styles&lt;/a&gt;
for Johann Sebastian Bach&amp;rsquo;s famous music,
&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Air_on_the_G_String&#34;&gt;Air on G String&lt;/a&gt;
and indicating which I preferred.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have received an unexpected number comments over the years, and
thought it was time to write an update of my thoughts in response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Primarily, I am responding to those who (correctly) criticized the
unfortunately chosen exemplar of the style that I preferred. I tried
to find better versions that might illustrate my perceptions. I also
integrated some thoughts based on how I perceive music as a singer and
as a dancer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;better-than-the-rushed-croatian-baroque-ensemble-s-performance&#34;&gt;Better than the rushed Croatian Baroque Ensemble&amp;rsquo;s performance?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I agreed quickly with the first commenters that the Croatian
ensemble&amp;rsquo;s performance was too perfunctory, even downright brutal and
unpleasant in various ways. I wish I had
chosen a better example of what I actually &lt;em&gt;like&lt;/em&gt; rather than &lt;em&gt;prefer
to the other two versions&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I searched YouTube for period-style performances that are
closer to what I envision than either the Croatian ensemble&amp;rsquo;s or
Koopman&amp;rsquo;s. It proved impossible for me to find a perfect performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-period-performance-i-like-more-christopher-hogwood&#34;&gt;A period performance I like more: Christopher Hogwood&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like this version by the late &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christopher_Hogwood&#34;&gt;Christopher Hogwood&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s Academy of
Ancient Music:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/nrtdhH8_47k&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a sweetness and &lt;em&gt;bouncy lightness&lt;/em&gt; to this version that I
like, but it is also somewhat anemic. Personally, I would play up more
contrast and fullness of sound and passion, but the overall tempo and
breathing to this version seems right to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;voices-of-music-richer-sound&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Voices of Music&amp;rdquo;: richer sound&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Voices of Music&amp;rdquo; here in a good performance:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/pzlw6fUux4o&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like the richness of sound in this performance. I miss the lighter,
more bouncy feeling that Hogwood brought out though. This performance
is a bit too legato for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;i-care-about-singing&#34;&gt;I care about singing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I approach this music from the viewpoint of singing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bouncy lightness is very important to me, along with the rhythmic
characterization. I feel this music as a song (it is an &amp;ldquo;air&amp;rdquo;, after
all), and I cannot help singing along when I hear it. Therefore, when
it&amp;rsquo;s taken too slow for me to sing and make it to natural breathing
points in phrases, that considerably lessens my pleasure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;yehudi-menuhin-solo-violin&#34;&gt;Yehudi Menuhin, solo violin&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s an interesting old black and white video of a performance by a young Yehudi Menuhin on violin with
accompaniment. It&amp;rsquo;s not a period performance, but moves along at a
decent &amp;ldquo;singing&amp;rdquo; tempo, as befits violin, that singing instrument.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34;
src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/08bDiKXW0gg&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;
allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I confess that I rather like this performance for its virtues,
although it distorts Bach&amp;rsquo;s music by so emphasizing just the musical
line, at the expense of the balance of the other voices and the
essential character of the dissonances among the voices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;more-menuhin-but-as-conductor&#34;&gt;More Menuhin, but as conductor&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s Yehudi Menuhin not as violin soloist but as conductor of the
Bath Festival Orchestra in 1960. Again, not a period performance, but
he takes the music briskly, and has the violins create sufficient
phrase delineations that I feel the music alertly as though it sings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s direct and clear, maybe not the most subtle and warm,
but I like it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/kaBAE4stNIo&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;dancing-is-possible-too&#34;&gt;Dancing is possible too&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also like to dance to expressive music. A pioneer of modern dance,
Doris Humphrey, famously choreographed a dance to a slowish
performance of this music:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/NjwJyaSIRqY&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not how I would dance to it, because I feel the music
differently. Surprisingly, I could find few examples on YouTube of
dancing to this music. I may consider choreographing a dance myself as
a project to express my own personal vision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing I would like to mention is that I feel that the &lt;em&gt;walking bass&lt;/em&gt;
is very important in this music and gives it the impetus. When played
too slow, the walking bass no longer feels like it&amp;rsquo;s walking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel this music in my legs, not just in my lungs. Yes, I have
actually hummed it to myself while walking in time to the bass
leisurely in the local park. There is a limit to how &amp;ldquo;leisurely&amp;rdquo; I can
walk without feeling frustrated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;ice-dancing&#34;&gt;Ice dancing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found this somewhat frenetic but nevertheless beautiful ice dancing
performance from the 1992 World Figure Skating Championships:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/1JjbwtM_E3g&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;recorder-quartet&#34;&gt;Recorder quartet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A final performance to enjoy: the Japanese &amp;ldquo;Sekishi Recorder Quartet&amp;rdquo;
playing their hearts out in 2009. I think it&amp;rsquo;s lovely: impeccable
phrasing, transparency,
and rich ensemble balance and tone. (As a twist, the melody line performer adds
his own ornamentations.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/pRRRK0UClNs&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was inspired by the accumulated comments on my previous post on
Bach&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Air on G String&amp;rdquo; that I decided to flesh out my thoughts by
using more example performances, as well as relate the orchestral
music to singing and dancing. I hope you have enjoyed these
explorations. There is no single &amp;ldquo;right&amp;rdquo; way to experience music, but
I wanted to share how I experience it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;ve read my previous post, does this one help clarify where
  I&amp;rsquo;m coming from with my musical values? Do you dance
  or sing? Does this affect how you perceive this piece of music and
  like to perform it or hear it performed?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pittsburgh Recorder Society: discovering the beauty of Alonso Lobo</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/05/18/pittsburgh-recorder-society-discovering-the-beauty-of-alonso-lobo/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 May 2014 17:48:23 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/05/18/pittsburgh-recorder-society-discovering-the-beauty-of-alonso-lobo/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We had another great turnout for the monthly meeting of the Pittsburgh Recorder Society. We got another new member, Joanna. I counted fifteen of us, total.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-recorder-society-2014-05-18/group.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Today, the highlight for me was discovering some music I don&amp;rsquo;t remember encountering before, by &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alonso_Lobo&#34;&gt;Alonso Lobo&lt;/a&gt;, who lived roughly 1555-1617. Fred passed out parts for his &amp;ldquo;Versa est in luctum&amp;rdquo;, a sacred motet for voice (which we are playing as a recorder ensemble instead).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This music is beautiful and new to me, and Fred provided instructive interpretive guidance I will discuss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d never heard of Lobo before (outside of recorder playing, I simply have very little knowledge of early pre-Baroque music) and had to look up Lobo after the meeting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;versa-est-in-luctum-by-alonso-lobo&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Versa est in luctum&amp;rdquo; by Alonso Lobo&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is passionate funeral music, written for a Spanish king&amp;rsquo;s funeral. I found an interesting &lt;a href=&#34;http://luiscfhenriques.com/alonso-lobos-versa-est-in-luctum/&#34;&gt;musicologist&amp;rsquo;s blog post about the work&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;English translation printed on our recorder arrangement parts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
My harp is turned to mourning and my music into the voice of those that weep.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fred put me on the alto 1 part. After some work on the piece, he called for those of us on alto 1 (there was at least one other person, but possibly no more, of us fifteen) to play louder, with more emotion, to really ring out. I had held back in part because I was afraid of going sharp if I blowed harder, but also in part because for other music we&amp;rsquo;ve been playing, I&amp;rsquo;ve been focusing on blending in playing tenor parts. I sometimes somehow get into a rut and &amp;ldquo;forget&amp;rdquo; the importance or impact of carrying the top line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fred was actually singing along quite expressively as he conducted us. It&amp;rsquo;s inspirational to me that we have a leader who so believes in the music he has us play, and seeks to help us bring out its essence. The interesting thing about this piece is that there are phrases of longer notes as well as those that are more agitated, with faster movement. So there is a lot of beautiful interplay and contrast among the voices as well as within their own span throughout the piece. Fred advised on providing separation at the end of phrases so that they can be heard better in contrast against other voices as they enter and leave in different places.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, the other first alto(s) and I did play more confidently and louder, as did the rest of the ensemble, and when we did that, it was an amazing feeling, the sense of filling the air and resonating. I live for experiences like this! Let&amp;rsquo;s keep it up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;a-performance-for-choir-you-should-check-out&#34;&gt;A performance for choir you should check out&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For reference, here is a fine performance by the Gabrieli Consort I discovered:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/yZe16Mpsmg8&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;group-recording-from-before&#34;&gt;Group recording from before&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fred brought in a little boombox so we could hear the recording he had made earlier of us playing &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/03/16/pittsburgh-recorder-society-something-new-recently-recording-our-practice-sessions/&#34;&gt;two months ago&lt;/a&gt;. We didn&amp;rsquo;t sound terrible, actually!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-recorder-society-2014-05-18/recording.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;snacks&#34;&gt;Snacks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ate three cookies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-recorder-society-2014-05-18/cookie1.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-recorder-society-2014-05-18/cookie2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-recorder-society-2014-05-18/cookie3.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In retrospect, I should not have eaten three cookies. Maybe two, or maybe one. I know, I made this observation &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/04/27/pittsburgh-recorder-society-palestrina-gombert-and-dolly-parton-cookies/&#34;&gt;last month&lt;/a&gt;. This time, I&amp;rsquo;m serious. Next meeting, I will eat no more than &lt;em&gt;two&lt;/em&gt; cookies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed being shown yet another beautiful piece of music and getting the opportunity to play it with others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How often do you discover beautiful music you have never heard before, through being given it to play? Is this experience different than just hearing it without playing it?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pittsburgh Recorder Society: Palestrina, Gombert, and Dolly Parton cookies</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/04/27/pittsburgh-recorder-society-palestrina-gombert-and-dolly-parton-cookies/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Apr 2014 17:47:27 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/04/27/pittsburgh-recorder-society-palestrina-gombert-and-dolly-parton-cookies/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We had a great turnout again for the monthly meeting of the Pittsburgh Recorder Society. We even got an enthusiastic new member, Andriy. There were around fifteen of us, total; we really filled the room!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our director Fred was inspirational again, encouraging and helping us to continue to refine our sound, our unity, our expression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every month, attending the Sunday recorder meeting is truly one of the things I look forward to most in life! Sometimes I feel emotionally naked and a bit anxious in our meetings, but I know that this is a safe place to grow and to contribute. Today was one of those days in which I really felt challenged to do my very best to make music together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;kyrie-of-the-missa-papae-marcelli-by-palestrina-revisited&#34;&gt;Kyrie of the &amp;ldquo;Missa Papae Marcelli&amp;rdquo; by Palestrina, revisited&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/16/excited-by-the-new-season-of-the-pittsburgh-recorder-society/&#34;&gt;Well over a year ago&lt;/a&gt;, we had begun work on a recorder ensemble arrangement of Palestrina&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Kyrie de la &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Missa_Papae_Marcelli&#34;&gt;Missa Papae Marcelli&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;, but had actually not picked up much on that, so I was delighted that Fred decided (especially now that we have more members) to start on this piece again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got a tenor 2 part and was happy to do my best to produce a rich inner voice blending it into the ensemble&amp;rsquo;s tapestry of sound. Fred emphasized that the original music did not have bar lines, and that each &amp;ldquo;Kyrie&amp;rdquo; phrase can and does begin on any beat of a &amp;ldquo;measure&amp;rdquo;, so we should focus on keeping the flow going. Of course, this being originally vocal music, I tried to &amp;ldquo;sing&amp;rdquo; on recorder, paying attention to entrances and breath control (I am still unable to last an entire breath in some of these phrases).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;mille-regres-by-nicolas-gombert-http-en-wikipedia-org-wiki-nicolas-gombert&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Mille Regres&amp;rdquo; by &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nicolas_Gombert&#34;&gt;Nicolas Gombert&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also started work on a recorder arrangement of &amp;ldquo;Mille Regres&amp;rdquo; by Nicolas Gombert, originally for voice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fred put me on the alto part and after we started playing, I realized I was the only one on the part, and felt anxious! There was nowhere to hide. It&amp;rsquo;s very different from playing on a tenor or bass part with a bunch of other people, or even when playing a part with just one other person. On the one hand, there is much more freedom, because when a voice is doubled, you have to work with someone to sound like one. Of course, you always have to blend with the rest of the ensemble, regardless, but when you&amp;rsquo;re alone, you realize that you do not have backup for your voice, that you are it. Strong entrances, making the high notes clear and rich, are totally up to you now. It&amp;rsquo;s a great responsibility and opportunity, and I felt myself focusing as deep as I could into every element of the music. After today&amp;rsquo;s first cut, I hope to continue to improve on bringing my part fully to life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a performance of the original music for voice:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/J_2kRgCxeHk&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;mille-regretz-by-josquin-des-prez&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Mille Regretz&amp;rdquo; by Josquin des Prez&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that elements of this music sounded familiar to me, because in fact it is based on the French chanson &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mille_Regretz&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Mille Regretz&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Josquin_des_Prez&#34;&gt;Josquin des Prez&lt;/a&gt;, which I was familiar with because in last year&amp;rsquo;s Mideast early music workshop, I took a voice class in which we performed it. I really enjoyed singing it (as tenor; sorry, I don&amp;rsquo;t know if anyone has a video of our performance at the final student concert).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a nice performance of &amp;ldquo;Mille Regretz&amp;rdquo; with just one singer per part:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/S0TNPoDYHFY&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;another-alto-solo&#34;&gt;Another alto solo&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was another piece we started (but there were not enough scores, so I had to share with Kristel; I need to ask for a copy to be emailed to me, but for now I don&amp;rsquo;t remember the name or composer) in which Fred again put me on a solo part, which was originally marked &amp;ldquo;soprano&amp;rdquo; but after a run through, he told me to read it on alto up an octave.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This assignment made me even more anxious because I actually start out with a full statement of the melody without any accompaniment, before everyone else starts to come in. I&amp;rsquo;m not used to be put on the spot like this. But again, it&amp;rsquo;s a great opportunity to really work on refining my technique and expression, and being aware that I am setting the stage for the whole piece to succeed. Also, it&amp;rsquo;s an upbeat, rhythmic piece rather than a melancholy, lyrical one, so it was great to have the opportunity to portray different moods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;snacks&#34;&gt;Snacks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As usual, people brought in snacks to share for the mid-meeting break.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Helen not only brought in the recipe for her delicious brownies from &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/03/16/pittsburgh-recorder-society-something-new-recently-recording-our-practice-sessions/&#34;&gt;last month&amp;rsquo;s meeting&lt;/a&gt;, but also a new batch of what she called &amp;ldquo;Dolly Parton&amp;rdquo; cookies, incorporating a lot of apple in them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The recipe for last month&amp;rsquo;s brownies:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-recorder-society-2014-04-27/recipe.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I ate three of this month&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Dolly Parton&amp;rdquo; squares:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-recorder-society-2014-04-27/cookie1.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-recorder-society-2014-04-27/cookie2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-recorder-society-2014-04-27/cookie3.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although setting a limit on three was better than no limit at all, after I got home, I did wonder whether maybe I should have limited myself to two; these were quite substantial and filling!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had another intense and joyful musical afternoon with a great group of friendly and fun recorder enthusiasts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is your favorite role when you are on a team? Do you like being a prominent soloist, or do you prefer to blend into the background? Or do you like to switch up your roles? What do you adjust when you switch?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pittsburgh Recorder Society: Something new recently: recording our practice sessions</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/03/16/pittsburgh-recorder-society-something-new-recently-recording-our-practice-sessions/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Mar 2014 18:39:46 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/03/16/pittsburgh-recorder-society-something-new-recently-recording-our-practice-sessions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-recorder-society-2014-03-16/group.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Pittsburgh Recorder Society&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I forgot to mention in my post about &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/02/16/pittsburgh-recorder-society-7-part-gabrieli-and-coconut-chocolate-cookies/&#34;&gt;last month&amp;rsquo;s Pittsburgh Recorder Society&amp;rsquo;s meeting&lt;/a&gt; that Fred has started recording our sessions; he&amp;rsquo;s set up a tripod and an audio recorder. I kind of didn&amp;rsquo;t pay attention because it was not emphasized and nobody talked much about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today was a different story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;recording&#34;&gt;Recording&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was more mention of recording than in the past, and Fred made jokes about checking out what we did and how it would be useful for us to listen and see how we progress. Interestingly, this seemed to have quite an effect on what we did. I definitely felt a lot more serious and alert. Although I already always do take our meetings seriously, I will confess right now that whenever Fred said, &amp;ldquo;OK, now let&amp;rsquo;s do this again, and with recording&amp;rdquo;, I really perked up and gave it my all, trying to play as musically as possible, paying attention to intonation, articulation, ensemble balance, and even that terrible habit many of us have of sucking our recorders after the end of a piece.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fred is right: it doesn&amp;rsquo;t really make sense, &lt;em&gt;logically&lt;/em&gt;, to goof off during rehearsal and then expect to play well in actual performance. In practice, we should do the reverse: play it as well as we can in rehearsal, so that when we perform, which is usually in less than ideal circumstances (anxiety, unusual location or acoustics, or being hectic in getting somewhere, or any number of other unexpected glitches), our performance might be &lt;em&gt;worse&lt;/em&gt; than what we did, but it will still be good. On the other hand, if we don&amp;rsquo;t give it our all in practice, then what miracle can get us even better in performance?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, the recording of our work was not at all some kind of grim task. I enjoyed the additional seriousness and care, and I think we&amp;rsquo;re sounding better and better every month. Amusingly, the most noticeable thing is that when we know we are being recorded, we end pieces much better, and then &lt;em&gt;dead silence&lt;/em&gt;. No rustling, no recorder sucking. Wow. I really enjoy that unity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;tenor-and-bass&#34;&gt;Tenor and bass&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the first recorder meeting in my three years in which I did not play soprano or alto recorder once! I have been much preferring to play tenor and bass, to provide inner or bottom voices, and letting the newer members of the group play the soprano and alto voices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;snacks&#34;&gt;Snacks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People brought in snacks to share, as usual, for the mid-meeting break.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-recorder-society-2014-03-16/snacks.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Snacks&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And of course, this being St. Patrick&amp;rsquo;s Day weekend, Helen had to bring special Irish-themed snacks to share. In addition to Irish cheese, she also brought homemade brownies that she said were from an actual Irish recipe! These were &lt;em&gt;fantastic brownies&lt;/em&gt;: chocolate, cocoa, good stuff. I had to eat them, again and again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In accordance with my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/01/16/a-system-for-quitting-eating-cookies/&#34;&gt;promise about &amp;ldquo;cookies&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, here is a photo of each individual one I ate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-recorder-society-2014-03-16/brownie1.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Brownie 1&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-recorder-society-2014-03-16/brownie2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Brownie 2&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Someone brought in a box of castle cookies. I ate one:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-recorder-society-2014-03-16/castle-cookie.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;While I was packing up to leave, I couldn&amp;rsquo;t resist temptation and ate my third Helen brownie:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-recorder-society-2014-03-16/brownie3.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Brownie 3&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In retrospect, &lt;strong&gt;this was a big mistake&lt;/strong&gt;. After getting home, I felt burdened by this third brownie. I would have been fine just eating the first two and the one cookie (along with some cheese and nuts that I also had).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve noticed that I have a problem when I eat a &amp;ldquo;one more for the road&amp;rdquo; cookie at events. I&amp;rsquo;ve decided to consciously watch out and &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; do that in the future. I should only eat as much as I can handle, and leave it at that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2014-04-27&#34;&gt;(Update of 2014-04-27)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By popular demand, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/04/27/pittsburgh-recorder-society-palestrina-gombert-and-dolly-parton-cookies/&#34;&gt;the following month, Helen brought in the recipe for these brownies&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pittsburgh Recorder Society: 7-part Gabrieli and coconut chocolate cookies</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/02/16/pittsburgh-recorder-society-7-part-gabrieli-and-coconut-chocolate-cookies/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Feb 2014 17:41:04 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/02/16/pittsburgh-recorder-society-7-part-gabrieli-and-coconut-chocolate-cookies/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Because so many people are now regularly attending the Pittsburgh Recorder Society monthly meetings, we have enough critical mass to work on larger ensemble pieces. Fred pulled out a 7-part &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Giovanni_Gabrieli&#34;&gt;Gabrieli&lt;/a&gt; piece for us from the 16th century. Fun! I look forward to continuing working on this in March.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also continued work on other pieces we started earlier in the season. Fred&amp;rsquo;s guidance is as inspiring as ever. I feel that every meeting of our group is a wonderful opportunity to grow as a musician.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After going home I found a trumpet ensemble performance of the Gabrieli online:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/PlfvhJPNuTE&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;snacks&#34;&gt;Snacks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People brought in snacks to share, as usual, for break time.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/recorder-2014-02-16/snacks.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Helen made super-tasty-looking &amp;ldquo;cookies&amp;rdquo; (I asked if they counted as cookies, and she said yes). Coconut plus coconut plus homemade equals &lt;em&gt;difficult to resist&lt;/em&gt;!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/01/16/a-system-for-quitting-eating-cookies/&#34;&gt;my new rule&lt;/a&gt;, here are the three cookies I ate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/recorder-2014-02-16/cookie1.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;My first cookie&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/recorder-2014-02-16/cookie2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;My second cookie&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/recorder-2014-02-16/cookie3.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;My third cookie&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I stopped at three, which was a good thing, because after I went home, I did feel a little bloated. I should really have eaten only two, I think. I did take one home for Abby to enjoy.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My first time at an English country dance music jam</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/01/25/my-first-time-at-english-country-dance-music-jam/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Jan 2014 19:39:03 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/01/25/my-first-time-at-english-country-dance-music-jam/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Relatively recently, a new English country dance music jam in the Pittsburgh area has been organized by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amarillismusic.com/aboutus.html&#34;&gt;Maro Avakian&lt;/a&gt;, whom I first met through joining in playing for the Holiday Ball &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/16/playing-recorder-and-flute-at-the-holiday-ball/&#34;&gt;two years ago&lt;/a&gt;. I was unable to make it to the first couple of meetings, but finally, on a nasty snowy Saturday, my schedule happened to be open, so I went.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not completely new to English country dance music. It was almost two years ago when I first encountered it, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/31/my-first-sampling-of-english-country-dance-and-contra-dance/&#34;&gt;as a dancer&lt;/a&gt;. As has happened several times now in my life, becoming familiar with the dance got me interested in the &lt;em&gt;music&lt;/em&gt; and in the idea of actually playing the music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that I&amp;rsquo;d already played some of this kind of music for myself as a result of my study of the Baroque flute, because method books I have for the instrument include a good amount of dance music from the era. In any case, the book we use for many tunes is the volume by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.canispublishing.com/&#34;&gt;Peter Barnes&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://mysite.verizon.net/peterabarnes/books.htm&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Barnes Book of English Country Dance Tunes&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, a fine anthology. Actually, I ordered my copy only last week and was lucky it arrived in the mail just in time!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://mysite.verizon.net/peterabarnes/Book1.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;instruments&#34;&gt;Instruments&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had a pretty good turnout given the weather. Apart from Maro on piano, we had people playing flute, Baroque flute, recorders, ukulele, mandolin, percussion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d brought my flute, Baroque flute, and soprano, alto, tenor recorders, but since there were already two others on modern flute and soprano recorder, I ended up playing just the Baroque flute, alto recorder, and tenor recorder. The Baroque flute is pretty hard to play in some of the keys, and also is kind of soft, so I mostly played the alto and tenor recorders. I gradually gravitated toward improvising inner voices with the tenor recorder. I think I will do that in the future also. In addition, I should bring my bass recorder, to add a yet lower instrument to our group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;improvisation&#34;&gt;Improvisation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had great discussions about tips and tricks for improvising lines and filling out chords. Needless to say, I was botching up a lot of stuff as I experimented, but you can&amp;rsquo;t learn if you don&amp;rsquo;t try!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It looks like I have a new musical outlet, English country dance music. I hope to continue participating in it. As with French traditional dance music, I like the improvisational nature of working with a tune with repetition.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pittsburgh Recorder Society continues to add members</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/11/17/pittsburgh-recorder-society-continues-to-add-members/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Nov 2013 19:40:37 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/11/17/pittsburgh-recorder-society-continues-to-add-members/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;At the third meeting of this season of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/PittsburghRecorderSociety&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Recorder Society&lt;/a&gt;, I was pleased to see that we continue to add members. Wow. We already had a huge turnout &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/10/20/the-biggest-pittsburgh-recorder-society-meeting-i-have-attended-in-two-years/&#34;&gt;last month&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-recorder-society-2013-11-17/group.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Snacks!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-recorder-society-2013-11-17/snacks.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I never expected my first wooden recorders to be Renaissance recorders</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/21/i-never-expected-my-first-wooden-recorders-to-be-renaissance-recorders/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2013 21:24:54 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/21/i-never-expected-my-first-wooden-recorders-to-be-renaissance-recorders/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/10/20/the-biggest-pittsburgh-recorder-society-meeting-i-have-attended-in-two-years/&#34;&gt;Yesterday, I noted&lt;/a&gt; that I picked up two recorders during the Pittsburgh Recorder Society meeting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They were these &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.vonhuene.com/Default.aspx?tabid=42&#34;&gt;Renaissance&lt;/a&gt; instruments:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mollenhauer-kynseker-recorders/boxed.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;In boxes&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mollenhauer-kynseker-recorders/assembled.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Assembled&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nice maple recorders, Mollenhauer Kynseker models:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mollenhauer.com/en/catalogue?page=shop.product_details&amp;amp;flypage=flypage.tpl&amp;amp;product_id=170&amp;amp;category_id=121&#34;&gt;Kynseker Soprano 4107&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mollenhauer.com/en/catalogue?page=shop.product_details&amp;amp;flypage=flypage.tpl&amp;amp;product_id=172&amp;amp;category_id=121&#34;&gt;Kynseker Alto 4217&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are my very first wooden recorders. All my other recorders are Yamaha plastic recorders, because they are inexpensive and easy to maintain. I&amp;rsquo;ve periodically considered buying wooden recorders, but to get some of clearly higher quality than the plastic ones is expensive!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-bother-with-renaissance&#34;&gt;Why bother with Renaissance?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I jumped at the opportunity to bid in the auction for these two Renaissance recorders to acquire them inexpensively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Up till recently, I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t have considered buying Renaissance recorders at all, because of the difference in construction and tonal quality from the Baroque-style recorders that I have and that we play in the Pittsburgh Recorder Society meetings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this summer at the Mideast early music workshop, I paid attention to people playing Renaissance recorders (for Renaissance music and other music too) and found the louder and &amp;ldquo;reedier&amp;rdquo; sound intriguing. I could see myself playing them in contexts in which this kind of sound quality would be advantageous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So now I have these two wooden recorders to play with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that the solo soprano recorder music by Jacob van Eyck from the Renaissance that &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/28/my-first-appearance-on-a-music-recital-program/&#34;&gt;I played last year&lt;/a&gt; would have entirely been suited to my new soprano Renaissance recorder! I may revisit that music to play it on the new instrument.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The biggest Pittsburgh Recorder Society meeting I have attended in two years!!</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/20/the-biggest-pittsburgh-recorder-society-meeting-i-have-attended-in-two-years/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Oct 2013 18:04:10 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/20/the-biggest-pittsburgh-recorder-society-meeting-i-have-attended-in-two-years/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;At the second meeting of this season of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/PittsburghRecorderSociety&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Recorder Society&lt;/a&gt;, I was amazed by the huge turnout. There were &lt;strong&gt;fourteen&lt;/strong&gt; of us, easily double the typical attendance in the past two seasons since &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/02/23/celebrating-two-years-of-playing-recorder/&#34;&gt;I first joined in 2011&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-recorder-society-2013-10-20/panorama.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Fred was very excited by the attendance and told us he would like for us to perform as an entire group sometime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/09/15/new-goals-for-a-new-season-of-the-pittsburgh-recorder-society/&#34;&gt;promised after last month&amp;rsquo;s meeting&lt;/a&gt;, I took the opportunity in this meeting to do some playing on my bass recorder. I also played tenor and soprano for some other pieces we worked on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;halloween-themed-desserts&#34;&gt;Halloween-themed desserts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since it is almost Halloween, Helen brought in some &amp;ldquo;scary&amp;rdquo; cupcakes that were, to me anyway, a sight to behold.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-recorder-society-2013-10-20/snacks.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-recorder-society-2013-10-20/scary-cupcake.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-recorder-society-2013-10-20/scary-cupcake-bottom.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;pittsburgh-s-rubber-duck&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh&amp;rsquo;s rubber duck&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People were talking about the planned departure later today of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/RubberDuckPittsburghPa&#34;&gt;our rubber duck&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, in the duck&amp;rsquo;s honor, I had brought my ukulele, and during the break I played &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/10/02/rubber-duckie-and-steel-city-ukuleles-rehearsal/&#34;&gt;Rubber Duckie on my ukulele&lt;/a&gt; while singing along, and Anita joined in the singing too. I had worked pretty hard to be able to passably play this song before our duck left. I still need more work on the song.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;more-recorders-for-me-to-play&#34;&gt;More recorders for me to play&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I picked up two recorders from Helen that I had bid on at the last meeting, when a large collection of recorders was given to us to be auctioned off. More on this later!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had another great time at the Pittsburgh Recorder Society monthly meeting. Every month, our Sunday afternoon meeting is something I truly look forward to.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Final rehearsal for my first ukulele gig: and some hard decisions about music in my life</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/04/final-rehearsal-for-my-first-ukulele-gig/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2013 22:15:33 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/04/final-rehearsal-for-my-first-ukulele-gig/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;The night before our Ecofest gig, those of us in the Steel City Ukuleles who are performing in it had one final rehearsal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a very good rehearsal. We&amp;rsquo;re sounding more and more together as an ensemble, ending solidly on each song the way we agreed, and singing more in tune and balance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, Sunny reminded us that we are &lt;em&gt;performing&lt;/em&gt;, and so we should not just grimly look at our music booklets, but instead, when we can, we should look up and smile and engage with the audience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;singing&#34;&gt;Singing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still don&amp;rsquo;t have all the songs down as much as I would like, but by the end of the two-hour rehearsal, I was totally &lt;em&gt;hoarse&lt;/em&gt;. I am ready to sing out strong while simultaneously playing my ukulele.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I just realized that &lt;strong&gt;in the past three months, I have sung more than in the previous forty years of my life combined&lt;/strong&gt;. Wow. And I&amp;rsquo;m loving it. There&amp;rsquo;s nothing like singing, especially singing with others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;performance-is-time-and-energy-consuming&#34;&gt;Performance is time and energy consuming&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I almost didn&amp;rsquo;t make it to the rehearsal. I&amp;rsquo;ve completely exhausted myself this week with work and other activities, and badly need a break. There are times, such as earlier today, when I felt overwhelmed by everything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, yesterday, in discussing my musical plans for the coming months with Abby, I made some decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is my last ukulele gig for the year, for sure. I want to get back to basics and work on my technique and in really mastering some songs, rather than get back on the treadmill of more material for performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, this winter, I am not planning to participate in performing on recorder for the holiday gigs at Phipps Conservatory &amp;ldquo;candlelight evenings&amp;rdquo; that I&amp;rsquo;ve treasured &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/05/busy-evening-performing-at-phipps-followed-by-rehearsal-for-another-gig/&#34;&gt;in 2011&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/09/playing-music-on-recorders-at-a-phipps-conservatory-candlelight-evening/&#34;&gt;in 2012&lt;/a&gt;. That was always a huge amount of work for me. Unless I can participate in significantly reduced capacity, I don&amp;rsquo;t see how I can manage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will probably perform in the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/14/pittsburgh-contras-and-squares-holiday-ball-2012/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Contras and Squares Holiday Ball&lt;/a&gt; again, because it&amp;rsquo;s something I&amp;rsquo;ve been doing with Abby every year, and because after two years of doing it, I know the music, and therefore it will not require much work to participate in (if I want to do some Irish flute and tin whistle solos, of course, then I can add as much extra work for myself that I want, ha).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-is-the-best-use-of-my-limited-time-and-energy-for-music&#34;&gt;What is the best use of my limited time and energy for music?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, there have been announcements and reminders for some time about recorder and ukulele &lt;em&gt;workshops&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;concerts&lt;/em&gt; coming up soon. I have decided not to sign up for any of them, because I really need some rest time on &lt;em&gt;weekends&lt;/em&gt; that I have not been getting; weekends are also the time when I can do more household chores and spend time with Abby.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find that my main enjoyment and improvement in music comes form what I do daily, anyway, rather than what I can possibly do in a long, extended workshop format. I&amp;rsquo;ve always been frustrated that when I attend a one or two day conference or workshop on any subject (computer programming, salsa dance, etc.), I don&amp;rsquo;t actually retain or engage with as much as I would like. There are ways to optimize these experiences, but that requires a certain kind of immediate followup that I don&amp;rsquo;t have time for right now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I will sadly miss the fantastic &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flanders-recorder-quartet.be/en/home/&#34;&gt;Flanders Recorder Quartet&lt;/a&gt; when they come to Pittsburgh in November, and I will miss the workshop Annie has arranged for them to give here for the local recorder community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I am going to miss &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.coolhanduke.com/&#34;&gt;Cool Hand Uke&lt;/a&gt; when he comes to Pittsburgh to give a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/Steel-City-Ukuleles/events/135233932/&#34;&gt;workshop&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/Steel-City-Ukuleles/events/138577782/&#34;&gt;concert&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Life is full of choices, especially for those of us who have many interests, not just one. This week I made some decisions about my involvement with music in October, November, and December.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>First rehearsal for my first ukulele gig: dealing with anxiety</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/09/26/first-rehearsal-for-my-first-ukulele-gig/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Sep 2013 23:09:23 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/09/26/first-rehearsal-for-my-first-ukulele-gig/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s now officially &lt;em&gt;two months&lt;/em&gt; since &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/08/23/another-unexpected-life-change-one-month-of-learning-to-play-ukulele/&#34;&gt;I started learning to play ukulele&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s hard to believe, but two months ago, I was still struggling to play three chords: I could play C, of course, but had trouble with G7, and had even worse trouble with F: I had no finger strength or dexterity and could not arch my fingers and everything was a painful buzz, and I could spend only five minutes a day practicing because of the pain on my uncalloused fingers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And after just over a month of playing, and joining the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/Steel-City-Ukuleles/&#34;&gt;Steel City Ukuleles&lt;/a&gt;, I had volunteered to &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/09/04/my-second-meeting-of-the-steel-city-ukuleles/&#34;&gt;perform in a gig for Ecofest in Regent Square&lt;/a&gt;, as a way to force myself to maintain momentum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this week, just in time, I got my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/09/23/finally-got-a-nice-new-ukulele-mainland-classic-mahogany-concert/&#34;&gt;brand new concert-sized ukulele&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/ecofest-2013-rehearsal-1.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;First Ecofest rehearsal&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The gig is in just over a week. I attended my first rehearsal with extreme anxiety. I was even thinking about bailing out instead of attending. Here&amp;rsquo;s why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;new-music-for-me&#34;&gt;New music for me&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/steel-city-ukuleles-bound-thing-1.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/steel-city-ukuleles-bound-thing-2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I went into rehearsal with basically &lt;em&gt;none&lt;/em&gt; of the songs we were going to perform. So it was basically a sight reading and singing session for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One reason is that I was waiting to get the official bound compilation of performance songs that we were to receive at the first rehearsal, which we did. I had not requested to get one ahead of time, because I was too busy all week anyway to make good use of it if I had possessed it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, it turns out that many of these songs are already familiar and played by most of the other members of the performance group; they are part of the general repertoire, for previous years&amp;rsquo; Ecofests as well as for other gigs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;new-performance-group-for-me&#34;&gt;New performance group for me&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that breaking into a performance group for the first time always involves an initial learning curve because there are those who already know everything inside and out. I still have very vivid memories of other times in my life when I have entered a performance group and felt lost for a while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was briefly in marching band, during the 9th grade in high school. As a new freshman, I was unfamiliar with the repertoire, the choreography, etc. It was a tricky experience for all us freshmen, of course, amidst the 10th, 11th, and 12th graders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, over a decade ago, for a couple of years I was a member of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://cmubdc.org/&#34;&gt;Carnegie Mellon University ballroom dance club&lt;/a&gt;, and I was on both the competition team as well as the formation team. I&amp;rsquo;d made ballroom dancing the main focus of my life, throwing myself into lessons and competition and being in performances with the formation team while still a beginner. I improved my dancing significantly and quickly as a result of jumping in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And more recently, I have been performing in a small &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/09/playing-music-on-recorders-at-a-phipps-conservatory-candlelight-evening/&#34;&gt;recorder quartet/quintet at winter holiday time&lt;/a&gt;. Practicing so that I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t totally flub everything always took a huge amount of work for me, but the side effect was that I really improved my recorder playing and musicianship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I know firsthand the benefits of just jumping in and being around very experienced team members who are inspirational to emulate and learn from, and to exert some healthy pressure on myself not to let the team down!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;listening-watching&#34;&gt;Listening, watching&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of what I did during rehearsal was listening and watching, while doing what I could to keep up and go and make dozens of mistakes everywhere. (It&amp;rsquo;s particularly important to boldly make those mistakes and write down what to work on for homework.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was no way I was going to be able to play everything at first sight. In fact, that&amp;rsquo;s not even the right way to think about the situation. This isn&amp;rsquo;t classical music where you really do &amp;ldquo;sight read&amp;rdquo;. This is music where almost everything is transmitted &lt;em&gt;by ear&lt;/em&gt;. Not knowing the melodies, and not having an actual score, I have to listen and figure out where the melodic lines roughly are, and where the chord changes are. I have to learn what the prevailing strum rhythms and breaks and mood the group has largely decided on. The goal is to learn how to blend in and contribute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t do much extended &lt;em&gt;singing&lt;/em&gt; during this rehearsal. But we have two more rehearsals after this one, so it was not necessary to get everything down right away. I would, of course, be doing my own homework, looking up YouTube videos, in between official rehearsals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For consistency, I found it very useful to focus my listening on one person at a time to emulate. Usually that person was Sunny, because she is leading us. Sometimes that was Adam, because I was sitting near him and because as a strong male voice, I could follow him especially in songs where we had male and female voices split.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fact that there were over a dozen of us in the group for this gig was very helpful to me, because it meant that there was much less pressure on me to get everything right. I don&amp;rsquo;t always have to sing, or sing everything. I don&amp;rsquo;t always have to play the tricky chord progressions that I&amp;rsquo;m not ready yet to get right. I can leave stuff out judiciously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;half-the-songs&#34;&gt;Half the songs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In two hours, we covered half the songs we planned to play at Ecofest. I felt there was still a huge amount of work for me to do in order to really contribute to the group, but no longer felt helpless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-cost-of-excellence&#34;&gt;The cost of excellence&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still think it&amp;rsquo;s a little crazy that I jumped into committing to performing when still a beginner at ukulele, but in the past couple of years, I have learned that shorter, tighter learning and creating cycles considerably speed up the improvement process, provided that one actually puts in the hard work on a daily basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s been a huge cost, unfortunately. I have let some things slide while focusing on ukulele in the past two months. For example, I have been playing chess very poorly. Last week, I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/09/26/the-chess-improver-the-psychology-of-not-winning-the-won-game/&#34;&gt;drew a game that I should have won&lt;/a&gt;. And just two days ago, disaster struck: in my fatigue, I lost a game I should have won. If I had known I was going to have ukulele take over my life outside of work, I would have chosen &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; to play in the current chess tournament.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now as in the past couple of years, I have chosen to sacrifice my chess performance when other things come up. This is why I rarely play chess tournaments any more: I hate playing worse than I am actually capable of playing. As I mentioned two weeks ago, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/09/15/saying-no-on-not-playing-in-the-pittsburgh-chess-league-this-season-for-the-cmu-tartans/&#34;&gt;I had anticipated becoming busy in November&lt;/a&gt;, but I had not anticipated being so busy now already, in September!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sunny led a great rehearsal for our Ecofest gig coming up. I really like some of these songs we&amp;rsquo;re working on, and left feeling that after more work, we can sound really good and have a lot of fun at the gig!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New goals for a new season of the Pittsburgh Recorder Society</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/09/15/new-goals-for-a-new-season-of-the-pittsburgh-recorder-society/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Sep 2013 20:40:25 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/09/15/new-goals-for-a-new-season-of-the-pittsburgh-recorder-society/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-recorder-society-2013-09-15.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Recorder group&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I was delighted to pay my membership dues at the first meeting of the new 2013-2014 season of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/PittsburghRecorderSociety&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Recorder Society&lt;/a&gt;. I hadn&amp;rsquo;t played recorder much since this July&amp;rsquo;s Mideast early music workshop, because of my having &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/08/23/another-unexpected-life-change-one-month-of-learning-to-play-ukulele/&#34;&gt;taken up ukulele the day after I got back from that&lt;/a&gt;; in fact, apart from that week-long workshop, I had not attended any meetings of the Pittsburgh Recorder Society since April (since I had to miss the May one on travel), and although there are meetings all through the summer as well, they only take place in the North Hills, which is kind of far for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As with the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/16/excited-by-the-new-season-of-the-pittsburgh-recorder-society/&#34;&gt;opening of the last season&lt;/a&gt;, we have exciting new plans for this season. And I have my own new plans in addition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;introductions&#34;&gt;Introductions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have some new members, which is always great, so we went around briefly introducing ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;raising-our-level&#34;&gt;Raising our level&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is really inspiring, though, is the large number of formerly &amp;ldquo;new&amp;rdquo; people who joined during last season and have stayed with the group, so that we are in fact growing in numbers. Not only that, we have all improved considerably in the past year. Our director Fred is so excited by how far we have come that he has plans for us to work on harder music and improve our individual technique and ensemble playing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today we started working on music by Bach and Buxtehude: some lovely contrapuntal pieces. I look forward to our polishing up this stuff and really doing the old masters proud!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;bass-recorder&#34;&gt;Bass recorder&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to continuing work on my technique and musicality, I decided that for this season, I would like to do play more on bass recorder. In the past year, I&amp;rsquo;ve gravitated toward deliberately volunteering to play tenor lines, to experience the unique position of bringing out the inner voice as well as making it blend harmoniously with the others. For the new season, I have an interest in focusing on the bass line, to experience being the rock solid underpinning of ensemble music. So I told Fred on my plan, and he&amp;rsquo;ll come up with some stuff for me to get into that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been playing recorder for two and a half years now, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/02/23/celebrating-two-years-of-playing-recorder/&#34;&gt;starting in spring 2011&lt;/a&gt;. I am happy to be continuing on, with the companionship of everyone in the Pittsburgh Recorder Society! Making music together is really special.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My second meeting of the Steel City Ukuleles: why I already signed up to perform before being ready</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/09/04/my-second-meeting-of-the-steel-city-ukuleles/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Sep 2013 22:40:45 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/09/04/my-second-meeting-of-the-steel-city-ukuleles/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve entered my seventh week of playing ukulele.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last month, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/08/23/another-unexpected-life-change-one-month-of-learning-to-play-ukulele/&#34;&gt;I wrote about&lt;/a&gt; finally starting to learn to play ukulele and then attending my first meeting of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/Steel-City-Ukuleles/&#34;&gt;Steel City Ukuleles&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I just attended &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/Steel-City-Ukuleles/events/117972052/&#34;&gt;my second meeting&lt;/a&gt; after having improved a huge amount in two weeks (oh, the joy of being a beginner).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adam led a great playlist of songs for us to go through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;steel-city-ukuleles-t-shirt&#34;&gt;Steel City Ukuleles T-shirt&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/steel-city-ukuleles-shirt.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin wearing Steel City Ukuleles shirt&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The first thing I did upon arrival at the session was to pay for and put on the Steel City Ukuleles T-shirt that Sunny said was for sale at my last meeting. I picked the blue one (there is also a red one). Very nice, and I&amp;rsquo;m proud to be wearing it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;singing&#34;&gt;Singing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two weeks ago, at my first meeting, I was only on my fifth week of playing the ukulele at all, and struggled to keep up with chords and their changes in real time while also strumming, much less singing, so I did very little singing (especially since I barely knew most of the songs).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This week, having some of the finger work more under control, I started trying to start singing along sometimes. One thing I forgot to emphasize about why I&amp;rsquo;ve always been attracted to the prospect of playing guitar or ukulele is that I like to sing, and the drawback of playing wind instruments (as I have spent the last two years playing recorders and flutes) is that I can&amp;rsquo;t do that while also singing. And I love the idea of being able to accompany myself while singing, being my own harmonic and rhythmic support. (This is also a great thing about piano, but I have barely any piano competence, unfortunately.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;music-new-to-me-and-the-transformation-of-taste&#34;&gt;Music new to me and the transformation of taste&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m learning all kinds of songs of all kinds of genres. This is a totally different world from what I&amp;rsquo;m used to. I feel myself undergoing a transformation the same way I did when I started playing recorder. Before playing recorder, I had relatively little interest in Baroque or Renaissance music. It was, frankly, &amp;ldquo;boring&amp;rdquo;. But when forced to actually play it, I began to understand and feel it and enjoy the subtleties of expression, from the point of view of the performer (and even the composer). In fact, I would admit that as a result, I have come to enjoy playing music rather than passively listening to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m experiencing the same transformation of my perception and taste and enjoyment now. There&amp;rsquo;s all this stuff that I haven&amp;rsquo;t much listened to, much less played or sung, whether blues, soul, rock, indie pop, country. Not all of the songs we go through are exciting to me, but I&amp;rsquo;ve been impressed by how many have &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt; that is catchy that I can enjoy and express. These are songs that in many cases, if I didn&amp;rsquo;t actively strum or sing, would be boring to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;still-need-my-own-instrument&#34;&gt;Still need my own instrument&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m still using the loaner banjolele, because the intonation of my Lanikai soprano ukulele is too far off (eventually I should figure out how to fix it).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I returned Linda&amp;rsquo;s electric tenor and she lent me another instrument, an inexpensive concert ukulele (pictured):&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/steel-city-ukuleles-shirt.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin wearing Steel City Ukuleles shirt&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s been a good thing for me to try out different instruments, before I buy a concert sized ukulele of my own, which I should do soon, because just a week ago, I signed up to perform in a gig!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;small-group-and-solo-playing&#34;&gt;Small group and solo playing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What has been really inspiring and was seeing some of the members of the group volunteer to sing and play something they wanted to share with the rest of us. I enjoy appreciating the vulnerability and individuality of soloing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, Heidi, Amber, and Sunny performed a song as a trio, with beautiful ukulele playing and singing in harmony.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/heidi-amber-sunny.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Heidi, Amber, and Sunny&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;i-decided-to-perform-before-i-was-ready&#34;&gt;I decided to perform before I was ready&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/ecofest-2013.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Wilkins Center Community Center Ecofest 2013&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Last week, Sunny put out a call for volunteers to perform for a gig in a month, at the second annual &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wsccpgh.org/&#34;&gt;Wilkins Center Community Center&lt;/a&gt; Ecofest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remembered something that has changed my life in the past couple of years: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.stevenpressfield.com/2010/07/start-before-youre-ready/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;start before you&amp;rsquo;re ready&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. In this case, it meant that since there was an opportunity to perform in a low-key, low-stress environment, I should seize it even though I don&amp;rsquo;t at all feel &amp;ldquo;ready&amp;rdquo;. In the past two years, I have done dozens of things before feeling &amp;ldquo;ready&amp;rdquo;, while in the last three decades, I accomplished very little in my life because I never felt &amp;ldquo;ready&amp;rdquo;. I learned in two years that perfectionism is the enemy, and that you have to just go out there and do stuff, and ideally as early as possible, to get early feedback (external or internal) for rapid improvement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I signed up to perform in the Ecofest on October 5. If you live in the Pittsburgh area, I invite you to come see some subset of us from the Steel City Ukuleles perform at the Ecofest in Regent Square! I&amp;rsquo;ll write up more details later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deciding to perform means committing to getting a lot better in a month, of course. It also means not slacking on getting my own quality instrument. Finally, it means devoting time to official rehearsals, time that will have to come out of somewhere. (The rehearsal dates have not yet been set.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m starting to settle in on playing ukulele. In my seventh week now, I&amp;rsquo;ve gotten far enough to know for sure that I want to continue playing and get serious. To prove that I am serious, I am planning to perform already in a month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-09-18&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-09-18)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two weeks later: a report on &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/09/18/my-third-meeting-of-the-steel-city-ukuleles/&#34;&gt;my third Steel City Ukuleles meeting&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Celebrating Claude Debussy&#39;s 151st birthday through unusual performances of Syrinx</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/08/23/celebrating-claude-debussys-151st-birthday-through-unusual-performances-of-syrinx/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Aug 2013 23:49:25 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/08/23/celebrating-claude-debussys-151st-birthday-through-unusual-performances-of-syrinx/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;There was &lt;a href=&#34;http://jessicamusic.blogspot.com/2013/08/stop-dumbing-down-debussy.html&#34;&gt;much ado&lt;/a&gt; over Google&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;celebrating&amp;rdquo; Claude Debussy&amp;rsquo;s 151st birthday through a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.slate.com/blogs/browbeat/2013/08/22/claude_debussy_google_doodles_claire_de_lune_for_composer_s_151st_birthday.html&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Claire de Lune&amp;rdquo; doodle&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that I do totally love this piece of music, but it may well be true that many people do not know much about a lot of the other great music he wrote.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;syrinx&#34;&gt;Syrinx&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I decided to celebrate the birthday in my own way. I chose Debussy&amp;rsquo;s famous work for solo flute, &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Syrinx_%28Debussy%29&#34;&gt;Syrinx&lt;/a&gt;, as a starting point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two years ago, I already linked to a fine performance of it on flute &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/22/james-galway-made-me-hate-flute/&#34;&gt;by Emmannuel Pahud&lt;/a&gt;. There are many other good performances on flute, but inspired by &lt;a href=&#34;http://emilysdomain.org/&#34;&gt;Emily O&amp;rsquo;Brien&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/21/mideast-early-music-workshop-a-life-changing-experience/&#34;&gt;performance that I attended last year of Syrinx on tenor recorder&lt;/a&gt;, I looked for other non-flute performances of this music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found two intriguing ones to share.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;tenor-recorder&#34;&gt;Tenor recorder&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One is another tenor recorder performance, by Kenjiro Hibi. This Japanese musician made it seem as though it were traditional Japanese shakuhachi music!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/6e0kag3K86Y&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;trumpet&#34;&gt;Trumpet&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I found this amazing performance on trumpet, by &lt;a href=&#34;http://alisonbalsom.com/&#34;&gt;Alison Balsom&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/FW-8vC9Kpfw&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found this through &lt;a href=&#34;http://musicalassumptions.blogspot.com/2013/08/the-many-faces-of-syrinx-for-debussys.html&#34;&gt;someone else&amp;rsquo;s blog post on Syrinx for Debussy&amp;rsquo;s birthday&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;more-on-syrinx&#34;&gt;More on Syrinx&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is some interesting discussion of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flutefocus.com/232-syrinx-by-debussy.html&#34;&gt;interpretation and editions&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point, of course, I must work on this piece and play it on flute. But not yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a fascination with music played in a context other than the original, such as on a different instrument. It was fun discovering some performances of Debussy&amp;rsquo;s Syrinx on recorder and trumpet.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Another unexpected life change: one month of learning to play ukulele</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/08/23/another-unexpected-life-change-one-month-of-learning-to-play-ukulele/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Aug 2013 21:26:10 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/08/23/another-unexpected-life-change-one-month-of-learning-to-play-ukulele/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Almost exactly one month ago, on Monday, July 22, I vowed to spend at least a couple of minutes a day for two weeks attempting to learn to play the ukulele.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is how the story began and how it has unfolded in the past month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;jim-weirich-on-ukulele-almost-three-years-ago-december-2-2010&#34;&gt;Jim Weirich on ukulele almost three years ago (December 2, 2010)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first time I ever remember seing and hearing a ukulele up close was during a Pittsburgh Ruby meetup on December 2, 2010. Jim Weirich was a guest speaker. Before his talk, he and &amp;ldquo;The Searchers&amp;rdquo; (Jean Lange on flute, Colin Dean on trumpet, Carol Nichols on clarinet) performed the Ruby song, &amp;ldquo;Has Anybody Seen My Code?&amp;rdquo; (alternate lyrics to &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Has_Anybody_Seen_My_Gal%3F_%28song%29&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Has Anybody Seen My Gal?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/vKrr7aXUc1E&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Immediately after this, I thought to myself, it would be fun to be playing ukulele and singing like Jim just did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;discovering-jake-shimabukuro-february-2011&#34;&gt;Discovering Jake Shimabukuro (February 2011)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two months later, on February 5, 2011, I accidentally came across a popular video of &lt;a href=&#34;http://jakeshimabukuro.com/&#34;&gt;Jake Shimabukuro&lt;/a&gt; playing tenor ukulele, &amp;ldquo;Ukulele weeps&amp;rdquo;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/puSkP3uym5k&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was &lt;em&gt;totally&lt;/em&gt; blown away by this performance, and was convinced of the limitless possibilities of the ukulele.  I instantly decided that I wanted to learn to play the instrument. I had never played a string instrument before: once I had tried guitar for a couple of minutes and given up forever because it had seemed way too hard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;quitting-chess&#34;&gt;Quitting Chess&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, at this point in my life, I was very dissatisfied by how I was spending my time outside of work. I had been playing tournament chess, but playing very poorly and without my heart really being in it in the past months of participation. I was feeling miserable about having two more rounds to play in the 2011 Pittsburgh Chess Club Championship. (In retrospect, I should have simply dropped out rather than continue my misery. But I had this idea that I should finish out what I start. Sometimes that&amp;rsquo;s true, but in this case, it clearly was not.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The very same day I discovered Jake Shimabukuro, I sent the link to my friend Farokh, telling him, &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;ve been thinking about taking up the ukulele for a while now. I tried learning guitar some years ago but the instrument was too big for me, so I&amp;rsquo;m looking for a small stringed instrument I could play a variety of music on.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I made up my mind on the spot that I was retiring from chess after finishing the tournament: the very same day I also wrote my friend Steve, &amp;ldquo;I have the idea of replacing chess with music seamlessly. If you recall, 2005 was supposed to be my &amp;lsquo;year of music&amp;rsquo;, but I started playing chess again after Christmas of 2004. It&amp;rsquo;s time to retire.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-happened-to-the-year-of-music-2005&#34;&gt;What happened to the &amp;ldquo;year of music&amp;rdquo;, 2005?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In August 2002, I bought a flute hoping to get back to playing the instrument, after not having done so in two decades, but I quickly gave up because it seemed too hard. This despite buying exactly one piece of sheet music with the plan to play it, &amp;ldquo;Aprs un rve&amp;rdquo;, which by the way I finally ended up playing a decade later, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/07/04/more-summer-musical-partying/&#34;&gt;at a party last month&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In late 2004, I decided that in 2005, I would give one more shot at playing music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Unfortunately&amp;rdquo;, on December 29, 2004, I went to a meeting of the Pittsburgh Chess Club for the first time, got hooked, and shortly after that, joined the club, and &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/08/30/why-i-do-not-play-chess-online-chess-as-a-human-activity/&#34;&gt;began playing in tournaments again for the first time in two decades&lt;/a&gt;. I spent a number of years making chess my main activity outside of work, until &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/10/flute-loving-it-again/&#34;&gt;I met Abby in late 2006&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Flute had to wait.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;recorder-vs-ukulele&#34;&gt;Recorder vs. ukulele?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back to February 5, 2011: this very day, I immediately told Abby that I wanted to play ukulele. She was skeptical, but had her friend Lynette lend me a soprano ukulele to try out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On February 15, 2011, after the last round of the 2011 Pittsburgh Chess Club Championship, I immediately &amp;ldquo;retired&amp;rdquo; from chess. (By the way, I &amp;ldquo;unretired&amp;rdquo; and &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/08/21/returning-to-chess/&#34;&gt;returned to tournament chess in fall 2012&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I immediately started to practice recorder regularly (because it seemed an &amp;ldquo;easy&amp;rdquo; gateway to playing any music at all without a steep learning curve: I was discouraged by my failure at flute years earlier), and also planned to start playing ukulele.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On February 19, 2011, I wrote Farokh about my progress: &amp;ldquo;After a couple of days of spending a minute or two trying to play the G7 chord on the ukulele, I can finally sort of do it, in isolation. I will keep toughening my left hand for some more days before trying to start real work on the ukulele. Meanwhile, today I took a break from the soprano recorder and started playing the alto, finally. Fingerings are the same, but the pitches are different, so it&amp;rsquo;s pretty confusing. Obviously it&amp;rsquo;s not a good idea to try to learn both simultaneously. The alto is harder to play for me because it&amp;rsquo;s bigger, but I like the sound a lot more, and in the long run, it&amp;rsquo;s more versatile, suitable for music the modern flute can play. So I may stick with the alto for a while before going back to the soprano. I&amp;rsquo;m very much enjoying getting back to music. It had kind of exited my life around five years ago (!!) since I got back into chess in 2005. I have now completely quit chess, cold turkey, to make time for music. Music is much more rewarding, in the end.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;recorder-wins-march-2011&#34;&gt;Recorder wins (March 2011)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On March 2, 2011, I finally ordered a soprano ukulele online, because the one lent to me simply had structural defects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I had the same frustrations as with the loaner ukulele. The instrument seemed very hard to play. On March 20, 2011, I went to my first meeting of the Pittsburgh Recorder Society. I was making progress with daily practice, and so I completely abandoned the ukulele. It collected dust for well over two years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that I did continue with recorder, largely because I found the Pittsburgh Recorder Society and joined it, and I have been playing recorder &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/02/23/celebrating-two-years-of-playing-recorder/&#34;&gt;ever since&lt;/a&gt;, even attending my first music camp less than two years later, the week-long &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/21/mideast-early-music-workshop-a-life-changing-experience/&#34;&gt;summer 2012 Mideast Early Music Workshop&lt;/a&gt;, which focuses on recorders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there had been a Pittsburgh ukelele group at the time, the course of my entire musical life could have been altered: I would not have spent the last two years of my musical life on recorders, modern flute, &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/baroque-flute/&#34;&gt;Baroque flute&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/irish-flute/&#34;&gt;Irish flute&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/tin-whistle/&#34;&gt;tin whistle&lt;/a&gt; (years that I treasure, so I am actually glad that I gave up ukulele when I did!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;steel-city-ruby-music-jam-august-2012&#34;&gt;Steel City Ruby music jam (August 2012)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fast-forward a year, to the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/08/22/steel-city-ruby-conf-review-part-1-its-about-people/&#34;&gt;first Steel City Ruby conference&lt;/a&gt;, where I knew Jim Weirich was going to be a speaker, and therefore that he was going to do a music jam. I brought my Irish flute, not really sure whether I was going to have the courage to join in, since I had only &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/02/my-first-french-music-jam-anxious-but-excited/&#34;&gt;just&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/03/petrified-at-a-music-jam-session-so-i-didnt-play-but-watched-and-listened/&#34;&gt;begun&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/07/another-terrifying-music-jam-session-but-i-played-a-little-bit-of-blues-and-old-time/&#34;&gt;music jamming&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ended up completely chickening out and choosing to go out for lunch instead, and when I came back they were still playing and I watched. I silently vowed to myself that the following year, if Jim was coming to Steel City Ruby again, I would not chicken out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;music-from-august-december-2012&#34;&gt;Music from August-December 2012&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I launched myself into the new local French music jam, going to my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/08/27/my-second-french-music-jam-playing-my-irish-flute-in-public-for-the-first-time/&#34;&gt;second one&lt;/a&gt; just shortly after Steel City Ruby, and then proceeding further, bit by bit overcoming my fear of being incompetent as a musician. The entire past year has been very rewarding for me musically, as I kept on practicing, playing, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/10/28/singing-and-playing-bossa-nova-favorite-chega-de-saudade-at-dunkin-donuts-for-j-jam/&#34;&gt;anywhere&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/10/27/singing-an-irish-ballad-as-an-asian-pirate-at-a-halloween-belly-dance-hafla/&#34;&gt;everywhere&lt;/a&gt;, on &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/09/playing-music-on-recorders-at-a-phipps-conservatory-candlelight-evening/&#34;&gt;recorders&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/17/finally-doing-some-latin-music-jamming-on-flute/&#34;&gt;flute&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/08/finally-performing-some-sonatas-for-baroque-flute/&#34;&gt;Baroque flute&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/14/pittsburgh-contras-and-squares-holiday-ball-2012/&#34;&gt;Irish flute and tin whistle&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/22/playing-tango-on-melodica-and-singing-christmas-carols/&#34;&gt;melodica&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/11/17/a-childhood-dream-come-true-i-am-now-finally-singing-for-real/&#34;&gt;voice&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;music-from-january-july-2013&#34;&gt;Music from January-July 2013&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of my newer musical activities this year: &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/26/music-i-just-played-for-the-first-time-recorder-sonata-tangos/&#34;&gt;tango on flute&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/28/my-first-blues-music-jam-happened-after-the-regular-french-music-jam/&#34;&gt;blues&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;back-to-string-instruments-viola-da-gamba-july-2013&#34;&gt;Back to string instruments? Viola da gamba (July 2013)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last month, I went to the week-long Mideast Early Music Workshop for the second time. (I&amp;rsquo;m still finishing up the full report to post.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The day I arrived at music camp, it turned out that the instructor for the class on &amp;ldquo;viol for the novice&amp;rdquo; was looking for one more person to show interest in learning viol (also known as viola da gamba), since there was only one student signed up at the time. (The &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Viol&#34;&gt;viol&lt;/a&gt; is a fretted instrument that you play with a bow.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought to myself, heck, I&amp;rsquo;ll give this a shot. It would be a no-risk attempt to try again to learn the basics of playing a string instrument!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I signed up. I was lent a treble viol.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was crazy hard for me to learn how to bow without making horrible sounds, and hard for me to play the most trivial melodies by fretting while bowing. Neither I nor the other beginner after just a week felt ready to even play a simple melody in the final student concert. I had spent quite a bit of time practicing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I learned a couple of things from this experience:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If I really wanted to, I could play a bowed string instrument; my strokes and control were clearly getting better every day.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If I really wanted to, I could play a fretted string instrument; I was slowly becoming able to pluck out a melody.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If I really wanted to, I could learn to be competent at viola da gamba, just like all my other workshop companions who told me they had started as total beginners years ago.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that I&amp;rsquo;m not very interested in playing viola da gamba, compared to lots of other things I could be doing. But the &lt;em&gt;confidence&lt;/em&gt; that I could if I wanted to was very empowering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;guitar-ukulele&#34;&gt;Guitar, ukulele&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that in June, before my music camp, Farokh had started learning to play guitar. On July 22, two days after I returned from music camp, he told me he getting very serious about guitar. This was quite impressive because unlike me, he did not even have any musical background at all in K-12. I was deeply moved by Farokh&amp;rsquo;s dedication and seriousness as an adult latecomer to music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So on July 22, I replied to him, &amp;ldquo;I will pick up my ukulele tonight and give it a go. There&amp;rsquo;s a new Pittsburgh uke meetup so if I can actually get going with it, there is a good place to continue.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;steel-city-ukuleles&#34;&gt;Steel City Ukuleles&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, there is a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/Steel-City-Ukuleles/&#34;&gt;Steel City Ukuleles&lt;/a&gt; meetup group. I have known about it for over a year, by accident from an &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pghcitypaper.com/pittsburgh/steel-city-ukuleles-keeps-strummin/Content?oid=1506609&#34;&gt;article in the Pittsburgh Post-Gazette&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So on March 28, I had written the organizer, &amp;ldquo;Hi, I just saw a local news article about the Steel City Ukuleles. I bought a soprano ukulele a year ago but have barely started learning to play it. I&amp;rsquo;m interested in getting going on it and maybe joining the group.&amp;rdquo; I got a friendly response, but given that I could not really play, and that I was already very busy with my recorder and flute activities, I had no time to try again to learn ukulele from scratch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was no way I would attend the meetup until I was at least a beginner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;practice&#34;&gt;Practice&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On July 22, I started &amp;ldquo;practicing&amp;rdquo; ukulele no more than five minutes a day (that&amp;rsquo;s as much as I could tolerate without calluses on my left fingers), and just trying to make the most basic chords after C work (which they never had earlier): G7, F. I kept on smudging and buzzing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On July 25, I was still having trouble getting an F to work. Farokh chided me for my feelings of discouragement on ukulele, saying he was making progress on guitar: &amp;ldquo;Have you practiced the F chord every day for weeks until you get it?  If not, you haven&amp;rsquo;t been sufficiently dedicated.  This is how people learn to play guitar; it&amp;rsquo;s like digging through a brick wall with a spoon!  You need to build up your dexterity.  It took me two weeks to play the G chord decently.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On July 28, six days after starting again with ukulele, and making tiny bits of progress, I wrote Farokh, &amp;ldquo;My plan with uke is to take just a few minutes a day for the next week or two, then reassess what next. I have to observe the advice I give everyone: something small every day for two weeks before giving anything up.&amp;rdquo; In my experience, when learning something new, the first two weeks can be very, very discouraging, but if you quit before the two weeks are up, you may never know how close you were to making the breakthrough that everyone else who persevered can make.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On July 31, I was continuing to make progress, playing longer than five minutes at a time. Calluses started forming. Fingers became more precise. Still could barely actually play, but the improvement was real. I decided to aim to get proficient enough to attend the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/Steel-City-Ukuleles/events/117972052/&#34;&gt;September 4 meeting of the Steel City Ukuleles&lt;/a&gt;. I did not feel I would be ready to attend the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/Steel-City-Ukuleles/events/117972012/&#34;&gt;August 7 meeting&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But at least I used the trick of &lt;em&gt;committing&lt;/em&gt; to the September meeting, by posting to the August event site introducing myself and saying I planned to come in September. I wanted people to know that I was just starting out and had a month to get ready. I also wanted people to remember that when I showed up, so that I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be just some random guy, but &lt;em&gt;the guy who told us a month ago he was going to come&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;books&#34;&gt;Books&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started working through some books on ukulele. Progress through them was very difficult, because some of the books just went way too fast, without explanation. These concise books are worthless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On August 3, I got hold of &amp;ldquo;The Complete Idiot&amp;rsquo;s Guide to Playing Ukulele&amp;rdquo;. This was useful, but had confusing orders of presentation and omissions in explanation. Still, I managed to learn some more chords (while still not playing anything quite right) and some fingerpicking while at it. I hit a wall pretty quickly though. The book has a lot of really hard stuff in it, and could occupy me for a year or two, I think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On August 10, I started working through &amp;ldquo;Ukulele for Dummies&amp;rdquo;, and made good progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;three-weeks-up&#34;&gt;Three weeks up&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After my three-week trial period of daily practice, I assessed my status.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the ups and downs of practice, I knew that I had made tremendous progress. Sometimes I would plateau for two days but then suddenly &amp;ldquo;get&amp;rdquo; something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still had trouble with the most basic barre chord, but actually, when I counted, I had learned around twelve chords and could do some basic progressions in some keys. I was buzzing out less and my fingers were starting to go just where they needed to go (if the chord changes were slow enough). It was an amazing feeling, the feeling of &lt;em&gt;being a beginner&lt;/em&gt; rather than &lt;em&gt;being nothing at all&lt;/em&gt; (which was the feeling I had during the whole first week and part of the second week).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ukulele calluses after one month:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/ukulele-calluses.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Ukulele calluses&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;bad-instrument&#34;&gt;Bad instrument?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I was getting increasingly annoyed by the fact that my instrument seems defective. The A string is sharp when fretted. I still don&amp;rsquo;t know what the problem is. I regret having bought this instrument years ago online, unseen and unplayed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;steel-city-ruby-2013-august-17-18&#34;&gt;Steel City Ruby 2013, August 17-18&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://conscientiousprogrammer.com/blog/2013/08/18/steel-city-ruby-2013-my-second-year-and-it-radically-changed-my-life-again-part-1/&#34;&gt;first morning&lt;/a&gt; of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://steelcityruby.org/&#34;&gt;Steel City Ruby&lt;/a&gt; conference, as I was about to leave home, I suddenly had a thought. Originally I was going to bring my Irish flute to the conference, as I had last year, to join a music jam with Jim Weirich (a speaker again at the conference).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tweeted, &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/franklinchen/status/368346099712786432&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Was thinking of bringing my uke to #scrc13 because of @jimweirich, but been learning it only 3 weeks, feel like imposter.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. Jim replied, &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/jimweirich/status/368348104397185024&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;oh yes! Please bring!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I did bring my ukulele. Early on in the day, it was announced that there would be a music jam on the second day of the conference. So the next day, I brought my ukulele in again. And so we had a music jam: Jim, PJ Hagerty, Carol Nichols, and me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was nervous, and couldn&amp;rsquo;t keep up with everything, but had a great time. It also happened to be the first time I ever played ukulele outside of just practicing at home. We did Jim&amp;rsquo;s Ruby song, the very one that I had seen him do almost three years ago at the Pittsburgh Ruby meetup, as well as his Lisp song, and a whole bunch of other stuff, like Hank Williams. (It&amp;rsquo;s hard to believe, but I hadn&amp;rsquo;t played music with other people in a month, since the Mideast Early Music Workshop ended, but I was really focused on personal ukulele practice like a monk.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some photos of us (sadly without Carol, who was sitting opposite the three of us):&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;https://pbs.twimg.com/media/BR4fd0xCUAEwWRq.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Looking for music to play&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;https://pbs.twimg.com/media/BR4mjIUCYAIde9U.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;PJ, Franklin, Jim&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So I ended up playing ukulele with others sooner than I had originally intended or expected. Also, at one point I briefly swapped instruments with Jim so that I could feel what it was like to play a tenor. Surprisingly to me, although it was of course &amp;ldquo;big&amp;rdquo;, it was not as unmanageable as I feared it might be. I always imagined that eventually I&amp;rsquo;d &amp;ldquo;graduate&amp;rdquo; to playing a tenor, after first playing soprano, then concert size, sort of like my progression on recorder of first soprano, then alto, then tenor, then finally &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/03/my-new-bass-and-sopranino-recorders-and-having-fun/&#34;&gt;bass&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;sunday-the-day-after&#34;&gt;Sunday: the day after&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The very day after the conference jam session, I got email about the Steel City Ukuleles meeting on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/Steel-City-Ukuleles/events/117971802/&#34;&gt;Wednesday&lt;/a&gt;. In my &amp;ldquo;planning&amp;rdquo;, I had neglected to realize that the group met twice a month, not just once a month! So I didn&amp;rsquo;t have to wait till September 4 after all. I felt I was probably already competent enough to function on Wednesday; I looked at the musical selections, and felt reassured that even if I still have problems with fast chord changes, I could participate without making a total mess of everything. So I signed up!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;monday-need-better-instrument&#34;&gt;Monday: need better instrument?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went to the local music store to check out concert size ukuleles, because if I need to get a better instrument, I think I might like that size better than the soprano. I have not made any decisions yet. I feel I need to improve further, to better understand instruments and try different kinds, before buying another one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;wednesday-my-first-time-at-steel-city-ukuleles&#34;&gt;Wednesday: my first time at Steel City Ukuleles&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I arrived, Linda lent me an electric tenor for me to try out. I ended up playing it for the whole two hours because the intonation was good, unlike my soprano. For the most part, I did not have difficulty with the larger instrument.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some photos:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://photos4.meetupstatic.com/photos/event/6/d/1/c/highres_274467932.jpeg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Steel City Ukuleles group photo&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As you can see, I ended up just leaving my soprano ukulele on the ground unused during this session:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://photos1.meetupstatic.com/photos/event/6/d/2/6/highres_274467942.jpeg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Another group photo&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As the meetup was winding down, because it got dark outside, and my fingers were tired, I captured some footage of &amp;ldquo;Has Anybody Seen My Gal?&amp;rdquo; being done by the group:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/LM1Pi2zX484&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How fitting it is that the very tune I first heard from Jim Weirich almost three years ago is the one to close out my first attendance of the Steel City Ukuleles!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-next&#34;&gt;What next?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A month ago, when I was only practicing ukulele five minutes a day, I was still doing some flute practice. But I have not been playing flute or recorder for quite some time now (last time was probably a week ago). I feel bad about this, but I seem to be in ukulele mode now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I need to keep flute and recorder in &amp;ldquo;maintenance mode&amp;rdquo; rather than just abandon them entirely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, it is of course very exciting to be a beginner at ukulele. To make massive improvements on ukulele, I &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; make it my musical &lt;em&gt;focus&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;instruments&#34;&gt;Instruments&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Linda warned me that her electric tenor ukulele has a high action. After playing it the next day at home, I realized that indeed it has a high action that shreds my left fingers. So it&amp;rsquo;s not working for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, Abby yesterday brought home a concert-sized &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Banjo_uke&#34;&gt;banjolele&lt;/a&gt; borrowed from a friend:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/banjolele.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Banjolele&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been using it to get the feel of the concert size while continuing to practice and learn, and so far it&amp;rsquo;s been working great, giving me confidence that I should in fact buy a concert size ukulele.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-09-23&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-09-23)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A month later, I actually did finally &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/09/23/finally-got-a-nice-new-ukulele-mainland-classic-mahogony-concert/&#34;&gt;buy a concert ukulele&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s been quite a journey, getting into music and into ukulele through seemingly chance and trivial events such as music at a Pittsburgh Ruby meetup and hearing about Jake Shimabukuro.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I&amp;rsquo;m so excited that I&amp;rsquo;m playing ukulele now. It&amp;rsquo;s a whole different music world for me. I&amp;rsquo;ll write more about what I mean, as I continue to progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-09-04&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-09-04)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two weeks after my first Steel City Ukuleles meeting, I went back for more, attending &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/09/04/my-second-meeting-of-the-steel-city-ukuleles/&#34;&gt;my second meeting&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>