<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Yehudi Menuhin on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/yehudi-menuhin/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Yehudi Menuhin on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/yehudi-menuhin/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Revisiting Bach&#39;s Air on G String, from a singing and dancing viewpoint</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/06/10/revisiting-bachs-air-on-g-string-from-a-singing-and-dancing-viewpoint/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jun 2015 23:46:26 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/06/10/revisiting-bachs-air-on-g-string-from-a-singing-and-dancing-viewpoint/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Three years ago, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/14/passion-of-bachs-air-on-the-g-string-three-different-interpretations/&#34;&gt;I wrote a post comparing three very different
performance styles&lt;/a&gt;
for Johann Sebastian Bach&amp;rsquo;s famous music,
&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Air_on_the_G_String&#34;&gt;Air on G String&lt;/a&gt;
and indicating which I preferred.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have received an unexpected number comments over the years, and
thought it was time to write an update of my thoughts in response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Primarily, I am responding to those who (correctly) criticized the
unfortunately chosen exemplar of the style that I preferred. I tried
to find better versions that might illustrate my perceptions. I also
integrated some thoughts based on how I perceive music as a singer and
as a dancer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;better-than-the-rushed-croatian-baroque-ensemble-s-performance&#34;&gt;Better than the rushed Croatian Baroque Ensemble&amp;rsquo;s performance?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I agreed quickly with the first commenters that the Croatian
ensemble&amp;rsquo;s performance was too perfunctory, even downright brutal and
unpleasant in various ways. I wish I had
chosen a better example of what I actually &lt;em&gt;like&lt;/em&gt; rather than &lt;em&gt;prefer
to the other two versions&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I searched YouTube for period-style performances that are
closer to what I envision than either the Croatian ensemble&amp;rsquo;s or
Koopman&amp;rsquo;s. It proved impossible for me to find a perfect performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-period-performance-i-like-more-christopher-hogwood&#34;&gt;A period performance I like more: Christopher Hogwood&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like this version by the late &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christopher_Hogwood&#34;&gt;Christopher Hogwood&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s Academy of
Ancient Music:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/nrtdhH8_47k&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a sweetness and &lt;em&gt;bouncy lightness&lt;/em&gt; to this version that I
like, but it is also somewhat anemic. Personally, I would play up more
contrast and fullness of sound and passion, but the overall tempo and
breathing to this version seems right to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;voices-of-music-richer-sound&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Voices of Music&amp;rdquo;: richer sound&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Voices of Music&amp;rdquo; here in a good performance:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/pzlw6fUux4o&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like the richness of sound in this performance. I miss the lighter,
more bouncy feeling that Hogwood brought out though. This performance
is a bit too legato for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;i-care-about-singing&#34;&gt;I care about singing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I approach this music from the viewpoint of singing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bouncy lightness is very important to me, along with the rhythmic
characterization. I feel this music as a song (it is an &amp;ldquo;air&amp;rdquo;, after
all), and I cannot help singing along when I hear it. Therefore, when
it&amp;rsquo;s taken too slow for me to sing and make it to natural breathing
points in phrases, that considerably lessens my pleasure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;yehudi-menuhin-solo-violin&#34;&gt;Yehudi Menuhin, solo violin&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s an interesting old black and white video of a performance by a young Yehudi Menuhin on violin with
accompaniment. It&amp;rsquo;s not a period performance, but moves along at a
decent &amp;ldquo;singing&amp;rdquo; tempo, as befits violin, that singing instrument.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34;
src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/08bDiKXW0gg&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;
allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I confess that I rather like this performance for its virtues,
although it distorts Bach&amp;rsquo;s music by so emphasizing just the musical
line, at the expense of the balance of the other voices and the
essential character of the dissonances among the voices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;more-menuhin-but-as-conductor&#34;&gt;More Menuhin, but as conductor&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s Yehudi Menuhin not as violin soloist but as conductor of the
Bath Festival Orchestra in 1960. Again, not a period performance, but
he takes the music briskly, and has the violins create sufficient
phrase delineations that I feel the music alertly as though it sings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s direct and clear, maybe not the most subtle and warm,
but I like it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/kaBAE4stNIo&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;dancing-is-possible-too&#34;&gt;Dancing is possible too&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also like to dance to expressive music. A pioneer of modern dance,
Doris Humphrey, famously choreographed a dance to a slowish
performance of this music:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/NjwJyaSIRqY&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not how I would dance to it, because I feel the music
differently. Surprisingly, I could find few examples on YouTube of
dancing to this music. I may consider choreographing a dance myself as
a project to express my own personal vision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing I would like to mention is that I feel that the &lt;em&gt;walking bass&lt;/em&gt;
is very important in this music and gives it the impetus. When played
too slow, the walking bass no longer feels like it&amp;rsquo;s walking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel this music in my legs, not just in my lungs. Yes, I have
actually hummed it to myself while walking in time to the bass
leisurely in the local park. There is a limit to how &amp;ldquo;leisurely&amp;rdquo; I can
walk without feeling frustrated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;ice-dancing&#34;&gt;Ice dancing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found this somewhat frenetic but nevertheless beautiful ice dancing
performance from the 1992 World Figure Skating Championships:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/1JjbwtM_E3g&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;recorder-quartet&#34;&gt;Recorder quartet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A final performance to enjoy: the Japanese &amp;ldquo;Sekishi Recorder Quartet&amp;rdquo;
playing their hearts out in 2009. I think it&amp;rsquo;s lovely: impeccable
phrasing, transparency,
and rich ensemble balance and tone. (As a twist, the melody line performer adds
his own ornamentations.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/pRRRK0UClNs&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was inspired by the accumulated comments on my previous post on
Bach&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Air on G String&amp;rdquo; that I decided to flesh out my thoughts by
using more example performances, as well as relate the orchestral
music to singing and dancing. I hope you have enjoyed these
explorations. There is no single &amp;ldquo;right&amp;rdquo; way to experience music, but
I wanted to share how I experience it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;ve read my previous post, does this one help clarify where
  I&amp;rsquo;m coming from with my musical values? Do you dance
  or sing? Does this affect how you perceive this piece of music and
  like to perform it or hear it performed?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>