<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Calves on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/calves/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Calves on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/calves/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>The dilemma of how to descend the Cathedral of Learning once at the top</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/11/03/the-dilemma-of-how-to-descend-the-cathedral-of-learning-once-at-the-top/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Nov 2013 09:34:44 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/11/03/the-dilemma-of-how-to-descend-the-cathedral-of-learning-once-at-the-top/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, right after I left one of the sessions of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.music.pitt.edu/events/43rd-annual-jazz-seminar-concert130813&#34;&gt;annual Pittsburgh Jazz Seminar&lt;/a&gt; at the William Pitt Union, I immediately crossed the street to the Cathedral of Learning, in order to climb up to the 36th floor (I last climbed the Cathedral &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/10/29/an-early-start-on-cathedral-of-learning-stair-climbing/&#34;&gt;three days ago&lt;/a&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/cathedral-2013-11-02.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;View of Cathedral of Learning&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I took off my shoes, stuffed my jacket into my backpack, and went up at an &amp;ldquo;easy&amp;rdquo; pace, taking about nine minutes:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/cathedral-2013-11-02-at-top.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;View from 36th floor window of Cathedral of Learning&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Then I faced the usual dilemma of how to get back down, except this time, the dilemma was magnified because of my time constraints: I really needed to get down and out &lt;em&gt;quickly&lt;/em&gt;, in order to make it to an important appointment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;choices-and-tradeoffs&#34;&gt;Choices and tradeoffs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;elevator-down&#34;&gt;Elevator down&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One option is to take one of the elevators down. This is what I&amp;rsquo;ve almost always done ever since doing the Cathedral of Learning stair climb.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, whether this is time-effective depends a lot on various factors, such as whether Pitt classes are being held, Pitt students are roaming around, or tourists are roaming around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that Saturday afternoon is a bad time to be taking the elevator. There were hordes of students as well as tourists throughout the building, and especially the tourists at the top floor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, I had noticed on the ground floor earlier that some of the elevators were out of service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/10/29/an-early-start-on-cathedral-of-learning-stair-climbing/&#34;&gt;three days ago I had a bad experience with the elevator&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;taking-the-stairs-down&#34;&gt;Taking the stairs down&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other option is to take the stairs back down, all the way. This option is one I take so rarely that I don&amp;rsquo;t even remember when I last did it. I probably did it once earlier this year, but have no specific memory of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The drawback of taking the stairs down is the extra impact on the body.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But since I needed to descend as quickly as possible, I felt I had no choice but to take the stairs. In fact, I not only used the stairs, but ran down all the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It wasn&amp;rsquo;t hard (thank you, gravity!), although it got boring and weird after a while, because it feels like forever going down 36 floors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-day-after&#34;&gt;The day after&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought everything was OK, but this morning, the day after, I woke up with a serious case of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Delayed_onset_muscle_soreness&#34;&gt;DOMS&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My &lt;em&gt;calves&lt;/em&gt; were totally tight and trashed. Oops. Maybe I could have prevented this by stretching after running down yesterday, but I had no time, and had to make my appointment. Or maybe I just plain overdid things, not being conditioned at all to running down so many steps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I&amp;rsquo;m suffering, but no permanent damage done, of course: I will be OK after a day or two.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-next&#34;&gt;What next?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So does this mean that the next time I climb the Cathedral, I will stick to the elevator?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, &lt;em&gt;no&lt;/em&gt;. I take the experience as a challenge:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;First, I want to defeat my sense of boredom going down, just as I&amp;rsquo;ve managed to defeat it on the way up. I will find something meditative and aesthetic about the process of descending the steps.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Clearly my soreness showed that my calves were insufficiently conditioned. The solution to that is not to avoid running down the steps, but to &lt;em&gt;keep doing it&lt;/em&gt;, in a smarter way. Therefore, my plan now is that on any final repetition of the Cathedral stair climb, I will take the stairs back down, rather than the elevator, regardless of elevator congestion concerns.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An accidental case of trashed calves during a workout has led me to treat it as a learning experience and a challenge to overcome in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2014-10-22&#34;&gt;(Update of 2014-10-22)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/10/22/climbing-the-cathedral-of-learning-to-get-to-the-harvard-classics/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;elevator modernization project&amp;rdquo; started in September 2014 and makes it even more attractive to just walk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>