<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Violin on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/violin/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Violin on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/violin/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Revisiting Bach&#39;s Air on G String, from a singing and dancing viewpoint</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/06/10/revisiting-bachs-air-on-g-string-from-a-singing-and-dancing-viewpoint/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jun 2015 23:46:26 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/06/10/revisiting-bachs-air-on-g-string-from-a-singing-and-dancing-viewpoint/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Three years ago, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/14/passion-of-bachs-air-on-the-g-string-three-different-interpretations/&#34;&gt;I wrote a post comparing three very different
performance styles&lt;/a&gt;
for Johann Sebastian Bach&amp;rsquo;s famous music,
&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Air_on_the_G_String&#34;&gt;Air on G String&lt;/a&gt;
and indicating which I preferred.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have received an unexpected number comments over the years, and
thought it was time to write an update of my thoughts in response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Primarily, I am responding to those who (correctly) criticized the
unfortunately chosen exemplar of the style that I preferred. I tried
to find better versions that might illustrate my perceptions. I also
integrated some thoughts based on how I perceive music as a singer and
as a dancer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;better-than-the-rushed-croatian-baroque-ensemble-s-performance&#34;&gt;Better than the rushed Croatian Baroque Ensemble&amp;rsquo;s performance?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I agreed quickly with the first commenters that the Croatian
ensemble&amp;rsquo;s performance was too perfunctory, even downright brutal and
unpleasant in various ways. I wish I had
chosen a better example of what I actually &lt;em&gt;like&lt;/em&gt; rather than &lt;em&gt;prefer
to the other two versions&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I searched YouTube for period-style performances that are
closer to what I envision than either the Croatian ensemble&amp;rsquo;s or
Koopman&amp;rsquo;s. It proved impossible for me to find a perfect performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-period-performance-i-like-more-christopher-hogwood&#34;&gt;A period performance I like more: Christopher Hogwood&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like this version by the late &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christopher_Hogwood&#34;&gt;Christopher Hogwood&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s Academy of
Ancient Music:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/nrtdhH8_47k&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a sweetness and &lt;em&gt;bouncy lightness&lt;/em&gt; to this version that I
like, but it is also somewhat anemic. Personally, I would play up more
contrast and fullness of sound and passion, but the overall tempo and
breathing to this version seems right to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;voices-of-music-richer-sound&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Voices of Music&amp;rdquo;: richer sound&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Voices of Music&amp;rdquo; here in a good performance:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/pzlw6fUux4o&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like the richness of sound in this performance. I miss the lighter,
more bouncy feeling that Hogwood brought out though. This performance
is a bit too legato for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;i-care-about-singing&#34;&gt;I care about singing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I approach this music from the viewpoint of singing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bouncy lightness is very important to me, along with the rhythmic
characterization. I feel this music as a song (it is an &amp;ldquo;air&amp;rdquo;, after
all), and I cannot help singing along when I hear it. Therefore, when
it&amp;rsquo;s taken too slow for me to sing and make it to natural breathing
points in phrases, that considerably lessens my pleasure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;yehudi-menuhin-solo-violin&#34;&gt;Yehudi Menuhin, solo violin&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s an interesting old black and white video of a performance by a young Yehudi Menuhin on violin with
accompaniment. It&amp;rsquo;s not a period performance, but moves along at a
decent &amp;ldquo;singing&amp;rdquo; tempo, as befits violin, that singing instrument.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34;
src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/08bDiKXW0gg&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;
allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I confess that I rather like this performance for its virtues,
although it distorts Bach&amp;rsquo;s music by so emphasizing just the musical
line, at the expense of the balance of the other voices and the
essential character of the dissonances among the voices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;more-menuhin-but-as-conductor&#34;&gt;More Menuhin, but as conductor&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s Yehudi Menuhin not as violin soloist but as conductor of the
Bath Festival Orchestra in 1960. Again, not a period performance, but
he takes the music briskly, and has the violins create sufficient
phrase delineations that I feel the music alertly as though it sings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s direct and clear, maybe not the most subtle and warm,
but I like it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/kaBAE4stNIo&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;dancing-is-possible-too&#34;&gt;Dancing is possible too&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also like to dance to expressive music. A pioneer of modern dance,
Doris Humphrey, famously choreographed a dance to a slowish
performance of this music:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/NjwJyaSIRqY&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not how I would dance to it, because I feel the music
differently. Surprisingly, I could find few examples on YouTube of
dancing to this music. I may consider choreographing a dance myself as
a project to express my own personal vision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing I would like to mention is that I feel that the &lt;em&gt;walking bass&lt;/em&gt;
is very important in this music and gives it the impetus. When played
too slow, the walking bass no longer feels like it&amp;rsquo;s walking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel this music in my legs, not just in my lungs. Yes, I have
actually hummed it to myself while walking in time to the bass
leisurely in the local park. There is a limit to how &amp;ldquo;leisurely&amp;rdquo; I can
walk without feeling frustrated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;ice-dancing&#34;&gt;Ice dancing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found this somewhat frenetic but nevertheless beautiful ice dancing
performance from the 1992 World Figure Skating Championships:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/1JjbwtM_E3g&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;recorder-quartet&#34;&gt;Recorder quartet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A final performance to enjoy: the Japanese &amp;ldquo;Sekishi Recorder Quartet&amp;rdquo;
playing their hearts out in 2009. I think it&amp;rsquo;s lovely: impeccable
phrasing, transparency,
and rich ensemble balance and tone. (As a twist, the melody line performer adds
his own ornamentations.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/pRRRK0UClNs&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was inspired by the accumulated comments on my previous post on
Bach&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Air on G String&amp;rdquo; that I decided to flesh out my thoughts by
using more example performances, as well as relate the orchestral
music to singing and dancing. I hope you have enjoyed these
explorations. There is no single &amp;ldquo;right&amp;rdquo; way to experience music, but
I wanted to share how I experience it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;ve read my previous post, does this one help clarify where
  I&amp;rsquo;m coming from with my musical values? Do you dance
  or sing? Does this affect how you perceive this piece of music and
  like to perform it or hear it performed?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My third year of celebrating Johann Sebastian Bach&#39;s birthday: who was this guy anyway?</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/03/31/my-third-year-of-celebrating-johann-sebastian-bachs-birthday-who-was-this-guy-anyway/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Mar 2014 21:23:31 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/03/31/my-third-year-of-celebrating-johann-sebastian-bachs-birthday-who-was-this-guy-anyway/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is my third year of celebrating the birthday of Johann Sebastian Bach. I did this &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/21/flute-update-celebrating-bachs-birthday/&#34;&gt;in 2012&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/21/my-second-year-of-celebrating-johann-sebastian-bachs-birthday/&#34;&gt;in 2013&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first year, I consciously chose to play some of his music rather than read about it (or about his life). The second year, I played some more of his music, on flute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year, I did something different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, I learned that I had gotten his birthday &amp;ldquo;wrong&amp;rdquo; in the past two years! This year I decided to celebrate the actual birthday (in terms of passing of time) rather than his birth date (which was March 21 according to the old Julian calendar). A minor detail, but symbolic of my intention.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/bach-gardiner.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Bobblehead and Gardiner&amp;#39;s book about J S Bach&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This photo is of &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/20/my-first-bobblehead-doll-guess-who/&#34;&gt;my Bach bobblehead&lt;/a&gt; next to a new book about Bach by John Eliot Gardiner that I just got out of the Carnegie Library today; I had decided that for this year, I would learn more about Bach, the man.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-brand-new-book-about-johann-sebastian-bach&#34;&gt;A brand new book about Johann Sebastian Bach&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A couple of months ago, I came across an interview &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.npr.org/blogs/deceptivecadence/2013/10/25/240780499/bach-unwigged-the-man-behind-the-music&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Bach unwigged: the man behind the music&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; with &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Eliot_Gardiner&#34;&gt;John Eliot Gardiner&lt;/a&gt;, who had finally come out with his long-awaited book about Johann Sebastian Bach, &amp;ldquo;Bach: Music in the Castle of Heaven&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Gardiner has been one of my favorite conductors for a quarter of a century; some of the very first CDs I bought in the late 1980s and early 1990s were of his recordings of Mozart&amp;rsquo;s music with the English Baroque Soloists; I still have them.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I learned that Gardiner tried to get inside the mind of Bach, through his music as well as texts, exploring the possible contradictions within them, and what that might mean about Bach&amp;rsquo;s inner thoughts and feelings about things. Obviously, this is a somewhat subjective exercise, but definitely an intriguing one. Also, Gardiner examined facts about Bach&amp;rsquo;s actual life, including arguments and disputes with authorities, and his basically crazy busy existence in all his professional and personal roles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I saw that interview transcript, I was a little curious, but not enough to rush out and get the book. But then I kept on seeing links to reviews of the book, and most recently, last month, after reading &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nybooks.com/articles/archives/2014/feb/20/why-bach-moves-us/&#34;&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt;, I thought, hmm, maybe sensationalist, but maybe worth checking out: Bach as &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;reformed teenage thug&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo;?!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I put the book on hold at the Carnegie Library and picked it up today. I haven&amp;rsquo;t started reading it yet, but&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;bach-a-passionate-life-a-bbc-documentary-free-to-watch-online&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Bach: A Passionate Life&amp;rdquo;, a BBC documentary (free to watch online)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started with a &amp;ldquo;shortcut&amp;rdquo; to the book: I found a documentary online that Gardiner was involved in. It&amp;rsquo;s still quite long (an hour and a half), but at least you get to see scenery, see musical excerpts being performed, and it&amp;rsquo;s not a 600-page book!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/SOO8IC8_VaY&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;playing-his-music&#34;&gt;Playing his music&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, I had to play some of his music to celebrate also. I pulled out my flute and ran some of his flute sonatas&amp;rsquo; movements along with keyboard backing tracks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-favorite-musical-selection-to-end-the-day-chaconne-from-partita-for-violin-no-2-http-en-wikipedia-org-wiki-partita-for-violin-no-2-28bach-29&#34;&gt;A favorite musical selection to end the day: &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Partita_for_Violin_No._2_%28Bach%29&#34;&gt;Chaconne from partita for violin no. 2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe one day I&amp;rsquo;ll write more about Bach&amp;rsquo;s Chaconne, but for today all I will say is, this is my favorite music of all time of any kind, and what I would hope to leave this world with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And here is my favorite performance, by the wonderful violinist &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gidon_Kremer&#34;&gt;Gidon Kremer&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s way intense:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/DBJPVnJ8m-Y&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m generally more interested in the artistic output of people rather than their life stories, but thanks to the positive and somewhat sensationalist coverage of Gardiner&amp;rsquo;s new book, I took the bait!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thoughts on attending the Duquesne Young Artist Performance Awards Winners Showcase</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/03/08/thoughts-on-attending-the-duquesne-young-artist-performance-awards-winners-showcase/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Mar 2014 17:01:35 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/03/08/thoughts-on-attending-the-duquesne-young-artist-performance-awards-winners-showcase/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that a ten-year-old boy I currently give private chess lessons to is also passionate about music, and his piano teacher had him submit a recording for the annual &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cmcpgh.org/competitions/performanceAwards.aspx&#34;&gt;Duquesne Young Artist Performance Awards&lt;/a&gt; competition, and his entry happened to be one of the around thirty chosen, ranging from ages 7-16, so he gave a performance at the Winners Showcase at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.duq.edu/academics/schools/music/facilities/pnc-recital-hall&#34;&gt;PNC Recital Hall&lt;/a&gt; of the Mary Papper School of Music of Duquesne University.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d seen him perform informally before, but was curious to see him on stage, and also to see other kids and where they were in their musical development and personal style, so I told his parents that I was going to attend to watch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d never been to an event like this before, a gathering of kids who had proven at least some level of ability by winning an award. I&amp;rsquo;m a latecomer to classical music, not having had much to do with it until I went to college. My younger sister did take up violin in junior high school and I went one or two of her performances with my parents, but to be frank, I was not very interested in or understanding of classical music then, so I remember almost nothing of what happened and must have snored through; all I really remember is &amp;ldquo;Please let this be over&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The young performers collectively actually played a decent variety of music of different eras and styles. The selections were mostly quite short, as they had to be of course because there were about thirty performers to go through in the space of less than two hours. One came up after another, with no break. It was pretty intense, actually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed getting a taste of what all these different kids had to offer musically, and I hope it was a positive experience for all of them. There was a lot of nervousness on display, but also some really touching resolve and mature calmness as well. I was happy to see my chess student get up there and play that grand piano with flair.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;reception&#34;&gt;Reception&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Afterwards, cookies at a reception. I was hungry. I could not &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/01/16/a-system-for-quitting-eating-cookies/&#34;&gt;resist&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/cookies-2014-03-08/cupcake.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/cookies-2014-03-08/cookie.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Chamber music concert at CMU featured Bach&#39;s Goldberg Variations arranged for string trio</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/11/19/chamber-music-concert-at-cmu-featured-bachs-goldberg-variations-arranged-for-string-trio/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Nov 2013 23:04:37 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/11/19/chamber-music-concert-at-cmu-featured-bachs-goldberg-variations-arranged-for-string-trio/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.cmu.edu/news/stories/archives/2013/november/images/chamber-recital_400x340.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;David Harding, Noah Bendix-Balgley, Lorna McGhee, Amit Peled&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I attended a special &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cmu.edu/news/stories/archives/2013/november/nov8_chambermusic.html&#34;&gt;chamber music concert at CMU&lt;/a&gt; that featured some truly excellent musicians.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-musicians&#34;&gt;The musicians&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was particularly interested in seeing &lt;a href=&#34;http://trioverlaine.com/bios/lorna-mcghee/&#34;&gt;Lorna McGhee&lt;/a&gt;, the current principal flute of the Pittsburgh Symphony Orchestra, and violinist &lt;a href=&#34;http://noahbendixbalgley.com/&#34;&gt;Noah Bendix-Balgley&lt;/a&gt;, the concertmaster, both of whom are relatively recent additions to the orchestra. The other two musicians, also fantastic, were violist and CMU professor &lt;a href=&#34;http://trioverlaine.com/bios/david-harding/&#34;&gt;David Harding&lt;/a&gt; and cellist &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amitpeled.com/&#34;&gt;Amit Peled&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;mozart-s-flute-quartet-no-1-in-d-major&#34;&gt;Mozart&amp;rsquo;s flute quartet no. 1 in D major&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lorna McGhee played in the first part of the program, which was Mozart&amp;rsquo;s first flute quartet. I was very curious how she would approach the work, because I&amp;rsquo;m very picky nowadays about the performance of music from the 18th century or earlier, which I far prefer to be both on period instruments and in period style. The typical &amp;ldquo;modern&amp;rdquo; performance I can no longer enjoy, because of stylistic anachronisms that in my mind invalidate the beauty and freshness of early music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed the quartet&amp;rsquo;s performance of the Mozart. The playing was crisp, lively, and transparent. There was little to quibble with in Lorna McGhee&amp;rsquo;s performance: she played with verve, sensitivity, and clarity. In some phrases she held a legato longer than I would like, but overall I quite liked the performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;bach-s-goldberg-variations-arranged-for-string-trio-by-dmitry-sitkovetsky&#34;&gt;Bach&amp;rsquo;s Goldberg Variations arranged for string trio by Dmitry Sitkovetsky&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bulk of the program was devoted to a performance by the string trio of the entire Goldberg Variations by Bach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past quarter century, I&amp;rsquo;ve listened to countless performances of the Goldberg Variations on all kinds of keyboard instrument, including harpsichord, fortepiano, and modern piano, but until tonight, I hadn&amp;rsquo;t bothered listening to Sitkovetsky&amp;rsquo;s arrangement for string trio that came out several years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought it worked out pretty well tonight, with the three string players working really hard to create dynamism and contrast along with unity in this monumental work. I couldn&amp;rsquo;t help but think that it&amp;rsquo;s actually harder to pull off as a trio than as a solo keyboard piece. What was particularly interesting was visually seeing and hearing (in the different tonal qualities) all the different voices in the music. They are there in the original version, of course, but experiencing the spatial separation just made me even more amazed by Bach&amp;rsquo;s creation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I appreciate the time the four musicians took to perform in this chamber music recital free to the public, and thank you, CMU, for bringing them in for these invigorating performances of Mozart and Bach!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Playing violin music on flute</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/05/03/playing-violin-music-on-flute/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 May 2013 23:32:33 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/05/03/playing-violin-music-on-flute/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I enjoyed another party at Henry&amp;rsquo;s. I have been very tired leading up to the Pittsburgh Marathon to run on Sunday. I took the day off from work as planned in order to get more reset, and picked up my race packet at the Expo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t play all that much music at the party, but the highlight for me was playing Fritz Kreisler&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alt-Wiener_Tanzweisen&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Liebesleid&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; on flute with Henry accompanying on piano. I totally love this little piece that Kreisler wrote for violin, and I enjoy making it work on flute. We were just having fun at the party, but eventually I want to make a real performance out of it, and record it myself, because I have &lt;em&gt;very strong&lt;/em&gt; ideas on how to play it to express what I feel in the music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;some-existing-performances-on-violin&#34;&gt;Some existing performances on violin&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;fritz-kreisler-himself&#34;&gt;Fritz Kreisler himself&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is Kreisler performing his own piece:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/AqQ2_2qd-5Y&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s a fine performance, but ironically, not actually my favorite!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;david-oistrakh&#34;&gt;David Oistrakh&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an interesting interpretation. It is still not as free as I like, but it is elegant and subtle in its expression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/x78axkl1q38&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;itzhak-perlman&#34;&gt;Itzhak Perlman&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A romantic rendition with great elements, but too fast and tight, not meditative enough, so overall it leaves me disappointed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/hJEkEL6Obzk&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;joshua-bell&#34;&gt;Joshua Bell&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a modern performance by Joshua Bell. This is an example of a performance that I &lt;em&gt;don&amp;rsquo;t like at all&lt;/em&gt;, being very square and without a lilt and freedom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/6jk16b9pvXY&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;ryu-goto&#34;&gt;Ryu Goto&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A fine performance I would put into the category of elegant and subtle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/DsSii7yDzi0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;katica-illenyi&#34;&gt;Katica Illenyi&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now this, I really love: a performance of extreme detail and personal expression. One of the most beautiful performances I have encountered!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/D0_hqoX-uXQ&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;gidon-kremer-with-martha-argerich&#34;&gt;Gidon Kremer with Martha Argerich&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My favorite performance is actually this unusual one of very extreme emotional expression. Note how Kremer stretches out time and also accelerates with many tempo changes (finely covered by Argerich, of course). He takes the dynamics down to an extreme, and varies his vibrato. He plays this piece as a deep story of love rather than just a lighthearted one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/dOr5mofvjsA&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;performances-on-flute&#34;&gt;Performances on flute&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the performances I found on YouTube with flute were really, really bad. Here are some of the exceptions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;unji-chung&#34;&gt;Unji Chung&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Very emotional reading. A good performance, but maybe too extroverted for my taste, too driving and with an over-powerful vibrato.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/BnsH-BvFRo4&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;oksana-sinkova&#34;&gt;Oksana Sinkova&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Expressive phrasing, coloring, tone, and deeply felt. She appears to be playing a wooden flute. Enchanting!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/UQmZMJZcAx4&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Music I just played for the first time: recorder sonata, tangos</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/01/26/music-i-just-played-for-the-first-time-recorder-sonata-tangos/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Jan 2013 23:03:10 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/01/26/music-i-just-played-for-the-first-time-recorder-sonata-tangos/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Abby and I went to Henry&amp;rsquo;s birthday party, marking an important anniversary: we attended his birthday party for the first time a year ago, and that began &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/01/27/a-new-friends-very-musical-birthday-party-changed-my-life/&#34;&gt;one of the most important developments in my entire life, my decision to make music playing an integral part of my life&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of music happened, as usual, and this time, unlike a year ago, I played. What a year it&amp;rsquo;s been!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;handel-s-recorder-sonata-in-g-minor&#34;&gt;Handel&amp;rsquo;s recorder sonata in G minor&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided to finally give a shot at playing, for the first time outside of home, &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Recorder_sonata_in_G_minor_%28HWV_360%29&#34;&gt;Handel&amp;rsquo;s recorder sonata in G minor, op. 1 no. 2&lt;/a&gt;, me being on alto recorder and Henry on piano.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This piece is extremely special to me, because I discovered it by accident as one of the first &amp;ldquo;real&amp;rdquo; recorder pieces that I started working on when I was just a beginner at recorder. A method book I was using at the time, one and half years ago, in May 2011, by Mario Duschenes, had a section with the title &amp;ldquo;How to practise a difficult piece&amp;rdquo;, and the example and suggestions on practice was the Andante from this recorder sonata by Handel. I hunted down the complete score of the recorder sonata and started to learn the whole thing. I did this intermittently over the course of a year or so while doing other things, but always had the intention of at some point polishing it up for actual performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main holdup eventually was that I wanted to be able to really express myself well, and incorporate my own ornamentations. To this end, I made some study of Baroque ornamentation and checked out a book I found in the library, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.oup.com/us/catalog/general/subject/Music/PerformanceStudiesAppliedMusic/WindsBrass/?view=usa&amp;amp;ci=9780198790013&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Playing Recorder Sonatas&amp;rdquo;, by Anthony Rowland-Jones&lt;/a&gt;. I have found this book quite useful as a guide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I had fun reading through this with Henry. Eventually I want to play it for real, as performance, in a setting with harpsichord continuo, rather than with piano.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-02-23&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-02-23)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ended up performing the recorder sonata with bass recorder accompaniment at the Pittsburgh Recorder Society&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/02/23/celebrating-two-years-of-playing-recorder/&#34;&gt;Midwinter Musical Feast&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;bach-s-flute-sonata-in-e-minor-bwv-1034&#34;&gt;Bach&amp;rsquo;s flute sonata in E minor, BWV 1034&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I played music by Johann Sebastian Bach on flute for the first time outside the home. I&amp;rsquo;ve held back because I feel like I&amp;rsquo;m still not doing the music justice, but decided I can&amp;rsquo;t hide forever my love of Bach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On modern flute with Henry on piano, I played the first movement of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sonata_in_E_minor_for_flute_or_recorder_and_basso_continuo&#34;&gt;Bach&amp;rsquo;s flute sonata in E minor&lt;/a&gt;. I would have considered playing it on Baroque flute, but the piano as well as the the party environment &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/21/my-first-time-singing-bossa-nova-also-a-temporary-farewell-to-baroque-flute/&#34;&gt;is not friendly for Baroque flute&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-03-21&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-03-21)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Bach&amp;rsquo;s birthday in 2013, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/21/my-second-year-of-celebrating-johann-sebastian-bachs-birthday/&#34;&gt;I reflected on&lt;/a&gt; how the very same recorder method book by Duschenes I mentioned above was the impetus for my getting into Bach flute sonatas!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;tangos&#34;&gt;Tangos&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I played tango on flute for the first time ever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/11/17/a-childhood-dream-come-true-i-am-now-finally-singing-for-real/&#34;&gt;sing tango for the first time recently&lt;/a&gt;, and also played &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/22/playing-tango-on-melodica-and-singing-christmas-carols/&#34;&gt;tango on melodica for the first time&lt;/a&gt;, but had not yet dared to play on flute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, I did, and not only that, one of them ended up becoming a flute-violin duet, in which Barbara (whom I met exactly a year ago at the last birthday party) played violin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story is that several months ago, in October, I got hold of a book of tangos for violin duet. I judged that with some modifications I could play the first part on flute, if only I could simultaneously find someone on violin (and someone on piano). The opportunity did not spontaneously arise until today!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, I played &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/El_Choclo&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;El Choclo&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; with just Henry on piano.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then Barbara joined in on violin and we played &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Por_una_Cabeza&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Por una Cabeza&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; with Henry. This was one of the most satisfying experiences of my life. It&amp;rsquo;s one thing playing duets with Henry, but it&amp;rsquo;s another having three to really fill in the harmonies and textures and two melodic voices playing off each other. Wow. I need to do this more often. And I have to confess, I never tire of this particular classic tango, because it&amp;rsquo;s so dramatic and expressive, and has that suddenly shift from major to the lyrical chorus in minor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;more-bach-double-violin-concerto&#34;&gt;More Bach: double violin concerto&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Barbara was so excited that she goaded me into trying to sight read &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Concerto_for_Two_Violins_%28Bach%29&#34;&gt;Bach&amp;rsquo;s double violin concerto&lt;/a&gt; on the spot together with Henry. I knew I was probably going to cause a minor disaster, but heck, it&amp;rsquo;s a party, we&amp;rsquo;re just having fun. And indeed, I got confused or lost many times, because first of all, I&amp;rsquo;m not so great on flute right now at all, and second, this music was for violin and some stuff was not very suitable for flute and also needed me to go up an octave all of a sudden because the violin has a bigger range. So, it was a struggle for me, but I enjoyed some nice moments in the less frantic slow movement, where the two melodic voices really combine beautifully.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, it was all in fun, Bach forgive me!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As at all of Henry&amp;rsquo;s parties, I strive to go to them prepared to do something better and new and interesting musically, for our enjoyment as well as that of the other guests. I had a great time again. I am so grateful for the past year of getting to know Henry and his sharing the gift of music with me!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ignoring branding: the double-blind test</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/01/03/ignoring-branding-the-double-blind-test/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jan 2012 06:49:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/01/03/ignoring-branding-the-double-blind-test/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;What is &amp;ldquo;really&amp;rdquo; the difference in quality between cheap and expensive wines, restaurants, hotels, medications, jeans, stereo equipment, computer software, etc? I&amp;rsquo;ve always been fascinated by this question, because I enjoy quality but do not enjoy paying top dollar needlessly, and am aware that price does not necessarily correlate with quality. In particular, brand names and other marketing tricks easily imbue a product or service with an artificial aura specifically for the purpose of luring consumers toward it, away from a practically similar competitors&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do the differences exist, do they matter, and what can we learn from the results of double-blind tests?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-to-act-when-there-are-differences&#34;&gt;How to act when there are differences&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not denying that there exist differences, or that sometimes it takes a real connoisseur to notice or appreciate the differences between, say, something of &amp;ldquo;high&amp;rdquo; quality (at 90th percentile, say) rather than of &amp;ldquo;extremely high&amp;rdquo; quality (at 99th percentile, say). But even if I notice a difference, I may not want to pay the price to get the higher quality. Suppose I could buy audio speakers for $50 that to me sounded 90th percentile, and I could get another set for $5000 that to me sounded 99th percentile. I would buy the $50 speakers. On the other hand, suppose I could buy running shoes for $50 that are 90th percentile, or shoes for $200 for 99th percentile. I would not hesitate to get the $200 shoes, because of the importance in my everyday quality of life in maximizing my running experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;coca-cola-and-pepsi-and-experts&#34;&gt;Coca-Cola and Pepsi and experts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lately there has been a lot of interest in objective &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blind_experiment&#34;&gt;tests&lt;/a&gt; to determine whether people can actually tell the difference between wines, soft drinks, medication, musical performers, etc. Probably the most famous in the past decade has been the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pepsi_Challenge&#34;&gt;Coca-Cola versus Pepsi&lt;/a&gt; soft drink wars. We all know the results: when taste tests were blind, people had different preferences than when not blind. This shows the power of advertising to influence our perceptions and preferences. And most recently, we&amp;rsquo;ve all been hearing about how people cannot tell the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wine_tasting#Blind_tasting&#34;&gt;difference between cheap wines and expensive wines&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When first hearing about these results, a lot of people get very angry and defensive, because of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cognitive_dissonance&#34;&gt;cognitive dissonance&lt;/a&gt;. One objection they sometimes raise (without even reading the details of the tests) is that yes, some undiscerning individuals might have been fooled, but real &amp;ldquo;experts&amp;rdquo; would not be (and by implication, they view themselves as real experts, in accordance with the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lake_Wobegon#The_Lake_Wobegon_effect&#34;&gt;Lake Wobegon effect&lt;/a&gt;). But in fact, these tests are done with experts as well as novices, and sometimes the experts even do worse than novices (this effect calls for its own blog post entirely).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-placebo-effect&#34;&gt;The placebo effect&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These matters are not just trivia for amusement. For example, it is an industry secret that the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Placebo&#34;&gt;placebo effect&lt;/a&gt; when it comes to medication is extremely strong, and even &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wired.com/medtech/drugs/magazine/17-09/ff_placebo_effect?currentPage=all&#34;&gt;getting stronger&lt;/a&gt;. There is controversy over the use or non-use of placebos in medical care. Let&amp;rsquo;s face it, medical patients are often very overbearing and demand medication from their physicians, who often give them some placebo to satisfy them. Since this actually &amp;ldquo;works&amp;rdquo;, is it wrong for doctors to lie to their patients (who seem to inadvertently create the incentive for such lies)?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the area of music, some years ago there was a big flap over a fraud of a classical pianist that went undetected for a long time: an aging &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joyce_Hatto&#34;&gt;Joyce Hatto&lt;/a&gt; passed off recorded performances of obscure pianists as her own, and became lauded for the revival of her recording career. Let&amp;rsquo;s face it: people like a heartwarming &amp;ldquo;human interest&amp;rdquo; story. We love stories about old pianists or athletes making a comeback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;can-you-identify-the-stradivarius&#34;&gt;Can you identify the Stradivarius?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I saw an article about a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.npr.org/blogs/deceptivecadence/2012/01/02/144482863/double-blind-violin-test-can-you-pick-the-strad?sc=fb&amp;amp;cc=fp&#34;&gt;double-blind violin test&lt;/a&gt; in which listeners heard a segment of music performed on two different violins and were asked to identify the Stradivarius. Apparently people did poorly, including expert violinists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article has already attracted over a hundred comments since yesterday, testifying to the interest people have in questions of branding and quality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;my-experience-with-the-test&#34;&gt;My experience with the test&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not a violinist. Although I would like to learn the violin sometime, I have never handled one. Furthermore, although I have listened to quite a lot of violin playing, I have never been interested in the Stradivarius story or mystique (or that of competing vintage violins). To put it bluntly: I don&amp;rsquo;t actually know what a Stradivarius sounds like. When I listen to a CD or go to a concert and hear a violin concerto or something, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/11/on-not-reading-concert-program-notes/&#34;&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t read the program notes&lt;/a&gt;, and therefore I have no idea what kind of violin someone is playing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got the correct answer in the listening test.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What does that even mean, though, given that I don&amp;rsquo;t know what a Stradivarius sounds like and don&amp;rsquo;t really care?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The two violin tracks sounded quite different to me. The best I could do was choose which one I liked better. If it wasn&amp;rsquo;t the Stradivarius, no big deal; if it was, no big deal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One violin sounded rough and raspy, and the other one was smooth. That&amp;rsquo;s all I could go on. I don&amp;rsquo;t know if a rough or smooth sound is actually considered desirable by aficionados. I don&amp;rsquo;t know what the Stradivarius is supposed to sound like. And who knows whether the violinist just happened to be doing very different things physically on the two tracks presented? It would have been better if there had been more samples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;deliberate-ignorance&#34;&gt;Deliberate ignorance?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to shield myself from what I consider extraneous noise, sometimes I enjoy deliberately being ignorant. Much of the music I like, I originally encountered without knowing its composer, performer, or title. I don&amp;rsquo;t really care if something was written by Mozart or whether he plagiarized it from someone else. If it is interesting, that&amp;rsquo;s fine, and if not, that&amp;rsquo;s also fine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recognize the virtues of tradition, of authority, but the branding effect privileges the old over the new in ways that the old probably would not have enjoyed. There is no way Mozart would have enjoyed having his early childhood music all collected and recorded as though it were as valuable as his later masterpieces. Unpublished drafts by dead novelists get more attention than published work by new writers. Nostalgia for the old, in the name of &amp;ldquo;authenticity&amp;rdquo;, always sells well. Older religions get more respect than newer ones, which get called cults for a while just because they are newer. Older political parties attract a following because of their branding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are not as clever or discerning as we tend to think we are, and are influenced in our perceptions and decision making by branding, sentimentality, framing, contexts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still, we can&amp;rsquo;t live without shortcuts for quality and consistency. It&amp;rsquo;s not possible to spend vast amounts of time doing one&amp;rsquo;s own blind tests on everything, and it&amp;rsquo;s not worth it either. We are human and should respect our limitations and imperfections. Humility and respect is the best we can do. Therefore, I don&amp;rsquo;t make fun of those who are &amp;ldquo;tricked&amp;rdquo; in double-blind tests. That&amp;rsquo;s us, that&amp;rsquo;s me, in some context or other.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>