<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Pittsburgh Recorder Society on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/pittsburgh-recorder-society/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Pittsburgh Recorder Society on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/pittsburgh-recorder-society/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Pittsburgh Recorder Society: discovering the beauty of Alonso Lobo</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/05/18/pittsburgh-recorder-society-discovering-the-beauty-of-alonso-lobo/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 May 2014 17:48:23 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/05/18/pittsburgh-recorder-society-discovering-the-beauty-of-alonso-lobo/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We had another great turnout for the monthly meeting of the Pittsburgh Recorder Society. We got another new member, Joanna. I counted fifteen of us, total.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-recorder-society-2014-05-18/group.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Today, the highlight for me was discovering some music I don&amp;rsquo;t remember encountering before, by &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alonso_Lobo&#34;&gt;Alonso Lobo&lt;/a&gt;, who lived roughly 1555-1617. Fred passed out parts for his &amp;ldquo;Versa est in luctum&amp;rdquo;, a sacred motet for voice (which we are playing as a recorder ensemble instead).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This music is beautiful and new to me, and Fred provided instructive interpretive guidance I will discuss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d never heard of Lobo before (outside of recorder playing, I simply have very little knowledge of early pre-Baroque music) and had to look up Lobo after the meeting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;versa-est-in-luctum-by-alonso-lobo&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Versa est in luctum&amp;rdquo; by Alonso Lobo&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is passionate funeral music, written for a Spanish king&amp;rsquo;s funeral. I found an interesting &lt;a href=&#34;http://luiscfhenriques.com/alonso-lobos-versa-est-in-luctum/&#34;&gt;musicologist&amp;rsquo;s blog post about the work&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;English translation printed on our recorder arrangement parts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
My harp is turned to mourning and my music into the voice of those that weep.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fred put me on the alto 1 part. After some work on the piece, he called for those of us on alto 1 (there was at least one other person, but possibly no more, of us fifteen) to play louder, with more emotion, to really ring out. I had held back in part because I was afraid of going sharp if I blowed harder, but also in part because for other music we&amp;rsquo;ve been playing, I&amp;rsquo;ve been focusing on blending in playing tenor parts. I sometimes somehow get into a rut and &amp;ldquo;forget&amp;rdquo; the importance or impact of carrying the top line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fred was actually singing along quite expressively as he conducted us. It&amp;rsquo;s inspirational to me that we have a leader who so believes in the music he has us play, and seeks to help us bring out its essence. The interesting thing about this piece is that there are phrases of longer notes as well as those that are more agitated, with faster movement. So there is a lot of beautiful interplay and contrast among the voices as well as within their own span throughout the piece. Fred advised on providing separation at the end of phrases so that they can be heard better in contrast against other voices as they enter and leave in different places.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, the other first alto(s) and I did play more confidently and louder, as did the rest of the ensemble, and when we did that, it was an amazing feeling, the sense of filling the air and resonating. I live for experiences like this! Let&amp;rsquo;s keep it up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;a-performance-for-choir-you-should-check-out&#34;&gt;A performance for choir you should check out&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For reference, here is a fine performance by the Gabrieli Consort I discovered:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/yZe16Mpsmg8&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;group-recording-from-before&#34;&gt;Group recording from before&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fred brought in a little boombox so we could hear the recording he had made earlier of us playing &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/03/16/pittsburgh-recorder-society-something-new-recently-recording-our-practice-sessions/&#34;&gt;two months ago&lt;/a&gt;. We didn&amp;rsquo;t sound terrible, actually!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-recorder-society-2014-05-18/recording.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;snacks&#34;&gt;Snacks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ate three cookies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-recorder-society-2014-05-18/cookie1.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-recorder-society-2014-05-18/cookie2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-recorder-society-2014-05-18/cookie3.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In retrospect, I should not have eaten three cookies. Maybe two, or maybe one. I know, I made this observation &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/04/27/pittsburgh-recorder-society-palestrina-gombert-and-dolly-parton-cookies/&#34;&gt;last month&lt;/a&gt;. This time, I&amp;rsquo;m serious. Next meeting, I will eat no more than &lt;em&gt;two&lt;/em&gt; cookies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed being shown yet another beautiful piece of music and getting the opportunity to play it with others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How often do you discover beautiful music you have never heard before, through being given it to play? Is this experience different than just hearing it without playing it?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pittsburgh Recorder Society: Palestrina, Gombert, and Dolly Parton cookies</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/04/27/pittsburgh-recorder-society-palestrina-gombert-and-dolly-parton-cookies/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Apr 2014 17:47:27 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/04/27/pittsburgh-recorder-society-palestrina-gombert-and-dolly-parton-cookies/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We had a great turnout again for the monthly meeting of the Pittsburgh Recorder Society. We even got an enthusiastic new member, Andriy. There were around fifteen of us, total; we really filled the room!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our director Fred was inspirational again, encouraging and helping us to continue to refine our sound, our unity, our expression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every month, attending the Sunday recorder meeting is truly one of the things I look forward to most in life! Sometimes I feel emotionally naked and a bit anxious in our meetings, but I know that this is a safe place to grow and to contribute. Today was one of those days in which I really felt challenged to do my very best to make music together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;kyrie-of-the-missa-papae-marcelli-by-palestrina-revisited&#34;&gt;Kyrie of the &amp;ldquo;Missa Papae Marcelli&amp;rdquo; by Palestrina, revisited&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/16/excited-by-the-new-season-of-the-pittsburgh-recorder-society/&#34;&gt;Well over a year ago&lt;/a&gt;, we had begun work on a recorder ensemble arrangement of Palestrina&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Kyrie de la &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Missa_Papae_Marcelli&#34;&gt;Missa Papae Marcelli&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;, but had actually not picked up much on that, so I was delighted that Fred decided (especially now that we have more members) to start on this piece again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got a tenor 2 part and was happy to do my best to produce a rich inner voice blending it into the ensemble&amp;rsquo;s tapestry of sound. Fred emphasized that the original music did not have bar lines, and that each &amp;ldquo;Kyrie&amp;rdquo; phrase can and does begin on any beat of a &amp;ldquo;measure&amp;rdquo;, so we should focus on keeping the flow going. Of course, this being originally vocal music, I tried to &amp;ldquo;sing&amp;rdquo; on recorder, paying attention to entrances and breath control (I am still unable to last an entire breath in some of these phrases).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;mille-regres-by-nicolas-gombert-http-en-wikipedia-org-wiki-nicolas-gombert&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Mille Regres&amp;rdquo; by &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nicolas_Gombert&#34;&gt;Nicolas Gombert&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also started work on a recorder arrangement of &amp;ldquo;Mille Regres&amp;rdquo; by Nicolas Gombert, originally for voice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fred put me on the alto part and after we started playing, I realized I was the only one on the part, and felt anxious! There was nowhere to hide. It&amp;rsquo;s very different from playing on a tenor or bass part with a bunch of other people, or even when playing a part with just one other person. On the one hand, there is much more freedom, because when a voice is doubled, you have to work with someone to sound like one. Of course, you always have to blend with the rest of the ensemble, regardless, but when you&amp;rsquo;re alone, you realize that you do not have backup for your voice, that you are it. Strong entrances, making the high notes clear and rich, are totally up to you now. It&amp;rsquo;s a great responsibility and opportunity, and I felt myself focusing as deep as I could into every element of the music. After today&amp;rsquo;s first cut, I hope to continue to improve on bringing my part fully to life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a performance of the original music for voice:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/J_2kRgCxeHk&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;mille-regretz-by-josquin-des-prez&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Mille Regretz&amp;rdquo; by Josquin des Prez&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that elements of this music sounded familiar to me, because in fact it is based on the French chanson &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mille_Regretz&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Mille Regretz&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Josquin_des_Prez&#34;&gt;Josquin des Prez&lt;/a&gt;, which I was familiar with because in last year&amp;rsquo;s Mideast early music workshop, I took a voice class in which we performed it. I really enjoyed singing it (as tenor; sorry, I don&amp;rsquo;t know if anyone has a video of our performance at the final student concert).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a nice performance of &amp;ldquo;Mille Regretz&amp;rdquo; with just one singer per part:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/S0TNPoDYHFY&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;another-alto-solo&#34;&gt;Another alto solo&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was another piece we started (but there were not enough scores, so I had to share with Kristel; I need to ask for a copy to be emailed to me, but for now I don&amp;rsquo;t remember the name or composer) in which Fred again put me on a solo part, which was originally marked &amp;ldquo;soprano&amp;rdquo; but after a run through, he told me to read it on alto up an octave.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This assignment made me even more anxious because I actually start out with a full statement of the melody without any accompaniment, before everyone else starts to come in. I&amp;rsquo;m not used to be put on the spot like this. But again, it&amp;rsquo;s a great opportunity to really work on refining my technique and expression, and being aware that I am setting the stage for the whole piece to succeed. Also, it&amp;rsquo;s an upbeat, rhythmic piece rather than a melancholy, lyrical one, so it was great to have the opportunity to portray different moods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;snacks&#34;&gt;Snacks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As usual, people brought in snacks to share for the mid-meeting break.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Helen not only brought in the recipe for her delicious brownies from &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/03/16/pittsburgh-recorder-society-something-new-recently-recording-our-practice-sessions/&#34;&gt;last month&amp;rsquo;s meeting&lt;/a&gt;, but also a new batch of what she called &amp;ldquo;Dolly Parton&amp;rdquo; cookies, incorporating a lot of apple in them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The recipe for last month&amp;rsquo;s brownies:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-recorder-society-2014-04-27/recipe.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I ate three of this month&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Dolly Parton&amp;rdquo; squares:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-recorder-society-2014-04-27/cookie1.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-recorder-society-2014-04-27/cookie2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-recorder-society-2014-04-27/cookie3.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although setting a limit on three was better than no limit at all, after I got home, I did wonder whether maybe I should have limited myself to two; these were quite substantial and filling!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had another intense and joyful musical afternoon with a great group of friendly and fun recorder enthusiasts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is your favorite role when you are on a team? Do you like being a prominent soloist, or do you prefer to blend into the background? Or do you like to switch up your roles? What do you adjust when you switch?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pittsburgh Recorder Society: Something new recently: recording our practice sessions</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/03/16/pittsburgh-recorder-society-something-new-recently-recording-our-practice-sessions/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Mar 2014 18:39:46 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/03/16/pittsburgh-recorder-society-something-new-recently-recording-our-practice-sessions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-recorder-society-2014-03-16/group.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Pittsburgh Recorder Society&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I forgot to mention in my post about &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/02/16/pittsburgh-recorder-society-7-part-gabrieli-and-coconut-chocolate-cookies/&#34;&gt;last month&amp;rsquo;s Pittsburgh Recorder Society&amp;rsquo;s meeting&lt;/a&gt; that Fred has started recording our sessions; he&amp;rsquo;s set up a tripod and an audio recorder. I kind of didn&amp;rsquo;t pay attention because it was not emphasized and nobody talked much about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today was a different story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;recording&#34;&gt;Recording&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was more mention of recording than in the past, and Fred made jokes about checking out what we did and how it would be useful for us to listen and see how we progress. Interestingly, this seemed to have quite an effect on what we did. I definitely felt a lot more serious and alert. Although I already always do take our meetings seriously, I will confess right now that whenever Fred said, &amp;ldquo;OK, now let&amp;rsquo;s do this again, and with recording&amp;rdquo;, I really perked up and gave it my all, trying to play as musically as possible, paying attention to intonation, articulation, ensemble balance, and even that terrible habit many of us have of sucking our recorders after the end of a piece.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fred is right: it doesn&amp;rsquo;t really make sense, &lt;em&gt;logically&lt;/em&gt;, to goof off during rehearsal and then expect to play well in actual performance. In practice, we should do the reverse: play it as well as we can in rehearsal, so that when we perform, which is usually in less than ideal circumstances (anxiety, unusual location or acoustics, or being hectic in getting somewhere, or any number of other unexpected glitches), our performance might be &lt;em&gt;worse&lt;/em&gt; than what we did, but it will still be good. On the other hand, if we don&amp;rsquo;t give it our all in practice, then what miracle can get us even better in performance?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, the recording of our work was not at all some kind of grim task. I enjoyed the additional seriousness and care, and I think we&amp;rsquo;re sounding better and better every month. Amusingly, the most noticeable thing is that when we know we are being recorded, we end pieces much better, and then &lt;em&gt;dead silence&lt;/em&gt;. No rustling, no recorder sucking. Wow. I really enjoy that unity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;tenor-and-bass&#34;&gt;Tenor and bass&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the first recorder meeting in my three years in which I did not play soprano or alto recorder once! I have been much preferring to play tenor and bass, to provide inner or bottom voices, and letting the newer members of the group play the soprano and alto voices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;snacks&#34;&gt;Snacks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People brought in snacks to share, as usual, for the mid-meeting break.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-recorder-society-2014-03-16/snacks.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Snacks&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And of course, this being St. Patrick&amp;rsquo;s Day weekend, Helen had to bring special Irish-themed snacks to share. In addition to Irish cheese, she also brought homemade brownies that she said were from an actual Irish recipe! These were &lt;em&gt;fantastic brownies&lt;/em&gt;: chocolate, cocoa, good stuff. I had to eat them, again and again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In accordance with my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/01/16/a-system-for-quitting-eating-cookies/&#34;&gt;promise about &amp;ldquo;cookies&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, here is a photo of each individual one I ate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-recorder-society-2014-03-16/brownie1.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Brownie 1&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-recorder-society-2014-03-16/brownie2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Brownie 2&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Someone brought in a box of castle cookies. I ate one:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-recorder-society-2014-03-16/castle-cookie.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;While I was packing up to leave, I couldn&amp;rsquo;t resist temptation and ate my third Helen brownie:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-recorder-society-2014-03-16/brownie3.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Brownie 3&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In retrospect, &lt;strong&gt;this was a big mistake&lt;/strong&gt;. After getting home, I felt burdened by this third brownie. I would have been fine just eating the first two and the one cookie (along with some cheese and nuts that I also had).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve noticed that I have a problem when I eat a &amp;ldquo;one more for the road&amp;rdquo; cookie at events. I&amp;rsquo;ve decided to consciously watch out and &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; do that in the future. I should only eat as much as I can handle, and leave it at that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2014-04-27&#34;&gt;(Update of 2014-04-27)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By popular demand, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/04/27/pittsburgh-recorder-society-palestrina-gombert-and-dolly-parton-cookies/&#34;&gt;the following month, Helen brought in the recipe for these brownies&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pittsburgh Recorder Society: 7-part Gabrieli and coconut chocolate cookies</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/02/16/pittsburgh-recorder-society-7-part-gabrieli-and-coconut-chocolate-cookies/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Feb 2014 17:41:04 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/02/16/pittsburgh-recorder-society-7-part-gabrieli-and-coconut-chocolate-cookies/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Because so many people are now regularly attending the Pittsburgh Recorder Society monthly meetings, we have enough critical mass to work on larger ensemble pieces. Fred pulled out a 7-part &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Giovanni_Gabrieli&#34;&gt;Gabrieli&lt;/a&gt; piece for us from the 16th century. Fun! I look forward to continuing working on this in March.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also continued work on other pieces we started earlier in the season. Fred&amp;rsquo;s guidance is as inspiring as ever. I feel that every meeting of our group is a wonderful opportunity to grow as a musician.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After going home I found a trumpet ensemble performance of the Gabrieli online:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/PlfvhJPNuTE&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;snacks&#34;&gt;Snacks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People brought in snacks to share, as usual, for break time.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/recorder-2014-02-16/snacks.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Helen made super-tasty-looking &amp;ldquo;cookies&amp;rdquo; (I asked if they counted as cookies, and she said yes). Coconut plus coconut plus homemade equals &lt;em&gt;difficult to resist&lt;/em&gt;!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/01/16/a-system-for-quitting-eating-cookies/&#34;&gt;my new rule&lt;/a&gt;, here are the three cookies I ate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/recorder-2014-02-16/cookie1.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;My first cookie&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/recorder-2014-02-16/cookie2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;My second cookie&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/recorder-2014-02-16/cookie3.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;My third cookie&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I stopped at three, which was a good thing, because after I went home, I did feel a little bloated. I should really have eaten only two, I think. I did take one home for Abby to enjoy.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pittsburgh Recorder Society continues to add members</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/11/17/pittsburgh-recorder-society-continues-to-add-members/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Nov 2013 19:40:37 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/11/17/pittsburgh-recorder-society-continues-to-add-members/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;At the third meeting of this season of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/PittsburghRecorderSociety&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Recorder Society&lt;/a&gt;, I was pleased to see that we continue to add members. Wow. We already had a huge turnout &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/10/20/the-biggest-pittsburgh-recorder-society-meeting-i-have-attended-in-two-years/&#34;&gt;last month&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-recorder-society-2013-11-17/group.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Snacks!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-recorder-society-2013-11-17/snacks.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I never expected my first wooden recorders to be Renaissance recorders</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/21/i-never-expected-my-first-wooden-recorders-to-be-renaissance-recorders/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2013 21:24:54 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/21/i-never-expected-my-first-wooden-recorders-to-be-renaissance-recorders/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/10/20/the-biggest-pittsburgh-recorder-society-meeting-i-have-attended-in-two-years/&#34;&gt;Yesterday, I noted&lt;/a&gt; that I picked up two recorders during the Pittsburgh Recorder Society meeting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They were these &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.vonhuene.com/Default.aspx?tabid=42&#34;&gt;Renaissance&lt;/a&gt; instruments:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mollenhauer-kynseker-recorders/boxed.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;In boxes&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mollenhauer-kynseker-recorders/assembled.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Assembled&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nice maple recorders, Mollenhauer Kynseker models:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mollenhauer.com/en/catalogue?page=shop.product_details&amp;amp;flypage=flypage.tpl&amp;amp;product_id=170&amp;amp;category_id=121&#34;&gt;Kynseker Soprano 4107&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mollenhauer.com/en/catalogue?page=shop.product_details&amp;amp;flypage=flypage.tpl&amp;amp;product_id=172&amp;amp;category_id=121&#34;&gt;Kynseker Alto 4217&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are my very first wooden recorders. All my other recorders are Yamaha plastic recorders, because they are inexpensive and easy to maintain. I&amp;rsquo;ve periodically considered buying wooden recorders, but to get some of clearly higher quality than the plastic ones is expensive!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-bother-with-renaissance&#34;&gt;Why bother with Renaissance?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I jumped at the opportunity to bid in the auction for these two Renaissance recorders to acquire them inexpensively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Up till recently, I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t have considered buying Renaissance recorders at all, because of the difference in construction and tonal quality from the Baroque-style recorders that I have and that we play in the Pittsburgh Recorder Society meetings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this summer at the Mideast early music workshop, I paid attention to people playing Renaissance recorders (for Renaissance music and other music too) and found the louder and &amp;ldquo;reedier&amp;rdquo; sound intriguing. I could see myself playing them in contexts in which this kind of sound quality would be advantageous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So now I have these two wooden recorders to play with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that the solo soprano recorder music by Jacob van Eyck from the Renaissance that &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/28/my-first-appearance-on-a-music-recital-program/&#34;&gt;I played last year&lt;/a&gt; would have entirely been suited to my new soprano Renaissance recorder! I may revisit that music to play it on the new instrument.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The biggest Pittsburgh Recorder Society meeting I have attended in two years!!</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/20/the-biggest-pittsburgh-recorder-society-meeting-i-have-attended-in-two-years/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Oct 2013 18:04:10 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/20/the-biggest-pittsburgh-recorder-society-meeting-i-have-attended-in-two-years/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;At the second meeting of this season of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/PittsburghRecorderSociety&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Recorder Society&lt;/a&gt;, I was amazed by the huge turnout. There were &lt;strong&gt;fourteen&lt;/strong&gt; of us, easily double the typical attendance in the past two seasons since &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/02/23/celebrating-two-years-of-playing-recorder/&#34;&gt;I first joined in 2011&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-recorder-society-2013-10-20/panorama.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Fred was very excited by the attendance and told us he would like for us to perform as an entire group sometime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/09/15/new-goals-for-a-new-season-of-the-pittsburgh-recorder-society/&#34;&gt;promised after last month&amp;rsquo;s meeting&lt;/a&gt;, I took the opportunity in this meeting to do some playing on my bass recorder. I also played tenor and soprano for some other pieces we worked on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;halloween-themed-desserts&#34;&gt;Halloween-themed desserts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since it is almost Halloween, Helen brought in some &amp;ldquo;scary&amp;rdquo; cupcakes that were, to me anyway, a sight to behold.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-recorder-society-2013-10-20/snacks.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-recorder-society-2013-10-20/scary-cupcake.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-recorder-society-2013-10-20/scary-cupcake-bottom.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;pittsburgh-s-rubber-duck&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh&amp;rsquo;s rubber duck&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People were talking about the planned departure later today of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/RubberDuckPittsburghPa&#34;&gt;our rubber duck&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, in the duck&amp;rsquo;s honor, I had brought my ukulele, and during the break I played &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/10/02/rubber-duckie-and-steel-city-ukuleles-rehearsal/&#34;&gt;Rubber Duckie on my ukulele&lt;/a&gt; while singing along, and Anita joined in the singing too. I had worked pretty hard to be able to passably play this song before our duck left. I still need more work on the song.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;more-recorders-for-me-to-play&#34;&gt;More recorders for me to play&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I picked up two recorders from Helen that I had bid on at the last meeting, when a large collection of recorders was given to us to be auctioned off. More on this later!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had another great time at the Pittsburgh Recorder Society monthly meeting. Every month, our Sunday afternoon meeting is something I truly look forward to.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New goals for a new season of the Pittsburgh Recorder Society</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/09/15/new-goals-for-a-new-season-of-the-pittsburgh-recorder-society/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Sep 2013 20:40:25 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/09/15/new-goals-for-a-new-season-of-the-pittsburgh-recorder-society/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-recorder-society-2013-09-15.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Recorder group&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I was delighted to pay my membership dues at the first meeting of the new 2013-2014 season of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/PittsburghRecorderSociety&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Recorder Society&lt;/a&gt;. I hadn&amp;rsquo;t played recorder much since this July&amp;rsquo;s Mideast early music workshop, because of my having &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/08/23/another-unexpected-life-change-one-month-of-learning-to-play-ukulele/&#34;&gt;taken up ukulele the day after I got back from that&lt;/a&gt;; in fact, apart from that week-long workshop, I had not attended any meetings of the Pittsburgh Recorder Society since April (since I had to miss the May one on travel), and although there are meetings all through the summer as well, they only take place in the North Hills, which is kind of far for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As with the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/16/excited-by-the-new-season-of-the-pittsburgh-recorder-society/&#34;&gt;opening of the last season&lt;/a&gt;, we have exciting new plans for this season. And I have my own new plans in addition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;introductions&#34;&gt;Introductions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have some new members, which is always great, so we went around briefly introducing ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;raising-our-level&#34;&gt;Raising our level&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is really inspiring, though, is the large number of formerly &amp;ldquo;new&amp;rdquo; people who joined during last season and have stayed with the group, so that we are in fact growing in numbers. Not only that, we have all improved considerably in the past year. Our director Fred is so excited by how far we have come that he has plans for us to work on harder music and improve our individual technique and ensemble playing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today we started working on music by Bach and Buxtehude: some lovely contrapuntal pieces. I look forward to our polishing up this stuff and really doing the old masters proud!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;bass-recorder&#34;&gt;Bass recorder&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to continuing work on my technique and musicality, I decided that for this season, I would like to do play more on bass recorder. In the past year, I&amp;rsquo;ve gravitated toward deliberately volunteering to play tenor lines, to experience the unique position of bringing out the inner voice as well as making it blend harmoniously with the others. For the new season, I have an interest in focusing on the bass line, to experience being the rock solid underpinning of ensemble music. So I told Fred on my plan, and he&amp;rsquo;ll come up with some stuff for me to get into that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been playing recorder for two and a half years now, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/02/23/celebrating-two-years-of-playing-recorder/&#34;&gt;starting in spring 2011&lt;/a&gt;. I am happy to be continuing on, with the companionship of everyone in the Pittsburgh Recorder Society! Making music together is really special.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Celebrating two years of playing recorder</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/02/23/celebrating-two-years-of-playing-recorder/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Feb 2013 23:33:58 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/02/23/celebrating-two-years-of-playing-recorder/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I was very excited to celebrate two years of playing recorder by attending the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.andrew.cmu.edu/user/lukas/pcars/Welcome.html&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Recorder Society&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ldquo;Midwinter Musical Feast&amp;rdquo; potluck and informal recital at Helen&amp;rsquo;s. Last year (2012) we didn&amp;rsquo;t have a winter party, but I still remember when two years ago (2011), on February 19, I started learning the alto recorder at home by myself, and then &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/26/i-dont-feel-like-practicing-but-im-gonna-do-it-anyway/&#34;&gt;decided to join the Pittsburgh Recorder Society&lt;/a&gt;. Helen was actually my first email contact from the group, and she had immediately invited me to come to the Midwinter Musical Feast, but not having actually met anybody yet, and also barely just beginning to play recorder, I was too intimidated and decided to skip the party and instead practice for two weeks before attending my first meeting of the group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last recorder potluck/recital I went to was &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/28/my-first-appearance-on-a-music-recital-program/&#34;&gt;half a year ago&lt;/a&gt;, when I played a bit on soprano recorder, Baroque flute, and modern flute. Abby had come with me, and her parents also attended. This time, Abby came again, as did her parents, and Abby brought her &lt;a href=&#34;tambura&#34;&gt;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tamburica&lt;/a&gt; to play some Balkan music selections:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/recorder-midwinter-2013/DSCN0017.JPG&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby on tamburitza&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(Additional photos of food and people are now &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/media/set/?set=a.445931198818142.1073741825.330712777006652&amp;amp;type=3&#34;&gt;up on Facebook&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-two-collaborations&#34;&gt;My two collaborations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for me, I prepared two pieces to play, both of which required a continuo accompanist. Because of time constraints, I did not actually get together with either of my collaborators, but did send them sound files of myself playing at home, as well as scores. So we never had any rehearsal together, but heck, this was just a party, so it wasn&amp;rsquo;t a big deal that we were going to wing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;handel-s-recorder-sonata-in-g-minor&#34;&gt;Handel&amp;rsquo;s recorder sonata in G minor&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last month, I ran through Handel&amp;rsquo;s short four-movement recorder sonata in G minor &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/26/music-i-just-played-for-the-first-time-recorder-sonata-tangos/&#34;&gt;with Henry on piano at a party&lt;/a&gt;, but my goal was always to perform it for real, to the best of my technical and interpretive ability, with period accompaniment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I actually rehearsed this with Annie, with her playing my portable electronic keyboard that has a harpsichord setting, but then it turned out she could not make it to the party, so I scrambled to find someone else, and I was thankful that Mike agreed to step in and play the continuo on bass recorder!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I worked rather hard on this piece, actually, in the sense of coming up with some fluency to be able to come up with spontaneous and personally expressive Baroque ornamentation in all the movements, especially the first. (I did not want to compose a fixed ornamentation to play.) I believe I had some success doing so, and felt that my effort was a respectful way to celebrate two years of recorder playing.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/recorder-midwinter-2013/DSCN0018.JPG&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin and Mike playing Handel&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;niccolò-dôthel-s-first-flute-and-cello-sonata-first-movement&#34;&gt;Niccolò Dôthel&amp;rsquo;s first flute and cello sonata, first movement&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/recorder-midwinter-2013/DSCN0020.JPG&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin and Karen playing Dôthel&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Two months ago, I had actually run through this piece on Baroque flute with piano accompaniment &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/22/playing-tango-on-melodica-and-singing-christmas-carols/&#34;&gt;at a party&lt;/a&gt;, but just sight read by Henry on piano and in a noisy environment that was not ideal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This time, I actually worked on playing it in a quiet environment. Karen Parsons, whom I actually formally met just before &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/21/mideast-early-music-workshop-a-life-changing-experience/&#34;&gt;last year&amp;rsquo;s Mideast early music workshop&lt;/a&gt;, which we both participated in, was kind enough to agree to play the continuo part on viola da gamba.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a false start and a scare though! What happened was that I had planned to play the piece on Annie&amp;rsquo;s wooden Baroque flute that she had lent to me, and I had in fact practiced it on this instrument just fine for days, but somehow, I could not make a sound at all on her flute after I performed the Handel recorder sonata. I was completely mystified. Luckily, I had a backup plan: I had brought along my own plastic Aulos Baroque flute, and I was perfectly able to play it instead, and so we proceeded. I am still not entirely certain why Annie&amp;rsquo;s flute suddenly failed to work for me; upon arriving at the party, I had actually warmed up the flute and played a few notes on it for confidence. My speculation is that it was a mistake to play recorder right before flute, and maybe my embouchure was slightly off on the particular instrument I had only been playing for a few days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, Karen and I had fun playing this light, elegant piece. I do wish I could have played it on Annie&amp;rsquo;s flute, though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;other-people&#34;&gt;Other people&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed hearing others in the recorder group playing their musical selections as well, especially those who were newer to the group. It makes me profoundly happy to be among others sharing music together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Pittsburgh Recorder Society usually holds these potluck/recitals twice a year, in winter and summer. I always cherish the opportunity to make a special dish to share for the potluck (this time I brought my own hearty vegetable soup) as well as prepare interesting music to share that I hope others will enjoy. And this time, being basically the second anniversary of my playing recorder, I felt especially grateful for all that everyone in the group has shared with me in the past two years! I actually do not know what my life would be like today if I had not begun playing music with the Pittsburgh Recorder Society two years ago. It changed everything for me.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Playing music on recorders at a Phipps Conservatory &#34;candlelight evening&#34;</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/12/09/playing-music-on-recorders-at-a-phipps-conservatory-candlelight-evening/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Dec 2012 20:46:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/12/09/playing-music-on-recorders-at-a-phipps-conservatory-candlelight-evening/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/recorders-at-phipps-2012/group-photo.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Sam, Franklin, Annie, Helen, Mike&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/recorders-at-phipps-2012/phipps-outside.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Entrance to Phipps&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;After almost two months of weekly music rehearsals, we (Annie, Helen, Mike, Sam, and I) finally performed as planned in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/events/136074939878556/&#34;&gt;Phipps Conservatory&lt;/a&gt;. It was a lot of fun. We came up with a huge batch of music that we hadn&amp;rsquo;t played &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/05/busy-evening-performing-at-phipps-followed-by-rehearsal-for-another-gig/&#34;&gt;at Phipps last year&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As people wandered around in the garden, sometimes they gathered to sit for a while to enjoy our music before moving on. We had our largest audiences earlier rather than later in the evening.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/recorders-at-phipps-2012/audience.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Audience at one point&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A sample photo and video, which I took while Sam, Helen, and Mike were playing in a trio, while Annie and I took a break. (Since there were five of us, we took turns playing either as a quartet or trio or as a quartet with a part doubled.)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/recorders-at-phipps-2012/trio.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Trio&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/1ExrZyU5cAU&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My full report on the event:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;several-weeks-of-preparation&#34;&gt;Several weeks of preparation&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/recorders-at-phipps-2012/music-scores.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;My music score binder&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We spent something like 16 hours in rehearsal, spread out over almost two months, before we performed. We first sight read a huge amount of music, nearly half of which we ended up deciding not to play this time, and worked on what we chose. I also spent time at home working on some trickier passages in some of the music. It was a pretty big time commitment, and at one point, the week before Thanksgiving, when I was really low on time and energy because of other commitments, I was feeling overwhelmed and suggested to the group that I might bail out this year because I was too tired to make it to one of the rehearsals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then I reconsidered, after realizing that missing one rehearsal was not the end of the world (since everyone else but Annie had missed at least one rehearsal already by then!), and that I didn&amp;rsquo;t have to play all the music, but could take turns with others if needed. (In the end, we each did take turns, since as five, we never needed all five of us when playing three or four part music.) After surviving that one week, I returned to rehearsal and was &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/11/19/preparing-for-december-9-recorder-performance-in-phipps-conservatory/&#34;&gt;re-energized to go through with the plan to perform again this year&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;at-phipps&#34;&gt;At Phipps&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We ended up playing for two hours, which was longer than the hour and a half of last year. We did have a lot more music, so that it took over an hour to run through all our music, before we took a break, and then started from the beginning again, choosing a subset of selections to repeat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As usual, I made various mistakes in performance that I simply never made in practice. I guess we all did, at one point or another. It happens. I am not as anxious about mistakes as I used to be. I&amp;rsquo;m a lot better at &lt;em&gt;recovery&lt;/em&gt; from a mistake than I used to be, and I&amp;rsquo;ve learned over my past year of music that recovery is far more important than never making a mistake. People can hear a little blip here, but as long as you get back on track quickly, without breaking the flow, it&amp;rsquo;s not the biggest deal in the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I am a lot more comfortable now with the mechanics of playing recorder, I have been focusing on contributing to ensemble unity of dynamics, articulation, etc. That&amp;rsquo;s the really fun part of playing together, after moving beyond the initial focus on getting the notes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing nice about having an audience, and a space in which to play all out, is that I felt inspired to play as beautifully as I could, getting the harmonies clean and ringing out. I just said that I made more mistakes in performance than in practice; but it is also true that I felt that I never played recorder more beautifully than tonight in some of the pieces. A paradox, perhaps, but one I can live with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sam&amp;rsquo;s wife came along to watch us. That was really nice, because there were times when the audience was otherwise very thin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am truly grateful to have had the opportunity to play in a little recorder ensemble again this year. Life is always kind of hectic at this time of year, but I am already looking forward to playing with the recorder gang again next year!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you to Annie, Helen, Mike, and Sam for having me be part of the holiday-themed music gig!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Preparing for December 9 recorder performance in Phipps Conservatory</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/11/19/preparing-for-december-9-recorder-performance-in-phipps-conservatory/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Nov 2012 23:40:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/11/19/preparing-for-december-9-recorder-performance-in-phipps-conservatory/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; time of year.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/phipps-candlelight.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Phipps Conservatory candlelight evening&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I just came back from another two-hour rehearsal (we&amp;rsquo;ve been having one every week) for an upcoming music gig.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll be performing with five other recorder players in one of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://phipps.conservatory.org/&#34;&gt;Phipps Conservatory&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ldquo;candlelight evenings&amp;rdquo;, Sunday, December 9, from 6 PM to 8 PM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Candlelight Evenings

Nov. 25, 2012 - Jan. 6, 2013

Extended Hours: Open until 10 p.m.

Winter Flower Show is even more enchanting at night - a time when glowing candles light the walkways and live music fills the air.

Experience the magic for yourself as we remain open until 10 p.m. daily from Nov. 23 - Jan. 6.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-this-event-is-special-to-me&#34;&gt;Why this event is special to me&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I reflect on having performed at Phipps last year as part of this recorder group, as the &lt;em&gt;first time&lt;/em&gt; I ever performed music in public since I was a kid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;last-year&#34;&gt;Last year&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year I wrote at length about my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/01/im-going-to-perform-music-much-sooner-than-i-expected-monday/&#34;&gt;anxiety and gratitude&lt;/a&gt; in anticipation of performing music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also wrote about the actual experience, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/05/busy-evening-performing-at-phipps-followed-by-rehearsal-for-another-gig/&#34;&gt;after it happened&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;grateful&#34;&gt;Grateful&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year I was very grateful for the opportunity to play with Annie, Helen, Mike, and Karen of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/PittsburghRecorderSociety&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Recorder Society&lt;/a&gt;. I practiced diligently outside of our rehearsals to try to get my parts down as well as I could, knowing that I was still prone to various slips. I also chose to not participate in some of the pieces that I felt I could not handle yet at my skill level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A year later, I&amp;rsquo;m far better a recorder player and musician. There&amp;rsquo;s no comparison between how I was a year ago and how I am now. Of course, I still have a &lt;em&gt;huge&lt;/em&gt; amount of further improvement as I continue to play music; I plan to continue to make large improvements year after year, decade after decade! My attitude is: &lt;strong&gt;I have only just begun&lt;/strong&gt;, after really just two years of practicing music seriously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year, Sam will join us also in performance, making six of us total. He&amp;rsquo;ll play not only recorder, but also bells and tambourines. This is going to be fun!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2012-12-09&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-12-09)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It quickly turned out that we were only five, because Karen was not going to be available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;anxiety&#34;&gt;Anxiety&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a year of playing a lot of music, both in private and in public, my anxiety has decreased considerably, and each time I perform in public, in particular, I become less self-conscious. What I&amp;rsquo;ve learned is to let go of my ego, and remember that I am playing so that people will enjoy the music: this is not about me, not about my mistakes, not about my brilliance, not about any of that stuff at all. It&amp;rsquo;s about conveying emotion and beauty, however imperfectly, and people sense that and respond to that. With this attitude, the only thing that can truly go wrong is &lt;em&gt;failing to connect to the audience&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, I&amp;rsquo;m &lt;em&gt;orders of magnitude&lt;/em&gt; less &lt;em&gt;shy&lt;/em&gt; now as a musician, and more generally, as a human being, after a year of putting myself out there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I look forward to playing again for a Phipps Conservatory &amp;ldquo;candlelight evening&amp;rdquo;. We have a lot of interesting new selections to play, with almost none of it being standard overdone Christmas carols.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re in Pittsburgh on Sunday, December 9, consider stopping by for a candlelit evening in Phipps Conservatory and hearing us play!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2012-12-09-1&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-12-09)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/09/playing-music-on-recorders-at-a-phipps-conservatory-candlelight-evening/&#34;&gt;A report on the performance&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Playing recorder in a group</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/10/21/playing-recorder-in-a-group/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Oct 2012 19:23:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/10/21/playing-recorder-in-a-group/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Today was the second meeting of the current season of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.andrew.cmu.edu/user/lukas/pcars/Welcome.html&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh chapter of the American Recorder Society&lt;/a&gt;. I reported last month on &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/16/excited-by-the-new-season-of-the-pittsburgh-recorder-society/&#34;&gt;how excited I was to begin the new season&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-recorder-dessert.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Pittsburgh Recorder Society dessert by Helen&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And it&amp;rsquo;s not just about the tasty desserts that Helen makes for us every month, of course (which basically compel me to exercise &lt;em&gt;before&lt;/em&gt; going to the meeting).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had some new people joining us today, including a woman who had been a member of the recorder society three decades ago, and now was retired and getting back into playing the recorder. It was great having her on board. We have some really good music selections from our director Fred to work on, hopefully toward a holiday performance by our group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She mentioned it being different and hard playing in an ensemble, since she was used to playing piano alone. Her comments made me immediately think back to where I was a year ago. Coincidentally, almost exactly a year ago, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/30/harder-to-play-in-a-group-than-alone/&#34;&gt;I wrote about the challenges of playing in a group&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m so grateful for the opportunity to play with others. It makes me realize that I spent far too much of my life being alone, doing everything alone, and that I was really missing out. Yes, being with others may be more difficult sometimes, but it completely changes my experience of life, making it so much richer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;fred-s-tips-i-appreciated-today&#34;&gt;Fred&amp;rsquo;s tips I appreciated today&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On one of the pieces we are working on, I&amp;rsquo;m playing the alto 1 line. Fred gave me really useful feedback. He noted that I was holding back and not playing &lt;em&gt;all out&lt;/em&gt;. I said that I was afraid of going squeaky on the high G. He said that we should always play all out, and that this alto 1 part is &amp;ldquo;glorious&amp;rdquo; and should &amp;ldquo;ring&amp;rdquo;. Furthermore, he also reminded us that when we practice (either at home or in a group), we should go &lt;em&gt;beyond&lt;/em&gt; what we&amp;rsquo;d do in performance, and exaggerate the elements of music that we want to bring out. There are a number of reasons for this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We must do more in practice so that when we are ready to perform, what we do will actually be easier than what we&amp;rsquo;ve done already again and again in private.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Our subjective perception of how we sound is inaccurate: what sounds like &amp;ldquo;overdoing&amp;rdquo; to us (without actually recording ourselves) may not sound like much to an actual audience.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Excited by the new season of the Pittsburgh Recorder Society</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/09/16/excited-by-the-new-season-of-the-pittsburgh-recorder-society/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Sep 2012 20:04:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/09/16/excited-by-the-new-season-of-the-pittsburgh-recorder-society/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today was the first meeting of the new season (September-May) of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.andrew.cmu.edu/user/lukas/pcars/Welcome.html&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh chapter of the American Recorder Society&lt;/a&gt; (and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/PittsburghRecorderSociety&#34;&gt;on Facebook&lt;/a&gt;). I was excited to be back, since the last time I actually played recorder at all was a month and a half ago at a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/28/my-first-appearance-on-a-music-recital-program/&#34;&gt;potluck/recital&lt;/a&gt;; I&amp;rsquo;ve been focused recently on playing &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/baroque-flute/&#34;&gt;Baroque flute&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/flute/&#34;&gt;modern flute&lt;/a&gt;, with a tiny bit of &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/piano/&#34;&gt;restarting piano&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have a new plan this season!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-new-plan-for-this-season&#34;&gt;A new plan for this season&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our director, Fred, told us of a new plan for this season, geared toward working toward pieces that we will actually perform in a concert as a complete ensemble. Last season we didn&amp;rsquo;t end up having a concert, for example. This year, his plan is to include work on music that has two choirs of voices, to make it easier for more people to be involved and also in order to make performance possible even if someone for some reason is not available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-music-we-worked-on-today&#34;&gt;The music we worked on today&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today we started working on the meditative &amp;ldquo;Kyrie de la &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Missa_Papae_Marcelli&#34;&gt;Missa Papae Marcelli&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo; by Palestrina (1562), and the joyful &amp;ldquo;Jubilate Deo&amp;rdquo; by Lodovico Viadana (1600s?).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Palestrina is gorgeous music and I am excited about our working toward play it beautifully as a unified ensemble:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/IIcrgNtyX0U&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also started work on &amp;ldquo;Jubilate Deo&amp;rdquo;, which is divided into two choirs:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/qrtxRkXRz5Y&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;stuff-someone-donated-to-us&#34;&gt;Stuff someone donated to us&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Someone donated a whole bunch of music to us and even some instruments. Here are the scores I picked up (there were plenty left over that others did not pick up, but I resisted the temptation to take more than I was ever going to work on):&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/donated-recorder-music.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Selection of recorder music someone donated to the Pittsburgh Recorder Society&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Baroque stuff, Handel, Telemann, sopranino &amp;ldquo;bird&amp;rdquo; tunes, old English airs and dances, a three volume set of &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/28/my-first-appearance-on-a-music-recital-program&#34;&gt;Van Eyck&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;music-or-chess&#34;&gt;Music or chess?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until today, I was not entirely sure whether I was going to make it to the recorder society meeting! Today happened to also be the first round of the new season of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pitt.edu/~schach/ChessPA/ChessLeague/wpapcl.htm&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Chess League&lt;/a&gt;, and recently &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/08/21/returning-to-chess/&#34;&gt;I committed to&lt;/a&gt; being an alternate player for a team playing in it. My understanding was that, being an alternate player, I would not often be depended on by our team to always be available to play, but because our top two boards were not going to play today, and I did not plan to play, we had to go as far down the list as our third and final alternate player. This meant that if something went wrong, we would have a forfeit. So I told the team captain that in case of emergency, I could play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All things being equal, I prioritize music in my life over chess, but I would have gone to play for the team to avoid a forfeit if that had been required today. But it turned out that because of the odd number of teams in our division, our team got a bye today, so that was perfect timing: I went to the recorder society meeting knowing that there was no conflict.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;trying-to-recruiting-someone-from-chess-into-music&#34;&gt;Trying to recruiting someone from chess into music&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By coincidence, yesterday when &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/15/deja-vu-in-chess-recognize-this-sicilian-pattern/&#34;&gt;I was at the chess club and ended up playing blitz&lt;/a&gt;, I ran into a fellow chess player I hadn&amp;rsquo;t talked with in years, and we were talking about the Pittsburgh Chess League and I mentioned that I didn&amp;rsquo;t intend to play chess today because I was going to play music instead. In the course of conversation, it turned out that he had just bought himself a recorder and was just starting to play it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I told him he should join the Pittsburgh Recorder Society, and that there were great beginner lessons before the general playing begins: &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/18/disagreement-on-the-use-of-time/&#34;&gt;over a year ago I had gone to these lessons by Fred&lt;/a&gt; and learned quite a lot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, he ended up not showing up today; it turned out that instead playing chess as an alternate for a team. I&amp;rsquo;ve reminded him that there are no more conflicts with chess in the upcoming months, so I hope to see him playing recorder in October! I will personally remind him again when the next meeting grows near. (Peter, if you&amp;rsquo;re reading this, please consider joining us!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s good to be playing recorder in an ensemble again. And I hope to bring in more people to the Pittsburgh Recorder Society, including beginners.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My first appearance on a music recital program</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/07/28/my-first-appearance-on-a-music-recital-program/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Jul 2012 23:41:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/07/28/my-first-appearance-on-a-music-recital-program/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-ars-recital-summer-2012.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Pittsburgh Recorder Society spring 2012 recital program&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A month and a half ago, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/06/15/preparing-for-my-first-solo-flute-performance-notes-on-perfectionism-and-high-standards/&#34;&gt;I reported on an upcoming music recital I was going to perform in&lt;/a&gt;. In fact, I did perform, on Sunday, June 17, 2012. &lt;em&gt;It was my first appearance in my life on a musical recital program, and my first time solo on modern flute.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The event was an informal spring dinner party/recital at Helen&amp;rsquo;s home for the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.andrew.cmu.edu/user/lukas/pcars/Welcome.html&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh chapter of the American Recorder Society&lt;/a&gt;. (By the way, we also have a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/PittsburghRecorderSociety&#34;&gt;Facebook page&lt;/a&gt; now.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why did I put myself on the spot, by volunteering to play, and what did I choose to play?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-recital-program&#34;&gt;The recital program&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The program had several of us perform a dozen musical selections in a variety combinations (also performing at the end but not listed on the program were Mike and Fred).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(This year, Abby had submitted for the program a piece for Bulgarian tambura, &amp;ldquo;Ihtimansko Horo&amp;rdquo;, and this is on the printed program, but at the last minute, she had problems as a result of restringing her instrument during the week, and ended up not performing, unfortunately.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Myself, I had chosen three musical selections to play:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Doen Daphne D&amp;rsquo;over Schoone Maeght&amp;rdquo; from Jacob Van Eyck&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Der Fluyten Lust-Hof&amp;rdquo;; solo soprano recorder&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lachlann Dubh (Scottish slow air); Baroque flute&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;II. Allegro from C.P.E. Bach&amp;rsquo;s sonata in A minor for solo flute, Wq 132; modern flute&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;background-why-i-played&#34;&gt;Background: why I played&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;last-year-s-party-recital&#34;&gt;Last year&amp;rsquo;s party/recital&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I only started playing recorder and joining the Pittsburgh Recorder Society just over a year ago. After I had only spent a couple of months playing alto recorder (and therefore being at a total beginner level), Helen held her party/recital on June 19, 2011, and invited people to volunteer to play. I was, of course, not ready to prepare anything I felt interesting enough to perform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, it did not even occur to me at the time that I would perform at all any time soon. But in fact, in addition to the prepared performances by several of the people, we also ended up playing something in a large group that we had worked on at the monthly meeting of the Pittsburgh Recorder Society. Even in such casual circumstances, I found myself almost paralyzed with anxiety, sitting there while Abby and other people sat and watched us play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It should be noted that at this point in my life last year, &lt;em&gt;I had not played music in front of a sitting audience in decades&lt;/em&gt;, and never with any seriousness; I was thirteen when I was last stumbling around playing in marching band with no enthusiasm and just an anonymous figure in a crowd:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/lamphere-high-marching-band.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin in Lamphere High School marching band uniform&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I survived playing casually in the group, as Abby watched and took photos that day:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-ars-recital-summer-2011/group.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Pittsburgh Recorder Society group performing at summer 2011 recital&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I have to confess that I was actually shaking and hyperventilating at times, messing up my breathing. It all seems so silly now, but that&amp;rsquo;s how it was. We do what we need to do, eventually become less sensitive, and move on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;setting-a-goal-and-deadline&#34;&gt;Setting a goal and deadline&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t tell anyone that June day last year, but after going home, I made a solemn vow to myself: I was going to spend the entire following year practicing recorder seriously and effectively, in order to be able to prepare something to play at the next party/recital. I had no idea what I was going to play, because the first step was simply to continue improving using some recorder method books, before actually trying to learn a real piece. My goal was to have something substantial to play, to display how much I had learned and improved. (And not shake with anxiety.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-i-chose-the-selections-i-played-this-year&#34;&gt;Why I chose the selections I played this year&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;which-instrument-s&#34;&gt;Which instrument(s)?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that in a single year, I had not only improved at alto recorder, but had also learned soprano recorder. I had also bought a tenor recorder and begun playing it (same fingerings as soprano recorder). And by fall last year, I had also &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/03/my-new-bass-and-sopranino-recorders-and-having-fun/&#34;&gt;bought a bass recorder&lt;/a&gt; and begun playing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Completely unexpectedly, in November I had begun &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/09/taking-up-flute-again-after-decades/&#34;&gt;trying to play modern flute again&lt;/a&gt;. Even more unexpectedly, later I also &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/30/bought-a-baroque-flute/&#34;&gt;decided to take up the Baroque flute&lt;/a&gt;, after having explained &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/17/flute-versus-recorder/&#34;&gt;why I had no plan to try Baroque flute anytime soon&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I also started playing the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/11/learning-another-instrument-the-tin-whistle/&#34;&gt;Irish tin whistle&lt;/a&gt;. It has been quite a year of music for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what instruments and music was I going to play for the recital at Helen&amp;rsquo;s?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-answer-play-three-of-my-instruments&#34;&gt;The answer: play three of my instruments&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided that I would pick three fairly short music selections and play them on three different instruments as appropriate for the music&amp;rsquo;s style and period. Also, to simply my preparation, I looked for music I could play alone rather than, say, requiring a keyboard accompaniment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;late-renaissance-or-early-baroque-1650s&#34;&gt;Late Renaissance or early Baroque (1650s?)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I chose to play a selection from Van Eyck to show off the soprano recorder. Actually, I had played this selection for an audience before (a blog post about that life-changing experience, a &amp;ldquo;Baroque jam session&amp;rdquo;, on Friday, April 27, is still to be written). It was by pure accident that I came across Van Eyck&amp;rsquo;s music to play; I had found the score in the Carnegie Library of Pittsburgh&amp;rsquo;s catalog while looking for any recorder music at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A personal reason I wanted to play this was that I had not heard any interpretation that I really liked, from CDs or YouTube. Therefore, I wanted to fill a hole and try to play the music the way I felt it. This is the fundamental reason I have been playing music rather than just listening to others do it: self-expression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&#34;update-of-2012-10-30&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-10-30)&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is the finally published post about the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/04/27/baroque-jam-session-at-cmu/&#34;&gt;Baroque jam session&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;traditional-scottish-air-1700s&#34;&gt;Traditional Scottish air (1700s?)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Baroque flute seemed appropriate to play this slow song. It could have used accompaniment, but I added it to the program too late to have someone accompany me on harp or mandolin or something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was a little hesitant to play the Baroque flute in public, because I had only really started playing it, and was clearly in need of serious improvement (in fact, it has been my main instrument of focus in the past month), but I thought I might as well put in a two-minute song for variety&amp;rsquo;s sake, and as a baseline since I had already decided that next year, I want to play the Baroque flute again at the 2013 party/recital, and much better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;late-baroque-or-pre-classical-1750s&#34;&gt;Late Baroque or pre-Classical (1750s?)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The CPE Bach sonata I had fallen in love with hearing it by accident on modern flute performed by &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/22/james-galway-made-me-hate-flute/&#34;&gt;Emmanuel Pahud&lt;/a&gt; when I was browsing YouTube one day for solo flute material. After hearing it, I vowed that one day I would play the whole thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I chose what seemed to be the easiest movement to focus on, and practiced it on modern flute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is, of course, a question of which flute is best suited for this music. Given the period, perhaps a simple system keyed wooden flute? But I don&amp;rsquo;t have one, and currently have no intention of getting one or learning to play it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would be possible to play it on a Baroque flute, but much more difficult. When I get better at Baroque flute, I just might consider playing CPE Bach on it, but I feel that the modern flute is not inappropriate for this music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-i-fared&#34;&gt;How I fared&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, I played. I got nervous, I made various errors I did not make in practice, I made errors that I made in practice, but I actually did manage to go up alone and play. I can&amp;rsquo;t pretend that I played very well (in fact, now, over a month later, I could play each of these selections noticeably better than I did), but I did what I could at the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, since Abby&amp;rsquo;s parents came to the party/recital this year, this was also the first time they ever saw me perform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was considerably less nervous than a year ago, but still more nervous than I really need to be. So next year, 2013, I expect to be more seasoned and more performance-ready.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After we all played, we enjoyed the potluck dinner and had a good time. What else could I ask for, an evening of music, food, and friends?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Sorry, I have no photos or videos of any of the activities. I was too busy experiencing rather than spectating, and I don&amp;rsquo;t think anyone actually took any photos or videos.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Pittsburgh Recorder Society spring potluck/recital means a lot to me because it was there last year that I continued to get to know the members, after having just joined, met new people, heard people play, and got the idea that I too could perform, if I worked at improving. I set some goals, was happy that Abby and her parents came along to see me perform, and the experience renewed my commitment to continuing to play and improve in the Pittsburgh Recorder Society group as well as on my own on Baroque flute and modern flute. I have every intention of having even more fun in my upcoming year of music!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Byron Janis on Overcoming Adversity</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/09/22/byron-janis-on-overcoming-adversity/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Sep 2011 20:57:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/09/22/byron-janis-on-overcoming-adversity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Imagine this.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You are an 11-year-old boy who is already an established prodigy at the piano, and you have an accident with your little finger and a glass door. Your finger is shredded, and losing a tendon and nerve in the surgery, and not being able to feel anything in the finger, you are told by the doctor to think of doing something else with your life than continue with piano.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do you do?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.byronjanis.com/&#34;&gt;Byron Janis&lt;/a&gt;, you decide to pursue your passion, finding ways to work around the defective finger, using other fingers and using your vision to monitor what the little finger is doing. The world doesn&amp;rsquo;t even know about your difficulty until you tell them after another sixty years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, I was privileged to hear Byron Janis speak today and perform a few pieces at the piano at a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cmu.edu/news/stories/archives/2011/september/sept12_byronjanis.html&#34;&gt;convocation at Carnegie Mellon University&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/byron-janis-speaking.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Byron Janis speaking&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/byron-janis-playing.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Byron Janis playing piano&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Janis spoke of overcoming not only the problem with his finger, but also the psoriatic arthritis he developed later. At a low point in his life, he ended up beginning to compose, and finding meaning in music through that avenue. &amp;ldquo;&lt;strong&gt;Passion&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;perseverance&lt;/strong&gt;!&amp;rdquo; he repeated again and again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I liked how down-to-earth he was in his talk. He grew up in Pittsburgh, after all: he&amp;rsquo;s one of ours!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-his-talk-touched-me&#34;&gt;Why his talk touched me&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a long time in my life, I was a musical dilettante, unwilling to put in the truly focused, disciplined effort to play an instrument well (I piddled around with flute and piano). I grew up believing that my hands were &amp;ldquo;too&amp;rdquo; small and my fingers &amp;ldquo;too&amp;rdquo; short. Also, my left hand&amp;rsquo;s pinky finger (and less so, my ring finger) got genuinely damaged in elementary school, and my left thumb got damaged in high school. (I do live with the consequences of those accidents every day.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, none of that should really have stopped me from doing what I can with what I have, if I care. Only when older and wiser did I realize that in the end, this is all we can do in life, and it is enough!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This February, I made a decision to seriously practice the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Recorder&#34;&gt;recorder&lt;/a&gt;. I joined the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.andrew.cmu.edu/user/lukas/pcars/Welcome.html&#34;&gt;local chapter&lt;/a&gt; of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.americanrecorder.org/&#34;&gt;American Recorder Society&lt;/a&gt;. For the first time in my life, I have made the effort to practice intelligently and efficiently, and most importantly, &lt;em&gt;regularly&lt;/em&gt; (as in approximately an hour every day of the week). And I believe I have done pretty well in the past eight months. I am continuing to improve my playing, and my enjoyment has deepened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not going to lie: every time I pick up my alto or tenor recorder (I also have a soprano and am planning to get a bass), I momentarily wish my hands were bigger, my right pinky longer, and my entire left hand less messed up, but such thoughts disappear quickly, because I am no longer willing to play victim, and instead focus on doing what I need to do to make music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wish Byron Janis well in his current mission to inspire everyone, from disadvantaged youths to injured veterans, to overcome adversity and follow their passion with perseverance!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>