<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Paleo on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/paleo/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Paleo on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/paleo/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Reflections on Food Day</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/10/24/reflections-on-food-day/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Oct 2012 22:38:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/10/24/reflections-on-food-day/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/food-day-2012-breakfast-1.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Soup and veggies&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A year ago I celebrated &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.foodday.org/&#34;&gt;Food Day&lt;/a&gt; for the first time, by sharing &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/24/every-day-is-food-day/&#34;&gt;some reflections on what food means to me&lt;/a&gt;. Today I review my reflections and some more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;buying-food&#34;&gt;Buying food&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I still take care to shop carefully for groceries and make our own tasty meals to eat. Some of our sources:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://kretschmannfarm.com/&#34;&gt;Kretschmann Farm&lt;/a&gt; CSA subscription for local produce&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.localharvest.org/miseras-organic-farm-M14896&#34;&gt;Misera&amp;rsquo;s Organic Farm&lt;/a&gt; for local &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/24/whats-a-nice-acorn-squash-like-you-doing-in-a-pot-of-spicy-lentils/&#34;&gt;chickens&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lewisfamilyfarms.com/&#34;&gt;Lewis Family Farms&lt;/a&gt; for local beef&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://pine-richland.patch.com/articles/stoney-lane-farm-a-little-bit-country-in-suburbia&#34;&gt;Stoney Lane Farm&lt;/a&gt; for local &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/28/thankful-for-the-free-range-orange-yolked-eggs/&#34;&gt;eggs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.traderjoes.com/&#34;&gt;Trader Joe&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.eastendfood.coop/&#34;&gt;East End Food Co-op&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our food choices are based on our concerns for both &lt;em&gt;health&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;sustainability&lt;/em&gt;. Our choices may have an impact on one or the other or both.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;cooking&#34;&gt;Cooking&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I started my blog over a year ago, I had thought I would be posting more about cooking, since I was doing a good amount of it, but as it turned out, during this year (2012), Abby took over almost all of the cooking for us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;diet&#34;&gt;Diet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both Abby and I have experimented in paleo directions in the past year. As a reminder, this doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean that we&amp;rsquo;re just going around chowing down on all the meat we can eat. It does mean that we have&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;considerably increased our consumption of vegetables&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;increased our consumption of various fats and oils&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;reduced our consumption of carbs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-question-of-carbs&#34;&gt;The question of carbs&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What we seemed to discover was that we needed some base level of carbs in order to maintain energy and weight levels. Through experimentation, Abby has focused on getting carbs through potatoes and sweet potatoes primarily, going almost completely off wheat. I, on the other hand, am still hooked on rice; I also still eat some wheat, but frankly, I can tell from the effects that I would probably do best to eliminate it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;rice-disaster&#34;&gt;Rice disaster?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, I wondered about brown rice, and even briefly experimented with &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/07/is-brown-rice-healthy-or-not/&#34;&gt;switching to white rice&lt;/a&gt;. The white rice experiment was a fast failure: the high glycemic index and lack of fiber didn&amp;rsquo;t help me at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More recently, there have been reports of &lt;em&gt;brown rice&lt;/em&gt; in particular having &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.consumerreports.org/cro/magazine/2012/11/arsenic-in-your-food/index.htm&#34;&gt;high levels of arsenic&lt;/a&gt;. This is rather disturbing, and Abby and I have agreed that I need to quickly re-evaluate my consumption of brown rice. I&amp;rsquo;ve committed to trying out some alternative source of calories/fiber.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-breakfast&#34;&gt;My breakfast&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My breakfast has remained fairly &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/01/26/improving-my-breakfast-and-other-meals/&#34;&gt;stable&lt;/a&gt; since &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/23/paleo-diet-experimentation/&#34;&gt;I quit oatmeal&lt;/a&gt;. Basically, I eat&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;veggies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;eggs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;nuts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a prune&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Depending on how I feel and what&amp;rsquo;s available, occasionally I&amp;rsquo;ll eat some bacon or fish, and sometimes I&amp;rsquo;ll add some sweet potatoes or other carbs, but typically that&amp;rsquo;s it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(I stopped the flax seeds, largely out of inconvenience of grinding them!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s what I happened to eat today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/food-day-2012-breakfast-1.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Soup and veggies&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/food-day-2012-breakfast-2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Eggs&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The soup and veggies were leftovers from big batches Abby or I had made earlier:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;my cauliflower leaf soup with garlic, carrots, sweet potatoes, curry powder, extra virgin olive oil&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;my stir-fried cauliflower florets with garlic, green peppers, coconut oil&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Abby&amp;rsquo;s spaghetti squash with onion and other stuff&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And on top of that I also ate two fried eggs with walnuts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-lunch-and-dinner&#34;&gt;My lunch and dinner&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lunch and dinner were combinations of various leftovers, all originally made by Abby (hence my not knowing the exact ingredients):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ground beef stew with green peppers, jalapeno, onion, various seasoning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;slow-cooked chicken with veggies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;leftover kale and onion&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;dinner included sauteed zucchini and other veggies Abby cooked tonight&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;brown rice&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;fasting&#34;&gt;Fasting&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes I deliberately fast for a meal or two. This happens when I just don&amp;rsquo;t feel all that hungry. I treat that as a signal from my body that I don&amp;rsquo;t really need to eat. My experiments have convinced me that &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Intermittent_fasting&#34;&gt;intermittent fasting&lt;/a&gt; helps with fat loss and mental clarity. It also helps me remember to be grateful, when I do eat again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are human beings, not robots. We need food. And food isn&amp;rsquo;t just &amp;ldquo;fuel&amp;rdquo;. It lives or has lived. It is complex. I am grateful to be living in a land of plenty, and that Abby has taken so much care to make varied and tasty dishes for us. But as the recent reports on arsenic reminds me, there is much we must continue to do to prevent the degradation of what we eat.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Joy of Eating Ice Cream for Breakfast</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/06/16/the-joy-of-eating-ice-cream-for-breakfast/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Jun 2012 19:27:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/06/16/the-joy-of-eating-ice-cream-for-breakfast/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/coffee-bean-blast.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Trader Joe&amp;#39;s Coffee Bean Blast ice cream&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Recently I started eating ice cream for breakfast. I was amused because this was something I haven&amp;rsquo;t done since I was a child, when my sister and I managed for a while to convince our parents to let us eat ice cream for breakfast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is there a contradiction between my eating ice cream for breakfast and my supposedly paying attention to my health?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-my-sister-and-i-got-to-eat-ice-cream-as-kids&#34;&gt;How my sister and I got to eat ice cream as kids&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As kids, my sister and I loved ice cream, of course. We managed to find a way to sometimes eat it for breakfast. Basically, we volunteered to make breakfast on some weekends. We had found some kid-oriented &amp;ldquo;cookbooks&amp;rdquo; at a garage sale or something at some point, and we learned about cinnamon toast and other such &amp;ldquo;American&amp;rdquo; breakfasts that were foreign to our parents. It was fun for us to take charge of breakfast once in a while, and have an excuse to make super-sugary concoctions to eat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frankly, it was easy enough for us in general to just say, &amp;ldquo;We&amp;rsquo;re eating American style&amp;rdquo;, in order to avoid eating rice porridge with dried shrimp bits and pork bone broth and greens (to tell the truth, I actually liked that, but at some point wanted to eat &amp;ldquo;American&amp;rdquo; like my classmates). But it was even more fun to be able to say, &amp;ldquo;We found this recipe in a &lt;em&gt;book&lt;/em&gt;.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A couple of times, we managed to get ice cream into the picture. We must have found a recipe that called for it. We got frozen waffles, and prepared them with syrup and topped with ice cream. I remember that being pretty good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;but-ice-cream-is-not-a-good-food&#34;&gt;But ice cream is not a good food&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have to explain that Abby and I don&amp;rsquo;t eat ice cream much any more. We&amp;rsquo;ve found that it is too sugary and makes us feel tired or bloated in large quantities. You don&amp;rsquo;t have to be &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/paleo/&#34;&gt;paleo&lt;/a&gt; to understand and experience the drawbacks of ice cream (not that we&amp;rsquo;re strictly paleo anyway).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I&amp;rsquo;m a big believer in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.t-nation.com/free_online_article/most_recent/in_defense_of_cheat_days&#34;&gt;intermittent cheating&lt;/a&gt;, so I&amp;rsquo;m happy to eat ice cream now and then as a special treat, but otherwise, I don&amp;rsquo;t really need it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-i-had-to-eat-ice-cream-for-breakfast&#34;&gt;Why I had to eat ice cream for breakfast&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t buy this bucket of Trader Joe&amp;rsquo;s Coffee Bean Blast ice cream; Abby did. She thought it would be a nice post-&lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/hiking/&#34;&gt;hike&lt;/a&gt; treat. Unfortunately, it has turned out in the past months that whenever we go out on a weekend for a hike or some other outdoors adventure, we come back in the evening, and it&amp;rsquo;s too late to eat this ice cream.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem is caffeine. Eating this ice cream would mess up our night of sleep. In fact, I verified this once, eating some of the ice cream in the evening: oops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frustrated, I didn&amp;rsquo;t know when I &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; eat this coffee ice cream. Clearly, the only time I could possibly eat it would be before late afternoon. Furthermore, the only safe context for me to eat something like this would be after I exercised. Since I have a preference for exercising in the morning before breakfast anyway, the perfect time for eating this ice cream was breakfast. Generally, after exercising, I can eat sugary foods to an extent without compromising my energy levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-i-did-to-earn-my-breakfast&#34;&gt;What I did to earn my breakfast&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went for a five-mile &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/running/&#34;&gt;run&lt;/a&gt; in &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/frick-park/&#34;&gt;Frick Park&lt;/a&gt;. I wore my Vibram FiveFingers Bikila LS shoes.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/vibram-fivefingers-bikila-ls.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Vibram FiveFingers Bikila LS shoes&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-real-breakfast&#34;&gt;My real breakfast&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At breakfast, I eat only two spoons of ice cream, actually. That is enough to satisfy me. At this rate, I&amp;rsquo;ll take forever to finish that tub. More reason for me to exercise every morning this summer!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I followed up with the rest of my breakfast, which is typical of what I&amp;rsquo;ve been eating since &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/23/paleo-diet-experimentation/&#34;&gt;completely abandoning my former oatmeal breakfast&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/breakfast-brentwood.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;My breakfast along with Brentwood 5K entry form&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Two &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/28/thankful-for-the-free-range-orange-yolked-eggs/&#34;&gt;eggs&lt;/a&gt; fried with spice mix and olive oil&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Spinach from our &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.kretschmannfarm.com/&#34;&gt;Kretschmann Farm&lt;/a&gt; box&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sweet potatoes and bacon bits&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Walnuts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Strawberries&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, and Abby I have signed up for the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.brentwood5k.com/&#34;&gt;Brentwood Firecracker 5K race&lt;/a&gt;. I last did that race eleven years ago, in 2001. I have a serious goal of beating my time from that year!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have only two more weeks of training with ice cream, before running the race. Wish me luck!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Snowing means sambar at Coriander India Grill</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/02/26/snowing-means-sambar-at-coriander-india-grill/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Feb 2012 12:10:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/02/26/snowing-means-sambar-at-coriander-india-grill/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/coriander-grill/store-front.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Coriander Grill&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, there was snow in Pittsburgh (almost all melted today, of course).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I had originally planned to be going on a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/pittsburghhikers/events/50162262/&#34;&gt;Meetup hike at Ohiopyle&lt;/a&gt;, carpooling with John, but on Friday we bailed out because of the weather forecast. We&amp;rsquo;ve done that hike a couple of times before, and will certainly do it again when it&amp;rsquo;s repeated in warmer weather anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Snow, however little there is of it, always makes me want to eat &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sambar_(dish)&#34;&gt;sambar&lt;/a&gt;. I love Indian food, and for some reason, I especially like sambar. Once every month or two, I crave going to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.coriandergrill.com/&#34;&gt;Coriander India Grill&lt;/a&gt; in Squirrel Hill, just a couple of blocks from where we live, to eat sambar and other good stuff. We&amp;rsquo;ve been to Coriander Grill several times, on different days and for lunch and dinner. There has been inconsistency, but I have reason to believe that lunch buffet on Saturday is a good time to go to Coriander.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/coriander-grill/sambar.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Sambar&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So the three of us went to Coriander for lunch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2014-01-13&#34;&gt;(Update of 2014-01-13)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I went to Coriander Grill for a Sunday dinner buffet yesterday, because we were hungry after a long hike, and I thought it would be a good idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We hadn&amp;rsquo;t been to Coriander for a while. They restricted their buffet days and increased the price. What we didn&amp;rsquo;t realize was that they also restricted the selection severely. Also, they kept on running out of food and not refilling frequently enough. Finally, we didn&amp;rsquo;t feel too well afterwards. I had a sleepless night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was very, very disappointed, and can no longer recommend Coriander Grill for their buffet. It is, of course, possible that their regular menu is still fine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;more-on-coriander-grill&#34;&gt;More on Coriander Grill&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The non-buffet menu at Coriander Grill is substantial. Abby and I have been there for dinner and sampled their &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Goa&#34;&gt;Goa&lt;/a&gt; Portuguese meat-based selections, for example. They also have Indian-Chinese dishes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lunch buffet is varied enough, and rotates, such that there is always something different there when we go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;preparation-for-lunch&#34;&gt;Preparation for lunch&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might be thinking, &amp;ldquo;Preparation for eating at a lunch buffet?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You bet. Eating at a buffet is &lt;em&gt;serious business&lt;/em&gt;, not to be undertaken lightly. It requires preparation of &lt;em&gt;mind, body, and spirit&lt;/em&gt;. (For amusement, check out this blog post on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://milkmiracle.net/2010/09/25/buffet/&#34;&gt;proper way to eat an an Indian buffet&lt;/a&gt;; please note that I am nowhere as &amp;ldquo;serious&amp;rdquo; as this guy, however.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;fasting&#34;&gt;Fasting&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The number one rule of eating at a buffet is, I plan to eat &lt;em&gt;a lot&lt;/em&gt;. A lot of &lt;em&gt;variety&lt;/em&gt;, and also a lot of volume. To do this effectively, fasting is necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe that &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.marksdailyapple.com/fasting/&#34;&gt;intermittent fasting&lt;/a&gt; is a good thing. I even believe that intermittent bingeing is a good thing. We are evolved to adapt to changes in food availability. Our bodies and minds are not designed to do the same thing over and over again, because then adaptation kicks in and we lose our physical and mental sharpness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that I didn&amp;rsquo;t eat very much on Friday (and had lost some weight during the week that I needed to make up), so on Saturday morning, when we decided to eat at Coriander, I was already partially prepared. Skipping breakfast was of course mandatory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;exercise&#34;&gt;Exercise&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did half an hour of intense exercise before lunch. I have learned from experience that exercise right before eating (whether for a buffet or just an ordinary meal) is effective in reducing gain of fat, redirecting toward muscle gain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, &lt;a href=&#34;http://ezinearticles.com/?Fasted-Cardio---Exercise-on-an-Empty-Stomach&amp;amp;id=4979785&#34;&gt;exercising on an empty stomach&lt;/a&gt; has additional benefits. Again, think about evolution. Our hunter-gatherer ancestors did not have &lt;sup&gt;24&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;7&lt;/sub&gt; access to junk food at all times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: usually, I do &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; exercise on a fully empty stomach, because there are drawbacks as well, as I learned from experience. Generally, I have found that eating a handful of nuts and possibly some dried fruit before exercising is optimal for me, in giving me some energy flow while keeping my head clear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;knowing-what-not-to-eat&#34;&gt;Knowing what not to eat&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no avoiding fatty, salty, starchy, sugary foods at a buffet. That&amp;rsquo;s part of the full experience. And that&amp;rsquo;s why I don&amp;rsquo;t eat at a buffet often, even a nice one like Coriander&amp;rsquo;s just blocks away from home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there are some guidelines that are very useful. The main thing is, I &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; eat rice or bread at a buffet. You don&amp;rsquo;t have to be &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/paleo/&#34;&gt;paleo&lt;/a&gt; or on some official low-carb diet to know that this is not worth the money, the bloat in your stomach, the wrecked blood sugar, and the fat gain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At an Indian buffet, I&amp;rsquo;m not really going to eat paleo-style. However, I&amp;rsquo;ll try to take it easy on breaded foods and especially the potatoes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;lunch-buffet&#34;&gt;Lunch buffet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lunch buffet offers two soups, a good selection of hot foods (including both meat/poultry/fish and vegetarian selections), and a cold section of salad, fruit, dessert.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/coriander-grill/two-soups.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Two soups provided&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/coriander-grill/buffet-left.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Left side of warm buffet&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/coriander-grill/buffet-right.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Right side of warm buffet&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/coriander-grill/buffet-cold.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Cold buffet&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-i-ate&#34;&gt;What I ate&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ate five rounds of food for lunch. (Yes, this was basically my meal for the entire day. In the evening yesterday, I did eat an apple and a snack, but no more than that.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first round (which I forgot to take a photo of), I ate a plate of hot food (Indian-Chinese chicken, fried veggie fritters, spinach, cauliflower/potatoes) and a full cup of sambar. I know the fried, breaded veggie fritters are not the healthiest food or buffet-optimal, but I enjoy having some.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For round 2, I had a bit of creamy chicken, vegetable korma, chickpeas, lentil dal, and more of the cauliflower/potatoes (I love that stuff). I am not a fan of creamy chicken or korma, but I always try a little bit of it because it&amp;rsquo;s there. I do very much like chickpeas and dal.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/coriander-grill/round-2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Round 2&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For round 3, I got more chickpeas, more dal, more spinach, more cauliflower/potatoes, my last veggie fritter, and a Tandoori-style chicken leg.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/coriander-grill/round-3.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Round 3&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For round 4, I got more Indian-Chinese chicken, more spinach, more chickpeas, more cauliflower/potatoes, and another cup of sambar! Halfway through this plate, I knew I was basically done eating.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/coriander-grill/round-4.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Round 4&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For my final round, I got a bit of salad (tomato, cucumber, lettuce, pickle, with some chutney), and a bit of cantaloupe and honeydew, and a wedge of lime. I like sucking lemon or lime at the end of a meal.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/coriander-grill/round-5.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Round 5&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;That was a lot of food! That was even more food than I normally eat at a buffet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and John ate some sugary desserts, but I had no room and no desire to have some myself. As I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/02/20/enjoying-more-french-dancing-in-pittsburgh/&#34;&gt;remembered recently&lt;/a&gt; at Gullifty&amp;rsquo;s, eating sugary desserts does not work well for me. I&amp;rsquo;ve resolved to do it only if something seems like it will be particularly tasty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;consequences&#34;&gt;Consequences&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I weighed myself when I got home. I had gained four pounds from the moment I left home to the point of return.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did end up getting sleepy in the afternoon and took a nap. I needed it anyway though, and I felt great the rest of the day, like I&amp;rsquo;d rebooted my body and satisfied some cravings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did gain quite a bit of extra weight, and pushed my fat percentage by one percent, but I know from experience this is temporary. My appetite today has been low, so I have naturally been eating less, and in a day or two I will have returned to my &amp;ldquo;normal&amp;rdquo; weight and fat percentage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like eating at buffets once every month or two. Having variety and knowing that I am giving my permission to eat all I want, rather than my usual policy of being much more moderate, adds a bit of excitement to my life, while probably also giving physical health benefits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-11-08&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-11-08)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year a new Indian restaurant opened in Pittsburgh, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.allindiapgh.com/&#34;&gt;All India&lt;/a&gt;. It is by far my favorite Indian restaurant in town now.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Improving my breakfast and other meals: a paleo progress report</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/01/26/improving-my-breakfast-and-other-meals/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jan 2012 09:40:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/01/26/improving-my-breakfast-and-other-meals/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In the past couple of months, I&amp;rsquo;ve made some large changes in my diet. Fundamentally, I&amp;rsquo;ve moved in a &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/paleo/&#34;&gt;paleo&lt;/a&gt; direction. The largest change was breakfast, where I completely gave up my old breakfast and &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/03/one-of-these-breakfasts-is-not-paleo/&#34;&gt;replaced it&lt;/a&gt;. After some experimentation, I&amp;rsquo;ve finally arrived at a breakfast template that seems optimal for me (as gauged by my morning energy level and other criteria I discuss below).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an example, here is what I ate this morning:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/breakfast-with-prune.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Breakfast with flax seeds and prune&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The ingredients, and what has changed, and why:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;recipe&#34;&gt;Recipe&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; tsp &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.organicfacts.net/organic-oils/organic-coconut-oil/health-benefits-of-coconut-oil.html&#34;&gt;coconut oil&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2 &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/28/thankful-for-the-free-range-orange-yolked-eggs/&#34;&gt;eggs&lt;/a&gt;, fried&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; clove of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.garlic-central.com/garlic-health.html&#34;&gt;garlic&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;some shakes of seasoning mix (salt, pepper, etc.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a dash of turmeric&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;some red pepper flakes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;butternut squash&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;spinach&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;uncooked &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.traderjoes.com/how-to/olive-oil.asp&#34;&gt;extra virgin olive oil&lt;/a&gt; on top of the veggies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;about 7 walnuts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 tsp &lt;a href=&#34;http://lowcarbdiets.about.com/od/whattoeat/a/flaxinfo.htm&#34;&gt;flax seeds&lt;/a&gt;, sprinkled on top of everything at the end&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 prune on the side&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;changes-and-rationale&#34;&gt;Changes and rationale&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;carbs&#34;&gt;Carbs&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I stopped my short experiment of eating potatoes or rice with breakfast because I found that my morning energy level was simply better without those high-glycemic carbs. I think there is a legitimate place for such carbs, but not in my current schedule, which does not (yet) include intensive exercise before breakfast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;additions&#34;&gt;Additions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I now always eat two eggs, instead of one. One wasn&amp;rsquo;t really enough to make me feel satisfied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recently added coconut oil, which I had not been using because some past experiments did not work out well. I think that was because of using too much. So I&amp;rsquo;m not using much now. Amusingly, my main use of coconut oil up till now has been to rub onto my skin during this dry winter season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve added more spices such as turmeric and hot red pepper to my breakfast because I like them and because they seem to give me a little wake-up boost and stimulate alertness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The flax seeds are new, as well as the prune. The prune is probably not &amp;ldquo;paleo&amp;rdquo;, according to someone or other, but as I&amp;rsquo;ve mentioned before, I get confused by the different paleo schools of thought, and I don&amp;rsquo;t follow any of them, but just use them as practical sources of ideas for self-experimentation. I have a very specific rationale for the use of flax seeds and prunes: I have to confess that I dealt with constipation issues when initially moving away from my big oatmeal breakfast to my paleo-style breakfast. I tried various solutions, but one that seems to have worked is the addition of flax seeds (which I typically only add for breakfast, but sometimes will also do for another meal too) and the prune. I have had no constipation issues since adding these to my breakfast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;other-meals&#34;&gt;Other meals&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been trying to kick my &amp;ldquo;addiction&amp;rdquo; to rice. I have gradually decreased my consumption of rice (white or brown). Almost imperceptibly, my craving for it has decreased continually. It&amp;rsquo;s now been a couple of days since I have been doing without rice for lunch, but I am still eating it for dinner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still love pizza, and have not yet eliminated it. It&amp;rsquo;s very hard to avoid both convenience and temptation when it&amp;rsquo;s provided at talks and meetings. However, on days when I plan to eat pizza, I have tried to get my metabolism up before eating it. That seems to help. I&amp;rsquo;ll still keep in my mind the idea of giving up pizza.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My experimentation with diet have continued over the months, and will continue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope my report may be of use to you if you are considering changing up your breakfast patterns away from the &amp;ldquo;standard&amp;rdquo; American sugary breakfasts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do you eat for breakfast that works for you? What do you similarly or differently from me?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reflections on 2011</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/12/31/reflections-on-2011/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Dec 2011 18:52:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/12/31/reflections-on-2011/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I reflect on my year of 2011 as it ends. Since I did not start blogging until September, I go into more detail of what happened before then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;january&#34;&gt;January&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I continued our project of massively reorganizing our home, a project that began when she moved in during summer 2010. We were very grateful that Abby&amp;rsquo;s father helped out a lot.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I continued getting rid of a lot of stuff, including another eighteen boxes of my books, as I became an initially reluctant &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/minimalism/&#34;&gt;minimalist&lt;/a&gt;. We sold or gave away a &lt;em&gt;huge&lt;/em&gt; number of various of belongings.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby started cooking much more than in the past, and we enjoyed trying new dishes of her making.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I enjoyed some light cross-country skiing in the winter, using the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Schenley_Park_Golf_Course&#34;&gt;Bob O&amp;rsquo;Connor Golf Course at Schenley Park&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I began a weekly Zen &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/meditation/&#34;&gt;meditation&lt;/a&gt; session offered at Carnegie Mellon University.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started moving very gradually toward a &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/paleo/&#34;&gt;paleo&lt;/a&gt; diet and exercise routine, and immediately experienced benefits. &amp;ldquo;The Paleo Solution&amp;rdquo; by &lt;a href=&#34;http://robbwolf.com/&#34;&gt;Robb Wolf&lt;/a&gt; was very useful.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started learning modern &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/javascript/&#34;&gt;JavaScript&lt;/a&gt; for a new project at work, getting into client-side Web development. As part of that, I learned &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/jquery/&#34;&gt;jQuery&lt;/a&gt; through a free &lt;a href=&#34;http://p2pu.org/&#34;&gt;P2PU&lt;/a&gt; course and used it in the project.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started using &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/XQuery&#34;&gt;XQuery&lt;/a&gt; at work to process XML in a clear and concise way. I had used XSLT in the past, but it was very unpleasant.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I decided, for various reasons, to stop writing new &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/perl/&#34;&gt;Perl&lt;/a&gt; scripts and move to &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/python/&#34;&gt;Python&lt;/a&gt; instead.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started playing in my final (and disastrous) &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/chess/&#34;&gt;chess&lt;/a&gt; tournament, the Pittsburgh Chess Club Championship (which I had won in 2006 and 2007).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;february&#34;&gt;February&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pittsburgh was all about the Steelers, and I went to a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Super_Bowl_XLV&#34;&gt;Super Bowl&lt;/a&gt; party for the first time, but we lost!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I read &amp;ldquo;The Art of Non-Conformity&amp;rdquo; by &lt;a href=&#34;http://chrisguillebeau.com/&#34;&gt;Chris Guillebeau&lt;/a&gt; and found it so inspiring that I decided to take action and start making big changes to my life, in my own way.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;One big change: I quit playing chess, cold turkey, after having been unenthusiastic about it for months already (and playing correspondingly poorly). When the passion and enjoyment are gone, there is no point in hanging onto something just because it has been such an important part of my life for years.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;After years of not playing any music at all, I started playing &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/recorder/&#34;&gt;recorder&lt;/a&gt;, and vowed to play every single day if possible. Ten months later, I am still playing recorder.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I began attending a lot of &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/16/pittsburgh-software-developer-communities/&#34;&gt;local software developer group meetings&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started learning the &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/scala/&#34;&gt;Scala&lt;/a&gt; programming language and decided to use it on a small project.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;march&#34;&gt;March&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I continued our meditation practice at CMU, and went to our first mini-&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sesshin&#34;&gt;sesshin&lt;/a&gt; on a Saturday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I continued practicing recorder every single day, and joined the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.andrew.cmu.edu/user/lukas/pcars/Welcome.html&#34;&gt;local chapter of the American Recorder Society&lt;/a&gt;. It was very exciting to meet new people and to get into a wide range of music I had never really listened to or played.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I saw a video of &lt;a href=&#34;http://jakeshimabukuro.com/&#34;&gt;Jake Shimabukuro&lt;/a&gt; playing &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/ukulele/&#34;&gt;ukulele&lt;/a&gt; so beautifully that I was inspired to buy a ukulele and start learning to play it. (Unfortunately, it would turn out that time constraints caused me not to pursue ukulele far. This will change in 2012.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I got pulled into the Ruby programming language because it is well-supported on Mac OS and it is easy to install libraries and tools, of which there are many that are quite useful.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I went to &lt;a href=&#34;http://farmtotablepa.com/&#34;&gt;Farm to Table&lt;/a&gt; in Pittsburgh, and after that, Abby started moving toward paleo eating, with even better results than my smaller experiments earlier.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I started our &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/hiking/&#34;&gt;hiking&lt;/a&gt; season in the spring. Hiking is special to us; it was one of our first shared activities (after initially meeting during salsa dancing), and one we return to again and again. When there is no calendar conflict and the weather is acceptable, we like hiking almost every weekend from spring through fall.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;{% img /images/steves-soup-hike-2011-03-26.jpg Abby in front of me at Steve&amp;rsquo;s Soup Hike %}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;april&#34;&gt;April&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started wearing &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/fivefingers/&#34;&gt;Vibram FiveFingers shoes&lt;/a&gt; almost all the time, whether walking or running (but not yet for hiking).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I went to &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/yoga/&#34;&gt;yoga&lt;/a&gt; at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.clpgh.org/locations/squirrelhill/&#34;&gt;Squirrel Hill Library&lt;/a&gt; for the first time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;may&#34;&gt;May&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I began my experiment with barefoot running, in observation of &lt;a href=&#34;http://barefootrunners.org/ibrd&#34;&gt;International Barefoot Running Day&lt;/a&gt;. I started walking around barefoot at work, ignoring the confused looks or comments of colleagues. (I still go barefoot at work.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I bought a &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/melodica/&#34;&gt;melodica&lt;/a&gt;, inspired by the amazing performances of &lt;a href=&#34;http://jnote.org/&#34;&gt;James Howard Young&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I took a little vacation, spending some days in New York visiting Nathaniel and Yael and their baby. I finally fulfilled my dream (from before marriage) of taking Abby to Coney Island to walk on the boardwalk and at the beach, eating pizza, and riding the Wonder Wheel, just as I once did when I was six years old.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I started doing research into major home renovations for the summer.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I visited my parents, and my sister Linda and her husband Andre also visited, with my mother throwing a delayed reception at home for the both of us who had gotten married in the past two years. Abby got to meet my parents&amp;rsquo; friends, finally. And I went running with my brother-in-law for the first time! Also, I took Abby to the little park in Ann Arbor where as a too-shy teenager I used to go and sit on a particular bench and wish I were sitting with my dream girl. Mission accomplished!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;june&#34;&gt;June&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;John and I did a tough 19-mile training hike on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rachelcarsontrails.org/rct&#34;&gt;Rachel Carson Trail&lt;/a&gt; and decided we&amp;rsquo;d had enough of that trail, and I decided I was probably not going to do the 35-mile &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rachelcarsontrails.org/rct/challenge&#34;&gt;Rachel Carson Trail Challenge&lt;/a&gt; again (having completed it three times in the past).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;{% img /images/rachel-carson-trail-2011-06-05.jpg John on Rachel Carson Trail %}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby started wearing Vibram FiveFingers more and more for walking and running, and even walking barefoot on the streets (something I had not yet seriously done myself at the time).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I stupidly threw out my back during exercise, and my back took weeks to fully recover (I could still run and hike, but not lift weights). Never again, I hope. I felt like a 90-year-old when my back was hurting constantly.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;We started some home improvement projects.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;july&#34;&gt;July&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started gravitating to almost exclusively body weight &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/strength-training/&#34;&gt;strength training&lt;/a&gt;, as a reaction to my having injured my back earlier.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I went kayaking on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kiskiminetas_River&#34;&gt;Kiski River&lt;/a&gt; with &amp;ldquo;Fireman Steve&amp;rdquo; and the kayaking gang.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;On a longish hike, Abby surprised me by wearing Vibram FiveFingers shoes and they worked great for her, making her much faster and less sore, and I made a note to ditch my trail running shoes (which I had been using for years for hiking) in favor of FiveFingers for my next hike (which I did, and I have not gone back to regular shoes for hiking!).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I finally took Abby to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sandhillberries.com/&#34;&gt;Sand Hill Berries&lt;/a&gt; for tasty pie for the first time, always having intended to take her there when dating, but never having been in the vicinity with her then.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Major home renovation finally began, after much research, and we got electrical upgrade, insulation, and bathroom demolition and rebuilding. Very disruptive to our lives for weeks!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I did another mini-&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sesshin&#34;&gt;sesshin&lt;/a&gt; at CMU.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;After a lifetime of almost never drinking coffee (average of maybe three or four cups a year), I became an avid espresso fan (one small cup a day) as a result of my boss getting a machine at work.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started doing more barefoot running.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;august&#34;&gt;August&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bathroom renovation done at last.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I were regularly hiking in Vibram FiveFingers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;{% img /images/abby-franklin-soup-hike-vibram.jpg Abby and Franklin on Steve&amp;rsquo;s Soup Hike part 3 wearing Vibram FiveFingers %}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby joined me to run in her first ever 5K race, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.runaroundthesquare.com/&#34;&gt;Run Around the Square&lt;/a&gt; in Regent Square (mostly on the trails of Frick Park). What a special day! This race was my first ever 5K race when I started running in races in 2000.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started to learn &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/accordion/&#34;&gt;accordion&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;september&#34;&gt;September&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started running to work two or three times a week.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I ran in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~kalp/PGR/&#34;&gt;CMU SCS Pretty Good Race 5K&lt;/a&gt; together, her second 5K race.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I went to &lt;a href=&#34;http://podcamppittsburgh.com/&#34;&gt;PodCamp Pittsburgh&lt;/a&gt;, and after that, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/22/starting-a-new-web-site/&#34;&gt;I started this blog&lt;/a&gt; and proceeded to maintain a habit of posting every day (a routine that has been modified since then).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;october&#34;&gt;October&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started expanding beyond just writing for my blog, and began contributing to the Web through &lt;a href=&#34;http://twitter.com/franklinchen&#34;&gt;my Twitter account&lt;/a&gt; as well as writing comments on other people&amp;rsquo;s blog posts.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started taking Stanford online classes: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ml-class.org/&#34;&gt;Machine Learning&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.db-class.org/&#34;&gt;Introduction to Databases&lt;/a&gt;. (Blog posts on my experiences to appear soon.) Unfortunately, as a result of the extra time commitment, October through December were quite hectic for me.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I continued to move more toward a paleo diet.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;november&#34;&gt;November&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started playing &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/flute/&#34;&gt;flute&lt;/a&gt; again.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Probably because of fatigue and a compromised immune system, I came down with a skin ailment that I got serious treatment for, but it took almost two months to completely clear up and I spent over a month truly miserable &lt;sup&gt;24&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;7&lt;/sub&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;december&#34;&gt;December&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started playing Baroque flute.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started playing tin whistle.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I prepared for and made it through two music performances, playing recorder and flute (and almost tin whistle).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I ended the year completely exhausted, on the verge of getting sick, and took a long break from blogging.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The final week, Abby and I were on a hectic travel schedule that involved meeting up with her parents, my parents, her sister Carrie, Carrie&amp;rsquo;s boyfriend Alain, Alain&amp;rsquo;s parents, Alain&amp;rsquo;s extended family, my sister Linda, and her husband Andre. I am grateful that we got to meet up with so many people (and arranged for various of the individuals to meet up with various of the others!), but the trip was quite stressful to me, because I was not physically or emotionally prepared for it at all. (I will report later on what I learned from the experience.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2011 was quite a year for me and Abby. We had many changes and adventures in our lives: our home, our diet, our exercise, our outdoors activities, travel. For me, the biggest changes were quitting chess, starting music practice and performance, throwing myself into blogging and tweeting, getting more and more active in local software developer groups, applying new (to me) development tools at work, and in the fall, taking Stanford online courses in computer science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although I ended the year in poor shape, because of being overbooked, I am very excited by how many positive changes took place. I have an entirely new set of plans and priorities to formulate soon for 2012 in collaboration with Abby, in hope of learning from the lessons of my failures and omissions of 2011, and restoring balance.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is brown rice healthy or not?</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/12/07/is-brown-rice-healthy-or-not/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Dec 2011 23:48:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/12/07/is-brown-rice-healthy-or-not/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been thinking for a year or two now about my relationship with rice, in conjunction with reading about &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/23/paleo-diet-experimentation/&#34;&gt;paleo diets&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;ve been eating rice, white or brown, for most of my life, and am now considering make some further changes to my diet (beyond &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/03/one-of-these-breakfasts-is-not-paleo/&#34;&gt;giving up oatmeal&lt;/a&gt; for an entire month now).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what now with rice?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;white-rice&#34;&gt;White rice&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was a kid, I ate white rice often, because it was something my mother provided for most meals. Actually, it was present for me at almost all meals, until I decided I wanted to eat, all the time, the sweet breakfast cereals I saw on TV.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I went off to college, I drastically changed my diet, being dependent on cafeteria food and also being tempted by opportunities to eat pizza and chicken wings and the like outside of the provided meals. I ate much less rice then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While in grad school at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cmu.edu/&#34;&gt;CMU&lt;/a&gt;, I got back into eating white rice, as a result of developing the habit of eating Indian food for lunch: I would buy lunch from either the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.tasteofindiapittsburgh.com/&#34;&gt;Taste of India&lt;/a&gt; present on campus or from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.srees.com/&#34;&gt;Sree&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/a&gt; food truck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;brown-rice-for-five-years&#34;&gt;Brown rice for five years&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For many years, I kept hearing that brown rice was healthier than white rice, and this advice was based on the idea that white rice has lost many of its nutrients and fiber during the refinement process. But I never ate brown rice because every time I tried making it, it came out unpalatable. Eventually I learned that I was making it wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2006, after hearing too often from a friend that white rice was &amp;ldquo;white death&amp;rdquo;, I took the plunge and bought a fancy Zojirushi Neuro Fuzzy rice cooker, to be able to make good brown rice as well as start eating steel cut oatmeal (which my friend also advocated eating). So it&amp;rsquo;s been over five years since I have been eating a lot of oatmeal (recently stopped) and brown rice (still going). And I have to confess that if one is going to eat steel cut oatmeal or brown rice, the Neuro Fuzzy cooker is the way to go, with its timer functions that make it trivial to generate really good results!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;paleo&#34;&gt;Paleo&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enter the paleo movement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started reading that maybe brown rice isn&amp;rsquo;t so healthy after all.  Sources such as &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.marksdailyapple.com/is-rice-unhealthy/&#34;&gt;Mark Sisson&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&#34;http://perfecthealthdiet.com/&#34;&gt;Jaminets&lt;/a&gt; argue that brown rice is harmful because of phytic acid that binds to nutrients and makes them inaccessible to us. I don&amp;rsquo;t know how true this is. But if it is true, it is worrying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sisson suggests soaking and fermenting brown rice. Having sort of tried this, I was disgusted by the results. Stephan Guyenet suggested a whole complicated-sounding protocol for &lt;a href=&#34;http://wholehealthsource.blogspot.com/2009/04/new-way-to-soak-brown-rice.html&#34;&gt;soaking brown rice&lt;/a&gt;. Looking at the comments gave me a headache.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-now&#34;&gt;What now?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what am I to do?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I eat brown rice in part to get fiber and in part to get (carb) calories. I have experimented with eating less brown rice lately, but am now considering doing an experiment in which I actually give it up for two weeks or so, to see how I feel. Giving up oatmeal has largely been a good thing for me; I rather enjoy eating a lot of veggies and more protein for breakfast. But getting rid of brown rice is much more radical.  Should I really go back to white rice?  I don&amp;rsquo;t know right now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2012-10-24&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-10-24)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Food Day in 2012, I wrote more about some &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/10/24/reflections-on-food-day/&#34;&gt;dilemmas with rice&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>One of these breakfasts is not paleo</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/11/03/one-of-these-breakfasts-is-not-paleo/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Nov 2011 22:33:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/11/03/one-of-these-breakfasts-is-not-paleo/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Over a week ago, I briefly discussed my plans to experiment more with a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/23/paleo-diet-experimentation/&#34;&gt;paleo-style diet&lt;/a&gt;. I decided to quit eating oatmeal for breakfast, cold turkey (no pun intended). I was going to stay off oatmeal for at least two weeks. Well, fourteen days of no oatmeal have gone by.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some photos of actual breakfasts I&amp;rsquo;ve had during these two weeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warning to the purists: one of these breakfasts is not paleo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/breakfast/2011-11-01-eggs-broccoli-walnuts.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Eggs, broccoli, walnuts&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/breakfast/2011-11-02-egg-lentil-soup.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Egg, lentil soup&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/breakfast/2011-11-03-eggs-broccoli-soup.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Eggs, broccoli, soup&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-three-breakfasts-depicted&#34;&gt;The three breakfasts depicted&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Two eggs, broccoli, walnuts, olive oil, spicy seasonings&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One egg, leftover &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/24/whats-a-nice-acorn-squash-like-you-doing-in-a-pot-of-spicy-lentils/&#34;&gt;lentil vegetable soup&lt;/a&gt; from freezer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Two eggs, broccoli, other leftover vegetable soup (exact contents unknown, since Abby made it)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also often use spinach in place of broccoli, and typically also eat a handful of nuts before anything else for breakfast, and take fish oil and vitamin D (the only supplements I take regularly).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;which-is-not-paleo&#34;&gt;Which is not paleo?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, the lentils are not paleo. However, Tim Ferriss &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.fourhourworkweek.com/blog/2010/09/19/paleo-diet-solution/&#34;&gt;eats them&lt;/a&gt;, and I like them and find them filling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;observations&#34;&gt;Observations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At first, I was having a lot of trouble maintaining my weight, because of a calorie deficit from skipping the carb and sugar heavy breakfast, and eating less pizza. I piled on more veggies through the day (mainly, eating more for breakfast and lunch) and have been eating more chicken and beef. I am still dependent on brown rice for lunch and dinner. I will try to formulate an experiment to reduce or eliminate that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My diet is still nowhere near paleo, because of the rice, some pizza cheating, and still eating a snack of a slice of rye bread with almond butter on most days. But the oatmeal is gone, and I don&amp;rsquo;t feel like going back. The protein/fat/veggie loaded breakfast makes me feel so much better. I am more alert from it, and when I exercise before lunch, I believe that I am more effective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m considering swapping out some of the rice in favor of lentils, for the fiber and protein. Of the legumes, I find lentils most filling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;controversy-over-paleo-and-the-nature-of-belief&#34;&gt;Controversy over paleo, and the nature of belief&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, a criticism of the paleo diet has been going around on the Web. It was offered by the anthropologist &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.npr.org/blogs/13.7/2011/10/27/141666659/the-paleo-diet-not-the-way-to-a-healthy-future&#34;&gt;Barbara J. King&lt;/a&gt;. She loves animals, is mostly vegetarian, and is concerned about factory farming and the environment. As an ex-vegetarian, certainly I share many of her concerns, and Abby and I go organic and local with our food choices (whether meat or anything else).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I think King weakens her voice by combining completely independent issues within one critique: one issue is purely scientific (what kind of diet is best for human health, and for which humans), and the others are ethical or philosophical or political. I think all the different issues should be analyzed and debated separately, then the interactions addressed. For example, what if a paleo-style diet is better for health for a substantial part of the population, and yet the demand for it creates pressure on food production? Then some kind of trade-off would need to be discussed. Or what if people moving to paleo results in fewer people eating processed food, sugar, and other products of entire industries that are arguably not beneficial to either people&amp;rsquo;s health or the environment?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a lot of &amp;ldquo;what ifs&amp;rdquo;. I believe King basically loves animals and would prefer to eliminate their use as food, globally. And that&amp;rsquo;s fine: I respect the views of ethical vegetarians, the way I respect Christians and Hindus and others who have some fundamental beliefs not to be questioned. But I think that if one starts with a fixed assumption that colors everything else in one&amp;rsquo;s life, one has to realize that one has weakened one&amp;rsquo;s ability to ask unpleasant questions that might have an undesirable answer. For example, someone who believes an embryo is a sacred life form has any moral choice other than to find every possible bit of argumentation against abortion, regardless of many questions surrounding it that lie outside the scope of the fetus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, I&amp;rsquo;m sure a lot of paleo fans simply love eating meat, and now have a  ideology suitable for rationalizing what they want to hear. From what I can tell, there&amp;rsquo;s also some intersection between paleo and certain political orientations as well. All this is very interesting to me as an observer of humanity, but for myself, I just want to know what&amp;rsquo;s true, what works (for many definitions of &amp;ldquo;works&amp;rdquo;), and have little patience for ideology. I want to know the answers, even if they call into question things I currently believe. In fact, I get excited when I&amp;rsquo;m wrong, because that means I&amp;rsquo;m alive and learning; since I don&amp;rsquo;t accept that by age 30, I&amp;rsquo;d already learned all the answers, I&amp;rsquo;d be pretty disappointed if every year since then I didn&amp;rsquo;t find something that I was wrong about and needed to correct!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Paleo diet experimentation</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/10/23/paleo-diet-experimentation/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Oct 2011 23:59:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/10/23/paleo-diet-experimentation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Three days ago, I stopped eating my usual breakfast: &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steel-cut_oats&#34;&gt;steel-cut oatmeal&lt;/a&gt; topped with fruit and nuts and maple syrup. I&amp;rsquo;d been eating oatmeal almost every day for breakfast for about 15 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the beginning of a gradual experiment toward more of a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paleolithic_diet&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Paleo diet&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is this &amp;ldquo;Paleo diet&amp;rdquo;, and why am I doing it, and why now, and how?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-s-a-paleo-diet&#34;&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s a Paleo diet?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I first heard of the &amp;ldquo;Paleo diet&amp;rdquo; an entire decade ago, back in 2002, from the &lt;a href=&#34;http://thepaleodiet.com/&#34;&gt;book&lt;/a&gt; of that name by Loren Cordain. The concept is much more popular now, with very passionate communities revolving around it, than it was then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The basic idea is simple: that our hunter-gatherer ancestors were healthy and that the Neolithic era, in which agriculture altered our diet (and our lifestyle) was the end of true human health. OK, I&amp;rsquo;m exaggerating, but that&amp;rsquo;s the idea in a nutshell: that we suffer from &amp;ldquo;diseases of civilization&amp;rdquo; because of eating stuff that we are not really evolutionarily adapted to, such as grains, beans, sugar, dairy, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not going to enter the debates over the evidence or the ideological tinges, because I&amp;rsquo;m never a &amp;ldquo;true believer&amp;rdquo; in anything anyway, and am an opportunist: I like to use interesting ideas and test whether they work for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-did-i-do-in-2002&#34;&gt;What did I do in 2002?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2002, I was still not very far removed from my one-year vegetarian experiment in 1999 (which included a couple of months of veganism). I was in drastically better health and fitness than prior to 1999, having lost 30 pounds, but knew that I could not simply chalk it up to my mostly-vegetarian diet. The fact that I was not eating junk food and processed food and crappy take-out, and had finally learned to really cook most meals for myself, clearly made a difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I was still having blood sugar issues, which I attributed to heavy consumption of refined carbs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found it hard to buy Cordain&amp;rsquo;s ideas completely. Speculation based on evolutionary &amp;ldquo;just so&amp;rdquo; stories has a long history, after all. Still, they were interesting ideas. I did find some better carbs for myself, e.g., losing the white rice and bread, going to brown rice, going to whole wheat bread, and eventually even getting away from whole wheat bread to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.foodforlife.com/&#34;&gt;Ezekiel sprouted grain bread&lt;/a&gt;. This was all based on self-experimentation, of course, not ideology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also eventually switched from old-fashioned oats to steel-cut oats, once I got a rice cooker with a timer and multiple settings that could make my steel-cut oatmeal for me every morning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Around 2007, finding out that I was definitely allergic to soy changed aspects of my diet also, since I had depended a lot on &amp;ldquo;vegetarian&amp;rdquo; type food that involved soy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In no way was I eating paleo yet, however. It just seemed too radical a change from my routine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-am-i-trying-this-now&#34;&gt;Why am I trying this now?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A year ago, the paleo diet came to my attention again in a big way, thanks to Tim Ferriss&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.fourhourworkweek.com/blog/2010/09/19/paleo-diet-solution/&#34;&gt;blog post about it&lt;/a&gt;. So I started thinking about it again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, I&amp;rsquo;d come across books such as &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.newtrendspublishing.com/SallyFallon/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nourishing Traditions&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; by Sally Fallon from the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.westonaprice.org/&#34;&gt;Weston A. Price Foundation&lt;/a&gt; that had their own take on &amp;ldquo;traditional&amp;rdquo; diets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in March 2011, Abby and I attended &lt;a href=&#34;http://farmtotablepa.com/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Farm to Table&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, a local conference that happened to be dominated by Weston A. Price people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby experimented with reducing her own consumption of cereals and breads and noticed some real benefits for herself. She actually has gone more paleo and more quickly than I have, so I have to confess that this makes it easier for me to also do my experiments, such that we&amp;rsquo;re not having major food incompatibilities eating together! For example, she gave up oatmeal almost entirely months ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;oatmeal&#34;&gt;Oatmeal&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I&amp;rsquo;ve been eating oatmeal so long, phasing it out for at least two weeks (my plan) will surely tell me something interesting about what it does to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still remember when I was having health problems in college and it took months to figure out, only by accident, that all that had happened was that I had become lactose intolerant, and so my eating Cheerios with milk every morning was causing me problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So self-experimentation is a great way to figure oneself out. Books and experts can&amp;rsquo;t do that for you. They can only give hints and possibilities. We are all different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;changes-so-far&#34;&gt;Changes so far&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, I&amp;rsquo;m not going all-out paleo (according to whatever school of thought on paleo: there are quite a lot of different interpretations of what is permitted or forbidden, as with any other &amp;ldquo;movement&amp;rdquo;). I still find it hard to believe that I should really be banning a whole lot of food I am used to eating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m starting with small but real experiments, to see what happens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, it is easy to get rid of oatmeal. I&amp;rsquo;ve already gone three days just fine. Instead, I eat an egg or two with a bowl of veggies (I especially like broccoli) and some nuts and olive oil and spices. I believe I already detect a much more stable morning energy level as a result.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a habit of eating too much pizza, as a result of going to seminars where pizza is inevitably served. Maybe I&amp;rsquo;ll pick off toppings and skip the bread, but I admit that sounds kind of unappetizing and weird.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, I have been eating brown rice for years, so it&amp;rsquo;s kind of hard for me to just give it up entirely. I&amp;rsquo;ll plan to reduce it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make up for the lost carbs, I expect to eat more vegetables and meat than in the past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;side-effects-so-far&#34;&gt;Side effects so far&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rapid loss of weight. I &lt;em&gt;do not&lt;/em&gt; want this! I am already light. I want to gain strength and vitality, not lose weight. I&amp;rsquo;m near the height and weight of Bruce Lee. What I&amp;rsquo;d like is more muscle, not lost weight. So I need to eat more fat to make up the caloric deficit of losing oatmeal.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Joys of Convict Conditioning: Bodyweight Exercising</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/10/17/the-joys-of-convict-conditioning-bodyweight-exercising/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Oct 2011 21:31:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/10/17/the-joys-of-convict-conditioning-bodyweight-exercising/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I spent the vast majority of my life completely, utterly sedentary. Let&amp;rsquo;s put it this way: I was on the phone with my father yesterday and he said he went to some free senior citizen fitness program in a mall and ended up getting sweaty, and seemed concerned. I said, &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m glad you got some good exercise!&amp;rdquo; In other words, I was raised to never get sweaty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But when I neared age 30, and was getting heavier and heavier, and almost certainly going &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prediabetes&#34;&gt;prediabetic&lt;/a&gt;, I decided to completely change my life. I took up &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/running/&#34;&gt;running&lt;/a&gt;, karate, dancing, and weight lifting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I always ended up having trouble with was weight lifting. I&amp;rsquo;d go to the gym and mess around with the machines since they were there, but although I built up some muscle, the whole process was boring, I never felt like I was really accomplishing anything, and I felt out of whack. It took years of trial and error to come to some sort of strength training regimen that I actually enjoyed and felt really benefited me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Probably my first step out of the confusing world of strength training was the book &lt;a href=&#34;http://store.coreperformance.com/store/Products/Core-Performance-Book__AP-BOOK.aspx&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Core Performance&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I still find the advice and exercises from the book tremendously useful, and highly recommend checking out the tips and videos free at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.coreperformance.com/&#34;&gt;Core Performance web site&lt;/a&gt;. (I will blog more about Core Performance in the future.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I found that when pressed for time, I would not necessarily be in the mood to get to my balance ball and free weights and do exactly what was in Core Performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, I gravitated toward a whole philosophy of &amp;ldquo;exercise anywhere, anytime, with no equipment necessary&amp;rdquo; that removes all excuses and mental friction. Welcome to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dragondoor.com/shop-by-department/books/b41/&#34;&gt;convict conditioning&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.dragondoor.com/assets/item/large/b411.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Convict Conditioning cover&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-goals&#34;&gt;My goals&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, let&amp;rsquo;s get straight what my goals are when it comes to strength training.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Not a goal&lt;/strong&gt;: getting big muscles, getting ripped. I&amp;rsquo;m a bit surprised by how many of my male friends are obsessed with getting ripped. A while ago I saw an interesting article discussing &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.freakonomics.com/2011/07/27/culture-bound-syndromes-run-amok/&#34;&gt;this obsession&lt;/a&gt;. Anyway, I have no goal of getting ripped (maybe because of my Asian cultural heritage, as suggested in the article), plus it is not possible for me anyway without steroids or something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Goal&lt;/strong&gt;: to feel fit, feel strong, and &lt;em&gt;be&lt;/em&gt; strong: i.e., so I can do reasonable things like lift and throw and punch and break a fall, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-is-convict-conditioning&#34;&gt;What is convict conditioning?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Convict conditioning basically refers to what one can do if, say, one were in jail and had no access to any particular equipment and wanted to get functionally strong, to do what is necessary to survive in such an environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OK, I don&amp;rsquo;t plan on being in such a grim survival environment, but I like the minimalist idea of making do with what one has, and not being dependent on any gadgets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, I found that once I started trying to really do pushups, pullups, and squats, they are &lt;em&gt;amazingly hard&lt;/em&gt;. I mean, it&amp;rsquo;s one thing just mechanically choosing weights at a gym and going through fixed motions with them, but it&amp;rsquo;s another thing being faced with your own body weight and realizing that you are naked, asking, &amp;ldquo;What can I do with my very body?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hate to sound mystical or something, but it&amp;rsquo;s like the distinction between subject and object blurs, and also the whole &amp;ldquo;isolating muscles&amp;rdquo; mentality disappears (which Core Performance started me on the path out of). I believe our bodies and minds are whole, and should work entirely in concert, not in isolation. So taking up bodyweight exercises seriously is, in the end, even a philosophical statement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not saying that we shouldn&amp;rsquo;t also take advantage of machines and gadgets (in fact, I still find balance balls, medicine balls, rowing machines, etc. to be useful). I&amp;rsquo;m just saying that I &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; enjoy exercise when away from all that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-detour-concerning-inactivity-and-exercise&#34;&gt;A detour concerning inactivity and exercise&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve come to believe that it is totally unnatural to compartmentalize one&amp;rsquo;s life the way I once did: sitting down working much of the day and then allocating some discrete block of time for exercise in some special location (home or gym).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reading &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.timferriss.com/&#34;&gt;Tim Ferriss&lt;/a&gt; and his long-running &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.fourhourworkweek.com/blog/&#34;&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt; and his recent book &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.fourhourbody.com/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The 4-Hour Body&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, as well as sources from the whole broad &lt;a href=&#34;http://robbwolf.com/&#34;&gt;paleo&lt;/a&gt;/&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.marksdailyapple.com/&#34;&gt;primal&lt;/a&gt; diet and lifestyle, and hearing about the research showing how bad it is to be &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.geekosystem.com/sitting-health-dangers/&#34;&gt;sitting&lt;/a&gt; for an extended period at all, I&amp;rsquo;ve made sure to take frequent breaks away from my computer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When taking a break, I might just walk to get some water or stretch, but now that I know of the benefits of intermittent sprints of intense activity, convict conditioning becomes even more relevant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;practical-advantages-of-bodyweight-exercising&#34;&gt;Practical advantages of bodyweight exercising&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From a practical point of view, pushups, pullups, and squats are great because I can do them almost anywhere, anytime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will often just get down on the floor at work or at home, and do various forms of pushups, or squats. That gets the blood flowing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pullups are trickier, because although I have tried doing them by grasping onto the top of my office door frame at work, it&amp;rsquo;s painful and unreliable.  However, at home, I have on the frame of one entryway a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.doorgym.net/&#34;&gt;Door Gym&lt;/a&gt; pullup bar, which I use at random times when passing through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Needless to say, bodyweight exercising comes in handy also when traveling, or attending some all-day conference or other such event. It&amp;rsquo;s easy to go hide somewhere momentarily and do a bunch of pushups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I have found in the past year that just doing a few seconds of intense activity to boost my metabolism before eating has a noticeable effect in decreasing my fat percentage. This stuff works!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;progress&#34;&gt;Progress&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pullups have always been really hard for me, but as of today, to my surprise, I&amp;rsquo;m finally up to eight reps from a dead hang.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still am nowhere near doing a single one-arm pullup or pushup. I love a challenge. We&amp;rsquo;ll see when I get there.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>