<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Constitution on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/constitution/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Constitution on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/constitution/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>How learning about the Magna Carta in high school changed my life</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/06/13/how-learning-about-the-magna-carta-in-high-school-changed-my-life/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Jun 2015 15:35:30 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/06/13/how-learning-about-the-magna-carta-in-high-school-changed-my-life/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I couldn&amp;rsquo;t help noticing the headlines in the news lately about the
800th anniversary of the
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Magna_Carta&#34;&gt;Magna Carta&lt;/a&gt;, that
historical document from 1215 in England. As I write, apparently there
is a
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bbc.com/news/uk-england-33116579&#34;&gt;celebration being held on the River Thames&lt;/a&gt;,
even. And I just found a Web site devoted entirely to this
&lt;a href=&#34;http://magnacarta800th.com/&#34;&gt;800th anniversary&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Magna Carta has not been on my mind for over thirty years since I
first learned about it in a social studies class in the ninth grade high
school in the early 1980s. But when I think about it, the surprising
truth is that learning about the Magna Carta was a &lt;em&gt;turning point&lt;/em&gt; in
my life as a new teenager (age twelve or thirteen), and the lessons I
learned have informed me throughout my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-is-the-magna-carta-associated-with&#34;&gt;What is the Magna Carta associated with?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Magna Carta in popular imagination is associated with &amp;ldquo;liberty&amp;rdquo;,
with &amp;ldquo;the people&amp;rdquo; rising up in revolt against arbitrary monarchy and
making King John sign a document guaranteeing basic rights, such as
the right to a fair trail and no taxation without representation; and
&amp;ldquo;equality&amp;rdquo;, putting the king himself under the scope of law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Magna Carta is thought of as an inspiration for
subsequent milestones in history such as the United States Declaration
of Independence and the &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/constitution/&#34;&gt;Constitution&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-truth-as-i-learned-it&#34;&gt;The truth as I learned it&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I took a required &amp;ldquo;social studies&amp;rdquo; class in the ninth grade in high
school. It was one of the most interesting and life-changing classes I
ever took. I remember more from that class than probably any other in
all of high school. I loved the class because it was a small honors
class, didn&amp;rsquo;t follow a standard textbook, the teacher had us engage in
discussions, and we did many interesting activities such as watch
films and play games and do simulations. She used a kind of &amp;ldquo;Socratic
method&amp;rdquo; to direct us and get us thinking and offering our opinions
with reasons. &lt;em&gt;This was the one of the first (and few) times in school
in which I felt I was being treated as an independent adult-to-be, not
as a child.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is what I learned in ninth grade social studies class from the
coverage of the Magna Carta:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John,_King_of_England&#34;&gt;King John&lt;/a&gt; was
just one of a line of random kings in history who gained their power
from accident of birth rather than anything else.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Our teacher made fun of an artist&amp;rsquo;s fictional depiction of King
John&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;signing&amp;rdquo; the Magna Carta, arguing that since King John was
illiterate, he could not have signed it, and usual practice was to
press his seal on documents. (Amusingly, there is still
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bbc.com/news/blogs-magazine-monitor-30879124&#34;&gt;online discussion of this detail&lt;/a&gt;
decades after my class.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The whole Magna Carta thing came out of a civil war. It wasn&amp;rsquo;t like
one side was really right and the king was particularly evil as far
as kings went back in the day.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A bunch of &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Landed_gentry&#34;&gt;landed nobility&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Collusion&#34;&gt;colluded&lt;/a&gt; to protect their
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Collective_bargaining&#34;&gt;collective interests&lt;/a&gt;.
Basically, they tried to form the first &amp;ldquo;union&amp;rdquo; against royal
interests.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This document did not have anything to do with &amp;ldquo;the people&amp;rdquo; as such
(who in those days lived in abject misery whether under the nobility
or the king). The Magna Carta was not for the &amp;ldquo;little people&amp;rdquo;. Its
clauses were specific about whom they applied to, i.e., &amp;ldquo;free men&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Magna Carta was the product of a power struggle among those who
already had power. It was about power and money. A bunch of
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rent-seeking&#34;&gt;rent-seeking&lt;/a&gt; nobility
didn&amp;rsquo;t like that the king was arbitrarily cutting in on them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Magna Carta was originally a flop: civil war continued, King
John ignored its rules. But it proved useful later symbolically when
conditions changed, proved to be something to rally around and
reinterpret for a new age.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;no-untarnished-heroes&#34;&gt;No untarnished heroes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest question that arose in discussion was, should we be
cynical about the Magna Carta because of what it was originally for,
as opposed to what it later became to stand for or how it inspired
more far-reaching change? I think we can ask that of anything,
especially, for those of us in the United States, of our own
perception of our Founding Fathers and the nature of the American
Revolution, which all occurred five hundred years after the Magna
Carta.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I learned from the study of history (which I enjoyed so much I
took two non-required world history courses in the tenth grade before
the required American history sequence in the eleventh grade) that
there are no easy answers, and that it is important to be skeptical of
mythologizing the past. I have remembered these lessons long after not
thinking about the Magna Carta again after that class in the ninth
grade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The noblemen who came up with the Magna Carta may have been thinking
only of themselves, but might have unwittingly paved the way for
others. Intention is one thing, but the final result is another
thing. (And history shows that there never is a final result either.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;some-interesting-resources-on-the-magna-carta&#34;&gt;Some interesting resources on the Magna Carta&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a &lt;a href=&#34;http://the-orb.net/textbooks/muhlberger/magna_carta.html&#34;&gt;medieval studies textbook section on the Magna Carta&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did not touch upon the religion aspect of the power struggles in the
medieval era (such as King John&amp;rsquo;s fights with the Pope; three hundred
years after King John, the whole
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Church_of_England&#34;&gt;Church of England&lt;/a&gt;
finally split off from Catholicism when King Henry VIII wanted to
annul a marriage but the Pope wouldn&amp;rsquo;t let him), but here is a
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/09531a.htm&#34;&gt;Catholic encyclopedia article about the Magna Carta&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s an article about a Magna Carta skeptic, a British judge who
calls it an insignificant, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/uknews/law-and-order/11670716/Magna-Carta-Turgid-document-was-eclipsed-by-the-French-says-top-judge.html&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;turgid document&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can search online for a whole lot more commentary, given the
hugeness of this 800th anniversary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;here-s-that-fictional-depiction&#34;&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s that fictional depiction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:A_Chronicle_of_England_-_Page_226_-_John_Signs_the_Great_Charter.jpg#/media/File:A_Chronicle_of_England_-_Page_226_-_John_Signs_the_Great_Charter.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;A Chronicle of England - Page 226 - John Signs the Great Charter.jpg&#34; src=&#34;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/d/d6/A_Chronicle_of_England_-_Page_226_-_John_Signs_the_Great_Charter.jpg&#34; height=&#34;480&#34; width=&#34;598&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#34;&lt;a href=&#34;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:A_Chronicle_of_England_-_Page_226_-_John_Signs_the_Great_Charter.jpg#/media/File:A_Chronicle_of_England_-_Page_226_-_John_Signs_the_Great_Charter.jpg&#34;&gt;A Chronicle of England - Page 226 - John Signs the Great Charter&lt;/a&gt;&#34; by &lt;a href=&#34;//en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_William_Edmund_Doyle&#34; class=&#34;extiw&#34; title=&#34;en:James William Edmund Doyle&#34;&gt;James William Edmund Doyle&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;a href=&#34;//en.wikipedia.org/wiki/James_William_Edmund_Doyle&#34; class=&#34;extiw&#34; title=&#34;w:James William Edmund Doyle&#34;&gt;Doyle, James William Edmund&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;span style=&#34;white-space:nowrap&#34;&gt;1864&lt;/span&gt;) &#34;&lt;a rel=&#34;nofollow&#34; class=&#34;external text&#34; href=&#34;http://books.google.com.sg/books?id=YcM_AAAAYAAJ&amp;amp;pg=PA226&#34;&gt;John&lt;/a&gt;&#34; in &lt;a rel=&#34;nofollow&#34; class=&#34;external text&#34; href=&#34;http://books.google.com.sg/books?id=YcM_AAAAYAAJ&#34;&gt;A Chronicle of England: B.C. 55 – A.D. 1485&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;//en.wikipedia.org/wiki/London&#34; class=&#34;extiw&#34; title=&#34;en:London&#34;&gt;London&lt;/a&gt;: Longman, Green, Longman, Roberts &amp;amp; Green, pp.&amp;nbsp;p. 226 Retrieved on &lt;span style=&#34;white-space:nowrap&#34;&gt;12 November 2010&lt;/span&gt;.. Licensed under Public Domain via &lt;a href=&#34;//commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/&#34;&gt;Wikimedia Commons&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;extrapolations&#34;&gt;Extrapolations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, all around us we see fights that are supposedly about principle
but are really power struggles. Instead of landed nobility, we have
powerful lobbying groups, multinational corporations, you name
it. When any of these interests collude to win a battle over some
other one, they might not be in the game for you and me, but for
themselves. The purported idea of &amp;ldquo;democracy&amp;rdquo; is in fact under siege
today on many fronts. In future blog posts, I will begin exploring
what some of these are; they mostly involve technology-based power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2015-06-14&#34;&gt;(Update of 2015-06-14)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the local paper, I just read this really interesting article by
University of Pittsburgh law professor Bernard Hibbits on the
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.post-gazette.com/news/world/2015/06/14/How-Magna-Carta-helped-make-America/stories/201506150001&#34;&gt;opportunistic use of the Magna Carta by Americans&lt;/a&gt; throughout history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2015-06-16&#34;&gt;(Update of 2015-06-16)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A random
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bbc.com/news/uk-33126723&#34;&gt;news article about the celebrations&lt;/a&gt;
feature nothing but photos or descriptions of an Archbishop, the
Queen, various Dukes, a Prince, a Princess, a Lord, a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.therichest.com/celebnetworth/politician/minister/david-cameron-net-worth/&#34;&gt;Prime Minister&lt;/a&gt;
who
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_Cameron#Inheritance_and_family_wealth&#34;&gt;inherited much wealth (a lot hidden in tax shelters)&lt;/a&gt;,
and had no photos of &amp;ldquo;regular people&amp;rdquo;, or quotes from them asking what
they thought of the lavish occasion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yeah, same old, same old, 800 years later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Learning about the Magna Carta as a twelve-year-old was an important
part of my growing up in life. I learned that people are human and
selfish and have different motivations, but sometimes can work toward
agreements at least among themselves as equals, and some other party
as well. But I also learned the lesson that there are always those
who are left out at the bargaining table, and that the nobility are
always looking out for themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When did you learn about the Magna Carta in school? Did you learn it
  in the same gritty way that I did, or in a more romanticized way?
  Are there things you learned in history classes in school that
  changed your life, changed what you believe and how you act (as a
  voter or activist)?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Observing Constitution Day with &#34;The Supreme Court and Privacy: The Fourth Amendment in the Digital Age&#34;</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/09/17/observing-constitution-day-with-the-supreme-court-and-privacy-the-fourth-amendment-in-the-digital-age/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2014 21:54:01 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/09/17/observing-constitution-day-with-the-supreme-court-and-privacy-the-fourth-amendment-in-the-digital-age/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have a habit of observing Constitution Day every year by attending a presentation at CMU and thinking about issues relating to the Constitution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year (2013), &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/09/17/on-not-celebrating-constitution-day-this-year&#34;&gt;I was too disheartened to observe Constitution Day but wrote a little bit about why&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year, I returned because the topic for discussion sounded interesting: &lt;a href=&#34;http://thebridge.cmu.edu/organization/SLO/calendar/details/466499&#34;&gt;Mary Jo Miller gave a talk &amp;ldquo;The Supreme Court and Privacy: The Fourth Amendment in the Digital Age&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; in the Posner Center. (Miller is a Staff Attorney for the Pennsylvania State Education Association and an adjunct professor in Carnegie Mellon&amp;rsquo;s Social and Decision Sciences Department.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/franklinmingchen/15274305882&#34; title=&#34;IMG_20140917_163751 by Franklin Chen, on Flickr&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3836/15274305882_f0eaf5d8fb.jpg&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; height=&#34;375&#34; alt=&#34;IMG_20140917_163751&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-fourth-amendment-http-en-wikipedia-org-wiki-fourth-amendment-to-the-united-states-constitution&#34;&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fourth_Amendment_to_the_United_States_Constitution&#34;&gt;fourth amendment&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
The right of the people to be secure in their persons, houses, papers, and effects, against unreasonable searches and seizures, shall not be violated, and no warrants shall issue, but upon probable cause, supported by oath or affirmation, and particularly describing the place to be searched, and the persons or things to be seized.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mary Jo Miller gave an entertaining and instructive talk in which she discussed various rulings by the Supreme Court involving interpretations of the fourth amendment in various circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, she reminded us that the fourth amendment came about because of the colonialists&amp;rsquo; bad experiences with England when arbitrary searches of people&amp;rsquo;s home happened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then she argued that although it is popularly held that there is a &amp;ldquo;conservative&amp;rdquo; (&amp;ldquo;originalist&amp;rdquo;) wing of the Supreme Court (typified currently by Scalia) and a &amp;ldquo;liberal&amp;rdquo; (&amp;ldquo;living Constitution&amp;rdquo;) wing (typified in the past by Stevens), on fourth amendment issues, they are not always split. In fact, she gave examples of where the Court was unanimous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The primary concern by the Court has been to respect (in the absence of probable cause) the doctrine that &amp;ldquo;each man&amp;rsquo;s home is his castle&amp;rdquo;. Miller gave examples involving surveillance of a marijuana grower&amp;rsquo;s home through a heat detector, as well as examining the contents of a drug dealer&amp;rsquo;s cell phone, as being judged a violation of fourth amendment rights because of what can be considered one&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;home&amp;rdquo;: a cell phone is actually a computer containing much of one&amp;rsquo;s possession, so it is in fact one&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;home&amp;rdquo; and requires a proper warrant in order to search it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s about the &amp;ldquo;exclusionary rule&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;fruits of the poison tree&amp;rdquo;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/franklinmingchen/15271576131&#34; title=&#34;IMG_20140917_164820 by Franklin Chen, on Flickr&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5596/15271576131_6c4a8f4d5f.jpg&#34; width=&#34;375&#34; height=&#34;500&#34; alt=&#34;IMG_20140917_164820&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-about-the-nsa&#34;&gt;What about the NSA?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After almost an hour, I had to leave, and therefore did not stay for questions and answers. I would have asked about what the current thinking is by the Court about NSA surveillance. When is information far enough removed that it is no longer considered one&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;home&amp;rdquo;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did enjoy this year&amp;rsquo;s Constitution Day observance at CMU. Mary Jo Miller gave an excellent talk discussing various Supreme Court rulings and different aspects of the fourth amendment.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On not celebrating Constitution Day this year, 2013</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/09/17/on-not-celebrating-constitution-day-this-year/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Sep 2013 08:42:26 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/09/17/on-not-celebrating-constitution-day-this-year/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;For several years, I&amp;rsquo;ve made a habit of observing &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Constitution_Day_(United_States)&#34;&gt;Constitution Day&lt;/a&gt; by attending the annual exhibit and lecture at CMU. Last year I reported on &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/18/is-constitution-day-constitutional/&#34;&gt;an interesting session about the very invention of Constitution Day&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://events.web.cmu.edu/ecal/event/137831259599848837&#34;&gt;This year&lt;/a&gt;, the program for the event &lt;a href=&#34;http://cmlibblog.wordpress.com/2013/08/13/constitution-day-celebration/&#34;&gt;held at the Posner Center&lt;/a&gt; at CMU read:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
David Harris, distinguished faculty scholar and professor of law at the University of Pittsburgh School of Law, will deliver a keynote speech titled &#34;How Will America Be Remembered? A Constitution Day Journey Into the Future&#34; at approximately 3:30 p.m. Light refreshments will be served. An original copy of the Bill of Rights will be on display.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ended up deciding not to attend today, for several reasons. One is that I have a lot of stuff to get done at work right now. But even if that weren&amp;rsquo;t the case, my heart was not into celebrating Constitution Day this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-will-america-be-remembered&#34;&gt;How will America be remembered?&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/6/60/Edward_Snowden-2.jpg/199px-Edward_Snowden-2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Because the story is still far from over, I haven&amp;rsquo;t said much on my blog about the events that have been unfolding for some months now since &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_Snowden&#34;&gt;Edward Snowden&lt;/a&gt; exposed information about the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2013_mass_surveillance_disclosures&#34;&gt;surveillance activities of the National Security Agency&lt;/a&gt;. He &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.theguardian.com/world/2013/jul/12/edward-snowden-full-statement-moscow&#34;&gt;explained his actions as justified by the violation of the 4th and 5th Amendments to the Constitution&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
The 4th and 5th Amendments to the Constitution of my country, Article 12 of the Universal Declaration of Human Rights, and numerous statutes and treaties forbid such systems of massive, pervasive surveillance. While the US Constitution marks these programs as illegal, my government argues that secret court rulings, which the world is not permitted to see, somehow legitimize an illegal affair. These rulings simply corrupt the most basic notion of justice -- that it must be seen to be done. The immoral cannot be made moral through the use of secret law.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I do a Web search for &amp;ldquo;Edward Snowden&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Constitution&amp;rdquo;, I mostly find pro-Snowden articles that affirm his point of view of the NSA programs as being unconstitutional. Here is &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.newsworks.org/index.php/blogs/brandywine-to-broad/item/56244-nsa-leaks-by-edward-snowden-threaten-constitutional-self-government&#34;&gt;one exception&lt;/a&gt; you may wish to read.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find it interesting that much of the media coverage of Edward Snowden&amp;rsquo;s actions do not actually reference his claim of unconstitutionality, but focus on other matters, such as the nature of his education or possible ulterior motives for leaking, or whether his actions may prove harmful to national security or other interests. These may be interesting and important questions, but sidestep his primary claim and stated motive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;too-early-to-tell&#34;&gt;Too early to tell&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did not attend the &lt;a href=&#34;http://wesa.fm/post/us-constitution-224-years-later-why-it-endures&#34;&gt;David Harris&lt;/a&gt;, although it might have been interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think Snowden&amp;rsquo;s actions and their repercussions will add an extra twist to the age-old question of whether the Constitution is to be interpreted under &amp;ldquo;original intent&amp;rdquo; or as a &amp;ldquo;living document&amp;rdquo;, and even whether the Constitution should be &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2012/12/31/opinion/lets-give-up-on-the-constitution.html&#34;&gt;abandoned&lt;/a&gt;, if interpretations either way simply come to be seen as purely political game-playing to justify &amp;ldquo;constitutional&amp;rdquo; as simply meaning &amp;ldquo;what I like&amp;rdquo;. The most interesting thing right now is that prominent voices on both the &amp;ldquo;left&amp;rdquo; and the &amp;ldquo;right&amp;rdquo; (the libertarian wing) have united in denouncing the activities of the NSA as unconstitutional.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not a political blog, and political theory is not my main area of interest or advocacy, but I thought it would be useful to make a few observations about current events for Constitution Day.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is Constitution Day Constitutional?</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/09/18/is-constitution-day-constitutional/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Sep 2012 11:01:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/09/18/is-constitution-day-constitutional/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.cmu.edu/posner-center/exhibits/special-images/billrights1.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Bill of Rights at CMU&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Yesterday was &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Constitution_Day_(United_States)&#34;&gt;Constitution Day&lt;/a&gt;, which I&amp;rsquo;ve &amp;ldquo;observed&amp;rdquo; in some fashion since 2005, which was when I saw the first annual announcement of its observance at Carnegie Mellon University. My memory is fuzzy about what I actually did on Constitution Day on most years, but I remember that in 2005 I stopped by the Posner Center to look at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cmu.edu/posner-center/exhibits/bill-of-rights.html&#34;&gt;one of the four existing copies of the US Bill of Rights&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, I watched Pittsburgh Councilman &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.billpeduto.com/&#34;&gt;Bill Peduto&lt;/a&gt; speak at CMU; I remember him focusing a lot on the Bill of Rights and our need to be vigilant in protecting our rights, and telling of his concerns resulting from incidents that happened during the &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittnews.com/newsstory/city-departments-to-investigate-circumstances-of-g-20-arrests/&#34;&gt;G-20&lt;/a&gt;. This year, Magisterial District Judge &lt;a href=&#34;http://judgepedia.org/index.php/Hugh_F._McGough&#34;&gt;Hugh F. McGough&lt;/a&gt; was the featured speaker at CMU; he spoke about the history of the Pennsylvania judicial system and of constitutions in general.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I never actually knew or thought about the origin and nature of Constitution Day until yesterday. I was surprised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-is-constitution-day-observed&#34;&gt;Why is Constitution Day observed?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out (and I did not know this until it was discussed during the presentation) that Constitution Day is a recent invention. It was first observed in 2005, after a bill on spending was amended by Senator Robert Byrd to include the establishment of Constitution Day. The law mandated that any school receiving federal funds had to observe Constitution Day and teach something about the American Constitution on that day (or an adjacent weekday in case of a weekend).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;posner-s-objection&#34;&gt;Posner&amp;rsquo;s objection&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happening to be present at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cmu.edu/posner-center/&#34;&gt;Posner Center&lt;/a&gt;, and in fact sitting next to me during the presentation, were &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rrdc.com/mgmt_bio_posner.html&#34;&gt;Henry Posner III&lt;/a&gt; and his wife. When a question was asked of them near the end of the presentation, regarding whether they thought the institution of Constitution Day was a good idea, Mr. Posner responded in a very interesting way.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.rrdc.com/images/posner.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Henry Posner III&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Mr. Posner quite emphatically stated that he objected to how Constitution Day was slipped into the spending bill with a &amp;ldquo;political&amp;rdquo; agenda and with a mandate and a condition (in order for a school to receive federal funding).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought this objection was interesting and could lead to a good debate, on Constitution Day itself of all days, about what is or should be constitutional, but I really had to leave right after the talk, so I did not stay around to discuss the matter with Mr. Posner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later in the evening, however, I did look up Mr. Posner, since by demeanor and words he struck me as probably having strong libertarian views. I believe I confirmed that in my Web searches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, as I came up with a catchy title for my blog post, I found that others had already used my title. Someone at the George Mason University School of Law in fact had already written &lt;a href=&#34;http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=893903&#34;&gt;a little paper&lt;/a&gt; with the exact title, &amp;ldquo;Is Constitution Day Constitutional?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And last year someone wrote an article, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2011/09/17/opinion/constitution-day-happy-illegal-holiday.html&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Happy Illegal Holiday!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-reactions&#34;&gt;My reactions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not a lawyer, and even if I were, the notion of what is &amp;ldquo;unconstitutional&amp;rdquo; is, as we have seen again and again in the divided opinions on the Supreme Court, controversial. I see the point in being unhappy with too many federal mandates, but at the same time, from a pragmatic point of view, Constitution Day observance does not appear to be too onerous, and I happen to have inadvertently enjoyed and learned from its observance at CMU over since 2005.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed CMU&amp;rsquo;s observance of Constitution Day this year, learning some things about Pennsylvania and other state history from the Honorable Hugh McGough as well as picking up on the history of Constitution Day itself and Mr. Posner&amp;rsquo;s objection to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-09-17&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-09-17)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/09/17/on-not-celebrating-constitution-day-this-year/&#34;&gt;chose not to celebrate Constitution Day in 2013&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2014-09-17&#34;&gt;(Update of 2014-09-17)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I returned to observing Constitution in &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/09/17/observing-constitution-day-with-the-supreme-court-and-privacy-the-fourth-amendment-in-the-digital-age/&#34;&gt;2014&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>