<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Pittsburgh on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/pittsburgh/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Pittsburgh on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/pittsburgh/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>How I avoid demotivating myself away from voting</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/01/how-i-avoid-demotivating-myself-away-from-voting/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Nov 2014 22:11:10 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/01/how-i-avoid-demotivating-myself-away-from-voting/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s that time of year again: three days from today is Election Day. I&amp;rsquo;ve written a few posts about voting over the past couple of years here already, and I&amp;rsquo;ve clearly changed my attitude about it over time:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/08/i-dont-know-if-i-should-vote-but-i-did/&#34;&gt;November 2011&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;April 2012: I was too apathetic to vote.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/11/06/i-decided-to-resign-myself-to-continue-voting/&#34;&gt;November 2012&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/05/21/voting-in-the-face-of-election-apathy/&#34;&gt;May 2013&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;November 2013: I voted but wrote nothing about it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/05/20/why-i-voted-yet-again/&#34;&gt;May 2014&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is my first post &lt;em&gt;before&lt;/em&gt; an Election Day rather than &lt;em&gt;after&lt;/em&gt; having voted. Why the change this time?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;reflections-on-my-past-behavior-and-attitudes&#34;&gt;Reflections on my past behavior and attitudes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have always been frustrated by politics and voting. That showed in my posts in the last three years. I always got very &lt;em&gt;emotional&lt;/em&gt; and torn about the whole process. I finally settled on a habit of trying to &lt;em&gt;minimize&lt;/em&gt; my involvement, not paying attention to any races or &amp;ldquo;debates&amp;rdquo; or any political coverage in the news until the night before Election Day, but I was still unhappy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-situation-now&#34;&gt;The situation now&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, it is still the case that I have not looked at any political coverage for Tuesday. In fact, I have no idea who&amp;rsquo;s running for what, with one major exception: Governor of Pennsylvania. That&amp;rsquo;s been in the news for a year now, and totally unavoidable if you live in PA at all, and especially if you bothered to vote in the primary in May, which I did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that I am accidentally less &lt;em&gt;angry&lt;/em&gt; now than I used to be, because unknown to me, Abby has intercepted all political flyers arriving in our mailbox or &lt;em&gt;on our doorknob&lt;/em&gt; (how dare they!) and recycled them, with one exception.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;negative-emotions-came-back&#34;&gt;Negative emotions came back&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I saw a flyer in a pile of mail. I tried not to see anything as I picked it up and recycled it, but it was impossible to see &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt;. I have to hand it to the designer: the name of the politician reached my eye somehow, even though I prided myself on not seeing a single word (at least consciously) of anything else on the flyer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A rush of disgust and anger came my way, as I reflected that actually, this is someone I already decided last May in the primary to vote for in the general election. As I&amp;rsquo;ve mentioned in previous posts, flyers that are shouting, negative, fear-mongering, and deceptive &lt;em&gt;piss me off&lt;/em&gt; and make me want to &lt;em&gt;puke down the throats&lt;/em&gt; of these politicians, &lt;em&gt;especially those I expect to vote for&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Note that in order to minimize bias, I have never heard this guy talk, and barely recall what he looks like, although I think I saw some head shot back in May. Also, I have no idea what he&amp;rsquo;s been doing or saying since May, or whether any truly major scandal has broken out, although I assume I would have heard by now if so. I will learn what I need to know on Monday night.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;taking-more-control&#34;&gt;Taking more control&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But now, after having &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/10/31/win-ugly-or-lose-pretty-do-you-agree/&#34;&gt;read that fascinating article yesterday about emotional manipulation&lt;/a&gt;, I have decided that these politicians are only doing the rational thing in their game, nothing personal. You might want to argue that this is a flaw in democracy, as many ancient and modern philosophers have, of course, but that would be another topic of discussion entirely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was also annoyed by the robocall on the answering machine at home today, from the same guy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;action-to-further-minimize-annoyance&#34;&gt;Action to further minimize annoyance&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We shut off the answering machine for our land line. We will not be answering any phone calls until after Election Day. Actually, we are not sure why we need any phones connected to our land line anyway, because in principle we could make sure all relevant accounts list our cell phones as our primary phone numbers (most already do but some old ones don&amp;rsquo;t yet). We only need the land line for DSL purposes. The land line has been mostly nothing but trouble, a target for robocalls of all kinds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, I wish there were a way to stop getting junk mail in general. Not just the election season junk mail, but all junk mail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There will be no Election Day blog post on Tuesday. I&amp;rsquo;ve said all I need to say for this Election Day.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Climbing the Cathedral of Learning to get to the Harvard Classics</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/10/22/climbing-the-cathedral-of-learning-to-get-to-the-harvard-classics/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Oct 2014 23:12:24 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/10/22/climbing-the-cathedral-of-learning-to-get-to-the-harvard-classics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I recently learned that the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Harvard_Classics&#34;&gt;Harvard Classics&lt;/a&gt;, a 51-volume set of classic writings first published in 1909, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.openculture.com/2014/03/the-harvard-classics-download-all-51-volumes-as-free-ebooks.html&#34;&gt;are now available for free download as ebooks&lt;/a&gt;. This isn&amp;rsquo;t really news, but was just something that appeared on my radar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What relevance such an ancient collection has today is an interesting question, especially in light of the fact that a century ago the concept of what was of interest in the history of the &amp;ldquo;world&amp;rdquo; was fairly narrow, but not something I&amp;rsquo;m discussing right now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a hunch where I could find a physical copy of the Harvard Classics. I tested my hunch:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/franklinmingchen/15415427937&#34; title=&#34;IMG_20141022_113213 by Franklin Chen, on Flickr&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5607/15415427937_62f9d10eae.jpg&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; height=&#34;375&#34; alt=&#34;IMG_20141022_113213&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;sightings&#34;&gt;Sightings&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have seen this type of material (including, of course sets of encyclopedias) in many places, including personal homes: dusty, hardly opened volumes handed down generation after generation, perhaps, or acquired at bargain prices from library or garage sales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But most interesting to me is seeing it in public places. In particularly, I suddenly had the suspicion (or unconscious memory) that the 36th floor of the Cathedral of Learning at Pitt, which has book shelves of many old books, might have the Harvard Classics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;climbing-the-cathedral&#34;&gt;Climbing the Cathedral&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/franklinmingchen/15601416745&#34; title=&#34;IMG_20141022_114120 by Franklin Chen, on Flickr&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3932/15601416745_5c49f2fbdf.jpg&#34; width=&#34;375&#34; height=&#34;500&#34; alt=&#34;IMG_20141022_114120&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I used my curiosity to stop by the Cathedral of Learning near lunch time and climb to the 36th floor, a curious form of exercise I hadn&amp;rsquo;t engaged in for quite some time, maybe almost a year by now. I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/04/i-had-no-choice-but-to-barefoot-climb-the-cathedral-of-learning/&#34;&gt;took off my shoes and socks&lt;/a&gt; and jacket, and stuffed them in my backpack before beginning the ascent. I am currently out of shape and started feeling nauseous probably around the 25th floor, but made it to the top:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/franklinmingchen/15415427937&#34; title=&#34;IMG_20141022_113213 by Franklin Chen, on Flickr&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5607/15415427937_62f9d10eae.jpg&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; height=&#34;375&#34; alt=&#34;IMG_20141022_113213&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There they were, the Harvard Classics!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/franklinmingchen/15601416115&#34; title=&#34;IMG_20141022_113305 by Franklin Chen, on Flickr&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3944/15601416115_470d900851.jpg&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; height=&#34;375&#34; alt=&#34;IMG_20141022_113305&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Physically old books have a durability and charm to them. Here&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;The Pilgrim&amp;rsquo;s Progress&amp;rdquo;, a book I actually acquired &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/12/22/a-favorite-poem-to-share-as-2013-comes-to-an-end&#34;&gt;by accident at age 9 along with many others&lt;/a&gt; but never really read (I tried but it was too confusing, despite the illustrations):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/franklinmingchen/15598756521&#34; title=&#34;IMG_20141022_113328 by Franklin Chen, on Flickr&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5615/15598756521_c5fe055973.jpg&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; height=&#34;375&#34; alt=&#34;IMG_20141022_113328&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-note-on-the-elevator-modernization-project&#34;&gt;A note on the &amp;ldquo;elevator modernization project&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After I climb to the top of the Cathedral of Learning, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/11/03/the-dilemma-of-how-to-descend-the-cathedral-of-learning-once-at-the-top/&#34;&gt;I have to choose whether to take an elevator down&lt;/a&gt;, and this time was no exception.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that an elevator appeared quickly before I had to decide whether to just walk down 36 floors, so I hopped in with some other people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I heard a lot of complaints about elevator waits thanks to elevators being out of service. People talked about waiting &lt;em&gt;fifteen to twenty minutes&lt;/em&gt; before giving up sometimes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I kept my mouth shut about the fact that it only takes far less time to either ascend or descend the entire Cathedral on the stairs; this is not a nation of walkers, and everyone has personal reasons not to take the stairs. There are many good reasons to improve accessibility between all the floors of the Cathedral for all people, and I have found the elevators unreliable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Getting back to the bottom, I saw a sign that explained the situation: there is an &amp;ldquo;elevator modernization project&amp;rdquo; in progress to try to considerably improve the elevator situation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/franklinmingchen/15577746826&#34; title=&#34;IMG_20141022_113740 by Franklin Chen, on Flickr&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3944/15577746826_4ee00263a0.jpg&#34; width=&#34;375&#34; height=&#34;500&#34; alt=&#34;IMG_20141022_113740&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found the Harvard Classics where I expected to find them! I will continue to climb the Cathedral in the future to see what other oldies exist up there. I am particularly interested in encyclopedias and &amp;ldquo;world history&amp;rdquo; books, having seen some really old ones in the past that were fascinating in either their short-sighted parochial nature or in their far-sighted prophetic correctness. I will report on what I find that might be particularly noteworthy.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A pretty exploratory fall hike in Frick Park and Duck Hollow</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/10/05/a-pretty-exploratory-fall-hike-in-frick-park-and-duck-hollow/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Oct 2014 20:25:28 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/10/05/a-pretty-exploratory-fall-hike-in-frick-park-and-duck-hollow/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Abby and I hadn&amp;rsquo;t gone hiking for a while, because of schedules, but decided on a free Sunday afternoon to simply go for an exploratory hike in our local Frick Park, as we&amp;rsquo;ve done many times before. There&amp;rsquo;s never any shortage of ways to try something new. Lately, this has meant exploring narrow and hilly trails that mountain bikers use. We have to be careful on these to avoid a bike coming down out of nowhere!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We hiked about eight miles, starting with familiar territory but then entering the very strange!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;photos&#34;&gt;Photos&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I took a few &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/franklinmingchen/sets/72157648426944075/&#34;&gt;photos&lt;/a&gt; along the way that you can check out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/franklinmingchen/15264950369/in/set-72157648426944075/player/&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; height=&#34;375&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen oallowfullscreen msallowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;frick-park&#34;&gt;Frick Park&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We started by walking to and then entering Frick Park at the Blue Slide Playground at Beechwood and Nicholson, then taking Riverview Trail and then the Firelane Trail Extension down into Fern Hollow onto the Firelane Trail, meeting up with the Deer Creek Trail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After crossing Commercial St, leaving Frick Park, we headed onto Nine Mile Run Trail. We noticed that the construction site that had been there for something like two years had finally been cleared away. It was about time!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was peaceful and relaxing on Nine Mile Run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/franklinmingchen/15451702525/in/set-72157648426944075/player/&#34; width=&#34;375&#34; height=&#34;500&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen oallowfullscreen msallowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;slag-heap&#34;&gt;Slag heap&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Continuing on Nine Mile Run Trail, we reached the bridge and I was originally planning to continue on Nine Mile Run Trail, but happened to notice an intriguing steep trail up on a slag heap area right at the bridge. What the heck, why not explore it? We wished we had brought hiking poles, but fashioned some sticks from tree branches lying around, and proceeded up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In theory I could have tried to figure out where we were, since I had my phone on me, but I like randomly exploring without having any idea where we are going; there was no way to get hopelessly lost anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were a whole bunch of switchbacks leading upward and we followed them for some time until reaching a particularly roller-coaster section going into a valley, and decided we had enough, especially since we spotted a mountain biker further up somewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/franklinmingchen/15428655696/in/set-72157648426944075/player/&#34; width=&#34;375&#34; height=&#34;500&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen oallowfullscreen msallowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We turned off and took a trail heading just downhill, hoping to emerge somewhere in &amp;ldquo;civilization&amp;rdquo; eventually, maybe rejoin Nine Mile Run Trail that we had abandoned at the bridge. Meanwhile, we had clear views of the Waterfront across the Monongahela River. I figured we were in Duck Hollow somewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;railroad-tracks&#34;&gt;Railroad tracks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/franklinmingchen/15265131148/in/set-72157648426944075/player/&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; height=&#34;375&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen oallowfullscreen msallowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, we emerged by the railroad tracks along the Mon. We walked along the railroad tracks for a bit and reached familiar territory, McFarren St. We got back onto the Nine Mile Run Trail to start heading home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/franklinmingchen/15428681816/in/set-72157648426944075/player/&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; height=&#34;375&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen oallowfullscreen msallowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/franklinmingchen/15265195427/in/set-72157648426944075/player/&#34; width=&#34;375&#34; height=&#34;500&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen oallowfullscreen msallowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/franklinmingchen/15448608681/in/set-72157648426944075/player/&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; height=&#34;375&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen oallowfullscreen msallowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;back-into-frick-park-and-home&#34;&gt;Back into Frick Park and home&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Many trails lead to home.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of returning the way we came, we took the very windy Iron Grate Trail instead, and eventually made it back to the Blue Slide Playground (taking Jay&amp;rsquo;s Short Cut) and back onto the streets of Squirrel Hill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-were-those-slag-heap-trails-anyway&#34;&gt;What were those slag heap trails anyway?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went online and looked for information on those slag heap trails and that whole area. As far as I can tell, the following are useful information from mountain bike community descriptions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mtbproject.com/trail/5492893/slag-heap-switchbacks-to-plateau&#34;&gt;Slag heap switchbacks to plateau&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mtbproject.com/trail/4676264/crater-trail&#34;&gt;Crater trail&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I had fun time on a great fall afternoon exploring trails we&amp;rsquo;d never been on before. We definitely plan to go back and explore more, with hiking poles, ha!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m amazed by and grateful for what we can experience outdoors in nature even while embedded in the city of Pittsburgh.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Observing Constitution Day with &#34;The Supreme Court and Privacy: The Fourth Amendment in the Digital Age&#34;</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/09/17/observing-constitution-day-with-the-supreme-court-and-privacy-the-fourth-amendment-in-the-digital-age/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2014 21:54:01 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/09/17/observing-constitution-day-with-the-supreme-court-and-privacy-the-fourth-amendment-in-the-digital-age/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have a habit of observing Constitution Day every year by attending a presentation at CMU and thinking about issues relating to the Constitution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year (2013), &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/09/17/on-not-celebrating-constitution-day-this-year&#34;&gt;I was too disheartened to observe Constitution Day but wrote a little bit about why&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year, I returned because the topic for discussion sounded interesting: &lt;a href=&#34;http://thebridge.cmu.edu/organization/SLO/calendar/details/466499&#34;&gt;Mary Jo Miller gave a talk &amp;ldquo;The Supreme Court and Privacy: The Fourth Amendment in the Digital Age&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; in the Posner Center. (Miller is a Staff Attorney for the Pennsylvania State Education Association and an adjunct professor in Carnegie Mellon&amp;rsquo;s Social and Decision Sciences Department.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/franklinmingchen/15274305882&#34; title=&#34;IMG_20140917_163751 by Franklin Chen, on Flickr&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3836/15274305882_f0eaf5d8fb.jpg&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; height=&#34;375&#34; alt=&#34;IMG_20140917_163751&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-fourth-amendment-http-en-wikipedia-org-wiki-fourth-amendment-to-the-united-states-constitution&#34;&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fourth_Amendment_to_the_United_States_Constitution&#34;&gt;fourth amendment&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
The right of the people to be secure in their persons, houses, papers, and effects, against unreasonable searches and seizures, shall not be violated, and no warrants shall issue, but upon probable cause, supported by oath or affirmation, and particularly describing the place to be searched, and the persons or things to be seized.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mary Jo Miller gave an entertaining and instructive talk in which she discussed various rulings by the Supreme Court involving interpretations of the fourth amendment in various circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, she reminded us that the fourth amendment came about because of the colonialists&amp;rsquo; bad experiences with England when arbitrary searches of people&amp;rsquo;s home happened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then she argued that although it is popularly held that there is a &amp;ldquo;conservative&amp;rdquo; (&amp;ldquo;originalist&amp;rdquo;) wing of the Supreme Court (typified currently by Scalia) and a &amp;ldquo;liberal&amp;rdquo; (&amp;ldquo;living Constitution&amp;rdquo;) wing (typified in the past by Stevens), on fourth amendment issues, they are not always split. In fact, she gave examples of where the Court was unanimous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The primary concern by the Court has been to respect (in the absence of probable cause) the doctrine that &amp;ldquo;each man&amp;rsquo;s home is his castle&amp;rdquo;. Miller gave examples involving surveillance of a marijuana grower&amp;rsquo;s home through a heat detector, as well as examining the contents of a drug dealer&amp;rsquo;s cell phone, as being judged a violation of fourth amendment rights because of what can be considered one&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;home&amp;rdquo;: a cell phone is actually a computer containing much of one&amp;rsquo;s possession, so it is in fact one&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;home&amp;rdquo; and requires a proper warrant in order to search it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s about the &amp;ldquo;exclusionary rule&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;fruits of the poison tree&amp;rdquo;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/franklinmingchen/15271576131&#34; title=&#34;IMG_20140917_164820 by Franklin Chen, on Flickr&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5596/15271576131_6c4a8f4d5f.jpg&#34; width=&#34;375&#34; height=&#34;500&#34; alt=&#34;IMG_20140917_164820&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-about-the-nsa&#34;&gt;What about the NSA?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After almost an hour, I had to leave, and therefore did not stay for questions and answers. I would have asked about what the current thinking is by the Court about NSA surveillance. When is information far enough removed that it is no longer considered one&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;home&amp;rdquo;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did enjoy this year&amp;rsquo;s Constitution Day observance at CMU. Mary Jo Miller gave an excellent talk discussing various Supreme Court rulings and different aspects of the fourth amendment.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thoughts on the construction of the new Frick Environmental Center</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/08/05/thoughts-on-the-construction-of-the-new-frick-environmental-center/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2014 21:12:30 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/08/05/thoughts-on-the-construction-of-the-new-frick-environmental-center/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Almost exactly twelve years ago, in 2002, tragedy struck in Frick Park in Pittsburgh. I was on a long evening run in Frick Park when I unwittingly came across what had happened earlier in the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;from-my-journal-august-4-2002&#34;&gt;From my journal, August 4, 2002&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;91 degrees, heat index 93. The Frick Park entrance was closed off for
some reason with tape, so that I could not access the water fountain I
had counted on using, so I ran up to Forbes instead and to Braddock to
get a fountain at that end of the park.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later in the evening, I found out what had happened:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Whoa!!!  The Frick Environmental Center was burned down in the
morning.  No wonder it was all closed off when I tried to run to the
water fountain.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was &lt;a href=&#34;http://old.post-gazette.com/neigh_city/20020805frickpark0805p1.asp&#34;&gt;reported the next day in the Post-Gazette&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;construction&#34;&gt;Construction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.post-gazette.com/local/city/2014/08/04/Frick-Environmental-Center-construction-begins/stories/201408040171&#34;&gt;Yesterday&lt;/a&gt;, construction of the new &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pittsburghparks.org/environmentalcenter&#34;&gt;Frick Environmental Center&lt;/a&gt; began, finally, after twelve years of uncertainty and controversy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On my evening run tonight (very cool, in the 60s, this summer, unlike the summer of twelve years ago!), I checked out the construction site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Road sign on Beechwood Blvd:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/franklinmingchen/14817138516&#34; title=&#34;Road sign for Frick Environmental Center by Franklin Chen, on Flickr&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3882/14817138516_f9529cdba9.jpg&#34; width=&#34;375&#34; height=&#34;500&#34; alt=&#34;Road sign for Frick Environmental Center&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Old burned building still there:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/franklinmingchen/14653568337&#34; title=&#34;Old Frick Environmental Center by Franklin Chen, on Flickr&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm6.staticflickr.com/5581/14653568337_6f5ec39932.jpg&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; height=&#34;375&#34; alt=&#34;Old Frick Environmental Center&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some trail detour signs:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.flickr.com/photos/franklinmingchen/14840109625&#34; title=&#34;Trails detoured for Frick Environmental Center construction by Franklin Chen, on Flickr&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://farm4.staticflickr.com/3914/14840109625_f49a9061fb.jpg&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; height=&#34;375&#34; alt=&#34;Trails detoured for Frick Environmental Center construction&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;controversy&#34;&gt;Controversy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was controversy because of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pghcitypaper.com/pittsburgh/natural-selection-critics-question-choice-of-site-for-new-frick-environmental-center/Content?oid=1760832&#34;&gt;concerns&lt;/a&gt; about the impact of the major development planned on Frick Park, which has been prized by many (certainly by me!) as the &amp;ldquo;wildest&amp;rdquo; space in Pittsburgh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I understand the concerns, and realize there are some major tradeoffs in creating a new, fancy Environmental Center. It is &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburghparks.wordpress.com/2014/06/26/like-a-pheonix-rebuilding-a-new-frick-environmental-center/&#34;&gt;argued by the Pittsburgh Parks Conservancy&lt;/a&gt; that there are potentially tremendous benefits to having a modern community facility for education, especially for children. While I regret that some of the wildness of this part of Frick Park will be demolished, I hope that bringing interesting programs to children, especially urban children who might otherwise fail to ever appreciate nature, will be worth the development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will miss not accessing some trails of the park from this direction for a while, but having sadly seen the old burned building lying around abandoned for twelve years, I look forward to its being replaced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;questions&#34;&gt;Questions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you live in the neighborhood of Frick Park, how do you feel about the controversy over the new Frick Environmental Center? Do you believe the risks are uncertain or not worthwhile? What do you think will be the actual outcome and impact, to the environment as well as to the community, of the development and of the planned educational center?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you do not live in the neighborhood, how do you feel about these fancy developments in general? Have you seen them turn out badly somewhere else? Or turn out well?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The growth of loyalty after seventeen years</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/07/22/the-growth-of-loyalty-after-seventeen-years/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2014 21:44:11 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/07/22/the-growth-of-loyalty-after-seventeen-years/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Tonight I finally got a haircut.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For two weeks I&amp;rsquo;d been looking for my &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/barber/&#34;&gt;barber&lt;/a&gt; Joe, of Harry&amp;rsquo;s Barber Shoppe in Squirrel Hill; I was due for my haircut. I&amp;rsquo;d called Joe&amp;rsquo;s phone number from work in the afternoon. I&amp;rsquo;d driven by on the way home (the shop is just a block away from home). I&amp;rsquo;d taken a walk on Saturday to see if he was open. No sign of him. I was worried. I began imagining the worst.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not kidding when I tell people that I don&amp;rsquo;t know what I&amp;rsquo;d do without Joe to cut my hair. He&amp;rsquo;s been the only one to cut my hair in the past seventeen years, apart from that one time he broke his hand and was out of commission for a while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first thought when I wondered whether Joe was OK was, if he was gone, I would miss not only a great cut (after the first couple of times in 1997, he figured out how to do things just the way I like), but also some kind of relationship. Since Joe is a lot older than me, I know that one day I will have to find a new barber; I was just thinking that when that day comes, I don&amp;rsquo;t want just a haircut, but I want some kind of relationship. Joe doesn&amp;rsquo;t just cut my hair. He asks me how my life is going; he was there before I was married, and now he inquires about Abby, whom he&amp;rsquo;s met, that time when I was waiting so long for my turn that she walked over and brought me dinner. He knows the structure of my head and the properties of my hair more than I do. We take turns guessing who&amp;rsquo;s singing the songs on his favorite radio station; I&amp;rsquo;ve absorbed some of his oldies into my consciousness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;lucky&#34;&gt;Lucky&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The whole haircut experience is about much more than my walking out with less hair. That&amp;rsquo;s why I was relieved to find him accidentally after an evening run in Frick Park that ended with my spotting in the distance the light in Joe&amp;rsquo;s shop and stopping by and seeing him there. It was already late in the evening, nearly 8:00 PM already, but he said he would take me (he was finishing up one guy in the chair), so I ran back home to change out of my running gear and get my wallet and return to the shop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joe said he was OK. He&amp;rsquo;s continued to have back trouble and reduced his work, but he&amp;rsquo;s still around. It does not even occur to me to get angry with him for causing me to look for him for two weeks. I&amp;rsquo;m simply grateful he&amp;rsquo;s OK and able to work and cheerful. He thanks me for being patient and returning to him again and again. That is all. The rest is philosophical banter about what is important in life, and chuckling to myself as I easily identify &amp;ldquo;drunky&amp;rdquo; Dean Martin on the radio singing &amp;ldquo;Ain&amp;rsquo;t That a Kick in the Head?&amp;rdquo; Such a dated song, I think, but it has a certain charm and who else could sing it in perfect character besides Dean Martin?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/2zBszbgkH8g&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;questions&#34;&gt;Questions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Are you loyal to someone who cuts your hair? What would you do (or have done) if that person is no longer present in your life?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The one thing I remember Lorin Maazel for</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/07/13/the-one-thing-i-remember-lorin-maazel-for/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Jul 2014 19:36:07 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/07/13/the-one-thing-i-remember-lorin-maazel-for/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;RIP, &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lorin_Maazel&#34;&gt;Lorin Maazel&lt;/a&gt;. A music conductor of fame and longevity has died (at age 84), generating no shortage of obituaries, such as &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2014/07/14/arts/music/lorin-maazel-brilliant-intense-and-enigmatic-conductor-dies-at-84.html&#34;&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Very often famous people die without my really having known much about them, and of course, this case was no exception. But this post isn&amp;rsquo;t about what I didn&amp;rsquo;t know, but what I do know, and &lt;em&gt;remember&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-ring-without-words&#34;&gt;The &amp;ldquo;Ring&amp;rdquo; Without Words&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lorin Maazel may have had a long and illustrious career, but actually, I don&amp;rsquo;t believe I have listened to a single of his recordings (I never saw him in performance) other than one, his &amp;ldquo;Ring Without Words&amp;rdquo; purely orchestral arrangement of Richard Wagner&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Der_Ring_des_Nibelungen&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Ring&amp;rdquo; cycle of operas&lt;/a&gt; that fits in a CD-length 75-minute &amp;ldquo;summary&amp;rdquo; of the epic operatic cycle (which takes more like 17 hours for a complete performance, spread out over four separate operas).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So he touched my life in a single, unusual, but quite &lt;em&gt;positive&lt;/em&gt; way. Ironically, the example obituary I mentioned does not even mention this work of Maazel&amp;rsquo;s. This illustrates that obituaries hardly tell the whole story of the contributions of someone to people&amp;rsquo;s lives. They may tell what is most prestigious or most scandalous, but may miss interesting quirky projects that have less measurable impact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-story&#34;&gt;My story&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://ecx.images-amazon.com/images/I/51lK9-us16L._SY300_.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;The Ring Without Words&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In my senior year of college, I came across a CD in the campus library on the Telarc label of Maazel&amp;rsquo;s recording of the &amp;ldquo;Ring Without Words&amp;rdquo;. At the time, I knew fairly little about Richard Wagner or his music, but I was intrigued by the concept, since I was &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; an opera fan, and didn&amp;rsquo;t mind trying out what some immediately criticized as a gimmicky &amp;ldquo;Reader&amp;rsquo;s Digest&amp;rdquo; concept by Maazel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I very much enjoyed the recording and listened to clips here and there without the &amp;ldquo;guilt&amp;rdquo; or confusion of choosing and listening to selected portions of recordings of the actual original operas. Basically, I appreciated Maazel&amp;rsquo;s role as a curator and summarizer that brought in curious new listeners like me. I still believe there is a role for &amp;ldquo;popularizers&amp;rdquo; of &amp;ldquo;classical music&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I just looked on YouTube and found this very short clip of a performance by Maazel of the &amp;ldquo;Ring Without Words&amp;rdquo;, so you can check it out to get an idea of how it works:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/h9ObRSy3D1E&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;authorial-intent&#34;&gt;Authorial intent&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I mentioned last year in &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/05/22/reflections-on-richard-wagners-200th-birthday/&#34;&gt;my post for Wagner&amp;rsquo;s 200th birthday&lt;/a&gt; that I had, before encountering Maazel&amp;rsquo;s CD, tried to watch the Metropolitan Opera&amp;rsquo;s four-evening TV broadcast in the summer of the &amp;ldquo;Ring&amp;rdquo; cycle and found it hard going. My overall philosophy was, and is, that &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/05/24/why-i-will-always-pronounce-gif-like-gift-and-not-like-jif/&#34;&gt;authorial intent is overrated&lt;/a&gt;. Fact is, if we were really serious about authorial intent, Wagner actually originally &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parsifal#The_ban_on_Parsifal_outside_Bayreuth&#34;&gt;forbade his opera &amp;ldquo;Parsifal&amp;rdquo; from being performed anywhere except in Bayreuth&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not saying we shouldn&amp;rsquo;t respect to one degree or other a composer&amp;rsquo;s original setting or wishes. Actually, I&amp;rsquo;m probably more respectful than most other people, because of my involvement with early music! I&amp;rsquo;m just saying that alternative arrangements and excerpts are always possible, and as long as they do not misrepresent themselves, I have no problem with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;pittsburgh&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might expect me to say something how Maazel turned the Pittsburgh Symphony Orchestra into a world-class orchestra, but actually, I moved to Pittsburgh in 1997 after Maazel had just left, so when I started attending PSO concerts, it was &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/06/08/heinz-hall-memories-at-the-pittsburgh-symphony-being-shocked-out-of-my-mind-upon-experiencing-prokofievs-second-piano-concerto-for-the-first-time/&#34;&gt;under Mariss Jansons&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the &lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.pittsburghsymphony.org/2014/07/statement-on-the-death-of-former-pittsburgh-symphony-orchestra-music-director-lorin-maazel/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Symphony Orchestra&amp;rsquo;s official statement on the passing of Lorin Maazel&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever else Lorin Maazel may have done in his life, one thing he did was bring Wagner to people like me, through his &amp;ldquo;Ring Without Words&amp;rdquo;. I am grateful he carried out this project. Also, more indirectly, he shaped the Pittsburgh Symphony Orchestra into the world-class orchestra it was by the time I moved to Pittsburgh, so I benefited from something he did that I never personally saw.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Third year at July 3 music party and finally participated in jamming</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/07/03/third-year-at-july-3-music-party-and-finally-participated-in-jamming/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jul 2014 22:11:59 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/07/03/third-year-at-july-3-music-party-and-finally-participated-in-jamming/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;The past two years, Abby and I have gone to an annual July 3 music potluck/party, and we went again this year. Both &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/03/petrified-at-a-music-jam-session-so-i-didnt-play-but-watched-and-listened/&#34;&gt;in 2012&lt;/a&gt; as well as &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/07/03/second-year-at-july-3-music-party-still-only-listening-without-playing/&#34;&gt;in 2013&lt;/a&gt;, I was too intimidated to participate in music jamming, and only watched. This year I was determined to contribute, and I brought my ukulele (which I only started learning &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/08/23/another-unexpected-life-change-one-month-of-learning-to-play-ukulele/&#34;&gt;a month after last year&amp;rsquo;s party&lt;/a&gt;, actually) and my Irish flute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;piano&#34;&gt;Piano&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After my first round of food at the potluck, I went to Susan&amp;rsquo;s piano and played David Raksin&amp;rsquo;s theme from &amp;ldquo;Laura&amp;rdquo;, which I had so botched up last month at the annual Pittsburgh Recorder Society potluck/recital. I play it much better now, although I somehow messed up the final chords today. There were a few people sitting around listening, and they wanted to hear more, but I didn&amp;rsquo;t have any more, so I scurried away to eat more food.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;old-time&#34;&gt;Old time&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As dinner started winding down, the old time musicians started gathering outside to play. I saw fiddles, banjos, and other instruments make an appearance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;blues&#34;&gt;Blues&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inside, the main guy who plays guitar and ukulele unpacked his soprano ukulele, and so I took out my concert ukulele, and two other guys with guitars appeared. Eventually a woman who sang also appeared, as well as a guy on fiddle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I felt very intimidated, because although I&amp;rsquo;ve gotten some experience jamming while on recorder or flute or tin whistle, my ukulele experience &lt;em&gt;without written music&lt;/em&gt; is still very minimal. Nevertheless, I joined in. I fumbled around, and had to ask what key each song was being played in, and even then, I&amp;rsquo;m still quite shaky in anticipating and knowing chord changes beyond the simplest I, IV, V, and some dominant and major 7th chords. I strummed very softly.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/music-2014-07-04/jamming.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Music jamming&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;They&amp;rsquo;re a great bunch, improvising melodic lines at will and even making up lyrics right on the spot, just as they had at the last two years when I only watched. And the singing in harmony was fantastic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby got a little bit of video footage of us at one point:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/zYb1aBioAao&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For two years, I was afraid to join in the music jams at this annual July 3 party. This year I joined in a little bit. If we attend the party again next year, I hope to be in a position to contribute even more! Many thanks to Susan for hosting this annual party!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thoughts on National Running Day 2014</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/06/04/thoughts-on-national-running-day-2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2014 19:19:21 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/06/04/thoughts-on-national-running-day-2014/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;This is my third year of celebrating &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.runningday.org/&#34;&gt;National Running Day&lt;/a&gt;. The first year, I did so by &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/06/06/i-celebrated-national-running-day-in-schenley-park-remembering-how-i-began-to-run-13-year-ago/&#34;&gt;running in Schenley Park&lt;/a&gt;; last year, I quietly did &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/06/05/celebrating-national-running-day-quietly-in-frick-park/&#34;&gt;my usual Frick Park run&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year, I ran in Frick Park again, a shorter run, because I took such a long break from running since last October, and only recently returned to regular running.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/frick-park-2014-06-04/frick.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;luna-venado-sandals&#34;&gt;Luna Venado Sandals&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since it was a shorter run of just 3 miles, I wore my thin &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lunasandals.com/products/luna-venado&#34;&gt;Luna Venado Sandals&lt;/a&gt; (only 7 mm thick) instead of the Luna Mono Sandals that I wore on last year&amp;rsquo;s run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/frick-park-2014-06-04/luna-venado-sandals-top.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Luna Venado Sandals&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/frick-park-2014-06-04/luna-venado-sandals-side.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Luna Venado Sandals&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;thoughts&#34;&gt;Thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m grateful that I have returned to running after many months off. It&amp;rsquo;s good for my body and most of all, my mind, actually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m grateful that I have no excuse to go out since I live so close to Frick Park.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m grateful that running is one of those things that (assuming your legs and feet are doing OK) you can do as slowly or as easily as you need or want to. I&amp;rsquo;m just ramping up slowly right now, and feel no anxiety about what level of fitness I&amp;rsquo;m at now. If I get tired, I can always walk, no shame. It&amp;rsquo;s all good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Do you run? Do you make it a ritual, as apparently I have, of taking time out periodically to reflect on what running means to you?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why I voted yet again</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/05/20/why-i-voted-yet-again/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 May 2014 22:52:11 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/05/20/why-i-voted-yet-again/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I voted again, as I&amp;rsquo;ve been doing regularly for some years now.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/voter-receipt-primary-2014.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;2014 PA primary election voter receipt&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But why?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/05/21/voting-in-the-face-of-election-apathy/&#34;&gt;vented a bit about voting&lt;/a&gt; but did so anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year, I paid almost no attention to any media coverage before the election. This included deleting answer machine messages, and summarily recycling all campaign flyers sent to my home, with an attempt not to even see who sent them. I don&amp;rsquo;t know if it&amp;rsquo;s just my imagination, but these flyers have gotten louder and more annoying and inane. I made the mistake of actually seeing &lt;em&gt;one&lt;/em&gt; of these flyers (and therefore know who it was from). In all caps and colored, bold text (if I recall correctly), it said something like&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Mike knows us.

And we know Mike.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That pretty much sums up what political campaigns are. And we know that psychologically, this stuff works. Just slamming someone&amp;rsquo;s name into our brains, creating &amp;ldquo;familiarity&amp;rdquo;, influences votes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yeah, I voted for Mike anyway. After all, &amp;ldquo;I know him&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;governor&#34;&gt;Governor&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I knew very little about the main race, the primary election for Pennsylvania governor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The night before, I did a little bit of research, largely on whom to vote &lt;em&gt;against&lt;/em&gt;. One candidate apparently stood out for pretty harsh negative ads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the whole, such negative ads turn me off. Now, I understand that psychologically, some people are motivated by negative ads to go vote against the target. But it&amp;rsquo;s actually difficult to anticipate exactly what the tradeoff is, in terms of attracting support vs. fueling the opposition. Obviously, I would never make a decision based purely on campaign tactics, but in this case, I figured I would go with someone not particularly different on issues who did &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; engage in this kind of behavior.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;but-why-vote-at-all&#34;&gt;But why vote at all?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wish I could tell you that I feel I&amp;rsquo;m making a difference by voting. I&amp;rsquo;m not sure that&amp;rsquo;s true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wish I could tell you that I feel it is my &amp;ldquo;civic duty&amp;rdquo; to vote, because I have the privilege of having the right to do so as a citizen of the United States. I&amp;rsquo;m not sure I feel that is my duty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The truth is, I vote every election day now simply because I&amp;rsquo;ve developed a &lt;em&gt;habit&lt;/em&gt; of it, and a &lt;em&gt;system&lt;/em&gt; (avoiding media coverage that would piss me off, and doing a bit of homework the night before election day). So, it&amp;rsquo;s just what I do now. I no longer question whether I will get out there and press the big red button. I just do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Do you vote? In every election or just high-profile primary or general elections, such as presidential? Why do you vote or not vote?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>When I&#39;m feeling too tired to venture out, there&#39;s always Frick Park</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/05/18/when-im-feeling-too-tired-to-venture-out-theres-always-frick-park/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 May 2014 22:27:39 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/05/18/when-im-feeling-too-tired-to-venture-out-theres-always-frick-park/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Because of the rain forecast and fatigue (I had a tough week), Abby and I ended up not venturing out of the city of Pittsburgh for a hike yesterday. But this afternoon, things seemed to clear up enough that we went for a hike in our local Frick Park. It was a bit chilly actually, so we wore raincoats and also I wore a hat in gloves (yes, it&amp;rsquo;s May).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s been a real blessing that Frick Park is so close to where we live, because that means we have no excuse not to go out into nature and to get some exercise, even if time or energy means we can&amp;rsquo;t do something more adventurous. Fact is, I took Abby around a bunch of trails that she had not yet explored, so there is no shortage of novelty in Frick Park itself! We were out for almost three hours. I led Abby to the network of trails by Nine Mile Run, then backtracked and went north of Fern Hollow, going up Tranquil Trail and branching off, before coming back down, and then back up toward home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Do you have a local favorite hangout (in nature or otherwise) that provides comfort and stimulation when you want to get out of the home but don&amp;rsquo;t want to go too far? How do you keep your experiences there interesting?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pittsburgh Recorder Society: discovering the beauty of Alonso Lobo</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/05/18/pittsburgh-recorder-society-discovering-the-beauty-of-alonso-lobo/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 May 2014 17:48:23 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/05/18/pittsburgh-recorder-society-discovering-the-beauty-of-alonso-lobo/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We had another great turnout for the monthly meeting of the Pittsburgh Recorder Society. We got another new member, Joanna. I counted fifteen of us, total.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-recorder-society-2014-05-18/group.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Today, the highlight for me was discovering some music I don&amp;rsquo;t remember encountering before, by &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alonso_Lobo&#34;&gt;Alonso Lobo&lt;/a&gt;, who lived roughly 1555-1617. Fred passed out parts for his &amp;ldquo;Versa est in luctum&amp;rdquo;, a sacred motet for voice (which we are playing as a recorder ensemble instead).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This music is beautiful and new to me, and Fred provided instructive interpretive guidance I will discuss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d never heard of Lobo before (outside of recorder playing, I simply have very little knowledge of early pre-Baroque music) and had to look up Lobo after the meeting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;versa-est-in-luctum-by-alonso-lobo&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Versa est in luctum&amp;rdquo; by Alonso Lobo&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is passionate funeral music, written for a Spanish king&amp;rsquo;s funeral. I found an interesting &lt;a href=&#34;http://luiscfhenriques.com/alonso-lobos-versa-est-in-luctum/&#34;&gt;musicologist&amp;rsquo;s blog post about the work&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;English translation printed on our recorder arrangement parts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
My harp is turned to mourning and my music into the voice of those that weep.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fred put me on the alto 1 part. After some work on the piece, he called for those of us on alto 1 (there was at least one other person, but possibly no more, of us fifteen) to play louder, with more emotion, to really ring out. I had held back in part because I was afraid of going sharp if I blowed harder, but also in part because for other music we&amp;rsquo;ve been playing, I&amp;rsquo;ve been focusing on blending in playing tenor parts. I sometimes somehow get into a rut and &amp;ldquo;forget&amp;rdquo; the importance or impact of carrying the top line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fred was actually singing along quite expressively as he conducted us. It&amp;rsquo;s inspirational to me that we have a leader who so believes in the music he has us play, and seeks to help us bring out its essence. The interesting thing about this piece is that there are phrases of longer notes as well as those that are more agitated, with faster movement. So there is a lot of beautiful interplay and contrast among the voices as well as within their own span throughout the piece. Fred advised on providing separation at the end of phrases so that they can be heard better in contrast against other voices as they enter and leave in different places.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, the other first alto(s) and I did play more confidently and louder, as did the rest of the ensemble, and when we did that, it was an amazing feeling, the sense of filling the air and resonating. I live for experiences like this! Let&amp;rsquo;s keep it up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;a-performance-for-choir-you-should-check-out&#34;&gt;A performance for choir you should check out&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For reference, here is a fine performance by the Gabrieli Consort I discovered:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/yZe16Mpsmg8&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;group-recording-from-before&#34;&gt;Group recording from before&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fred brought in a little boombox so we could hear the recording he had made earlier of us playing &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/03/16/pittsburgh-recorder-society-something-new-recently-recording-our-practice-sessions/&#34;&gt;two months ago&lt;/a&gt;. We didn&amp;rsquo;t sound terrible, actually!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-recorder-society-2014-05-18/recording.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;snacks&#34;&gt;Snacks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ate three cookies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-recorder-society-2014-05-18/cookie1.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-recorder-society-2014-05-18/cookie2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-recorder-society-2014-05-18/cookie3.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In retrospect, I should not have eaten three cookies. Maybe two, or maybe one. I know, I made this observation &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/04/27/pittsburgh-recorder-society-palestrina-gombert-and-dolly-parton-cookies/&#34;&gt;last month&lt;/a&gt;. This time, I&amp;rsquo;m serious. Next meeting, I will eat no more than &lt;em&gt;two&lt;/em&gt; cookies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed being shown yet another beautiful piece of music and getting the opportunity to play it with others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How often do you discover beautiful music you have never heard before, through being given it to play? Is this experience different than just hearing it without playing it?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A short Sunday hike in Frick Park</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/05/11/a-short-sunday-hike-in-frick-park/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 May 2014 21:09:24 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/05/11/a-short-sunday-hike-in-frick-park/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Abby and I had planned to go on a hike yesterday, but rain discouraged us, plus we had a late start to the day, and we were planning to check out part of the Bach Festival in Pittsburgh anyway (and did). This afternoon, it was nice and clear, so we did a little exploratory hike in Frick Park.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A little stream crossing:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/frick-park-2014-05-11/stream-crossing.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Poison ivy lurks everywhere:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/frick-park-2014-05-11/poison-ivy.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A bridge that has gotten lopsided:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/frick-park-2014-05-11/bridge.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Ducks:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/frick-park-2014-05-11/ducks.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pittsburgh Recorder Society: Palestrina, Gombert, and Dolly Parton cookies</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/04/27/pittsburgh-recorder-society-palestrina-gombert-and-dolly-parton-cookies/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Apr 2014 17:47:27 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/04/27/pittsburgh-recorder-society-palestrina-gombert-and-dolly-parton-cookies/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We had a great turnout again for the monthly meeting of the Pittsburgh Recorder Society. We even got an enthusiastic new member, Andriy. There were around fifteen of us, total; we really filled the room!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our director Fred was inspirational again, encouraging and helping us to continue to refine our sound, our unity, our expression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every month, attending the Sunday recorder meeting is truly one of the things I look forward to most in life! Sometimes I feel emotionally naked and a bit anxious in our meetings, but I know that this is a safe place to grow and to contribute. Today was one of those days in which I really felt challenged to do my very best to make music together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;kyrie-of-the-missa-papae-marcelli-by-palestrina-revisited&#34;&gt;Kyrie of the &amp;ldquo;Missa Papae Marcelli&amp;rdquo; by Palestrina, revisited&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/16/excited-by-the-new-season-of-the-pittsburgh-recorder-society/&#34;&gt;Well over a year ago&lt;/a&gt;, we had begun work on a recorder ensemble arrangement of Palestrina&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Kyrie de la &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Missa_Papae_Marcelli&#34;&gt;Missa Papae Marcelli&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;, but had actually not picked up much on that, so I was delighted that Fred decided (especially now that we have more members) to start on this piece again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got a tenor 2 part and was happy to do my best to produce a rich inner voice blending it into the ensemble&amp;rsquo;s tapestry of sound. Fred emphasized that the original music did not have bar lines, and that each &amp;ldquo;Kyrie&amp;rdquo; phrase can and does begin on any beat of a &amp;ldquo;measure&amp;rdquo;, so we should focus on keeping the flow going. Of course, this being originally vocal music, I tried to &amp;ldquo;sing&amp;rdquo; on recorder, paying attention to entrances and breath control (I am still unable to last an entire breath in some of these phrases).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;mille-regres-by-nicolas-gombert-http-en-wikipedia-org-wiki-nicolas-gombert&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Mille Regres&amp;rdquo; by &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nicolas_Gombert&#34;&gt;Nicolas Gombert&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also started work on a recorder arrangement of &amp;ldquo;Mille Regres&amp;rdquo; by Nicolas Gombert, originally for voice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fred put me on the alto part and after we started playing, I realized I was the only one on the part, and felt anxious! There was nowhere to hide. It&amp;rsquo;s very different from playing on a tenor or bass part with a bunch of other people, or even when playing a part with just one other person. On the one hand, there is much more freedom, because when a voice is doubled, you have to work with someone to sound like one. Of course, you always have to blend with the rest of the ensemble, regardless, but when you&amp;rsquo;re alone, you realize that you do not have backup for your voice, that you are it. Strong entrances, making the high notes clear and rich, are totally up to you now. It&amp;rsquo;s a great responsibility and opportunity, and I felt myself focusing as deep as I could into every element of the music. After today&amp;rsquo;s first cut, I hope to continue to improve on bringing my part fully to life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a performance of the original music for voice:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/J_2kRgCxeHk&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;mille-regretz-by-josquin-des-prez&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Mille Regretz&amp;rdquo; by Josquin des Prez&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that elements of this music sounded familiar to me, because in fact it is based on the French chanson &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mille_Regretz&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Mille Regretz&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Josquin_des_Prez&#34;&gt;Josquin des Prez&lt;/a&gt;, which I was familiar with because in last year&amp;rsquo;s Mideast early music workshop, I took a voice class in which we performed it. I really enjoyed singing it (as tenor; sorry, I don&amp;rsquo;t know if anyone has a video of our performance at the final student concert).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a nice performance of &amp;ldquo;Mille Regretz&amp;rdquo; with just one singer per part:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/S0TNPoDYHFY&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;another-alto-solo&#34;&gt;Another alto solo&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was another piece we started (but there were not enough scores, so I had to share with Kristel; I need to ask for a copy to be emailed to me, but for now I don&amp;rsquo;t remember the name or composer) in which Fred again put me on a solo part, which was originally marked &amp;ldquo;soprano&amp;rdquo; but after a run through, he told me to read it on alto up an octave.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This assignment made me even more anxious because I actually start out with a full statement of the melody without any accompaniment, before everyone else starts to come in. I&amp;rsquo;m not used to be put on the spot like this. But again, it&amp;rsquo;s a great opportunity to really work on refining my technique and expression, and being aware that I am setting the stage for the whole piece to succeed. Also, it&amp;rsquo;s an upbeat, rhythmic piece rather than a melancholy, lyrical one, so it was great to have the opportunity to portray different moods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;snacks&#34;&gt;Snacks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As usual, people brought in snacks to share for the mid-meeting break.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Helen not only brought in the recipe for her delicious brownies from &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/03/16/pittsburgh-recorder-society-something-new-recently-recording-our-practice-sessions/&#34;&gt;last month&amp;rsquo;s meeting&lt;/a&gt;, but also a new batch of what she called &amp;ldquo;Dolly Parton&amp;rdquo; cookies, incorporating a lot of apple in them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The recipe for last month&amp;rsquo;s brownies:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-recorder-society-2014-04-27/recipe.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I ate three of this month&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Dolly Parton&amp;rdquo; squares:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-recorder-society-2014-04-27/cookie1.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-recorder-society-2014-04-27/cookie2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-recorder-society-2014-04-27/cookie3.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although setting a limit on three was better than no limit at all, after I got home, I did wonder whether maybe I should have limited myself to two; these were quite substantial and filling!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had another intense and joyful musical afternoon with a great group of friendly and fun recorder enthusiasts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is your favorite role when you are on a team? Do you like being a prominent soloist, or do you prefer to blend into the background? Or do you like to switch up your roles? What do you adjust when you switch?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Life: cooking, eating with friends, music jamming, dancing</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/03/29/life-cooking-eating-with-friends-music-jamming-dancing/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Mar 2014 23:38:31 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/03/29/life-cooking-eating-with-friends-music-jamming-dancing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Abby and I went to a French potluck dance party at Lisa&amp;rsquo;s, the first one we&amp;rsquo;ve attended together in &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/05/25/learning-the-congo-de-captieux-traditional-french-dance/&#34;&gt;ten months&lt;/a&gt; (although I went to one without Abby &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/09/14/back-to-french-dance-potluck-and-party/&#34;&gt;half a year ago&lt;/a&gt; when she was out of town).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a wonderful experience, one that we&amp;rsquo;ve missed for two months, since we have not gone out to a party with friends since Abby got a new job and we&amp;rsquo;ve had to adapt to that big change in our lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although we still had to leave early, I was reminded of what I really enjoy in life, deep down: nothing fancy, just getting together and having fun and being creative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;music-jamming&#34;&gt;Music jamming&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hadn&amp;rsquo;t done French music jamming in months, so when Abby and I arrived, and dinner was still being prepared, and John said &amp;ldquo;hey, let&amp;rsquo;s play&amp;rdquo;, I pulled out my flutes (both my standard Boehm flute and my wooden Irish flute) and went at it with him on melodeon. We hadn&amp;rsquo;t played together in half a year! Susan joined in at some point, also on melodeon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We played mazurka and Schottische and other music for about half an hour, from John&amp;rsquo;s memory, as I tried to follow along by ear. I realized how much I miss French music jamming. Lisa&amp;rsquo;s been hosting it again recently, but there have been schedule conflicts for me, but it looks like we&amp;rsquo;ll be getting on a schedule that works for me. I&amp;rsquo;m coming back!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I was taking a break, John played a multi-section hanter dro that Fabien and Lisa started dancing to, and I joined them in their line and picked it up. Again, something I hadn&amp;rsquo;t done in a while, and almost forgotten the unique pleasure of!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;potluck&#34;&gt;Potluck&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This seemed to me the biggest French potluck party yet, with almost twenty people present, I believe. We met some new people as well as old friends.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/french-potluck-2014-03-29/dinner.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;At dinner&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I baked a butternut squash to bring. I only very, very lightly seasoned it, to not detract from the natural flavor of the squash:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;butternut squash, sliced in half, placed in roasting pan&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;salt&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;pepper&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;cayenne pepper&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;butter&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;extra virgin olive oil&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;brown sugar&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/french-potluck-2014-03-29/squash.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Butternut squash&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Abby made a kale and mushroom dish:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/french-potluck-2014-03-29/kale.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Kale&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The other guests all brought a lot of great homemade food, and Lisa and Alex provided tasty and filling entrees and desserts. A fantastic meal!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/french-potluck-2014-03-29/food1.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Food&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/french-potluck-2014-03-29/food2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Food&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/french-potluck-2014-03-29/food3.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Food&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, there were &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/03/21/time-to-taste-the-world-thoughts-on-expanding-my-food-tastes-as-an-adult/&#34;&gt;Brussels sprouts, and I enjoyed them&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/french-potluck-2014-03-29/brussels-sprouts.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Brussels sprouts&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;cookies-and-other-desserts&#34;&gt;Cookies (and other desserts)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In accordance with &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/01/16/a-system-for-quitting-eating-cookies/&#34;&gt;my rule&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Music-themed cookies homemade from molds:

&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/french-potluck-2014-03-29/musical-cookies.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Musical cookies&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ate one, of a dancing couple:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/french-potluck-2014-03-29/dance-cookie.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A slice of yummy chocolatey thing:

&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/french-potluck-2014-03-29/chocolatey.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Chocolatey&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A slice of chocolate cake:

&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/french-potluck-2014-03-29/chocolate-cake.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Chocolate cake&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Unfortunately, I think I should have cut myself a smaller slice, instead of accepting a precut slice.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A tiny piece of a very rich, buttery thing:

&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/french-potluck-2014-03-29/another-dessert.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A non-homemade cookie from a box (I didn&amp;rsquo;t need to eat this):

&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/french-potluck-2014-03-29/box-cookie.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;dancing&#34;&gt;Dancing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After dinner, Lisa and Fabien started off the dancing portion of the evening, by re-teaching the &amp;ldquo;Congo de Captieux&amp;rdquo; set dance that Lisa and Lynn had taught &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/05/25/learning-the-congo-de-captieux-traditional-french-dance/&#34;&gt;ten months ago&lt;/a&gt;. It had been so long that Abby and I barely remembered it and were practically learning it from scratch again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of eventually got through it! I got sweaty again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After that, there was a break, and since it was already &amp;ldquo;late&amp;rdquo; (for Abby and me on our current schedule), we had to say goodbye, just as the &amp;ldquo;regular&amp;rdquo; French dance portion of the evening was about to begin (bourres, waltzes, mazurkas, hanter dro, more music jamming, etc.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some photos of dancing that I took before we left early:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/french-potluck-2014-03-29/dancing1.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/french-potluck-2014-03-29/dancing2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/french-potluck-2014-03-29/dancing3.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a beautiful evening that filled my belly and soul. It&amp;rsquo;s been such a blessing to have been brought into this world of French traditional dance and music through the enthusiasm and generosity of Lisa &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/01/23/discovering-french-traditional-dance-in-pittsburgh/&#34;&gt;two years ago&lt;/a&gt; and many others. I feel like my life has been immeasurably enriched.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re in the Pittsburgh area and want to join in, we always welcome more dancers and musicians. (Or even if you&amp;rsquo;re not in the Pittsburgh area, as we&amp;rsquo;ve had visitors from further away.)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>