<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Memory on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/memory/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Memory on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/memory/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>My second ever blindfold chess game</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/03/17/my-second-ever-blindfold-chess-game/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Mar 2013 23:56:20 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/03/17/my-second-ever-blindfold-chess-game/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I spent much of the time at Henry&amp;rsquo;s St. Patrick&amp;rsquo;s Day party &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/17/finally-doing-some-latin-music-jamming-on-flute/&#34;&gt;playing music&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I decided to take a break, I went to the chess room and thought I&amp;rsquo;d just sit down and watch some of the kids play chess. I hadn&amp;rsquo;t played any chess at one of these parties in a long time, because it&amp;rsquo;s just too one-sided.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it turned out that when I sat down, people were leaving the chess board. So  I said to Henry (who was also taking a break from music and socializing), &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;ll play you blindfolded!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;blindfold-chess&#34;&gt;Blindfold chess&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blindfold_chess&#34;&gt;Blindfold chess&lt;/a&gt; is when someone plays a game of chess without having any sight of the board (or equivalent, e.g., touch). The game has to be played using only memory, no recording devices of any kind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s actually a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.blindfoldchess.net/&#34;&gt;recent book on blindfold chess&lt;/a&gt; that I have not yet looked at.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-blindfold-game-with-henry&#34;&gt;My blindfold game with Henry&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At one of Henry&amp;rsquo;s parties last year, there actually was a blindfold game conducted, between Henry and one of the boys who regularly attends his parties with his family, Ari. Henry played blindfold, while Ari had sight of the board, and I took charge of moving the pieces. That game ended in a draw because although Henry was winning, he forgot where all of his pieces were at a critical point and stalemated young Ari! After that game, I had suggested that someday I would like to play a blindfold game again, having done so once back in around thirteen years ago, when I was in graduate school. In fact, by sheer coincidence, that first ever blindfold game was in the office of my classmate &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/17/finally-doing-some-latin-music-jamming-on-flute/&#34;&gt;Andrej who was responsible for starting me on listening to Cuban music&lt;/a&gt;!! (Curiously, I don&amp;rsquo;t actually remember how my first blindfold chess game (with Andrej) turned out. I think we adjourned it at some point and did not continue it.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I played blindfold against Henry, who had sight of the board. I was nervous because unlike Ari, Henry is actually a seasoned tournament player (currently rated 1823), having actually drawn me in a rated game several years ago (with both of us being sighted).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My primary concern, not being trained at all in how to play blindfold chess effectively, was to make sure that I did not forget something that could lead to my quickly losing. So I decided to try to simplify. This, of course, meant reducing my own chances of winning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-game&#34;&gt;The game&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t remember all the moves in the game, but remember most of them and the most important positions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I took White and won a Pawn out of the opening but then gave it back. Although I eventually acquired a clear advantage in the middle game, I decided to simplify rather than lose track of my pieces. This was an important position in which I was White, to move:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/blindfold/middle.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Middle game&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I ended up winning a Pawn going into a Rook and Pawn endgame, which was clearly supposed to be drawn:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/blindfold/end.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Ending&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But I acquired some winning chances after a while. I squandered my best chance, as a result of starting to lose track of what pieces were where. It was unexpectedly difficult (without a deliberate attempt on my part at a system) to keep track of exactly where our Rooks and Kings were, since there was so much shuffling around. If I were playing blindfold again, I would come up with a simple system to remember this kind of information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had some other winning chances later, because of my active King, but as a result of some simplification, we finally reached a clearly dead drawn position:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../chess/blindfold/dead-draw.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Draw is imminent&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The game ended when, after several more moves, I clearly could not make further progress and offered a draw, which Henry accepted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was pleased not to lose my second ever blindfold chess game, ha! Well, it was just a casual game late at a party, so neither Henry nor I were playing our best. In a real game, I would be very lucky to escape losing against a sighted Henry, I think.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I changed how I live after reading Joshua Foer&#39;s &#34;Moonwalking with Einstein&#34;</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/12/24/i-changed-how-i-live-after-reading-joshua-foers-moonwalking-with-einstein/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Dec 2012 20:20:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/12/24/i-changed-how-i-live-after-reading-joshua-foers-moonwalking-with-einstein/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.strangehistory.net/blog/wp-content/uploads/2011/02/memory.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Memory&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Recently I heard about the journalist &lt;a href=&#34;http://joshuafoer.com/&#34;&gt;Joshua Foer&lt;/a&gt; who embarked on a remarkable journey in which he ended up covering a story about memory and then actually training his own and in the process becoming the United States Memory champion. I watched his hilarious and inspiring &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ted.com/talks/joshua_foer_feats_of_memory_anyone_can_do.html&#34;&gt;TED talk&lt;/a&gt; and ended up reading his book &lt;a href=&#34;http://joshuafoer.com/moonwalking-with-einstein/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Moonwalking with Einstein: The Art and Science of Remembering Everything&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After reading this book, I made a firm decision to &lt;em&gt;immediately change my life&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A confession: I have all my life, since childhood, struggled with what I considered a bad memory (compared to &amp;ldquo;normal&amp;rdquo;, as in my peers).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;examples-of-my-concern-about-my-memory&#34;&gt;Examples of my concern about my memory&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I took a quick look at my blog posts in the past year, to see where I might have bemoaned my bad memory, and here are a few examples:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I complained about not remembering &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/18/i-want-to-sing/&#34;&gt;song lyrics&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I noted that not remembering &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/10/flute-loving-it-again/&#34;&gt;dance steps and choreography&lt;/a&gt; forced me to fall back on improvisation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I mentioned &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/14/for-real-geeks-today-is-not-pi-day-but-half-tau-day/&#34;&gt;memorizing fifty digits of pi&lt;/a&gt;, but did not say how grueling a task it was and how ashamed I was that I retained very little and never wanted to do it again.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I noted how I was &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/04/21/my-first-time-in-a-public-music-jam-intense-fun-with-chris-norman-and-david-greenberg/&#34;&gt;forced into improvisation in music because of memory problems&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I told a story of &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/06/08/heinz-hall-memories-at-the-pittsburgh-symphony-being-shocked-out-of-my-mind-upon-experiencing-prokofievs-second-piano-concerto-for-the-first-time/&#34;&gt;misremembering an event in the past and then reconstructing what really happened&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;major-life-decisions-i-made-based-on-my-belief-i-had-a-bad-memory&#34;&gt;Major life decisions I made based on my belief I had a bad memory&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some things that I&amp;rsquo;ve told almost nobody in my life before, but now feel I should speak out about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;school&#34;&gt;School&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I shaped my entire experience in school around trying to avoid having to rely on my memory. History and other subjects terrified me. I was so conscious about my problems that in middle school, during one of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rif.org/&#34;&gt;Reading is Fundamental&lt;/a&gt; free book distributions, I greedily picked up &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.harrylorayne.com/&#34;&gt;Harry Lorayne&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;How to Develop a Super Power Memory&amp;rdquo;. Unfortunately, after looking at it, I was discouraged by its odd ideas and just didn&amp;rsquo;t really give any of them a try at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Biology terrified me, to the point that in my first year of high school, &lt;em&gt;I chose not to take any science course at all&lt;/em&gt; because biology would have been the first course for me to take. Later, I did take biology, delayed from most of my college-bound peers, in the tenth grade, and survived it (but have almost no memory of what I &amp;ldquo;learned&amp;rdquo;). In my senior year of high school, I took Advanced Placement biology, which was a total nightmare of memorization, solely for the purpose of not ever having to take biology again when going to college (and in fact, I did get credit for it and therefore succeeded in my goal). Note: since childhood, I was actually very fascinated by biology, so it was with sadness that I decided I had to avoid further study in biology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to avoidance, my fear of memorization also pushed me into certain directions based primarily on the lack of need for memorization: by the end of high school, I had discovered that math and physics were great for me because they did not require much memorization. Everything was based primarily on basic principles that, if you learned, you could build on top of using logical reasoning rather than memorization. Logic was the connective that kept things together in my mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;language-learning&#34;&gt;Language learning&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Learning foreign languages has always been fascinating to me, ever since as a side effect of studying for spelling bees in elementary school and middle school, I found a trick to help deal with my memory problems: looking up the etymologies of words in the dictionary enabled me to see enough logical and historical connections between words to be able to spell pretty well. But when it came to remembering and using the meanings of words as I learned French, for example, I was lost. I loved learning grammar because it was about figuring out the logical patterns, but hated learning vocabulary. Unfortunately, without a sufficient working vocabulary, my facility in languages was limited in oral communication, and even reading texts was painful, requiring constant dictionary lookup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So even though I&amp;rsquo;ve actually taken entire courses in French, German, Italian, and Spanish, and taught myself Latin, I&amp;rsquo;ve always felt that I somehow wasted my time, because I mostly remember grammar and pronunciation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-new-motivation&#34;&gt;My new motivation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was excited to watch Joshua Foer&amp;rsquo;s talk and read his book, because if an average guy can become the national memory champion through proven techniques, then a below-average guy like me should be able to get to average and even beyond. Given that I believe that I am capable of improving at many things I&amp;rsquo;m not so good at, why have I spent so much of my life not believing that about my memory? I created this self-limiting myth that I now intend to shatter. 2013 will be the year when I make massive improvements to my memory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-book&#34;&gt;The book&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I loved Joshua Foer&amp;rsquo;s book. He is not only a very good storyteller, taking the reader deep into the strange world of memory championships, but he also explains the time-honored techniques that every memory champion uses and that he used, and describes the scientific research on memory. There is no trickery involved, just changing your attitude and putting in the work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book is not just a good story and a how-to manual, though. It is really a &lt;em&gt;philosophical&lt;/em&gt; exploration of what it means to be human, and what we have lost since the ancient times when memory was not only useful but critical, because we didn&amp;rsquo;t have the technological aids that we have now. It made me think about how I should balance time-saving technology and old-fashioned ways of dealing with life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-principle-behind-memory-techniques&#34;&gt;The principle behind memory techniques&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main idea behind remembering well is that we have to encode memories in such a way that they are truly concrete and vivid, because that&amp;rsquo;s what we humans remember.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &amp;ldquo;memory palace&amp;rdquo; is a well-known technique (that I remembered from Harry Lorayne&amp;rsquo;s book in my childhood, but never implemented). It involves creating a space in your mind that you already know, and then put things you want to remember into that space by associating them with images located in specific places in the space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foer discussed one of the open secrets of how to come up with vivid images to remember: &amp;ldquo;When forming images, it helps to have a dirty mind&amp;rdquo;. He quotes ancient handbooks on memory that advise using images of beautiful women, or images of &amp;ldquo;singular ugliness&amp;rdquo;, modified through disfigurement or comic effects. This can get awkward. When he was training to memorize a deck of cards, he writes, &amp;ldquo;it invariably meant inserting family members into scenes so raunchy I feared I was upgrading my memory at the expense of tormenting my subconscious. The indecent acts my own grandmother has had to commit in the service of my remembering the eight of hearts are truly unspeakable (if not, as I might have previously guessed, unimaginable)&amp;rdquo;. Also, his coach Ed said, &amp;ldquo;I eventually had to excise my mother from my deck&amp;hellip; I recommend you do the same&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-plans-for-memory-improvement&#34;&gt;My plans for memory improvement&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m starting small with my memory improvement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;languages&#34;&gt;Languages&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a &amp;ldquo;test&amp;rdquo;, I&amp;rsquo;ve gotten back into language learning/review, using &lt;a href=&#34;http://duolingo.com/&#34;&gt;Duolingo&lt;/a&gt; (about which I&amp;rsquo;ll write much more later), focusing on Spanish, which I took three semesters of a decade ago, but have been embarrassed to feel incompetent in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past, I had no reliable way to remember new words as I learn them. Now, I paused for 5-10 seconds, maybe even longer if I need to (I expect to become more quick and fluid with experience), to create a suitable image.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You don&amp;rsquo;t really want to know what kinds of images I create for my memory. I think one of the problems I always had with my memory was being ashamed of &amp;ldquo;inappropriate&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;illogical&amp;rdquo; imagery. I always wanted to remember through logical association. Now, I have given myself permission to be as raunchy, disgusting, sarcastic, or bizarre as I need, and just accept that. So in some sense, embracing memory improvement, for me, involves self-acceptance. I created shocking images to remember the Spanish words for &amp;ldquo;cranberry&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;box&amp;rdquo;, for example, but they do the job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve already seen huge improvements in my learning of new words, which I do every day. I wish I had used this technique years, decades ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My goal: getting the vocabulary down will be a big part of becoming actually functional in Spanish. I would like to achieve near-native conversational Spanish ability in a year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;numbers&#34;&gt;Numbers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have always been bad at remembering numbers. I intend to set up a practice for using the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mnemonic_major_system&#34;&gt;Major System&lt;/a&gt; in order to get into remembering numbers better. It&amp;rsquo;s embarrassing and potentially actually dangerous when I don&amp;rsquo;t have my phone or computer on me and I am supposed to remember a phone number, for example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My goal: remember all numbers that should be important in my life. (Sorry, pi, you are not important.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;others&#34;&gt;Others&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I think about it, there is so much that I could gain from remembering all kinds of things better. I will explore my ideas later, after first mastering the fundamentals and gaining confidence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a real sense, we are what we remember. If we don&amp;rsquo;t remember, then what was the point? Joshua Foer&amp;rsquo;s experience and his book have inspired me to move forward in recapturing one of the ancient skills and delights, that of remembering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How do you feel about your memory? Is it something you care about improving? Or is our technological outsourcing of our memory perfectly fine?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Heinz Hall Memories: at the Pittsburgh Symphony, being shocked out of my mind upon experiencing Prokofiev&#39;s second piano concerto for the first time; also, a note on human memory</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/06/08/heinz-hall-memories-at-the-pittsburgh-symphony-being-shocked-out-of-my-mind-upon-experiencing-prokofievs-second-piano-concerto-for-the-first-time/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 08 Jun 2012 21:01:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/06/08/heinz-hall-memories-at-the-pittsburgh-symphony-being-shocked-out-of-my-mind-upon-experiencing-prokofievs-second-piano-concerto-for-the-first-time/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Last month, the Pittsburgh Symphony Orchestra on its blog called for people to &lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.pittsburghsymphony.org/2012/05/heinz-hall-memories/&#34;&gt;share their Heinz Hall memories for the 40th anniversary celebration&lt;/a&gt;. Upon reading that, two memories immediately came to my mind. I describe one of them here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;prokofiev-s-second-piano-concerto&#34;&gt;Prokofiev&amp;rsquo;s second piano concerto&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was in Heinz Hall for the Pittsburgh Symphony on January 21, 2000. It was a dreary winter day, with snow and poor driving conditions, but I felt compelled to use my ticket and go downtown for the concert.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the program at the concert were &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Piano_Concerto_No._2_(Prokofiev)&#34;&gt;Prokofiev&amp;rsquo;s second piano concerto&lt;/a&gt; and Bruckner&amp;rsquo;s fourth symphony. The Prokofiev was played by Mikhail Rudy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I remember is my jaw dropping while Rudy played the first movement of the Prokofiev concerto. I had never heard this concerto before; I had listened to the first, third, and fifth concertos many times before on cassette tape as well as CD but I had never owned a recording of the second or fourth!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This concerto was really dark and virtuosic, with violent dissonances and runs, quite unlike the more widely known concertos. When the solo cadenza began, I got restless and astounded as the cadenza kept going and going, as though taking up half of the entire first movement. This seemed outrageously long, and the music just got wilder and I thought the piano was taking a real beating, but I was truly fascinated by the perverseness of Prokofiev&amp;rsquo;s conception.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the whole concert ended, I walked out in a daze (in fact, I was so mentally disrupted that I was lucky to make it home alive driving on the parkway under really bad winter conditions).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will always remember that visceral experience with the Prokofiev concerto, and every time I hear it now, I can imagine myself back in Heinz Hall experiencing it for the very first time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;an-example-of-the-fragility-of-memory&#34;&gt;An example of the fragility of memory&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A confession: I had to look up my email archive and my journal to get my story completely correct above, after the first draft that I wrote without consulting them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am always a little suspicious when people tell of their memories from long ago (or even not so long ago), because human memory is not like computer memory. Human memory involves re-creation and simply cannot be trusted without hard evidence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, my immediate &amp;ldquo;memory&amp;rdquo; of the concert I just described, when I was not relying on any external sources, was &lt;em&gt;false&lt;/em&gt; in several ways. I was lucky to be able to locate old email archives and my daily journal from twelve years ago in order to determine what really happened!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-friend-who-wasn-t-there-part-1&#34;&gt;The friend who wasn&amp;rsquo;t there (part 1)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, I was very confident that I had gone to a concert with a particular friend, and that we had looked at each other in amazement during the cadenza. It turns out that I had not gone to this concert with my friend, and I had driven to it alone! It was easy for me to &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Confabulation&#34;&gt;confabulate&lt;/a&gt; because back in around 1997-1999, I had in fact gone to many PSO concerts in Heinz Hall on Fridays with him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, I did correctly remember discussing my experience with him. It turns out that I reported back to him about the Prokofiev concerto, and we talked about it, and in fact, he lent me a CD of it to listen to as a result.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Note: please read part 2 of &amp;ldquo;the friend who wasn&amp;rsquo;t there&amp;rdquo; below.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-wrong-pianist&#34;&gt;The wrong pianist&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my struggle to remember, I had thought that the pianist was probably &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pittsburghsymphony.org/pghsymph.nsf/bios/yefim+bronfman&#34;&gt;Yefim Bronfman&lt;/a&gt;. I was not actually confident about this, however. I was right not to be confident, because in fact, it was Mikhail Rudy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have an explanation for this mistake. It turns out that the CD I borrowed from my friend was Bronfman playing the concerto, and according to my journal, I listened to this CD on February 4, 2000!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, I did correctly remember seeing Bronfman playing in Heinz Hall. Again, my journal shows that on May 12, 2000, the final concert of the season, Yefim Bronfman played Beethoven under Mariss Jansons, and I was very impressed with the concert:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
I actually stood up to applaud Bronfman and Jansons for the Beethoven and the Stravinsky, something I have never done at a PSO concert.  It was a special concert.  Jansons seemed inspired, possibly because it was the season finale and the place was packed?  I mean, I&#39;m not a Stravinsky fan, but the Stravinsky was just so well played.  The Beethoven was fantastic.  I thought I&#39;d be all jaded from knowing this concerto inside out since first listening to it in 1988, but the performance was amazing.  The whole piece was great, but especially the first movement, in which Bronfman and Jansons and the orchestra were like one mind, the interplay seamless.

One thing about Bronfman:  he had a lot of energy, but seemed kind of percussive or heavy sometimes.  A minor complaint about a pianist who seemed great from the performance I saw.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-correctness-of-memory&#34;&gt;The correctness of memory&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;my-reaction&#34;&gt;My reaction&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My journal entry for the day of the concert included this comment I jotted down into my &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Palm_(PDA)&#34;&gt;Palm PDA&lt;/a&gt; at intermission:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Intermission.  There was an encore by Mikhail Rudy.  The Prokofiev piano concerto no. 2 is the most bizarre piano concerto I&#39;ve ever heard.  Quite perverse.  The clashing harmonies are one thing, but the organization is another.  Long, extended solo passages.  Huge cadenza in the first movement.  Just freakish.  I will have to look it up on the Web.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think I fairly accurately remembered my impression of the music that I wrote at the beginning of this post before I consulted my journal entry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;my-friend-who-was-there-part-2&#34;&gt;My friend who was there (part 2)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After writing a draft of this blog post, I told my friend about my false memory, but he replied that he too remembers the concert!! He just doesn&amp;rsquo;t remember going to it with me. This is quite possible. By 2000, because of other social circles and logistics, we did not always go to the concerts together, even if we both did end up there, sitting in different places.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He remembers this concert being eye-opening also, in that although he had listened to the concerto on recordings (as I mentioned, he lent me one shortly after this concert), it had not connected with him deeply until the live concert.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it appears that my memory was partially correct: although we had not sat together at the concert, most likely we chatted during intermission and shared our amazement then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The exercise of trying to get accurate the details of a memorable Heinz Hall experience from twelve years ago turned into a fascinating exploration of the malleability of human memory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But even if some details were fuzzy, my falling in love with Prokofiev&amp;rsquo;s wayward second piano concerto remains an eternal truth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;bonus-video&#34;&gt;Bonus video&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I&amp;rsquo;ve never seen Yefim Bronfman playing Prokofiev&amp;rsquo;s second piano concerto, but YouTube comes to the rescue. If you want to check out the wild cadenza I mentioned, it occurs between 5:00 and 9:19 in this video:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/CCeo1vyewEg&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2013-11-08&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-11-08)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I happened to see on the PSO blog &lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.pittsburghsymphony.org/2013/11/the-most-amazing-rendition-of-prokofievs-second-piano-concerto/&#34;&gt;a post about someone else&amp;rsquo;s experience with a recent performance of this concerto with the PSO&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My first time in a public music jam: intense fun with Chris Norman and David Greenberg</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/04/21/my-first-time-in-a-public-music-jam-intense-fun-with-chris-norman-and-david-greenberg/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Apr 2012 13:44:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/04/21/my-first-time-in-a-public-music-jam-intense-fun-with-chris-norman-and-david-greenberg/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://fbcdn-sphotos-a.akamaihd.net/hphotos-ak-ash3/544714_10150682065771513_55075526512_9775036_876594193_n.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;David Greenberg and Chris Norman and the rest of us&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Friday evening, Abby and I packed up various musical instruments of ours, and attended an event that I had been eagerly awaiting for over three weeks since I first found out about it from Annie of the local &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.andrew.cmu.edu/user/lukas/pcars/Welcome.html&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh recorder gang&lt;/a&gt;: a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rbsp.org/Jam%20Session%20Flyer.pdf&#34;&gt;jam session open to the public&lt;/a&gt; being offered by &lt;a href=&#34;http://chrisnorman.com/&#34;&gt;Chris Norman&lt;/a&gt;, flutist, and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.davidgreenberg.ca/&#34;&gt;David Greenberg&lt;/a&gt;, violinist the day before &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rbsp.org/11-12c6.aspx&#34;&gt;their concert&lt;/a&gt; the next evening to close the current season of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rbsp.org/&#34;&gt;Renaissance and Baroque of Pittsburgh&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was so excited by this opportunity to jam with such esteemed musicians. Norman and Greenberg specialize in playing Irish, Scottish, Cape Breton and Baroque music. I&amp;rsquo;ve come to love playing the rhythmic, danceable music of the old days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I learned a lot from the experience, and would like to share what I learned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;some-photos-of-the-event&#34;&gt;Some photos of the event&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/pages/Pittsburgh-Renaissance-and-Baroque/55075526512&#34;&gt;Facebook page of the Pittsburgh Renaissance and Baroque&lt;/a&gt; has a bunch of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/media/set/?set=a.10150682065546513.394216.55075526512&amp;amp;type=3&#34;&gt;photos of the event&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;ve used a couple of these here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;preparation&#34;&gt;Preparation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;my-instruments&#34;&gt;My instruments&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been spending most of my daily music practice all year working on the modern &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/flute/&#34;&gt;flute&lt;/a&gt;; I have not reported on my progress in over a month because I&amp;rsquo;ve been too busy &lt;em&gt;doing&lt;/em&gt; rather than &lt;em&gt;writing&lt;/em&gt;, but will catch up with the writing sometime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But for this jam session, I had decided very quickly that I was &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; going to be bringing my modern flute to play, because I do prefer to play older music on other instruments; I planned to bring the following instruments instead:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;my &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/tin-whistle/&#34;&gt;tin whistle&lt;/a&gt;, which I bought the week of St. Patrick&amp;rsquo;s Day in March (for a party I haven&amp;rsquo;t written about yet but which radically changed my life)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;an assortment of &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/recorder/&#34;&gt;recorders&lt;/a&gt;: I decided to just bring my soprano and alto&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;my &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/baroque-flute/&#34;&gt;Baroque flute&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, interspersed with my continuing work on the modern flute, I have also done some maintenance practice of tin whistle and recorders. The most difficult challenge was trying to get serious about Baroque flute: the one-keyed flute is &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.oldflutes.com/charts/onekey/index.htm&#34;&gt;very, very, very tricky to play in tune&lt;/a&gt;. Sometimes I wonder whether it&amp;rsquo;s worth the bother. But I tend to be inspired by quirky challenges whose benefit I don&amp;rsquo;t fully understand immediately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ideally, I would own an &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.caseyburnsflutes.com/cat_d.php&#34;&gt;Irish flute&lt;/a&gt;, preferably with a number of keys to aid with intonation and fingering, but given that I don&amp;rsquo;t currently intend to specialize in Irish music, and am still working with the tin whistle anyway, I cannot at all justify buying an Irish flute at this time. So I&amp;rsquo;ve been working on using the related Baroque flute instead, for traditional Irish or Scottish music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;abby-s-instruments&#34;&gt;Abby&amp;rsquo;s instruments&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby started learning mandolin just this year, joining the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pittsburghmandolinsociety.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Mandolin Orchestra&lt;/a&gt;, so I was excited that she decided early on to bring it to the jam session. (And I look forward to seeing her play for the first time in the orchestra&amp;rsquo;s concert on Mother&amp;rsquo;s Day coming up in three weeks!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She also brought a frame drum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-event&#34;&gt;The event!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;arrival&#34;&gt;Arrival&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I arrived a little late, so I scrambled to get ready while a whole bunch of people were already gathered. Many people were sitting in back just to watch and listen, while maybe twenty of us were armed with instruments of all kinds, ready to have some fun!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://fbcdn-sphotos-a.akamaihd.net/hphotos-ak-prn1/541085_10150682067126513_55075526512_9775042_292845062_n.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;We played lots of different instruments&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We ran into half a dozen people we knew from various of our musical circles, including Annie from recorder, a guy Abby knew from mandolin, and some fellow &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/16/playing-recorder-and-flute-at-the-holiday-ball/&#34;&gt;Holiday Ball&lt;/a&gt; musicians.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was intrigued by the couple of people who had actual keyed Irish flutes and eager to hear them play (it would turn out, of course, that they were very, very good).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;music-scores&#34;&gt;Music scores&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So each of us got a packet of around twenty pages of music. We didn&amp;rsquo;t play all of it, of course, but it was a good basis for sight reading along with Chris and David leading the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much of the music went at breakneck pace that I&amp;rsquo;m still not proficient enough to sight reading perfectly, but my (yet unreported) musical adventures in the past month have made me far less self-conscious about perfection and figure out ways to cope:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it&amp;rsquo;s not necessary to play all the notes; in fast music, you can contribute just fine playing only one main note per measure or harmony change&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;you can also substitute a different, easier melodic line that is compatible with the chords&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;since sections are repeated many times, you can add more during repetitions as you feel ready to&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it&amp;rsquo;s not the end of the world to miscalculate sometimes and squeak out a harsh dissonant error; the music just keeps going, so don&amp;rsquo;t look back, only forward&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;learning-by-ear-improvisation&#34;&gt;Learning by ear, improvisation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I expected, much of the time we didn&amp;rsquo;t play music from the handed out scores at all. This was the fun I was anticipating all along (I had not really expected music scores at all, actually).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost half the time, Chris would ask us for music suggestions to offer up &lt;em&gt;by example&lt;/em&gt;, so that the volunteer would play (or sing) the melody, then the rest of us would start &amp;ldquo;learning&amp;rdquo; it by ear and join in and continue with repetitions. I had not anticipated the call for volunteers, else I would have come prepared with some favorite tunes to offer!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some people were more familiar with various tunes being offered up than I was, since they had a lot more experience with Irish, Scottish and other such music than me, so I felt awkward and lost trying to learn and play on the spot, without written music, but it was part of the whole fun, really stretching what I have usually been doing with music (very oriented toward following a written score).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve mentioned before my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/10/flute-loving-it-again/&#34;&gt;poor memory&lt;/a&gt; having a considerable impact on my life, and I worked around it again, given that I could not quickly learn the details of a melody, by just giving up and improvising around the harmony changes instead. I would like to find ways to improve my memory, but for now, I work around my limitations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;a-charming-tangent-involving-an-oboe&#34;&gt;A charming tangent involving an oboe&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it turned out that a young woman among us had come with a Baroque oboe tuned to A415 instead of the modern A440 tuning. This caused confusion, of course, when she tried to play from written scores. I&amp;rsquo;m not sure what she ended up doing: the only choices were to mentally transpose from the written scores (when we were playing music from them) or just ignore the scores and learn by ear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, Chris and David repeatedly wanted to play with her and asked her what music she had on her, and she had a variety of Baroque music scores with her (she said she was actually giving a recital the next day), and so they tried to play some stuff just with her while doing their own mental transposition so that she would get to play without mental transposition! Check out Chris hovering over the score trying to do the really hard work of transposing on the fly:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://fbcdn-sphotos-a.akamaihd.net/hphotos-ak-ash4/s720x720/295215_10150682067841513_395463764_n.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Baroque oboist with Chris and David&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;dancing&#34;&gt;Dancing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Periodically, a number of people got up to dance in the space at the side, especially when we played waltzes. It was nice to see people moving.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://fbcdn-sphotos-a.akamaihd.net/hphotos-ak-ash3/529154_10150682066471513_55075526512_9775039_758574985_n.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;A couple dancing&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;i-m-caught-on-a-photo-playing-baroque-flute&#34;&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m caught on a photo playing Baroque flute&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spent a fair amount of time playing the tin whistle, and some time on my recorders, but in the end gravitated toward the Baroque flute because it was mellower and I could draw less attention to my mistakes by playing it instead!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that a photo was taken that included me when I was playing my Baroque flute. In this photo, you can also see a guy playing tin whistle (this guy also at one point volunteered to sing a tune, and did so with quite a powerful voice, a great rendition).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://fbcdn-sphotos-a.akamaihd.net/hphotos-ak-ash2/35507_10150682067581513_55075526512_9775044_1738151368_n.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;A fellow tin whistle player, and me on Baroque flute&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My posture is really bad here. I need to sit up straight and keep my head over my body rather than straining over my neck. My only excuse is that this photo was probably taken two hours into the jam session when it was almost over, and I was having energy issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-note-on-energy-requirements&#34;&gt;A note on energy requirements&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was totally exhausted after the jam session. After Abby and I drove back home, we both had to eat something. We were starving. We should have taken a snack break at the jam session.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I weighed myself and I had lost weight. The mental demands on me were considerable, and I had really spent myself. Given that I have lost weight before when taking exams in school, or playing in chess tournaments, or doing similar activities that combine both mental demands and personal anxiety, I should have been better prepared with fuel at the event. I get the impression that I burn more energy by thinking hard than by running.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was my first time ever at a public music jam session, and I quite enjoyed it. I am grateful to Chris Norman and David Greenberg, and the Pittsburgh Renaissance and Baroque, for providing it to the community. I am always very happy for opportunities to play music with Abby, and keep remembering how she got me into this particular early traditional dance music world, through our first musical time together at the Holiday Ball.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got self-feedback about musical shortcomings for me to keep working on in order to enjoy future jam sessions, and I learned that I really need food to keep me fueled for optimal musicality!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>For real geeks, today is not Pi Day, but Half-Tau Day</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/03/14/for-real-geeks-today-is-not-pi-day-but-half-tau-day/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Mar 2012 18:52:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/03/14/for-real-geeks-today-is-not-pi-day-but-half-tau-day/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://s3.amazonaws.com/ksr/projects/39714/photo-full.jpg?1309271700&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Say no to pi&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Today, many of us geeks celebrate &lt;a href=&#34;http://piday.org/&#34;&gt;Pi Day&lt;/a&gt;, because &lt;em&gt;π = 3.1415926535897932384626433&amp;hellip;&lt;/em&gt; is such an important number in math and science. I have to confess that I have never celebrated Pi Day, but it was just last year that I found out there was a movement &lt;em&gt;against&lt;/em&gt; celebrating Pi Day, and advocating the celebration of &lt;a href=&#34;http://tauday.com/&#34;&gt;Tau Day&lt;/a&gt; instead, where the special constant (which a community has chosen to be denoted by the Greek letter &amp;ldquo;tau&amp;rdquo;, &lt;em&gt;τ&lt;/em&gt;) is &lt;em&gt;2π&lt;/em&gt;, which is &lt;em&gt;6.283&amp;hellip;&lt;/em&gt;. Upon examining the evidence briefly, I had immediately agreed that indeed, we should not be celebrating Pi Day, and that therefore, today is simply &lt;a href=&#34;http://halftauday.com/&#34;&gt;Half-Tau Day&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If this is getting &lt;strong&gt;much&lt;/strong&gt; too geeky for you, feel free to ignore the rest of this blog post. Otherwise, bear with me!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-dark-days-with-π&#34;&gt;My dark days with &lt;em&gt;π&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suffered through the use of &lt;em&gt;π&lt;/em&gt; throughout high school, when we learned trigonometry and all the cosines and sines involved radians from 0 to &lt;em&gt;2π&lt;/em&gt;. Why is a complete revolution around the circle 2 times a constant, rather than being its own constant? And then there was calculus, same story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I even got sucked into true geekery, memorizing nearly 50 digits of &lt;em&gt;π&lt;/em&gt; in the summer after I graduated from high school. I still remember what happened: I was in a van traveling from Frankfurt to Jena, East Germany (this was 1987 before the fall of the Berlin Wall) as a member of the US team for the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/International_Physics_Olympiad&#34;&gt;International Physics Olympiad&lt;/a&gt; when I got really bored, and fellow teammate &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.linkedin.com/pub/bryan-beatty/13/497/581&#34;&gt;Bryan Beatty&lt;/a&gt; wrote out in pencil by memory the first 50 digits of &lt;em&gt;π&lt;/em&gt; into the front cover of a book I had on me, and I proceeded to memorize those digits (no, I did not remember them forever).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Doing math and physics homework in college, I got burned repeatedly by the extra work of carrying around factors of 2 and canceling them out when doing arithmetic, because of the incorrect definition of the &amp;ldquo;circle constant&amp;rdquo; as &lt;em&gt;π&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-08-06&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-08-06)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While doing some cleaning, I happened to find in my office the very book that I had on me during the trip and that Bryan wrote into (not the inside front cover, but the inside back cover)!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/book-with-pi.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pi.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-08-22&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-08-22)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found out that the physicist Hugh Young, the author of the book I have that Bryan wrote &lt;em&gt;π&lt;/em&gt; into, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cmu.edu/news/stories/archives/2013/august/aug22_hughyoungobit.html&#34;&gt;just died&lt;/a&gt;. RIP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-mystery-of-2π&#34;&gt;The mystery of &lt;em&gt;2π&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;2π&lt;/em&gt; keeps on popping up in places other than in high school trigonometry and calculus. As Michael Hartl points out in his excellent &lt;a href=&#34;http://tauday.com/tau-manifesto&#34;&gt;Tau Manifesto&lt;/a&gt;, anyone who has used the Gaussian (&amp;ldquo;bell curve&amp;rdquo;) distribution, through work in probability, statistics, machine learning, etc., sees the square root of &lt;em&gt;2π&lt;/em&gt; all the time, and engineers and physicists see &lt;em&gt;2π&lt;/em&gt; all the time when doing the Fourier transform. Eventually we just learn to immediately think that &lt;em&gt;π&lt;/em&gt; is just half of something. For example, if you&amp;rsquo;re doing an integral only on half the &lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt;-axis, you remember to use &lt;em&gt;π&lt;/em&gt;. This is stupid, carrying around that extra 2 everywhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conceptually&lt;/strong&gt;, the fundamental constant is clearly &lt;em&gt;2π&lt;/em&gt;, not &lt;em&gt;π&lt;/em&gt;. That is the argument we &lt;strong&gt;τ&lt;/strong&gt;-believers accept: our concepts should be mapped to our notation. I strongly recommend that disbelievers watch Hartl&amp;rsquo;s hilarious talk on &lt;em&gt;τ&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/H69YH5TnNXI&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-importance-of-good-notation-for-concepts-and-some-more-examples&#34;&gt;The importance of good notation for concepts, and some more examples&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://terrytao.wordpress.com/advice-on-writing-papers/use-good-notation/&#34;&gt;Good notation&lt;/a&gt; is actually important in communicating ideas, expressing them, thinking them. Good notation reduces mental clutter and pointless work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In physics, there is the concept of frequency. It turns out &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Angular_frequency&#34;&gt;angular frequency&lt;/a&gt; is more convenient to use, hence instead of writing the frequency &lt;em&gt;f&lt;/em&gt;, we prefer to work with &amp;ldquo;omega&amp;rdquo;, which is &lt;em&gt;ω = 2πf&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a related example of the usefulness of choosing a proper numerical constant, consider the original &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Planck_constant&#34;&gt;Planck&amp;rsquo;s constant&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;h&lt;/em&gt;. Physicists quickly realized that it was much more convenient to use the reduced constant &lt;em&gt;ħ&lt;/em&gt;, which is just &lt;em&gt;h&lt;/em&gt; divided by &lt;em&gt;2π&lt;/em&gt;. When writing equations in quantum mechanics, nobody uses &lt;em&gt;h&lt;/em&gt;. We use &lt;em&gt;ħ&lt;/em&gt; (pronounced &amp;ldquo;h bar&amp;rdquo;). The annoying factor of &lt;em&gt;2π&lt;/em&gt; is removed from the picture. In fact, in my former life as a physics student, most of the work we did involved using &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Natural_units&#34;&gt;natural units&lt;/a&gt;, in which equations and calculations are simplified by simply setting &lt;em&gt;c&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;ħ&lt;/em&gt; to 1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OK, we all know that it is completely hopeless to convert the world to using τ instead of π. Just as it is &amp;ldquo;completely hopeless&amp;rdquo; for the United States to become a multi-party political system or abolish the Electoral College.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nevertheless, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.math.utah.edu/~palais/pi.html&#34;&gt;π is wrong!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, and on June 28 this year, you bet I&amp;rsquo;ll be celebrating Tau Day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;P.S. Please don&amp;rsquo;t take any of this too seriously: I don&amp;rsquo;t!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Flute: loving it again, remembering why I dance, and how I met my wife!</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/03/10/flute-loving-it-again/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Mar 2012 21:28:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/03/10/flute-loving-it-again/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, after four days of &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/07/flute-taking-a-break-while-clarifying-my-goals&#34;&gt;not even touching my (modern) flute&lt;/a&gt; and having spent the time having fun with my Baroque flute instead, I felt the urge to return to the modern flute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still have not regained the inclination to continue working on the orchestra music I still have to improve a lot on in the coming week, but I rediscovered the joy of simply playing my instrument.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;sound-intonation&#34;&gt;Sound, intonation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The perpetual challenges of getting clean sounds and accurate pitches on the Baroque flute in the past four days have given me an increased appreciation for the modern flute. I picked it up and spent time just trying to make beautiful sounds. Freed from the stress of orchestra practice, I felt much more relaxed on the instrument than I have for a while now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To my surprise (but not really), I have improved considerably on the flute after not playing it for four days. I really needed a break, a consolidation of lessons learned. My production of tones is much improved, and high notes are squeaking less.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;music-for-dance&#34;&gt;Music for dance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing I&amp;rsquo;ve truly come to realize is that I particularly enjoy playing rhythmic music suitable for dancing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, every time I attend a dance, and there is live music, I experience a strange internal conflict: I do like to dance, but sometimes, I&amp;rsquo;d rather be on the other side of the dance floor, being the musical performer! The &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; time I&amp;rsquo;ve been on the other side has been at last year&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburghcontra.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Contras and Squares&lt;/a&gt; Holiday Ball.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most recent instance of my wishing I could sometimes stop dancing and just join the musicians has been at the local &lt;a href=&#34;http://coalcountry.org/frenchdance.html&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh French dance workshop and social&lt;/a&gt;, where we&amp;rsquo;ve had live piano, fiddle, and of course, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~gdyke/&#34;&gt;Gregory&lt;/a&gt; on his Irish flute. I wonder whether at some point I might be qualified to play for the event, using either my modern flute or Baroque flute. (By the way, it was held again today, but unfortunately, Abby and I chose not to go because we had too many things to do this weekend.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;remembering-dancing&#34;&gt;Remembering dancing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday I spent time playing along to a score/CD set I&amp;rsquo;ve mentioned before, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/World-Music-Cuba-Flute-play-along/dp/3702465804&#34;&gt;World Music Cuba&lt;/a&gt;. While playing the bolero, cha cha, and mambo pieces in particular, I felt I was returning &amp;ldquo;home&amp;rdquo; in many ways. This was among the first music I heard and saw people dancing to when I was curious and visited the &lt;a href=&#34;http://cmubdc.org/&#34;&gt;CMU Ballroom Dance Club&lt;/a&gt; in 2000, and fell in love with, and learned to dance to. I also played along to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Play-along-Argentina-Flute-World-Music/dp/3702465871&#34;&gt;World Music Argentina&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;some-photos-of-my-ballroom-dance-days&#34;&gt;Some photos of my ballroom dance days&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some photos of me dancing in 2002 with my last dance partner, Amy, before I quit competitive ballroom dancing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here we are at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dcdancesportinferno.com/&#34;&gt;DC DanceSport Inferno&lt;/a&gt; in 2002 doing a hockey stick in international rumba:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/ballroom/dcdi-2002-hockey-stick.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Amy and Franklin at DCDI 2002 in rumba&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And here were are at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://comp.cornelldancesport.org/&#34;&gt;Cornell DanceSport Classic&lt;/a&gt; in 2002 in cha cha, rumba, and tango:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/ballroom/cornell-2002-new-yorker.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Amy and Franklin at Cornell 2002 in cha cha&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/ballroom/cornell-2002-hockey-stick.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Amy and Franklin at Cornell 2002 in rumba&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/ballroom/cornell-2002-tango-promenade.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Amy and Franklin at Cornell 2002 in tango&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;dancing-with-abby&#34;&gt;Dancing with Abby&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But never mind the ballroom dance days. It was through salsa dancing that I met my wife!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;how-i-met-abby&#34;&gt;How I met Abby&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was through dancing that I met Abby in the first place. After quitting dancing in 2003, I never danced again until late 2006, when my friend Jon told me he had recently started salsa dancing (because of a girlfriend who got him into it) and invited me to join him at a free outdoors dance, and I went. Then as I re-entered the Pittsburgh salsa dance scene, I kept running into Abby.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;some-photos-of-us-dancing-salsa&#34;&gt;Some photos of us dancing salsa&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are not many photos of Abby dancing with me, because when I&amp;rsquo;m dancing, I&amp;rsquo;m not holding my camera, but here are some photos a friend took at a big salsa dance weekend at the Palisades in McKeesport in April 2008, a year after we started dating in 2007.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/palisades-2008/abby-franklin.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby and Franklin dancing salsa at Palisades&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/palisades-2008/abby-franklin-hair.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby and Franklin dancing salsa at Palisades, hair flying&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;expression-and-improvisation-in-dance-and-in-music&#34;&gt;Expression and improvisation in dance and in music&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;dance&#34;&gt;Dance&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One reason I gave up ballroom dancing was that I felt there was an overemphasis on &amp;ldquo;syllabus steps&amp;rdquo; (I realize this is an oversimplification of the ballroom dance culture; all very good ballroom dancers go beyond the syllabus mindset). After quitting ballroom dancing, I explored Argentine tango, which is all about improvisation, but I left it because (at the time) it seemed that most of the women in the local scene were very tall, which made dancing awkward for me. I got into salsa because freed from the closed embrace, there was clearly a lot of room for personal improvisation. Ironically, I first got into making stuff up as a result of my imperfect memory: I could never memorize long choreography of step patterns, whether I was doing ballroom dancing or anything else. So I would always make a &amp;ldquo;mistake&amp;rdquo;, then I would make something out of the mistake. I learned that as long as you get back in time with the music, and keep the lead and follow communication strong, there is no such thing really as a mistake. You just keep going, with whatever is happening at the present moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I now have a long-term goal of developing my technique and releasing my inhibitions so that I can improvise musically at will. Yesterday, I played with improvising when playing bolero, cha cha, and tango. It was a lot of fun and profoundly satisfying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;music&#34;&gt;Music&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I actually credit my study of the recorder and the Baroque flute for reawakening me to my dream of free expression and improvisation. Baroque music leaves room for a lot of interpretation of trills and ornamentation and articulation (subject, of course, to &amp;ldquo;good taste&amp;rdquo;). I want to go beyond that, but it has been a great starting point. For some reason, too much exposure to later music (such as Beethoven) had turned me into a score-reader, since such later music has so much already marked up for the performer to simply &lt;em&gt;obey&lt;/em&gt;. The sparse annotations in Renaissance and Baroque music give one much more freedom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am enjoying playing the flute again, now that I know what I really want to do with it. And I would like to merge my dance and music lives, just as Abby has always played the Balkan music she also dances to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2012-03-12&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-03-12)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ended up &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/12/quitting-the-cmu-all-university-orchestra-one-of-the-hardest-decisions-in-my-life/&#34;&gt;quitting the CMU AUO&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2013-01-26&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-01-26)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost a year later, I finally played tangos on flute &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/26/music-i-just-played-for-the-first-time-recorder-sonata-tangos/&#34;&gt;at a party&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2013-03-17&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-03-17)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost exactly a year later, I ended up playing selections from the World Music Cuba book &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/17/finally-doing-some-latin-music-jamming-on-flute/&#34;&gt;at a party&lt;/a&gt;, and improvising freely with two other guys!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I want to sing</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/11/18/i-want-to-sing/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Nov 2011 23:37:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/11/18/i-want-to-sing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Periodically through my life, I have secretly wanted to &lt;strong&gt;sing&lt;/strong&gt;. By that, I mean, &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; sing, as in not holding back, and doing it in the presence of other people, and longer than just a few seconds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The funny thing is, when I was a child, I un-self-consciously sang all the time. I remember singing when I was three years old, singing along to TV commercials and sing-along books. My parents sang to me. That was my first experience of music. The famous Julie Andrews movie &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Sound_of_Music_(film)&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Sound of Music&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; has always been special to me (despite encountering a surprising amount of mockery of it later in life) because when I was three, and my parents watched in TV, they sang along and I did too, &lt;em&gt;do-re-mi&lt;/em&gt;. I was so captivated that I even recorded it off the TV on audio cassette at that early age (and still have it, but it&amp;rsquo;s been years since it was playable).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what happened? Why did I stop singing with other people around? Why did I even start feeling embarrassed singing just to myself? And what now?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;childhood-and-adolescence&#34;&gt;Childhood and adolescence&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still have audio cassettes of myself singing at age ten, along with my younger sister. As late as ten I was still singing. Stealing tunes from TV or radio or just making stuff up. We also had old books of traditional American songs from library or garage sales that we&amp;rsquo;d flip through and try to sight read.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was when I hit puberty that everything changed, and I clammed up. My voice was funny. I didn&amp;rsquo;t like talking or singing any more. Worse, I became aware of many things, such as who was &amp;ldquo;good&amp;rdquo; at singing, sports, math, or whatever. Life became very painful. The easy way out was that if I felt I was inferior at something, I would choose not to do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the sixth grade, I took a required music class taught by Ms. Gates, whom I didn&amp;rsquo;t like at all. She was mean. I didn&amp;rsquo;t like her or our assignments. So I didn&amp;rsquo;t do my homework, and was about to flunk when my parents were called in. (My entire adolescence was a nightmare for my parents, who also had to deal with my almost flunking out of life science, starting to use four-letter words at home, growing my hair long and combing it funny, starting every argument with &amp;ldquo;this is a free country&amp;rdquo;, etc.) I made up the work, but with nothing other than resentment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing I really hated about music class was being made to sing. Before ever taking a music class, I liked singing. Taking the music class made me hate singing. I felt like I was being judged, and I especially hated singing stuff I didn&amp;rsquo;t like at all. I eventually figured out that I could just lip-sync and pretend to sing and get by.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So after middle school, I went silent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;high-school&#34;&gt;High school&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Actually, in high school I secretly started singing again, but just to myself. Bizarrely, I found a loophole in my self-imposed silence. I was taking French and somehow discovered the light operetta music of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jacques_Offenbach&#34;&gt;Jacques Offenbach&lt;/a&gt;, who is famous for the can-can. I became utterly obsessed with his catchy music, and found by accident that although in non-singing life I was painfully self-conscious about pronouncing French, when I sang I was happy to speak French, so it was a good way to learn and practice French! Also, I found by accident that although I was no longer willing to sing anything in English, if I sang in French, that was a &amp;ldquo;different&amp;rdquo; activity and OK. Very strange, but in my own room, I was completely OK with singing French operetta to myself. It was as though &lt;em&gt;I&lt;/em&gt; was not the one singing and making a fool of himself, but someone else, some French character. I would get into character and feel free of constraints (as long as I was alone).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I especially liked Offenbach&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/La_belle_H%C3%A9l%C3%A8ne&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;La Belle Hélène&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; and memorized entire arias of the shepherd-disguised Paris. More generally, I was happy to sing random French songs I came across, such as &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Je_te_veux&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Je te Veux&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. More generally, sentimental waltzes were my favorite discoveries during my melancholy high school years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;college-and-beyond&#34;&gt;College and beyond&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In college, I discovered the entire classical music world. (Some of the story was told in my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/09/taking-up-flute-again-after-decades&#34;&gt;post about flute&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As far as singing was concerned: I made a new friend who was into all things German (literature, music), and listened to songs (&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lied&#34;&gt;Lieder&lt;/a&gt;) by Beethoven, Schubert, Mahler, and others. I got into reading some stuff in translation and listening to instrumental music, but the language barrier prevented me from really enjoying listening to the songs. Eventually I took German to help me out, and so I finally started to sing along to Schubert, in particular.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later I learned Italian as well, primarily to sing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But all this in private.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;recent-years&#34;&gt;Recent years&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In recent years, I&amp;rsquo;ve started singing a little bit in other people&amp;rsquo;s presence. I think it all began because I got an office mate at work some years ago. Since it is actually my habit to hum or sing to myself every day, it was hard to contain myself in his presence. Eventually I hit upon a way to be OK with singing a little bit around him: if I sang in an parodistic way or substituted silly lyrics in place of the real lyrics, I would lose some of my self-consciousness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, this has also been true at home, where I sing some of this nonsense to Abby, who is sometimes annoyed by how silly or disgusting the made-up lyrics are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;now&#34;&gt;Now&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a plan. &lt;strong&gt;It is time to sing for real, without fear or embarrassment&lt;/strong&gt;. Playing recorder (and now flute as well) this year has been a breakthrough for me, musically and physically. I feel that playing wind instruments has given me more confidence to sing with my own voice, and that singing to myself has been good for my instrumental play as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I told Abby that I would like for us to sing together. And I would like to sing for real in front of my office mate also, not just &amp;ldquo;sing&amp;rdquo; nonsense. And somehow I should find an outlet for singing even more publicly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To do all that, I need to start learning and relearning lyrics. I have a rather poor memory for lyrics. That&amp;rsquo;s another reason I don&amp;rsquo;t sing out of the context of following some score on the computer or from a book. I don&amp;rsquo;t know exactly how to fix this problem, but maybe it&amp;rsquo;s just a matter of practice. I have started to make a list of songs whose melodies I know, but whose lyrics I don&amp;rsquo;t, so that I can start filling in the gaps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Singing is too fun to be just outsourced to the professionals. It must become a real part of my life, not a secret part of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently I came across this passionate little &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId=97320958&#34;&gt;speech by Brian Eno&lt;/a&gt; about the importance of singing. It inspired me to make a plan and write this blog post. May we all go forth and sing!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2012-11-17&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-11-17)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost exactly a year later, I have made progress in getting up the courage to &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/11/17/a-childhood-dream-come-true-i-am-now-finally-singing-for-real/&#34;&gt;really start singing&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>