<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Smartphone on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/smartphone/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Smartphone on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/smartphone/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Thoughts upon uninstalling &#34;Temple Run 2&#34; from my phone</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/05/16/thoughts-upon-uninstalling-temple-run-2-from-my-phone/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 May 2014 20:37:34 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/05/16/thoughts-upon-uninstalling-temple-run-2-from-my-phone/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have a confession to make.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/thumb/c/c4/TempleRun.jpg/150px-TempleRun.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Temple Run logo&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Two years ago, when I finally got my first &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/22/paradox-i-will-observe-the-national-day-of-unplugging-but-just-bought-my-first-smartphone-this-week/&#34;&gt;smartphone&lt;/a&gt;, I downloaded a free game, &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Temple_Run&#34;&gt;Temple Run&lt;/a&gt;, and quickly became a bit obsessed with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was the first computer game I had played in &lt;em&gt;twenty years&lt;/em&gt;, actually; although in college I played a fair number of games (including actual physical arcade games in the basement of the college dining hall), including &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dark_Castle&#34;&gt;Dark Castle&lt;/a&gt;, which I commandeered friends&amp;rsquo; Macs to play (I owned only an Apple IIe in college, for word processing purposes), the last time I played computer games was in grad school twenty years ago, when I conquered a Mac game called &amp;ldquo;Kung Fu Chivalry&amp;rdquo;. Somehow, after actually winning that game, I totally lost interest in playing computer games again (despite being annoyed about never finishing &amp;ldquo;Beyond Dark Castle&amp;rdquo;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I noticed that my reaction time and coordination were quite rusty after twenty years away from this kind of game, and was determined to get good at Temple Run. I was really bad for a while, but then everything started falling into place, and I got good enough that I got a bit bored. I forgot about the game for a long time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Months later, &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Temple_Run_2&#34;&gt;Temple Run 2&lt;/a&gt; came out, and I got that, and deleted the original Temple Run. The graphics were much better and the action was more interesting, but again, I got good enough that I got bored. Eventually I stopped playing the game. It&amp;rsquo;s probably been almost a year since I last played it, actually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I still had it on my phone, just in case I got &amp;ldquo;bored&amp;rdquo; or wanted to check up on my reaction time to see if I had retained my improvements. I never did end up playing it again though. Finally, I just deleted it, to free up space on my phone and to commit to saying goodbye to the game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thoughts flashed through my mind as I deleted the game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;we-are-always-choosing-how-to-spend-our-time-we-must-own-our-choices&#34;&gt;We are always choosing how to spend our time; we must own our choices&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I felt guilty every time I played the game on the phone (or the iPad, on which I had also installed the game, but I didn&amp;rsquo;t play it often on that). Part of me thought it was a waste of time. Part of me rationalized that I was &amp;ldquo;training&amp;rdquo; my brain and fingers to improve my overall reaction time and motor coordination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t like feeling guilty about anything&lt;/em&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;d rather just &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; the thing in all good conscience, or &lt;em&gt;not do&lt;/em&gt; it at all. At some point, I resolved the dissonance for good by no longer playing the game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;i-noticed-how-i-had-let-the-smartphone-intrude-on-my-life&#34;&gt;I noticed how I had let the smartphone intrude on my life&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously, upon getting my first smartphone, I was excited by all the things I could do that I couldn&amp;rsquo;t do before. I could check my email anywhere, read my RSS feeds, Facebook, etc. I even loaded up some of my books onto the phone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found myself pulling out the phone to play the game when I was &amp;ldquo;bored&amp;rdquo; while riding in a car or something. Then I realized that I was missing the scenery, or just plain quiet time away from technology. Eventually, I decided to minimize the use of my phone when away from home or work, where I&amp;rsquo;m already in front of a computer most of the time already anyway. Yes, I can spend several hours without checking my phone for email (especially if I&amp;rsquo;m in the middle of nowhere with no reception).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;i-got-sucked-in-by-fear-of-losing-my-accumulated-wealth&#34;&gt;I got sucked in by fear of losing my accumulated &amp;ldquo;wealth&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I took so long to delete the game because I kept thinking that if I ever wanted to keep playing, I had racked up a lot of points and &amp;ldquo;unlocked&amp;rdquo; various powers, so I wanted to keep all that &amp;ldquo;just in case&amp;rdquo;. So keeping the game wasn&amp;rsquo;t even really about my enjoyment of it any more; I just liked the &amp;ldquo;wealth&amp;rdquo; I had accumulated. I was hoarding what was really worthless. The only thing I could do with my unlocked powers was continue playing the game to earn more powers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-was-once-fun-and-useful-may-become-stale&#34;&gt;What was once fun and useful may become stale&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still believe that it was worth spending some time playing the game. It really did improve my mental functioning to a degree. But there were no further benefits to be gained. It is worth periodically evaluating whether old activities or habits are still doing us any good, even if they once did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had my fun with Temple Run, learned some things about myself along the way, and now am done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How do you feel when you uninstall a favorite game or app, or declutter in some other way? Do you feel sadness? Relief? Regret? Pride?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My Rachel Carson Trail hike for the year (13.4 miles): and how this is about love and gratitude</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/05/12/my-rachel-carson-trail-hike-for-the-year/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 May 2013 22:24:40 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/05/12/my-rachel-carson-trail-hike-for-the-year/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today I did my first hike of the year (normally I would have done hiking already in the spring, but the combination of Abby&amp;rsquo;s broken foot and my Pittsburgh Marathon training this year resulted in no space for hiking until after the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/05/06/2013-pittsburgh-marathon-my-135th-race-was-my-worst-i-finished/&#34;&gt;marathon, which I did seven days ago&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first hike of the year just happened to turn out to be a grueling Rachel Carson Trail hike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, I reported on the two Rachel Carson Trail Challenge goal training hikes I did in &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/04/29/a-pretty-rachel-carson-trail-challenge-goal-training-hike/&#34;&gt;late April&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/06/03/a-totally-exhausting-rachel-carson-trail-challenge-goal-training-hike/&#34;&gt;early June&lt;/a&gt;. This year, I did the fourth of eight of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rachelcarsontrails.org/rct/challenge/rctc13/goaltraining&#34;&gt;year&amp;rsquo;s goal training hikes&lt;/a&gt; offered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sunday, May 12&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Leader: Donna Stolz 412-303-6102, Eileen Lessman 412-760-8863&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;13.4 miles&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Elevation change: 5055 ft&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;This hike begins in North Park and heads over to Emmerling Park, then up and over Rich Hill and Lefever Hill. We end at the Log Cabin Road checkpoint location. Meet at Log Cabin Road parking area. Take Route 28 to Exit #12. Turn right at the end of the ramp, then right at the stop sign onto Little Deer Creek Road (aka Russellton Road). Travel about 1.5 miles and turn right on Log Cabin Road. Park about 100 yards ahead on the right.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As of this year, I&amp;rsquo;ve decided to do &lt;em&gt;only one&lt;/em&gt; Rachel Carson Trail hike a year, so this was it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is my report on the hike, as well as my long-awaited explanation of why this trail means so much to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;weather&#34;&gt;Weather&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The conditions were good. It was kind of chilly and windy, probably 45-50 degrees throughout the hike. The sun came and went. There were only short periods of light drizzling rain, thankfully.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;footwear&#34;&gt;Footwear&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Vibram FiveFingers KSO Trek shoes I wore last year on the Rachel Carson Trail developed holes, as a result of which I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/08/28/five-reasons-we-just-stocked-up-on-vibram-fivefingers-kso-trek-shoes/&#34;&gt;stocked up on some new ones&lt;/a&gt;. The pair that I opened, I&amp;rsquo;ve worn only a couple of times, and I wore this pair today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;comparison-with-last-year-s-hike&#34;&gt;Comparison with last year&amp;rsquo;s hike&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/06/03/a-totally-exhausting-rachel-carson-trail-challenge-goal-training-hike/&#34;&gt;Last year on the 18.1 mile hike&lt;/a&gt;, I was stupid about my smartphone, and this year I was smarter. Today&amp;rsquo;s hike was a shorter 13.4, so I was sure the battery would last long enough, if I didn&amp;rsquo;t take photos with flash. And of course, I always have a phone charge in my car now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year&amp;rsquo;s hike went east to west and ended in North Park. This year&amp;rsquo;s hike went west to east and started in North Park. But being shorter, it did not end in Springdale. It is really a different hike when you go on the same trail but in a different direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might enjoy comparing the photos in different directions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;meeting-up-at-log-cabin-road&#34;&gt;Meeting up at Log Cabin Road&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;John and I arrived on time but not early, which meant that when we arrived, we saw a whole contingent of people already carpooling to head to North Park. We never saw those people again. Oops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, although we were ready to go with the hike leader, Donna, latecomers kept on showing up, and we were lenient and waited for them, before all the rest of us remaining headed to North Park.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Waiting for latecomers:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_08.03.20.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Because of Route 910 closures, some detours were necessary as Donna&amp;rsquo;s husband drove us to North Park.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;hike&#34;&gt;Hike&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In North Park about to begin:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_08.45.23.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_08.45.26.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;By the time we started, there were only a handful of us together as a group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was momentarily confused because I saw someone running in the &lt;em&gt;wrong direction&lt;/em&gt; on the trail and thought she might be one of us, and was worried. I tried to follow her to call out to her, but she disappeared quickly:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_08.45.34.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, Donna called out to me, and I rejoined the group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In North Park, a few sections of the trail are on the road, but then we go into the woods for real:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_08.51.43.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_08.51.49.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_08.52.15.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a whole bunch of stream crossings while in North Park. Some of them are easier than others. I should note that one of the harder ones had some fast water and basically ensured that your feet would get wet, because the logs were floating and not completely safe to step on. Some people jumped, but that&amp;rsquo;s not safe. Wearing KSO Trek shoes, since the temperature was around 50, I was fine just getting my feet wet by walking through the water.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_09.05.16.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_09.05.22.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_09.10.50.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_09.10.56.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Out of the woods onto the railroad tracks (note that hiking in the reverse direction is tricky because it&amp;rsquo;s not well-marked where to get off the railroad tracks into the woods; John and I got lost the last time we did the reverse hike and had to backtrack!).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_09.18.50.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_09.19.23.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a good amount of road walking on this section of the Rachel Carson Trail.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_09.27.01.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_09.27.14.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_09.29.46.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_09.53.40.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Crossing Route 8:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_10.03.01.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Finally, the power lines:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_10.04.28.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_10.05.59.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_10.22.47.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I am a bit sentimental about this section of trail in Hampton Park because Abby and I have done some cross country skiing here in winter, when she used to live up here before we got married and she moved to Pittsburgh.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_10.29.52.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Abby and I have also hung out here in the past watching birds.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_10.32.38.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_10.37.55.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_10.41.13.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_10.48.38.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_10.49.37.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_10.54.37.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here is where John and I got lost. I was distracted by this sight and made a turn toward it (the trail turned in the opposite direction) to check it out:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_10.55.25.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;OK, &amp;ldquo;acidic condensate collection tank&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_10.56.02.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Hmm, this didn&amp;rsquo;t look familiar.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_10.57.12.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_11.05.31.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;John and I turned back. We lost about ten minutes.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_11.06.42.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_11.07.38.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_11.15.12.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_11.18.16.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;No animals out and about today!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_11.41.38.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_11.43.09.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Funny how this happens to me once or twice each hike:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_12.01.43.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What the heck is this going on?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_12.07.33.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Uphill.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_12.07.53.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_12.11.35.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_12.19.47.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Finally at Emmerling Park, about 3 hours and 45 minutes into the hike.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_12.28.15.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I hung out at Emmerling Park for about ten or fifteen minutes, using the restroom and then playing on the swing relieving my aching feet while waiting for John and the others to catch up and also use the restroom. The truth is, I was ready to stop hiking already, feeling tired. I was also sore because of two falls I had sustained earlier in the hike. One of the falls involved my tripping on my right foot, causing me to land hard on my left, reinjuring my left knee that I had hurt before the marathon in a fall down the stairs. My left knee was causing me serious pain again now in the hike. I also fell on a steep downhill earlier, landing directly on my butt and on the palm of my left hand, which reinjured my left elbow. Finally, my right Achilles was killing me, because I had not adjusted the strap of my shoe properly; I had readjusted it during the hike, but the damage was already done. I was quite ready to stop hiking, but there were still two hours to go! Oops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Red flower:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_12.49.45.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_12.49.54.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;And now we got to sections of the trail that are abused by ATVs and rutted and muddy. (We ended up encountering someone on an ATV, in fact.)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_13.02.18.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Standing water:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_13.05.17.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_13.14.42.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_13.22.04.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_13.24.59.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No fun at all hiking through these muddy ruts:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_13.28.24.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Finally back into open space:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_13.29.43.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Looking back down the big hill:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_13.33.09.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s John and the rest down at the bottom:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_13.34.50.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We keep on going up:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_13.34.55.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_13.38.45.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Finally at the top, looking back:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_13.39.36.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_13.49.12.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_13.51.14.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_13.58.01.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s going on here?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_14.05.03.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_14.05.28.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_14.09.45.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_14.15.19.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_14.20.47.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_14.21.07.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Finally back to the parking lot!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2013-05-12/2013-05-12_14.25.11.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;after&#34;&gt;After&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We hiked something like 5 hours and 45 minutes. It felt really long to us, as our first hike of the year. My feet were killing me. I was happy to take my shoes off and drive us back home barefoot!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, my phone still barely had battery power left when we finished. I&amp;rsquo;m not sure it would have lasted another hour. This is useful to know. Of course, I immediately plugged it into my car charger! I should get an extra battery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-hike-this-trail-at-all&#34;&gt;Why hike this trail at all?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby is confused why I like occasionally (once or twice a year) hiking on the Rachel Carson Trail, even though much of the time I find it tiring and weird. I&amp;rsquo;ve never fully explained this in words, so here, finally, is my explanation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have many sentimental reasons to hike this trail. One is that eight years ago, in late May of 2005, when a local running friend said he was doing the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rachelcarsontrails.org/rct/challenge/rctc05&#34;&gt;Rachel Carson Trail Challenge&lt;/a&gt;, I had taken an entire half year off from running was feeling sad and lonely. I looked up the Challenge online, and happened to find that &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rachelcarsontrails.org/rct/challenge/rctc05/training&#34;&gt;training hikes led by Barb Peterson&lt;/a&gt; were being offered in just a few days, and although I had no intention whatsoever to do the Challenge, I thought the training hikes would be a fun way to do and see something different. After doing the third of four, I was so excited by the novelty that I ended up signing up for the Challenge!! With only three weeks left, there was not much training I could do for it, but I figured that if I just took it slowly, I should be able to finish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2005 Challenge was an ordeal for me to finish, but I did, and the side effect was that I fell in love with hiking in general. I met people through doing the Challenge, and in 2006 I roped John into joining me on some longer training hikes, where we met more people, and some of them I began hiking with outside the context of the Challenge, in places like the Laurel Highlands. This was before the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/pittsburghhikers/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Hiking Meetup&lt;/a&gt; was formed in May 2007 and made it much easier to find people to hike with. So the 2005 Challenge had the side effect of getting me into making hiking a regular part of my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, as I was training for the 2007 Challenge, that was the time when I had just met Abby and was dancing with her, but we were not dating yet. When we were chatting at a salsa dance, I learned that she liked to hike and was intrigued. I invited her to join me and John for an April 29 Rachel Carson Trail Challenge training hike that happened to be passing through Hampton (as today&amp;rsquo;s hike did), and she said she would join us for part of it. A comic series of events then took place, in which John and I arrived at Hampton earlier than she had expected, so she had not yet made it to Hampton to meet up with us. When I paused to call her, and she said she would meet us in the trail, John and I got confused and lost because of miscommunication. I kept having to call her again and again until we finally found her, and she set us straight back onto the trail and hiked with us for a bit before turning back. That was my first interaction with Abby outside of dancing; I got to see how she gracefully handled my clumsy mistakes during this outing and how helpful she was. It was a month after that when we finally started dating. Eventually, I proposed right after a hike led by one of the guys I originally first met through a Rachel Carson Trail Challenge training hike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I associate the Rachel Carson Trail not only with falling in love with hiking, and with meeting lots of interesting people I still hike with all these years later, but also I am reminded of how I fell in love with Abby and how hiking is a big part of what we have done and do. It is slightly ironic, of course, that she does not enjoy doing most sections of the Rachel Carson Trail, so in recent years I have been hiking it either alone or with John. And that is why I try to limit how often I hike on the trail; I&amp;rsquo;ve decided now to do it only once a year, so that I spend less time on hiking that Abby doesn&amp;rsquo;t do with me, in order to share more hiking with her. But I would like to spend good time on the trail once a year from now on to remember what it means to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, despite the strange hybrid nature of the trail, I believe in its existence and maintenance. It is a reminder that even in urban/suburban environments, there is still an underlying primitive nature that we can enjoy. The volunteers of the Rachel Carson Trails Conservancy work hard to keep this unusual resource open to the public.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/11/fascinating-bushwhacking-hike-at-pa-state-game-land-51-dunbar/&#34;&gt;Example from March 2012 of the kind of hike that Abby and I have enjoyed doing.&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Rachel Carson Trail will always have a special place in my heart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to Donna for keeping us company for most of the hike as trail sweep, and her husband for driving us to the start!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2013 Pittsburgh Marathon: my 135th race was the worst I finished, but I did!</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/05/06/2013-pittsburgh-marathon-my-135th-race-was-my-worst-i-finished/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 May 2013 20:23:08 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/05/06/2013-pittsburgh-marathon-my-135th-race-was-my-worst-i-finished/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/runner-of-steel.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin Chen, runner of steel&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/lying-down.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin lying down&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, for my birthday, I ran the Pittsburgh Marathon for the second time. The first time was &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/30/why-and-how-i-am-going-to-run-the-2013-pittsburgh-marathon/&#34;&gt;ten years ago, in 2003&lt;/a&gt;. That was an ordeal in which I had aimed at finishing in 3:30 and in fact run the first half in 1:45, but then faltered badly to struggle to finish in a &lt;a href=&#34;http://runhigh.com/.2003%20Results%20A/R050403AA.html&#34;&gt;chip time of 3:53:25&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My second Pittsburgh Marathon went even worse. I had wanted to finish in 4:00, but instead &lt;a href=&#34;http://results.active.com/events/dicks-sporting-goods-pittsburgh-marathon&#34;&gt;finished in 4:38:21&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was my 135th race in my life, and the worst of them all that I actually finished (I failed to finish one 30K race because of severe illness that should have kept me from going to the start line at all).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s my report on what happened, why, my thankfulness for all the good that came from the experience, and my running plans for the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;coming-back-from-injury-and-burnout&#34;&gt;Coming back from injury and burnout&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it&amp;rsquo;s important to understand that my poor performance did not come from nowhere. I had battled injury and burnout &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/05/04/i-spent-the-past-week-not-knowing-whether-i-could-run-in-the-2013-pittsburgh-marathon-tomorrow/&#34;&gt;for some time&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Logically&lt;/em&gt;, I should not have gone to the start line at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;night-before&#34;&gt;Night before&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got zero sleep the night before the race. Terrible, but my body was probably confused by the carb-loaded diet as well as my insistence on spending the whole day napping because I was so tired. I had felt that I had to do that napping because I was not going to be able to sleep well at night anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;early-morning-on-race-day&#34;&gt;Early morning on race day&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Super early, Abby drove us to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.visitpittsburgh.com/essentials/neighborhoods/north-shore/&#34;&gt;North Shore&lt;/a&gt; to park. Then we napped for a bit before heading to the nearest &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pittsburgh_Light_Rail&#34;&gt;light rail (aka &amp;ldquo;T&amp;rdquo;)&lt;/a&gt; station to wait for a ride downtown:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/go-downtown.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby and I wait for T&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We got downtown finally, I dropped off a bag of post-race flip-flops at Gear Check, time was starting to run out, and I got in line for a Port-a-pottie:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/port-a-potties.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Port-a-potties&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It was 15 minutes before I did what I needed to do. Then I had to quickly head to my corral.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;clothing&#34;&gt;Clothing&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/franklin-before-marathon.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin before marathon&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;What I wore:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the &lt;em&gt;same blue singlet&lt;/em&gt; I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/30/why-and-how-i-am-going-to-run-the-2013-pittsburgh-marathon/&#34;&gt;wore in the 2003 Pittsburgh Marathon ten years ago&lt;/a&gt; (my favorite running shirt that I have actually worn for probably at least 70 of my races in over a decade, as well as most of my warm-weather casual runs also!!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Brooks Infiniti Short III that I bought at Elite Runners and Walkers before the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/30/report-on-just-a-short-run-my-first-half-marathon-in-nine-years/&#34;&gt;Just A Short Run half marathon in March&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Luna Sandals (Venado) that I&amp;rsquo;ve been wearing for almost all of my runs in the past month, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/04/13/my-final-16-mile-long-run-before-pittsburgh-marathon-featured-two-radical-experiments/&#34;&gt;maximum distance of 16 miles&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;CEP compression calf sleeves, which I had worn just &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/04/20/on-overtraining-and-feeling-injured-two-weeks-before-the-pittsburgh-marathon/&#34;&gt;one other time&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/22/paradox-i-will-observe-the-national-day-of-unplugging-but-just-bought-my-first-smartphone-this-week/&#34;&gt;phone&lt;/a&gt;, in a SPIbelt.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;on my back, I pinned a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/04/20/on-overtraining-and-feeling-injured-two-weeks-before-the-pittsburgh-marathon/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;We are all Boston Marathoners at heart&amp;rdquo; bib&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a long-sleeve T-shirt on top of my singlet, since it was cold (under 50 degrees F?) before the race; the plan was to discard this T-shirt before the race (and hope that people collect it and find a good home for it!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;entering-the-corral&#34;&gt;Entering the corral&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the second race in my life in which I have carried a phone. I planned to use it only in case of emergency, and in order to meet up with Abby afterwards, but as you can see, while I had a chance, I took some photos also.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/corral-c.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Corral C&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I was assigned to corral C because of my estimated finish time of 4:00 that I had written down when signing up for the marathon months ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This was my first mistake.&lt;/em&gt; Given my comeback from injury and inactivity, the truly logical thing for me to have done was to set a very conservative goal of simply finishing the marathon without terrible suffering. Given that I ended up finishing in 4:38, I might as well have moved back into another corral and &lt;em&gt;planned&lt;/em&gt; to finish in the 4:20-4:30 range, in which case I bet I would have done that with minimal pain and suffering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the future, I resolve to face the facts on the ground in any event as strenuous as a marathon. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t make any sense what I did, especially given that I was perfectly smart when &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/30/report-on-just-a-short-run-my-first-half-marathon-in-nine-years/&#34;&gt;in March I did my first half marathon in nine years and ran it conservatively and had a great experience&lt;/a&gt;! I am capable of logical reasoning and have actually executed it in the past. But apparently the marathon puts me into a hyper-emotional frame of mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;pace&#34;&gt;Pace?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, I had chosen not to sign up to follow an &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pittsburghmarathon.com/pace-team&#34;&gt;official pacer&lt;/a&gt;, because on all my long training runs, I had found my own pace by feel, and done well ignoring pacers. My plan was simply to go slow and then get faster. I did look around for pace signs. I only saw one from where I was standing: a sign near the front of the corral for finishing in 3:50. I looked back and saw no other signs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This was my second mistake.&lt;/em&gt; Given that I had not done any serious running for ten days, with my longest run being only two miles, and my last &amp;ldquo;long&amp;rdquo; run was an eleven-mile run fifteen days ago, I should have realized that whatever &amp;ldquo;feel&amp;rdquo; I had for pace was gone, and I should have moved back in the corral till I found a 4:00-finishing pacer, at least (but as mentioned earlier, what I should have done was move into a slower corral altogether and then found a suitable pacer there).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;race-start&#34;&gt;Race start&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a moment of silence for Boston.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Star-Spangled Banner, then the waves began. A photo as mine was approaching the start line, around 7:05 AM:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/start-line.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;About to reach the start line&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Then we went.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;wrong-pace&#34;&gt;Wrong pace&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I honestly thought I was going slow. I was hardly breathing at all. I was going so &amp;ldquo;slow&amp;rdquo; that I pulled out my phone to take some photos. But then I got very confused, because the 3:50 pacer was still in my sight after many minutes:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/early.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Early in the marathon&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I could not process this information. Part of me wanted to slow down, but I felt like I was barely running. Part of me believed that the pacer must be slow, but come on, these pacers are supposed to be reliable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I &lt;em&gt;made the mistake&lt;/em&gt; of not trusting the pacer. It sounds crazy, but I really felt like I was going too slow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;slowing-down&#34;&gt;Slowing down?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point, I lost sight of the pacer, so I felt reassured that I must have slowed down properly. Here&amp;rsquo;s another problem: I did not keep track of my mile splits because the mass of people made it hard for me to actually reliably spot any mile markers on the course; I don&amp;rsquo;t even know how many actually existed.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/bridge.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Crossing bridge&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I even took a photo of myself 40 minutes into the marathon feeling fine.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/franklin-early.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There were spectators on bridges, some of them positioned seemingly precariously.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/spectators-on-bridges.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Spectators on bridge&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At some point I realized that I could see the 3:50 pacer up ahead. I got worried. It was unlikely that I was magically super-fit now. But I didn&amp;rsquo;t feel like slowing down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point I must have started slowing down, because eventually I saw a 3:55 pacer pass me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still, it appears from the alert system that I signed up for (to notify my parents by email, and Abby by text message, and my Facebook friends and Twitter followers), that I did the first 10K (6.2 miles) in 55:29, meaning an average pace of 8:56 and estimated finish time of 3:54:04. That&amp;rsquo;s much faster than the 9:08 pace I had intended for a 4:00 finish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;really-slowing-down&#34;&gt;Really slowing down&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started really slowing down before even reaching the Birmingham Bridge. I knew I was getting into serious trouble. It was crazy, but my left knee was bothering me, and my left quads had started to twitch. So I had gone only about 11 miles and I was already struggling.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/birmingham-bridge.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;On Birmingham Bridge&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You have to understand how &lt;em&gt;nonsensical&lt;/em&gt; it is for me to be having muscle cramping after running only 11 miles at a pace that is actually slow for an 11-mile run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if we assumed, falsely, that I got to mile 11 at the same pace as during my first 6.2 miles (8:56), note that I ran an entire half marathon (13.1 miles) in late March, only in the beginning of marathon training, at an average of 8:28 pace, and was totally fine with no cramping during the race. And after a couple of weeks of further training, I had felt much stronger during a 16-mile run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So basically, it was a cruel joke I played on myself that I was in such poor condition that I was cramping up after 11 miles at a slow pace. I was very angry at myself that I had made a complete &lt;em&gt;travesty&lt;/em&gt; of my marathon, &lt;em&gt;just like in 2003&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;halfway-and-change-of-plan&#34;&gt;Halfway, and change of plan&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I slowed down more in Oakland to keep the left quad twitching under control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the alert system, I got halfway in 1:59:46, average pace of 9:09, and estimated finish time of 3:59:31. But of course, by then, I knew that I was done for. I was just going to continue slowing down and suffering, for &lt;em&gt;over two more hours&lt;/em&gt;, if I finished at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I finally saw the 4:00 pace group pass me, somehow that was a real blow to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At 9:27 AM, not too long after the halfway point, I texted Abby: &amp;ldquo;Severe pain. Very slow, just aim finish. Maybe 4:30.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now my main thought was to focus on making it to Annie (of the Pittsburgh Recorder Society), who was going to watch for me in Highland Park, just before mile 20. I had told her to expect me around 10 AM, and Annie had even posted to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/photo.php?fbid=463404163737512&amp;amp;set=a.368839359860660.86924.330712777006652&amp;amp;type=1&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Recorder Society Facebook page&lt;/a&gt; telling everyone I was running.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was so not going to make it for 10 AM. But I wanted to go slowly enough that I could hold off the quad cramping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;despair&#34;&gt;Despair&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At around 9:49 AM, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.runoverit.com/&#34;&gt;Chris&lt;/a&gt; passed me and said hello. I told him I was doing very badly. He wasn&amp;rsquo;t doing as well as he had hoped, but was moving along, unlike me. Here&amp;rsquo;s a photo I had the presence of mind to take only as he had already gone way ahead (in the blue shirt):&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/chris.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Chris up ahead in blue shirt&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At 9:54 AM, I made a video statement on my phone, just for myself: &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m after mile 17 or something, in Homewood. I&amp;rsquo;m doing really badly, but I&amp;rsquo;m still running, and that&amp;rsquo;s all I can say about that.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/12inzKGZGRU&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/despair.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Despair after mile 17 in Pittsburgh Marathon&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;annie&#34;&gt;Annie&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At 10:11 AM, not yet at Annie&amp;rsquo;s, I was contemplating quitting, because the pains I was experiencing (right quads twitching also, and even my arms and hands, mysteriously, in spots where I had old injuries years ago, plus a really bad blister on my right foot where I had all those skin problems earlier, and less bad but very annoying constant chafing of the Luna Sandals straps) were so terrible. I decided to just take a break at a fluid station and squat and stretch. I texted Abby: &amp;ldquo;Very bad shape. Rested some.&amp;rdquo; I also finally &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/franklin.chen/posts/10201315392704609&#34;&gt;posted to Facebook&lt;/a&gt;, &amp;ldquo;In very bad shape. Trying to finish anyway.&amp;rdquo; I was not actively reading Facebook during the marathon at all, but did notice a lot of notifications, and assumed they were words of encouragement from my friends; I didn&amp;rsquo;t want to read them until I was done, because I felt I might let them down. Abby replied, &amp;ldquo;What is your plan?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At 10:19, I said, &amp;ldquo;Don&amp;rsquo;t know. Walking, blister and cramping.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A note on the blistering and chafing: it got really warm and I got sweaty, so that was part of the problem. I had not run in these sandals in such conditions before: I had mostly run in dry, cold conditions of 35-50 degrees F. Also, I had forgotten about road hazards: there were cups of water and Gatorade all over around the aid stations and my feet were sticky and wet for much of the marathon. It was a rather unpleasant feeling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I kept running/walking. I saw Annie. I decided there and then, seeing her, that I was going to finish, rather than just bail out and crash on her couch or something pathetic like that. I shouted that I was in severe pain but planned to continue on! She took a photo of me, which I knew was going to be on Facebook before too long, so I&amp;rsquo;d better make good on my promise to her!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/franklin-in-highland-park.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin in Highland Park&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At 10:29, I texted Abby: &amp;ldquo;Got to Annie. Running again.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I then focused on just continuing to move, slowing to a walk if I needed to in order to deal with cramping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;mile-22&#34;&gt;Mile 22&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At 10:51, I reached S Aiken, just before mile 22. This is an important point in the course for me, not only because it begins a downhill, but also because it is where my friend Nathaniel cheered me on ten years ago when I was also suffering.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/aiken.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;S Aiken&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;strip-district&#34;&gt;Strip District&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point, I was getting discouraged again and started walking, when I accidentally spotted Deb and Mark watching. Seeing familiar faces among the spectators is definitely helpful! Upon seeing them, I felt ashamed of my walking and my negative thoughts. I went up to them, and they were going to take a picture of me, and I got all determined, and &lt;em&gt;screamed&lt;/em&gt;, &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m going to finish this thing!!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/im-going-to-finish-this-thing.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin determined to finish&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I kept on running, and did not stop, even though I saw many people walking, and also saw many relay runners zooming by. I decided that I was not only going to finish (it was now clear that I could), but that I was going to finish as strong as I could, even though it would count for nothing. I was going to run at the edge of quad twitching, all the way to the end. It was going to hurt far more than if I just ran very slowly to finish, but I didn&amp;rsquo;t come this far just to walk if I could run. I was determined to push.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/franklin-in-strip.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin in Strip District&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As I got closer and closer, I periodically texted Abby the street I had just crossed, so that she would know roughly when I was going to finish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;finish-line&#34;&gt;Finish line&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so I finished. I finished in a state of my quads twitching like firecrackers. I got my medal. I kept on walking. I grabbed a bag of chips and water. I forgot to look for other stuff, like Smiley Cookies (that Abby later said she saw were being handed out). I just wanted to stop the twitching, get my bag from Gear Check, get out of my Luna Sandals into some comfortable, cushioned flip-flops, use a Port-a-potty, and finally find Abby and the &amp;ldquo;CMU tent&amp;rdquo;, which I assumed was just a section of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pittsburghmarathon.com/PCC&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Corporate Challenge Tent&lt;/a&gt;. (I had bought a bracelet for Abby earlier so that she could have access to the tent.)&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/after.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;After finishing&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I could barely walk after I started cooling down, because I got stiffer and stiffer. It took me forever to make it to the Finish Line Festival area, and I was so mentally drained that I had to call Abby to have her tell me where the tent was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;videos-update-of-2013-05-23&#34;&gt;Videos (update of 2013-05-23)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburgh.cbslocal.com/2013/05/05/2013-marathon-finish-line-videos/&#34;&gt;Videos of the Pittsburgh Marathon have been posted&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found myself in &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburgh.cbslocal.com/video/8844851-2013-marathon-finish-line-44000-45000/&#34;&gt;one of the sets of videos&lt;/a&gt;, for those who finished in a clock time between 4:40:00 and 4:50:00.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see me at around 4:44:35 and finishing at about 4:44:40 here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&#39;text/javascript&#39; src=&#39;http://CBSPIT.images.worldnow.com/interface/js/WNVideo.js?rnd=998125;hostDomain=video.pittsburgh.cbslocal.com;playerWidth=615;playerHeight=365;isShowIcon=true;clipId=8844851;flvUri=;partnerclipid=;adTag=Sport;advertisingZone=CBS.PITTS%252Fworldnowplayer;enableAds=true;landingPage=;islandingPageoverride=false;playerType=STANDARD_EMBEDDEDscript;controlsType=fixed&#39;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://video.pittsburgh.cbslocal.com&#34; title=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-tent-and-the-pittsburgh-campus-challenge&#34;&gt;The tent and the Pittsburgh Campus Challenge&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I signed up for the Pittsburgh Campus Challenge through Carnegie Mellon University, there was advertised to be &amp;ldquo;gourmet food, private massages, and more&amp;rdquo; in the tent. The reality was actually quite different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby said it was a good thing she made it to the tent before too late (she had gone back to nap in the car after seeing me off), because by 10 AM, half marathoners had eaten much of the food already, and she had remembered to save some for me for later! There was still food left, but much of the good stuff was gone. And it wasn&amp;rsquo;t really &amp;ldquo;gourmet&amp;rdquo;. There was dry fried chicken, rolls, pasta left, as far as I could tell, other than the pancakes Abby had saved from earlier, and  a Panera Bread sandwiches she also saved for me.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/abby.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/tent-food.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Tent food&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There was a signup sheet for massage by Massage Envy, however, and a very long wait, as I got my massage after one hour and twenty minutes, which was actually OK because I was so sore I simply needed to be left alone for a while to just eat and eat and rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;cmu-won&#34;&gt;CMU won!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I came into the tent, there was confusion because I didn&amp;rsquo;t have a sticker on my bib indicating that I had access to the tent. Apparently I was supposed to have gotten a sticker at some point, but I don&amp;rsquo;t remember getting instructions about that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When they learned I was with CMU, however, they gave me the prize for CMU winning the Pittsburgh Campus Challenge, to hand over to Pattye at CMU. We beat Pitt!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/pittsburgh-campus-challenge.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Pittsburgh Campus Challenge prize&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;feet&#34;&gt;Feet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My feet were terribly sore. I got one blood-filled blister:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/blister.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Blister on right foot&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But otherwise, the damage was not as bad as I had thought. During the marathon, I had wondered sometimes about all the stickiness I felt on my feet, but it was not blood after all; it was a mixture of energy gel, Gatorade, orange juice, and whatever else was left on the road that got onto my feet:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/feet.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I had two chafing spots from the straps, but they were not serious. All in all, my feet were in much condition after wearing the Luna Sandals than they were ten years ago after wearing standard socks and running shoes. The drawback is that my feet were horribly sore, although after one night of rest, the foot soreness is actually all gone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;one-day-later&#34;&gt;One day later&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I do have a different problem: one day later, numbness in my left foot remains, because I had adjusted my strap for my left foot too tightly, out of fear of it coming off. &lt;em&gt;Overly tight strap was a big mistake.&lt;/em&gt; I did make an adjustment at some point during the race, but I could at least have loosened the strap earlier when I felt discomfort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In all my previous runs, my left foot has never fallen out. I hope the numbness goes away in another day.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/feet-day-after.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;My feet the day after&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;legs&#34;&gt;Legs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My legs were utterly trashed, as might be expected given how I had tortured them for so long. At first, I thought it was just my quads and hamstrings, but once I pulled off the calf sleeves, I realized that my calves were trashed too, but had &lt;em&gt;completely&lt;/em&gt; avoided cramping because of the compression. I count this as a total success for the calf sleeves, because in the marathon ten years ago, my calves were seizing up in the second half, not just my quads. &lt;em&gt;I will always wear calf sleeves in the future in long runs or hikes&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Em of Massage Envy was very helpful in getting me able to sort of walk, so that I could go with Abby back over to the North Shore to our car (I had to walk across the bridge, then waited as she brought the car over).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-marathon-2013/massage-envy.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Massage Envy&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Overall, I think wearing the Luna Sandals was the correct decision, despite the drawbacks. I did &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; have toe jamming, toe blistering, toe cramping that I believe I would have had in other footwear. I did not have ankle soreness of any kind. Or shin splints. I did not have any right knee pain at all, just left (and almost certainly because of my fall on Thursday). I could have used more cushioning though. But my order of the thicker Luna Sandals (the new Mono model) has not yet shipped.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;thanks&#34;&gt;Thanks!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a lot to be thankful for even though in some sense this marathon was truly a debacle for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am thankful that this race returned to Pittsburgh after suspension in 2004-2008, as Dick&amp;rsquo;s Sporting Goods rose up to be the title sponsor. I am amazed by how large and popular the Pittsburgh Marathon has become since I last ran it ten years ago. I think it&amp;rsquo;s great that the city has this annual celebration of its neighborhoods and of the running community. The Pittsburgh Marathon is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; just about the marathon, but about just regular fitness running, free workshops on health and exercise, and celebrating a sport that brings everyone together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am thankful to Pattye Stragar for spreading word of the Pittsburgh Campus Challenge through the CMU fitness mailing list.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am thankful to Steel City Road Runners for their well-organized Saturday long runs that got me out during the cold months when I otherwise might have chosen to just sleep in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am thankful to my friends who encouraged me as I progressed through my training and in my discouraging days before the marathon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am thankful to Annie and Deb and Mark for being spectators I saw and knew who gave me additional motivation to keep going.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am thankful to all the spectators and volunteers I don&amp;rsquo;t know who offered cheers, water, orange slices, music, and everything else that reminded me that humanity is caring and helpful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And of course, I am particularly thankful to my wife Abby, who has been so patient these months as I have pursued this marathon thing that she thinks is crazy (OK, I know it is crazy), and helped me every single day. Abby, this whole experience has truly deepened my appreciation of you, and I will never forget what we went through together to make this birthday present happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;did-i-achieve-my-goals&#34;&gt;Did I achieve my goals?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s go back to &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/30/why-and-how-i-am-going-to-run-the-2013-pittsburgh-marathon/&#34;&gt;my blog post from three months ago where I stated my goals for the marathon&lt;/a&gt;. What did I actually achieve?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;maintain a smart pace: failed (totally)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;finish strong: succeeded (insofar as I pushed as hard as I could for the last three miles approximately)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;avoid leg muscle cramping: failed miserably with the quads, succeeded with the calves&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;avoid foot blistering: failed (got one bad blister)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;conquer the hills: neutral (didn&amp;rsquo;t feel particularly bad at hills as such)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it would seem that I basically failed, as far as the marathon itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I think I succeeded, in a larger context:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t expect to be wearing huaraches for a marathon, but I did wear Luna Sandals! I proved to myself it could be done.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As a side effect of marathon training, I got myself into much better shape than I have been in for the past half decade, and did my first half marathon in nine years, and set up exercise habits I hope to make permanent independent of any future marathoning.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Abby&amp;rsquo;s help as I took on the task of training made a profound impression on me.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The outpouring of support from friends was a welcome surprise to me, because in my last Pittsburgh Marathon, I mostly went about it alone, telling only a few people about it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-did-i-fail-so-miserably&#34;&gt;Why did I fail so miserably?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe I failed mostly because I didn&amp;rsquo;t have the proper training. I started too late, I didn&amp;rsquo;t have enough time to more gradually absorb increased training volume, I could have used an extra month or two of more long runs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also did not adapt properly to setbacks that should have led me to change my goals drastically. There was a downward spiral in terms of injury, fatigue, and loss of calm reason.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-next&#34;&gt;What next?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;done-with-the-marathon&#34;&gt;Done with the marathon&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I told Abby that this is it: no more racing marathons again, ever. I mean it. I&amp;rsquo;m facing the reality that this is not the right event for me. I believe I could do a good marathon, but what it would take is not worth the effort. The sacrifices that I made, and Abby made, were considerable. There are other things we could be doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I look forward to our returning to &amp;ldquo;normal&amp;rdquo; life as I recover.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;running&#34;&gt;Running&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, I totally enjoyed getting back into year-round running. I will never go into winter hibernation again. I still have to figure out ideal footwear for the coldest and snow/ice/water-ridden conditions for next winter, of course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;half-marathons&#34;&gt;Half marathons&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Doing Just A Short Run again gave me confidence that I can &amp;ldquo;master&amp;rdquo; the half marathon distance. I would like to continue doing half marathons. I have decided to do the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mtchalfmarathon.com/&#34;&gt;Montour Trail Half Marathon&lt;/a&gt; in September. This means I will have to skip the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~kalp/PGR/&#34;&gt;CMU Pretty Good Race&lt;/a&gt;, which is always held the Friday before this Saturday race, but it&amp;rsquo;s time for me to get back into doing half marathon and 10K and 5K (and even mile) races, distances that I can actually work on being able to run well without wrecking myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heck, I might even run the Pittsburgh Half Marathon a year from now! (Although I don&amp;rsquo;t actually want to think about that for a while.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In isolation, the 2013 Pittsburgh Marathon may be considered to be a total debacle for me, the worst race I&amp;rsquo;ve finished out of the 135 races I&amp;rsquo;ve showed up for in my life. But I&amp;rsquo;m glad I went through the process of training for it, and I&amp;rsquo;m grateful for it as a vehicle of self-discovery: I faced some unpleasant truths about various poor decisions I made. And I&amp;rsquo;m grateful for the opportunity to share my journey with friends and family.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.guardian.co.uk/sport/blog/2012/jun/22/50-olympic-stunning-moments-emil-zatopek&#34;&gt;Emil Zatopek&lt;/a&gt; said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
If you want to run, run a mile. If you want to experience a different life, run a marathon.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-05-09&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-05-09)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second day after the marathon, I was still in physical and emotional pain, and wrote a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/05/07/why-i-feel-sad-when-people-congratulate-me-for-finishing-the-pittsburgh-marathon/&#34;&gt;little rant expressing my disappointment&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third day, I was able to walk normally and was emotionally recovering as well and was embarrassed by my rant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fourth day, I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/05/09/back-to-what-running-is-really-about-for-me/&#34;&gt;went out for a short run and reflected on what running is really about for me&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-12-22&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-12-22)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I just wanted to point out a much healthier attitude and experience of a marathon gone badly: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.letsrun.com/news/2013/11/time-life/&#34;&gt;this is a really beautiful article&lt;/a&gt; that every disappointed racer should read.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recognize that I trapped myself during March and April with increasingly unbalanced expectations of my marathon, and lost all calmness and perspective. I still don&amp;rsquo;t know whether I will run a marathon again, but if I do, I vow to do it with a clear mind and body.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On finally upgrading my Samsung Galaxy S II phone to Jelly Bean</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/04/08/on-finally-upgrading-my-samsung-galaxy-s-ii-phone-to-jelly-bean/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Apr 2013 20:11:58 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/04/08/on-finally-upgrading-my-samsung-galaxy-s-ii-phone-to-jelly-bean/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A year ago, I got my first smartphone, a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/22/paradox-i-will-observe-the-national-day-of-unplugging-but-just-bought-my-first-smartphone-this-week/&#34;&gt;Samsung Galaxy SII through T-Mobile&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point I upgraded it to &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Android_version_history&#34;&gt;Ice Cream Sandwich&lt;/a&gt;. Unfortunately, that introduced a &lt;em&gt;terrible&lt;/em&gt; limitation for my phone: I found that I could not disable the shutter-clicking sound effect when capturing video!! I looked online and found that it was not possible without rooting. This made me truly angry because it meant that my phone was &lt;em&gt;unusable&lt;/em&gt; for capturing video. Friends told me I should &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Android_rooting&#34;&gt;root&lt;/a&gt; the phone already, rather than submit to Samsung&amp;rsquo;s draconian disabling of the preference to turn off the shutter sound.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jelly Bean just finally arrived for my phone. I installed it, and the problem went away. Whew.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A totally exhausting Rachel Carson Trail Challenge goal training hike (18.1 miles</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/06/03/a-totally-exhausting-rachel-carson-trail-challenge-goal-training-hike/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Jun 2012 23:42:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/06/03/a-totally-exhausting-rachel-carson-trail-challenge-goal-training-hike/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In April, I reported on a nice &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/04/29/a-pretty-rachel-carson-trail-challenge-goal-training-hike/&#34;&gt;8.9 mile hike on the Rachel Carson Trail&lt;/a&gt; I did with John, the second of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rachelcarsontrails.org/rct/challenge/rctc12/goaltraining&#34;&gt;eight goal training hikes for the Rachel Carson Trail Challenge&lt;/a&gt;. I looked forward to doing a really long hike on the Rachel Carson Trail with John as my last hike on this trail for the year, and today was the one opportunity I had (during a very busy spring and summer weekend schedule) to get it in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The description of today&amp;rsquo;s hike, the seventh of eight:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sunday, June 3, 2012&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Leader: Craig Fowler 412-491-6643&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;18.1 miles&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Elevation change: 6915 ft.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;On this hike we&amp;rsquo;ll cover the second half of this year&amp;rsquo;s Challenge course. Starting in Springdale near the Springdale Veterans Association Hall, we&amp;rsquo;ll hike through Springdale then hit Log Cabin hill, Lefever Hill, and Rich Hill. Then we&amp;rsquo;ll stick the landing in North Park. Meet at the Harmar Shelter in North Park. Directions: Take I279 north to the McKnight Road exit and travel 6.4 miles north. Take the North Park/Ingomar Rd. exit east and turn right at the third traffic light onto Babcock Blvd., then take the next left onto Hemlock Drive, then left again into the swimming pool lot. Follow the perimeter drive all the way back and bear right. The Harmar Shelter is ahead on the left, behind the guardrail.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that a lot of things went wrong during this hike, but we survived!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;volunteering&#34;&gt;Volunteering&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier in the season, there had been a call for volunteers to lead or assist in the goal training hikes. I felt like giving back to the Rachel Carson Trail community, but didn&amp;rsquo;t feel ready yet to actually lead a hike. Instead, I accepted the role of helping (with John) by assisting in one of the longer ones, serving as trail sweeps in the back, aiding Miranda.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;footwear&#34;&gt;Footwear&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also wanted to do a very long hike as a test of whether my feet could hold up in Vibram FiveFingers KSO Trek shoes, on tough terrain as well as a very long distance. I always had problems (toe jamming, blistering, knee and ankle pain) wearing trail running shoes in the past hiking the Rachel Carson Trail in previous years when going about 20 miles or longer. In April&amp;rsquo;s Rachel Carson Trail hike, my feet got sore but otherwise I felt great. But I didn&amp;rsquo;t know how things would scale up to a much longer distance. So this was an opportunity to test my limits in FiveFingers shoes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;camera&#34;&gt;Camera&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/22/paradox-i-will-observe-the-national-day-of-unplugging-but-just-bought-my-first-smartphone-this-week/&#34;&gt;I have a smartphone, finally&lt;/a&gt;, I no longer have to lug around the bulky digital camera that I&amp;rsquo;ve had to use for the past couple of years for taking photos. So I decided to bring just the phone for this hike. On the April hike, my new phone&amp;rsquo;s camera had been dead for days (I ended up getting a replacement phone, whew!), so I had used John&amp;rsquo;s camera.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;meeting-up-at-north-park&#34;&gt;Meeting up at North Park&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;John and I had a weird carpooling arrangement to get to North Park. Only John and I were hiking, but Abby needed to be up in the vicinity to visit her parents and pick up her car that they had, so we all went together. Abby dropped us off, the idea being that her parents were going to stop by North Park later in the morning to give her car back so that she could drive back home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Parked at Harmar Shelter:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2012-06-03/2012-06-03_08.11.20.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;hike&#34;&gt;Hike&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It took quite a while to ride back in a carpool to Springdale for the start. That just made us think of how long it would take to hike back to North Park!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here I am, ready to start hiking:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2012-06-03/2012-06-03_08.52.05.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Denser and higher greenery in June than a month ago:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2012-06-03/2012-06-03_09.00.53.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Years ago, when I did the Rachel Carson Trail Challenge, the trail in Springdale went through a section of land called the &amp;ldquo;roller coaster&amp;rdquo;. Sadly, in recent years, because of problems landowners had with misbehaving hikers, they revoked the permission they had given for so long to go through their land. This force some rerouting of the trail through the streets of Springdale. Ironically, the rerouting resulted in the trail finally actually passing by the &lt;a href=&#34;http://rachel_carson_homestead.myupsite.com/&#34;&gt;Rachel Carson Homestead&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2012-06-03/2012-06-03_09.15.03.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Some dirt road hiking:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2012-06-03/2012-06-03_09.22.15.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A critter!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2012-06-03/2012-06-03_09.26.37.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Butterfly:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2012-06-03/2012-06-03_09.32.10.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Inevitable road walking, part of the whole Rachel Carson Trail experience:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2012-06-03/2012-06-03_10.14.12.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Up:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2012-06-03/2012-06-03_10.20.34.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Nice view into the distance:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2012-06-03/2012-06-03_10.23.54.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2012-06-03/2012-06-03_10.27.49.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2012-06-03/2012-06-03_10.32.43.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Now descending toward the road:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2012-06-03/2012-06-03_10.35.29.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Looking back toward John:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2012-06-03/2012-06-03_10.37.49.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In the woods:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2012-06-03/2012-06-03_10.45.23.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the &amp;ldquo;Rachel Carson Trail&amp;rdquo; signs, yellow on brown:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2012-06-03/2012-06-03_10.52.30.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Back to road:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2012-06-03/2012-06-03_11.08.39.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Dirt road:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2012-06-03/2012-06-03_11.17.59.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Big descent coming up; you can see how there will be a valley:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2012-06-03/2012-06-03_11.19.29.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2012-06-03/2012-06-03_11.23.27.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The thing to remember is that after getting to the bottom, the trail does &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; go back up. It actually makes a left.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2012-06-03/2012-06-03_11.23.33.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2012-06-03/2012-06-03_11.26.37.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In the woods again:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2012-06-03/2012-06-03_11.43.49.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2012-06-03/2012-06-03_11.58.15.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Stream crossing:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2012-06-03/2012-06-03_12.30.28.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2012-06-03/2012-06-03_12.31.41.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is very convenient that the trail passes through Emmerling Park, because you can get water from the fountain and use the restrooms here before going on.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2012-06-03/2012-06-03_12.39.41.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2012-06-03/2012-06-03_12.48.05.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;An unpleasant section of high-speed road with no sidewalk:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2012-06-03/2012-06-03_13.15.13.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2012-06-03/2012-06-03_13.22.33.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2012-06-03/2012-06-03_13.28.44.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Animals!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2012-06-03/2012-06-03_13.34.43.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2012-06-03/2012-06-03_14.13.51.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2012-06-03/2012-06-03_14.16.44.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2012-06-03/2012-06-03_14.22.55.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2012-06-03/2012-06-03_14.28.48.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2012-06-03/2012-06-03_14.28.52.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2012-06-03/2012-06-03_14.33.12.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2012-06-03/2012-06-03_14.36.40.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2012-06-03/2012-06-03_14.43.42.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2012-06-03/2012-06-03_14.58.16.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Looking like it might rain:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2012-06-03/2012-06-03_15.14.01.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-2012-06-03/2012-06-03_15.18.08.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;oops&#34;&gt;Oops&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OK, at this point, six and a half hours into a very long hike, my phone&amp;rsquo;s battery ran out!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was a problem because John and I had gotten separated from anyone else for some time already, and I worried about not being able to communicate with the hike leaders, whose responsibility it was to make sure everyone was accounted for at the end of the hike. Craig had my phone number, but I couldn&amp;rsquo;t call him and he couldn&amp;rsquo;t call me. Nor could I call Abby to let her know when John and I were done and heading home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;finishing-the-hike&#34;&gt;Finishing the hike&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We made it to North Park, but then &lt;em&gt;got lost&lt;/em&gt; in the trails. I had route maps on my phone, but my phone was dead. &lt;em&gt;Luckily&lt;/em&gt;, I had brought some paper printouts of some road maps of North Park (but no trail maps!!). As long as we got out of the woods and onto the roads, I was sure we would find the shelter and my car and be OK. At worst, there would be people around in North Park we could ask for more detailed directions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then it began to rain. Really hard. My paper maps were getting blurry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We eventually got to a road, and asked random people where the Harmar Shelter was, but they didn&amp;rsquo;t know. After some wandering around, we finally figured out where we were on the printed maps I had (the rain had stopped), and backtracked toward the shelter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then all of a sudden, John pointed at a car and said, &amp;ldquo;That car looks a lot like yours!&amp;rdquo; I replied that a lot of cars looked like mine, and ignored him. But then he noticed some distinguishing features and said it looked like it actually was mine. We were lucky, because it turned out the car was mine!! (Later I would learn from Abby that she had moved the car from where it had been parked in front of the shelter, to some random place further away, and texted me about the move, but of course, since I had not been checking my phone during the hike, and it died, I had no idea.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, we made a note of where the car was before heading to the shelter. We saw no trace of Craig or Miranda. Oh great. Since Abby had moved the car, Craig must have left without waiting for us to return because he saw our car gone and assumed we had returned faster and had already gone home! (Later it would turn out that he had texted me as well as left voice mail asking me where I was and then after not getting a reply said he was leaving because he assumed we had finished.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The shelter had a big, noisy party going on. We asked some random drunk guy if we could borrow his cell phone to make a call. He was kind enough to lend us the phone, and I called Craig (I was so fortunate that I had written in pen Craig&amp;rsquo;s number on one of the pieces of paper I had on me during the hike), and cleared up the confusion over whether we had finished or gone home. Then I called Abby and let her know John and I were OK, and drove us home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;after&#34;&gt;After&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was very happy to have made it home, and ate a ton of food. I noticed that my toes were numb, from all the hiking and the cold of stream crossing and rain. Also, my ankles were very stiff. The soles of my feet were quite sore. But I had no other leg soreness. So the experiment with footwear partially succeeded. (The numb toes were OK again after a couple of hours.) But still, I cannot imagine hiking more than 20 miles comfortably with the Vibram FiveFingers KSO Trek. My feet were simply very sore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;lessons-learned&#34;&gt;Lessons learned&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I learned many lessons during this exhausting hike:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Trail sweep can be a lonely, arduous task. I&amp;rsquo;m used to hiking with a pack of people, or at least having a pack in sight. Not being the fastest hikers on this hike, being the sweep meant actually being left behind!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I am immediately buying a phone charger for my car. It would have saved a lot of trouble if I had been able to charge my phone upon reaching it, in order to access missed text messages and voice mail.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I am &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; going to completely rely on the phone again for directions or maps. I will always have backup paper printouts of all important information, and in fact, put them in plastic bags in case of rain.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I will turn off automatic flash in order to save the phone battery when taking photos. Also, turn off unnecessary apps, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The FiveFingers shoes didn&amp;rsquo;t work too badly, but for a truly long distance are not cushioned enough.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In the final hours, John and I simply were no longer enjoying the hike, but just wanted to finish. We don&amp;rsquo;t really want to do a hike this long or grueling again. We did about 20 miles today (extra distance beyond 18.1 because of getting lost in various places). &lt;em&gt;Never again&lt;/em&gt; do I want to hike this long on the Rachel Carson Trail. In 2005, 2006, and 2007, I did the full 34-mile Challenge just to prove I could, not because I actually enjoyed it as such. I don&amp;rsquo;t need to kill myself any more. I enjoy doing long, varied, meditative hikes, but there is a limit to how much I actually enjoy. 8 or 9 miles, as in the hike a month ago, is probably optimal for me.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I knew that this Rachel Carson Trail hike was going to be tough, but it got a lot tougher than I expected. I learned a lot as a result of the experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to Craig for checking up on us and leading the hike and Miranda for being with us on the sweep during the beginning, and thanks to Abby for taking us to the hike!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A pretty Rachel Carson Trail Challenge goal training hike (8.9 miles)</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/04/29/a-pretty-rachel-carson-trail-challenge-goal-training-hike/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Apr 2012 23:22:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/04/29/a-pretty-rachel-carson-trail-challenge-goal-training-hike/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Every spring, I like to do one or two of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rachelcarsontrails.org/rct/challenge/rctc12/goaltraining&#34;&gt;Rachel Carson Trail Challenge goal training hikes&lt;/a&gt; for fun even though I no longer do the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rachelcarsontrails.org/rct/challenge/&#34;&gt;Rachel Carson Trail Challenge&lt;/a&gt; because three times was enough for me. Since this year&amp;rsquo;s Challenge proceeds east to west, all of the goal training hikes this year also go east to west.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The description of today&amp;rsquo;s hike, the second of eight that increase in length till the longest one in June:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sunday, April 29, 2012&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Leader: Brian Droz 412-848-4810&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;8.9 miles&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Elevation change: 4925 ft.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;On this hike we start at the Bull Creek Road checkpoint location in Tarentum and quickly encounter a steep uphill climb followed by even steeper ups and downs - including Crawford Run hill and Murray Hill. We pass through Agan Park and end in Springdale. Meet at the Springdale Veterans Association Hall parking lot in Springdale. Directions: Take Route 28 to Exit #11 (Harmarville). After exiting onto Route 910 head towards Harmarville, turn left at the second traffic light onto Freeport Road and travel about 4 miles through 9 more traffic lights. The Springdale Veterans Association Hall entrance will be on your left just past the last light. Park on the far side of the lot.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;meeting-up&#34;&gt;Meeting up&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;John and I drove up to the meeting place in Springdale. It was a cold morning!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m wearing my Vibram FiveFingers KSO Trek shoes as I have been doing for some time now for all my hiking.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-challenge-goal-training-2/franklin-cold.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin ready to hike&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;(Note: since Abby was elsewhere this morning using our camera, and my brand new smartphone&amp;rsquo;s camera had died and I was waiting for a replacement phone, John and I used his camera to take photos during the hike.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note the tower that will serve as the landmark when hiking back here:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-challenge-goal-training-2/landmark.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;hike&#34;&gt;Hike&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then we carpooled to the Bull Creek Road checkpoint in Tarentum further north and east.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The start of the hike from this checkpoint is by Route 28:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-challenge-goal-training-2/bull-creek-start.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I let John go ahead so that I could stay back and take photos without holding up anyone behind me:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-challenge-goal-training-2/john-start.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Now John has his camera back and took a photo of me going up:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-challenge-goal-training-2/franklin-going-up.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Closeup of some garlic mustard:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-challenge-goal-training-2/garlic-mustard-flowering.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Finally in the woods:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-challenge-goal-training-2/in-the-woods.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A horse!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-challenge-goal-training-2/horse.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A phone tower; these things prove to be useful landmarks:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-challenge-goal-training-2/phone-tower.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A descent along a power line:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-challenge-goal-training-2/descent.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s the season for May apples:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-challenge-goal-training-2/may-apple.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Going down and up, which is what the Rachel Carson Trail in this section is about:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-challenge-goal-training-2/go-down-go-up.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The Allegheny River is visible:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-challenge-goal-training-2/view-of-allegeny-river.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-challenge-goal-training-2/allegheny-river.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Emerging onto a road section of the this urban trail:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-challenge-goal-training-2/emerging-to-road.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Stream crossing:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-challenge-goal-training-2/stream-crossing.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-challenge-goal-training-2/rachel-carson-trail-sign.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Looking back after finishing my very steep descent:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-challenge-goal-training-2/very-steep-descent.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Trillium:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-challenge-goal-training-2/trillium.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Ah, the power line experience:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-challenge-goal-training-2/following-power-lines.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s two hours since we started hiking, and getting warmer, so my shell and hat and gloves are off. I&amp;rsquo;m wearing my &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rachelcarsontrails.org/rct/challenge/rctc06&#34;&gt;2006 Rachel Carson Trail Challenge&lt;/a&gt; T-shirt:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-challenge-goal-training-2/franklin-in-rachel-carson-trail-challenge-2006-shirt.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Down and up:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-challenge-goal-training-2/big-down-and-up.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Sometimes I get things stuck between my big toe and my second toe:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-challenge-goal-training-2/stuck-between-toes-of-kso-trek.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the less pleasant aspects of the Rachel Carson Trail is the road sections, where there is no sidewalk and the speed limit is 40 mph or higher!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-challenge-goal-training-2/scary-road-walking.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Now we&amp;rsquo;re really by the Allegheny River:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-challenge-goal-training-2/allegheny-river-1.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-challenge-goal-training-2/allegheny-river-2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Red flowers (sorry, I don&amp;rsquo;t know much about flowers and do not know what they are):&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-challenge-goal-training-2/flower.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The home stretch! See the tower that I mentioned as a landmark before the hike?&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-challenge-goal-training-2/home-stretch.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Back to the landmark:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/rachel-carson-trail-challenge-goal-training-2/back-to-landmark.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The 8.9 hike took about 3:20.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed doing my first Rachel Carson Trail hike of the year. Earlier in the year is better because the hikes are shorter and the weather is cooler.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to Brian Droz for leading this hike!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Two weeks after getting my first smartphone</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/04/03/two-weeks-after-getting-my-first-smartphone/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Apr 2012 17:53:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/04/03/two-weeks-after-getting-my-first-smartphone/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I got my first smartphone in my life &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/22/paradox-i-will-observe-the-national-day-of-unplugging-but-just-bought-my-first-smartphone-this-week/&#34;&gt;just two weeks ago&lt;/a&gt;, a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Samsung_Galaxy_S_II&#34;&gt;Samsung Galaxy S II&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;ve been too busy to actually sit down and read the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.samsung.com/us/support/owners/product/SGH-T989ZKBTMB&#34;&gt;279-page manual&lt;/a&gt;, but here are some observations on how I&amp;rsquo;ve used the smartphone so far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;i-am-already-plugged-in-through-other-devices&#34;&gt;I am already plugged in through other devices&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, in my everyday life I tend to be near a computer and don&amp;rsquo;t use my smartphone:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At work, I use my work computer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When I go to scheduled talks or meetings, I bring my laptop or iPad, so that I can take notes and look stuff up.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At home, I have my laptop and iPad.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My preference is for the larger display and keyboard when possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;wifi-in-public-places&#34;&gt;WiFi in public places&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have found myself looking for WiFi in public places in order to check email and the like when otherwise idle (I try to avoid needlessly using my data plan). I suppose that in the past, I would have just sat around waiting, or just left instead of spending more time somewhere unnecessarily. Some examples:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At the public library, my usual pattern is to just return stuff, check stuff out, and leave. I have caught myself hanging around just to check my email before leaving. Arguably there is no point in this behavior.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;While Abby and I were looking for stuff in a store, I quickly got bored of waiting for her and found it actually productive to connect to free WiFi and read email and blog and Twitter feeds; in the past, I would have just sat down somewhere and closed my eyes or something.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;During the long intermission at a concert I went to alone, not knowing anyone there, I spent time online rather than just sitting around. (Arguably I could have spent some time socializing with strangers, but I have tended not to do that.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;other-uses-in-public-in-the-past-two-weeks&#34;&gt;Other uses in public in the past two weeks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s handy having a decent camera on me at all times. I have used it in a couple of situations in which in the past I would have had to consciously bring a bulky camera along (which I don&amp;rsquo;t like to do):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Taking a photo after a concert.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Taking a photo of some notes written on a board.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Taking a photo of a flyer posted up.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Taking a photo of two dogs at play at the office.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Capturing some video during a dance party.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-failed-experiment-at-the-gym&#34;&gt;A failed experiment at the gym&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not one who has ever plugged into an iPod while exercising. However, I did an experiment today, hoping to watch a lecture video while at the gym. This failed miserably. Any vigorous movement (on a rowing machine, on a treadmill) resulted in my fear that the phone would fall, and definitely the headset with wires was very clumsy: the wires flapping around, and the short length of the wires.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suppose using a Bluetooth headset would fix a couple of these problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the real problem is that I supposedly watched the whole lecture, but I don&amp;rsquo;t actually remember much of it!! Multitasking in certain contexts doesn&amp;rsquo;t work for me. The thing is that yesterday I was watching lecture videos while at home, and that worked, but the situation was very different: I was doing strength training, I was using a large display on my computer, and I was alone, with no distracting noises or other people around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;on-the-road&#34;&gt;On the road&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I haven&amp;rsquo;t used the phone out on the road for navigation or the like yet. The next time we do some travel, we&amp;rsquo;ll see how useful the phone becomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;i-was-that-annoying-person-briefly&#34;&gt;I was that &lt;em&gt;annoying person&lt;/em&gt; (briefly)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I caught myself being the annoying person distracted in public walking down the street while fumbling with my phone and almost walking into someone. I did that twice, last week. I will not do that again. There was no reason whatsoever for me to be even plugged in during those moments. And if there are reasons, I could easily stop walking and stand somewhere out of the way to do my business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The good news is that at the two parties I&amp;rsquo;ve been to in the past two weeks, I was not the annoying person who pulled out a phone to do stuff. I will admit that during a bathroom break or two I did pull out the phone, but at least that was very brief and in private. In principle, I should avoid feeling bored at parties: the whole point of them, after all, is to bring people together, and so I should be engaging with people who are at the party, rather than looking at my Twitter feed or something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not a whole lot has changed since I got my first smartphone, in part because I haven&amp;rsquo;t learned all the features yet or gotten serious about apps for the phone. I&amp;rsquo;ll continue being aware of how I use it and report on anything interesting that happens.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What I did immediately after the National Day of Unplugging</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/03/24/what-i-did-immediately-after-the-national-day-of-unplugging/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Mar 2012 19:40:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/03/24/what-i-did-immediately-after-the-national-day-of-unplugging/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/22/paradox-i-will-observe-the-national-day-of-unplugging-but-just-bought-my-first-smartphone-this-week/&#34;&gt;The past 24 hours&lt;/a&gt;, I observed the &lt;a href=&#34;http://nationaldayofunplugging.org/&#34;&gt;National Day of Unplugging&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not a report on what I learned during that experience. I will be working on that report, which will probably be spread out over multiple posts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a report of what I did, &amp;ldquo;plugged in&amp;rdquo;, right after the event ended.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-i-immediately-did-after-finishing-the-national-day-of-unplugging&#34;&gt;What I immediately did after finishing the National Day of Unplugging&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Made a phone call to Abby, who has been in North Carolina since yesterday.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Turned on my home computer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Announced on Facebook and Twitter that I was back from unplugging! (Funny that this is the first thing I did online.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Checked my emails: I have around 30 to deal with. That&amp;rsquo;s not bad, but I know that usually, I receive the least email on Saturdays.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Started to &amp;ldquo;catch up&amp;rdquo; on my RSS feeds, Facebook, Twitter, Google+.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;emails-i-missed&#34;&gt;Emails I missed&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Notification about a Meetup event for tomorrow morning. If I had known about it earlier, I might have planned today differently. It is &amp;ldquo;too late&amp;rdquo; now to change tomorrow&amp;rsquo;s plans, so I will not be attending that event. (There is a different Meetup event I&amp;rsquo;m going to in the afternoon.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Notification about multiple Meetup events further in the future I may be interested in attending; need to look at the details and add to my online calendar if I decide to go.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Party invitation on Facebook. &lt;strong&gt;This is why I can&amp;rsquo;t quit Facebook; people actually use it.&lt;/strong&gt; Need to look at my online calendar and discuss with Abby.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Continuing old and new email threads involving various friends; I need to catch up and participate.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Notifications about new comments in my blog&amp;rsquo;s threads and other people&amp;rsquo;s blogs&amp;rsquo; threads where I&amp;rsquo;d indicated I want to be notified; sometimes this is useful, but other times less so. I will respond promptly to the comment on my old blog post.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Never-ending emails about new bills and statements I need to inspect and deal with.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Notifications about a bunch of new people following me on Twitter. I&amp;rsquo;ve long since given up on looking up every single new follower (or unfollower). I do like to make note of Pittsburgh locals I may have met in person or should meet, however.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Various mailing lists and other notifications.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;facebook&#34;&gt;Facebook&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OK, so it took about 15 minutes to catch up on browsing Facebook. That&amp;rsquo;s actually longer than I expected. Typically I check Facebook once or twice a day, and I&amp;rsquo;ve imagined that I don&amp;rsquo;t spend more than 5 minutes a day on Facebook, but apparently I&amp;rsquo;m wrong. Interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe I should spend less time on Facebook, because in reality, most of what I see there is not really necessary for me to see; it&amp;rsquo;s just idle people-watching for me, and the value of that is unclear to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;google&#34;&gt;Google+&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll be honest: I spend very little time on Google+. It&amp;rsquo;s just not where most people I know (as in &amp;ldquo;non-geeks&amp;rdquo;) are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;rss-feeds&#34;&gt;RSS feeds&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lots of articles to sort through. For fun, as I go through them to save those I cannot just skim in 15 seconds, but want to read in depth later, I am listing the topics of the saved ones here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Eclipse plugin for automatic Javadoc comments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Improvised Persian music for Nowruz&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Claims that Twitter Bootstrap is the way to go for web site design&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Privacy and how to pay for it&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Formal mathematical model of film success or failure&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to fix local issues: government or not?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The stresses on women in today&amp;rsquo;s world&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Plight of the introvert&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Calibre and freedom for ebooks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Guido and callbacks in Python&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A new blogging platform called Svbtle (sic)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Collection of historical chess footage on YouTube&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saturday is a slow day. On a weekday I typically find more new stuff to read.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;twitter&#34;&gt;Twitter&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I hit Twitter, to scroll down and see what I missed. I get tremendous value from Twitter, actually, that I cannot get from other sources. Perhaps that is the subject for a future blog post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-new-smartphone&#34;&gt;My new smartphone&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still need to get going on setting up and really using my new smartphone. This task may need to wait until Monday or Tuesday, since I have a lot of stuff I need to get done tonight and tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve talked about the first things I&amp;rsquo;ve done after getting back online. I&amp;rsquo;ll continue monitoring my online activities as they happen. One thing &amp;ldquo;unplugging&amp;rdquo; has done for me is give me (at least temporarily) a more conscious than usual awareness of what I do online. This will be a step toward streamlining my online activities.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Paradox? I will observe the National Day of Unplugging but just bought my first smartphone this week!</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/03/22/paradox-i-will-observe-the-national-day-of-unplugging-but-just-bought-my-first-smartphone-this-week/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Mar 2012 21:22:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/03/22/paradox-i-will-observe-the-national-day-of-unplugging-but-just-bought-my-first-smartphone-this-week/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/unplug.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;National Day of Unplugging 2012&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Just in February, I heard of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://nationaldayofunplugging.org/&#34;&gt;National Day of Unplugging&lt;/a&gt; scheduled for March 23-24, 2012, and immediately put it on my calendar, with the hope of observing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For some time, I&amp;rsquo;ve been &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/02/02/2-new-daily-habits-of-mine-in-a-distracting-world/&#34;&gt;struggling with being increasingly plugged into the Internet&lt;/a&gt;, and Clay Johnson has been advocating an &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.informationdiet.com/&#34;&gt;information diet&lt;/a&gt;, so I decided to do this day of unplugging as an experiment, to observe what my habits have been and learn something about myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ironically, on Wednesday I just bought my first smartphone, after years of never having used one. So what&amp;rsquo;s going on?!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/phones/samsung-galaxy-s-ii.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Brand new Samsung Galaxy S II&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-an-information-diet&#34;&gt;Why an information diet?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spend a lot of time in front of a computer, whether at work, at home on my main computer (a 2008 MacBook connected to an external display), or on my iPad 2. The first thing I have to say up front is that &lt;strong&gt;I am not a Luddite&lt;/strong&gt;. I actively use technology as a tool, as an extension of myself. As a software developer, I actively create tools to help people do their jobs. I use the Web as a source of knowledge, wisdom, and social connection. It is completely unimaginable what my life would be like if not for the past 15 years of Web access. In fact, my life was completely different in every possible way before the Web came along, and I was a completely different person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So my goal is not to &amp;ldquo;unplug&amp;rdquo; permanently, or &lt;em&gt;arbitrarily&lt;/em&gt; set limits on computer or Internet use. My goal is to take control of the resources in an active, deliberate way, rather than default to passively being overwhelmed both by distractions and by too much of a good thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The diet needs to extend to every aspect of being plugged in. For me, the main problem is too much useful information: given any topic I&amp;rsquo;m interested in, I could spend forever learning about it online, even if I need to focus my limited time and attention on fewer topics rather than many. For others, the social aspect may be the main problem. Even for me, an introvert, it is hard to keep up with the social networks I&amp;rsquo;m part of; I always have too many emails to deal with at length.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Michael Ellsberg just put up a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ellsberg.com/friendlessness&#34;&gt;heartfelt video&lt;/a&gt; in which he talks about the social aspect of overload; I recommend watching it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;observing-the-national-day-of-unplugging&#34;&gt;Observing the National Day of Unplugging&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the National Day of Unplugging, I will monitor in detail what I miss when I unplug, and what I gain when I unplug, and then report back on what I learned, what surprised me, and how I might change up my regular routines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have not already made plans that require being plugged in on Saturday, I suggest joining me in observing the &lt;a href=&#34;http://nationaldayofunplugging.org/&#34;&gt;National Day of Unplugging&lt;/a&gt; and sharing what you learned from it also!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-my-first-smartphone&#34;&gt;Why my first smartphone?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;old-phone-died&#34;&gt;Old phone died&lt;/h3&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/phones/motorola-razr-v3t.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Motorola Razr V3t with blank display&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The short story is that on Tuesday, the display of my five-year-old cell phone, a Motorola Razr V3t I bought in January 2007, went blank, and so it was time to finally upgrade my phone. I had been thinking for a year or two now of getting a smartphone, because the display had become flaky and battery life decreasing, but had not because&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I did not really &lt;em&gt;need&lt;/em&gt; a smartphone.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Smartphones are expensive.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data plans are expensive.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;why-a-smartphone-not-a-new-dumbphone&#34;&gt;Why a smartphone, not a new &amp;ldquo;dumbphone&amp;rdquo;?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing I missed about not having a smartphone was having a high-quality camera on me at all times. I believe a camera is a very useful tool in many situations, for photos and videos. I hardly ever used the terrible camera of my old cell phone. I also never put any apps on it, never listened to any music on it. My old cell phone was just for making phone calls; I never texted either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many other reasons a smartphone could be useful in my life (for example, during travel I could have used a smartphone in the past couple of years!), but instead of listing speculations, I&amp;rsquo;ll just see what happens and report on the benefits. Meanwhile, I realize that the potential for it becoming a distraction truly exists, because for five years since the iPhone came out, I see, on a daily basis, people being completely, &lt;em&gt;utterly&lt;/em&gt; distracted by their smartphones in a way that I hope I never will be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are much cheaper data plans now than in the past, so it finally seemed reasonable to get a smartphone now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s been two days since I bought my new phone, and I actually haven&amp;rsquo;t had any time yet to do much with it. All I&amp;rsquo;ve done is learn how to make a call and answer the phone, and connect it to WiFi and email.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have an interest in possibly getting into developing apps for mobile devices, and maybe actually owning a smartphone will encourage me to give it a shot!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;which-smartphone&#34;&gt;Which smartphone?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have an iPad 2 and use Macs, so you might think I would get an iPhone, but I didn&amp;rsquo;t. Why? First of all, I&amp;rsquo;m on T-Mobile, and there&amp;rsquo;s no iPhone support for T-Mobile. Second, developing for Android is more pleasant than developing for iOS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.samsung.com/global/microsite/galaxys2/html/&#34;&gt;Samsung Galaxy S II&lt;/a&gt;. Yes, it&amp;rsquo;s expensive, but given my policy of using devices for many years (my first car lasted me 14 years, and I&amp;rsquo;m still using a 2008 MacBook), I have found from experience that I last longer between upgrades if I get something that isn&amp;rsquo;t entry level. I don&amp;rsquo;t want to be buying a new smartphone for another five years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ironically, just after I bought this phone, I saw an article saying that &lt;a href=&#34;http://lifehacker.com/5895699/if-youre-in-the-market-for-an-android-phone-you-might-want-to-wait&#34;&gt;now is the time to wait for the Samsung Galaxy S III and the like&lt;/a&gt;. (I didn&amp;rsquo;t even bother to skim that article, after following the link to it, because the last thing I need is &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Buyer&#39;s_remorse&#34;&gt;buyer&amp;rsquo;s remorse&lt;/a&gt;.) But let&amp;rsquo;s face it, one could wait forever for everything. I needed a new phone now. And the iPad 3 just came out, but Abby and I have made much use of the iPad 2 during the time we&amp;rsquo;ve owned it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, I&amp;rsquo;ll keep note of advice such Henrik Edberg&amp;rsquo;s recent blog post about &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.positivityblog.com/index.php/2012/03/22/smartphone-attention/&#34;&gt;how not to let your smartphone take over your attention and life&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I look forward both to observing the National Day of Unplugging and also to exploring how my new smartphone can benefit my life. I don&amp;rsquo;t think it is necessarily paradoxical to embrace technology while also being careful and reflective about it, just being honest with ourselves and observing ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>