<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Johannes Brahms on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/johannes-brahms/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Johannes Brahms on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/johannes-brahms/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Discovering the beautiful keyboard playing of Robert Hill by accident on YouTube changed my life</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/08/21/discovering-the-beautiful-keyboard-playing-of-robert-hill-by-accident-on-youtube-changed-my-life/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2014 22:14:23 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/08/21/discovering-the-beautiful-keyboard-playing-of-robert-hill-by-accident-on-youtube-changed-my-life/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.mh-freiburg.de/typo3temp/_processed_/csm_prof.-dr.-robert-hill_c7981b16bc.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Robert Hill&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Recently, I completely accidentally discovered a fascinating musician, &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Hill_%28musician%29&#34;&gt;Robert Hill&lt;/a&gt;, on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/user/earlymus&#34;&gt;YouTube&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story is as you might expect: I heard a piece of music, and wanted to find some performance of it by somebody, anybody on YouTube as long as it had a decent user rating (yes, I find ratings actually useful when checking out unfamiliar music), and I happened to come across some random guy&amp;rsquo;s performance, and it was so fascinating that I looked at other uploads of his, subscribed to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/user/earlymus&#34;&gt;his YouTube channel&lt;/a&gt;, and looked him up on the Web to find out who he was!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s especially great that he regularly uploads new videos to his YouTube channel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So who is Robert Hill, and why do I like his performances so much that I&amp;rsquo;m recommending that you check them out?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-i-found-robert-hill&#34;&gt;How I found Robert Hill&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The short story is that I just heard someone playing, on piano, Johann Sebastian Bach&amp;rsquo;s Allemande from the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/French_Suites_%28Bach%29&#34;&gt;French Suite&lt;/a&gt; no. 4 in E-flat, BWV 815.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note that I actually have had very little interest in much of Bach&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Works_for_keyboard_by_J.S._Bach&#34;&gt;keyboard music&lt;/a&gt; and have almost completely ignored them for decades&lt;/em&gt;; there are only two exceptions: the Goldberg Variations and some of the Well-Tempered Clavier.  In particular, I have not listened to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/French_Suites_%28Bach%29&#34;&gt;French Suites&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/English_Suites_%28Bach%29&#34;&gt;English Suites&lt;/a&gt;, or &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Partitas_for_keyboard_%28Bach%29&#34;&gt;Partitas&lt;/a&gt; at all!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But because I just accidentally heard this Allemande played live, and liked it, I wanted to hear it again when I got home, and so I went to YouTube to find it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found a lot of performances online, of course, but I&amp;rsquo;m a sucker for the unusual, so I was particularly interested when I saw in the search results a link to some guy, Robert Hill, performing it on an unusual instrument I had never heard of in my life, a &amp;ldquo;lute-harpsichord&amp;rdquo;. And it got well over a hundred thumb-up ratings and only one thumb-down, so of course I was going to check it out!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I watched the video, and was &lt;em&gt;totally blown away&lt;/em&gt; by the beauty of the performance:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The instrument has a gorgeous sound.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Robert Hill played very expressively, with the full freedom and emotion that treasure.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Structurally, I could hear the different voices and phrases with total clarity because of how he plays.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This single performance made me think that I needed to give old Bach another shot and check out more of his keyboard music.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Listen for yourself (it&amp;rsquo;s less than two minutes long):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/woh8UHdjl1M&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;who-is-robert-hill&#34;&gt;Who is Robert Hill?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did a Web search on Robert Hill and found &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Hill_%28musician%29&#34;&gt;information about him&lt;/a&gt;. He is an American keyboard instrument performer (especially early keyboard instruments such as harpsichord, clavichord, lute-harpsichord, fortepiano) and musicologist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had to search hard to find an actual Web site of his own, and it&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://robert-hill.tripod.com/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. It basically looks like it hasn&amp;rsquo;t been updated since around 2001, which is also his last recording time period on his &lt;a href=&#34;http://robert-hill.tripod.com/id11.html&#34;&gt;discography&lt;/a&gt;. At some point he must have decided to just share his music through YouTube. He is a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mh-freiburg.de/lehrende/person/details/hill/&#34;&gt;music professor in Freiburg&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I just mentioned, my fascination with the performances of Robert Hill comes from his &lt;em&gt;expressiveness&lt;/em&gt;, which comes about from adjustments of tempo, rhetorical gestures, ornamentation, rhythmic sense. He plays a lot more expressively than many keyboard musicians do today, and I like that. I now believe that I was turned off by much of Bach&amp;rsquo;s keyboard music not because of Bach, but because of the relatively bland performances his music has received, especially from modern pianists. Bach was an emotional man living in an emotional age (the Baroque era of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Doctrine_of_the_affections&#34;&gt;affect&lt;/a&gt;), and I feel blessed that musicians like Robert Hill are taking this seriously. There are others, of course, besides him, but I think his performances have a particular edge to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;regular-harpsichord&#34;&gt;Regular harpsichord&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is an example of Robert Hill playing regular harpsichord.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;bach-s-allemande-from-the-partita-in-d-major-bwv-828&#34;&gt;Bach&amp;rsquo;s Allemande from the Partita in D major, BWV 828&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I discovered this beautiful, haunting work of music by Bach for the first time, by sheer accident, when browsing Hill&amp;rsquo;s YouTube channel (live performance from 1997):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/oEoqPSFklkE&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I cannot believe I went four decades without ever having heard this piece in my life. Now I can&amp;rsquo;t get it out of my head.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hill did some extreme things in this performance (tempo modifications and hesitations) that are not to my taste, but I applaud him for having the courage to play from the heart, because much of what he did spoke to mine! He lives dangerously. Maybe that&amp;rsquo;s why he only posts live recording clips to YouTube now rather than make CDs?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;fortepiano&#34;&gt;Fortepiano&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He also plays fortepiano, which is a fascinating instrument I love. I have mentioned my first experience with a fortepiano in college in a blog post earlier this year celebrating the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/03/08/happy-300th-birthday-carl-philipp-emanuel-bach/&#34;&gt;300th birthday of Johann Sebastian&amp;rsquo;s son Carl Philipp Emanuel&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;cpe-bach-s-fantasie-in-f-sharp-minor&#34;&gt;CPE Bach&amp;rsquo;s Fantasie in F-sharp minor&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heck, I had to check out Hill&amp;rsquo;s performance of my favorite CPE Bach keyboard work. In my earlier blog post, I had praised Andreas Staier&amp;rsquo;s performance I discovered in college, but now having heard Hill&amp;rsquo;s, I have another favorite (live from April 2014). This totally plays up Hill&amp;rsquo;s maximally emotive expressive style:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/LOT_nUPvE98&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;js-bach-well-tempered-clavier-selections&#34;&gt;JS Bach: Well-Tempered Clavier selections&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was fascinating to find Hill performing JS Bach on fortepiano; I had never heard anyone playing JS Bach on fortepiano before. I love that he experiments with different styles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The famous WTC I, Prelude in C major, in a fluid, beautiful Romantic-style (vs. Baroque-style) performance he just uploaded a couple of days ago:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/jiBQD0vV5qI&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A totally gorgeous Romantic-style interpretation of the slow Bach WTC I, Prelude in C# minor:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/9iGj4U7nqqY&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love how he makes full use of the expressive possibilities of the fortepiano (power and dynamics and sustain).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;beethoven-s-moonlight-sonata&#34;&gt;Beethoven&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Moonlight&amp;rdquo; sonata&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, he plays Beethoven too, on fortepiano.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that Beethoven did call it &amp;ldquo;sonata quasi fantasia&amp;rdquo; so it should be played freely &amp;ldquo;like a fantasy&amp;rdquo;, freely, and he does this. If you&amp;rsquo;ve only heard it played more &amp;ldquo;squarely&amp;rdquo;, check this out. In this case, I prefer a more subtle freedom than the exaggerated gestures Hill provides, because I feel he disrupts the rhythmic flow too much, so I consider his experiment not a full success, but still, I respect his willingness to go all out:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/6gpmZsqOzZs&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;pianoforte&#34;&gt;Pianoforte!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, of course Robert Hill plays the modern piano too. And I love what he does with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;brahms&#34;&gt;Brahms&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hill brings out the different voices very well, the counterpoint through the thick textures of Brahms. These are truly beautiful performances of some of &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/05/07/happy-birthday-johannes-brahms/&#34;&gt;my favorite piano music of all time, Brahms&amp;rsquo; intermezzi&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A passionate performance of Op. 117, No. 2 in B-flat minor:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/U_rlk4H-DQ0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And Op. 119, No. 1 in B minor (some favorite performances of which I discussed in &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/05/07/happy-birthday-johannes-brahms/&#34;&gt;my blog post last year&lt;/a&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/NOpe_KvXQzA&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is one of the most emotionally raw performances I have ever heard of this intermezzo. Hill makes the most of the suspensions, silences, dissonances, and clashing lines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Discovering the musical performances of Robert Hill on keyboard instruments has been one of the happy surprises of my life this year. Not only has he provided me listening pleasure, but also has sharpened my conception of what the music he plays is about and how to express it. He has forever changed my expectation from myself of how I should play music. I expect that from now on, I will never again hold back from &amp;ldquo;weird&amp;rdquo; interpretations that I feel come from my heart and mind. I don&amp;rsquo;t expect that all my experiments will succeed, but seeing someone else try, and publicly, how can I not do likewise?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Have you recently discovered a musician who has changed your hearing and/or your own playing? Who was it and what did you learn?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reflections on Richard Wagner&#39;s 200th birthday: beautiful music without a future</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/05/22/reflections-on-richard-wagners-200th-birthday/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 May 2013 08:14:55 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/05/22/reflections-on-richard-wagners-200th-birthday/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A couple of days ago, I was driving and had the radio on and heard Richard Wagner&amp;rsquo;s prelude to act 1 of his opera &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Die_Meistersinger_von_N%C3%BCrnberg&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Die Meistersinger&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, and was transported into the lush musical world that is so uniquely Wagner: seductive orchestral colors, chromatic harmony, melodic motifs, fine storytelling, stirring climaxes, and in this particular musical excerpt, ironic yet clever use of counterpoint. I had to pull over for a while to finish listening to the prelude and fully enjoy the &lt;em&gt;guilty&lt;/em&gt; rush of emotional excitement in this fun but over-the-top piece. Why the guilt?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;controversy&#34;&gt;Controversy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The controversial music composer &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_Wagner&#34;&gt;Richard Wagner&lt;/a&gt; was born 200 years ago. In keeping with the media&amp;rsquo;s love of arbitrarily nice round numbers and anniversaries, there&amp;rsquo;s a lot of commentary about celebrations of his birthdays or reasons &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; to celebrate. Here are just a few articles that came up during a Web search:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.washingtonpost.com/entertainment/music/germany-celebrates-200th-birthday-of-composer-richard-wagner/2013/05/22/b8f93924-c2b2-11e2-9642-a56177f1cdf7_story.html?tid=pm_entertainment_pop&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Germany celebrates 200th birthday of Richard Wagner, Hitler&amp;rsquo;s favorite composer&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://fullcomment.nationalpost.com/2013/05/22/barbara-kay-if-you-must-listen-to-wagner-do-it-in-private/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;If you must listen to Wagner, do it in private&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.towntopics.com/wordpress/2013/05/22/whistling-in-the-dark-on-wagners-200th-birthday/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Whistling in the dark on Wagner&amp;rsquo;s 200th birthday&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://jessicamusic.blogspot.com/2013/05/dear-richard-i-need-to-tell-you.html&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Dear Richard, I need to tell you something&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.newyorker.com/online/blogs/culture/2013/05/wagner-bicentennial-birthday-music-recordings.html&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;A Wagner birthday roast&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;None of this commentary actually addresses my mixed feelings about Wagner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;wagner-s-anti-semitism&#34;&gt;Wagner&amp;rsquo;s anti-Semitism?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much of the commentary touches upon Wagner&amp;rsquo;s anti-Semitism and Adolf Hitler&amp;rsquo;s use of Wagner in Germany for Nazi purposes. I will &lt;em&gt;not be discussing&lt;/em&gt; these (important) issues because others already do, and because I tend toward the view that people are imperfect and I would like to be able to assess their important and good work even if they could be judged as unpleasant or downright evil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;love-the-music-hate-the-man&#34;&gt;Love the music, hate the man?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I also do not agree with the sentiment of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.independent.co.uk/voices/comment/on-the-200th-anniversary-of-wagners-birth-lets-learn-to-love-the-music--yet-still-hate-the-man-8614155.html&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Let&amp;rsquo;s learn to love the music, yet still hate the man&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. I don&amp;rsquo;t think there is a total separation between Wagner&amp;rsquo;s music and everything else about him. In Wagner&amp;rsquo;s case, in particular, he specifically designed his music around a certain philosophy about the world, about &lt;em&gt;art&lt;/em&gt;. And that is what I really find interesting and unsettling, somewhat along the lines of Friedrich Nietzsche&amp;rsquo;s critique of his one-time friend, &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Case_of_Wagner&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Case of Wagner&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nietzsche_contra_Wagner&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Nietzsche contra Wagner&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;music-and-philosophy&#34;&gt;Music and philosophy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wagner&amp;rsquo;s philosophizing about the nature of and purpose of music embraced the notion of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gesamtkunstwerk&#34;&gt;Gesamtkunstwerk&lt;/a&gt;, the &amp;ldquo;total work of art&amp;rdquo;, that would unify all the arts, hence his development of his form of opera, the &amp;ldquo;music drama&amp;rdquo;, whose purpose was to unify music, poetry, theater in a grand and serious spectacle to inspire the audience. He proposed the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Music_of_the_Future&#34;&gt;Zukunftsmusik&lt;/a&gt;, or &amp;ldquo;music of the future&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;modernism&#34;&gt;Modernism?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Wagner&amp;rsquo;s day in the late 19th century, there was &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/War_of_the_Romantics&#34;&gt;fierce rivalry among the German Romantics&lt;/a&gt; on the direction of musical evolution. Roughly, there was the camp of Johannes Brahms (whose &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/05/07/happy-birthday-johannes-brahms/&#34;&gt;birthday I celebrated a few weeks ago&lt;/a&gt;, considered &amp;ldquo;conservative&amp;rdquo;, and the camp of Wagner, which considered itself &amp;ldquo;modern&amp;rdquo;. Aspects of this &amp;ldquo;war&amp;rdquo; seem quaint and exaggerated now, and Brahms has been &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.economist.com/node/367351&#34;&gt;re-evaluated&lt;/a&gt; in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/1996/09/29/arts/old-brahms-a-modernist-in-more-ways-than-one.html&#34;&gt;recent&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.americansymphony.org/concert_notes/the-other-voice-of-johannes-brahms&#34;&gt;decades&lt;/a&gt;, and the big tent of Western art music has historically learned from both camps&amp;rsquo; methods and sensibilities, but Wagner, at least, took very seriously his own self-importance and self-promotion as an artist/philosopher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An interesting question to me is, what is Wagner&amp;rsquo;s relationship to &lt;em&gt;modernism&lt;/em&gt;, both in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Modernism_%28music%29&#34;&gt;musical sense&lt;/a&gt; and in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Modernism&#34;&gt;more general sense&lt;/a&gt;, typically applied to the late 19th century and early 20th century trends in literature, art, architecture, and society that are still relevant today?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;tristan&#34;&gt;Tristan&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.guardian.co.uk/friday_review/story/0,,381181,00.html&#34;&gt;harmonic and other innovations&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tristan_und_Isolde&#34;&gt;Tristan und Isolde&lt;/a&gt; in 1865 (it is arguable that Franz Liszt was the real innovator first) can be considered the beginning of modernism in music (in the sense of dissolution of Western tonality). Check out this performance of the beginning of the prelude to act 1 along with a score annotated with harmonic analysis:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/Pwk3BKipjtQ&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s my favorite full performance of the prelude as well as the final sung Liebestod, by the great Wilhelm Furtwängler conducting and Kirsted Flagstad singing. It truly blew my mind when I first discovered and heard this music while in college.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/SQO7QIgNvA0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;who-claims-modernism&#34;&gt;Who claims modernism?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the modernist &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Second_Viennese_School&#34;&gt;Second Viennese School&lt;/a&gt; under Arnold Schönberg liked to claim Brahms as one of their own, and in even more revisionism recently, there have been attempts to situate &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.upress.umn.edu/book-division/books/modernism-after-wagner&#34;&gt;Wagner as the inspiration for modernism in the larger sense&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(A few of my notes about Schönberg &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/25/thank-you-glenn-gould/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Also, it is too large a topic for now, but I plan to write more later about modernism and postmodernism and post-postmodernism in music, in the context of today&amp;rsquo;s music and in my own experience of music, whether listening or performing.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;wagner-s-legacy&#34;&gt;Wagner&amp;rsquo;s legacy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe Wagner failed, that his philosophy was a dead end, and that his music was a dead end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This despite the fact that, of course, he changed the course of Western musical history, both by provoking the modernist backlash against his theatricalism and chromaticism, while paving the way for, say, Mahler and Bruckner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have enjoyed and continue to occasionally listen again to marvelous music by Wagner, but &lt;em&gt;not in the way he intended&lt;/em&gt;. I have never attended a performance of one of his operas. I have only seen (on TV or video) or listened to bits of his operas that are sung (rather than purely instrumental excerpts). Two decades ago, I did try to watch the mammoth &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Der_Ring_des_Nibelungen&#34;&gt;Ring cycle&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/1990/06/18/arts/review-television-taking-the-17-hour-plunge-with-wagner-s-ring-at-the-met.html&#34;&gt;broadcast on TV by the Metropolitan Opera&lt;/a&gt; over four long evenings, but my attention span allowed me to only drift in and out of consciousness periodically during that attempt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps most damning of all is that shortly after that TV experience, I rather enjoyed listening to Lorin Maazel&amp;rsquo;s album, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/music/dp/B000003CUJ&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Ring Without Words&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, basically showing that for me, Wagner totally failed as a philosopher, because I like his music best without the &amp;ldquo;poetry&amp;rdquo; (his lyrics, which he wrote himself, don&amp;rsquo;t make much sense to me) and without the on-stage drama.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even then, I cannot listen to his music much without feeling unclean. There is a sense in which I cannot separate his music from his philosophy and his wider artistic and cultural aims. Even if he had not been an anti-Semite, there should be controversy over him and his legacy. There is a sense in which I agree with some of the old-fashioned concerns about his music: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.guardian.co.uk/music/2013/may/22/wagner-bad-for-your-mental-health&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Wagner as mental health menace?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. In Nietzsche&amp;rsquo;s words, Wagner and his music are &lt;em&gt;decadent&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2014-07-13&#34;&gt;(Update of 2014-07-13)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/07/13/what-i-remember-lorin-maazel-for/&#34;&gt;RIP, Lorin Maazel&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;music-is-powerful&#34;&gt;Music is powerful&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it&amp;rsquo;s pretty delicious decadence. Last month a friend splurged on going to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://ringcycle.metoperafamily.org/&#34;&gt;Metropolitan Opera&amp;rsquo;s performance of the Ring&lt;/a&gt;, and I decided to indulge in listening to Siegfried&amp;rsquo;s funeral march in &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/G%C3%B6tterd%C3%A4mmerung&#34;&gt;Götterdämmerung&lt;/a&gt;. As usual, the experience left me in tears. Wagner, master psychologist, master manipulator of emotions, master composer, weaving the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leitmotif&#34;&gt;leitmotifs&lt;/a&gt;, summing up the whole tragic story of the Ring:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/L8wHteSOwW4&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And for sheer &lt;em&gt;hypnotism&lt;/em&gt;, listen to Furtwängler again, with the prelude to act 1 of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lohengrin_%28opera%29&#34;&gt;Lohengrin&lt;/a&gt;. Close your eyes, turn out the lights, and listen. Beautiful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/I_m7PN5sn1U&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More hypnosis: prelude to act 1 of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parsifal&#34;&gt;Parsifal&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;ve chosen an old Furtwängler performance again:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/EZhSUX5Ix68&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;back-to-die-meistersinger&#34;&gt;Back to Die Meistersinger&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, to end where I started, with the prelude to act 1 of Die Meistersinger that I happened to enjoy on the radio, here is Furtwängler again, conducting a performance of it live. &lt;strong&gt;Warning: this is a video of a live performance in 1942 in Germany with swastikas in the background, so you may not wish to view this.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/3rM96_RS1Os&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, this video is totally creepy, but I thought it would be appropriate to close on this jarring note. Die Meistersinger was, after all, Wagner&amp;rsquo;s telling of a story to glorify old Germany, and was a favorite opera of the Nazis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(And the subject of Furtwängler, a conductor I have many mixed feelings about, will have to wait for another blog post as well.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I cannot help but admire and be affected by Wagner&amp;rsquo;s music, but at the same time feel that his entire philosophy and aim was bankrupt. I&amp;rsquo;ve touched on only a little bit of how I have come to feel this, since the larger issues go beyond Wagner, but I don&amp;rsquo;t yet have complete thoughts and rationales to offer at this time. As with the towering figure of Beethoven, his musical and cultural legacy is still controversial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;postscript&#34;&gt;Postscript&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided I wanted to end more positively. My favorite piece of Wagner&amp;rsquo;s is one that was actually always intended to be purely instrumental and is self-contained, not just an excerpt: the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Siegfried_Idyll&#34;&gt;Siegfried Idyll&lt;/a&gt;. Oh wait, again we all subvert his intention anyway, because he composed it for his wife Cosima&amp;rsquo;s birthday (what a beautiful present to wake up to in the morning) and only ever intended it to be performed privately!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furtwängler again:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/_jlzEFg-zkY&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2014-07-11&#34;&gt;(Update of 2014-07-11)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I just saw yet another article about &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.newrepublic.com/article/118331/forbidden-music-michael-haas-reviewed-james-loeffler&#34;&gt;Wagner and anti-Semitism&lt;/a&gt;. The topic never goes anyway, and I don&amp;rsquo;t think it should. That said, I don&amp;rsquo;t personally have anything to add to the discussion, but offer the link if you feel you need to engage further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2015-01-14&#34;&gt;(Update of 2015-01-14)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I saw yet another (and excellent) article &lt;a href=&#34;http://mosaicmagazine.com/essay/2015/01/wagner-and-the-jews/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Wagner and the Jews&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Happy birthday, Johannes Brahms! 3 takes on a musical favorite</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/05/07/happy-birthday-johannes-brahms/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 May 2013 20:41:13 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/05/07/happy-birthday-johannes-brahms/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;It turns out today is the 180th birthday of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Johannes_Brahms&#34;&gt;Johannes Brahms&lt;/a&gt;, born May 7, 1833, so I thought I&amp;rsquo;d share some of my favorite music by this great composer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;piano&#34;&gt;Piano&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I discovered Brahms while a freshman in college and a total newcomer to classical music, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/09/taking-up-flute-again-after-decades/&#34;&gt;upon taking a course called &amp;ldquo;Piano Music of the 19th Century&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; because it sounded like it was an easy way to get required &amp;ldquo;core curriculum&amp;rdquo; credit (no musical background was required for this appreciation course). Instead of being just a throwaway survey course I took just to get credit, the course &lt;em&gt;changed my life&lt;/em&gt;. Sometimes that actually happens, when the instructor is passionate and communicative!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We listened to and discussed various of Brahms&amp;rsquo; miniature piano pieces he called &amp;ldquo;intermezzi&amp;rdquo;, op. 116, 117, 118, and 119. Part of what we were supposed to do was tell stories about how the pieces made us feel and why (in terms of some kind of story that involved identifying musical ideas and development).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although I went on to listen to other music by Brahms, for myself, I still have considerable nostalgia for the piano intermezzi Brahms wrote late in life, and this is so appropriate, I guess, given that they have a decidedly nostalgic, melancholic flavor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have many favorites among these sets of piano pieces, but decided to share just one of them today, &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Four_Pieces_for_Piano,_Op._119_%28Brahms%29&#34;&gt;op. 119&lt;/a&gt; no. 1 in B minor. The melancholic arpeggiated descending thirds and ambiguous harmonies, with a longing melodic line above the inner voices, make this a perfect example of Brahmsian beauty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;imagery&#34;&gt;Imagery&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I listen to this, I imagine sitting by a window, alone, as raindrops slowly and repeatedly drip down, and the clouds come and go, while occasionally a ray of sun peeks through and smiles, and occasionally there is a burst of thunder. Meanwhile, the wind is blowing and sometimes stops a raindrop from continuing to fall, or blows it back upward. I look through the window, and the world is gray and blurry, and the raindrops tell the story of what is going on outside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;three-interpretations&#34;&gt;Three interpretations&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are three interpretations I found on YouTube. I personally like the raindrops to linger and accelerate and decelerate with rubato, and this guy &amp;ldquo;Ferien7&amp;rdquo; plays that up, taking a leisurely 3:44 for the whole piece:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/KtWynSHgKH4&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I link to this video by an unknown because I like how YouTube can be a source of what I find to be good performances by people who are passionate about a particular piece but are not necessarily famous professionals or well-established recording artists. I have no idea who &amp;ldquo;Ferien7&amp;rdquo; is, but I like this performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another interpretation along similar veins, but by someone much more famous, and tighter (3:38), is by one of my all-time favorite historic pianists, &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sviatoslav_Richter&#34;&gt;Sviatoslav Richter&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/ACOvOqLqCkM&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, here is a very different, fascinating interpretation by &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Heinrich_Neuhaus&#34;&gt;Heinrich Neuhaus&lt;/a&gt;, actually Richter&amp;rsquo;s teacher, which is very fast (2:52), and emphasizes the unbroken melodic line and the drama, over the individual notes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/GYrgVp90jvQ&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2014-08-21&#34;&gt;(Update of 2014-08-21)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A year later, I found another interpretation, by Robert Hill, which I love for its extreme freedom. Check it out in &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/08/21/discovering-the-beautiful-keyboard-playing-of-robert-hill-by-accident-on-youtube-changed-my-life/&#34;&gt;my blog post about Robert Hill&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;More&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you liked this piece, check out the other intermezzi by Brahms.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>