<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Film on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/film/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Film on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/film/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>On re-experiencing VHS tapes again</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/16/on-re-experiencing-vhs-tapes-again/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Nov 2014 21:27:49 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/16/on-re-experiencing-vhs-tapes-again/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I stopped serious study of ballroom dance sometime around 2003, over ten years ago, because I was discouraged by not finding a maximally compatible dance partner. I ended up closing the chapter of my life that started in 2000 when ballroom dance consumed almost all of my time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently I brought up several boxes of ballroom dance instruction videos from those days, with the idea that even though I&amp;rsquo;m not longer doing ballroom dancing with anyone any more (Abby is not very interested in ballroom dance), I might find it enjoyable to continue developing my dance skills and use the videos as part of exercise also. Almost all of these videos are VHS tapes. I have almost no dance videos on DVD, as I was very late in acquiring a DVD player: actually, one day, my mother bought me a DVD player because she was tired of visiting me and having no way to watching any DVDs she brought!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had mixed emotions and memories as I started going through these videos again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-was-i-late-to-cds-and-dvds&#34;&gt;Why was I late to CDs and DVDs?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier in life, I was very late in getting a CD player also; I bought only &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/09/12/rip-ray-dolby-yes/&#34;&gt;cassette tapes&lt;/a&gt; and LPs until late in college, around 1990, when I finally buckled to pressure and bought a CD player. I am generally not an early adopter of technology. I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/22/paradox-i-will-observe-the-national-day-of-unplugging-but-just-bought-my-first-smartphone-this-week/&#34;&gt;bought my first smartphone in 2012&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why the resistance to technology? Partly it&amp;rsquo;s just a matter of cost. But more fundamentally, I worried about the long-term durability of digital media. It turns out that I shouldn&amp;rsquo;t have worried quite so much, because backing up has turned out to be quite feasible and inexpensive. But in the early days of CDs and DVDs, I was not going to be ripping them and storing them on super-expensive hard drives, so my worry was about the physical media of CDs and DVDs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;was-i-was-right-about-the-disadvantages-of-digital-media&#34;&gt;Was I was right about the disadvantages of digital media?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that I was partially right. Some of my old CDs and DVDs did become unplayable after a decade or two, but very few.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bigger problem is that Abby and I sometimes check out DVDs from the public library and find that they have enough scratches that when watching a film we often miss entire minutes and scenes because of damaged playback! This has happened so many times that I question the value of ever checking out a DVD from the library again that looks even a little scratched. What a waste!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The advantage of analog media such as LPs and cassette tapes and VHS tapes is that in some ways they are more fault tolerant. I remember the old days of splicing tape, for example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But actually, analog media get corrupted easily enough by magnetism, mold, etc. I do have tapes that are unplayable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The killer feature of digital media was always indexing and random access. It&amp;rsquo;s a real hassle not being able to skip from one dance lesson to the next, or get a table of contents, in these dance videos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s far less efficient using VHS videos for instruction than indexed digital media. That said, I see why people stream video these days rather than buy or borrow DVDs; physical digital media are fragile. But what would libraries do if they stopped acquiring and serving CDs and DVDs?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Charlie Chaplin, a daughter, a granddaughter: changing my perception of &#34;Smile&#34;</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/04/16/charlie-chaplin/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Apr 2014 22:01:39 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/04/16/charlie-chaplin/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;So today is the 125th birthday of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charlie_Chaplin&#34;&gt;Charlie Chaplin&lt;/a&gt;. I could assume that he needs no introduction, being one of the famous pioneers of film, but I have to confess that I have never myself actually watched the entirety of any of his films. I went through much of my life not knowing much about him at all, in fact, other than caricatures of his famous character &amp;ldquo;the little tramp&amp;rdquo;, which to me just seemed dated and weird, and therefore not of interest. So I never looked further into his films or his life: it was all just ancient history to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But two years ago, by chance, I learned more about him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-song-smile&#34;&gt;The song &amp;ldquo;Smile&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two years ago, I discovered that the music for the famous song &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Smile_%28Charlie_Chaplin_song%29&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Smile&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; was actually composed by Chaplin. This intrigued me, so I learned a bit more about him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, here is a video clip from his 1936 film &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Modern_Times_%28film%29&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Modern Times&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; featuring the musical theme that became the song &amp;ldquo;Smile&amp;rdquo;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/Ps6ck1ejoAw&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;family&#34;&gt;Family&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing I learned is that Chaplin had a very complicated family life, with four marriages, the last of whom was 36 years younger than him (and eventually had eight children with him). One of these children was &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Geraldine_Chaplin&#34;&gt;Geraldine Chaplin&lt;/a&gt;. Her name rang a bell, because I vaguely remembered seeing her in the 1973 film &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Three_Musketeers_%281973_film%29&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Three Musketeers&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; way back!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that not only did his daughter Geraldine also take up acting, but her daughter, &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oona_Castilla_Chaplin&#34;&gt;Oona Chaplin&lt;/a&gt; also did. Indeed, I found all this out by accident: two years ago, I had been looking for a karaoke version of &amp;ldquo;Smile&amp;rdquo; to sing along to, when by accident I found a video of Geraldine and Oona Chaplin singing &amp;ldquo;Smile&amp;rdquo; together! It was fascinating watching this performance of Charlie Chaplin&amp;rsquo;s music by a daughter and granddaughter of his:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/PSPP6EM_CcY&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;biography&#34;&gt;Biography&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A couple of days ago, I saw this interesting &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.spectator.co.uk/books/9179261/charlie-chaplin-by-peter-ackroyd-review/&#34;&gt;review of a biography of Charlie Chaplin&lt;/a&gt; calling him a &amp;ldquo;monster&amp;rdquo;. Of course, we know that an actor&amp;rsquo;s character&amp;rsquo;s persona may not match real life. Such is the complexity of humanity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;other-performances-of-smile&#34;&gt;Other performances of &amp;ldquo;Smile&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There have been many famous classic performances of &amp;ldquo;Smile&amp;rdquo; since it became a song with lyrics in 1954. I&amp;rsquo;ll share here one that is kind of creepy, yet compelling, maybe appropriately so given what we know of Chaplin&amp;rsquo;s complicated life. Here&amp;rsquo;s a video of Judy Garland singing the song. I find it utterly over the top but hard to resist; she gives the song a crazed intensity and sadness rather than a comfortable feel-good reading. Of course, her personal life was also a mess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/GAQfwpEDdOw&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-i-perceive-smile-now&#34;&gt;How I perceive &amp;ldquo;Smile&amp;rdquo; now&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I knew about Chaplin&amp;rsquo;s satirical film &amp;ldquo;Modern Times&amp;rdquo; and the man himself, I suppose I considered &amp;ldquo;Smile&amp;rdquo; something of a wishful, sentimental song, although with a lovely melody and seductive harmonic progression, but now it&amp;rsquo;s completely impossible for me to think of this song without a sense of irony.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How about you? How have you perceived the song up till now? Did you know the back stories? How do you perceive the song now, after reading this post? Can you hear it or sing it again the way you did before?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Watching &#34;Hable con ella&#34; (&#34;Talk to her&#34;) (2002): thoughts on art, crime, and ethics</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/12/26/hable-con-ella-talk-to-her-thoughts-on-art/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Dec 2013 10:38:33 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/12/26/hable-con-ella-talk-to-her-thoughts-on-art/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/en/4/43/Talk_to_Her_English_movie_poster_fairuse.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Talk to her&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;After a decade of putting it off, I finally watched &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pedro_Almod%C3%B3var&#34;&gt;Pedro Almodóvar&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s 2002 film, &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Talk_to_Her&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Hable con ella&amp;rdquo; (&amp;ldquo;Talk to her&amp;rdquo;)&lt;/a&gt;. I was actually on the verge of going to a local movie theater to watch it a decade ago when circumstances in my life changed and I put it on hold. But Abby and I just watched it together, partially because Almodóvar has been on my mind since &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/12/19/appreciating-the-unique-singer-la-lupe/&#34;&gt;I re-listened to some music sung by La Lupe a couple of days ago&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out to be a fantastic film, totally gripping and moving, no slow or pointless moments, really tight. One of my favorite films of all time, surely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was also disturbing on many levels, as great art often is. Abby and I had some conversations about some of the issues, but there was even more still on my mind, so I decided to share them here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: there are some serious &lt;strong&gt;spoilers&lt;/strong&gt; in this post, so if you haven&amp;rsquo;t watched the film yet, please stop reading now and &lt;em&gt;go watch it&lt;/em&gt; first. In any case, I am skipping important plot elements in order to focus on particular themes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-rape&#34;&gt;The rape&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s cut to the chase. In this film, a really weird guy, Benigno, who is depicted as unhealthily obsessed with a young woman ends up being one of her primary caretakers (he is a nurse) in the hospital when she slips into a coma after an accident. When we encounter him in the story, he&amp;rsquo;s already been taking care of her for four years. We see him bathing her and massaging her in a way that might be considered loving and caring, but also creepy and too intimate, especially given how he had secretly stalked her before the whole accident. Everyone thinks he&amp;rsquo;s gay (he lied to fool her father), so nobody seems to seriously question his care of her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the story, we are led to believe (it was not depicted) that during the course of the story, he raped her and got her pregnant. Miraculously, at some point after her pregnancy was discovered, she woke from her four-year coma, but the child was stillborn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;my-reaction&#34;&gt;My reaction&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can go online and see a lot of reactions to this rape, say, the IMDB forums. Some disbelieve, some try to justify her awakening as making up for his crime, others say they refuse to watch the film because they heard what the story is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Myself, I disbelieved at first, despite the very clear signal straight from the film director himself. I thought, maybe it was the other main character, or the other man besides him. I thought this even though I knew it could not be. I found it &lt;em&gt;very interesting&lt;/em&gt; that despite the obvious (except that I didn&amp;rsquo;t see it happen), I &lt;em&gt;did not want to believe&lt;/em&gt; that his man, even though he was clearly weird and inappropriately obsessed with the comatose woman, did this. I examined myself and asked why I did not want to believe. One reason was that other being all weird, he came across as being very gentle and caring, both towards her (taking care of her inert body) and to the other main character Marco, who became a close friend of his. For all we knew, he was still a virgin. And she hadn&amp;rsquo;t gotten pregnant after four years of his care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, my &amp;ldquo;reasoning&amp;rdquo; was completely ridiculous. How did I know that he wasn&amp;rsquo;t molesting her for four years, and just being careful about it, and only accidentally slipping up one night after watching that silent film he talked to her about?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I was very uncomfortable that aspects of his personality and behavior that made me feel sympathetic to him &lt;em&gt;in general&lt;/em&gt; led me to doubt that he was capable of something horrible. This brought up memories of being confused and cynical in the light of revelations in recent years that some people&amp;rsquo;s heroes were in fact very flawed: for example, the big Penn State scandal involving &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jerry_Sandusky&#34;&gt;Jerry Sandusky&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joe_Paterno&#34;&gt;Joe Paterno&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s apparent role in concealing Sandusky&amp;rsquo;s repeated sexual abuse of young boys. Or &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lance_Armstrong&#34;&gt;Lance Armstrong&lt;/a&gt; finally confessing to being a drug doper in sport. Or the history of sexual abuse by priests and other leaders in many religious institutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that I was detached from all those cases, not having any emotional involvement with the &amp;ldquo;heroes&amp;rdquo; in question, so it was easy for me to scoff at those who went out of their way to demonize the victims and proclaim their heroes innocent. So I was pretty disturbed that just through skillful storytelling, the film director here was able, for a split second, to cause me to doubt the obvious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;bullfighting-and-respect-for-different-cultures&#34;&gt;Bullfighting and respect for different cultures&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another thing that disturbed me was the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bullfighting&#34;&gt;bullfighting&lt;/a&gt;. I am hardly a member of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.peta.org/issues/animals-in-entertainment/animals-used-entertainment-factsheets/bullfighting-tradition-tragedy/&#34;&gt;PETA&lt;/a&gt;, but I find bullfighting frightening and perverse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, I am slightly ambivalent about this attitude. But only slightly. OK, it&amp;rsquo;s an important cultural institution in Spain, and I am definitely not one to lightly dismiss long-standing traditions that clearly have served a purpose of some kind over centuries, even millennia. But I&amp;rsquo;m not a relativist who thinks everything&amp;rsquo;s OK somewhere. For example, there are long traditions of human slavery that &amp;ldquo;we&amp;rdquo; (in, say, the US where I live and grew up) consider &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; to be OK, and &amp;ldquo;we&amp;rdquo; believe that women should have the right to vote, that &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Female_genital_mutilation&#34;&gt;female genital mutilation&lt;/a&gt; is unacceptable, that the ancient Chinese &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Foot_binding&#34;&gt;foot binding&lt;/a&gt; of women was an atrocity, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You could argue that it&amp;rsquo;s just sheer cultural conditioning that I happen to believe in what &amp;ldquo;we&amp;rdquo; believe, but nevertheless, I feel justified in my judgment and can&amp;rsquo;t apologize for it. So if you&amp;rsquo;re reading this and you&amp;rsquo;re Spanish and offended, I don&amp;rsquo;t know how to sugarcoat it, but bullfighting freaks me out. The best I can say is, there are probably things I believe in or do that you find disgusting also.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;cognitive-dissonance-and-hypocrisy&#34;&gt;Cognitive dissonance and hypocrisy?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The weird thing is, even as I felt disgust at seeing all the blood during the bullfighting scenes in the film, I felt unease at my participating in a very sanitized version of the whole thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m talking about the ballroom dance &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pasodoble&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;paso doble&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, which is a kind of weird, transformed re-enactment of a bullfight theme. I have never actually danced paso doble in competition, but have practiced basic steps and movements, and have &lt;em&gt;fantasized&lt;/em&gt; about being some kind of macho bullfighter. See, in most of the standard ballroom dances, the focus of display and movement is almost entirely on the follower, the woman. In &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; the paso doble, the man is really the focus, being the bullfighter. (The follower is, bizarrely, his cape: the bull is invisible and only implied.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still periodically do a paso doble &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/13/video-review-dancing-with-the-stars-cardio-dance-2006/&#34;&gt;dance workout&lt;/a&gt;. When I do this dance workout, you can bet I&amp;rsquo;m not thinking about bloody bulls or the possibility of being gored to death. Somehow the whole thing has been sanitized. I feel slightly weird about this &amp;ldquo;Anglo&amp;rdquo; appropriation of a cultural tradition. I would say I feel slightly weird about the other sanitized and standardized Latin ballroom dances too (rumba, cha cha, samba) that have &amp;ldquo;authentic&amp;rdquo; roots from, for example, Cuba and Brazil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I feel only &amp;ldquo;slightly&amp;rdquo; weird, because cultural borrowing and appropriation is something that has always happened. I don&amp;rsquo;t think we can or ought to stop it, any more than I can go around sniffing that a lot of &amp;ldquo;Chinese food&amp;rdquo; in American restaurants is not much like what I know to be more &amp;ldquo;authentic&amp;rdquo;. The best I can do is &lt;em&gt;know the difference&lt;/em&gt;, rather than reject evolution or borrowing of traditions. So, for example, I have watched videos of Cuban salsa, which differs from urban North American studio or club salsa. I did study &amp;ldquo;Argentine tango&amp;rdquo; after engaging in the heavily stylized and very different ballroom tango. I think these can all reasonably coexist, as long as one knows what each is and not pretend something is what it is not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;gender-roles&#34;&gt;Gender roles&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then somehow everything brought me to the issue of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gender_role&#34;&gt;gender roles&lt;/a&gt;. In the film, the bullfighter main character is a woman, Lydia. Unusual. That led me to think about other weird issues I have dealt with concerning ballroom dancing, and couple dancing in general where there is a clear separation between leader and follower. Are these dances a weird kind of anachronism? I have definitely met women who rejected or were openly uneasy about taking part in this kind of dancing, but obviously, as Abby and I have gone out dancing, we know of plenty of women who are OK with it. In fact, we often see women dancing the leader role, and admittedly less often, men dancing the follower role. I tend to think there&amp;rsquo;s not really a problem with this kind of dancing, given that people really can and do switch roles these days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;do-the-ends-justify-the-means&#34;&gt;Do the ends justify the means?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some final thoughts: what happens when we accept that something is disturbing? Especially when we rationalize away our discomfort?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, why did Almodóvar tell a story about a rapist who some would like to say possibly &amp;ldquo;helped&amp;rdquo; a comatose woman awake? What if that were true? Does it make his crime any less bad? And what about intent? Does intent matter in an action? Fodder for your philosophy classes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And what about the film itself? What is the response to those who refuse to watch this film because of a rape? Has Almodóvar committed a crime by making the character a sympathetic, tragic one? Or is this &amp;ldquo;only&amp;rdquo; art? Or is it because it is high art that it is justified?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that reminds me of the controversy over &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roman_Polanski&#34;&gt;Roman Polanski&lt;/a&gt;, many of whose beautiful, profound films I have enjoyed through my life? He fled the US in 1977 after statutory rape of a 13-year-old girl. In 2009 there was controversy after the US tried to extradite him, and a lot of film fans apparently came to his defense. Were they making the mistake of making an allowance for a great film maker that they would not have made for some random guy? Is my continuing to watch his films a crime? Should I be boycotting his films?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of questions, and I think no easy answers. Of course, our actions reveal our implicit answers. What we say does not matter. What we do does.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-science-added-2014-01-05&#34;&gt;The science (added 2014-01-05)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing I forgot to discuss was the matter of whether people in vegetative states are actually aware of what is going on around them. Assuming they have some awareness, that makes a lot of what happened in the film kind of creepy (but also, what happens in real life in hospitals).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a recent post about &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.spring.org.uk/2014/01/patients-in-vegetative-state-can-respond-emotionally-to-loved-ones.php&#34;&gt;emotional awareness in patients in a vegetative state&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2014-04-27&#34;&gt;(Update of 2014-04-27)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A great article on &lt;a href=&#34;http://mosaicscience.com/story/mind-readers&#34;&gt;vegetative states&lt;/a&gt; just came my way, reminding me of the discomfort I felt when watching this film.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, a great film is one that somehow makes me think about life and humanity in the broadest possible ways, even though I didn&amp;rsquo;t really want to. I guess Pedro Almodóvar struck a home run with this film.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not the kind of film I want to watch every night, because then I end up spending hours thinking about stuff. But there it is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Do you find this kind of film too disturbing to watch or to think about? Are you concerned by inaccurate scientific portrayals in film? Are you concerned about films that make you sympathetic toward someone who is not only disturbed but also a criminal?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>