<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Wedding on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/wedding/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Wedding on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/wedding/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Playing Baroque flute at my friend&#39;s wedding reception</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/08/12/playing-baroque-flute-at-my-friends-wedding-reception/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Aug 2012 23:50:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/08/12/playing-baroque-flute-at-my-friends-wedding-reception/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/new-mexico/wedding.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Steve and Kelly&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Today was a very special day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was the wedding day of one of my best friends, Steve, whom I first met in Pittsburgh over a decade ago. Abby and I were thrilled to have been able to travel to be there for Steve and to meet and get to know Kelly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It suddenly started raining very hard at the outdoor wedding, which caused a lot of improvised changes in plans, but the rain cleared up eventually and everything went well: the details do not matter when we&amp;rsquo;re talking about love and friendship and family. It was a lovely ceremony; the couple customized their own vows, which were funny as well as deeply serious and moving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;planning-for-my-small-musical-role&#34;&gt;Planning for my small musical role&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a small role to play. When Steve had told me about the wedding, I had immediately asked him if he would like me to play some music for him (since all the weddings I&amp;rsquo;ve been to have involved a DJ or some friend handling iTunes off a laptop at some point). Eventually, after more important details were planned out, such as a string quartet hired to play before the wedding and during the ceremony, it was decided that I could play for maybe ten minutes after dinner at the reception in order to transition to the toasts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided to bring my plastic &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/baroque-flute/&#34;&gt;Baroque flute&lt;/a&gt; as being the best instrument to withstand easy travel to New Mexico.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I memorized some of the traditional music I&amp;rsquo;ve played before on Baroque flute, taking selections from an &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/04/21/my-first-time-in-a-public-music-jam-intense-fun-with-chris-norman-and-david-greenberg/&#34;&gt;Irish/Scottish/Acadian set of scores&lt;/a&gt; as well the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/05/14/playing-french-music-for-first-time-and-dancing-blues-for-first-time/&#34;&gt;French traditional dance music I got from Gregory&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-the-music-situation-turned-out&#34;&gt;How the music situation turned out&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, because of the rain, the string quartet had to stay inside, so there was no music for the ceremony itself, unfortunately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, because of the rain, the sound system driven in by the bride&amp;rsquo;s brother got wet and was inoperable, so there was not going to be an iTunes-based background music during the dinner reception.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So ironically, my little music performance after dinner turned out to have some more prominence than I expected, simply because of the rain. I played a selection of songs, solo, including spontaneous ornamentation during the repeats, of course. I did not play entirely without stumbling, but was pretty inspired because Steve&amp;rsquo;s niece, about two years old, ended up turning around on her chair, standing up to face me, and smiling and dancing to the music!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was touched that a number of people came up to me later and said they enjoyed the performance. Somehow, in a single moment, I remembered why I have chosen the musical path I deliberately put myself on &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/12/quitting-the-cmu-all-university-orchestra-one-of-the-hardest-decisions-in-my-life/&#34;&gt;earlier this year&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- no photo of niece because of privacy --&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/new-mexico/franklin-flute.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin playing Baroque flute&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I felt very honored to be able to attend my friend Steve&amp;rsquo;s wedding and to provide a bit of musical entertainment for the guests at the reception. And to see his niece all excited and dancing while I played basically made my year.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>