<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Cups on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/cups/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Cups on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/cups/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Steel City Ukuleles: back to plain good fun, including the cups song</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/16/steel-city-ukuleles-back-to-plain-good-fun/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2013 22:06:02 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/10/16/steel-city-ukuleles-back-to-plain-good-fun/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s been over a week since I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/10/05/performing-with-the-steel-city-ukuleles-at-the-wilkins-school-community-center-ecofest-2013-with-videos/&#34;&gt;performed as part of the Steel City Ukuleles in the Wilkins School Community Center Ecofest&lt;/a&gt;. I was very relieved to have no more self-imposed performance obligations for a while, feeling burned out for a while, to tell the truth. But I was ready to get back into playing just for fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;members-choice&#34;&gt;Members&amp;rsquo; choice!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had a fun &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/Steel-City-Ukuleles/events/140097142/&#34;&gt;session this week&lt;/a&gt; in which all of us had earlier been invited to submit music we personally wanted to play. I had submitted &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mr._Sandman&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Mister Sandman&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, a song I&amp;rsquo;ve loved since (amusingly) first hearing it when watching &amp;ldquo;Back to the Future&amp;rdquo; way back. I was really excited to finally be singing it and playing it with others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We did various other member-contributed selections also, including a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cups_%28song%29&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Cups&amp;rdquo; song&lt;/a&gt; that apparently has become all the craze because of moving cups around as part of percussion! Three of us had practiced ahead of time to play the cups. I have to say I was impressed:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/cups.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Cups&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;rubber-duckie&#34;&gt;Rubber Duckie&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We went over &amp;ldquo;Rubber Duckie&amp;rdquo; again. I love this song. I&amp;rsquo;m getting better at singing and strumming it simultaneously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;kazoo&#34;&gt;Kazoo&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I finally bought a cheap kazoo for use in the future (several of us used kazoos in the Ecofest performance, but I did not have a kazoo at the time), as Jack got a whole bunch to sell to us:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/kazoo.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Kazoo&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed getting back to just plain fun with singing and playing ukulele, with no more performances in the near future that I&amp;rsquo;ve volunteered to be a part of.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>