<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Minimalism on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/minimalism/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Minimalism on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/minimalism/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Reflections on 2011</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/12/31/reflections-on-2011/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Dec 2011 18:52:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/12/31/reflections-on-2011/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I reflect on my year of 2011 as it ends. Since I did not start blogging until September, I go into more detail of what happened before then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;january&#34;&gt;January&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I continued our project of massively reorganizing our home, a project that began when she moved in during summer 2010. We were very grateful that Abby&amp;rsquo;s father helped out a lot.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I continued getting rid of a lot of stuff, including another eighteen boxes of my books, as I became an initially reluctant &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/minimalism/&#34;&gt;minimalist&lt;/a&gt;. We sold or gave away a &lt;em&gt;huge&lt;/em&gt; number of various of belongings.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby started cooking much more than in the past, and we enjoyed trying new dishes of her making.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I enjoyed some light cross-country skiing in the winter, using the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Schenley_Park_Golf_Course&#34;&gt;Bob O&amp;rsquo;Connor Golf Course at Schenley Park&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I began a weekly Zen &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/meditation/&#34;&gt;meditation&lt;/a&gt; session offered at Carnegie Mellon University.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started moving very gradually toward a &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/paleo/&#34;&gt;paleo&lt;/a&gt; diet and exercise routine, and immediately experienced benefits. &amp;ldquo;The Paleo Solution&amp;rdquo; by &lt;a href=&#34;http://robbwolf.com/&#34;&gt;Robb Wolf&lt;/a&gt; was very useful.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started learning modern &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/javascript/&#34;&gt;JavaScript&lt;/a&gt; for a new project at work, getting into client-side Web development. As part of that, I learned &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/jquery/&#34;&gt;jQuery&lt;/a&gt; through a free &lt;a href=&#34;http://p2pu.org/&#34;&gt;P2PU&lt;/a&gt; course and used it in the project.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started using &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/XQuery&#34;&gt;XQuery&lt;/a&gt; at work to process XML in a clear and concise way. I had used XSLT in the past, but it was very unpleasant.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I decided, for various reasons, to stop writing new &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/perl/&#34;&gt;Perl&lt;/a&gt; scripts and move to &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/python/&#34;&gt;Python&lt;/a&gt; instead.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started playing in my final (and disastrous) &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/chess/&#34;&gt;chess&lt;/a&gt; tournament, the Pittsburgh Chess Club Championship (which I had won in 2006 and 2007).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;february&#34;&gt;February&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pittsburgh was all about the Steelers, and I went to a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Super_Bowl_XLV&#34;&gt;Super Bowl&lt;/a&gt; party for the first time, but we lost!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I read &amp;ldquo;The Art of Non-Conformity&amp;rdquo; by &lt;a href=&#34;http://chrisguillebeau.com/&#34;&gt;Chris Guillebeau&lt;/a&gt; and found it so inspiring that I decided to take action and start making big changes to my life, in my own way.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;One big change: I quit playing chess, cold turkey, after having been unenthusiastic about it for months already (and playing correspondingly poorly). When the passion and enjoyment are gone, there is no point in hanging onto something just because it has been such an important part of my life for years.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;After years of not playing any music at all, I started playing &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/recorder/&#34;&gt;recorder&lt;/a&gt;, and vowed to play every single day if possible. Ten months later, I am still playing recorder.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I began attending a lot of &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/16/pittsburgh-software-developer-communities/&#34;&gt;local software developer group meetings&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started learning the &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/scala/&#34;&gt;Scala&lt;/a&gt; programming language and decided to use it on a small project.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;march&#34;&gt;March&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I continued our meditation practice at CMU, and went to our first mini-&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sesshin&#34;&gt;sesshin&lt;/a&gt; on a Saturday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I continued practicing recorder every single day, and joined the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.andrew.cmu.edu/user/lukas/pcars/Welcome.html&#34;&gt;local chapter of the American Recorder Society&lt;/a&gt;. It was very exciting to meet new people and to get into a wide range of music I had never really listened to or played.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I saw a video of &lt;a href=&#34;http://jakeshimabukuro.com/&#34;&gt;Jake Shimabukuro&lt;/a&gt; playing &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/ukulele/&#34;&gt;ukulele&lt;/a&gt; so beautifully that I was inspired to buy a ukulele and start learning to play it. (Unfortunately, it would turn out that time constraints caused me not to pursue ukulele far. This will change in 2012.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I got pulled into the Ruby programming language because it is well-supported on Mac OS and it is easy to install libraries and tools, of which there are many that are quite useful.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I went to &lt;a href=&#34;http://farmtotablepa.com/&#34;&gt;Farm to Table&lt;/a&gt; in Pittsburgh, and after that, Abby started moving toward paleo eating, with even better results than my smaller experiments earlier.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I started our &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/hiking/&#34;&gt;hiking&lt;/a&gt; season in the spring. Hiking is special to us; it was one of our first shared activities (after initially meeting during salsa dancing), and one we return to again and again. When there is no calendar conflict and the weather is acceptable, we like hiking almost every weekend from spring through fall.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;{% img /images/steves-soup-hike-2011-03-26.jpg Abby in front of me at Steve&amp;rsquo;s Soup Hike %}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;april&#34;&gt;April&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started wearing &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/fivefingers/&#34;&gt;Vibram FiveFingers shoes&lt;/a&gt; almost all the time, whether walking or running (but not yet for hiking).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I went to &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/yoga/&#34;&gt;yoga&lt;/a&gt; at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.clpgh.org/locations/squirrelhill/&#34;&gt;Squirrel Hill Library&lt;/a&gt; for the first time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;may&#34;&gt;May&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I began my experiment with barefoot running, in observation of &lt;a href=&#34;http://barefootrunners.org/ibrd&#34;&gt;International Barefoot Running Day&lt;/a&gt;. I started walking around barefoot at work, ignoring the confused looks or comments of colleagues. (I still go barefoot at work.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I bought a &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/melodica/&#34;&gt;melodica&lt;/a&gt;, inspired by the amazing performances of &lt;a href=&#34;http://jnote.org/&#34;&gt;James Howard Young&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I took a little vacation, spending some days in New York visiting Nathaniel and Yael and their baby. I finally fulfilled my dream (from before marriage) of taking Abby to Coney Island to walk on the boardwalk and at the beach, eating pizza, and riding the Wonder Wheel, just as I once did when I was six years old.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I started doing research into major home renovations for the summer.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I visited my parents, and my sister Linda and her husband Andre also visited, with my mother throwing a delayed reception at home for the both of us who had gotten married in the past two years. Abby got to meet my parents&amp;rsquo; friends, finally. And I went running with my brother-in-law for the first time! Also, I took Abby to the little park in Ann Arbor where as a too-shy teenager I used to go and sit on a particular bench and wish I were sitting with my dream girl. Mission accomplished!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;june&#34;&gt;June&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;John and I did a tough 19-mile training hike on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rachelcarsontrails.org/rct&#34;&gt;Rachel Carson Trail&lt;/a&gt; and decided we&amp;rsquo;d had enough of that trail, and I decided I was probably not going to do the 35-mile &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rachelcarsontrails.org/rct/challenge&#34;&gt;Rachel Carson Trail Challenge&lt;/a&gt; again (having completed it three times in the past).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;{% img /images/rachel-carson-trail-2011-06-05.jpg John on Rachel Carson Trail %}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby started wearing Vibram FiveFingers more and more for walking and running, and even walking barefoot on the streets (something I had not yet seriously done myself at the time).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I stupidly threw out my back during exercise, and my back took weeks to fully recover (I could still run and hike, but not lift weights). Never again, I hope. I felt like a 90-year-old when my back was hurting constantly.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;We started some home improvement projects.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;july&#34;&gt;July&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started gravitating to almost exclusively body weight &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/strength-training/&#34;&gt;strength training&lt;/a&gt;, as a reaction to my having injured my back earlier.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I went kayaking on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kiskiminetas_River&#34;&gt;Kiski River&lt;/a&gt; with &amp;ldquo;Fireman Steve&amp;rdquo; and the kayaking gang.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;On a longish hike, Abby surprised me by wearing Vibram FiveFingers shoes and they worked great for her, making her much faster and less sore, and I made a note to ditch my trail running shoes (which I had been using for years for hiking) in favor of FiveFingers for my next hike (which I did, and I have not gone back to regular shoes for hiking!).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I finally took Abby to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sandhillberries.com/&#34;&gt;Sand Hill Berries&lt;/a&gt; for tasty pie for the first time, always having intended to take her there when dating, but never having been in the vicinity with her then.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Major home renovation finally began, after much research, and we got electrical upgrade, insulation, and bathroom demolition and rebuilding. Very disruptive to our lives for weeks!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I did another mini-&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sesshin&#34;&gt;sesshin&lt;/a&gt; at CMU.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;After a lifetime of almost never drinking coffee (average of maybe three or four cups a year), I became an avid espresso fan (one small cup a day) as a result of my boss getting a machine at work.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started doing more barefoot running.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;august&#34;&gt;August&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bathroom renovation done at last.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I were regularly hiking in Vibram FiveFingers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;{% img /images/abby-franklin-soup-hike-vibram.jpg Abby and Franklin on Steve&amp;rsquo;s Soup Hike part 3 wearing Vibram FiveFingers %}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby joined me to run in her first ever 5K race, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.runaroundthesquare.com/&#34;&gt;Run Around the Square&lt;/a&gt; in Regent Square (mostly on the trails of Frick Park). What a special day! This race was my first ever 5K race when I started running in races in 2000.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started to learn &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/accordion/&#34;&gt;accordion&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;september&#34;&gt;September&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started running to work two or three times a week.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I ran in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~kalp/PGR/&#34;&gt;CMU SCS Pretty Good Race 5K&lt;/a&gt; together, her second 5K race.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I went to &lt;a href=&#34;http://podcamppittsburgh.com/&#34;&gt;PodCamp Pittsburgh&lt;/a&gt;, and after that, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/22/starting-a-new-web-site/&#34;&gt;I started this blog&lt;/a&gt; and proceeded to maintain a habit of posting every day (a routine that has been modified since then).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;october&#34;&gt;October&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started expanding beyond just writing for my blog, and began contributing to the Web through &lt;a href=&#34;http://twitter.com/franklinchen&#34;&gt;my Twitter account&lt;/a&gt; as well as writing comments on other people&amp;rsquo;s blog posts.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started taking Stanford online classes: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ml-class.org/&#34;&gt;Machine Learning&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.db-class.org/&#34;&gt;Introduction to Databases&lt;/a&gt;. (Blog posts on my experiences to appear soon.) Unfortunately, as a result of the extra time commitment, October through December were quite hectic for me.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I continued to move more toward a paleo diet.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;november&#34;&gt;November&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started playing &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/flute/&#34;&gt;flute&lt;/a&gt; again.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Probably because of fatigue and a compromised immune system, I came down with a skin ailment that I got serious treatment for, but it took almost two months to completely clear up and I spent over a month truly miserable &lt;sup&gt;24&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;7&lt;/sub&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;december&#34;&gt;December&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started playing Baroque flute.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started playing tin whistle.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I prepared for and made it through two music performances, playing recorder and flute (and almost tin whistle).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I ended the year completely exhausted, on the verge of getting sick, and took a long break from blogging.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The final week, Abby and I were on a hectic travel schedule that involved meeting up with her parents, my parents, her sister Carrie, Carrie&amp;rsquo;s boyfriend Alain, Alain&amp;rsquo;s parents, Alain&amp;rsquo;s extended family, my sister Linda, and her husband Andre. I am grateful that we got to meet up with so many people (and arranged for various of the individuals to meet up with various of the others!), but the trip was quite stressful to me, because I was not physically or emotionally prepared for it at all. (I will report later on what I learned from the experience.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2011 was quite a year for me and Abby. We had many changes and adventures in our lives: our home, our diet, our exercise, our outdoors activities, travel. For me, the biggest changes were quitting chess, starting music practice and performance, throwing myself into blogging and tweeting, getting more and more active in local software developer groups, applying new (to me) development tools at work, and in the fall, taking Stanford online courses in computer science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although I ended the year in poor shape, because of being overbooked, I am very excited by how many positive changes took place. I have an entirely new set of plans and priorities to formulate soon for 2012 in collaboration with Abby, in hope of learning from the lessons of my failures and omissions of 2011, and restoring balance.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is time money?</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/11/01/is-time-money/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Nov 2011 21:52:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/11/01/is-time-money/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently I came across a blog post claiming that &lt;a href=&#34;http://thenonconsumeradvocate.com/2011/10/time-is-not-money/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;time is not money&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. Reading it, and the many comments that supported the author&amp;rsquo;s thesis, I felt oddly concerned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not here to refute &amp;ldquo;time is not money&amp;rdquo;, but to briefly explain my concern.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;life&#34;&gt;Life&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s start with life itself, rather than time or money. We are born. We live, by making sure our fundamental needs are met: eating, drinking, maintaining health, recovering from illnesses and accidents, etc. Beyond providing for our fundamental needs, we may do all kinds of other activities also, ranging from more sophisticated entertainment, socializing, trying to achieve fame, etc. At some point, we die.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;time&#34;&gt;Time&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because we die, time is important, since we want to live and enjoy it and our time is limited. All things being equal, we would rather have more of life rather than less of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;money&#34;&gt;Money&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unless we are hunter-gatherers who have access to free food, etc., we need some kind of money, as a store of value and a means of exchange for what we need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;time-is-money&#34;&gt;Time is money&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In modern industrial society, much of what we depend on and assume as a basic need (such as a non-primitive, legal, stable place to live) can only be obtained through money. We obtain that money by trading time for it, by using our time to be productive to society and obtain money in return. Hence, &amp;ldquo;time is money&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;money-is-time&#34;&gt;Money is time&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The relation between time and money is symmetry. Time is money, and money is time. The entire history of the modern industrialized world has been to enable conversion of money to time. Division of labor, so that we don&amp;rsquo;t have to spend our lives making all our own clothing and growing all our own food, has increased efficiency. Labor-saving technologies such as swords, knives, pencils, microwaves, and dishwashers save us time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;time-is-money-is-time&#34;&gt;Time is money is time&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So there is a cycle in our lives in which we have time, some of which we spend &amp;ldquo;employed&amp;rdquo; doing &amp;ldquo;work&amp;rdquo;, convert it into money, and then spend some of that money to buy us more time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are, of course, opportunities to use time or money elsewhere than in that cycle. We may have extra time that we can choose to spend in some other way than converting it directly to money. We can spend the extra time hanging out with family and friends, watching a movie, and doing all kinds of things we enjoy; in other words, use the extra time to &lt;em&gt;live&lt;/em&gt;. The author of the blog post seems to be arguing that she enjoys doing all those things, and therefore time is not money. It is this last leap that does not make sense to me. Nobody ever said that all time must be converted to money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, some break the cycle by not converting money back to time, but converting it into possessions instead. Unfortunately, at some point one has to remember that &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.library.csi.cuny.edu/dept/history/lavender/cherries.html&#34;&gt;you can&amp;rsquo;t take your dough when you go, go, go&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;for-some-time-really-is-money&#34;&gt;For some, time really is money&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason I am disturbed by the attack on &amp;ldquo;time is money&amp;rdquo; is that a lot of people have very little money, and the best way for them to get more, in order to be able to live better and create a virtuous cycle in which they can generate more time, is precisely to convert as much of their time as possible into money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Time is money&amp;rdquo; is a powerful message that immigrants to our nation have applied again and again to start out starving and end up feeding themselves and their families. The single mother who spends a large amount of her time working multiple jobs so that she can feed her children and proudly see them be the first in the family to graduate from college is living &amp;ldquo;time is money&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, I wonder if the attack on &amp;ldquo;time is money&amp;rdquo; is a perspective resulting from having enough money and therefore not needing to generate more. That is a state of living that is obviously pleasant, and congratulations to all who have put in enough time that they have all the money they need and can scale back. I&amp;rsquo;m actually quite sympathetic to the &amp;ldquo;minimalist&amp;rdquo; view of life and money: know how much money you need, and spend the extra on time. I just don&amp;rsquo;t think the minimalist message is useful, yet, to the unemployed single mother without health insurance, who will have very little time on this earth if she doesn&amp;rsquo;t convert the time she has to money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although I support minimalism, I don&amp;rsquo;t think it is in conflict with &amp;ldquo;time is money&amp;rdquo;, or equivalently, &amp;ldquo;money is time&amp;rdquo;. I see minimalism as a way to maximize one&amp;rsquo;s own life choices, rather than a way to be angry at other people for making different ones. I fear that blogs such as the &lt;a href=&#34;http://thenonconsumeradvocate.com/&#34;&gt;Non-Consumer Advocate&lt;/a&gt; may be more of a preaching-to-the-choir forum than a way to help non-minimalists evaluate different ways of living. I sense anger and contempt in that blog.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Really taking up the challenge of minimalism</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/10/19/really-taking-up-the-challenge-of-minimalism/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Oct 2011 21:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/10/19/really-taking-up-the-challenge-of-minimalism/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, I talked about &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/18/disagreement-on-the-use-of-time/&#34;&gt;use of &lt;strong&gt;time&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Today, I am talking about &lt;strong&gt;space&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have too much &lt;em&gt;stuff&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that. I&amp;rsquo;ve known that for years. I&amp;rsquo;ve not been happy about it. But I&amp;rsquo;ve also not been happy about getting rid of my &lt;em&gt;stuff&lt;/em&gt;. When I got married, I had to get rid of probably half of my &lt;em&gt;stuff&lt;/em&gt;, to make space for Abby to move in, but I did not part with them happily.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I &lt;strong&gt;still&lt;/strong&gt; have too much &lt;em&gt;stuff&lt;/em&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;ve been promising to get rid of more, but have dragged my feet on the project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This time is different.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.missminimalist.com/jol-mmfront-180-bb.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Front cover of The Joy of Less by Francine Jay&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-promise&#34;&gt;My promise&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I made a promise to Abby, and now I&amp;rsquo;m making a promise in public, to complete the project.  Yes, I know, there are claims that one should &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ted.com/talks/derek_sivers_keep_your_goals_to_yourself.html&#34;&gt;keep one&amp;rsquo;s goals to oneself&lt;/a&gt;, but I&amp;rsquo;m ignoring them this time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Objectively, I know all the reasons not to have a lot of &lt;em&gt;stuff&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, I&amp;rsquo;m familiar with George Carlin&amp;rsquo;s great monologue:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/MvgN5gCuLac&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And yes, I&amp;rsquo;ve read &lt;a href=&#34;http://zenhabits.net/about/&#34;&gt;Leo Babauta&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s book, &lt;a href=&#34;http://thepowerofless.com/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Power of Less&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which did help me make radical changes to my life a couple of years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although I&amp;rsquo;ve made much progress in the past two to three years, it was never enough. We got rid of over a thousand books (as I mentioned in yesterday&amp;rsquo;s post), through selling on Amazon and donating to various sources. We got rid of most of my LPs, started getting rid of some of my CDs and DVDs. Etc. But there is still a lot left. Not only books, music, movies, but also computer parts, cables, old pens, unused small appliances, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby deserves credit for having taken charge of most of the decluttering that we&amp;rsquo;ve done. Minimalism comes to her much more easily than it does to me. I&amp;rsquo;m the one who has all that stuff in the basement going unused!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My &amp;ldquo;pack rat&amp;rdquo; mentality always lurks around, ready to emerge at any time to defend keeping something. So I never completed the project of &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; letting go. There was always something to keep that deep down I knew I didn&amp;rsquo;t really need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;another-book-on-minimalism&#34;&gt;Another book on minimalism&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But another book on minimalism has really inspired me to go further with my &amp;ldquo;decluttering&amp;rdquo;: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.missminimalist.com/about/&#34;&gt;Francine Jay&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0984087311?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;amp;tag=missminimalist-20&amp;amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;amp;creative=390957&amp;amp;amp;creativeASIN=0984087311&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Joy of Less, A Minimalist Living Guide&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For some reason, this book&amp;rsquo;s conversational tone and detailed exploration of why we keep stuff was inspirational to me. I have to confess that some books and web sites on minimalism that I have looked at in the past seemed a bit too manic and preachy, and turned me off. They made minimalism look like some kind of self-righteous game, a competition, a form of reverse-snobbery (&amp;ldquo;oh, look at me, I have only a hundred possessions!&amp;rdquo;). Also, they made it sound easy to make the leap to minimalism, and since I find the leap very difficult, I got discouraged.  I just didn&amp;rsquo;t relate well, emotionally, to those sources of advice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Often, advice or information or stories meant to be helpful or interesting might fall on deaf ears if the audience does not in a deep way identify with the author. That is an insight I am still in the process of grappling with as I try to figure out how to make my blog maximally useful to you, my reader!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;helpful-insights-and-ideas&#34;&gt;Helpful insights and ideas&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are just a few of the helpful ideas from the book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-stuff-is&#34;&gt;What stuff is&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To begin, the author classifies stuff as one of the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;useful&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;beautiful&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;emotional&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Classification is helpful because it enables us to reflect on the &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; of having something, and distinguish different functions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;you-are-not-what-you-own&#34;&gt;You are not what you own&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A powerful message, because often we have stuff just because someone else has it or because we want to show off, whether through unnecessary furniture or decorations or even a large book collection (I plead guilty to the latter in the past).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are what we &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;now&lt;/em&gt;; not what we &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; to remind us of what we &lt;em&gt;did&lt;/em&gt; (I used to keep around a bunch of trophies that I finally admitted were really pointless to hang onto).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;less-stress-and-more-freedom&#34;&gt;Less stress and more freedom&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The author tells us to think of how carefree and happy we were in college, when we had the least amount of stuff. We were learning, living, having fun. And we were not tied down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s true, though: I do remember a time when I had almost nothing, and that was fine. Strange how things changed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;space&#34;&gt;Space&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Life is the space between our things.&amp;rdquo; An intriguing image!  The author urges us to focus on what we &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt;, rather than what we &lt;em&gt;own&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;enjoy-without-owning&#34;&gt;Enjoy without owning&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The author says, &amp;ldquo;In pursuing a minimalist lifestyle, we need to resist the temptation to recreate the outside world within our abodes.&amp;rdquo; We can &amp;ldquo;shift some of our pleasures and activities into the public realm.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I immediately understand how one can enjoy without owning, because for much of my life I did not own much. Libraries were one way I enjoy plenty without owning. Interestingly, today it is even easier now to enjoy without owning. Having Internet access, we can enjoy the resources from a vast digital world!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;pareto-principle&#34;&gt;Pareto principle&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The author invokes the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pareto_principle&#34;&gt;Pareto principle&lt;/a&gt;, which she interprets in our context as &amp;ldquo;we use 20 percent of our stuff 80 percent of the time&amp;rdquo;. So we could actually get rid of most of what we have and not really miss it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I highly recommend this book to anyone who is even thinking about decluttering project, however big or small.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I make major progress on my continuing minimalism project, I&amp;rsquo;ll write about it!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>