<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Concerts on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/concerts/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Concerts on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/concerts/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Why go to concerts by amateur music groups?</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/12/12/why-go-to-concerts-by-amateur-music-groups/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Dec 2011 21:13:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/12/12/why-go-to-concerts-by-amateur-music-groups/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-historical-music-society-concert/program.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Program&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;On Sunday, Abby and I carpooled with Helen and Mike (of the &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/recorder/&#34;&gt;recorder&lt;/a&gt; gang) to Ambridge for a free concert given by the &lt;a href=&#34;http://pghhistoricalmusicsociety.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Historical Music Society&lt;/a&gt; as part of a Christmas-themed event in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.oldeconomyvillage.org/&#34;&gt;Old Economy Village&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That was a long way to drive to see an amateur group give a concert. So why did we pile into the car?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main draw was that there was going to be a performance of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brandenburg_concertos#Brandenburg_Concerto_No._4_in_G_major.2C_BWV_1049&#34;&gt;Bach&amp;rsquo;s Brandenburg concerto 4&lt;/a&gt;, including as soloists the local &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/baroque-flute/&#34;&gt;Baroque flute&lt;/a&gt; players Karen Parsons and Laura Lockard, and violinist and conductor William Lockard. I was very curious to see some Baroque flutists in action, since I had only recently &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/30/bought-a-baroque-flute/&#34;&gt;bought a Baroque flute&lt;/a&gt;. Also, I love Bach&amp;rsquo;s Brandenburg concerto 4 (which I tried to sight read for alto recorder a while ago but is still too hard for me).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The concert featured a variety of early music, including some music specifically written for the original orchestra of historic Old Economy Village back in the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-historical-music-society-concert/orchestra-left.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Left view of orchestra&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-historical-music-society-concert/orchestra-right.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Right view of orchestra&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-historical-music-society-concert/harp-viol-flute.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Harp, viola da gamba, and flute&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below are the soloists in the Brandenburg 4:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-historical-music-society-concert/brandenburg-4.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Soloists for the Brandenburg 4&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;concert-review&#34;&gt;Concert review&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Going to an event like this, my expectations are not very high. In fact, once upon a time, I would not really bother to attend a concert of amateur performers because of high standards programmed into my mind as a result of easy access to any number of current or classic music recordings by professionals. And no, I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t have bothered to attend this particular concert if not for the draw of the Baroque flutists and the personal connections as well as expectations that they would be decent (which they were).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the concert, some of the violins were perpetually out of tune, and there were constant glitches everywhere, whether in the cello, horns, whatever. One has to simply be patient and decide to enjoy the performances as they are. Sometimes the struggle even adds to the excitement. The Brandenburg 4 is not easy, and even at the slow tempos chosen, the imperfections in execution combined with honest enthusiasm made me appreciate even more how special it was that Bach wrote such brilliant and passionate music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;in-praise-of-amateurism-and-imperfection&#34;&gt;In praise of amateurism and imperfection&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am an amateur musician, and not yet a very skilled one, so I recognize my limitations. I can miss notes, create uneven and ragged phrasing, fall apart at high speed, play out of tune, and make all kinds of other errors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think that being out there myself playing now, I am more appreciative than I used to be of other amateurs who love music and put themselves out there also in all their imperfection. And interestingly, I learn from that also. By hearing someone play less than perfectly, I better see that in myself and have a basis for becoming more self-aware and improving. Paradoxically, it is less useful to see someone perform at professional perfection, because that&amp;rsquo;s too far away from where I am. I consider this true whatever the field: music, chess, computer programming. Just being around perfection does not help one&amp;rsquo;s own practice and appreciation. It helps also to be around those of a somewhat higher level. That makes it easier to think, &amp;ldquo;I could be up at that level also, with work&amp;rdquo;, which is much easier to think than, &amp;ldquo;I could be Einstein or Beethoven&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;you-too-can-participate&#34;&gt;You too can participate!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Especially today, when some people are fearful and avoid doing anything that they don&amp;rsquo;t think they will be immediately expert at, I think there is a powerful message to spread. If you love music, please consider joining us amateurs who go around playing it and sharing it and helping each other improve! You don&amp;rsquo;t have to be perfect to enjoy performing. You can sing, or pick up that instrument you haven&amp;rsquo;t touched since childhood, and start up again! The media would have us believe that we are unworthy and that the best we can do is choose not to be an active music maker and instead just buy and consume recordings from the pros. There is certainly nothing wrong with appreciating the pros and supporting their beautiful performances, but we too can dance and sing, with enthusiasm and without shame!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;personal-connections&#34;&gt;Personal connections&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The recorder gang knows Laura Lockard from her involvement with a music workshop held in the summer (which I may attend next summer). They also seemed to know the other solo flutist, Karen Parsons. Also, Abby and I have our own connection to Karen Parsons: it&amp;rsquo;s her farm that we sometimes get &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/28/thankful-for-the-free-range-orange-yolked-eggs&#34;&gt;eggs&lt;/a&gt; from! Very small world, this Pittsburgh or western PA region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;postscript&#34;&gt;Postscript&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you love the Brandenburg 4, check out this amazing melodica rendition of the last movement by James Howard Young, all by himself on multiple tracks:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/_YE3akDmw9Q&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On not reading concert program notes</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/11/11/on-not-reading-concert-program-notes/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Nov 2011 23:06:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/11/11/on-not-reading-concert-program-notes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have a confession to make. When attending a music concert or dance performance, I never really look at the program notes they pass out. Furthermore, I feel sufficiently guilty that I always take the printout or brochure home, &amp;ldquo;just in case&amp;rdquo; I feel like actually sitting down and reading it. I never do. Several years ago I finally took a whole box of Pittsburgh Symphony Orchestra programs and recycled them, never having ever read any of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, when I check out a CD or DVD from the library, I don&amp;rsquo;t really look at the liner notes either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s going on? And should I feel guilty? And what should I make of tonight&amp;rsquo;s dance performance Abby and I &amp;ldquo;accidentally&amp;rdquo; ended up watching because we didn&amp;rsquo;t know the full program up front?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;last-saturday-s-concert-by-sonia-lee-http-www-sonialeemusic-com-and-robert-bocchino-http-www-cs-cmu-edu-rbocchin&#34;&gt;Last Saturday&amp;rsquo;s concert by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sonialeemusic.com/&#34;&gt;Sonia Lee&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~rbocchin/&#34;&gt;Robert Bocchino&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last set of program notes I have on hand are from last Saturday&amp;rsquo;s concert, part of the Aspinwall Presbyterian Performing Arts Series, with Sonia playing the harpsichord and Rob playing the baroque violin in one of the works. It was a nice little concert I heard about through the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.andrew.cmu.edu/user/lukas/pcars/Welcome.html&#34;&gt;local recorder society&lt;/a&gt;. I know Rob from our playing recorder together in the group, and met his wife Sonia through him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;choosing-to-go&#34;&gt;Choosing to go&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before the concert, I had a decent idea of what kind of music was going to be played: harpsichord and baroque violin mean, well, some kind of early music. To tell the truth, I don&amp;rsquo;t even remember if I ever carefully read the email announcement about the concert, other than who was playing and where and when! My thought wasn&amp;rsquo;t about specific pieces of music to expect, but was just, &amp;ldquo;Hey, I haven&amp;rsquo;t heard Sonia play harpsichord except briefly at that one potluck dinner at Helen&amp;rsquo;s, and I haven&amp;rsquo;t yet heard Rob play baroque violin yet, and I&amp;rsquo;m not all that familiar with Renaissance or Baroque music (yet), so I&amp;rsquo;m in!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;sitting-down-eyes-glazed-over&#34;&gt;Sitting down, eyes glazed over&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pattern is always the same. I get to the location of the concert, there are only minutes before it is to start, I sit down, I have a couple of pages of text handed to me by someone when I entered, and the last thing I feel like doing is &lt;em&gt;reading&lt;/em&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;m here to &lt;em&gt;listen&lt;/em&gt;, and secondarily, to &lt;em&gt;watch&lt;/em&gt;, not to read. It&amp;rsquo;s like, the &lt;em&gt;reading&lt;/em&gt; part of my brain wants to shut down for a while. I spend the vast majority of my life reading. I like getting a real break!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;program-outline&#34;&gt;Program outline&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s the information I have in my hand? Names of composers and pieces, with movement names, years of composer&amp;rsquo;s birth and death, year of composition. Doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean much to me. Either I already know the composer or piece, in which it is superfluous, or I don&amp;rsquo;t know, in which case the information is practically meaningless to me. Who the heck is Gaspard Le Roux? Do I really care? And what does &amp;ldquo;Sonatina No. 8 in A minor&amp;rdquo; really mean to me? It means a certain form in a certain key, but other than that, not much. I am, of course, grateful to get this outline of the concert. It&amp;rsquo;s good to have a rough idea of time period, how long each piece might be, when to clap, when intermission happens, etc. Still, I find myself sometimes guiltily distracted by this piece of paper. Am I going to make noise while trying to glance at it during performance. Is it going to fall on the floor? Can I keep it open?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I see Mike (one of our recorder gang who also came to the concert) scribbling on his outline. Ah, taking notes? I&amp;rsquo;ve done that before. I&amp;rsquo;m too lazy to do it this time, although I have observations about the acoustics in this church, matters of interpretation by Sonia and Rob, etc. Just too lazy this particular evening. In fact, I spend most of the concert with my eyes &lt;em&gt;closed&lt;/em&gt;, my preferred method for listening to music. I don&amp;rsquo;t really need to see anything when at a concert. It just distracts me. Rob is doing something funny with his neck; do I really need to see or think about that (after the concert, he says it&amp;rsquo;s something because of how the baroque violin is held, and without a neck rest).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;program-notes&#34;&gt;Program notes&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trying to read the program notes before the concert and at intermission, I just get tired and nervous. I feel like I should digest this information and somehow have it enhance my listening experience. But it doesn&amp;rsquo;t. In fact, I think it never does. I feel guilty about being ignorant. Poor Gaspard Le Roux: what would he think if he knew? Oh wait, he&amp;rsquo;s dead, and doesn&amp;rsquo;t know. And probably he wouldn&amp;rsquo;t care either. He&amp;rsquo;d probably be excited that hundreds of years after his death, someone out there is playing his music, and people are listening!  His &amp;ldquo;elegant Courante demonstrates rhythmic variety, including the use of hemiolas at cadential points.&amp;rdquo; Oops, was I supposed to wait breathlessly to notice the hemiolas and congratulate myself? Oops, I only read that now, so I don&amp;rsquo;t even remember the hemiolas? Did I miss them? Does it matter if I did? I can&amp;rsquo;t hear every single interesting musical device in my first listening of random music. Heck, I can&amp;rsquo;t hear everything in recorded music I have listened to a dozen times! I suppose I feel annoyed that program notes make me think I&amp;rsquo;m missing something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, the long biographies of the performers. I know marketing is vital to a performer, but personally, when I go to a concert, I don&amp;rsquo;t really need to know a performer&amp;rsquo;s long distinguished record of performance and scholarship. (That also goes for attending academic lectures and seminars, usually prefaced by some kind of long list of awards the speaker has received.) It&amp;rsquo;s up to my ears, not text on a page, to determine whether I enjoy the performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;tonight-s-recorder-concert-plus-an-unintended-dance-performance-bonus&#34;&gt;Tonight&amp;rsquo;s recorder concert, plus an unintended dance performance &amp;ldquo;bonus&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fast forward to tonight, when Abby and I went to the Convention Center to attend a free concert, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.aosa.org/pittsburgh/wanderings.html&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Wanderings&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, that was mentioned on the recorder mailing list. The concert, free to the public, started at 7:45 PM, and was part of some big multi-day conference of the American Orff-Schulwerk Association. I still don&amp;rsquo;t know exactly what that is (yes, I know, I could explore the web site and read it, and maybe I will eventually). I was just going for the free concert, which featured a recorder player, Nina Stern, with a percussionist Peter Maund. I was excited to go because this was the first time I&amp;rsquo;ve ever seen a professional recorder player, and so I wanted to know what a famous pro sounds like, and make note of how I can sound better myself!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a nice concert. The place was packed, because after all, this was part of a big conference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;no-detailed-program-or-program-notes&#34;&gt;No detailed program or program notes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Possibly because the actual participants of the conference had their own packet of information already, Abby and I didn&amp;rsquo;t get any program or program notes. That was fine with me. All I really needed to know was, a famous recorder player was there, and &amp;ldquo;will take you on a musical voyage from Medieval Italy to Armenia, from the Balkans to the Middle East, performing ancient melodies, vibrant estampies from the 14th century and traditional dances from Bulgaria and Serbia.&amp;rdquo; Enough detail for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As it turned out, Nina did say a few words about each set of pieces they performed, either before or after performing it. &lt;strong&gt;I love this format.&lt;/strong&gt; Much better than wasting time typing up stuff or copying and pasting impersonal text. I enjoy hearing the information very close to listening to the music, thereby making it memorable to relate to. And it adds a personal touch, because I get to hear her speak, and not just appear on stage and play music and walk off without saying a word. That&amp;rsquo;s always bizarre to me. I like to know a real human being is up there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No pieces of paper or brochure. Just the way I like it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I would have liked it even more if Nina and Peter had told us exactly which instruments they were playing, because they kept swapping them out. Myself, I was carefully trying to determine which recorders she was playing (she played around four different ones). I could not see very well from where we were sitting, so I could only determine from sound and length that she played tenor, alto, and soprano, but I would have liked to know something about their construction also (a few words would have been enough).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;totally-bizarre-dance-performance-by-das-collectif&#34;&gt;Totally bizarre dance performance by Das Collectif&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we get to the really weird stuff.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.aosa.org/011conference/images/Das-Collectif-web.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Das Collectif&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Because I didn&amp;rsquo;t know the full program for the evening, only having seen the announcement of the &amp;ldquo;Wanderings&amp;rdquo; recorder concert, I hadn&amp;rsquo;t known that after the intermission, there was going to be a one-hour long modern dance performance by a group called &amp;ldquo;Das Collectif&amp;rdquo; from Austria. So when Abby and I sat down, we assumed there was going to be more music, not that the recorder concert was over and something completely different was going to come. If I had checked the time, I would have known, but I didn&amp;rsquo;t. The announcement for the recorder concert did say 7:45 to 8:45. Well, what happened was we sat down, and &amp;ldquo;Das Collectif&amp;rdquo; came on stage, as scheduled, to perform &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.aosa.org/pittsburgh/das_collectif.html&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Stomping La Luna&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Example text from the description: &amp;ldquo;Gradually the light wakes up the dead and a mysterious, eerie activity of the revived corpses sets in. They start fighting, gambling and enjoying the moment of their regained lives. They search for forms of communication and discover each other. In dynamic, spacious movements they are showing their undisguised emotions. The night covers up what is forbidden, the light shows what is hidden.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Years ago I used to watch dance of all sorts, from ballet to jazz, modern, tap, ballroom, so seeing weird stuff doesn&amp;rsquo;t faze me. But it had been a while, so &amp;ldquo;Stomping La Luna&amp;rdquo; was quite strange. The demands on the dancers were quite considerable during the full hour: rolling around, bending, twitching, reciting text, singing and humming (often in lovely harmony), playing percussion instruments (including their own bodies and the floor), and even a violin solo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the web site there is a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.aosa.org/011conference/documents/Suites-des-scenes.pdf&#34;&gt;program&lt;/a&gt; for &amp;ldquo;Stomping La Luna&amp;rdquo;. I just looked at it. It wouldn&amp;rsquo;t really have helped to have seen it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have to be honest: if I had seen the description of &amp;ldquo;Stomping La Luna&amp;rdquo;, I would have planned to leave after the recorder concert. But having it foisted on me by surprise, I had to see it through to find out how it would end! It was entertaining enough, although totally bizarre. Not something I would deliberately attend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;update-of-2014-04-27&#34;&gt;(Update of 2014-04-27)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over two years later, one day, for some reason, I was thinking about &amp;ldquo;Stomping La Luna&amp;rdquo;, so I looked online to refresh my memory, and I found a video of excerpts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/gF7oxiKVjv8&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Not&lt;/em&gt; reading program outlines or program notes can lead to more discoveries, more attention, more surprises: living in the moment rather than trying to match up someone&amp;rsquo;s description of a concert or dance performance with the real thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Embracing the unexpected can be easier if one does not have prior warning of weird it might be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Do you like to read program notes for a concert or other performance event? Do you find them useful in improving your enjoyment of the program? Or do you prefer, as I do, to let go of reading anything, and just deliberately get surprised by something completely new, without preconceptions or prior knowledge?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I Love Music but Rarely Listen to It Now</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/10/02/i-love-music-but-rarely-listen-to-it-now/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Oct 2011 17:15:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/10/02/i-love-music-but-rarely-listen-to-it-now/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Yesterday there was a concert, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.post-gazette.com/pg/11272/1178247-388.stm&#34;&gt;much-anticipated&lt;/a&gt;, part of the current season of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rbsp.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Renaissance &amp;amp; Baroque&lt;/a&gt;, that I didn&amp;rsquo;t attend. I felt slightly sad because I&amp;rsquo;m sure it was interesting, and also because fellow members of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.andrew.cmu.edu/user/lukas/pcars/Welcome.html&#34;&gt;local chapter&lt;/a&gt; of the American Recorder Society had been talking about going and urging me to come along.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.post-gazette.com/pg/images/201109/renbar0929_juilliard_baroqu_330.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Juilliard Baroque Ensemble&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This was not the only concert in the past couple of years that I have chosen not to attend. So why have I chosen to skip these opportunities?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once upon a time I listened to a lot of music. I listened to the radio, I bought a lot of LPs, cassette tapes, and finally, CDs. I went to concerts. It&amp;rsquo;s not as though I have completely lost interest in listening to music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What happened was simply that I ran out of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Time is &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.my168hours.com/&#34;&gt;limited to 168 hours a week&lt;/a&gt;. Therefore, the phrase &amp;ldquo;I don&amp;rsquo;t have time for X&amp;rdquo; is usually a euphemism for, &amp;ldquo;I do have time for Y and Z, but not for X&amp;rdquo;. Example translations of &amp;ldquo;don&amp;rsquo;t have time&amp;rdquo; language that people use:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;dl&gt;
  &lt;dt&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I don&#39;t have time to exercise.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;I chose to spend an hour watching sports on TV rather than playing a sport myself.&lt;/dd&gt;

  &lt;dt&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I don&#39;t have time to talk with my children.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;I do have time to work crazy hours at the office and play golf with my boss in order to make a lot of money.&lt;/dd&gt;

  &lt;dt&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I don&#39;t have time to cook.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;I don&#39;t like to cook or clean up, and therefore instead of whipping up a 15-minute stir-fry, I would rather commute to a restaurant, wait, order, wait, eat, wait, pay, wait, and return home hours later.&lt;/dd&gt;

  &lt;dt&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I don&#39;t have time to get good at salsa dancing.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
  &lt;dd&gt;I have time to spend hours going to clubs to dance, and prefer to spend vast amounts of time being social and having fun than perfecting my basic technique.&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;scarcity-and-decision-making&#34;&gt;Scarcity and decision making&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, time management is all a matter of &lt;em&gt;priorities&lt;/em&gt;. Time is a scarce resource. We &lt;em&gt;choose&lt;/em&gt; how to work within constraints of scarcity. (Note that some people like to make a lot of judgments about how we &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; be spending our time, but that is not the topic at hand; time management is.) In the end, I make my choices, and you make your choices. And we can and do change our choices over our lifetime, based on either our preferences or information about what is required to achieve various goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier in life, I was more of a spectator of life than I am now. I watched a lot of TV and movies, listened to a lot of music, went to concerts and lectures. It just happens that now, I prefer to be more &lt;em&gt;active&lt;/em&gt;. Not that listening to music is necessarily &lt;em&gt;passive&lt;/em&gt;: you can&amp;rsquo;t call it passive that I collected probably two dozen recordings of my favorite symphony, Beethoven&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Symphony_No._3_(Beethoven)&#34;&gt;Eroica&lt;/a&gt;, listened to them repeatedly, compared them, hummed along to them (I was not quite as obsessive as &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.grunin.com/eroica/&#34;&gt;Eric Grunin&lt;/a&gt;, however). But eventually I made a decision to more or less stop listening when I could be playing, and also to seek out what is new to me rather than continue with the old.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last night, instead of sitting in a concert hall listening to music, I stayed home, practiced &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/recorder/&#34;&gt;recorder&lt;/a&gt;, started reading some &lt;a href=&#34;blog/2011/09/30/free-to-the-people-since-1895/&#34;&gt;library books&lt;/a&gt;, and spent time with Abby. This is what I preferred to do with my evening hours yesterday instead of attending a concert. Life is good when you know your priorities, make your choices, act accordingly, and don&amp;rsquo;t go around in &lt;a href=&#34;http://psychcentral.com/blog/archives/2011/04/14/fomo-addiction-the-fear-of-missing-out/&#34;&gt;fear of missing out&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;postscript&#34;&gt;Postscript&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, now and then I still watch a movie or pull out a CD or attend a concert, and enjoy it. Just not so often.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And since the Eroica symphony is a permanent and profound part of my psyche, sometimes I find myself humming it to myself from memory. This tends to happen when it&amp;rsquo;s a nice sunny day and I&amp;rsquo;m on a run in the woods and feeling in a &amp;ldquo;heroic&amp;rdquo; mood. The music then fits perfectly because I will then run at a decent stride rate of &lt;a href=&#34;http://runningtimes.com/Article.aspx?ArticleID=11419&#34;&gt;180 steps per minute&lt;/a&gt;, corresponding exactly to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.marathonguide.com/training/coachmindy/everybreath.cfm&#34;&gt;breathing in a 3-3 rhythm&lt;/a&gt; and following Beethoven&amp;rsquo;s infamous (but I believe appropriate) metronome marking of 60 for the first movement! Great running music, 15 minutes of genius.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/variations/scores/adh1166/large/sco10001.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Beethoven&amp;#39;s Eroica, first page&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>