<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Irish Flute on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/irish-flute/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Irish Flute on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/irish-flute/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Third year at July 3 music party and finally participated in jamming</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/07/03/third-year-at-july-3-music-party-and-finally-participated-in-jamming/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jul 2014 22:11:59 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/07/03/third-year-at-july-3-music-party-and-finally-participated-in-jamming/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;The past two years, Abby and I have gone to an annual July 3 music potluck/party, and we went again this year. Both &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/03/petrified-at-a-music-jam-session-so-i-didnt-play-but-watched-and-listened/&#34;&gt;in 2012&lt;/a&gt; as well as &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/07/03/second-year-at-july-3-music-party-still-only-listening-without-playing/&#34;&gt;in 2013&lt;/a&gt;, I was too intimidated to participate in music jamming, and only watched. This year I was determined to contribute, and I brought my ukulele (which I only started learning &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/08/23/another-unexpected-life-change-one-month-of-learning-to-play-ukulele/&#34;&gt;a month after last year&amp;rsquo;s party&lt;/a&gt;, actually) and my Irish flute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;piano&#34;&gt;Piano&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After my first round of food at the potluck, I went to Susan&amp;rsquo;s piano and played David Raksin&amp;rsquo;s theme from &amp;ldquo;Laura&amp;rdquo;, which I had so botched up last month at the annual Pittsburgh Recorder Society potluck/recital. I play it much better now, although I somehow messed up the final chords today. There were a few people sitting around listening, and they wanted to hear more, but I didn&amp;rsquo;t have any more, so I scurried away to eat more food.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;old-time&#34;&gt;Old time&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As dinner started winding down, the old time musicians started gathering outside to play. I saw fiddles, banjos, and other instruments make an appearance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;blues&#34;&gt;Blues&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inside, the main guy who plays guitar and ukulele unpacked his soprano ukulele, and so I took out my concert ukulele, and two other guys with guitars appeared. Eventually a woman who sang also appeared, as well as a guy on fiddle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I felt very intimidated, because although I&amp;rsquo;ve gotten some experience jamming while on recorder or flute or tin whistle, my ukulele experience &lt;em&gt;without written music&lt;/em&gt; is still very minimal. Nevertheless, I joined in. I fumbled around, and had to ask what key each song was being played in, and even then, I&amp;rsquo;m still quite shaky in anticipating and knowing chord changes beyond the simplest I, IV, V, and some dominant and major 7th chords. I strummed very softly.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/music-2014-07-04/jamming.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Music jamming&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;They&amp;rsquo;re a great bunch, improvising melodic lines at will and even making up lyrics right on the spot, just as they had at the last two years when I only watched. And the singing in harmony was fantastic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby got a little bit of video footage of us at one point:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/zYb1aBioAao&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For two years, I was afraid to join in the music jams at this annual July 3 party. This year I joined in a little bit. If we attend the party again next year, I hope to be in a position to contribute even more! Many thanks to Susan for hosting this annual party!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Life: cooking, eating with friends, music jamming, dancing</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/03/29/life-cooking-eating-with-friends-music-jamming-dancing/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Mar 2014 23:38:31 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/03/29/life-cooking-eating-with-friends-music-jamming-dancing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Abby and I went to a French potluck dance party at Lisa&amp;rsquo;s, the first one we&amp;rsquo;ve attended together in &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/05/25/learning-the-congo-de-captieux-traditional-french-dance/&#34;&gt;ten months&lt;/a&gt; (although I went to one without Abby &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/09/14/back-to-french-dance-potluck-and-party/&#34;&gt;half a year ago&lt;/a&gt; when she was out of town).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a wonderful experience, one that we&amp;rsquo;ve missed for two months, since we have not gone out to a party with friends since Abby got a new job and we&amp;rsquo;ve had to adapt to that big change in our lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although we still had to leave early, I was reminded of what I really enjoy in life, deep down: nothing fancy, just getting together and having fun and being creative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;music-jamming&#34;&gt;Music jamming&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hadn&amp;rsquo;t done French music jamming in months, so when Abby and I arrived, and dinner was still being prepared, and John said &amp;ldquo;hey, let&amp;rsquo;s play&amp;rdquo;, I pulled out my flutes (both my standard Boehm flute and my wooden Irish flute) and went at it with him on melodeon. We hadn&amp;rsquo;t played together in half a year! Susan joined in at some point, also on melodeon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We played mazurka and Schottische and other music for about half an hour, from John&amp;rsquo;s memory, as I tried to follow along by ear. I realized how much I miss French music jamming. Lisa&amp;rsquo;s been hosting it again recently, but there have been schedule conflicts for me, but it looks like we&amp;rsquo;ll be getting on a schedule that works for me. I&amp;rsquo;m coming back!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I was taking a break, John played a multi-section hanter dro that Fabien and Lisa started dancing to, and I joined them in their line and picked it up. Again, something I hadn&amp;rsquo;t done in a while, and almost forgotten the unique pleasure of!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;potluck&#34;&gt;Potluck&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This seemed to me the biggest French potluck party yet, with almost twenty people present, I believe. We met some new people as well as old friends.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/french-potluck-2014-03-29/dinner.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;At dinner&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I baked a butternut squash to bring. I only very, very lightly seasoned it, to not detract from the natural flavor of the squash:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;butternut squash, sliced in half, placed in roasting pan&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;salt&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;pepper&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;cayenne pepper&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;butter&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;extra virgin olive oil&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;brown sugar&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/french-potluck-2014-03-29/squash.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Butternut squash&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Abby made a kale and mushroom dish:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/french-potluck-2014-03-29/kale.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Kale&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The other guests all brought a lot of great homemade food, and Lisa and Alex provided tasty and filling entrees and desserts. A fantastic meal!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/french-potluck-2014-03-29/food1.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Food&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/french-potluck-2014-03-29/food2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Food&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/french-potluck-2014-03-29/food3.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Food&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, there were &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/03/21/time-to-taste-the-world-thoughts-on-expanding-my-food-tastes-as-an-adult/&#34;&gt;Brussels sprouts, and I enjoyed them&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/french-potluck-2014-03-29/brussels-sprouts.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Brussels sprouts&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;cookies-and-other-desserts&#34;&gt;Cookies (and other desserts)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In accordance with &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/01/16/a-system-for-quitting-eating-cookies/&#34;&gt;my rule&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Music-themed cookies homemade from molds:

&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/french-potluck-2014-03-29/musical-cookies.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Musical cookies&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ate one, of a dancing couple:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/french-potluck-2014-03-29/dance-cookie.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A slice of yummy chocolatey thing:

&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/french-potluck-2014-03-29/chocolatey.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Chocolatey&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A slice of chocolate cake:

&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/french-potluck-2014-03-29/chocolate-cake.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Chocolate cake&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Unfortunately, I think I should have cut myself a smaller slice, instead of accepting a precut slice.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A tiny piece of a very rich, buttery thing:

&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/french-potluck-2014-03-29/another-dessert.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A non-homemade cookie from a box (I didn&amp;rsquo;t need to eat this):

&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/french-potluck-2014-03-29/box-cookie.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;dancing&#34;&gt;Dancing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After dinner, Lisa and Fabien started off the dancing portion of the evening, by re-teaching the &amp;ldquo;Congo de Captieux&amp;rdquo; set dance that Lisa and Lynn had taught &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/05/25/learning-the-congo-de-captieux-traditional-french-dance/&#34;&gt;ten months ago&lt;/a&gt;. It had been so long that Abby and I barely remembered it and were practically learning it from scratch again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of eventually got through it! I got sweaty again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After that, there was a break, and since it was already &amp;ldquo;late&amp;rdquo; (for Abby and me on our current schedule), we had to say goodbye, just as the &amp;ldquo;regular&amp;rdquo; French dance portion of the evening was about to begin (bourrées, waltzes, mazurkas, hanter dro, more music jamming, etc.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some photos of dancing that I took before we left early:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/french-potluck-2014-03-29/dancing1.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/french-potluck-2014-03-29/dancing2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/french-potluck-2014-03-29/dancing3.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a beautiful evening that filled my belly and soul. It&amp;rsquo;s been such a blessing to have been brought into this world of French traditional dance and music through the enthusiasm and generosity of Lisa &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/01/23/discovering-french-traditional-dance-in-pittsburgh/&#34;&gt;two years ago&lt;/a&gt; and many others. I feel like my life has been immeasurably enriched.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re in the Pittsburgh area and want to join in, we always welcome more dancers and musicians. (Or even if you&amp;rsquo;re not in the Pittsburgh area, as we&amp;rsquo;ve had visitors from further away.)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Finally doing some Latin music jamming on flute; also Irish and French</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/03/17/finally-doing-some-latin-music-jamming-on-flute/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Mar 2013 23:36:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/03/17/finally-doing-some-latin-music-jamming-on-flute/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;St. Patrick&amp;rsquo;s Day weekend means, of course, a party at Henry&amp;rsquo;s. Last year Abby and I even went to two of his St. Patrick&amp;rsquo;s Day parties! At the first, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/17/st-patricks-day-party-playing-tin-whistle-and-flute/&#34;&gt;I played tin whistle for the first time&lt;/a&gt;, and I played some easy recorder music &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/30/a-delayed-st-patricks-day-party-playing-tin-whistle-and-alto-recorder/&#34;&gt;at the second&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year, I reflected on how far I&amp;rsquo;ve come musically, and as usual, wanted to do something new and challenging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;irish-music&#34;&gt;Irish music&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I brought my tin whistle and Irish flute ready to jam. It turned out that Barbara had come with violin ready for some Irish jamming also. When she went at it with Henry on piano, she ended up playing &amp;ldquo;Danny Boy&amp;rdquo; (&amp;ldquo;Londonderry Air&amp;rdquo;) as one selection. Unfortunately, I had planned on playing it on flute, &amp;ldquo;redeeming&amp;rdquo; myself after being terrible on flute a year ago &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/17/st-patricks-day-party-playing-tin-whistle-and-flute/&#34;&gt;when I tried it&lt;/a&gt;, so since she had already done it, I quietly scrapped my original plan. No problem: there were many other things to play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Barbara joined me and Henry in some jigs, reels, and waltzes that I pulled out, some of which I did on tin whistle and some of which I did on Irish flute. That was fun, if pretty exhausting: lots and lots of notes, not so easy to just plain sight read. But of course, nobody has to play all the notes. That&amp;rsquo;s the beauty of this music. There never were official notes anyway; these are traditional tunes with a certain recognizable rhythm and shape and harmonic movement, but everyone does the notes differently anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;french-music&#34;&gt;French music&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d asked Vasili to learn on accordion &amp;ldquo;Les Ormeaux&amp;rdquo;, which I had learned just recently &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/02/25/stepping-it-up-at-the-french-and-blues-jam/&#34;&gt;at a French jam&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s not actually a traditional tune, but it&amp;rsquo;s a great one. Unfortunately, it turned out that Vasili had learned it in a different key from the one I was using on modern flute, so one of us (him) transposed on the fly to try to match, and the result therefore wasn&amp;rsquo;t as good as it could have been. Next time! Anyway, Abby and I jammed with Vasili on stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;latin-music&#34;&gt;Latin music&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;bolero&#34;&gt;Bolero&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The musical highlight for me was my debut in playing Latin, or more specifically, Cuban music. I fell in love with this music when I was &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/10/flute-loving-it-again/&#34;&gt;introduced to Latin ballroom dance back in 2000&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started off with an unnamed bolero from a World Music Cuba book I had first encountered &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/02/22/flute-progress-still-hanging-in-there/&#34;&gt;a year ago when I was just barely playing flute&lt;/a&gt;. I got on flute and Henry enthusiastically improvised along on piano and we took a couple of turns. That was great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I pulled out &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pbs.org/buenavista/music/songs/dos_gardenias.html&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Dos Gardenias&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, one of my favorite boleros of all time (and the bolero is one of my favorite musical genres). (By the way, I am working on being ready to sing this and other boleros before too long, making my debut as a bolero singer.) Again, more fun opportunities for inventiveness for Henry and me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;buena-vista-social-club&#34;&gt;Buena Vista Social Club&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, I first encountered &amp;ldquo;Dos Gardenias&amp;rdquo; through Ibrahim Ferrer of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Buena_Vista_Social_Club_%28album%29&#34;&gt;Buena Vista Social Club&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/5pKW7qvYSHU&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Buena Vista Social Club&amp;rdquo; was a very important music recording to me. At a time in my life around thirteen years ago when I was trying to explore Latin music and asked around for suggestions, my grad school classmate Andrej recommended this CD to me and my musical world was changed forever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;cha-cha&#34;&gt;Cha cha&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I pulled out an unnamed cha cha from the World Music Cuba book. We really went wild for this one, especially since Chad, one of Henry&amp;rsquo;s piano students (and a fine improviser) decided to join us and sat at the piano with Henry as both of them played with me and we kept going and going and I became very excited and inspired along with them. Wow. That was one of the most intense musical experiences I&amp;rsquo;ve ever had. It was frightening (didn&amp;rsquo;t know when I&amp;rsquo;d hit the limits of my technique or inventiveness) and exhilarating at the same time. When I was done, I was sweating from all the effort. Abby said she&amp;rsquo;d never seen me so animated before playing music, since she&amp;rsquo;s only ever seen me play Baroque and other such music mainly, or Irish and French. Well, Latin jazz is different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;chess&#34;&gt;Chess&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point in the evening, I needed a break from playing music and from socializing and decided to rest. However, it turned out that my &amp;ldquo;rest&amp;rdquo; consisted of relaxing in a chair while closing my eyes and&amp;hellip; &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/17/my-second-ever-blindfold-chess-game/&#34;&gt;playing blindfold chess&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2014-03-16&#34;&gt;(Update of 2014-03-16)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I couldn&amp;rsquo;t make it to Henry&amp;rsquo;s St. Patrick Day party in 2014. I felt sad about this, but our other plans made earlier made it impractical to try to attend.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My first blues music jam happened after the regular French music jam</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/01/28/my-first-blues-music-jam-happened-after-the-regular-french-music-jam/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jan 2013 23:26:28 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/01/28/my-first-blues-music-jam-happened-after-the-regular-french-music-jam/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s been over two months since the last French music jam, which was in November. I didn&amp;rsquo;t write about it because there was nothing particularly remarkable about it compared to the whole past year of French music jams: there was Lisa, John, Allison, a new fiddler Liz, and Leslie joining us on banjo again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tonight, an addition was made to the program. For some time I had suggested to Lisa that for French/blues dance night, maybe there should be a blues jam in addition to the French jam. She liked that idea, got hold of people she knew who were interested, and so tonight was the first blues jam!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was actually &lt;em&gt;my first full participation in a blues jam&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was very anxious, but I&amp;rsquo;ve grown somewhat used to feeling anxious at least once a month in the past two years pushing myself into unfamiliar territory repeatedly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, there were some changes for the French jam. Here&amp;rsquo;s how the evening went.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;french-jam&#34;&gt;French jam&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this new year of French music jamming, John, Lisa, and others have kicked things off by transcribing some of their favorite tunes by listening to recordings, watching YouTube, or from memory, in order to share so that we can learn and play them. John couldn&amp;rsquo;t make it tonight, ironically, because he was sick, but I was very exciting that we started exploring a lot of new tunes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I showed up, it was just Lisa on fiddle, Allison on piano (she also brought her button accordion), and me. Enough to get going. (I switched between Irish flute and modern flute as needed depending on the key.) Later, Donna also showed up, on fiddle, and Jess showed up, on clarinet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We played for quite some time, including old favorites we already knew, for the dancers, and learning some new tunes. I think we were at it for two hours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;blues-jam&#34;&gt;Blues jam&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As some of the French dance crowd went home and the blues dance crowd came in, the blues jam began. There was Anders on piano, whom I recognized from his having played blues indoors at a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/03/petrified-at-a-music-jam-session-so-i-didnt-play-but-watched-and-listened/&#34;&gt;summer party&lt;/a&gt;; I may have seen him elsewhere also at &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/10/07/my-first-contra-dance-workshop-unexpected-fun./&#34;&gt;contra dance&lt;/a&gt; or something. I met Michael and Billy, who both had guitars and harmonicas. And all three of them were apparently willing to sing!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was really intimidated. I&amp;rsquo;m still totally, utterly a novice at blues, although I started working on that last year. I wasn&amp;rsquo;t even sure whether I shouldn&amp;rsquo;t pack up my flute and go home. After all, I&amp;rsquo;d already spent a lot of time on music this evening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But something happened that made me stay! Allison seemed like she was about to pack up too, but was curious, and stayed. No longer on piano, she was on her button accordion. We both confessed to never having done this before, but stayed on. I thought she was doing quite well. I wasn&amp;rsquo;t doing so well, but I participated in bits. (But no, I did not sing.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for playing for dancers, I think the dancers were sometimes confused by the experiment, because they didn&amp;rsquo;t have their usual iTunes playlist to dance to. Not everything we did was really suitable to the dancing they wanted to do. We&amp;rsquo;ll have to eventually figure out what works for the dancers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically, when it came to my first blues jam experience, I felt sort of the way I did when I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/05/14/playing-french-music-for-first-time-and-dancing-blues-for-first-time/&#34;&gt;first got into playing French music eight months ago&lt;/a&gt;: anxious, uncertain, embarrassed. But if I work at this and get more comfortable and better, the feeling will pass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d like to do more blues jamming. There is a bit of a problem in that this has made for a very long and late evening. I think that&amp;rsquo;s just the nature of the blues music/dance world. I&amp;rsquo;ll have to plan my schedule accordingly if I want to integrate a regular blues jam into my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And of course, I should continue my studies of the blues.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pittsburgh Contras and Squares Holiday Ball 2012</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/12/14/pittsburgh-contras-and-squares-holiday-ball-2012/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Dec 2012 23:50:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/12/14/pittsburgh-contras-and-squares-holiday-ball-2012/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/holiday-ball-2012/grand-march.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Grand March&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So this year I joined Abby again to play in the &amp;ldquo;Holiday Ball Orchestra&amp;rdquo; as I had &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/16/playing-recorder-and-flute-at-the-holiday-ball/&#34;&gt;done for the first time last year&lt;/a&gt;, for the annual &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/pages/Pittsburgh-Holiday-Ball/283731778337030&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Contras and Squares Holiday Ball&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My experience at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/events/383908395031216/&#34;&gt;this year&amp;rsquo;s event&lt;/a&gt; compared to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/events/308706299154491/&#34;&gt;last year&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/a&gt;, and thoughts about the future:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;preparation&#34;&gt;Preparation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, I was much more &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/11/24/preparing-to-play-irish-flute-in-the-holiday-ball/&#34;&gt;prepared&lt;/a&gt; this second time than the first time. Not only have I been playing any music at all for an entire extra year, but also, I had prior knowledge of and access to most of the music that is played every year, so I could start my practice well before the event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;costumes&#34;&gt;Costumes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby wanted me to dress up again. Since people enjoyed my wearing red pants last year, I wore them again this year. I was tired of the whole green thing, however, and so I wore a pink shirt and red vest to go all out on the red theme. I added a sport jacket also, one that had been too big for me my whole life till now; it turns out that my blazer that I wore last year is too small now, as my chest has noticeably expanded in the past year (probably because of weight lifting, posture changes, and playing wind instruments). I added a beret that I&amp;rsquo;d never worn before.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/holiday-ball-2012/franklin.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Abby came up with her own colorful outfit.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/holiday-ball-2012/abby-octave-mandolin.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;venue&#34;&gt;Venue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was afraid that Swisshelm Park Community Center would be super cold again like last year, but I did bring my Handeze fingerless gloves just in case. It turned out that the place was warm (it&amp;rsquo;s been a very warm &amp;ldquo;winter&amp;rdquo;), and so I did not have any problems feeling cold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;on-stage&#34;&gt;On stage&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year I think there were somewhat fewer musicians in the Holiday Ball Orchestra than last year. I thought this was actually a good thing. Last year there were some real problems with space and also with ensemble balance (there were a whole lot of violins last year, for example).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;instruments&#34;&gt;Instruments&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I brought my modern flute, wooden keyless Irish flute, and tin whistle. Last year I had played primarily recorder, but this year I chose not to play recorder at all: the Irish flute was what I wanted to use as much as possible for this music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also brought my melodica! I had practiced playing the Hallelujah Chorus part of the Grand March using it and was excited to make my melodica debut. I also planned to use it in some of the Christmas songs, such as &amp;ldquo;Frosty the Snowman&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby brought an &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Octave_mandolin&#34;&gt;octave mandolin&lt;/a&gt; she had been borrowing. She started playing mandolin just this year, and octave mandolin just in the past couple of weeks, I think. This instrument is so much better suited to the music, she says, than her tamburitza she played last year.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/holiday-ball-2012/instruments.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Our instruments&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Several &amp;ldquo;kazumpets&amp;rdquo; (kazoo trumpets) were also provided by Lynette and Jim, and passed out to whoever wanted to play them during certain songs. Abby took one.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/holiday-ball-2012/abby-kazumpet.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby with kazumpet&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;dancing&#34;&gt;Dancing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since Abby and I have now actually done some &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/10/07/my-first-contra-dance-workshop-unexpected-fun/&#34;&gt;contra dancing together&lt;/a&gt;, there was a question of whether we would do any dancing. Abby and I discussed this before the event; Abby was very excited to play music on octave mandolin, and so she did not want to dance, so we did no dancing. Like I said last year: &amp;ldquo;We can always dance some other time.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the other musicians were very excited about dancing and pre-arranged to spend one half or the other of the time dancing instead of playing music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I saw a lot of familiar faces among the dancers, thanks to having met some of them when doing French and contra dances at CMU, and others I met from non-dance contexts elsewhere in the past year in Pittsburgh. It was nice to see my friend Henry and his girlfriend Gina at the dance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;off-and-running&#34;&gt;Off and running&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marlin was the caller again as usual and the evening proceeded with the Grand March and then the whole big assortment of jigs, reels, waltzes, Christmas songs, and a couple of interesting new pieces for this year.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/holiday-ball-2012/grand-march.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Grand March&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t have additional interesting photos or videos to share from during the event, because I took none: after the initial Grand March, I was entirely focused just on playing music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;overall-experience&#34;&gt;Overall experience&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was far less nervous than I was last year. Also, I positioned myself near, rather than deliberately far away from, a microphone, in order to be more audible. I don&amp;rsquo;t actually know what I sounded like, but some dancers during intermission commented that they liked the sound of the wooden Irish flute, so I guess it must have been audible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Playing music for hours is tiring, especially when it is so fast and there are so many notes. Of course, nobody is required to play all the notes all the time. I picked and chose when to take breaks, typically alternating repeats or entire sections. And there is definitely a limit to how long I can play flutes before my mouth gives up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the second half, a guy who had danced during the first half played a keyed Irish flute and tin whistle with us. I hadn&amp;rsquo;t seen him at the two of three rehearsals I had attended, so I hadn&amp;rsquo;t known someone else would be playing those instruments. As a result, I changed some things up in the second half, by playing the tin whistle sometimes when he was playing the flute, and vice versa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did play the melodica as planned, but noticed that the intonation was poor in the lower notes, so I backed off. I&amp;rsquo;ll have to fix this problem before I do more melodica playing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I chose not to force myself to &amp;ldquo;achieve&amp;rdquo; some of the &amp;ldquo;goals&amp;rdquo; I set last year, which were to do some solos and nontrivial ornamentation/improvisation. I felt that because of the natural of my musical focus all this year, I hadn&amp;rsquo;t had time to devote to getting good enough to really justify taking the spotlight for some tunes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The music is still crazy fast: I am still not able to play everything quite properly at the appropriate tempo. Frustrating, but that&amp;rsquo;s OK. I expect to continue to improve my technique; I&amp;rsquo;m already so much better than I was last year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I very much enjoyed performing for the Holiday Ball this year. And I feel like the Holiday Ball Orchestra sounded better this year than we did last year, and some dancers remarked on this also. I think there are several reasons for this. One is that we had some people coming back for the second time (like me), much improved. Another is that there were slightly fewer people, which I think creates a tighter ensemble.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;goals-for-the-future&#34;&gt;Goals for the future&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right now, I&amp;rsquo;m just totally exhausted and happy to be done with music performance of any kind this year. It&amp;rsquo;s been a very tough week, a very tough month, and a very tough two months in my life, with all the things that piled up on me since the end of October.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because December always ends up being so frantic for me, for next year I need to better plan what activities I pursue during this time of year. Last year, I was totally set on playing again this year in the Holiday Ball. Now, I am not sure whether I will continue for next year. It&amp;rsquo;s a question of priorities, and I need to plan what I will be doing next year in December. If I do it again next year, then clearly I want to be doing some solos!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;thank-yous&#34;&gt;Thank yous&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, I have to thank Lynette for organizing the music scores and putting it into booklets for everyone. Jim made the kazumpets. Donna, Allison, and Maro led the rehearsals as well as conducted and played their instruments with enthusiasm; I&amp;rsquo;ve been really happy to have met them a year ago, because I&amp;rsquo;ve been encountering them in other musical contexts in Pittsburgh in the past year too!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We play for the dancers, and so I really appreciate it when they take note of our playing and respond to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And none of this would happened without Abby, who got me into the whole scene in the first place. I&amp;rsquo;ve met so many musicians and dancers, and tried out different instruments and musical styles and dances in the past year, thanks to Abby!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Oblivion obsession: time to start playing melodica!</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/12/02/oblivion-obsession-time-to-start-playing-melodica/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Dec 2012 21:32:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/12/02/oblivion-obsession-time-to-start-playing-melodica/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have been obsessed for some time with Piazzolla&amp;rsquo;s beautiful tango piece &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.astor-piazzolla.org/astor-piazzolla-oblivion/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Oblivion&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. I was planning to perform it some time on flute, but today, by accident, I decided that I want to play it on my &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.grothmusic.com/p-4654-hohner-s32-student-32-key-melodica.aspx&#34;&gt;melodica&lt;/a&gt; instead!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/hohner-student-32-melodica.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Hohner Student 32 Melodica&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-melodica-came-into-the-picture&#34;&gt;How melodica came into the picture&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This afternoon was the first rehearsal of the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/11/24/preparing-to-play-irish-flute-in-the-holiday-ball/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Holiday Ball Orchestra&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. (Today was also round 4 of the Pittsburgh Chess League team matches, but as I did once before for round 1, I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/16/excited-by-the-new-season-of-the-pittsburgh-recorder-society/&#34;&gt;prioritized music over chess&lt;/a&gt; and told the team I could not play.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the rehearsal, I played both flute and Irish flute, depending on the key. Afterward, while socializing, I happened to ask about the ukuleles that some people had. I mentioned that I still hadn&amp;rsquo;t gotten around to learning ukulele, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/11/learning-another-instrument-the-tin-whistle/&#34;&gt;despite having intended to&lt;/a&gt; and bought a soprano a long while back. I just found it very hard to get started with my first string instrument, and other things came up. I joked about the other instruments I have that I don&amp;rsquo;t play, including my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/01/run-shadyside-5k-outrunning-mickey-mouse-and-lending-a-trumpet/&#34;&gt;melodica&lt;/a&gt;. Lynette said in all seriousness that I was welcome to play it at the Holiday Ball.
So after I got home, I pulled out the melodica.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-is-the-melodica-good-for&#34;&gt;What is the melodica good for?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that I don&amp;rsquo;t think the melodica works well at all for the Holiday Ball music, actually. The instrument is not best at fast runs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;But&lt;/strong&gt;, since I had the instrument out: I decided to try playing it &lt;em&gt;in place of flute&lt;/em&gt; for some music I&amp;rsquo;ve been working on, such as tango and bossa nova. And I discovered that &lt;em&gt;melodica works great&lt;/em&gt; for these kinds of music! Then one thing led to another, and I was searching for covers of various songs on melodica on YouTube, and found quite a lot of cool performances by people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So now I&amp;rsquo;m completely serious about preparing to use my melodica in actual musical performances. Frankly, a lot of music I&amp;rsquo;ve been playing on flute sounds better with a darker, reeded instrument such as the melodica. For example, I&amp;rsquo;ve been playing jazzy bossa nova that I think really works best with a saxophone, but I don&amp;rsquo;t (yet!) play saxophone. The melodica works well as a substitute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In tango, of course, a bandoneón is the traditional instrument, and accordions are commonly used instead. Here, again, the melodica is great, for the melody line anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, other music that involves accordions or harmonicas work great with melodica as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;piazzolla-s-oblivion&#34;&gt;Piazzolla&amp;rsquo;s Oblivion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I am confessedly obsessed with &amp;ldquo;Oblivion&amp;rdquo;, here are some performances I found moving or otherwise useful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;flute-guitar&#34;&gt;Flute/guitar&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s Cavatina Duo on flute and guitar:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/sZD7aGqmO6w&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;melodica-with-chamber-group&#34;&gt;Melodica with chamber group&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is someone playing melodica:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/fG0TcCFUrBQ&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;melodica-and-piano-discovered-2013-08-22&#34;&gt;Melodica and piano (discovered 2013-08-22)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Japanese duo:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/AAP4GB8T8DI&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;accordion&#34;&gt;Accordion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s my friend Henry playing his solo arrangement for accordion:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/FrOHDEMOhkc&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;bandoneón-and-piano&#34;&gt;Bandoneón and piano&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Julian Rowlands and Ivo de Greef:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/sj-JUBIGKnE&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;violin-and-orchestra&#34;&gt;Violin and orchestra&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vesko Eschkenazy:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/kP6Vgm4k4xc&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;voice&#34;&gt;Voice&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wow. Wow. Milva singing French lyrics, Piazzolla himself on bandoneón!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/lzC1kKZGxBg&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;recorder-quartet-discovered-2013-08-22&#34;&gt;Recorder quartet (discovered 2013-08-22)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Japanese recorder quartet, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.geocities.jp/sekishirecorderquartet/english.htm&#34;&gt;Sekishi Recorder Quartet&lt;/a&gt;. Very nice!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/3PmaOyZNWo8&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;tango-dancers&#34;&gt;Tango dancers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, here are Daniela Pucci and Luis Bianchi dancing to the piece:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/RdU3eORpNhY&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, here is Daniela Pucci explaining why she gave up her MIT academic faculty career for tango:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/7BbAt1gnkBE&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are a tango fan, make sure to read Daniel Pucci&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.thedelicatestrength.com/?p=1522&#34;&gt;great article on tango dance connection&lt;/a&gt;. It is consonant with my own dance philosophy as well as music philosophy!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By accident, I have rediscovered the melodica, and now intend to work on it as a serious melodic instrument!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2014-10-23&#34;&gt;(Update of 2014-10-23)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/09/13/finally-playing-piazzollas-oblivion-on-flute/&#34;&gt;I put up more videos&lt;/a&gt; I found of &amp;ldquo;Oblivion&amp;rdquo; while thinking back to 2013 when I did play it on flute after all.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Preparing to play Irish flute in the Holiday Ball</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/11/24/preparing-to-play-irish-flute-in-the-holiday-ball/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Nov 2012 20:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/11/24/preparing-to-play-irish-flute-in-the-holiday-ball/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://pittsburghcontra.org/wp-content/uploads/2011/12/contra_header21.png&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Pittsburgh Contras and Squares&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A very important event for me last year was joining Abby in playing music at the annual &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburghcontra.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Contras and Squares&lt;/a&gt; Holiday Ball at the Swisshelm Park Community Center as part of the &amp;ldquo;Holiday Ball Orchestra&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today I started to prepare to play music for the Holiday Ball (Friday, December 14) again: I have three weeks to practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What progress have I made in the past year on the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/16/playing-recorder-and-flute-at-the-holiday-ball/&#34;&gt;goals I listed after last year&amp;rsquo;s event&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;improvement-at-instruments&#34;&gt;Improvement at instruments&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, I wrote: &amp;ldquo;I want to be much better at all the instruments I would play in it (recorder, flute, tin whistle)&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My status this year:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m better at &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/recorder/&#34;&gt;recorder&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m much better at &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/flute/&#34;&gt;flute&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve only barely worked on &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/tin-whistle/&#34;&gt;tin whistle&lt;/a&gt;, but am automatically better at it because of getting better at other instruments.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I unexpectedly got an &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/irish-flute/&#34;&gt;Irish flute&lt;/a&gt;, which I have mostly been playing for &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/french-dance/&#34;&gt;French dance&lt;/a&gt;, but which &lt;strong&gt;I intend to be my main instrument for the Holiday Ball&lt;/strong&gt;!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From a sound and style point of view, the Irish flute is clearly the best of my instruments to use for the Holiday Ball. So I read through my copies of the Holiday Ball music (lots of jigs, reels, waltzes) tonight at speed, to see where I stand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, I could play (on any instrument) barely any of the music at speed, even on my best instrument at the time, which was soprano recorder. I was reduced to sitting out some tunes or playing just a single note each measure, when I otherwise would have been unable to continue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, I found that I could get through most of the selections OK at speed, but somewhat sloppily and inaccurately. I would &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; be happy to have to perform this music at speed tonight; I would rather sit out or simplify rather than try to play something beyond me. But I have three weeks to improve significantly, and I believe I can improve enough that when the time comes, I won&amp;rsquo;t be sitting out most of the tunes the way I kind of did last year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the fingering of the tin whistle is the same as for my keyless Irish flute, I can also choose to use the tin whistle where I feel appropriate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;microphone&#34;&gt;Microphone&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, I wrote: &amp;ldquo;I want to be proficient and confident enough to sit by a microphone&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea of being in the foreground is still a bit daunting to me, but I think after I get in some good practice over the next week or so, I&amp;rsquo;ll feel confident about not just being in the background the way I was last year. I do think it would be nice to have an audible Irish flute in our performance for the dancers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;solos&#34;&gt;Solos&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, I wrote: &amp;ldquo;I want to do some solos, with stylistically appropriate improvisations&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even scarier. I&amp;rsquo;ve been working through &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/_posts/2012/06/12/ordered-the-casey-burns-small-handed-irish-flute/&#34;&gt;Grey Larsen&amp;rsquo;s book&lt;/a&gt;, which is amazingly detailed and good, but as Irish music has &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; at all been my focus during this year of music for me, I&amp;rsquo;m nowhere at the level of passing for a traditional Irish musician. Still, there is time to work up a sound basic practical level of ornamentation, I think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll have to evaluate, after a week or two, what I feel comfortable doing on stage. The basic rule is: better to play an melody simply and beautifully, unornamented, rather than do something badly and in poor taste and technique!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;dance&#34;&gt;Dance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, I wrote: &amp;ldquo;Maybe I should learn some of the dances and perform some too&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that in fact, I did learn some &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/10/07/my-first-contra-dance-workshop-unexpected-fun/&#34;&gt;contra dance&lt;/a&gt;, so depending on how Abby would like to split up playing music and dancing, I would be, unlike last year, totally up for participating as a dancer as well as a musician.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a lot of fun playing music at the Holiday Ball last year and hope to enjoy it again, and this time with a higher level of musicality and a higher level of contribution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re in the Pittsburgh area and like contra dancing, make sure to put Friday, December 14 on your calendar already, and come to the Holiday Ball!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Singing an Irish ballad as an Asian pirate at a Halloween belly dance Hafla</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/10/27/singing-an-irish-ballad-as-an-asian-pirate-at-a-halloween-belly-dance-hafla/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Oct 2012 23:02:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/10/27/singing-an-irish-ballad-as-an-asian-pirate-at-a-halloween-belly-dance-hafla/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/khafif-hafla-2012/franklin-flute.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin as pirate playing Irish flute&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Tonight, I dressed as an Asian pirate and sang an Irish pirate ballad on stage at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.khafif.com/&#34;&gt;Khafif&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/events/269693989803391/&#34;&gt;annual Halloween belly dance hafla&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/khafif-hafla-2012/group-photo.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Group photo&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Three days ago, I would not have guessed I would be playing this small role in the hafla!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;last-year&#34;&gt;Last year&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I had gone to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/events/211476745586621/&#34;&gt;last year&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/a&gt; instance of Khafif&amp;rsquo;s annual Halloween &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.urbandictionary.com/define.php?term=hafla&#34;&gt;hafla&lt;/a&gt; for the first time, and there was a lot of belly dancing, live music, and food. At the time, I was just a spectator, and hadn&amp;rsquo;t even gone in a costume (the announced theme was &amp;ldquo;video games&amp;rdquo;). I have to confess that it is usually very difficult to convince me to put on a costume for an event, because I don&amp;rsquo;t like standing out and I like dressing comfortably.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;this-year-s-call-for-performers&#34;&gt;This year&amp;rsquo;s call for performers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year, the theme was &amp;ldquo;pirates&amp;rdquo;. Abby and I were going again, since she plays music at these haflas as a member of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/pages/Balkan-Babes/147472071948959&#34;&gt;Balkan Babes&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three months ago, Jenn, one of the organizers, issued on Facebook a call for performers, both dancers and musicians.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I originally had no particular plan to go in costume, or to play some music at the hafla, but I just happened to notice a guy post:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Well, I&#39;m a folk singer, specializing in Irish and Scottish songs. I can&#39;t think of anything &#34;pirate&#34; in the playlist at the moment, but I&#39;ve got a number of nautical themed pieces.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I had become sufficiently interested in Irish music in the past months that I had &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/06/12/ordered-the-casey-burns-small-handed-irish-flute/&#34;&gt;ordered an Irish flute&lt;/a&gt; and expected delivery at any moment, I immediately replied to the guy:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
I like playing Irish whistle and flute music; maybe we can come up with some pirate theme together?
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;three-days-ago&#34;&gt;Three days ago&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was never any resumption of discussion of the Irish music idea, so I didn&amp;rsquo;t follow up, since &lt;em&gt;it never occurred to me&lt;/em&gt; to want to come up with some kind of solo performance of something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then this Wednesday, three days ago, I got a message from Jenn:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
I was wondering if you guys were still wanting to play a song or two for us this weekend for the Halloween Hafla? You are more than welcome. Let us know and if so, do you guys know any piratey music. It&#39;s been awhile since we last communicated and things might have changed since late July.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;research-and-preparation&#34;&gt;Research and preparation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided to see if I could quickly find a suitable &amp;ldquo;Irish pirate&amp;rdquo; song in order to learn it and get other people to perform it with me, with my playing it on Irish flute (an instrument I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/30/got-my-new-casey-burns-small-handed-irish-flute/&#34;&gt;did receive in the summer&lt;/a&gt; and have been playing, ironically, mainly for &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/10/15/french-music-jam-with-unexpected-new-musicians/&#34;&gt;French music&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;irish-pirate-ballads&#34;&gt;Irish pirate ballads&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Out of sheer luck, the very top Google hit for &amp;ldquo;Irish pirate music&amp;rdquo; turned up a CD called &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.folkways.si.edu/dan-milner-guest-artists/irish-pirate-ballads-and-other-songs-of-the-sea/celtic/music/album/smithsonian&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Irish pirate ballads&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, and also out of sheer luck, I found that the Carnegie Library had a copy of this CD.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The very next day, Thursday, I picked up the CD from the library. I listened to it and identified a song that I liked that really was about an authentic Irish pirate, and decided that I would learn it and perform it on Irish flute. The song was &amp;ldquo;The Ballad of O&amp;rsquo;Bruadair&amp;rdquo;, also known as &amp;ldquo;Out on the Ocean&amp;rdquo;. It is apparently about Micheal O&amp;rsquo;Bruadair, a 17th century pirate and smuggler, who of course eventually was hanged for his crimes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I responded to Jenn saying that I had found a song, and I asked around whether anyone wanted to accompany me or sing along. I got no response, but figured someone would turn up. I printed out ten copies of the lyrics, which can be found &lt;a href=&#34;http://mudcat.org/thread.cfm?threadid=124787&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, with the idea that at worst, I would pass these out and ask for audience participation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The melody was pretty simple, and I played it several times on my flute to get it down, and also watched a performance of the song on YouTube:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/093nkli_98A&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I was very pressed for time before the weekend, I didn&amp;rsquo;t bother to write down the melody in music notation; I thought I had it pretty well memorized. I considered writing it down &amp;ldquo;just in case&amp;rdquo;, but never got around to it, despite a note to myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;pirate-costume&#34;&gt;Pirate costume&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/khafif-hafla-2012/franklin-abby.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin and Abby&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, having decided to perform music at the hafla, I decided that I had to wear a costume also. There was no way I was going to show up without a costume this year, given that I was going to be on stage. After throwing around some ideas, I decided that since I have a karate gi, I was going to wear it, and throw on a red belt and a red bandanna, and call myself an Asian pirate. Abby gave me a chain to wear around my neck also.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;at-the-hafla&#34;&gt;At the hafla&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The program:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/khafif-hafla-2012/program.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Program&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The event began with several nice belly dance performances. (I expect photos and videos to pop up on the event site eventually.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;after-intermission&#34;&gt;After intermission&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was supposed to play right after intermission. I had already walked around passing out copies of the lyrics of the song.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Unfortunately, my mind went totally blank as I headed backstage; I had totally forgotten the melody of the song, and had no sheet music to fall back on.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the Balkan Babes got on stage instead while I tried to retrieve the melody by using my smartphone to look up the YouTube performance I had viewed at home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are the Balkan Babes in action, a photo I took backstage after I had figured out my song (Abby is on the right):&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/khafif-hafla-2012/balkan-babes.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Balkan Babes after intermission&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Luckily, I was able to get the melody back into my head with the aid of my smartphone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;my-turn&#34;&gt;My turn&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since nobody was accompanying me, my idea was to get the audience to help out by singing while I played the flute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided to start singing the song myself, to get into &amp;ldquo;pirate&amp;rdquo; character and to encourage people to sing with me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It turns out that this is the first time in my entire life I have sung alone on stage.&lt;/strong&gt; I hadn&amp;rsquo;t originally planned this. In fact, I had never even sung this song at home when I was learning it; my whole plan had been to sing it only if someone else was singing it with me, and I was hoping to do a little bit of singing with someone and then being free to improvise on the flute for a while before ending.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some people did eventually join in a little bit, which was cool, but when I stopped after two verses (of the four in total) to pick up my flute, people thought the song was over or something, and did not continue clapping, stomping their feet, and singing. This was an awkward moment. I decided to just launch into playing the flute, but was too flustered by the context switch, too overloaded with anxiety, to come up with the fancy improvisation that I had intended, and don&amp;rsquo;t even remember exactly what I did, except I did finish up at the end of a verse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I survived!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apparently Abby was backstage and got a short video clip of me onto my smartphone I had left behind:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/BPhyCauHmx0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-rest-of-the-hafla&#34;&gt;The rest of the hafla&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a lot more creative belly dancing for the rest of the evening, and then the Balkan Babes singing and playing music after the belly dancing was done. Lots of food to continue to eat. It was a fun event; it&amp;rsquo;s always especially nice to see little kids out there dancing too while watching their mothers perform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m grateful to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.khafif.com/&#34;&gt;Khafif&lt;/a&gt; for organizing this spectacular Halloween show every year, and grateful to Jenn for reminding me that in July I had thought of playing some music, and for including me on the program at the last minute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I played just a really tiny role in the hafla, but it was nevertheless a big deal to me. As for all the unplanned mishaps that occurred, well, I&amp;rsquo;ve learned this year that something unexpected always seems to happen no matter what, and although we can learn from experience (I will never forget a backup plan of a printed score again), the important thing is to just keep going, whatever has just gone &amp;ldquo;wrong&amp;rdquo;. The audience doesn&amp;rsquo;t need to know any of that; all they see is what you make the best effort of doing in the moment.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>French music jam with unexpected new musicians</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/10/15/french-music-jam-with-unexpected-new-musicians/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Oct 2012 23:45:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/10/15/french-music-jam-with-unexpected-new-musicians/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Tonight was my fourth participation in &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/28/another-french-music-jam-also-announcing-cats-dance/&#34;&gt;Lisa&amp;rsquo;s French traditional dance music jam&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The evening started quietly, because only Lisa and John and I were present at first, and nobody else. Apparently people were either in classes or had other engagements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We always love having more people join us in making music, so it was great that unexpectedly, we got two people into playing with us before I had to leave after two hours! So where did they come from?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;three-of-us&#34;&gt;Three of us&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it was just the three of us, Lisa and John played over some new tunes they had worked on earlier, so that I could pick them up. I&amp;rsquo;m much better now at learning music by ear. I&amp;rsquo;m still not very fast at picking up tunes, but I&amp;rsquo;m definitely better. Furthermore, although they had scribbled down some scores on paper to keep track of the different new songs, I found the handwritten attempts sufficiently difficult to decipher that I chose to completely ignore them. This is a new attitude for me: in the past, I would have scrambled to get a written score if possible. Now, I&amp;rsquo;ve grown used to doing without, and not worrying about making mistakes or learning more slowly than if I had a score. It took me &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/05/14/playing-french-music-for-first-time-and-dancing-blues-for-first-time/&#34;&gt;five months&lt;/a&gt; to reach this point of relative comfort with uncertainty, confusion, and imperfection, ha!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;dancers&#34;&gt;Dancers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Very few dancers showed up at all during the evening. As a result, the ones that did show up expecting to dance started watching us continue to play music instead. But then John started saying, &amp;ldquo;Hey, grab an instrument and join us!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Someone I hadn&amp;rsquo;t met before, Georgia, had started learning some chords on mandolin recently, and she got sucked into joining us as John handed her his mandolin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later, Leslie arrived. She regularly attends to dance. Since there were hardly any dancers around, we said, hey, want to play? John pointed to two banjo cases he had on the floor, so she went and tried one banjo and then switched to the other, and the next thing we knew, we were all playing together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Georgia and Leslie do play other musical instruments and sing, but they just happen not to &amp;ldquo;really&amp;rdquo; play mandolin or banjo. I thought it was pretty cool that the unfortunate lack of dancers led to their unexpectedly joining us as musicians. I guess we&amp;rsquo;ll see whether they start playing more with us!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The small number of musicians and dancers might have made the evening less interesting than past sessions, but it was great that we spontaneously added to our musical group for the evening.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Another French music jam; also, announcing CATS Dance</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/09/28/another-french-music-jam-also-announcing-cats-dance/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Sep 2012 20:55:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/09/28/another-french-music-jam-also-announcing-cats-dance/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://thebridge.cmu.edu/images/W170xL170/0/noshadow/Organization/603b06cbdc7847018dce159a5ed99543.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;CATS Dance photo&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;On Monday I participated for my third time in Lisa&amp;rsquo;s French traditional dance music jam.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/08/27/my-second-french-music-jam-playing-my-irish-flute-in-public-for-the-first-time/&#34;&gt;Last time&lt;/a&gt;, I started playing my &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/irish-flute/&#34;&gt;Irish flute&lt;/a&gt; at the jam, continued playing my &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/baroque-flute/&#34;&gt;Baroque flute&lt;/a&gt;, and left my modern flute at home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This time, I changed things up. Also, we got a new musician playing a new instrument!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;instruments-and-musicians&#34;&gt;Instruments and musicians&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lisa was on fiddle as usual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we had John, who brought and used various kinds of accordions and his mandolin. (He had also brought recorders, in case I wanted to play with him, but I did not bring my recorders.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Allison was on piano.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Donna was on fiddle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most exciting to me was that Cindy came and played &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Autoharp&#34;&gt;autoharp&lt;/a&gt;. I think the addition of the harmonic accompaniment and countermelodies she provided was really nice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-instruments&#34;&gt;My instruments&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; bring my Baroque flute this time. I made a decision this week that I was no longer going to try to play my Baroque flute in most public situations. I have been frustrated that its soft sound gets drowned out by other instruments and just by people talking and socializing at parties. Therefore, when playing the Baroque flute in public, I will reserve it for very quiet performance situations only.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did bring my Irish flute, which served well when we were playing in appropriate keys.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have begun caving in and bringing my modern flute. It can be played more easily in all kinds of keys, and has the power to actually be heard. Maybe one day I&amp;rsquo;ll have a keyed wooden flute to play traditional music on, but that day is not near at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So after some experimentation, I believe I&amp;rsquo;m come to the right instrument(s) for different situations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;carnegie-alliance-of-traditional-and-social-dance-cats-dance&#34;&gt;Carnegie Alliance of Traditional and Social Dance (CATS Dance)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d like to take this opportunity to promote the new CMU-based dance group, the &lt;a href=&#34;http://thebridge.cmu.edu/organization/catsdance&#34;&gt;Carnegie Alliance of Traditional and Social Dance&lt;/a&gt;. Check out also their &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/catsdancepgh&#34;&gt;Facebook page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This group has been formed in order to grow a local community of people interested in all kinds of traditional and social dance, French dance being just one example; contra dancing and other folk dancing are also being explored.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In particular, this group exists because there is increasing interest among young people in these kinds of dances and music. The Pittsburgh dance scene has sometimes been dominated by older people, and it&amp;rsquo;s good to get younger people involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last week CATS Dance organized an outing to the regular &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburghcontra.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Contras and Squares&lt;/a&gt; Friday dance. Tomorrow there will be a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/events/105195582969170/&#34;&gt;French dance workshop and social dance&lt;/a&gt; held directly on CMU campus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These workshops and dances are, of course, open to everyone, not just CMU students. Abby and I are not CMU students, but &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/01/23/discovering-french-traditional-dance-in-pittsburgh/&#34;&gt;started attending&lt;/a&gt; these workshops at CMU in January. All ages and levels of dancers are always welcome! If you&amp;rsquo;re curious, drop by and check it out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first contra dance workshop to be hosted at CMU has also already been scheduled, for Sunday, October 7. Since I&amp;rsquo;ve never been to a contra dance workshop (although I had a sampling of contra dance at a birthday party &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/31/my-first-sampling-of-english-country-dance-and-contra-dance&#34;&gt;six months ago&lt;/a&gt;; I was very confused by it then), I hope Abby and I will make it to this workshop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2012-10-07&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-10-07)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/10/07/my-first-contra-dance-workshop-unexpected-fun/&#34;&gt;Abby and I did make it to the contra dance workshop&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I continue to greatly enjoy the regular French music jam and meeting and playing with more musicians. Meanwhile, although I have not done much dancing lately, I am excited about the creation of CATS Dance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2012-10-15&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-10-15)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out the latest update on the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/10/15/french-music-jam-with-unexpected-new-musicians/&#34;&gt;French music jam&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Living Appalachian music of Southwestern Pennsylvania: Mark Tamsula and Richard Withers with Ellen Gozion </title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/09/23/living-appalachian-music-of-southwestern-pennsylvania/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Sep 2012 22:15:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/09/23/living-appalachian-music-of-southwestern-pennsylvania/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As I periodically do, I went to the Carnegie Library of Pittsburgh on a Sunday afternoon to check out a musical event, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.clpgh.org/events/details.cfm?event_id=69114&#34;&gt;part of the regular World Kaleidoscope series&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.appalachianmusic.net/&#34;&gt;Mark Tamsula and Richard Withers&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://ellengozion.com/&#34;&gt;Ellen Gozion&lt;/a&gt; were there to perform some Appalachian music with very local southwestern Pennsylvanian roots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mark talked a good bit about going through the materials collected by the historian Samuel Bayard. It was interesting to me that his research in reviving the music that Bayard documented forced Mark to get more involved in reading music, since as a traditional musician he was used to learning everything by ear, but nobody is alive any more who originally played some of this music, and all that is left to document it is scores!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/appalachian-music/three.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Mark Tamsula, Richard Withers, Ellen Gozion&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/appalachian-music/irish-flute.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Richard Withers on Irish flute&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The two instrumentalists played quite a variety of instruments: fiddle, banjo, flute, guitar, harmonica, accordion, Irish flute. I enjoyed the variety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ellen Gozion sang some traditional ballads. She has a perfect voice and spirit for this music, singing with great purity and depth of emotional expression. Wow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the little concert, they promoted the new CD &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.upinthebattenhouse.com/&#34;&gt;Up in the Batten House&lt;/a&gt; and talked about upcoming projects.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My second French music jam: playing my Irish flute in public for the first time</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/08/27/my-second-french-music-jam-playing-my-irish-flute-in-public-for-the-first-time/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Aug 2012 22:37:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/08/27/my-second-french-music-jam-playing-my-irish-flute-in-public-for-the-first-time/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Tonight I participated for the second time in a new little &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/groups/182324948478861/&#34;&gt;French traditional dance&lt;/a&gt; music jam session that &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/02/my-first-french-music-jam-anxious-but-excited/&#34;&gt;started up in July&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This time, I played not only my &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/baroque-flute/&#34;&gt;Baroque flute&lt;/a&gt; (which happens to be the instrument I&amp;rsquo;ve mostly been playing for the past two months), but also my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/30/got-my-new-casey-burns-small-handed-irish-flute/&#34;&gt;new Irish flute I got a month ago&lt;/a&gt;. I did &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; bring my modern flute at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we did the last time, after we played around for an hour or so, we then played for dancers for another hour. I enjoyed the experience a lot, and was less nervous than I was the first time. I am slowly improving at learning a tune, without a score, while someone is playing it, and then imitating the melodic line or filling in a harmonically sensible line on the fly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;instruments-and-musicians&#34;&gt;Instruments and musicians&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I finally received my Irish flute a month ago and have spent some minutes every day breaking it in at home. Tonight was its &amp;ldquo;debut&amp;rdquo; in public. I enjoyed the louder, stronger sound.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still used the Baroque flute, for key signatures that my keyless Irish flute does not work well for (half-holing is a pain).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also had fiddles, melodeon, guitar, mandolin (not all at the same time, since John was switching between melodeon and mandolin depending on the key of the song, given the limitations of the melodeon), and I felt that the Irish flute was balanced pretty well with the other instruments, better than the Baroque flute did in the first session in July (when it was often drowned out).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We lost some musicians from last time, because one of them left town, and the clarinetist has a class in the evening and therefore cannot arrive till later, when she comes to dance. But we had two new people!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our little French music group is gaining momentum. I&amp;rsquo;m very excited! Also, as the CMU fall semester starts, there are plans to really promote French and other traditional music and dance in the form of an official CMU student organization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2012-09-28&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-09-28)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/28/another-french-music-jam-also-announcing-cats-dance/&#34;&gt;CATS Dance successfully launched in September&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Got my new Casey Burns Small-Handed Irish flute!</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/07/30/got-my-new-casey-burns-small-handed-irish-flute/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jul 2012 20:37:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/07/30/got-my-new-casey-burns-small-handed-irish-flute/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m excited that I finally got my Casey Burns Small-Handed Folk Flute, a fine keyless Irish flute, that &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/06/12/ordered-the-casey-burns-small-handed-irish-flute/&#34;&gt;I ordered almost two months ago&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are photos of my flute, assembled and disassembled:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/irish-flute/casey-burns-small-handed-folk-flute-assembled.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Casey Burns Small-Handed Folk Flute, assembled&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/irish-flute/casey-burns-small-handed-folk-flute-disassembled.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Casey Burns Small-Handed Folk Flute, disassembled&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I have to start breaking it in, gradually, over the next month, according to the instructions.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My first French music jam: anxious but excited</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/07/02/my-first-french-music-jam-anxious-but-excited/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jul 2012 23:45:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/07/02/my-first-french-music-jam-anxious-but-excited/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Tonight I participated for the first time in a new local &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/groups/182324948478861/&#34;&gt;French traditional dance&lt;/a&gt; music jam session that is getting off the ground, organized by Lisa. I was really excited about the formation of our group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How did this come about?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;inspired-by-gregory&#34;&gt;Inspired by Gregory&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What happened was that after &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/05/14/playing-french-music-for-first-time-and-dancing-blues-for-first-time/&#34;&gt;Gregory left us this summer&lt;/a&gt;, I told Lisa that I really wanted to do the kind of thing Gregory had been doing, playing French music for dancers. Lisa was excited about this and thought it would be cool for herself to start playing fiddle again. She found some other people who were interested in playing French music together, and so we met up!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;instruments&#34;&gt;Instruments&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tonight, I played both my &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/baroque-flute/&#34;&gt;Baroque flute&lt;/a&gt; and my modern flute. I didn&amp;rsquo;t really want to play the modern flute, but there were times when we played some music in keys I wasn&amp;rsquo;t comfortable with on Baroque flute. Meanwhile, it will take a long time for the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/06/12/ordered-the-casey-burns-small-handed-irish-flute/&#34;&gt;Irish flute I ordered&lt;/a&gt; to be made and shipped. I really want to use the louder Irish flute when feasible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lisa had her fiddle, and someone else also had a fiddle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A guy brought his melodeon (button accordion), which unfortunately is limited in the keys it can play in. He sometimes used the old upright piano also. There was someone else who also used the piano.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there was someone on clarinet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-it-went&#34;&gt;How it went&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was quite nervous, because much of what we did was not from printed scores, but from people&amp;rsquo;s memories of their favorite tunes. I in fact ended up using my phone to send Lisa a PDF of Gregory&amp;rsquo;s French music score compilation so that she could print it out for some of us!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I quickly noticed that my Baroque flute was being drowned out by the other instruments. So I pulled out my modern flute sometimes in order to be heard more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We went on for quite some time as the dancers arrived and became restless, and then we played for them for about an hour. Actually, I was heard better then, because Lisa and some other musicians gave introductory lessons or themselves wanted to dance. The result was that after a while, it was just Donna on fiddle, John on melodeon, and me on Baroque flute playing for the dancers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s really a joy playing music for people to dance to. I feel like I&amp;rsquo;m starting to fulfill my dream that &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/10/flute-loving-it-again/&#34;&gt;I dared to mention in March: that of being the musician rather than the dancer at a dance&lt;/a&gt;. During his time here in Pittsburgh, I was really inspired by the example of Gregory (who has finished his stay in the country and gone back to Europe) to start learning tunes by ear, ornamenting, and improvising. I&amp;rsquo;m still quite a beginner at this approach to music, but this is what I&amp;rsquo;ve always wanted to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first French music jam and new format for the French dance (live music instead of iTunes) was a great start of something new. We were all so excited that we definitely want to continue doing this. I look forward to continuing to play together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2012-08-27&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-08-27)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And less than two months later, I am &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/08/27/my-second-french-music-jam-playing-my-irish-flute-in-public-for-the-first-time/&#34;&gt;still involved in the new French music jam&lt;/a&gt;, and finally with my own Irish flute!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ordered the new Casey Burns Small-Handed Irish flute</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/06/12/ordered-the-casey-burns-small-handed-irish-flute/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Jun 2012 21:39:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/06/12/ordered-the-casey-burns-small-handed-irish-flute/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.caseyburnsflutes.com/img/FFBWST.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Casey Burns Folk Flute&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I have finally submitted an order for the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.caseyburnsflutes.com/ff.php&#34;&gt;Casey Burns Small-Handed Folk Flute&lt;/a&gt;, after having sat on the decision for two weeks and discussing it with Abby.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;rationale&#34;&gt;Rationale&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically, I am committed in the long run to exploring Irish music seriously, so this is not just a whimsical purchase. Also, I can obviously use this flute to play other traditional, non-Irish music as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ordered this flute along with &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.caseyburnsflutes.com/grey_book.php&#34;&gt;Grey Larsen&amp;rsquo;s highly acclaimed book, &amp;ldquo;The Essential Guide to Irish Flute and Tin Whistle&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, a book that I expect to serve as a comprehensive tutorial and reference for years&amp;rsquo; worth of study!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>