<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Barefoot Running on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/barefoot-running/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Barefoot Running on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/barefoot-running/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Thoughts on an unexpected winter barefoot run</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/01/20/thoughts-on-an-unexpected-winter-barefoot-run/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Jan 2013 08:14:12 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/01/20/thoughts-on-an-unexpected-winter-barefoot-run/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/barefoot-running-winter.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Barefoot running in winter&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, I went on my first ever &lt;em&gt;winter barefoot run&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; what you think; or maybe, it &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; what you think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;sunny-day&#34;&gt;Sunny day&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, there was still some snow on the ground. But it was purely residual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a sunny day. A &lt;em&gt;warm&lt;/em&gt; day, temperature of about 53 degrees F.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Originally I had planned to go for a run like I did a couple of days ago, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/17/winter-running-in-vibram-fivefingers-shoes-revisited/&#34;&gt;in Vibram FiveFingers shoes&lt;/a&gt;. But I changed my mind when I realized just how warm it was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Impulsively, I just hopped out the door in my short-sleeve T-shirt and shorts, and &lt;em&gt;barefoot&lt;/em&gt;, because it seemed that I could. What other winter have I had, during my lifetime spent in the northern United States, when I could go out running barefoot?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-run&#34;&gt;The run&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ended up running less than about three miles, because I faced some annoyances:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the roads and sidewalks were actually pretty cold&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;there was a lot of debris out there (ouch!), left behind after the snow melted; some of it was clearly salt crystals&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;putting-on-shoes&#34;&gt;Putting on shoes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ended up going back home and putting on my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/26/walking-and-running-in-invisible-shoes-a-review&#34;&gt;Xero Shoes (4mm Connect)&lt;/a&gt; that have become my favorite running footwear (when the weather allows; I stopped wearing them last fall shortly after the Great Race 10K, which was &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/30/running-my-10th-great-race-10k-obscene-but-in-a-good-way/&#34;&gt;my first race running in them&lt;/a&gt;). I felt much better wearing these huaraches and went back out to run another three miles.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/xero-shoes-winter.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Xero Shoes 4mm Connect&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;somber-thoughts&#34;&gt;Somber thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a good time running outside as though it were spring or fall, but actually, I get worried every time this winter I am able to do something like this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s not normal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it&amp;rsquo;s not good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wunderground.com/blog/weatherhistorian/comment.html?entrynum=112&#34;&gt;2012 was a record warm year for the continental United States&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s not pleasant contemplating &lt;a href=&#34;http://climate.nasa.gov/&#34;&gt;global climate change&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s been nice being able to run in winter here in Pittsburgh without being all bundled up. But that is a constant reminder to me that something weird has been happening to our planet.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Walking and running in Invisible Shoes: a review of the Connect</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/07/26/walking-and-running-in-invisible-shoes-a-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jul 2012 21:28:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/07/26/walking-and-running-in-invisible-shoes-a-review/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;For three weeks now, I have been wearing a pair of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.invisibleshoe.com/&#34;&gt;Invisible Shoes&lt;/a&gt; huaraches almost exclusively when walking and running outside. I have worn them daily walking, and I have run in them on roads, on sidewalks, on grass, and in park trails.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a review of the 4mm sole Connect model (I might get a 6mm sole Contact later).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is what the shoes look like with &amp;ldquo;slip-on/slip-off&amp;rdquo; lacing:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/invisible-shoes-connect/without-feet.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/invisible-shoes-connect/bottom.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As you can see, the sole is quite thin, just 4mm:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/invisible-shoes-connect/side-view.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Here are some photos of me wearing the shoes:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/invisible-shoes-connect/grass.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/invisible-shoes-connect/asphalt.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-wear-such-a-thin-shoe&#34;&gt;Why wear such a thin shoe?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ten years ago, in 2002, I learned about the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tarahumara_people&#34;&gt;Tarahumara&lt;/a&gt; Native Americans who live in Mexico and are famed for long-distance running. I was fascinated that they chose to run in minimalist huaraches. At the time, I was doing a lot of serious &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/running/&#34;&gt;running&lt;/a&gt;, and perpetually had problems with running shoes. I figured out from trial and error that the more minimalist I got, the more I enjoyed the feel of running and the fewer injuries I received, but I didn&amp;rsquo;t know how minimalist I could really get before the cons outweighed the pros. By 2002, I had gotten as far as wearing racing flats by New Balance and Asics for races and some of my training runs, but no shoe was perfect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had also tried wearing a variety of ordinary sandals for walking and running, but they had all kinds of ergonomic problems that led me to give up on them. The strapping systems, the substantial (by my standards) heels, and the curved &amp;ldquo;arch support&amp;rdquo; all caused discomfort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fast-forward to 2009, when I bought my first pair of Vibram FiveFingers minimalist shoes. These changed my life, being sufficiently minimalist to defeat a number of problems I&amp;rsquo;ve had with traditional mono-toed shoes. As long-time readers of &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/fivefingers/&#34;&gt;this blog know&lt;/a&gt;, I&amp;rsquo;ve been wearing them exclusively for all kinds of activities, ranging from regular everyday walking to running on roads, running on trails, hiking, kayaking, rafting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past year, I have tried a little bit of &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/barefoot-running/&#34;&gt;barefoot running&lt;/a&gt;, but that is still too extreme for me to do often or for a long period of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I decided that now was the time to try to get more minimalist than FiveFingers, toward the &amp;ldquo;barefoot&amp;rdquo; feel, but without the most glaring drawbacks of being barefoot. Luckily, the surprising popularity of &lt;a href=&#34;http://chrismcdougall.com/&#34;&gt;Chris McDougall&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/a&gt; book &amp;ldquo;Born to Run&amp;rdquo; has resulted in a good number of people selling minimalist huaraches for running.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;buying&#34;&gt;Buying&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Barefoot Ted had long sold his version of huaraches, the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lunasandals.com/&#34;&gt;Luna Sandals&lt;/a&gt;. I decided to try, instead, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.invisibleshoe.com/&#34;&gt;Invisible Shoes&lt;/a&gt;, because these are more minimalist than the Luna, which in its classic form has a 6mm sole as well as a foot bed. I may well try the Luna at some point, but my goal for now is to approximate the barefoot feel, rather than pick the best huaraches for serious rugged use, and work up from there. So I went for the 4mm Connect version of the Invisible Shoes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For now, instead of buying a DIY kit, I decided that the simplest hassle-free way to break into huaraches was to buy a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lunasandals.com/&#34;&gt;custom-made&lt;/a&gt; shoe that had the soles cut and punched and laced up, ready to immediately wear. I traced my foot, scanned the trace, and emailed it, and quickly received my pair in the mail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are interested in trying out huaraches, I recommend following this route if the thought of DIY problems might otherwise discourage you. I may go DIY in the future, now that I see the final product.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;tying&#34;&gt;Tying&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question of how to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.invisibleshoe.com/tying/&#34;&gt;tie&lt;/a&gt; laces always pops up. For now, I have not experimented with different methods in order to evaluate what works best for me for secureness and comfort. I have been using the slip-on/slip-off system that came with the shoe, adjusting it as needed when my foot feels too tight or too loose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;walking&#34;&gt;Walking&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I got Invisible Shoes, my regular walking shoes were my Vibram FiveFingers KSO shoes. But once I got the Invisible Shoes, I completely stopped wearing the KSO for everyday walking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;pros&#34;&gt;Pros&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My toes have real freedom. Toe shoes like the Vibram FiveFingers compartmentalize the toes, so although they solve my wide-foot problem, they do not give me total freedom of the whole front of the foot that I like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good ventilation, like being barefoot. FiveFingers get hot in summer, resulting in sweat and sometimes blisters. I don&amp;rsquo;t get blisters walking in Invisible Shoes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the slip-on/slip-off system, I really can slip on and off easily. Since I like going barefoot indoors, it&amp;rsquo;s a plus to be able to slip on and off the shoes so easily.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;cons&#34;&gt;Cons&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is some rubbing at key points on the foot: the knot in the lacing system on top of the foot, and the lacing that passes between the big toe and the second toe. In practice, none of this has been a real problem except when it&amp;rsquo;s raining and my feet get wet, in which case I get chafed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The soles, being so thin, flop around a bit. Occasionally a sole will fold under and cause me to trip, but this happens very rarely. The main problem is mostly social: the flopping sound draws attention; I prefer to walk very silently (which I can do in most closed shoes).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The thinness of the soles also result in my feet getting very hot when I&amp;rsquo;m just standing for a period of time on hot asphalt or concrete (this is the same problem as I have when going barefoot). So standing at a street intersection waiting for a long light or in a parking lot while putting stuff into a car is not so pleasant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The thinness of the soles means walking over rough terrain is not always pleasant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that all the problems with the thinness of the soles might not be present if I had the 6mm sole rather than the 4mm sole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;running&#34;&gt;Running&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Disclaimer: I have run only four or five times in these shoes so far, so I will accumulate more experience as I continue to run in them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;pros-1&#34;&gt;Pros&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Running in these shoes on the roads and sidewalks is predictable and pleasant, very much like running barefoot. I am considering doing more tests to determine whether to run a road race 5K or 10K in these shoes! I have not run at race pace in these shoes yet. I may need to adjust lacing systems in order to feel confident about running at maximum speed without a flopping or lace-loosening problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;cons-1&#34;&gt;Cons&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is sole flopping when running. Actually there is less flopping than when walking, though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Running in the trails has not worked too smoothly. The 4mm sole really is quite thin for trail running. I noticed this when running in Frick Park, where some of the trails are more rocky than others. I also noticed this even when running in &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/06/18/walking-the-scenic-route-through-schenley-park-to-work/&#34;&gt;Schenley Park on the Pretty Good Race course&lt;/a&gt;, where the downhill section had me periodically hitting rocks harder than comfortable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is also the annoyance of stuff getting between the foot and the sole when running in the trails. Since I don&amp;rsquo;t like stopping, I&amp;rsquo;ve tried to simply flex my foot to let the material slide back out during the next couple of strides, and this mostly works. But I got one blister during a run on the trails, possibly because of loose material that got between my foot and the sole that I didn&amp;rsquo;t bother completely shaking out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 4mm Connect model of Invisible Shoes is great for walking around in. For running, I need to do more tests to find out how they hold up in more demanding conditions of speed and terrain. I would also like to compare the 4mm Connect model with the 6mm Contact model.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Walking the scenic route through Schenley Park to work</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/06/18/walking-the-scenic-route-through-schenley-park-to-work/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Jun 2012 22:08:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/06/18/walking-the-scenic-route-through-schenley-park-to-work/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Two months ago, I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/04/16/one-week-of-commuting-on-foot-because-of-cmu-carnival/&#34;&gt;spent a whole week&lt;/a&gt; commuting to work at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cmu.edu/&#34;&gt;Carnegie Mellon University&lt;/a&gt; by walking instead of driving, because of the annoyances of parking during Carnival week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because I enjoyed that experience so much, since then, I have walked to/from work at least once a week! Usually my route has included either Forbes Avenue or Schenley Drive, but once I went on other roads through Schenley Park.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last week I started making the trails of Schenley Park part of my walk. This adds probably half a mile to the walk (for a total of just less than 2.5 miles from home to work); time efficiency was why I had not taken this indirect route before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some photos of my walk to CMU last week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;going-barefoot-to-schenley-park&#34;&gt;Going barefoot to Schenley Park&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went barefoot the entire way from home to Schenley Park.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/commute-schenley-park/barefoot.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Barefoot&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Reaching the Schenley Park sign on Hobart Street:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/commute-schenley-park/hobart.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Schenley Park sign on Hobart Street&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;About to enjoy barefoot running on the grass to cross Beacon Street and Bartlett Street to reach the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.examiner.com/article/schenley-park-bartlett-street-playground&#34;&gt;Bartlett Playground&lt;/a&gt;. Note that the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.tour.pitt.edu/tour-080.html&#34;&gt;Cathedral of Learning&lt;/a&gt; is visible in the background.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/commute-schenley-park/beacon-bartlett-grass.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Grass at Hobart Street and Beacon Street&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Arriving at the Bartlett Shelter sign:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/commute-schenley-park/bartlett-shelter.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Sign for Bartlett Shelter&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Right behind the playground is the entrance to the Panther Hollow Trail:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/commute-schenley-park/bartlett-panther-hollow-trail.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Sign for Panther Hollow Trail&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;panther-hollow-trail-to-schenley-park-cafe-and-visitor-center&#34;&gt;Panther Hollow Trail to Schenley Park Cafe and Visitor Center&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This section of the Panther Hollow Trail that I followed all the way to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pittsburghparks.org/schenleyparkcafe&#34;&gt;Schenley Park Cafe and Visitor Center&lt;/a&gt; is the all-downhill section of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~kalp/PGR/&#34;&gt;Pretty Good Race 5K&lt;/a&gt; course that I ran on to &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/06/06/i-celebrated-national-running-day-in-schenley-park-remembering-how-i-began-to-run-13-year-ago/&#34;&gt;celebrate National Running Day on June 6&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My apologies to the barefoot purists, but I immediately found the trail too rough for my bare feet and put on my Vibram FiveFingers KSO shoes:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/commute-schenley-park/vibram-fivefingers-kso.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Vibram FiveFingers KSO shoes on Panther Hollow Trail&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A typical view while running downhill on the Panther Hollow Trail for about 0.9 mile:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/commute-schenley-park/panther-hollow-trail-downhill.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Panther Hollow Trail going downhill&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A sign at the base of the steps that lead up to the Schenley Park Cafe and Visitor Center. I appreciate the renovations in the Pittsburgh parks in the past several years that include such features as the new signs that I think help visitors a lot.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/commute-schenley-park/steps-sign.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Schenley Park sign at base of steps&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Finally out of the trail:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/commute-schenley-park/schenley-park-cafe-and-visitor-center.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Schenley Park Cafe and Visitor Center&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;across-flagstaff-hill-to-my-office-at-carnegie-mellon-university&#34;&gt;Across Flagstaff Hill to my office at Carnegie Mellon University&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A view of Phipps Conservatory as well as the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.tour.pitt.edu/tour-080.html&#34;&gt;Cathedral of Learning&lt;/a&gt; in the distance:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/commute-schenley-park/phipps-cathedral.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Phipps Conservatory&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One is probably not supposed to do so, but I climbed up the stone border (about four feet high) to enter Flagstaff Hill. The more circuitous route to my office would be to take Schenley Drive, which curves around, but it&amp;rsquo;s shorter (and also more scenic and strenuous) to go up the hill directly and steeply, and then descend.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/commute-schenley-park/flagstaff-hill.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Flagstaff Hill&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Taking in the view of the Cathedral of Learning against the lovely blue sky, while running through the grass on Flagstaff Hill:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/commute-schenley-park/cathedral-of-learning-from-flagstaff-hill.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Cathedral of Learning visible from Flagstaff Hill&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;My office is barely visible through the trees as I descend:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/commute-schenley-park/office-through-trees.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Office visible through trees&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A convenient path to Frew Street:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/commute-schenley-park/path-to-frew-street.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Path to Frew Street&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At my office building:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/commute-schenley-park/office-building.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;My office building&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a lot of fun on a nice day to walk to work the &amp;ldquo;long&amp;rdquo; way that goes through the trails of Schenley Park and also Flagstaff Hill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am so grateful that Pittsburgh is friendly and stimulating for walking in. And, of course, I am grateful that &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mary_Schenley&#34;&gt;Mary Schenley&lt;/a&gt; donated the land to Pittsburgh way back that became Schenley Park.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Your Day Without Shoes and my very first day out completely without shoes</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/06/07/your-day-without-shoes-and-my-very-first-day-out-completely-without-shoes/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Jun 2012 21:02:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/06/07/your-day-without-shoes-and-my-very-first-day-out-completely-without-shoes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/your-day-without-shoes-abby-franklin.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby and Franklin without shoes in DC&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/your-day-without-shoes-musicians.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby and Franklin without shoes in DC&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;

May 26, 2012 was &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.primalfootalliance.org/ydws/&#34;&gt;Your Day Without Shoes&lt;/a&gt;, which Abby and I tried to observe, even though we were in DC at my sister&amp;rsquo;s at the time, visiting our new &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/nephew/&#34;&gt;nephew&lt;/a&gt;, and therefore we were in an unfamiliar environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out that although Abby did spend the day without shoes, I wore shoes once in the morning and then not again the rest of the day. I&amp;rsquo;ll explain why, and also describe my actual very first day without shoes (while being out and about), which was today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;ok-so-why-barefoot&#34;&gt;OK, so why barefoot??&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some reasons I&amp;rsquo;ve been experimenting with walking or running barefoot in the past year or two:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;my long history of problems with shoes of all kinds, because they mostly don&amp;rsquo;t fit me well or rub me or cause me knee and other problems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;curiosity, novelty&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a varied and heightened sensory life experience&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;working out kinks in my body balance and movement form&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;moving well barefoot is good training for moving well in shoes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t have an ideological reason for going barefoot. I am sympathetic to the idea that our feet work pretty well because of our evolutionary history, but I am not a primitivist. I am typing this at a computer, illuminated by light that is not coming from the sun or moon. I am a pragmatist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;your-day-without-shoes&#34;&gt;Your Day Without Shoes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;how-i-failed&#34;&gt;How I failed&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the official &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.primalfootalliance.org/ydws/&#34;&gt;Your Day Without Shoes&lt;/a&gt;, I had hoped to do entirely without shoes, but in the end, I chickened out and wore my trusty Vibram FiveFingers KSO shoes in a morning errand driving my brother-in-law to a grocery store, Harris Teeter, to buy food for a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/05/31/some-pretty-attacking-chess-at-a-party-last-weekend/&#34;&gt;barbecue we were going to have&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I have never been barefoot in a grocery store before, and certainly not in some unknown store I&amp;rsquo;ve never scoped out in advance, I felt it was too risky to cause possible &amp;ldquo;trouble&amp;rdquo; on a simple errand that we had to run. If there had been no time pressure and I had been alone (not inconveniencing my brother-in-law and indirectly, our party guests for the afternoon), maybe I would have given it a shot. Or maybe not, given that I have not gone barefoot in a grocery store at home in Pittsburgh yet!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have repeatedly gotten in some trouble when attempting to be barefoot in public. I am not the kind of person who likes to deliberately cause confrontations; I realize, of course, that this makes me part of the problem, not speaking up. But I get not only words and looks of disapproval, but &amp;ldquo;official&amp;rdquo;-looking people who make up painfully obvious made-up sermons about &amp;ldquo;laws&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;rules&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;health codes&amp;rdquo;. In principle, I could go out of my way to contact appropriate authorities in order to defend myself, but right now, not being a barefoot zealot but a novice experimenting, I have settled for experimenting where it is &amp;ldquo;safe&amp;rdquo; while building up my barefooting experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Safe&amp;rdquo; for me right now is roughly:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;anywhere outside a public building, such as on the streets, sidewalks, grass, parks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;at home&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;at work (while not being in a gym or library or other such place where &amp;ldquo;official&amp;rdquo; looking people go around telling people how to behave)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;in my car&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;at other people&amp;rsquo;s homes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a place I frequent where I basically know the people in charge and have inferred they&amp;rsquo;re OK with my being barefoot&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;abby-and-i-experimented-with-going-barefoot-the-rest-of-the-day&#34;&gt;Abby and I experimented with going barefoot the rest of the day&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;eastern-market&#34;&gt;Eastern Market&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I did go barefoot later in the morning, after my grocery shopping errand, when we went to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.easternmarket-dc.org/&#34;&gt;Eastern Market&lt;/a&gt;, which was hustling and bustling on a Saturday. We were there to check out the outside action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, it was very sunny and hot that day (I think the temperature was up to 90F!), and some of the outside brick and asphalt surfaces were burning hot, too hot to really walk on. We ended up looking for surfaces under shade, or painted white, to step on, but there were not many such surfaces. So we had to basically &amp;ldquo;run&amp;rdquo; in order to minimize foot contact with the ground. We didn&amp;rsquo;t last very long out there and headed back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That was a rookie mistake to have made. Well, we learn by failing small. We&amp;rsquo;re no purists about barefooting, just curious and pragmatic experimenters. No more going barefoot again in such conditions!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;evening-walk&#34;&gt;Evening walk&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a long day, cleaning up from the party, it was starting to get dark outside, and cooler, and Abby and I went out for a little walk in the neighborhood. So we went out barefoot, in keeping with the theme for the day. The walk was nice. Without the burning sun, the sidewalks and roads were just fine for walking on barefoot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby came up with the idea that when we went home, we should start doing some barefoot walking together after dinner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-very-first-day-out-without-shoes&#34;&gt;My very first day out without shoes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today was my very first day out without shoes. I hadn&amp;rsquo;t intended on that, here&amp;rsquo;s what happened:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;yesterday&#34;&gt;Yesterday&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday I went for a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/06/06/i-celebrated-national-running-day-in-schenley-park-remembering-how-i-began-to-run-13-year-ago/&#34;&gt;nice run for National Running Day&lt;/a&gt;. Usually when I run in the trails, I wear my Vibram FiveFingers KSO Trek shoes, because they give me more protection and never blister me. But yesterday I wanted to experiment (yet again) with wearing the more truly minimalist KSO shoes, which, unfortunately, have had a history of blistering me badly because of the design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The run was great, and over the months I have adapted (thanks to periodic barefooting) to landing even more subtly and efficiently so that even with the KSO shoes, I do not find the rocks or tree roots out on the trail to be too uncomfortable to deal with. Unfortunately, I still got a blister at my usual rubbing spot at the side of my big toe joint. (You may be able to spot it in the photos below.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/national-running-day-vibram-fivefingers-kso.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin&amp;#39;s Vibram FiveFingers KSO shoes&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/national-running-day-barefoot.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin&amp;#39;s Vibram FiveFingers KSO shoes&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out yesterday that because of the blister, I just didn&amp;rsquo;t want to wear any shoes for the rest of the day, and in fact I didn&amp;rsquo;t. I went barefoot from the time I finished my run to the time I left work and drove home, and I was barefoot the rest of the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;today&#34;&gt;Today&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today my blister had subsided (it will probably be &amp;ldquo;OK&amp;rdquo; tomorrow), but I still did not feel like wearing shoes. So I went to work barefoot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, it was sunny and the asphalt in the parking lot was very hot. I did what I could to ease my walk out of the parking lot to my office (basically, &amp;ldquo;run&amp;rdquo; when on hot surfaces), but frankly, it was not pleasant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went home from work barefoot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then after dinner, I ran barefoot in Squirrel Hill from home to the monthly meeting of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://pghrb.heroku.com/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Ruby&lt;/a&gt; group. Afterwards, I ran back home. So that was my day without shoes!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Little by little, I have expanded my barefooting experience, and plan to continue exploring. I find it very enjoyable and surprising that after more than a year, I am no longer very uncomfortable walking on typical city sidewalks and roads (unless there is hot direct sun involved with darker surfaces).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>International Barefoot Running Day 2012: my second year of celebration and my first barefoot trail run</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/05/06/international-barefoot-running-day-2012-my-second-year-of-celebration-and-my-first-barefoot-trail-run/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 May 2012 20:11:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/05/06/international-barefoot-running-day-2012-my-second-year-of-celebration-and-my-first-barefoot-trail-run/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/international-barefoot-running-day-2012/ibrdposter_lg.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Official poster of International Barefoot Running Day 2012&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One year ago (May 1, 2011), I celebrated the first annual &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.thebarefootrunners.org/pages/IBRD/&#34;&gt;International Barefoot Running Day&lt;/a&gt; by running 0.6 mile on the streets of my neighborhood. That was the very first time in my life I was &amp;ldquo;brave&amp;rdquo; enough to &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/barefoot-running/&#34;&gt;run barefoot&lt;/a&gt; outside (other than one failed attempt I discuss below).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, I pushed the envelope by running a full 2 miles barefoot, including a 0.5 mile trail loop on Frick Park. &lt;strong&gt;This was my first time ever running barefoot on the trails.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/international-barefoot-running-day-2012/barefoot.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;My two feet&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/international-barefoot-running-day-2012/barefoot-soles.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Soles of my two feet after barefoot run&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the story of why I got into barefoot running, and what progress I&amp;rsquo;ve made in the past year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-first-barefoot-run-outside&#34;&gt;My first barefoot run outside&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have to start with my first barefoot run outside. This happened in summer 2002, on the track at Carnegie Mellon University. I did only one lap. I did this as an experiment as I was learning from trial and error that running with lighter shoes seemed to feel better for me, and decreased injuries to my knees and shins, in particular.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have to understand, this happened a decade ago, well before minimalist and barefoot running became much more widespread, through &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.chrismcdougall.com/&#34;&gt;Chris McDougall&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rsquo;s bestselling book, &lt;em&gt;Born to Run&lt;/em&gt;, that came out in 2009 (I read the book in May 2009 and highly recommend it to &lt;strong&gt;all&lt;/strong&gt; runners!). At the time, my experiments as a runner had led me in the following progression of shoes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;heavy &amp;ldquo;motion control&amp;rdquo; shoes (because I overpronated so much initially as an overweight non-runner)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;lighter &amp;ldquo;neutral&amp;rdquo; shoes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;lightweight trainer&amp;rdquo; shoes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;racing flats&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea of really running barefoot never occurred to me, but I wanted to experiment with simply doing a bit of controlled training (on the predictable surface of a track) barefoot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a few attempts, I gave up. I suffered from&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;blistered feet&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;very sore Achilles tendons and calves&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;shin splits&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So for almost a decade, I simply never tried running barefoot again, even on a track.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;transition-to-vibram-fivefingers-shoes&#34;&gt;Transition to Vibram FiveFingers shoes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have raved repeatedly on this blog about my use of &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/fivefingers/&#34;&gt;Vibram FiveFingers&lt;/a&gt; minimalist shoes. They are my regular shoes now (when not in winter) for running (road and trail), street walking, trail hiking. They came to my attention through a friend in 2009, and in conjunction with my reading McDougall&amp;rsquo;s book, I bought my first pair of FiveFingers shoes in fall of 2009.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It took me two years of occasional use to really build up distance with the minimalist shoes and change my form in many ways such that I no longer experience any undue pain on stress on my muscles or joints. By 2011, I was ready to use them as my everyday footwear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-next-step-barefoot&#34;&gt;The next step: barefoot&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the idea of barefoot running kept on haunting me. The difference between running in even minimalist shoes and barefoot is vast. I experienced a lot of fears:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;fear of possible injury to the skin from rocks, glass, other objects&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;fear possible hygiene issues (what am I stepping on?)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;fear of sheer skin sensitivity and pain&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past year, since my tiny experiment on May 1, 2011, I have been doing small amounts of outdoors barefoot walking and running, mostly in the context of walking or running home 2 miles from work, and going barefoot at the office (I have always gone barefoot indoors at home, since I grew up under the Asian custom of leaving shoes at the door). Over time, I have addressed my fears to some extent:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I have learned to visually scan the surface I am running on, to avoid obvious hazards&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I have learned to accept that heck, will I really get hurt from stepping on a surface that might have some tiny amount (which I can&amp;rsquo;t even see) of dried spit, insect parts, or dog poo?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I have become more efficient and less fearful of the sensations of landing on patches of rough concrete, twigs, debris, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have grown to be fairly comfortable walking or running on concrete and asphalt, where the surfaces are mostly predictable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-final-frontier-barefoot-trail-running&#34;&gt;The final frontier: barefoot trail running&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But my experiments last year of even walking off the road and grass onto the trails of Frick Park had me whimpering after a few seconds, feeling totally unready to seriously walk or run on the trails.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Until today.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In honor of the second annual &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.thebarefootrunners.org/pages/IBRD/&#34;&gt;International Barefoot Running Day&lt;/a&gt;, I went for a 2 mile barefoot run today that included a 0.5 mile trail loop. The soles of my feet suffered a bit, but I actually managed to do this run without screaming or giving up. I came home with some hot spots on my soles, but nothing much worse than when I run 2 miles just on concrete and asphalt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A year ago, I would not have believed that I would run a full half mile barefoot on the trails. But that was a year ago. A year ago, I would not have believed that I would be doing today many of the things that I have only begun doing last year (such as writing my own blog, playing music, programming in JavaScript). Things change. And all that is required is to take one small step at a time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-next&#34;&gt;What next?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still cannot imagine running barefoot for more than half a mile, or on much more difficult terrain than the one trail section in Frick Park. We&amp;rsquo;ll see what I have to report next year for the third International Barefoot Running Day!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reflections on 2011</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/12/31/reflections-on-2011/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Dec 2011 18:52:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/12/31/reflections-on-2011/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I reflect on my year of 2011 as it ends. Since I did not start blogging until September, I go into more detail of what happened before then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;january&#34;&gt;January&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I continued our project of massively reorganizing our home, a project that began when she moved in during summer 2010. We were very grateful that Abby&amp;rsquo;s father helped out a lot.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I continued getting rid of a lot of stuff, including another eighteen boxes of my books, as I became an initially reluctant &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/minimalism/&#34;&gt;minimalist&lt;/a&gt;. We sold or gave away a &lt;em&gt;huge&lt;/em&gt; number of various of belongings.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby started cooking much more than in the past, and we enjoyed trying new dishes of her making.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I enjoyed some light cross-country skiing in the winter, using the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Schenley_Park_Golf_Course&#34;&gt;Bob O&amp;rsquo;Connor Golf Course at Schenley Park&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I began a weekly Zen &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/meditation/&#34;&gt;meditation&lt;/a&gt; session offered at Carnegie Mellon University.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started moving very gradually toward a &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/paleo/&#34;&gt;paleo&lt;/a&gt; diet and exercise routine, and immediately experienced benefits. &amp;ldquo;The Paleo Solution&amp;rdquo; by &lt;a href=&#34;http://robbwolf.com/&#34;&gt;Robb Wolf&lt;/a&gt; was very useful.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started learning modern &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/javascript/&#34;&gt;JavaScript&lt;/a&gt; for a new project at work, getting into client-side Web development. As part of that, I learned &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/jquery/&#34;&gt;jQuery&lt;/a&gt; through a free &lt;a href=&#34;http://p2pu.org/&#34;&gt;P2PU&lt;/a&gt; course and used it in the project.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started using &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/XQuery&#34;&gt;XQuery&lt;/a&gt; at work to process XML in a clear and concise way. I had used XSLT in the past, but it was very unpleasant.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I decided, for various reasons, to stop writing new &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/perl/&#34;&gt;Perl&lt;/a&gt; scripts and move to &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/python/&#34;&gt;Python&lt;/a&gt; instead.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started playing in my final (and disastrous) &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/chess/&#34;&gt;chess&lt;/a&gt; tournament, the Pittsburgh Chess Club Championship (which I had won in 2006 and 2007).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;february&#34;&gt;February&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pittsburgh was all about the Steelers, and I went to a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Super_Bowl_XLV&#34;&gt;Super Bowl&lt;/a&gt; party for the first time, but we lost!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I read &amp;ldquo;The Art of Non-Conformity&amp;rdquo; by &lt;a href=&#34;http://chrisguillebeau.com/&#34;&gt;Chris Guillebeau&lt;/a&gt; and found it so inspiring that I decided to take action and start making big changes to my life, in my own way.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;One big change: I quit playing chess, cold turkey, after having been unenthusiastic about it for months already (and playing correspondingly poorly). When the passion and enjoyment are gone, there is no point in hanging onto something just because it has been such an important part of my life for years.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;After years of not playing any music at all, I started playing &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/recorder/&#34;&gt;recorder&lt;/a&gt;, and vowed to play every single day if possible. Ten months later, I am still playing recorder.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I began attending a lot of &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/16/pittsburgh-software-developer-communities/&#34;&gt;local software developer group meetings&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started learning the &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/scala/&#34;&gt;Scala&lt;/a&gt; programming language and decided to use it on a small project.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;march&#34;&gt;March&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I continued our meditation practice at CMU, and went to our first mini-&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sesshin&#34;&gt;sesshin&lt;/a&gt; on a Saturday.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I continued practicing recorder every single day, and joined the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.andrew.cmu.edu/user/lukas/pcars/Welcome.html&#34;&gt;local chapter of the American Recorder Society&lt;/a&gt;. It was very exciting to meet new people and to get into a wide range of music I had never really listened to or played.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I saw a video of &lt;a href=&#34;http://jakeshimabukuro.com/&#34;&gt;Jake Shimabukuro&lt;/a&gt; playing &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/ukulele/&#34;&gt;ukulele&lt;/a&gt; so beautifully that I was inspired to buy a ukulele and start learning to play it. (Unfortunately, it would turn out that time constraints caused me not to pursue ukulele far. This will change in 2012.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I got pulled into the Ruby programming language because it is well-supported on Mac OS and it is easy to install libraries and tools, of which there are many that are quite useful.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I went to &lt;a href=&#34;http://farmtotablepa.com/&#34;&gt;Farm to Table&lt;/a&gt; in Pittsburgh, and after that, Abby started moving toward paleo eating, with even better results than my smaller experiments earlier.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I started our &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/hiking/&#34;&gt;hiking&lt;/a&gt; season in the spring. Hiking is special to us; it was one of our first shared activities (after initially meeting during salsa dancing), and one we return to again and again. When there is no calendar conflict and the weather is acceptable, we like hiking almost every weekend from spring through fall.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;{% img /images/steves-soup-hike-2011-03-26.jpg Abby in front of me at Steve&amp;rsquo;s Soup Hike %}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;april&#34;&gt;April&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started wearing &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/fivefingers/&#34;&gt;Vibram FiveFingers shoes&lt;/a&gt; almost all the time, whether walking or running (but not yet for hiking).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I went to &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/yoga/&#34;&gt;yoga&lt;/a&gt; at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.clpgh.org/locations/squirrelhill/&#34;&gt;Squirrel Hill Library&lt;/a&gt; for the first time.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;may&#34;&gt;May&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I began my experiment with barefoot running, in observation of &lt;a href=&#34;http://barefootrunners.org/ibrd&#34;&gt;International Barefoot Running Day&lt;/a&gt;. I started walking around barefoot at work, ignoring the confused looks or comments of colleagues. (I still go barefoot at work.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I bought a &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/melodica/&#34;&gt;melodica&lt;/a&gt;, inspired by the amazing performances of &lt;a href=&#34;http://jnote.org/&#34;&gt;James Howard Young&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I took a little vacation, spending some days in New York visiting Nathaniel and Yael and their baby. I finally fulfilled my dream (from before marriage) of taking Abby to Coney Island to walk on the boardwalk and at the beach, eating pizza, and riding the Wonder Wheel, just as I once did when I was six years old.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I started doing research into major home renovations for the summer.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I visited my parents, and my sister Linda and her husband Andre also visited, with my mother throwing a delayed reception at home for the both of us who had gotten married in the past two years. Abby got to meet my parents&amp;rsquo; friends, finally. And I went running with my brother-in-law for the first time! Also, I took Abby to the little park in Ann Arbor where as a too-shy teenager I used to go and sit on a particular bench and wish I were sitting with my dream girl. Mission accomplished!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;june&#34;&gt;June&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;John and I did a tough 19-mile training hike on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rachelcarsontrails.org/rct&#34;&gt;Rachel Carson Trail&lt;/a&gt; and decided we&amp;rsquo;d had enough of that trail, and I decided I was probably not going to do the 35-mile &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rachelcarsontrails.org/rct/challenge&#34;&gt;Rachel Carson Trail Challenge&lt;/a&gt; again (having completed it three times in the past).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;{% img /images/rachel-carson-trail-2011-06-05.jpg John on Rachel Carson Trail %}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby started wearing Vibram FiveFingers more and more for walking and running, and even walking barefoot on the streets (something I had not yet seriously done myself at the time).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I stupidly threw out my back during exercise, and my back took weeks to fully recover (I could still run and hike, but not lift weights). Never again, I hope. I felt like a 90-year-old when my back was hurting constantly.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;We started some home improvement projects.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;july&#34;&gt;July&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started gravitating to almost exclusively body weight &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/strength-training/&#34;&gt;strength training&lt;/a&gt;, as a reaction to my having injured my back earlier.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I went kayaking on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kiskiminetas_River&#34;&gt;Kiski River&lt;/a&gt; with &amp;ldquo;Fireman Steve&amp;rdquo; and the kayaking gang.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;On a longish hike, Abby surprised me by wearing Vibram FiveFingers shoes and they worked great for her, making her much faster and less sore, and I made a note to ditch my trail running shoes (which I had been using for years for hiking) in favor of FiveFingers for my next hike (which I did, and I have not gone back to regular shoes for hiking!).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I finally took Abby to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sandhillberries.com/&#34;&gt;Sand Hill Berries&lt;/a&gt; for tasty pie for the first time, always having intended to take her there when dating, but never having been in the vicinity with her then.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Major home renovation finally began, after much research, and we got electrical upgrade, insulation, and bathroom demolition and rebuilding. Very disruptive to our lives for weeks!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I did another mini-&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sesshin&#34;&gt;sesshin&lt;/a&gt; at CMU.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;After a lifetime of almost never drinking coffee (average of maybe three or four cups a year), I became an avid espresso fan (one small cup a day) as a result of my boss getting a machine at work.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started doing more barefoot running.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;august&#34;&gt;August&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bathroom renovation done at last.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I were regularly hiking in Vibram FiveFingers.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;{% img /images/abby-franklin-soup-hike-vibram.jpg Abby and Franklin on Steve&amp;rsquo;s Soup Hike part 3 wearing Vibram FiveFingers %}&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby joined me to run in her first ever 5K race, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.runaroundthesquare.com/&#34;&gt;Run Around the Square&lt;/a&gt; in Regent Square (mostly on the trails of Frick Park). What a special day! This race was my first ever 5K race when I started running in races in 2000.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started to learn &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/accordion/&#34;&gt;accordion&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;september&#34;&gt;September&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started running to work two or three times a week.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I ran in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~kalp/PGR/&#34;&gt;CMU SCS Pretty Good Race 5K&lt;/a&gt; together, her second 5K race.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I went to &lt;a href=&#34;http://podcamppittsburgh.com/&#34;&gt;PodCamp Pittsburgh&lt;/a&gt;, and after that, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/22/starting-a-new-web-site/&#34;&gt;I started this blog&lt;/a&gt; and proceeded to maintain a habit of posting every day (a routine that has been modified since then).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;october&#34;&gt;October&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started expanding beyond just writing for my blog, and began contributing to the Web through &lt;a href=&#34;http://twitter.com/franklinchen&#34;&gt;my Twitter account&lt;/a&gt; as well as writing comments on other people&amp;rsquo;s blog posts.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started taking Stanford online classes: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ml-class.org/&#34;&gt;Machine Learning&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.db-class.org/&#34;&gt;Introduction to Databases&lt;/a&gt;. (Blog posts on my experiences to appear soon.) Unfortunately, as a result of the extra time commitment, October through December were quite hectic for me.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Abby and I continued to move more toward a paleo diet.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;november&#34;&gt;November&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started playing &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/flute/&#34;&gt;flute&lt;/a&gt; again.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Probably because of fatigue and a compromised immune system, I came down with a skin ailment that I got serious treatment for, but it took almost two months to completely clear up and I spent over a month truly miserable &lt;sup&gt;24&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;7&lt;/sub&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;december&#34;&gt;December&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started playing Baroque flute.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I started playing tin whistle.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I prepared for and made it through two music performances, playing recorder and flute (and almost tin whistle).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I ended the year completely exhausted, on the verge of getting sick, and took a long break from blogging.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The final week, Abby and I were on a hectic travel schedule that involved meeting up with her parents, my parents, her sister Carrie, Carrie&amp;rsquo;s boyfriend Alain, Alain&amp;rsquo;s parents, Alain&amp;rsquo;s extended family, my sister Linda, and her husband Andre. I am grateful that we got to meet up with so many people (and arranged for various of the individuals to meet up with various of the others!), but the trip was quite stressful to me, because I was not physically or emotionally prepared for it at all. (I will report later on what I learned from the experience.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2011 was quite a year for me and Abby. We had many changes and adventures in our lives: our home, our diet, our exercise, our outdoors activities, travel. For me, the biggest changes were quitting chess, starting music practice and performance, throwing myself into blogging and tweeting, getting more and more active in local software developer groups, applying new (to me) development tools at work, and in the fall, taking Stanford online courses in computer science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although I ended the year in poor shape, because of being overbooked, I am very excited by how many positive changes took place. I have an entirely new set of plans and priorities to formulate soon for 2012 in collaboration with Abby, in hope of learning from the lessons of my failures and omissions of 2011, and restoring balance.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>