<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Piano on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/piano/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Piano on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/piano/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Accidentally discovering and performing some music by Brazilian composer Ernesto Nazareth: Coração que Sente</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/12/29/accidentally-discovering-and-performing-some-music-by-brazilian-composer-ernesto-nazareth-cora%C3%A7%C3%A3o-que-sente/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Dec 2015 23:05:10 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/12/29/accidentally-discovering-and-performing-some-music-by-brazilian-composer-ernesto-nazareth-cora%C3%A7%C3%A3o-que-sente/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In November, I fell in love with some music I accidentally discovered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What happened was that I was looking for some music for &lt;em&gt;flute&lt;/em&gt; and
&lt;em&gt;guitar&lt;/em&gt; to play, with me on flute and one of my friends on guitar, and
I did a simple search in the
&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/30/free-to-the-people-since-1895/&#34;&gt;local library&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;http://librarycatalog.einetwork.net/&#34;&gt;online catalog&lt;/a&gt;, and at the top
sorted by date was
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.halleonard.com/product/viewproduct.action?itemid=49044167&amp;amp;&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Brazilian folk tunes for flute and guitar&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;,
which came with a CD of sample performance tracks,
so I picked it up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What followed was a series of explorations that resulted in unexpected
changes in my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;exploring-the-brazilian-music-in-the-score-book&#34;&gt;Exploring the Brazilian music in the score book&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I listened to some tracks on the CD of this book of arrangements and
found the music (Brazilian polkas, tangos, waltzes) really
enchanting. Most of the music was by a composer
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ernesto_Nazareth&#34;&gt;Ernesto Nazareth&lt;/a&gt;,
who lived 1863-1934. I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t call this music &amp;ldquo;folk tunes&amp;rdquo;: it&amp;rsquo;s
a sophisticated combination of popular and classical styles using
catchy dance rhythms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m a real sucker for waltzes, so at first I thought I would pick one
of the beautiful waltzes to choose to suggest to play with a partner
on guitar. It came down to &amp;ldquo;Confidências&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;Coração que Sente&amp;rdquo;
(English translation: &amp;ldquo;Heart that Feels&amp;rdquo;). The
latter was much easier and shorter, as I learned while sight reading
through it with the CD track, so I thought I was done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;finding-astounding-performances-of-coração-que-sente-on-youtube&#34;&gt;Finding astounding performances of &amp;ldquo;Coração que Sente&amp;rdquo; on YouTube&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking for performances of the piece on YouTube to get an idea of
how people play it, I immediately entered a strange new world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, I learned that the original music was for
&lt;em&gt;piano&lt;/em&gt;. OK. Then, while listening to and/or watching a dozen or so
videos of performances of this piece (OK, I was obsessed), I found a
huge variety of interpretations, and some of them spoke to me more
than others. Some I found light and boring. The ones that interested
me were the ones that were extremely intense and probing. You might
think this music was just fluff, but I found a dark undercurrent
behind it that spoke to me, in that its different sections (the piece
is roughly in rondo form) present clear emotional contrasts, with
longing, melancholy, and manic excitement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;arthur-moreira-lima&#34;&gt;Arthur Moreira Lima&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A very intense performance I found was by a pianist named
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arthur_Moreira_Lima&#34;&gt;Arthur Moreira Lima&lt;/a&gt;
in 1975, used after the fact as soundtrack on YouTube for a silent
film using footage from 1929. What an odd pairing!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lima goes all out in Romantic expressiveness, with extensive rubato
and dynamic and rhythmic flexibility. It was completely different from
the relatively straight, danceable version on the flute/guitar CD
demo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have to listen to his performance (ignore the film or watch it, as
you wish):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Mmjt8RrfXtA&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;joão-carlos-assis-brasil&#34;&gt;João Carlos Assis Brasil&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even more extreme than Lima was this weird guy João Carlos Assis
Brasil, who is apparently so unknown in the English-speaking world
that Wikipedia doesn&amp;rsquo;t have an entry on him, although I found this
random
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.bach-cantatas.com/Bio/Assis-Brasil-Joao-Carlos.htm&#34;&gt;pieced-together bio&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His live performance here from 2013 is the single most extreme, yet
deepest, interpretation of this waltz I found (he adds his own
ornamentation). I was deeply moved by it. (Warning, bad sound
quality.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/iG_o94sU1tE&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;other-good-performances&#34;&gt;Other good performances&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://pt.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fernanda_Chaves_Canaud&#34;&gt;Fernanda Canaud&lt;/a&gt;,
with a very expressive performance (including her own extensive
embellishments), uses drastic changes in articulation and tempo for
contrast. I particularly liked how naturally she seemed to express her
personality through the piece:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/-DfOYvNCaqk&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://pt.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maria_Teresa_Madeira&#34;&gt;Maria Theresa Madeira&lt;/a&gt;
captures well the moods of the different sections of the piece; I
really like the rhythmic alertness and drive throughout:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/eeztzLsF6Cc&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some random YouTube guy named Ilton, playing a really crappy upright
piano, but with amazing rhythmic expression that I totally love (if he
played this on a good piano, I would consider his interpretation one
of my favorites, period):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/b-gYk_YUoIM&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://lucianoalves.com.br/&#34;&gt;Luciano Alves&lt;/a&gt;, 2013, in an elegant
performance:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/y8LchR8Mi5Y&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://pt.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marcelo_Bratke&#34;&gt;Marcelo Bratke&lt;/a&gt; in a
relaxed, easygoing, dream interpretation with a lilt (but after all
the intense interpretations, I find this tame, I confess):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Pn5vYhfQYHs&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-performance-that-made-me-decide-to-learn-and-play-the-piece&#34;&gt;The performance that made me decide to learn and play the piece&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I spent a lot of time listening to and watching performances of the
piece, but one performance was the one that made me decide to go learn
and play the piece! It was this one by some random guy Marcelo Chiarella:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/QaQL9VlJy8s&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why? Because I could &lt;em&gt;relate to&lt;/em&gt; his playing:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;He wasn&amp;rsquo;t some famous pro pianist, as far as I could tell.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The sound quality was good and the recording was as though I were
standing right there, made me feel like I was in his home, and
nobody else there.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I could see his hands up close.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I liked various things he did with expression (especially when he
&lt;em&gt;wasn&amp;rsquo;t&lt;/em&gt; pedaling).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I knew that I could be much more expressive and personal
(remember, the title in English translation is &amp;ldquo;Heart that feels&amp;rdquo;)
while playing this piece &lt;em&gt;solo&lt;/em&gt;, on piano, than in a flute/guitar
duet. So I decided to go for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;finding-an-official-free-score&#34;&gt;Finding an official free score&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had to find a score. Luckily, it turned out that there was some
big
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ernestonazareth150anos.com.br/&#34;&gt;150-year anniversary celebration for Ernesto Nazareth&lt;/a&gt;
in 2013, and I found an official &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ernestonazareth150anos.com.br/files/uploads/work_elements/work_43/coracao_que_sente_piano.pdf&#34;&gt;free PDF score&lt;/a&gt; on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ernestonazareth150anos.com.br/works/view/43&#34;&gt;page for the piece&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That page also had a story about the title of the piece and why it was
composed. It was in Portuguese, so I tried with the help of Google
Translate to translate it (I only studied Portuguese for several weeks
many years ago), and pieced together (I hope I didn&amp;rsquo;t get this too
wrong) that Nazareth dedicated it to a student of his, Gabriella
Crauz, who had showed great emotion as Nazareth described the last
days of a dying nephew, as though she had been there herself
experiencing what he experienced as he saw the sights in the city one
last time. (If you know Portuguese, please correct me if I got the
story wrong.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This story only added to the sense I already had that this seemingly
simple piece hid a depth of emotion that some performers already
revealed for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-performance-of-coração-que-sente&#34;&gt;My performance of &amp;ldquo;Coração que Sente&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I started working on the piece, I had to decide where and when to
perform it. It turned out that I learned that friends who mean a lot
to me decided to move. This was really tough news to me, and they have
always invited me and Abby to their December holiday party, where I
play music, so I decided that I was going to perform the piece at
their (now farewell) party and openly dedicate my performance to them,
because they are human beings of deep feeling, hence &amp;ldquo;Heart that
feels&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I performed the piece at the party the day after Christmas. In my
nervousness, I completely lost my train of thought a couple of times
and botched things up inexplicably (I had gone through the piece with
no errors so many times at home), but I made it through, and my
gesture was appreciated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I then decided to quickly record myself at home soon after (and still
botched some things up), so here I am. This is for Henry and Gina:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34;
src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/VBOS9btMUPI&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;
allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;other-music-by-ernesto-nazareth&#34;&gt;Other music by Ernesto Nazareth&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spent all this time talking about just one piece by Nazareth, but he
wrote much more, and more substantial pieces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I totally love Fernanda Canaud&amp;rsquo;s performance of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ernestonazareth150anos.com.br/works/view/133&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Batuque&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, &amp;ldquo;Coração
que Sente&amp;rdquo;, and
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ernestonazareth150anos.com.br/works/view/136&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Odeon&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;
(the performance of &amp;ldquo;Coração que Sente&amp;rdquo; is very different from the one
I posted above: more inward, refined, beautiful rather than super-dramatic):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/U6WaAgRWqaw&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is Nazareth playing his own pieces in recordings from 1912-1930:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/eZS3bDNJEUY&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a one-hour special documentary video &amp;ldquo;Nazareth Revisitado&amp;rdquo;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/TJAT3pJJR6M&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-note-on-the-english-language-oriented-web&#34;&gt;A note on the English-language-oriented Web&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found a whole world of music and musicians that barely register in
the English-language-oriented part of the Web. Most of what I found
when trying to look up Nazareth or various Brazilian pianists was in
Portuguese. So it&amp;rsquo;s been really humbling to remember that many in the
English-speaking world might not even know about all these Brazilian
composers and musicians who are not big enough stars to warrant
international fame.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am grateful for accidentally discovering an entire world of
Brazilian music and performers of it through my search in the local
library catalog for music to play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am grateful for friends who inspire me by their examples as human
beings of genuine and great feeling.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The single greatest performance of Bach&#39;s Goldberg Variations: Pierre Hantaï with rhythmic drive and life</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/05/the-single-greatest-performance-of-bachs-goldberg-variations-pierre-hantai/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Nov 2014 22:32:07 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/05/the-single-greatest-performance-of-bachs-goldberg-variations-pierre-hantai/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been listening to JS Bach&amp;rsquo;s Goldberg Variations for a quarter of a century now. I haven&amp;rsquo;t actually said much about this piece on this blog, although I did mention attending a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/11/19/chamber-music-concert-at-cmu-featured-bachs-goldberg-variations-arranged-for-string-trio/&#34;&gt;concert featuring a string trio arrangement of it a year ago&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a favorite recording, out of probably a dozen recordings I have heard since a college friend introduced me to the piece performed by Glenn Gould on piano . Several years ago I discovered my true favorite, upon encountering &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pierre_Hanta%C3%AF&#34;&gt;Pierre Hantaï&lt;/a&gt; on harpsichord in a CD recording.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-hantaï-stands-out-for-me&#34;&gt;Why Hantaï stands out for me&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given that there are plenty of other performances that I consider worthy, why is Hantaï&amp;rsquo;s by far my favorite?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;sustained intensity (many performances have me getting bored and sleepy)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;rhythmic&lt;/em&gt; drive is always there; the music never droops&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;subtlety and shape to all phrasing and contrast&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;no distractions of self-absorption (many performances have certain kinds of oddities that are magnified when spread out over an hour or more)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;nice harpsichord sound&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: I once didn&amp;rsquo;t like harpsichord, and always preferred a piano when possible, but now I actually prefer Bach&amp;rsquo;s music on harpsichord, because of the nature of articulation and decay and how dissonances are more delicious on this instrument.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a treat I just found by accident: a video of Hantaï performing the Goldberg Variations. Watch it if you care about the Goldberg Variations at all!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/9NYqiKm3gng&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you are already a fan of the Goldberg Variations, what is your favorite performance, and why? Also, does it matter to you whether piano or harpsichord is used?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lessons to learn from pianist Dejan Lazić&#39;s attempt to remove a critic&#39;s bad review</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/02/lessons-to-learn-from-pianist-dejan-lazics-attempt-to-remove-a-critics-bad-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Nov 2014 17:25:32 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/11/02/lessons-to-learn-from-pianist-dejan-lazics-attempt-to-remove-a-critics-bad-review/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I never heard of the pianist Dejan Lazić until a news article about him started circulating: he was upset about a 2010 review of a concert of his, written by a Washington Post critic. Because a link to this review appeared high in Web searches of his name, he asked the Washington Post to remove the review under the EU&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Right_to_be_forgotten&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;right to be forgotten&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; law. The result: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.washingtonpost.com/news/the-intersect/wp/2014/10/31/pianist-asks-the-washington-post-to-remove-a-concert-review-under-the-e-u-s-right-to-be-forgotten-ruling/&#34;&gt;this article in the Washington Post about the situation&lt;/a&gt; that came to my attention from music blogs I follow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t have much to add to the commentary about the important questions about politics or philosophy regarding the &amp;ldquo;right to be forgotten&amp;rdquo;; there are very complex questions there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, Lazić claimed he has a right to control his public image, to make the Web reflect the &amp;ldquo;truth&amp;rdquo; about his concert performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what about unintended consequences?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;unintended-consequences&#34;&gt;Unintended consequences&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously, one could argue that the law has resulted in unintended consequences in people trying to use the law for more than what it was in spirit aimed to do, which was to protect people from defamation or a past that no longer reflects who they are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main unintended consequence, however, as far as I&amp;rsquo;m concerned, is what Alex Ross said without words, in his &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.therestisnoise.com/2014/11/the-unfortunate-mr-lazi%C4%87.html&#34;&gt;blog post here with a screen shot&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically, what Lazić did is to make himself a household name, with one of the top Web search hits now being exactly the article about him trying to remove an article. Talk about going meta! He has pretty much guaranteed that he will be known for possibly the rest of his career as &amp;ldquo;the guy who was upset by a negative review and tried to have it taken down&amp;rdquo;. I don&amp;rsquo;t think he intended for that to happen. This article about his trying to remove a bad review is surely going to be the top hit for his name now!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many actions have unintended consequences, if you didn&amp;rsquo;t think far enough ahead or have contingency plans. And even if you are powerful enough and arrogant enough to think you have everything figured out, and don&amp;rsquo;t consider what &lt;em&gt;reaction&lt;/em&gt; you might get from your action, and entire chains of actions and reactions, then something further down the road can still wreck everything you tried to start; for example, the Iraq War and the entire &amp;ldquo;War on Terror&amp;rdquo; has destabilized Iraq and the entire Middle East, and has created more terrorists than existed before it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t think there was any realistic scenario under which a lone pianist looking for fame could have killed that bad review in a major newspaper. An obscure pianist could kill a bad review in an obscure blog, probably. But once you are big enough, anything you do is news in itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;ignore-negative-reviews&#34;&gt;Ignore negative reviews&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would advise Dejan Lazić to focus on making good music, getting more positive reviews from many sources. It is definitely possible that critics can kill a career, and certainly in the past, vicious powerful critics have silenced musicians, but in today&amp;rsquo;s world, people do know to look at more than one source of trusted information. I for one would not rely solely on one random Washington Post music critic&amp;rsquo;s review of a musician to determine whether to give that musician&amp;rsquo;s work a listen: actually, I would just go look for audio or video samples to &lt;em&gt;hear for myself&lt;/em&gt;. The world is different now than when the critics really did have more power than they have now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you are a musician, do you agree with what Lazić tried to do? If so, why?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you are a music fan, how seriously do you take the top negative hits when you search for an unfamiliar musician?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I just saw and heard the most amazing performance of Schumann&#39;s Fantasy for piano by Alexandre Moutouzkine</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/08/28/i-just-saw-and-heard-the-most-amazing-performance-of-schumanns-fantasy-for-piano-by-alexandre-moutouzkine/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Aug 2014 23:42:37 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/08/28/i-just-saw-and-heard-the-most-amazing-performance-of-schumanns-fantasy-for-piano-by-alexandre-moutouzkine/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My single favorite work of music by Robert Schumann is his &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fantasie_in_C_%28Schumann%29&#34;&gt;Fantasie in C for piano&lt;/a&gt;, Op. 17. I was introduced to this piece in a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/05/07/happy-birthday-johannes-brahms/&#34;&gt;course for non-musicians I took first semester of freshman year in college&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have to confess that in the past two decades since discovering that piece, I never found a perfect performance of it, although Sviatoslav Richter&amp;rsquo;s came close, and I remember rushing to buy it when it was reissued on CD (back when one had to wait to transition from LPs). But I always felt something was missing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I just accidentally discovered the performance of a lifetime, captured in &lt;em&gt;video&lt;/em&gt; on YouTube. Why did I like this one so much?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;youtube-accidental-find&#34;&gt;YouTube accidental find&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just last week I had a YouTube accidental find, of &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/08/21/discovering-the-beautiful-keyboard-playing-of-robert-hill-by-accident-on-youtube-changed-my-life/&#34;&gt;Robert Hill&lt;/a&gt;. I had another find now, while not even searching for Schumann. Somehow my YouTube sidebar popped up a suggestion to check out a performance of Schumann&amp;rsquo;s Fantasie in C for piano by some random dude named Alexandre Moutouzkine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The YouTube video appeared to be highly rated, and was recorded live at a piano competition in 2011. &lt;em&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m a sucker for live performances with actual video&lt;/em&gt;, so I checked it out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;alexandre-moutouzkine&#34;&gt;Alexandre Moutouzkine&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First impressions are important. Well, I was hooked after just twenty seconds, because he was playing it the way I hear it in my mind! The lyrical flow and phrasing and drama got me hooked. Not square, but freely emotional, yet under control. My experience was also much enhanced by seeing him in action, as he moved his body completely in sync with the music, as though his entire being was part of the instrument. I&amp;rsquo;m not a fan of musicians who move a lot but don&amp;rsquo;t actually add to the musical expression, but it seemed like this guy was the real deal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before a minute was up, I was already totally entranced by his fluidity of tempo and dynamic contrast. He was maxing out on emotional expression in just the way that I&amp;rsquo;ve always wanted to hear and see this piece performed. Schumann wrote this in a dark period of life when it was not clear he would ever get to marry Clara Wieck (which he eventually did).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll stop with the blow-by-blow, but just say that I was sitting on the edge of my seat at home for half an hour while he performed the entirety of this piece. I was not disappointed. It was like the spirit of Schumann had entered him and he was showing how Schumann felt. The final movement, the slow movement, was particularly lovely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A bit of nitpicking: of course there were some botched notes, but it would be stupid to focus on that; more seriously, the second movement (fiendishly difficult to play, admittedly) was not as solid as it could have been. But I loved the first and third movements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;video-vs-just-audio&#34;&gt;Video vs. just audio?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My experience does leave me with some questions. Is it possible that I am actually &lt;em&gt;deceived&lt;/em&gt; about the quality of interpretation because there was video and I saw the performer up close? What if there were video of Richter available? Would it change my mind about him either positively or negatively? Some naysayers would argue we should do some kind of blind comparison. But I don&amp;rsquo;t think that. Because I perform music now as an amateur, and prefer attending live performances of music, I understand now (as I did not when I merely collected audio recordings and listened) that the &amp;ldquo;music&amp;rdquo; does not just exist on paper or as audio, but as the full performance context, and seeing video helps a lot in filling in that context.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This issue has come up this year &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.henle.de/blog/en/2014/03/31/listeners-are-also-only-human/&#34;&gt;in the news&lt;/a&gt;, and I may write more about it in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some naysayers in the YouTube comments decry the physical emoting by Alexandre Moutouzkine, but I do not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am ready to admit that at least part of what was missing for me in listening to Sviatoslav Richter was that I did not &lt;em&gt;see&lt;/em&gt; him, but only heard him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;listen-for-yourself&#34;&gt;Listen for yourself&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the video.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/mGgya_-xvdo&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;more-about-alexandre-moutouzkine&#34;&gt;More about Alexandre Moutouzkine&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only after watching the video did I do a Web search on this young guy. He&amp;rsquo;s 34 now and here&amp;rsquo;s a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alexandre_Moutouzkine&#34;&gt;Wikipedia page about him&lt;/a&gt;. Definitely someone to keep an eye on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;performances-by-sviatoslav-richter&#34;&gt;Performances by Sviatoslav Richter&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to compare (but only audio, no video), here is Sviatoslav&amp;rsquo;s classic 1961 studio recording (the one I&amp;rsquo;ve treasured for decades):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/CEjhA3QVdJA&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s also a 1959 Prague live recording, which I was not aware of till looking Richter up on YouTube just now; it does have more of a sense of freedom than the studio recording:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/FzmTmOUb9Sw&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;video-footage-of-richter-in-action&#34;&gt;Video footage of Richter in action&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is video footage of Richter in action in other music. I particularly like this video of Richter playing Brahms&amp;rsquo; intermezzo in E minor, Op. 116, No. 5. You can see Richter rocking rhythmically to the music as he plays it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/wSsobHfa37A&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was very pleased to have discovered Alexandre Moutouzkine&amp;rsquo;s live performance of Schumann&amp;rsquo;s Fantasie in C for piano. Time will tell whether I will always consider it as amazing as I do now, but it really touched my heart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Do you consider it important to experience music live and/or visually? Or do you think that is just a distraction and the best way to experience music is privately through pure audio?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Discovering the beautiful keyboard playing of Robert Hill by accident on YouTube changed my life</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/08/21/discovering-the-beautiful-keyboard-playing-of-robert-hill-by-accident-on-youtube-changed-my-life/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2014 22:14:23 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/08/21/discovering-the-beautiful-keyboard-playing-of-robert-hill-by-accident-on-youtube-changed-my-life/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.mh-freiburg.de/typo3temp/_processed_/csm_prof.-dr.-robert-hill_c7981b16bc.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Robert Hill&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Recently, I completely accidentally discovered a fascinating musician, &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Hill_%28musician%29&#34;&gt;Robert Hill&lt;/a&gt;, on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/user/earlymus&#34;&gt;YouTube&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story is as you might expect: I heard a piece of music, and wanted to find some performance of it by somebody, anybody on YouTube as long as it had a decent user rating (yes, I find ratings actually useful when checking out unfamiliar music), and I happened to come across some random guy&amp;rsquo;s performance, and it was so fascinating that I looked at other uploads of his, subscribed to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/user/earlymus&#34;&gt;his YouTube channel&lt;/a&gt;, and looked him up on the Web to find out who he was!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s especially great that he regularly uploads new videos to his YouTube channel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So who is Robert Hill, and why do I like his performances so much that I&amp;rsquo;m recommending that you check them out?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-i-found-robert-hill&#34;&gt;How I found Robert Hill&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The short story is that I just heard someone playing, on piano, Johann Sebastian Bach&amp;rsquo;s Allemande from the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/French_Suites_%28Bach%29&#34;&gt;French Suite&lt;/a&gt; no. 4 in E-flat, BWV 815.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note that I actually have had very little interest in much of Bach&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Works_for_keyboard_by_J.S._Bach&#34;&gt;keyboard music&lt;/a&gt; and have almost completely ignored them for decades&lt;/em&gt;; there are only two exceptions: the Goldberg Variations and some of the Well-Tempered Clavier.  In particular, I have not listened to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/French_Suites_%28Bach%29&#34;&gt;French Suites&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/English_Suites_%28Bach%29&#34;&gt;English Suites&lt;/a&gt;, or &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Partitas_for_keyboard_%28Bach%29&#34;&gt;Partitas&lt;/a&gt; at all!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But because I just accidentally heard this Allemande played live, and liked it, I wanted to hear it again when I got home, and so I went to YouTube to find it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found a lot of performances online, of course, but I&amp;rsquo;m a sucker for the unusual, so I was particularly interested when I saw in the search results a link to some guy, Robert Hill, performing it on an unusual instrument I had never heard of in my life, a &amp;ldquo;lute-harpsichord&amp;rdquo;. And it got well over a hundred thumb-up ratings and only one thumb-down, so of course I was going to check it out!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I watched the video, and was &lt;em&gt;totally blown away&lt;/em&gt; by the beauty of the performance:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The instrument has a gorgeous sound.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Robert Hill played very expressively, with the full freedom and emotion that treasure.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Structurally, I could hear the different voices and phrases with total clarity because of how he plays.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This single performance made me think that I needed to give old Bach another shot and check out more of his keyboard music.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Listen for yourself (it&amp;rsquo;s less than two minutes long):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/woh8UHdjl1M&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;who-is-robert-hill&#34;&gt;Who is Robert Hill?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did a Web search on Robert Hill and found &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_Hill_%28musician%29&#34;&gt;information about him&lt;/a&gt;. He is an American keyboard instrument performer (especially early keyboard instruments such as harpsichord, clavichord, lute-harpsichord, fortepiano) and musicologist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had to search hard to find an actual Web site of his own, and it&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://robert-hill.tripod.com/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. It basically looks like it hasn&amp;rsquo;t been updated since around 2001, which is also his last recording time period on his &lt;a href=&#34;http://robert-hill.tripod.com/id11.html&#34;&gt;discography&lt;/a&gt;. At some point he must have decided to just share his music through YouTube. He is a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mh-freiburg.de/lehrende/person/details/hill/&#34;&gt;music professor in Freiburg&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I just mentioned, my fascination with the performances of Robert Hill comes from his &lt;em&gt;expressiveness&lt;/em&gt;, which comes about from adjustments of tempo, rhetorical gestures, ornamentation, rhythmic sense. He plays a lot more expressively than many keyboard musicians do today, and I like that. I now believe that I was turned off by much of Bach&amp;rsquo;s keyboard music not because of Bach, but because of the relatively bland performances his music has received, especially from modern pianists. Bach was an emotional man living in an emotional age (the Baroque era of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Doctrine_of_the_affections&#34;&gt;affect&lt;/a&gt;), and I feel blessed that musicians like Robert Hill are taking this seriously. There are others, of course, besides him, but I think his performances have a particular edge to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;regular-harpsichord&#34;&gt;Regular harpsichord&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is an example of Robert Hill playing regular harpsichord.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;bach-s-allemande-from-the-partita-in-d-major-bwv-828&#34;&gt;Bach&amp;rsquo;s Allemande from the Partita in D major, BWV 828&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I discovered this beautiful, haunting work of music by Bach for the first time, by sheer accident, when browsing Hill&amp;rsquo;s YouTube channel (live performance from 1997):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/oEoqPSFklkE&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I cannot believe I went four decades without ever having heard this piece in my life. Now I can&amp;rsquo;t get it out of my head.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hill did some extreme things in this performance (tempo modifications and hesitations) that are not to my taste, but I applaud him for having the courage to play from the heart, because much of what he did spoke to mine! He lives dangerously. Maybe that&amp;rsquo;s why he only posts live recording clips to YouTube now rather than make CDs?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;fortepiano&#34;&gt;Fortepiano&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He also plays fortepiano, which is a fascinating instrument I love. I have mentioned my first experience with a fortepiano in college in a blog post earlier this year celebrating the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/03/08/happy-300th-birthday-carl-philipp-emanuel-bach/&#34;&gt;300th birthday of Johann Sebastian&amp;rsquo;s son Carl Philipp Emanuel&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;cpe-bach-s-fantasie-in-f-sharp-minor&#34;&gt;CPE Bach&amp;rsquo;s Fantasie in F-sharp minor&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Heck, I had to check out Hill&amp;rsquo;s performance of my favorite CPE Bach keyboard work. In my earlier blog post, I had praised Andreas Staier&amp;rsquo;s performance I discovered in college, but now having heard Hill&amp;rsquo;s, I have another favorite (live from April 2014). This totally plays up Hill&amp;rsquo;s maximally emotive expressive style:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/LOT_nUPvE98&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;js-bach-well-tempered-clavier-selections&#34;&gt;JS Bach: Well-Tempered Clavier selections&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was fascinating to find Hill performing JS Bach on fortepiano; I had never heard anyone playing JS Bach on fortepiano before. I love that he experiments with different styles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The famous WTC I, Prelude in C major, in a fluid, beautiful Romantic-style (vs. Baroque-style) performance he just uploaded a couple of days ago:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/jiBQD0vV5qI&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A totally gorgeous Romantic-style interpretation of the slow Bach WTC I, Prelude in C# minor:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/9iGj4U7nqqY&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love how he makes full use of the expressive possibilities of the fortepiano (power and dynamics and sustain).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;beethoven-s-moonlight-sonata&#34;&gt;Beethoven&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Moonlight&amp;rdquo; sonata&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, he plays Beethoven too, on fortepiano.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that Beethoven did call it &amp;ldquo;sonata quasi fantasia&amp;rdquo; so it should be played freely &amp;ldquo;like a fantasy&amp;rdquo;, freely, and he does this. If you&amp;rsquo;ve only heard it played more &amp;ldquo;squarely&amp;rdquo;, check this out. In this case, I prefer a more subtle freedom than the exaggerated gestures Hill provides, because I feel he disrupts the rhythmic flow too much, so I consider his experiment not a full success, but still, I respect his willingness to go all out:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/6gpmZsqOzZs&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;pianoforte&#34;&gt;Pianoforte!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, of course Robert Hill plays the modern piano too. And I love what he does with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;brahms&#34;&gt;Brahms&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hill brings out the different voices very well, the counterpoint through the thick textures of Brahms. These are truly beautiful performances of some of &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/05/07/happy-birthday-johannes-brahms/&#34;&gt;my favorite piano music of all time, Brahms&amp;rsquo; intermezzi&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A passionate performance of Op. 117, No. 2 in B-flat minor:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/U_rlk4H-DQ0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And Op. 119, No. 1 in B minor (some favorite performances of which I discussed in &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/05/07/happy-birthday-johannes-brahms/&#34;&gt;my blog post last year&lt;/a&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/NOpe_KvXQzA&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is one of the most emotionally raw performances I have ever heard of this intermezzo. Hill makes the most of the suspensions, silences, dissonances, and clashing lines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Discovering the musical performances of Robert Hill on keyboard instruments has been one of the happy surprises of my life this year. Not only has he provided me listening pleasure, but also has sharpened my conception of what the music he plays is about and how to express it. He has forever changed my expectation from myself of how I should play music. I expect that from now on, I will never again hold back from &amp;ldquo;weird&amp;rdquo; interpretations that I feel come from my heart and mind. I don&amp;rsquo;t expect that all my experiments will succeed, but seeing someone else try, and publicly, how can I not do likewise?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Have you recently discovered a musician who has changed your hearing and/or your own playing? Who was it and what did you learn?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Third year at July 3 music party and finally participated in jamming</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/07/03/third-year-at-july-3-music-party-and-finally-participated-in-jamming/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jul 2014 22:11:59 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/07/03/third-year-at-july-3-music-party-and-finally-participated-in-jamming/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;The past two years, Abby and I have gone to an annual July 3 music potluck/party, and we went again this year. Both &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/03/petrified-at-a-music-jam-session-so-i-didnt-play-but-watched-and-listened/&#34;&gt;in 2012&lt;/a&gt; as well as &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/07/03/second-year-at-july-3-music-party-still-only-listening-without-playing/&#34;&gt;in 2013&lt;/a&gt;, I was too intimidated to participate in music jamming, and only watched. This year I was determined to contribute, and I brought my ukulele (which I only started learning &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/08/23/another-unexpected-life-change-one-month-of-learning-to-play-ukulele/&#34;&gt;a month after last year&amp;rsquo;s party&lt;/a&gt;, actually) and my Irish flute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;piano&#34;&gt;Piano&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After my first round of food at the potluck, I went to Susan&amp;rsquo;s piano and played David Raksin&amp;rsquo;s theme from &amp;ldquo;Laura&amp;rdquo;, which I had so botched up last month at the annual Pittsburgh Recorder Society potluck/recital. I play it much better now, although I somehow messed up the final chords today. There were a few people sitting around listening, and they wanted to hear more, but I didn&amp;rsquo;t have any more, so I scurried away to eat more food.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;old-time&#34;&gt;Old time&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As dinner started winding down, the old time musicians started gathering outside to play. I saw fiddles, banjos, and other instruments make an appearance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;blues&#34;&gt;Blues&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inside, the main guy who plays guitar and ukulele unpacked his soprano ukulele, and so I took out my concert ukulele, and two other guys with guitars appeared. Eventually a woman who sang also appeared, as well as a guy on fiddle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I felt very intimidated, because although I&amp;rsquo;ve gotten some experience jamming while on recorder or flute or tin whistle, my ukulele experience &lt;em&gt;without written music&lt;/em&gt; is still very minimal. Nevertheless, I joined in. I fumbled around, and had to ask what key each song was being played in, and even then, I&amp;rsquo;m still quite shaky in anticipating and knowing chord changes beyond the simplest I, IV, V, and some dominant and major 7th chords. I strummed very softly.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/music-2014-07-04/jamming.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Music jamming&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;They&amp;rsquo;re a great bunch, improvising melodic lines at will and even making up lyrics right on the spot, just as they had at the last two years when I only watched. And the singing in harmony was fantastic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby got a little bit of video footage of us at one point:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/zYb1aBioAao&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For two years, I was afraid to join in the music jams at this annual July 3 party. This year I joined in a little bit. If we attend the party again next year, I hope to be in a position to contribute even more! Many thanks to Susan for hosting this annual party!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thoughts on attending the Duquesne Young Artist Performance Awards Winners Showcase</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/03/08/thoughts-on-attending-the-duquesne-young-artist-performance-awards-winners-showcase/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Mar 2014 17:01:35 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/03/08/thoughts-on-attending-the-duquesne-young-artist-performance-awards-winners-showcase/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that a ten-year-old boy I currently give private chess lessons to is also passionate about music, and his piano teacher had him submit a recording for the annual &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cmcpgh.org/competitions/performanceAwards.aspx&#34;&gt;Duquesne Young Artist Performance Awards&lt;/a&gt; competition, and his entry happened to be one of the around thirty chosen, ranging from ages 7-16, so he gave a performance at the Winners Showcase at the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.duq.edu/academics/schools/music/facilities/pnc-recital-hall&#34;&gt;PNC Recital Hall&lt;/a&gt; of the Mary Papper School of Music of Duquesne University.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d seen him perform informally before, but was curious to see him on stage, and also to see other kids and where they were in their musical development and personal style, so I told his parents that I was going to attend to watch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d never been to an event like this before, a gathering of kids who had proven at least some level of ability by winning an award. I&amp;rsquo;m a latecomer to classical music, not having had much to do with it until I went to college. My younger sister did take up violin in junior high school and I went one or two of her performances with my parents, but to be frank, I was not very interested in or understanding of classical music then, so I remember almost nothing of what happened and must have snored through; all I really remember is &amp;ldquo;Please let this be over&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The young performers collectively actually played a decent variety of music of different eras and styles. The selections were mostly quite short, as they had to be of course because there were about thirty performers to go through in the space of less than two hours. One came up after another, with no break. It was pretty intense, actually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed getting a taste of what all these different kids had to offer musically, and I hope it was a positive experience for all of them. There was a lot of nervousness on display, but also some really touching resolve and mature calmness as well. I was happy to see my chess student get up there and play that grand piano with flair.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;reception&#34;&gt;Reception&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Afterwards, cookies at a reception. I was hungry. I could not &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/01/16/a-system-for-quitting-eating-cookies/&#34;&gt;resist&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/cookies-2014-03-08/cupcake.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/cookies-2014-03-08/cookie.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thoughts on returning to ukulele after almost two months off: returning to piano was the reason</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/03/05/thoughts-on-returning-to-ukulele-after-almost-two-months-off/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2014 21:32:59 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/03/05/thoughts-on-returning-to-ukulele-after-almost-two-months-off/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;I finally made it again to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/Steel-City-Ukuleles/events/158392272/&#34;&gt;latest Steel City Ukuleles meetup&lt;/a&gt;, after an absence of almost two months! What happened?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of what happened was that after the last meeting in mid-January, I had some battles with illness and fatigue and also got very busy. For whatever reason, I just plain lost interest in playing ukulele. It was like a switch flipped off. And each time a meetup came, I kind of intended to attend anyway, in hope of rekindling my interest, but it always turned out that something came up that was more important and so I missed two meetings in February that I otherwise did sign up for but canceled at the last minute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;piano&#34;&gt;Piano&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But on a deeper level, what happened was that in mid-January, right before the last meetup I attended, I learned that a boy I have been giving private chess lessons to was progressing rapidly in piano; his mother had sent me some video clips, and he played various pieces that were dear to me. This really shook my world, because I had &amp;ldquo;given up&amp;rdquo; on piano many times in my life, and never studied or practiced it seriously. &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/13/back-to-piano-too/&#34;&gt;Over two years ago, I wrote a little about this.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In particular, seeing a kid playing pieces that I never mastered made me feel deep regret that I had not stuck to teaching myself piano or getting professional instruction at some point in my life. So almost immediately upon learning about what he was up to, I decided to give piano a shot again. As a result, I completely dropped ukulele and flute, and focused my limited music time on recorder (in maintenance mode mostly) and piano.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got from the library not only the Alfred adult piano course again, but also the fantastic &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.carlhumphries.com/piano-books.html&#34;&gt;Carl Humphries &amp;ldquo;Piano Handbook&amp;rdquo; as well as &amp;ldquo;Piano Workbook&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. They are really good. I wish this kind of self-teaching material had existed two or three decades ago. I would have snapped it up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I have been making more progress on piano than I ever did twenty years ago when I last really tried. This has been exciting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;ukulele-influence-on-piano-playing&#34;&gt;Ukulele influence on piano playing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The interesting thing is that even before I started practice, I was already instantly better than ever before. I was initially surprised, but then realized that everything I&amp;rsquo;ve done on ukulele has magically helped me at piano even without my touching the instrument. In particular:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;left hand strength and coordination came simply from playing ukulele&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;awareness of harmonic changes and coordination with melody came from the multitasking and partial improvisation of singing and strumming simultaneously&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I&amp;rsquo;ve been delighted that once again, improving at one musical instrument is helping me with other instruments as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;piano-influence-on-ukulele-playing&#34;&gt;Piano influence on ukulele playing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All through February, I wasn&amp;rsquo;t in the mood to play ukulele at all. But by March, I suddenly felt the itch to pick up the instrument again, and I did, and magically found that I was playing &lt;em&gt;much better&lt;/em&gt; than I had ever before. Again, I was initially surprised. But maybe I should not have been:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;left hand precision and flexibility was considerably improved, leading to better chord changes (with less sight) as well as much better barring and also finally nailing certain hard chords such as the basic E chord&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;spatial awareness of moving up the fret board was improved&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;singing and sight-reading chord changes simultaneously became much easier&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;returning-to-the-meetup&#34;&gt;Returning to the meetup&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was having so much fun working on some songs for myself on ukulele while singing much better than ever, that I was happy to return to the Steel City Ukuleles meetup to do this with others. (Also, during the winter I confess to feeling somewhat antisocial and not excited about driving through cold, snow, and ice to meetups, frankly.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a great time! I especially enjoyed, in the final minutes of the session, when it was request time, that I requested &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/My_Favorite_Things_%28song%29&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;My Favorite Things&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; and we went through it. I love that song (and this was also when I noticed that I could play an E chord without much effort, actually).&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/scu-2014-03-05/group.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Steel City Ukuleles&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h3 id=&#34;cookies&#34;&gt;Cookies&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Someone told me that in February, she had brought in Chinese cookies from Hong Kong that her son had given her, to share with me for Chinese New Year, but I had not showed up. It was touching that I was missed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apparently the New Year party featuring wine and snacks was so popular that every meeting since then has involved wine and snacks (including this time a bottle of wine brought by a guy whose father makes wine)!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was really hungry and ate some cookies, so here are photos according to &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/01/16/a-system-for-quitting-eating-cookies/&#34;&gt;my rule&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/scu-2014-03-05/cookie1.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/scu-2014-03-05/cookie2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following turned out not to really be a cookie, but was some kind of bread with cheese or something. It was not my thing, and if I had known, I would not have taken it, but once I bit into it, I had to finish it:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/scu-2014-03-05/cookie3.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s still going to hard to juggle practicing all the instruments I have, but it&amp;rsquo;s encouraging that working intensively on one seems to transfer benefits to playing another. So I&amp;rsquo;m going to keep working on piano while also maintaining ukulele. I have to confess it&amp;rsquo;s hard to do much with recorder or flute at the moment though. They&amp;rsquo;ve been put on the back burner.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>RIP Ray Dolby: yes, I still have cassette tapes!</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/09/12/rip-ray-dolby-yes/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Sep 2013 20:43:54 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/09/12/rip-ray-dolby-yes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ray_Dolby&#34;&gt;Ray Dolby&lt;/a&gt; has &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.theguardian.com/world/2013/sep/13/audio-pioneer-dolby-dies&#34;&gt;died&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know him for one thing, basically: invention of his noise reduction system, so valuable back in the days when almost of my music was on cassette tape (I had LPs also) and I was inseparable from my Sony Walkman.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still have a cassette tape deck with Dolby B, C, and S. I don&amp;rsquo;t use it any more because I have long since given away almost all of my cassette tapes, both prerecorded and recorded off radio, LPs, or CDs (before I finally got a CD player late in college).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some of the few cassette tapes I still own, simply because I don&amp;rsquo;t have LPs or CDs of these recordings by Sviatoslav Richter. I don&amp;rsquo;t remember which music store I walked out of with these finds way back in the early 1990s! But it was a real treasure finding a variety of Schubert performances by Richter. For example, one of these Monitor label cassette tapes has an old performance of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Piano_Sonata_in_C_major,_D._840_%28Schubert%29&#34;&gt;Schubert&amp;rsquo;s unfinished C major piano sonata, D. 840&lt;/a&gt; that differs considerably from his later performance that I have a CD of.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/dolby/richter.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Sviatoslav Richter on cassette tapes&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I did some research. Apparently the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.classicalmusicguide.com/viewtopic.php?f=10&amp;amp;t=35776&#34;&gt;Monitor release is of a 1961 performance&lt;/a&gt; and the later recording is from 1979.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like both performances, but the extreme slowness of the later recording makes it more eccentric, if in some ways deeper. But they really are quite different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is the 1961 on YouTube, sounding better than my noisy cassette tape ever did:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/JK1AYAyZUIY&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, RIP, Ray Dolby: you improved the listening experience of countless cassette tape users for years!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>RIP Marian McPartland of Piano Jazz</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/08/23/rip-marian-mcpartland-of-piano-jazz/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Aug 2013 22:30:35 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/08/23/rip-marian-mcpartland-of-piano-jazz/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marian_McPartland&#34;&gt;Marian McPartland&lt;/a&gt;, longtime host of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.npr.org/series/15773266/marian-mcpartland-s-piano-jazz&#34;&gt;NPR&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Piano Jazz&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; on the radio, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.npr.org/blogs/therecord/2013/08/21/161653933/marian-mcpartland-piano-jazz-host-has-died&#34;&gt;has died&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really enjoyed dipping into her radio program over the years, hearing her play hearing her guests play, listening to the conversations. The main impression I always had was alertness and &lt;em&gt;warmth&lt;/em&gt;. RIP.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>More summer musical partying, and another ten-year-old dream fulfilled!</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/07/04/more-summer-musical-partying/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Jul 2013 23:25:39 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/07/04/more-summer-musical-partying/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I went to a party at Gina&amp;rsquo;s. We hadn&amp;rsquo;t been over in &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/22/playing-tango-on-melodica-and-singing-christmas-carols/&#34;&gt;more than half a year&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had a great time, sharing a ton of food (I made a cabbage dish of my own invention that included onion, garlic, olive oil, cumin seeds, thyme, lime juice, salt and pepper) and hanging out inside as well as in the backyard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I somehow started an arm wrestling competition with the guys, and then we challenged each other to pullups and chinups too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also ended up playing three games of speed chess at a time handicap (my 3 minutes to his 10 minutes). I barely managed to win all three games. The final game should have been a draw, but I won through a swindle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;music&#34;&gt;Music&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I told Henry I was much improved musically since &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/05/03/playing-violin-music-on-flute/&#34;&gt;we played together two months ago&lt;/a&gt;. A lot of things have been falling in place for me. Of course, this only makes me be more ambitious about music to play, and in return, get humbled yet again by how much more improvement is left for me!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;telemann-s-flute-sonata-in-b-minor-tmv-41-h4&#34;&gt;Telemann&amp;rsquo;s flute sonata in B minor, TMV 41:h4&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One piece we tackled was &lt;a href=&#34;http://imslp.org/wiki/Flute_Sonata,_TWV_41:h4_%28Telemann,_Georg_Philipp%29&#34;&gt;Telemann&amp;rsquo;s flute sonata in B minor, TMV 41:h4&lt;/a&gt;. I had only actually gone over the first two movements, so we were both sight reading the last two. That was something of a wreck for me, but gives me homework to do: originally I had not actually planned on learning the whole sonata, now I want to!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;bach-s-flute-sonata-in-e-major-bwv-1035&#34;&gt;Bach&amp;rsquo;s flute sonata in E major, BWV 1035&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another piece we did was &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sonata_in_E_major_for_flute_or_recorder_and_basso_continuo&#34;&gt;Bach&amp;rsquo;s flute sonata in E major, BWV 1035&lt;/a&gt;, which I have already mentioned my obsession with in a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/21/my-second-year-of-celebrating-johann-sebastian-bachs-birthday/&#34;&gt;blog post over three months ago&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: I am still not playing this on Baroque flute or modern flute, because of the difficulty! I have been working with a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.universaledition.com/Sonata-F-major-BWV-1035-for-treble-recorder-basso-continuo-Johann-Sebastian-Bach/composers-and-works/composer/32/work/4801&#34;&gt;recorder transcription for F major&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because I have actually been playing more of this sonata myself in the past months, I have come to change my mind about performances I listed in that blog post! There is nothing like actually studying and playing a piece of music to change one&amp;rsquo;s perception of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My favorite performance so far I&amp;rsquo;ve found on YouTube is by Wilbert Hazelzet on Baroque flute. It&amp;rsquo;s split over two parts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/ZGtjxNeBTAs&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/Oetbg7eRa60&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, Henry and I ran through the sonata. Again, I had not actually ever run through the final movement, so it was an embarrassing sight reading scramble for me. But he really enjoyed the last movement, and I did too, and realized that I wanted to actually study and practice it. It&amp;rsquo;s funny how I came to enjoy this movement much more after having tried to play it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;gabriel-fauré-après-un-rêve-fulfilling-my-ten-year-old-dream&#34;&gt;Gabriel Fauré, Après un rêve: fulfilling my ten-year-old dream&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After all the Baroque stuff, I decided to play something different with Henry. I pulled out my modern flute, and we did Fauré&amp;rsquo;s song &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trois_m%C3%A9lodies,_Op.7_%28Faur%C3%A9%29&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Après un rêve&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; in a flute and piano arrangement that I bought in 2003.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a story I have never told anyone until now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I bought that score because I was in love with the song, but never imagined that I would be able to sing it properly. So I thought to myself that if I ever played flute again (recall that the last time I had touched flute was twenty years earlier, in childhood), my goal would be to at least be able to play &lt;em&gt;this one song&lt;/em&gt; on flute reasonably close to how I feel it should be played or sung. (There is also a second piece for flute that I wanted to play as well. I will reveal it once I have actually played it with someone.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ever since I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/09/taking-up-flute-again-after-decades/&#34;&gt;got back to flute almost two years ago&lt;/a&gt;, &amp;ldquo;Après un rêve&amp;rdquo; has been on my mind as well as on my shelf, and as a measure of progres, I have actually periodically pulled it out to try to play it. For well over a year, I could not play it anywhere near how I want it to sound. Here&amp;rsquo;s a piano accompaniment track I&amp;rsquo;ve been using in the past months:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/EAAe0GDO928&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eight months ago, I fulfilled a childhood dream, by throwing myself into singing, and in fact, one song I did sing was &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/11/17/a-childhood-dream-come-true-i-am-now-finally-singing-for-real/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Après un rêve&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;! I still don&amp;rsquo;t sing it as well as I&amp;rsquo;d like, and will continue working on singing it, but singing in general has had a tremendous positive transferring effect on my flute playing! I am now almost able to play &amp;ldquo;Après un rêve&amp;rdquo; how I want (the remaining difficulties being cleaning up the high passages in the arrangement as well as controlling the breath there as well). In any case, I went and played it with Henry for the first time, and it wasn&amp;rsquo;t horrible. In summary, ten years after I bought that score with wishful thinking, I made my dream reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, here&amp;rsquo;s a nice performance on flute that inspires me:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/95f57lYWgks&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;roland-de-lassus-http-en-wikipedia-org-wiki-orlande-de-lassus-as-recorder-duets&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Orlande_de_Lassus&#34;&gt;Roland de Lassus&lt;/a&gt;, as recorder duets&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The surprise of the day was when, after watching me mess around with bass recorder, Henry got the idea of playing recorder duets with me. I hadn&amp;rsquo;t known that he played recorder. He said he could play recorders in C (soprano and tenor), and since I didn&amp;rsquo;t have my tenor on me, I gave him my soprano recorder. He picked up a book and went through it to find some early music duets that we could do on recorders. We did some with soprano and bass, then I switched to alto and we did soprano and alto for the rest we found in the book. It was immense fun!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/recorder-duets-with-henry.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Henry and Franklin on recorders&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel blessed to have the opportunity and inspiration from Henry to continue improving at playing music, and stretch myself further. I have come so far in the past two years.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Second year at July 3 music party: still only listening without playing</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/07/03/second-year-at-july-3-music-party-still-only-listening-without-playing/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jul 2013 22:10:07 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/07/03/second-year-at-july-3-music-party-still-only-listening-without-playing/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/07/03/petrified-at-a-music-jam-session-so-i-didnt-play-but-watched-and-listened/&#34;&gt;Last year Abby and I went&lt;/a&gt; to a July 3 music potluck/party at Susan&amp;rsquo;s for the first time. We attended again. I brought my flute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again I enjoyed hearing two groups of people playing music. I am not so much into the &amp;ldquo;old time&amp;rdquo; music, however, which the group outside in the backyard was playing, so I hung out inside instead, where I liked much better the blues guitar and ukulele and singing and piano. &lt;em&gt;I would like to join in one day&lt;/em&gt; myself, but today did not feel up to it. I never took out my flute; it didn&amp;rsquo;t seem appropriate for any of the music anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2014-07-04&#34;&gt;(Update of 2014-07-04)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/07/03/third-year-at-july-3-music-party-and-finally-participated-in-jamming/&#34;&gt;my third year&lt;/a&gt; of this annual party, I actually played both piano and ukulele!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Happy birthday, Johannes Brahms! 3 takes on a musical favorite</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/05/07/happy-birthday-johannes-brahms/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 May 2013 20:41:13 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/05/07/happy-birthday-johannes-brahms/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;It turns out today is the 180th birthday of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Johannes_Brahms&#34;&gt;Johannes Brahms&lt;/a&gt;, born May 7, 1833, so I thought I&amp;rsquo;d share some of my favorite music by this great composer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;piano&#34;&gt;Piano&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I discovered Brahms while a freshman in college and a total newcomer to classical music, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/09/taking-up-flute-again-after-decades/&#34;&gt;upon taking a course called &amp;ldquo;Piano Music of the 19th Century&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; because it sounded like it was an easy way to get required &amp;ldquo;core curriculum&amp;rdquo; credit (no musical background was required for this appreciation course). Instead of being just a throwaway survey course I took just to get credit, the course &lt;em&gt;changed my life&lt;/em&gt;. Sometimes that actually happens, when the instructor is passionate and communicative!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We listened to and discussed various of Brahms&amp;rsquo; miniature piano pieces he called &amp;ldquo;intermezzi&amp;rdquo;, op. 116, 117, 118, and 119. Part of what we were supposed to do was tell stories about how the pieces made us feel and why (in terms of some kind of story that involved identifying musical ideas and development).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although I went on to listen to other music by Brahms, for myself, I still have considerable nostalgia for the piano intermezzi Brahms wrote late in life, and this is so appropriate, I guess, given that they have a decidedly nostalgic, melancholic flavor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have many favorites among these sets of piano pieces, but decided to share just one of them today, &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Four_Pieces_for_Piano,_Op._119_%28Brahms%29&#34;&gt;op. 119&lt;/a&gt; no. 1 in B minor. The melancholic arpeggiated descending thirds and ambiguous harmonies, with a longing melodic line above the inner voices, make this a perfect example of Brahmsian beauty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;imagery&#34;&gt;Imagery&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I listen to this, I imagine sitting by a window, alone, as raindrops slowly and repeatedly drip down, and the clouds come and go, while occasionally a ray of sun peeks through and smiles, and occasionally there is a burst of thunder. Meanwhile, the wind is blowing and sometimes stops a raindrop from continuing to fall, or blows it back upward. I look through the window, and the world is gray and blurry, and the raindrops tell the story of what is going on outside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;three-interpretations&#34;&gt;Three interpretations&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are three interpretations I found on YouTube. I personally like the raindrops to linger and accelerate and decelerate with rubato, and this guy &amp;ldquo;Ferien7&amp;rdquo; plays that up, taking a leisurely 3:44 for the whole piece:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/KtWynSHgKH4&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I link to this video by an unknown because I like how YouTube can be a source of what I find to be good performances by people who are passionate about a particular piece but are not necessarily famous professionals or well-established recording artists. I have no idea who &amp;ldquo;Ferien7&amp;rdquo; is, but I like this performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another interpretation along similar veins, but by someone much more famous, and tighter (3:38), is by one of my all-time favorite historic pianists, &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sviatoslav_Richter&#34;&gt;Sviatoslav Richter&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/ACOvOqLqCkM&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, here is a very different, fascinating interpretation by &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Heinrich_Neuhaus&#34;&gt;Heinrich Neuhaus&lt;/a&gt;, actually Richter&amp;rsquo;s teacher, which is very fast (2:52), and emphasizes the unbroken melodic line and the drama, over the individual notes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/GYrgVp90jvQ&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2014-08-21&#34;&gt;(Update of 2014-08-21)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A year later, I found another interpretation, by Robert Hill, which I love for its extreme freedom. Check it out in &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/08/21/discovering-the-beautiful-keyboard-playing-of-robert-hill-by-accident-on-youtube-changed-my-life/&#34;&gt;my blog post about Robert Hill&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;more&#34;&gt;More&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you liked this piece, check out the other intermezzi by Brahms.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Singing and playing tango and jazz at an unexpected music party</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/04/12/singing-and-playing-tango-and-jazz-at-an-unexpected-music-party/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Apr 2013 23:20:59 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/04/12/singing-and-playing-tango-and-jazz-at-an-unexpected-music-party/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/bob-party-2013-04-12/henry-franklin.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Henry and Franklin performing El Choclo&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I suddenly got email from Henry on a Friday afternoon while I was at work. He invited me to join him at some guy&amp;rsquo;s party in the evening to play some tangos, since the party was going to have an &amp;ldquo;Argentina&amp;rdquo; theme. My first thought was that Abby was not going to be able to go, and I myself had made plans to rest up before my very important training run Saturday morning for the Pittsburgh Marathon, but the opportunity to meet some new musicians and other people, and express my love for passionate tango music, made me decide, after consulting with Abby, to attend the party.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The good news was that I had done some tango music earlier, so there was some reuse possible. Last year, I had finally worked up the courage to do some singing, and rather enjoyed singing classic traditional tango in particular, such as &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/11/17/a-childhood-dream-come-true-i-am-now-finally-singing-for-real/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Por una Cabeza&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. And this year, I had finally given a shot at playing &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/01/26/music-i-just-played-for-the-first-time-recorder-sonata-tangos/&#34;&gt;tango on flute&lt;/a&gt;, playing both &amp;ldquo;El Choclo&amp;rdquo; as well as &amp;ldquo;Por una Cabeza&amp;rdquo; (as a flute-violin duet).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bad news was that someone else was already going to play &amp;ldquo;Por una Cabeza&amp;rdquo; on violin, so that left me with only one other tango I had played with Henry before, &lt;a href=&#34;http://joanveronica.hubpages.com/hub/The-Tango-La-Cumparsita-El-Choclo-and-Mi-Buenos-Aires-Querido&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;El Choclo&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, whose contrasts of staccato/legato and minor/major, with a lot of room for rubato and ornamental bravado quite appeal to me.. I wanted a tango to sing, and by sheer coincidence, I knew exactly which tango I always wanted to sing, but had only half-sung it to myself in private: this was &lt;a href=&#34;http://joanveronica.hubpages.com/hub/Outstanding-Tango-selection-Mi-Buenos-Aires-Querido-Uno-and-Caminito&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Uno&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, by &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mariano_Mores&#34;&gt;Mariano Mores&lt;/a&gt; from 1943.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;uno&#34;&gt;Uno&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By coincidence, only a couple of days ago, the Spanish actress/singer &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sara_Montiel&#34;&gt;Sara Montiel&lt;/a&gt; died, and in her memory I rewatched and &lt;a href=&#34;https://plus.google.com/100967806642012078047/posts/6xV5iasmXxj&#34;&gt;reposted&lt;/a&gt; a video clip of her singing &amp;ldquo;Uno&amp;rdquo; in a film:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/5Z7rHztinaM&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe that I first came across &amp;ldquo;Uno&amp;rdquo; by accident when some years ago I found Montiel&amp;rsquo;s performance while searching for other tangos. In any case, it was love at first hearing, and made it to my list of tangos I wanted to sing some day. I&amp;rsquo;d put off this project for some good reasons, but today I decided I wanted to give it a shot!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I hastily found a score, printed out the lyrics, and after eating dinner at home after work, and just an hour or so before the party, I worked on being able to sing the Spanish lyrics without completely stumbling over myself. Most songs in Spanish I can sing with no problem, but &amp;ldquo;Uno&amp;rdquo; features a huge number of words in the lyrics, which means there are considerable challenges:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;pronouncing Spanish at basically spoken speed (I&amp;rsquo;m not that fluent yet)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;breaking up the words into logical and emotional groupings at speed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;singing Spanish in the face of many, many instances of word pairs with vowels in between&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I knew I wasn&amp;rsquo;t going to get everything perfect in time in less than half an hour of determining where to break things up and where to link things, and actually doing this fluently, so I was nervous, but I&amp;rsquo;ve learned that when it comes to music, perfect technique is not the most important thing; I felt I could reasonably well convey the emotional content of this song despite imperfections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-party&#34;&gt;The party&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a great party, with food, music, and conversation, and I was excited to meet a whole bunch of new people of all ages. I hope the next time Bob and his wife host another music party, Abby will be able to attend too!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before the musical part of the party began, Henry and I spent about five minutes in the basement, with him on the upright piano down there, and me singing, trying to read through &amp;ldquo;Uno&amp;rdquo; together so that it would be at least halfway presentable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We performed &amp;ldquo;El Choclo&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Uno&amp;rdquo; near the end of the program (since we were last minute additions that didn&amp;rsquo;t make it onto the printed program). I was physically shaking while doing both of them, because I was in front of a completely new crowd of people and just wasn&amp;rsquo;t as prepared as I would have preferred. But it was a friendly crowd, and the audience seemed to enjoy our music-making. I was happy to have contributed something to the &amp;ldquo;Argentina&amp;rdquo; theme with some authentic Golden Age tango music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What was really enjoyable about this music party was that so many of the guests participated in performing something: young and old, amateur and professional. This welcoming atmosphere was wonderful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;jazz-improvisation&#34;&gt;Jazz, improvisation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the official music program ended, some people continued to jam. This guy I met, Keith, was particularly interesting to me, as he is a wind player, and played both soprano saxophone and flute on the program, and then after the program, was doing jazz standards on alto saxophone. I was so inspired by this that I decided I wanted to do some jazz also. I bring a little binder of music nowadays when I go to musical parties, just in case, and happened to have on me &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jazzstandards.com/compositions-0/sweetlorraine.htm&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Sweet Lorraine&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;, which I had never played before other than to myself with a CD track. So I got Henry to the piano so that we could just go for it and improvise to the chord changes. We totally got into it and I really enjoyed the jamming. I really enjoy nothing more than improvisation, and appreciate that Henry is game for doing this with me, as when we were doing it with Latin jazz (bolero and cha cha) &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/03/17/finally-doing-some-latin-music-jamming-on-flute/&#34;&gt;last month&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had tremendous fun attending Bob&amp;rsquo;s party, seeing so many people sing or play an instrument, all of us sharing our love of music together. I was very inspired by everyone who contributed something of their unique soul there, and I feel like this is what life is all about.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>RIP Bebo Valdés, master pianist of Cuban music</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/03/22/rip-bebo-valdes/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Mar 2013 20:08:56 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/03/22/rip-bebo-valdes/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.billboard.com/files/styles/promo_650/public/media/bebo-chucho-valdes-650-430.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Bebo and Chucho&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I just heard about the death of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bebo_Vald%C3%A9s&#34;&gt;Bebo Valdés&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.npr.org/blogs/ablogsupreme/2013/03/22/175080694/bebo-vald-s-giant-of-cuban-music-is-dead?ft=1&amp;amp;f=1039&#34;&gt;at age 94 in Sweden&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I discovered this Cuban musician a decade ago, when, as a big fan of Latin (especially Cuban) dance and music, I bought the documentary &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Calle_54&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Calle 54&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; when it came out. I had heard the playing of his son &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chucho_Vald%C3%A9s&#34;&gt;Chucho&lt;/a&gt; and was very curious how Bebo&amp;rsquo;s playing might differ. The father had a more old-fashioned style, of course. But he was good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most moving scene in the entire film was that of father and son playing together, on two pianos, improvising on the famous Cuban song &amp;ldquo;La Comparsa&amp;rdquo; by &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ernesto_Lecuona&#34;&gt;Ernesto Lecuona&lt;/a&gt;. The communication between them and the interplay and contrasts were quite fascinating and touching to me. They got very emotional during their session and I could not help being moved to tears myself. The scene made me think about the story of Bebo&amp;rsquo;s decision to leave Cuba for Sweden, abandoning his family, and how he met up again with Chucho for this documentary! For me, reflecting on my own relationship with my father over the years (who is still very much alive and well; I see him once or twice a year, and will see him again soon), the scene was electric.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-bebo-chucho-scene-from-calle-54&#34;&gt;The Bebo/Chucho scene from &amp;ldquo;Calle 54&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/enblfWLM4n0&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some highlights:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At the beginning, Bebo starts off with flourishes and then the theme, while Chucho provides a little bit of harmonic filler.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Then Chucho starts adding more countermelody.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At 2:01, they smile at each other as Bebo changes the key and lets Chucho take charge. Bebo goes into a lot of elaborate, passionate ornamentation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At 2:46, when the melody goes from minor to major, this is when things start getting intense: watch the two looking at each other with increasing emotion.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At 3:39, Bebo signals to slow things down. They end, slyly without a harmonic resolution. Then Chucho gets up and hugs his father.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rest in peace, Bebo Valdés.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>