<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Melodica on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/melodica/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Melodica on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/melodica/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Discovering the Eolina, a beautiful musical instrument</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/02/18/discovering-the-eolina-a-beautiful-musical-instrument/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2015 20:56:18 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/02/18/discovering-the-eolina-a-beautiful-musical-instrument/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I just discovered a musical instrument that was new to me, the
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.melodicaworld.com/post_reviews/ballone-burini-eolina-45/&#34;&gt;Eolina&lt;/a&gt;,
which has a surprisingly beautiful sound, given that it is a form of
melodica, which although a perfectly fine instrument I enjoy playing,
does not have the loveliest, most refined sound.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I encountered the Eolina through my following the
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/user/GerardvanR&#34;&gt;YouTube channel&lt;/a&gt; of Gerard
van Reenen, who is just some random musician I found on YouTube at some
point in the past couple of years through some music search that I
have now completely forgotten.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His specialty is playing duets with himself, by playing a wind
instrument with one hand while accompanying himself on a
keyboard instrument. Remarkably, he often makes this work quite well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what exactly is an Eolina, and what does it sound like?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;example-a-handel-sonata-performed-on-eolina-and-organ&#34;&gt;Example: a Handel sonata performed on Eolina and organ&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out Gerard van Reenen&amp;rsquo;s self-duet on Eolina and organ of George
Frideric Handel&amp;rsquo;s sonata in B-flat major, HWV 377. I really like this
performance, showcasing his musicality on both instruments, and the
expressiveness of the Eolina, which is an upscale melodica made of
wood rather than plastic and therefore has more subtlety and
smoothness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/zNvV5WXRP1Q&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;another-example&#34;&gt;Another example&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was so curious about the Eolina that I tried to find other uses of
it on YouTube.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some musicians performing Piazzolla&amp;rsquo;s tango &amp;ldquo;Oblivion&amp;rdquo;, with
one of them playing an Eolina:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34;
src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/U0h39B6blVE&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;
allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Over two years ago,
&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/02/oblivion-obsession-time-to-start-playing-melodica/&#34;&gt;I had attempted to play &amp;ldquo;Oblivion&amp;rdquo; on my cheap melodica&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;d
love to have access to an Eolina sometime!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I always enjoy discovering a new musical instrument, and the Eolina
counts as one, even if it is just a wooden melodica.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Had you heard of or heard an Eolina before you read this blog post?
  What do you think of the sound? What do you think of melodicas in
  general? They are not so commonly used except as teaching
  instruments for children, so does that affect your perception?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Finally playing Piazzolla&#39;s &#34;Oblivion&#34; on flute</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/09/13/finally-playing-piazzollas-oblivion-on-flute/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2013 23:49:09 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/09/13/finally-playing-piazzollas-oblivion-on-flute/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Almost a year ago, I almost played Piazzolla&amp;rsquo;s tango &amp;ldquo;Oblivion&amp;rdquo; on flute with piano accompaniment by Henry &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/02/oblivion-obsession-time-to-start-playing-melodica/&#34;&gt;at a party&lt;/a&gt; but I ended up playing melodica instead of flute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having the opportunity to play with Henry again, this time I played it on flute, finally! I had found an oboe and piano arrangement which we used, sight reading it. I think the arranger filled in his own ornamentation into the melodic line. I only used that as a guide. Personally, when I play &amp;ldquo;Oblivion&amp;rdquo;, I improvise my own embellishments on the spot, depending on my mood. I play it very freely: it cries out for self-expression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2014-10-23-some-other-performances-of-oblivion&#34;&gt;(Update of 2014-10-23) Some other performances of &amp;ldquo;Oblivion&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/02/oblivion-obsession-time-to-start-playing-melodica/&#34;&gt;blog post of 2012&lt;/a&gt;, I embedded a lot of my favorite performances I found on YouTube of &amp;ldquo;Oblivion&amp;rdquo;. Here are some more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;flute-cello-piano-trio-mathilde-caldérini-zoé-karlikow-aurèle-marthan&#34;&gt;Flute/cello/piano trio (Mathilde Caldérini, Zoé Karlikow, Aurèle Marthan)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Very beautiful performance, great unity and balance and expression from all three musicians.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/DDCB1GqwL0I&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;7-flute-choir&#34;&gt;7 flute choir&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An unusual 7-flute arrangement, with all parts played by the same person, Manja Thessin! A bonus is that the video is a beautiful demonstration of tango dancing by David and Kim Benitez of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.tangomovement.com/&#34;&gt;Tango Movement&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/qvzgzpft8Xg&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;j-oublie-voice-elena-lydia-stamellou&#34;&gt;J&amp;rsquo;oublie (voice), Elena-Lydia Stamellou&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lovely, pure voice with piano accompaniment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/vfP4UF_1cUY&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;piano-improvisational-gila-goldstein&#34;&gt;Piano, improvisational, Gila Goldstein&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A gorgeous, floating performance, very free, with lovely touches in filling in inner voices and adding drama effectively through contrast, detail, and improvisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/J5meF7u3HpY&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;guitar-duo-katrin-klingeberg-and-sebastián-montes&#34;&gt;Guitar duo, Katrin Klingeberg and Sebastián Montes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What a partnership! A passionate performance with contrasting moods, immense focus, really captures the spirit of the piece.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/gONVtoQaovQ&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;guitar-solo-ryuji-kunimatsu&#34;&gt;Guitar solo, Ryuji Kunimatsu&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wow, one guy on guitar, all by himself, in his own arrangement, beautifully expressive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/2WZBOawjNiQ&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;melodica-and-piano-one-musician-simultaneously-haim-shapira&#34;&gt;Melodica and piano, one musician simultaneously! Haim Shapira&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A novelty item, definitely. There are compromises from trying to arrange to play both melodica and piano at the same time, but this is a fascinating free arrangement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/-R_jdtCACQw&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;piano-solo-arrangement-viktoriya-yermolyeva&#34;&gt;Piano solo arrangement, Viktoriya Yermolyeva&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A very passionate performance on piano by the arranger herself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/w1azi_oJGxY&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;digital-piano-solo-roland-fp4&#34;&gt;Digital piano solo (Roland FP4),&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Really quite good, based on Yermolyeva&amp;rsquo;s arrangement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/_Av7LcGRcd8&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Playing tango on melodica and singing Christmas carols</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/12/22/playing-tango-on-melodica-and-singing-christmas-carols/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Dec 2012 23:57:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/12/22/playing-tango-on-melodica-and-singing-christmas-carols/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I went to a Christmas party at Gina&amp;rsquo;s, and of course there had to be a lot of music-making. Probably ten of us at some point or another were playing music. There was singing, flutes, accordions, piano, mandolin, etc., on all kinds of music, for hours and hours, even in separate rooms simultaneously. I did a lot of sitting and listening to others and also some participation of my own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, personally, my favorite moments that I was involved in were the following.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;piazzolla-s-oblivion-on-melodica-and-piano&#34;&gt;Piazzolla&amp;rsquo;s Oblivion on melodica and piano&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Henry and I did Piazzolla&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Oblivion&amp;rdquo;, with me on melodica, and him accompanying on piano. I&amp;rsquo;ve &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/02/oblivion-obsession-time-to-start-playing-melodica/&#34;&gt;recently mentioned wanting to do this&lt;/a&gt;, so I was happy to have this opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My cheap secondhand student melodica has poor intonation on the lower notes, unfortunately, as &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/14/pittsburgh-contras-and-squares-holiday-ball-2012/&#34;&gt;I observed recently when playing it in the Pittsburgh Contras and Squares Holiday Ball&lt;/a&gt;. So the results were not ideal. I&amp;rsquo;ve decided that if I want to continue playing the melodica seriously, I need a better instrument.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve decided that next time I play &amp;ldquo;Oblivion&amp;rdquo; again, it will be on flute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;niccolò-dôthel-s-first-flute-and-cello-sonata-first-movement-http-imslp-org-wiki-6-sonatas-for-flute-and-cello-op-2-28d-c3-b4thel-niccol-c3-b2-29&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://imslp.org/wiki/6_Sonatas_for_Flute_and_Cello,_Op.2_%28D%C3%B4thel,_Niccol%C3%B2%29&#34;&gt;Niccolò Dôthel&amp;rsquo;s first flute and cello sonata, first movement&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For variety, I threw in some Baroque music to play with Henry on piano for continuo. We did the first movement of Dôthel&amp;rsquo;s first flute and cello sonata. I had first heard this by accident, while following a discussion &lt;a href=&#34;http://launch.groups.yahoo.com/group/earlyflute/message/12041&#34;&gt;three months ago&lt;/a&gt; on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://launch.groups.yahoo.com/group/earlyflute/&#34;&gt;Yahoo &amp;ldquo;early flute&amp;rdquo; group&lt;/a&gt;, in which one of the posters, Javier Gelati, put up a link to a YouTube video of himself playing it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/HmMoNwm-Hx8&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found this piece so delightful and suitable for the Baroque flute that I decided I wanted to play it, and worked on it, and so I finally got the chance to play it with someone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2013-02-23&#34;&gt;(Update of 2013-02-23)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ended up playing this piece again, but in a quiet recital environment, with viola da gamba continuo, at the Pittsburgh Recorder Society&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/02/23/celebrating-two-years-of-playing-recorder/&#34;&gt;Midwinter Musical Feast&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;have-yourself-a-merry-little-christmas&#34;&gt;Have Yourself a Merry Little Christmas&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of my favorite Christmas songs is &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Have_Yourself_a_Merry_Little_Christmas&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Have Yourself a Merry Little Christmas&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. It can still bring tears to my eyes. It brings back a lot of winter memories of being alone for one reason or another, while out and about and hearing it playing in stores and subway stations. Those days are over, but still, the song is really quite moving. Especially, I prefer the original lyrics, &amp;ldquo;Until then we&amp;rsquo;ll have to muddle through somehow&amp;rdquo;, to the alternate lyrics Frank Sinatra popularized, &amp;ldquo;Hang a shining star upon the highest bough&amp;rdquo;. The original melancholy lyrics underline the message of a hope for the future that is not yet reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So for the first time, I sang this song for others to hear, with Henry on piano.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, the classic performance (with the original lyrics) is the beautiful one by Judy Garland:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/5g4lY8Y3eoo&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;christmas-carols-with-other-people&#34;&gt;Christmas carols with other people&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I had the opportunity to sing a lot of Christmas carols with a number of other guests, some of whom were music students with astounding voices. Since they were female, I tried to blend in along with the pianist to fill in some harmony. I have basically no real experience in doing this, but it was fun, and I really enjoyed singing with other people.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pittsburgh Contras and Squares Holiday Ball 2012</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/12/14/pittsburgh-contras-and-squares-holiday-ball-2012/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Dec 2012 23:50:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/12/14/pittsburgh-contras-and-squares-holiday-ball-2012/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/holiday-ball-2012/grand-march.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Grand March&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;So this year I joined Abby again to play in the &amp;ldquo;Holiday Ball Orchestra&amp;rdquo; as I had &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/16/playing-recorder-and-flute-at-the-holiday-ball/&#34;&gt;done for the first time last year&lt;/a&gt;, for the annual &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/pages/Pittsburgh-Holiday-Ball/283731778337030&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Contras and Squares Holiday Ball&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My experience at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/events/383908395031216/&#34;&gt;this year&amp;rsquo;s event&lt;/a&gt; compared to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/events/308706299154491/&#34;&gt;last year&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/a&gt;, and thoughts about the future:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;preparation&#34;&gt;Preparation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, I was much more &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/11/24/preparing-to-play-irish-flute-in-the-holiday-ball/&#34;&gt;prepared&lt;/a&gt; this second time than the first time. Not only have I been playing any music at all for an entire extra year, but also, I had prior knowledge of and access to most of the music that is played every year, so I could start my practice well before the event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;costumes&#34;&gt;Costumes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby wanted me to dress up again. Since people enjoyed my wearing red pants last year, I wore them again this year. I was tired of the whole green thing, however, and so I wore a pink shirt and red vest to go all out on the red theme. I added a sport jacket also, one that had been too big for me my whole life till now; it turns out that my blazer that I wore last year is too small now, as my chest has noticeably expanded in the past year (probably because of weight lifting, posture changes, and playing wind instruments). I added a beret that I&amp;rsquo;d never worn before.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/holiday-ball-2012/franklin.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Abby came up with her own colorful outfit.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/holiday-ball-2012/abby-octave-mandolin.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;venue&#34;&gt;Venue&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was afraid that Swisshelm Park Community Center would be super cold again like last year, but I did bring my Handeze fingerless gloves just in case. It turned out that the place was warm (it&amp;rsquo;s been a very warm &amp;ldquo;winter&amp;rdquo;), and so I did not have any problems feeling cold.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;on-stage&#34;&gt;On stage&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year I think there were somewhat fewer musicians in the Holiday Ball Orchestra than last year. I thought this was actually a good thing. Last year there were some real problems with space and also with ensemble balance (there were a whole lot of violins last year, for example).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;instruments&#34;&gt;Instruments&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I brought my modern flute, wooden keyless Irish flute, and tin whistle. Last year I had played primarily recorder, but this year I chose not to play recorder at all: the Irish flute was what I wanted to use as much as possible for this music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also brought my melodica! I had practiced playing the Hallelujah Chorus part of the Grand March using it and was excited to make my melodica debut. I also planned to use it in some of the Christmas songs, such as &amp;ldquo;Frosty the Snowman&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby brought an &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Octave_mandolin&#34;&gt;octave mandolin&lt;/a&gt; she had been borrowing. She started playing mandolin just this year, and octave mandolin just in the past couple of weeks, I think. This instrument is so much better suited to the music, she says, than her tamburitza she played last year.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/holiday-ball-2012/instruments.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Our instruments&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Several &amp;ldquo;kazumpets&amp;rdquo; (kazoo trumpets) were also provided by Lynette and Jim, and passed out to whoever wanted to play them during certain songs. Abby took one.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/holiday-ball-2012/abby-kazumpet.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Abby with kazumpet&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;dancing&#34;&gt;Dancing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since Abby and I have now actually done some &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/10/07/my-first-contra-dance-workshop-unexpected-fun/&#34;&gt;contra dancing together&lt;/a&gt;, there was a question of whether we would do any dancing. Abby and I discussed this before the event; Abby was very excited to play music on octave mandolin, and so she did not want to dance, so we did no dancing. Like I said last year: &amp;ldquo;We can always dance some other time.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the other musicians were very excited about dancing and pre-arranged to spend one half or the other of the time dancing instead of playing music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I saw a lot of familiar faces among the dancers, thanks to having met some of them when doing French and contra dances at CMU, and others I met from non-dance contexts elsewhere in the past year in Pittsburgh. It was nice to see my friend Henry and his girlfriend Gina at the dance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;off-and-running&#34;&gt;Off and running&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marlin was the caller again as usual and the evening proceeded with the Grand March and then the whole big assortment of jigs, reels, waltzes, Christmas songs, and a couple of interesting new pieces for this year.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/holiday-ball-2012/grand-march.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Grand March&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t have additional interesting photos or videos to share from during the event, because I took none: after the initial Grand March, I was entirely focused just on playing music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;overall-experience&#34;&gt;Overall experience&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was far less nervous than I was last year. Also, I positioned myself near, rather than deliberately far away from, a microphone, in order to be more audible. I don&amp;rsquo;t actually know what I sounded like, but some dancers during intermission commented that they liked the sound of the wooden Irish flute, so I guess it must have been audible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Playing music for hours is tiring, especially when it is so fast and there are so many notes. Of course, nobody is required to play all the notes all the time. I picked and chose when to take breaks, typically alternating repeats or entire sections. And there is definitely a limit to how long I can play flutes before my mouth gives up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the second half, a guy who had danced during the first half played a keyed Irish flute and tin whistle with us. I hadn&amp;rsquo;t seen him at the two of three rehearsals I had attended, so I hadn&amp;rsquo;t known someone else would be playing those instruments. As a result, I changed some things up in the second half, by playing the tin whistle sometimes when he was playing the flute, and vice versa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did play the melodica as planned, but noticed that the intonation was poor in the lower notes, so I backed off. I&amp;rsquo;ll have to fix this problem before I do more melodica playing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I chose not to force myself to &amp;ldquo;achieve&amp;rdquo; some of the &amp;ldquo;goals&amp;rdquo; I set last year, which were to do some solos and nontrivial ornamentation/improvisation. I felt that because of the natural of my musical focus all this year, I hadn&amp;rsquo;t had time to devote to getting good enough to really justify taking the spotlight for some tunes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The music is still crazy fast: I am still not able to play everything quite properly at the appropriate tempo. Frustrating, but that&amp;rsquo;s OK. I expect to continue to improve my technique; I&amp;rsquo;m already so much better than I was last year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I very much enjoyed performing for the Holiday Ball this year. And I feel like the Holiday Ball Orchestra sounded better this year than we did last year, and some dancers remarked on this also. I think there are several reasons for this. One is that we had some people coming back for the second time (like me), much improved. Another is that there were slightly fewer people, which I think creates a tighter ensemble.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;goals-for-the-future&#34;&gt;Goals for the future&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right now, I&amp;rsquo;m just totally exhausted and happy to be done with music performance of any kind this year. It&amp;rsquo;s been a very tough week, a very tough month, and a very tough two months in my life, with all the things that piled up on me since the end of October.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because December always ends up being so frantic for me, for next year I need to better plan what activities I pursue during this time of year. Last year, I was totally set on playing again this year in the Holiday Ball. Now, I am not sure whether I will continue for next year. It&amp;rsquo;s a question of priorities, and I need to plan what I will be doing next year in December. If I do it again next year, then clearly I want to be doing some solos!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;thank-yous&#34;&gt;Thank yous&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, I have to thank Lynette for organizing the music scores and putting it into booklets for everyone. Jim made the kazumpets. Donna, Allison, and Maro led the rehearsals as well as conducted and played their instruments with enthusiasm; I&amp;rsquo;ve been really happy to have met them a year ago, because I&amp;rsquo;ve been encountering them in other musical contexts in Pittsburgh in the past year too!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We play for the dancers, and so I really appreciate it when they take note of our playing and respond to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And none of this would happened without Abby, who got me into the whole scene in the first place. I&amp;rsquo;ve met so many musicians and dancers, and tried out different instruments and musical styles and dances in the past year, thanks to Abby!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Oblivion obsession: time to start playing melodica!</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/12/02/oblivion-obsession-time-to-start-playing-melodica/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Dec 2012 21:32:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/12/02/oblivion-obsession-time-to-start-playing-melodica/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have been obsessed for some time with Piazzolla&amp;rsquo;s beautiful tango piece &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.astor-piazzolla.org/astor-piazzolla-oblivion/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Oblivion&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. I was planning to perform it some time on flute, but today, by accident, I decided that I want to play it on my &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.grothmusic.com/p-4654-hohner-s32-student-32-key-melodica.aspx&#34;&gt;melodica&lt;/a&gt; instead!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/hohner-student-32-melodica.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Hohner Student 32 Melodica&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-melodica-came-into-the-picture&#34;&gt;How melodica came into the picture&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This afternoon was the first rehearsal of the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/11/24/preparing-to-play-irish-flute-in-the-holiday-ball/&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Holiday Ball Orchestra&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. (Today was also round 4 of the Pittsburgh Chess League team matches, but as I did once before for round 1, I &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/09/16/excited-by-the-new-season-of-the-pittsburgh-recorder-society/&#34;&gt;prioritized music over chess&lt;/a&gt; and told the team I could not play.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the rehearsal, I played both flute and Irish flute, depending on the key. Afterward, while socializing, I happened to ask about the ukuleles that some people had. I mentioned that I still hadn&amp;rsquo;t gotten around to learning ukulele, &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/11/learning-another-instrument-the-tin-whistle/&#34;&gt;despite having intended to&lt;/a&gt; and bought a soprano a long while back. I just found it very hard to get started with my first string instrument, and other things came up. I joked about the other instruments I have that I don&amp;rsquo;t play, including my &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/01/run-shadyside-5k-outrunning-mickey-mouse-and-lending-a-trumpet/&#34;&gt;melodica&lt;/a&gt;. Lynette said in all seriousness that I was welcome to play it at the Holiday Ball.
So after I got home, I pulled out the melodica.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-is-the-melodica-good-for&#34;&gt;What is the melodica good for?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that I don&amp;rsquo;t think the melodica works well at all for the Holiday Ball music, actually. The instrument is not best at fast runs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;But&lt;/strong&gt;, since I had the instrument out: I decided to try playing it &lt;em&gt;in place of flute&lt;/em&gt; for some music I&amp;rsquo;ve been working on, such as tango and bossa nova. And I discovered that &lt;em&gt;melodica works great&lt;/em&gt; for these kinds of music! Then one thing led to another, and I was searching for covers of various songs on melodica on YouTube, and found quite a lot of cool performances by people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So now I&amp;rsquo;m completely serious about preparing to use my melodica in actual musical performances. Frankly, a lot of music I&amp;rsquo;ve been playing on flute sounds better with a darker, reeded instrument such as the melodica. For example, I&amp;rsquo;ve been playing jazzy bossa nova that I think really works best with a saxophone, but I don&amp;rsquo;t (yet!) play saxophone. The melodica works well as a substitute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In tango, of course, a bandoneón is the traditional instrument, and accordions are commonly used instead. Here, again, the melodica is great, for the melody line anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, other music that involves accordions or harmonicas work great with melodica as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;piazzolla-s-oblivion&#34;&gt;Piazzolla&amp;rsquo;s Oblivion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I am confessedly obsessed with &amp;ldquo;Oblivion&amp;rdquo;, here are some performances I found moving or otherwise useful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;flute-guitar&#34;&gt;Flute/guitar&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s Cavatina Duo on flute and guitar:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/sZD7aGqmO6w&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;melodica-with-chamber-group&#34;&gt;Melodica with chamber group&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is someone playing melodica:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/fG0TcCFUrBQ&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;melodica-and-piano-discovered-2013-08-22&#34;&gt;Melodica and piano (discovered 2013-08-22)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Japanese duo:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/AAP4GB8T8DI&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;accordion&#34;&gt;Accordion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s my friend Henry playing his solo arrangement for accordion:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/FrOHDEMOhkc&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;bandoneón-and-piano&#34;&gt;Bandoneón and piano&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Julian Rowlands and Ivo de Greef:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/sj-JUBIGKnE&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;violin-and-orchestra&#34;&gt;Violin and orchestra&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vesko Eschkenazy:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/kP6Vgm4k4xc&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;voice&#34;&gt;Voice&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wow. Wow. Milva singing French lyrics, Piazzolla himself on bandoneón!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/lzC1kKZGxBg&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;recorder-quartet-discovered-2013-08-22&#34;&gt;Recorder quartet (discovered 2013-08-22)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Japanese recorder quartet, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.geocities.jp/sekishirecorderquartet/english.htm&#34;&gt;Sekishi Recorder Quartet&lt;/a&gt;. Very nice!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/3PmaOyZNWo8&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;tango-dancers&#34;&gt;Tango dancers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, here are Daniela Pucci and Luis Bianchi dancing to the piece:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/RdU3eORpNhY&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, here is Daniela Pucci explaining why she gave up her MIT academic faculty career for tango:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/7BbAt1gnkBE&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are a tango fan, make sure to read Daniel Pucci&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.thedelicatestrength.com/?p=1522&#34;&gt;great article on tango dance connection&lt;/a&gt;. It is consonant with my own dance philosophy as well as music philosophy!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By accident, I have rediscovered the melodica, and now intend to work on it as a serious melodic instrument!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2014-10-23&#34;&gt;(Update of 2014-10-23)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2013/09/13/finally-playing-piazzollas-oblivion-on-flute/&#34;&gt;I put up more videos&lt;/a&gt; I found of &amp;ldquo;Oblivion&amp;rdquo; while thinking back to 2013 when I did play it on flute after all.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why go to concerts by amateur music groups?</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/12/12/why-go-to-concerts-by-amateur-music-groups/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Dec 2011 21:13:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/12/12/why-go-to-concerts-by-amateur-music-groups/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-historical-music-society-concert/program.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Program&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;On Sunday, Abby and I carpooled with Helen and Mike (of the &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/recorder/&#34;&gt;recorder&lt;/a&gt; gang) to Ambridge for a free concert given by the &lt;a href=&#34;http://pghhistoricalmusicsociety.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Historical Music Society&lt;/a&gt; as part of a Christmas-themed event in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.oldeconomyvillage.org/&#34;&gt;Old Economy Village&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That was a long way to drive to see an amateur group give a concert. So why did we pile into the car?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main draw was that there was going to be a performance of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brandenburg_concertos#Brandenburg_Concerto_No._4_in_G_major.2C_BWV_1049&#34;&gt;Bach&amp;rsquo;s Brandenburg concerto 4&lt;/a&gt;, including as soloists the local &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/baroque-flute/&#34;&gt;Baroque flute&lt;/a&gt; players Karen Parsons and Laura Lockard, and violinist and conductor William Lockard. I was very curious to see some Baroque flutists in action, since I had only recently &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/30/bought-a-baroque-flute/&#34;&gt;bought a Baroque flute&lt;/a&gt;. Also, I love Bach&amp;rsquo;s Brandenburg concerto 4 (which I tried to sight read for alto recorder a while ago but is still too hard for me).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The concert featured a variety of early music, including some music specifically written for the original orchestra of historic Old Economy Village back in the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-historical-music-society-concert/orchestra-left.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Left view of orchestra&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-historical-music-society-concert/orchestra-right.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Right view of orchestra&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-historical-music-society-concert/harp-viol-flute.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Harp, viola da gamba, and flute&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below are the soloists in the Brandenburg 4:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/pittsburgh-historical-music-society-concert/brandenburg-4.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Soloists for the Brandenburg 4&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;concert-review&#34;&gt;Concert review&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Going to an event like this, my expectations are not very high. In fact, once upon a time, I would not really bother to attend a concert of amateur performers because of high standards programmed into my mind as a result of easy access to any number of current or classic music recordings by professionals. And no, I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t have bothered to attend this particular concert if not for the draw of the Baroque flutists and the personal connections as well as expectations that they would be decent (which they were).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the concert, some of the violins were perpetually out of tune, and there were constant glitches everywhere, whether in the cello, horns, whatever. One has to simply be patient and decide to enjoy the performances as they are. Sometimes the struggle even adds to the excitement. The Brandenburg 4 is not easy, and even at the slow tempos chosen, the imperfections in execution combined with honest enthusiasm made me appreciate even more how special it was that Bach wrote such brilliant and passionate music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;in-praise-of-amateurism-and-imperfection&#34;&gt;In praise of amateurism and imperfection&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am an amateur musician, and not yet a very skilled one, so I recognize my limitations. I can miss notes, create uneven and ragged phrasing, fall apart at high speed, play out of tune, and make all kinds of other errors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think that being out there myself playing now, I am more appreciative than I used to be of other amateurs who love music and put themselves out there also in all their imperfection. And interestingly, I learn from that also. By hearing someone play less than perfectly, I better see that in myself and have a basis for becoming more self-aware and improving. Paradoxically, it is less useful to see someone perform at professional perfection, because that&amp;rsquo;s too far away from where I am. I consider this true whatever the field: music, chess, computer programming. Just being around perfection does not help one&amp;rsquo;s own practice and appreciation. It helps also to be around those of a somewhat higher level. That makes it easier to think, &amp;ldquo;I could be up at that level also, with work&amp;rdquo;, which is much easier to think than, &amp;ldquo;I could be Einstein or Beethoven&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;you-too-can-participate&#34;&gt;You too can participate!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Especially today, when some people are fearful and avoid doing anything that they don&amp;rsquo;t think they will be immediately expert at, I think there is a powerful message to spread. If you love music, please consider joining us amateurs who go around playing it and sharing it and helping each other improve! You don&amp;rsquo;t have to be perfect to enjoy performing. You can sing, or pick up that instrument you haven&amp;rsquo;t touched since childhood, and start up again! The media would have us believe that we are unworthy and that the best we can do is choose not to be an active music maker and instead just buy and consume recordings from the pros. There is certainly nothing wrong with appreciating the pros and supporting their beautiful performances, but we too can dance and sing, with enthusiasm and without shame!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;personal-connections&#34;&gt;Personal connections&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The recorder gang knows Laura Lockard from her involvement with a music workshop held in the summer (which I may attend next summer). They also seemed to know the other solo flutist, Karen Parsons. Also, Abby and I have our own connection to Karen Parsons: it&amp;rsquo;s her farm that we sometimes get &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/28/thankful-for-the-free-range-orange-yolked-eggs&#34;&gt;eggs&lt;/a&gt; from! Very small world, this Pittsburgh or western PA region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;postscript&#34;&gt;Postscript&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you love the Brandenburg 4, check out this amazing melodica rendition of the last movement by James Howard Young, all by himself on multiple tracks:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/_YE3akDmw9Q&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I&#39;m going to perform music much sooner than I expected: Monday</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/12/01/im-going-to-perform-music-much-sooner-than-i-expected-monday/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Dec 2011 23:19:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/12/01/im-going-to-perform-music-much-sooner-than-i-expected-monday/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/s-a-t-recorders.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;My soprano, alto, tenor recorders&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Next week on Monday, I am to join a handful of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.andrew.cmu.edu/user/lukas/pcars/Welcome.html&#34;&gt;local recorder players&lt;/a&gt; in playing holiday-themed music at a &lt;a href=&#34;http://phipps.conservatory.org/exhibits-and-events/featured-event.aspx?eventid=259&#34;&gt;Candlelit Evening at Phipps Conservatory&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will be my first time in public since I was a kid in band, and also my first time performing as part of such a small ensemble. It will be quite a new experience for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;grateful&#34;&gt;Grateful&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel very grateful for the opportunity to contribute to the performance group. I only started playing recorder &lt;em&gt;nine months ago&lt;/em&gt;, and never had any intention to start performing before at least a year of hard work to get sufficiently decent, but they think I&amp;rsquo;ve been improving a lot and invited me to join them for some holiday music that they say is &amp;ldquo;easy&amp;rdquo;. (I have not seen the music yet and will see it for the first time tomorrow evening at rehearsal. I will try to get there early!) It does mean a lot to me that they trust I can do my share playing a part in a quintet or sextet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;anxiety&#34;&gt;Anxiety&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I definitely feel anxiety at the thought of performing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the anxiety has to do with unknowns: I have not even seen the music and sight read it yet!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also have anxieties about playing wrong notes, totally losing my place, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But my anxiety is lessened when I think about how bad it would be if I made various errors. First of all, this is not some kind of formal concert where people are sitting silently watching your every move; we are playing incidental music while people check out the sights in Phipps Conservatory. Second, I trust those I am playing with: I have played with them (in a non-performance setting) for months, and know what kind of supportive people they are, and feel a rapport with them, such that I know they wouldn&amp;rsquo;t scream at me if I made a few mistakes here and there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;even-more-performance-opportunities&#34;&gt;Even more performance opportunities&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;pittsburgh-contras-and-squares-holiday-ball&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Contras and Squares Holiday Ball&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, I&amp;rsquo;m expecting to play in another holiday-oriented gig that Abby is playing in and wants me to join: the annual Holiday Ball of the &lt;a href=&#34;http://pittsburghcontra.org/&#34;&gt;Pittsburgh Contras and Squares&lt;/a&gt;. I still don&amp;rsquo;t know whether I&amp;rsquo;ll choose to play recorder or flute or whatever other instrument in this (I do have a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/01/run-shadyside-5k-outrunning-mickey-mouse-and-lending-a-trumpet/&#34;&gt;melodica&lt;/a&gt; too)! The first rehearsal is next week and I plan to attend.  I have been assured that this is a pretty informal affair, where musicians have fun contributing as they can and dancers appreciate the live music and get to have their fun also.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(No, I&amp;rsquo;m not going to play at the Holiday Ball the &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/11/30/bought-a-baroque-flute/&#34;&gt;Baroque flute I just got yesterday and started to learn&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;update-of-2011-12-16&#34;&gt;(Update of 2011-12-16)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I reported on &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/12/16/playing-recorder-and-flute-at-the-holiday-ball/&#34;&gt;playing in the Holiday Ball&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;carnegie-mellon-all-university-orchestra&#34;&gt;Carnegie Mellon All-University Orchestra&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I am considering joining, in January after winter break, the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.andrew.cmu.edu/user/auo/&#34;&gt;Carnegie Mellon All-University Orchestra&lt;/a&gt;, playing (modern) flute. This is a non-audition orchestra, so I don&amp;rsquo;t have to be super good to be a part of it. Nevertheless, I have a month or so to continue improving a lot on the flute before I can judge whether I should join it. If I do, then that will be the first time ever in an orchestra!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being non-audition, the CMU AUO is not a very good orchestra. And I know firsthand, because I went to one of their free concerts many years ago because I knew someone who was in it. But life would be tragic if only super good musicians could play music together, just as life would be tragic if only elite individuals in society were allowed or encouraged to read or write or do arithmetic or cook or garden or run or write computer programs. (That&amp;rsquo;s my social commentary for today; I will expand on this theme in later writings.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;update-of-2012-03-12&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-03-12)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/02/01/joining-an-orchestra-learning-in-the-face-of-terror/&#34;&gt;I did join the CMU AUO in January&lt;/a&gt;, but &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/12/quitting-the-cmu-all-university-orchestra-one-of-the-hardest-decisions-in-my-life/&#34;&gt;quit in March&lt;/a&gt;, one of my hardest but best decisions in my life!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am excited to start performing music in public for this holiday season. I have been quite content to just play music informally without an audience, or playing it for myself, but I have to admit that even for an introvert like me, part of the entire pleasure of playing music at all is that of connecting to the minds, hearts, bodies of people who appreciate what you communicate and express to them. Even when I play alone, I imagine connecting somehow with the universe in some strange way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2012-11-19&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-11-19)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A year later, I reported on &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/11/19/preparing-for-december-9-recorder-performance-in-phipps-conservatory/&#34;&gt;preparing for the 2012 holiday gig at Phipps&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Run Shadyside 5K: Outrunning Mickey Mouse and Lending a Trumpet</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/10/01/run-shadyside-5k-outrunning-mickey-mouse-and-lending-a-trumpet/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Oct 2011 09:47:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/10/01/run-shadyside-5k-outrunning-mickey-mouse-and-lending-a-trumpet/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My alarm starts blaring at 6:30 AM on a cold, dark Saturday morning, and I&amp;rsquo;m tired and sleepy, and briefly wonder why I preregistered on Wednesday to run today&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.runshadyside.com/&#34;&gt;Run Shadyside 5K&lt;/a&gt; race. But a commitment is a commitment, so I get, check the weather forecast, get dressed, eat something, and head off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Little do I know that today I will just manage to outrun Mickey Mouse, far exceed my race time goal, and lend someone my trumpet that has been lying around unused!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/franklin-and-mickey-mouse-eric.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin and Eric after the race&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;pre-race&#34;&gt;Pre-race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since it was cold, in the 40s, and there was a possibility it could rain (although things looked clear), I wore a long-sleeve shirt and gloves and a hat along with my shorts and Bikila LS shoes (this was the third race in which I used these shoes).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After my successful &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/25/blistered-but-blissful-in-the-burgh/&#34;&gt;Great Race 10K&lt;/a&gt; toughened me up, I was ready to run a &amp;ldquo;fast&amp;rdquo; 5K race. I had run a 5K in August in 24:36, and another in September in 24:36, but these were mostly off-road and hilly, so I expected that I should definitely go under 24:00 in this mostly flat road race, I targeted 23:30 as an ambitious goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing you have to realize is that I hadn&amp;rsquo;t run a decent 5K in years, so my goal was to really gut it out in this one. My fastest 5K was in 2003, in 20:37. I slowed down gradually to 22:04 in 2007, but later in 2007, as my life entered turmoil, I slowed to 23:30, then 24:39 in 2008, 25:20 in 2009, and 26:41 in 2010. So I have been using races this year as a gauge of my gradual &amp;ldquo;comeback&amp;rdquo; to my former level of fitness (taking aging into account, of course).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-race&#34;&gt;The race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/QslAbd-_TsA&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The gun went off and the race played out for me as most largish races do: I took care not to go out too fast, but a lot of people always act otherwise and pass me like crazy during the first minutes of the race. I just &lt;a href=&#34;http://sethgodin.typepad.com/seths_blog/2011/09/run-your-own-race.html&#34;&gt;run my own race&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a mile, things were mostly settled down. I noticed a guy ahead of me wearing a hat with Mickey Mouse ears.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/mickey-mouse-ears-hat-profile.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Mickey Mouse ears hat&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, the gap between the guy and me was ever so slowly increasing. I decided at that moment that with two miles to go, I was going to do what I could to beat this guy. This goal was going to be the single purpose of my life for the next 15 minutes (approximately).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To motivate myself even further, I used the mind trick of publicly proclaiming my goal. I know this technique is &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ted.com/talks/derek_sivers_keep_your_goals_to_yourself.html&#34;&gt;controversial&lt;/a&gt; and can backfire, but I think it depends on context. Every time I found myself running side by side with someone (whether someone I was passing or someone who had caught up to me), I told him that I was going to catch Mickey Mouse. Somehow saying that always gave me a bit of energy each time, and I would pass the guy I just talked with and not look back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I pushed really hard but for the whole second mile had still not yet closed the gap with Mickey Mouse. Sometimes I could not even see him, but I always made sure to find him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Around halfway through the third mile, I started closing on Mickey Mouse. For the first time in the race, I was totally confident that I had what it took to beat him. I finally overtook him when the finish line was in sight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;final-sprint&#34;&gt;Final sprint&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But that was not all. I saw the clock and was surprised to find that I was going to come in well under 23:00!  In the excitement, I decided to go wild.  I &lt;strong&gt;screamed&lt;/strong&gt;, as though I were dying, as I launched into a big sprint to pass probably a dozen people as I stumbled over the finish line in something like 22:46.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Man, that was cathartic. This is only the second time I have ever screamed in a race (and I have run in well over a hundred in the past decade). I had let out a scream during a sprint finish at the Pretty Good Race 5K in September, but it was a short scream, not this prolonged seconds-long one that I let out today. I supposed that in the past decade I used to be too shy to do a thing like that, but it felt so good today that I may do it in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was reminded of how in karate class I was instructed on how important it was to use the &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kiai&#34;&gt;kiai&lt;/a&gt; shout as a projection of energy. But then I reflected, my scream was not objectively the best way to end a race. If I had enough energy to scream, then I should have been able to run faster before that point, so a smarter race would have been to push even harder before the somewhat wasteful sprint. Nevertheless, at the very moment today, the scream seemed the thing to do, for psychological reasons, at least.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;post-race&#34;&gt;Post-race&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mickey Mouse came in seconds later. I went up to him and shook his hand, then grabbed some water and food and started walking back to my car (parked almost a mile away), since I needed to cool down from the race, and wanted to get my camera and warm clothing to bring back to the post-race party.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the way back from my car, I saw Mickey Mouse, but without the ears. He was walking with his family and I approached him and had his mother take a photo of us. His name is &lt;a href=&#34;http://ericbrockmeyer.com/&#34;&gt;Eric&lt;/a&gt; and he said he wasn&amp;rsquo;t the only one with Mickey Mouse ears: a bunch of Disney Research people were all wearing them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got back to the post-race party and happened to see a guy I know from lots of previous races in the past decade, Ron Romanoff, and had him take a photo of me:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-shadyside-2011-franklin.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Franklin after Run Shadyside 5K 2011&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;bumping-into-ben-paul&#34;&gt;Bumping into Ben Paul&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-shadyside-2011-festivities.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Festivities after Run Shadyside 5K 2011&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-shadyside-2011-pancakes.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Pancakes after Run Shadyside 5K 2011&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I saw a sign for pancakes, and suddenly realized that I had totally forgotten about the post-race pancake breakfast. I put away the half-eaten bagel I was munching on and headed toward the pancakes, and whom did I see but &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.communiteach.com/post/10818529188&#34;&gt;Ben Paul&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/run-shadyside-2011-ben-paul.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Ben Paul with coffee after Run Shadyside 5K 2011&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I had first met and talked with Ben at &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/09/22/starting-a-new-web-site/&#34;&gt;PodCamp Pittsburgh&lt;/a&gt;, although I had heard his name much earlier since he was one of the founders of &lt;a href=&#34;http://communiteach.com/&#34;&gt;CommuniTeach&lt;/a&gt;. CommuniTeach is a really great concept, providing a way for people who want to learn stuff, or teach it, or both, to get together. Back in June, Abby and I had attended a CommuniTeach session on &lt;a href=&#34;http://communiteach.com/learnitss.php?glid=151&#34;&gt;fermentation&lt;/a&gt;. We learned to make kefir and sauerkraut and experiment with various fermented veggie combinations involving radishes, carrots, zucchini, onion, fennel seeds, you name it. Since July (when our first batch was ready), we&amp;rsquo;ve been enjoying tasty fermented veggies to complement our meals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are curious about teaching or learning anything in the Pittsburgh area, I highly recommend that you sign up on &lt;a href=&#34;http://communiteach.com/&#34;&gt;CommuniTeach&lt;/a&gt; and check it out! I also find the &lt;a href=&#34;http://twitter.com/#!/CommuniTeach&#34;&gt;@CommuniTeach&lt;/a&gt; very useful to follow, and there is also a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.facebook.com/pages/CommuniTeach/99389138220&#34;&gt;Facebook site&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;music&#34;&gt;Music&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I mentioned to Ben that I&amp;rsquo;d been reading about him from the links that he&amp;rsquo;s posted. I&amp;rsquo;d just learned that he played melodica, and I said that I have a melodica too, but have not been playing it. I said I was also learning accordion recently. I asked him about ukulele, since he had mentioned it somewhere, and he suggested that a bunch of us find a way to teach ourselves together. I pointed out that unfortunately, I was already focusing a lot of my musical time on playing recorder and for now my ukulele goals are on hold. He couldn&amp;rsquo;t believe I played recorder, since he hates the sound, ha! I happened to mention that I had too many instruments I didn&amp;rsquo;t play, such as a trumpet. He got excited, because he needs a trumpet to play, and I offered to lend him mine. So we decided that he could meet up at my place to pick it up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We looked at the posted race results and Ben couldn&amp;rsquo;t find himself listed. He was pretty bummed about that. It was his first race! It turned out that he had not attached the race chip to his shoe, but it was still attached to his race number on his shirt. Oops. Nevertheless, in case anyone ever doubts it: I hereby declare myself as a witness to Ben Paul having run his first race today in Shadyside!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;trumpet-finally-finds-a-happy-player&#34;&gt;Trumpet finally finds a happy player!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s Ben with my trumpet. Enjoy playing it, Ben!&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/ben-paul-with-franklins-trumpet.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Ben Paul with Franklin&amp;#39;s trumpet&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;rain&#34;&gt;Rain&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It started raining outside just as Ben left with the trumpet. I am &lt;em&gt;so&lt;/em&gt; grateful that it did not rain during the race! I was prepared to deal with it (I have run cold half marathons during which it rained the whole time), but it would not have been so much fun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2012-10-06&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-10-06)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following year, sadly, I did not do Run Shadyside again, because of a schedule conflict with &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/10/06/the-fineview-stepathon-2012-pittsburghs-grueling-urban-trail-race/&#34;&gt;the Fineview Stepathon that I did instead&lt;/a&gt;. We&amp;rsquo;ll have to see what the schedules are for 2013.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>