<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Oblivion on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/oblivion/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Oblivion on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/oblivion/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Discovering the Eolina, a beautiful musical instrument</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/02/18/discovering-the-eolina-a-beautiful-musical-instrument/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2015 20:56:18 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2015/02/18/discovering-the-eolina-a-beautiful-musical-instrument/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I just discovered a musical instrument that was new to me, the
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.melodicaworld.com/post_reviews/ballone-burini-eolina-45/&#34;&gt;Eolina&lt;/a&gt;,
which has a surprisingly beautiful sound, given that it is a form of
melodica, which although a perfectly fine instrument I enjoy playing,
does not have the loveliest, most refined sound.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I encountered the Eolina through my following the
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/user/GerardvanR&#34;&gt;YouTube channel&lt;/a&gt; of Gerard
van Reenen, who is just some random musician I found on YouTube at some
point in the past couple of years through some music search that I
have now completely forgotten.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His specialty is playing duets with himself, by playing a wind
instrument with one hand while accompanying himself on a
keyboard instrument. Remarkably, he often makes this work quite well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what exactly is an Eolina, and what does it sound like?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;example-a-handel-sonata-performed-on-eolina-and-organ&#34;&gt;Example: a Handel sonata performed on Eolina and organ&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out Gerard van Reenen&amp;rsquo;s self-duet on Eolina and organ of George
Frideric Handel&amp;rsquo;s sonata in B-flat major, HWV 377. I really like this
performance, showcasing his musicality on both instruments, and the
expressiveness of the Eolina, which is an upscale melodica made of
wood rather than plastic and therefore has more subtlety and
smoothness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/zNvV5WXRP1Q&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;another-example&#34;&gt;Another example&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was so curious about the Eolina that I tried to find other uses of
it on YouTube.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some musicians performing Piazzolla&amp;rsquo;s tango &amp;ldquo;Oblivion&amp;rdquo;, with
one of them playing an Eolina:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34;
src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/U0h39B6blVE&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;
allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Over two years ago,
&lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/02/oblivion-obsession-time-to-start-playing-melodica/&#34;&gt;I had attempted to play &amp;ldquo;Oblivion&amp;rdquo; on my cheap melodica&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;d
love to have access to an Eolina sometime!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I always enjoy discovering a new musical instrument, and the Eolina
counts as one, even if it is just a wooden melodica.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Had you heard of or heard an Eolina before you read this blog post?
  What do you think of the sound? What do you think of melodicas in
  general? They are not so commonly used except as teaching
  instruments for children, so does that affect your perception?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>