<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Wingfield Pines on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/wingfield-pines/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Wingfield Pines on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/wingfield-pines/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Cold but pretty winter hike in Wingfield Pines</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/01/18/cold-but-pretty-winter-hike-in-wingfield-pines/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Jan 2014 20:10:22 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2014/01/18/cold-but-pretty-winter-hike-in-wingfield-pines/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Less than three weeks ago, Abby and I went on a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2014/01/01/happy-new-year-with-a-boyce-mayview-park-hike-wetlands/&#34;&gt;great hike in Boyce-Mayview Park in Upper St. Clair, led by Gary Byrdman&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today we went on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/pittsburghhikers/events/160997422/&#34;&gt;another hike with Gary, very close to the Boyce-Mayview Park, but in a neighboring park&lt;/a&gt;, the Wingfield Pines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;cold&#34;&gt;Cold!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a beautiful day, clear sky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it was pretty freaking cold, hovering around 10F, I think, maybe a bit higher. I was slightly underdressed, and paid the price. I should have worn my thicker gloves and also long underwear. After getting home, it took a long time for my body to return to normal. The problem is that in previous winters of my life, I have not gone out hiking when the temperature is below 20F, so this was a first for me. Now I know better what I need to wear.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/wingfield-pines-abby-franklin.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Wingfield Pines&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;about-the-park&#34;&gt;About the park&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We parked across the street from the park entrance because the parking area at the entrance is pretty small. Across the street is a large parking lot for the community center.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were just six of us braving the cold for this hike. Gary and others being locals, told us a lot about the history of the park. It was really fascinating. The land has undergone many changes of ownership and restoration over the years. I looked online after the hike and found useful information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The land is currently owned by the Allegheny Land Trust and here is the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.alleghenylandtrust.org/properties/wingfield/overview/&#34;&gt;official site of the area&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had a leisurely hike, going about five miles in two and a half hours, stopping often to check out the sights. One of us brought her dog along. She lives nearby and walks her dog twice a day here! What she really loves is that it&amp;rsquo;s officially a legal off-leash area for dogs. So this place is great for dog lovers who want their dogs to truly get their exercise! We bumped into some happy-looking dogs and their owners during the hike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.hedinenv.com/projectpages/wingfieldpines.htm&#34;&gt;water treatment system&lt;/a&gt; is pretty interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;photos&#34;&gt;Photos&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t take many photos because every time I took off my gloves to be able to use my phone camera, my fingers got super cold, so I gave up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But photos some others of us took are available &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.meetup.com/pittsburghhikers/photos/19589162&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Julie took particularly detailed and beautiful photos of cardinals, bluebirds, woodpeckers, and ducks that we saw.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;coming-back-in-spring-and-summer&#34;&gt;Coming back in spring and summer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I will definitely come back in spring and summer. The park is lovely in winter, but it will be even more gorgeous in spring and summer, quite obviously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To get an idea of what the place is like when it&amp;rsquo;s not winter, here is a sample link I found to &lt;a href=&#34;http://upperstclair.patch.com/groups/around-town/p/wingfield-pines-shines-on-a-wet-afternoon&#34;&gt;local coverage&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A video:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/4KmHnkG4Enc&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out Wingfield Pines, in Upper St. Clair. It&amp;rsquo;s less than a half-hour drive from Pittsburgh. It&amp;rsquo;s beautiful.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>