<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Winterfest on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/winterfest/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Winterfest on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/winterfest/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>East End Food Co-op Winterfest 2012</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/12/15/east-end-food-co-op-winterfest-2012/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Dec 2012 23:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/12/15/east-end-food-co-op-winterfest-2012/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Abby and I went to the annual &lt;a href=&#34;http://eastendfoodcoop.com/&#34;&gt;East End Food Co-op&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/events/433775433346947/&#34;&gt;Winterfest&lt;/a&gt; again, as we have done with John for the third year now. It was held again at the Jewish Community Center in Squirrel Hill.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/eefc-winterfest-2012/flyer.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Flyer&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;people&#34;&gt;People&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/eefc-winterfest-2012/people.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;People&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There seemed to be more people than last year, possibly because of the very mild weather this December. I remember marching or driving in the snow in the past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As usual, there were children of all ages, from a tiny baby to older kids running around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;food&#34;&gt;Food&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/eefc-winterfest-2012/food.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Food&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There was a relatively limited selection of vegetarian and vegan food. There was not as much food as last year, and not as much variety either. Some items (such as the tasty latkes) ran out quickly, so that when I went back for seconds, they were already gone. I guess it&amp;rsquo;s hard to calculate how much food is needed each year; last year there was so much left over that we were told to box up leftovers to take home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were surprised that there was no salad. There were many appetizer-type breaded foods and some generic-looking cheese cubes. Starved for more protein options, I tried to load up on a lentil-based spread, but quantities of that were limited. The food selection and allocation was strange this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In another twist, all rather than some of the desserts this year were apparently gluten-free. This was great for Abby, since she has discovered over the past year that she does well to minimize wheat in her diet. I have also noticed that I also do better without wheat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;music&#34;&gt;Music&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was a little confused this year because the local live musical entertainment was not identified in the flyers or online. I asked on the event page and even asked on the Food Co-op&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/pages/East-End-Food-Co-op/125568984134681&#34;&gt;Facebook page&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://plus.google.com/101694168941295846546&#34;&gt;Google+ page&lt;/a&gt;, but nobody responded. It seems that nobody is really engaging in conversations on these sites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, we went and there were three local guitarists who performed solo sets, one after another, while we were stuffing ourselves with food and hanging out, running into some people we knew.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/eefc-winterfest-2012/guitarist1.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Guitarist&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/eefc-winterfest-2012/guitarist2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Guitarist&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;



&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/eefc-winterfest-2012/guitarist3.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Guitarist&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Abby and I felt bad because the musical format didn&amp;rsquo;t seem to work so well. A solo guitarist speaking about his or her musical selections and then performing from the heart seems out of place at an event like this that is not quiet and intimate, where the musicians are just background entertainment. A bigger, louder group commands more attention and engagement, especially if playing uptempo dance-oriented music. Here, we could barely hear the solo guitarists talk and sing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We left the Winterfest relatively early, after about two hours there (around 9:39 PM, so I don&amp;rsquo;t know if there were other musicians after the three we saw. We left slightly early because we were still tired from all we&amp;rsquo;d done over the week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was good to see so many people come to the Winterfest this year, but the format of the food and the musical entertainment was kind of strange. Nevertheless, I welcomed the annual opportunity to hang out and eat with other members and supporters of the East End Food Co-op.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fun at the East End Food Co-op Winterfest</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/12/18/fun-at-the-east-end-food-co-op-winterfest/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Dec 2011 18:52:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/12/18/fun-at-the-east-end-food-co-op-winterfest/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Saturday, Abby and I went to the annual &lt;a href=&#34;http://eastendfoodcoop.com/&#34;&gt;East End Food Co-op&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.facebook.com/events/144638855639374/&#34;&gt;Winterfest&lt;/a&gt; with John, as we did last year, and were joined by Mark, Jin, and their daughter Julia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This family-friendly annual event serves as a fund raiser, and features a variety of vegetarian and vegan food as well as live music. This year, the draw was &lt;a href=&#34;http://davidshelow.com/guitar/performance/ensemble.php&#34;&gt;Bury the Cabbage&lt;/a&gt;, a group playing Irish traditional music.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/eefc-winterfest-2011/bury-the-cabbage.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Bury the Cabbage&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Every year, I&amp;rsquo;ve bumped into a good number of people here that I haven&amp;rsquo;t seen for a while, and this year was no exception.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;young-children&#34;&gt;Young children&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The little kids quickly and spontaneously found one another other and started running around and playing, so Julia had her fun. They all seemed to like the balloon man.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/eefc-winterfest-2011/balloons.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Young children love balloons&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;food&#34;&gt;Food&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was plenty of food available at the Winterfest. It was all vegetarian and vegan. I stuffed myself silly, especially enjoying the roasted peppers, eggplant, zucchini, and sweet potato pancakes. There was pasta with tofu, falafel, mushroom, salad, fruit, and other selection. I sampled them all.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/eefc-winterfest-2011/getting-food.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;People getting food&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There was a wide selection of cookies, carefully classified. Some were vegan, others were gluten-free. There were too many varieties for me to even try one of each.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/eefc-winterfest-2011/cookies.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Wide selection of cookies&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h2 id=&#34;people-in-pittsburgh&#34;&gt;People in Pittsburgh&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abby and I recognized one person in the Irish band, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.lesgetchell.com/&#34;&gt;Les&lt;/a&gt;. We had met him at a party at one point but not known much about him. It&amp;rsquo;s funny how in Pittsburgh it is easy to run into the same person in different contexts!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We saw &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cleanlink.com/sm/article/Endurance-Running-Takes-Will-Desire--550&#34;&gt;Sam Bertenthal&lt;/a&gt; again with his son Fernando. Sam is a local ultrarunner whom I first met in &lt;a href=&#34;../../images/franklin-finishing-sammys-birthday-run-2006.jpg&#34;&gt;2006&lt;/a&gt; when I ran in his annual &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.runnersworld.com/community/forums/runner-communities/masters/sammys-6-hour-birthday-run-race-report-new-twists?plckFindPostKey=Cat:Runner%20CommunitiesForum:648106477Discussion:926106577Post:836106577&#34;&gt;Sammy&amp;rsquo;s Birthday Run&lt;/a&gt; for the first time. I ran just 27.5 miles that year (long enough to go beyond the marathon distance of 26.2 for my own pride), and went back to do the same in &lt;a href=&#34;../../images/franklin-finishing-sammys-birthday-run-2008.jpg&#34;&gt;2008&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sam said hello and reminded me that next year he will be holding his race on July 14. We&amp;rsquo;ll see whether I&amp;rsquo;m up for it again. I haven&amp;rsquo;t been running long distances in recent years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also saw some other people we recognized as regulars to the Winterfest, such as Linda of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.salsaritmodance.org/&#34;&gt;Salsa Ritmo&lt;/a&gt;, a salsa dance instructor through whom Abby and I actually first got together at a party of hers (and Linda&amp;rsquo;s dance partner is Mark Fuhs, who was my classmate at CMU when I got him into ballroom dancing, then he discovered salsa and got serious about it and became an instructor).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.myspace.com/kimberleefaught&#34;&gt;Kimberlee Faught&lt;/a&gt; is a regular at the annual Winterfest also. If you live in the city of Pittsburgh, you&amp;rsquo;ve probably seen her around playing violin in Squirrel Hill on Murray or Forbes (or elsewhere) when the weather is nice. I bump into her running in 5K races also!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I mention all this only because I really want to highlight how much I love that in Pittsburgh, I never feel alone. Wherever I go, I&amp;rsquo;ll run into someone I know or have met from somewhere. This feel is very important to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;music-and-dancing&#34;&gt;Music and dancing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We enjoyed listening to the music, and Abby and I got up to dance a couple of waltzes (last year . There were some people who attempted to do Irish step dancing. Unfortunately, Abby and I don&amp;rsquo;t know it, so we didn&amp;rsquo;t try it. Maybe that&amp;rsquo;s something else worth learning!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sorry, no videos this year of Abby and me dancing! Last year John did get video of us &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SKWXpkHF20g&#34;&gt;dancing waltz to Zydeco Dogz&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I noticed that &lt;a href=&#34;http://brucefoley.com/&#34;&gt;Bruce Foley&lt;/a&gt; of Bury the Cabbage was playing what looked like an oversized tin whistle, so during a break I asked him about the instrument. Indeed, it was a whistle in D an octave lower than the little tin whistle I had started playing. He said the best place to get these whistles is &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.burkewhistles.com/&#34;&gt;Burke&lt;/a&gt;. I have to confess I&amp;rsquo;m not currently in the market for a low whistle, much less any professional-grade whistle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;interviews-about-the-east-end-food-co-op-updated-2012-12-04&#34;&gt;Interviews about the East End Food Co-op (updated 2012-12-04)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the party, there was a call for volunteers to be interviewed about the East End Food Co-op, how they use it, and what it means to them. Here&amp;rsquo;s a video that was made from the interviews.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe src=&#34;http://player.vimeo.com/video/37628327?badge=0&#34; width=&#34;500&#34; height=&#34;281&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen allowFullScreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://vimeo.com/37628327&#34;&gt;Winterfest with the East End Food Co-op&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href=&#34;http://vimeo.com/user10547223&#34;&gt;East End Food Co-op&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&#34;http://vimeo.com&#34;&gt;Vimeo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was getting to be bedtime for Julia, so Mark and Jin prepared to go home, and John, Abby, and I also packed up (we were all told to take leftover food, of which there was plenty) and went home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With filling our bellies, hearing a variety of music on different instruments and, dancing, hanging out with friends, people-watching, it was a fun evening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am grateful to the East End Food Co-op for organizing this annual event and providing the food, and the Jewish Community Center for hosting its location again. I am grateful that Mark, Jin, Julia, and John were able to join Abby and me for the evening. I am grateful for the opportunity to listen to excellent live music and dance to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;update-of-2012-15-15&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-15-15)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following year, we attended the annual Winterfest &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/12/15/east-end-food-co-op-winterfest-2012/&#34;&gt;again&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>