<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Franz Liszt on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/franz-liszt/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Franz Liszt on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/franz-liszt/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Flute update: celebrating Bach&#39;s birthday, using a Thumbport, improvising to bossa nova</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/03/21/flute-update-celebrating-bachs-birthday/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Mar 2012 20:57:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2012/03/21/flute-update-celebrating-bachs-birthday/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s been eleven days since &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/10/flute-loving-it-again/&#34;&gt;my last blog post on my flute progress&lt;/a&gt;. During this time, there have been various changes in my life, including &lt;em&gt;radical&lt;/em&gt; changes in my musical life. It will take me a couple of additional blog posts to discuss these changes, but for now, I&amp;rsquo;ll talk only about today&amp;rsquo;s snapshot of my flute activity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;update-of-2012-03-12&#34;&gt;(Update of 2012-03-12)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had ended up &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/12/quitting-the-cmu-all-university-orchestra-one-of-the-hardest-decisions-in-my-life/&#34;&gt;quitting the CMU AUO&lt;/a&gt;, and then having a &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/17/st-patricks-day-party-playing-tin-whistle-and-flute/&#34;&gt;wonderful musical experience a birthday party&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;thumbport&#34;&gt;Thumbport&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://www.thumbport.com/images/position.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Thumbport&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Today I received a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.thumbport.com/&#34;&gt;Thumbport II&lt;/a&gt; I ordered recently. It&amp;rsquo;s a snap-on device that helps with holding a flute, by making it easier to balance the flute on the right thumb, thereby decreasing rolling of the flute and pressure on the right pinkie finger. I tried it for the first time today and it seems useful. We&amp;rsquo;ll see if it helps a bit with my form and &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2012/03/07/flute-taking-a-break-while-clarifying-my-goals/&#34;&gt;injury issues&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;i-celebrated-the-327th-birthday-of-johann-sebastian-bach&#34;&gt;I celebrated the 327th birthday of Johann Sebastian Bach&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t follow celebrity birthdays, but I could not avoid hearing about the birthday of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Johann_Sebastian_Bach&#34;&gt;Johann Sebastian Bach, born in 1685&lt;/a&gt;, thanks to some music blogs I follow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How to celebrate? The last time I celebrated a composer&amp;rsquo;s birthday, it was last October, for Franz Liszt&amp;rsquo;s 200th birthday. Then, I listened to a piece of music by the composer and &lt;a href=&#34;../../blog/2011/10/22/happy-200th-birthday/&#34;&gt;wrote up my impressions of it&lt;/a&gt;. Today, I again had the option to read about Bach or his music, and but I mostly chose to play his music, in order to celebrate as &lt;em&gt;actively&lt;/em&gt; as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;playing-the-cello-suite-no-1-in-g-major-bwv-1007&#34;&gt;Playing the cello suite no. 1 in G major, BWV 1007&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I sight read a bunch of old Bach&amp;rsquo;s music that eventually I should practice seriously to play well, including various minuets and bourrées.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the main piece I sight read was the full &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cello_Suites_(Bach)&#34;&gt;cello suite&lt;/a&gt; no. 1 in G major, using an &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.pjb.com.au/mus/arr.html&#34;&gt;arrangement for flute by Peter Billam&lt;/a&gt;. (I had actually obtained this a long time ago intending to play it on alto &lt;a href=&#34;../../categories/recorder/&#34;&gt;recorder&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This music is deceptively simple but really quite beautiful. Even visually it is pleasing: check out Bach&amp;rsquo;s handwritten score:&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/9/9c/Bachs1a.gif&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Bach cello suite no. 1, first page&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;h4 id=&#34;visual-animation&#34;&gt;Visual animation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the way, you must check out the following unconventional visual animated representation of this music (see the creator&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.chenalexander.com/2011/baroque-bach-cello/&#34;&gt;blog post about its construction&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe src=&#34;http://player.vimeo.com/video/31179423?title=0&amp;amp;byline=0&amp;amp;portrait=0&#34; width=&#34;400&#34; height=&#34;225&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen allowFullScreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://vimeo.com/31179423&#34;&gt;Baroque.me: J.S. Bach - Cello Suite No. 1 - Prelude&lt;/a&gt; from &lt;a href=&#34;http://vimeo.com/alexanderchen&#34;&gt;Alexander Chen&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&#34;http://vimeo.com&#34;&gt;Vimeo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;bossa-nova&#34;&gt;Bossa nova&lt;/h2&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://s3.amazonaws.com/halleonard-closerlook/00843016/00843016FC.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Latin Jazz: 10 Latin Jazz Classics&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Today I also picked up from the public library another play-along score/CD set, this time a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.halleonard.com/product/viewproduct.do?itemid=843016&amp;amp;lid=1&amp;amp;keywords=latin&amp;amp;seriesfeature=JZPLYA&amp;amp;&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Latin jazz&amp;rdquo; collection&lt;/a&gt;. Apart from the famous mambo &amp;ldquo;Ran Kan Kan&amp;rdquo; by Tito Puente, the rest was actually bossa nova, which was what I got it for. Recently I decided to get more into playing jazz and working on improvisation. Since I love the harmonies and tunes of classic bossa nova, I decided this was a good place to get started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a lot of fun playing around with the accompaniment CD. Actually, I would also like to sing this music, but unlike with salsa and bolero, where I am completely comfortable singing in Spanish, I am not proficient in the Portuguese language and it trips me up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I just thought I&amp;rsquo;d provide a short update on some of my current musical activities, until I have time to write about the big changes I&amp;rsquo;ve made in my musical life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-musical-tangent-bach-s-goldberg-variations&#34;&gt;A musical tangent: Bach&amp;rsquo;s Goldberg Variations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In turns out there is a whole series of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.npr.org/blogs/deceptivecadence/148455347/goldberg-week&#34;&gt;posts on the NPR music blog about the Goldberg Variations&lt;/a&gt;. I could not resist dipping into this series, because I am a Goldberg geek. I would like someday to get good enough on piano to play much of it.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Happy 200th birthday, Franz Liszt!</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/10/22/happy-200th-birthday/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Oct 2011 22:08:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2011/10/22/happy-200th-birthday/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It turns out that today is the 200th anniversary of the birth of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Franz_Liszt&#34;&gt;Franz Liszt&lt;/a&gt;, the always &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2011/10/23/arts/music/looking-at-franz-liszt-on-his-bicentenary.html&#34;&gt;controversial&lt;/a&gt; pianist and composer of the 19th century in Europe. It has become a commonplace that Liszt was music&amp;rsquo;s first &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.npr.org/2011/10/22/141617637/how-franz-liszt-became-the-worlds-first-rock-star&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;rock star&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;. And there is always the debate over his &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.npr.org/blogs/deceptivecadence/2011/10/21/141562068/franz-liszt-at-200-an-important-but-not-great-composer&#34;&gt;importance&lt;/a&gt; as a composer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These days, I don&amp;rsquo;t care much about such debates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, I&amp;rsquo;m here to share with you one piano piece by Liszt that I discovered and listened to today and found quite beautiful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not being too familiar with Liszt&amp;rsquo;s music (other than half a dozen of his most popular works that often pop up on TV or in the movies or cartoons), I chose to celebrate Liszt&amp;rsquo;s birthday by listening to a piano work of his that I either hadn&amp;rsquo;t heard before or had but had not &lt;em&gt;listened&lt;/em&gt; to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;les-jeux-d-eaux-à-la-villa-d-este&#34;&gt;Les Jeux d&amp;rsquo;eaux à la Villa d&amp;rsquo;Este&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got this YouTube link of Claudio Arrau playing &lt;em&gt;Les Jeux d&amp;rsquo;eaux à la Villa d&amp;rsquo;Este&lt;/em&gt; (The Fountains of the Villa d&amp;rsquo;Este) from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.therestisnoise.com/2011/10/liszt-200.html&#34;&gt;Alex Ross&amp;rsquo;s blog post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found this music beautiful: evocative, passionate, yet restorative: I listened to it after my run in Frick Park today, relaxing with my eyes closed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Try this: click below to start the audio playback, and then read my text below, visualizing along with me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;video-with-visualization&#34;&gt;Video with visualization&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;420&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/embed/2DoGOGS3lC8&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is the late 1800s, and we are lucky enough to have the opportunity to travel in Italy, exploring its culture and history. It&amp;rsquo;s all new to us. Maybe we read something in books, but we have not been there. This is not the era of trains, planes, and web sites yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We find ourselves at the garden in Villa d&amp;rsquo;Este, rich with Renaissance history and architecture. It is quiet and peaceful. Nobody else is around.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/Tivoli-large-fountain-close-da-as-m4-as-m4.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Fountains&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;We sit down and admire the fountains and let our thoughts wander as the water flows. We hear and see the spraying and trickling, glistening under the sun. The air is cool from the movement, and we smell the freshness of the air amidst the trees and the earth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The water has a life of its own, dancing to its own rhythm and patterns. Each jet or drop or trickle speaks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A moment of silence as we zoom in on the water, and nothing but the water. We no longer see trees or buildings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is the water at the top, and at the bottom. They are moving differently, independently. Different rhythms. At the top the water is light and dances quickly, fluttering and suspended; at the bottom, a pool collecting and receiving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a story behind every drop of water, its trajectory, its renewal as it comes up, as though toward heaven, fades and falls, merges with the rest at the bottom. We hear the stories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a story of exuberance and lightheartedness, of youth striving to reach the sun. There is a story of homecoming, of comfort and wisdom. There is a story saying, we are all the same, and you were one of us, and we gave birth to you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The old ones are now speaking; the roles are reversed. Both young and old excited and moving fast. Old to young, rising up. We see the path of life as it always is, as it must be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Come back to us, the old say. The young say, we are not ready yet, we want to be free, we want to see the stars, we want to kiss them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is getting dark in the day, and sleep calls. Gently the old puts the young to bed. Tomorrow is another day. Everything is OK, everything will always be OK.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>