<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Franz Schubert on Franklin Chen</title>
    <link>http://franklinchen.com/categories/franz-schubert/atom/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Franz Schubert on Franklin Chen</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://franklinchen.com/categories/franz-schubert/atom/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>RIP Ray Dolby: yes, I still have cassette tapes!</title>
      <link>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/09/12/rip-ray-dolby-yes/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Sep 2013 20:43:54 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://franklinchen.com/blog/2013/09/12/rip-ray-dolby-yes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ray_Dolby&#34;&gt;Ray Dolby&lt;/a&gt; has &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.theguardian.com/world/2013/sep/13/audio-pioneer-dolby-dies&#34;&gt;died&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know him for one thing, basically: invention of his noise reduction system, so valuable back in the days when almost of my music was on cassette tape (I had LPs also) and I was inseparable from my Sony Walkman.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still have a cassette tape deck with Dolby B, C, and S. I don&amp;rsquo;t use it any more because I have long since given away almost all of my cassette tapes, both prerecorded and recorded off radio, LPs, or CDs (before I finally got a CD player late in college).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some of the few cassette tapes I still own, simply because I don&amp;rsquo;t have LPs or CDs of these recordings by Sviatoslav Richter. I don&amp;rsquo;t remember which music store I walked out of with these finds way back in the early 1990s! But it was a real treasure finding a variety of Schubert performances by Richter. For example, one of these Monitor label cassette tapes has an old performance of &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Piano_Sonata_in_C_major,_D._840_%28Schubert%29&#34;&gt;Schubert&amp;rsquo;s unfinished C major piano sonata, D. 840&lt;/a&gt; that differs considerably from his later performance that I have a CD of.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;figure &gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;../../images/dolby/richter.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Sviatoslav Richter on cassette tapes&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I did some research. Apparently the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.classicalmusicguide.com/viewtopic.php?f=10&amp;amp;t=35776&#34;&gt;Monitor release is of a 1961 performance&lt;/a&gt; and the later recording is from 1979.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like both performances, but the extreme slowness of the later recording makes it more eccentric, if in some ways deeper. But they really are quite different.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is the 1961 on YouTube, sounding better than my noisy cassette tape ever did:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&#34;560&#34; height=&#34;315&#34; src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/JK1AYAyZUIY&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, RIP, Ray Dolby: you improved the listening experience of countless cassette tape users for years!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>